<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 27</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="book">
                <head>Scipio in Spain</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the position of affairs in Spain.
                        In Italy the consul Marcellus recovered Salapia, which was betrayed to him,
                        and gained forcible possession of two places belonging to the
                        Samnites-Marmoreae and Heles. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> 3000 of
                        Hannibal's troops who had been left to garrison these towns were destroyed.
                        The plunder, of which there was a considerable quantity, was given to the
                        soldiers; 60,000 bushels of wheat and 28,000 of barley were also found
                        there. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The satisfaction derived from this
                        success was, however, more than counterbalanced by a defeat which was
                        sustained a few days later not far from Herdonea. This city had revolted
                        from Rome after the disaster of Cannae, and Cn. Fulvius, the proconsul, was
                        encamped before it in the hope of recovering it. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He had chosen a position for his camp which was not
                        sufficiently protected, and the camp itself was not in a proper state of
                        defence. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Naturally a careless general, he
                        was still less cautious now that he had reason to hope that the inhabitants
                        were weakening in their allegiance to the Carthaginians, since the news had
                        reached them of Hannibal's withdrawal into Bruttium after losing Salapia.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This was all duly reported to Hannibal
                        by emissaries from Herdonea, and the intelligence made him anxious to save a
                        friendly city and at the same time hopeful of catching his enemy when off
                        his guard. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In order to forestall any
                        rumours of his approach he proceeded to Herdonea by forced marches, and as
                        he approached the place he formed his men in battle order with the view of
                        intimidating the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Roman
                        commander-his equal in courage, but far inferior to him in tactical skill
                        and in numbers-hastily formed his line and engaged. The action was begun
                        most vigorously by the fifth legion and the allies on the left wing.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Hannibal, however, had instructed his
                        cavalry to wait until the attention of the infantry was completely taken up
                        with the battle and then to ride round the lines; one division to attack the
                        Roman camp, the other the rear of the Roman line. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He told his staff that he had defeated a Cn. Fulvius, a
                        praetor, on the same ground two years before, and as the names were the
                        same, so the result of the fight would be the same. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> His anticipations were realised, for after the lines
                        had closed and many of the Romans had fallen in the hand-to-hand fighting,
                        though the ranks still held their ground with the standards, the tumultuous
                        cavalry charge in the rear threw into disorder first the sixth legion
                        stationed in the second line, and then, as <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> the Numidians pressed on, the fifth legion and finally
                        the front ranks with their standards. Some were scattered in flight, others
                        were cut down between the two bodies of assailants. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> It was here that Cn. Fulvius fell together with eleven
                        military tribunes. As to the number of those killed, who could definitely
                        state it, when I find in one author the number given as 13,000, in another
                        not more than 7000? The victor took possession of the camp and its spoil.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As he learnt that Herdonea was
                        prepared to go over to the Romans and would not remain faithful after his
                        withdrawal, he transported the whole population to Metapontum and Thurii and
                        burnt the place. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Its leading citizens who
                        were discovered to have held secret conferences with Fulvius were put to
                        death. Those Romans who escaped from the fatal field fled by various routes,
                        almost wholly weaponless, to Marcellus in Samnium. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus was not particularly disturbed
                        by this serious disaster. He sent a despatch to the senate informing them of
                        the loss of the general and his army at Herdonea and <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> adding that he himself was the same Marcellus who had
                        beaten Hannibal when flushed with his victory at Cannae, that he intended to
                        meet him and would soon put an end to any pleasure he might feel at his
                        recent success. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In Rome itself there was
                        great mourning for what had happened and great apprehension as to what might
                        happen in the future. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul marched
                        out of Samnium and advanced as far as Numistro in Lucania. Here he encamped
                        on level ground in full view of Hannibal, who was occupying a hill.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To show the confidence he felt, he was
                        the first to offer battle, and when Hannibal saw the standards emerging from
                        the gates of the camp, he did not decline the challenge. They formed their
                        lines so that the Carthaginian rested his right on the hill, while the Roman
                        left was protected by the town. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The troops
                        who were first engaged were, on the Roman side, the first legion and the
                        right wing of the allies; those under Hannibal comprised the Spanish
                        infantry and the Balearic slingers. When the action had commenced the
                        elephants were driven on to the field. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        contest was prolonged from the third hour of the day until nightfall, and
                        when the front lines were worn out, the third legion relieved the first and
                        the left wing of the allies took the place of the right. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Fresh troops also came into action on the other side,
                        with the result that instead of a spiritless and exhausted struggle a fierce
                        fight broke out anew between men who were fresh in mind and body. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Night, however, separated the combatants whilst
                        the victory was yet undecided." The following day the Romans remained under
                        arms from sunrise till well on in the day, ready to renew the contest.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But as no enemy showed himself, they
                        began to gather the spoils of the field, and after collecting the bodies of
                        the slain into one heap, they burnt them. Hannibal broke up his camp quietly
                        at night and withdrew into Apulia. When daylight revealed the enemies'
                        flight, Marcellus made up his mind to follow in his track. He left the
                        wounded with a small guard at Numistro under the charge of L. Furius
                        Purpurio, one of his military tribunes, and came up with Hannibal at
                        Venusia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Here for some days there were
                        skirmishes between the outposts and slight actions in which both cavalry and
                        infantry took part, but no regular battle. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> In nearly every case the Romans had the advantage. Both armies traversed
                        Apulia without fighting any important action, Hannibal marching by night
                        always on the look-out for a chance of surprise or ambush, Marcellus never
                        moving but in daylight, and then only after careful reconnoitring. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Capua, in the meantime, Flaccus was
                        occupied with the sale of the property of the principal citizens and the
                        farming of the revenues from that part of the territory which had become
                        Roman domain-land; the impost being paid in corn. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> As though there was never to be wanting some reason or
                        other for treating the Capuans with severity, disclosures were made of a
                        fresh crime which had been hatched in secret. Fulvius had moved his men out
                        of the houses in Capua, partly through fear lest his army should demoralised
                        by the attractions of the city, as Hannibal's had been, and partly that
                        there might be houses to go with the land which was being let. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The troops were ordered to construct military
                        huts just outside the walls and gates. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Most of these they made of wattle or planking; some used plaited osiers and
                        covered them with straw, as though deliberately designing them to feed a
                        conflagration. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> One hundred and seventy
                        Capuans with the brothers Blossius at their head formed a plot to set fire
                        to all these huts simultaneously in the night. Some slaves belonging to the
                        Blossian household betrayed the secret. On receiving the information the
                        proconsul at once ordered the gates to be shut and the troops to arm. All
                        those involved in the crime were arrested, examined under torture, found
                        guilty, and summarily executed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        informers received their freedom and 10,000 ases each. The people of Nuceria
                        and Acerrae having complained that they had nowhere to live, as Acerrae was
                        partly destroyed by fire and Nuceria completely demolished, Fulvius sent
                        them to Rome to appear before the senate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Permission was given to the Acerrans to rebuild those houses which had been
                        burnt, and <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> as the people of Nuceria had
                        expressed their desire to settle at Atella, the Atellans were ordered to
                        remove to Calatia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In spite of the many
                        important incidents, some favourable, some unfavourable, which were
                        occupying the public attention, the citadel of Tarentum was not lost sight
                        of. M. Ogulnius and P. Aquilius were appointed commissioners for the
                        purchase of corn in Etruria, and a force of 1000 men drawn from the home
                        army, with an equal number from the allied contingents, conveyed it to
                        Tarentum. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The summer was now drawing to a close, and
                        the date of the consular elections was near at hand. Marcellus wrote to say
                        that it would be against the interests of the republic to lose touch with
                        Hannibal, as he was being pressed steadily back, and avoided anything like a
                        battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate were reluctant to
                        recall him just when he was most effectively employed; at the same time they
                        were anxious lest there should be no consuls for the coming year. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> They decided that the best course would be to
                        recall the consul Valerius from Sicily, though he was outside the borders of
                        Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate instructed L. Manlius
                        the City praetor to write to him to that effect, and at the same time to
                        send on the despatch from M. Marcellus that he might understand the reason
                        for the senate recalling him rather than his colleague from his province.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was about this time that envoys
                        from King Syphax came to Rome. They enumerated the successful battles which
                        the king had fought against the Carthaginians, and declared that there was
                        no people to whom he was a more uncompromising foe than the people of
                        Carthage, and none towards whom he felt more friendly than the people of
                        Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He had already sent envoys to the
                        two Scipios in Spain, now he wished to ask for the friendship of Rome from
                        the fountain-head. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate not only
                        gave the envoys a gracious reply, but they in their turn sent envoys and
                        presents to the king-the men selected for the mission being L. Genucius, P.
                        Poetelius, and P. Popillius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The presents
                        they took with them were a purple toga and a purple tunic, an ivory chair
                        and a golden bowl weighing five pounds. After their visit to Syphax they
                        were commissioned to visit other petty kings in Africa and <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> carry as a present to each of them a toga
                        praetexta and a golden bowl, three pounds in weight. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> M. Atilius and Manlius Acilius were also despatched to
                        Alexandria, to Ptolemy and Cleopatra, to remind them of the alliance already
                        existing, and to renew the friendly relations with Rome. The presents they
                        carried to the king were a purple toga and a purple tunic and an ivory
                        chair; to the queen they gave an embroidered palla and a purple cloak.
                        During the summer in which these incidents occurred numerous portents were
                        reported from the neighbouring cities and country districts. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> A lamb is said to have been yeaned at Tusculum
                        with its udder full of milk; the summit of the temple of Jupiter was struck
                        by lightning and nearly the whole of the roof stripped off; <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> the ground in front of the gate of Anagnia was
                        similarly struck almost at the same time and continued burning for a day and
                        a night without anything to feed the fire; at Anagnia Compitum the birds had
                        deserted their nests in the grove of Diana; <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> at Tarracina snakes of an extraordinary size leaped out of the sea like
                        sporting fishes close to the harbour; at Tarquinii a pig had been farrowed
                        with the face of a man; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> in the district
                        of Capena four statues near the Grove of Feronia had sweated blood for a day
                        and a night. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The pontiffs decreed that
                        these portents should be expiated by the sacrifice of oxen; a day was
                        appointed for solemn intercessions to be offered up at all the shrines in
                        Rome, and on the following day similar intercessions were to be offered in
                        Campania, at the grove of Feronia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On receiving his letter of recall the
                        consul M. Valerius handed over the army and the administration of the
                        province to the praetor Cincius, and gave instructions to M. Valerius
                        Messala, the commander of the fleet, to sail with a part of his force to
                        Africa and harry <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the coast and at the
                        same time find out what he could about the plans and preparations of
                        Carthage. Then he left with ten vessels for Rome, which he reached after a
                        good voyage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Immediately on his arrival he
                        summoned a meeting of the senate and laid before them a report of his
                        administration. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For nearly sixty years, he
                        said, Sicily had been the scene of war both by land and sea, and the Romans
                        had suffered many serious defeats there. Now he had completely reduced the
                        province, there was not a Carthaginian in the island, nor was there a single
                        Sicilian amongst those who had been driven away who had not now returned.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They had all been repatriated, and
                        were settled in their own cities and ploughing their own fields. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Once more the desolated land was under tillage,
                        the land which enriched its cultivators with its produce and formed an
                        unfailing bulwark against scarcity for Rome in times of war and peace,
                        alike. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the consul had addressed the
                        senate, Muttines and others who had done good service to Rome were
                        introduced, and the promises which the consul had made were redeemed by the
                        bestowal of honours and rewards upon them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        A resolution was carried in the Assembly, with the sanction of the senate,
                        conferring the full Roman citizenship on Muttines. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> M. Valerius, meanwhile, having reached the African
                        shore with his fifty ships before daybreak, made a sudden descent on the
                        territory of Utica. Extending his depredations far and wide he secured
                        plunder of every kind including a large number of prisoners. With these
                        spoils he returned to his ships and sailed back to Sicily, entering the port
                        of Lilybaeum, within a fortnight of his departure. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The prisoners were subjected to a close examination,
                        and the following facts were elicited and duly forwarded to Laevinus that he
                        might understand the position in Africa: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        5000 Numidians were at Carthage with Gala's son, Masinissa, a young man of
                        great energy and enterprise; other mercenary troops were being raised
                        throughout Africa to be sent over to Spain to reinforce Hasdrubal, so that
                        he might have as large a force as possible with which to cross over into
                        Italy and join his brother, Hannibal. The Carthaginians, believed that in
                        adopting this plan they were sure of victory. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> In addition to these preparations an immense fleet was
                        being fitted out to recover Sicily, <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> and
                        it was expected to appear off the island in a short time. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The consul communicated this intelligence
                        to the senate, and they were so impressed by its importance that they
                        thought the consul ought not to wait for the elections, but return at once
                        to his province after naming a Dictator to preside over the elections.
                        Matters were delayed somewhat by the debate which followed. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> The consul said that when he reached Sicily he
                        would nominate M. Valerius Messalla, who was at that time commanding the
                        fleet, as Dictator; the senators on the other hand asserted that no one who
                        was outside Roman soil, i.e., who was beyond the frontiers of Italy, could
                        be nominated Dictator: <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> M. Lucretius, one
                        of the tribunes of the plebs, took the sense of the House upon the question,
                        and the senate made a decree, requiring the consul, previously to his
                        departure from the City, to put the question to the people, whom they wished
                        to have nominated Dictator, and then to nominate the man whom the people had
                        chosen. If the consul declined to do this, then the praetor was to put the
                        question, and if he refused, then the tribunes were to bring the matter
                        before the people. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> As the consul refused
                        to submit to the people what was within his own rights, and had inhibited
                        the praetor from doing so either, it fell to the tribunes to put the
                        question, and the plebs resolved that Q. Fulvius, who was then at Capua,
                        should be nominated. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> But the day before
                        the Assembly met, the consul left secretly in the night for Sicily, and the
                        senate, thus left in the lurch, ordered a despatch to be sent to Marcellus,
                        urging him to come to the aid of the Commonwealth which his colleague had
                        deserted, and nominate the man whom the people had resolved to have as
                        Dictator. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Q. Fulvius was accordingly
                        nominated Dictator by the consul M. Claudius, and under the same resolution
                        of the plebs P. Licinius Crassus, the Pontifex Maximus, was named by Q.
                        Fulvius as his Master of the Horse. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the Dictator's arrival in Rome he sent
                        C. Sempronius Blaesus, who had been his second in command in Capua, to the
                        army in Etruria, to relieve C. Calpurnius, to whom he had sent written
                        instructions to take over the command of his own army at Capua. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> He fixed the earliest possible date for the
                        elections, but they could not be closed owing to a difference between the
                        tribunes and the Dictator. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The junior
                        century of the Galerian tribe had obtained the first place in the order of
                        voting, and they had declared for Q. Fulvius and Q. Fabius. The other
                        centuries, summoned in their order, would have gone the same way, had not
                        two of the tribunes of the plebs-Caius Arrenius and his brother
                        Lucius-intervened. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They said that it was
                        infringing the rights of his fellow-citizens for a magistrate to extend his
                        period of office, and it was <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> a still
                        greater offence for the man who was conducting the elections to allow
                        himself to be elected. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If, therefore, the
                        Dictator accepted votes for himself, they should place their veto on the
                        proceedings, but if the names of any others than himself were put up, they
                        would not stop the election. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Dictator
                        defended the procedure by alleging the authority of the senate and a
                        resolution of the Assembly as precedents. "When Cneius Servilius," he said,
                        "was consul and the other consul had fallen in battle at Lake Thrasymenus,
                        this question was referred by authority of the senate to the plebs, and they
                        passed a resolution that as long as there was war in Italy the people had
                        the right to reappoint as consuls, any who had been consuls, as often as
                        they pleased. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I have an old precedent for
                        my action in this instance in the case of L. Postumius Megellus, who was
                        elected consul together with C. Junius Bubulcus at the very election over
                        which he was presiding as interrex, and a recent one in the case of
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> Q. Fabius Maximus, who would
                        certainly never have allowed himself to be re-elected if it had not been in
                        the interest of the State." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A long discussion followed, and at last
                        an agreement was come to between the Dictator and the tribunes that they
                        would abide by the opinion of the senate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        In view of the critical position of the State, the senate saw that the
                        conduct of affairs ought to be in the hands of old and tried men of ability
                        and experience in war, and that there ought to be no delay in the elections.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The tribunes gave way and the
                        elections were held. Q. Fabius Maximus was returned as consul for the fifth
                        time, and Q. Fulvius Flaccus for the fourth time. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The elections of praetors followed, the successful
                        candidates being: L. Veturius Philo, T. Quinctius Crispinus, C. Hostilius
                        Tubulus and C. Aurunculeius. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As soon as
                        the magistrates were appointed for the year, Q. Fulvius laid down his
                        office. At the close of this summer a Carthaginian fleet of forty vessels
                        under the command of Hamilcar sailed across to Sardinia and laid waste the
                        territory of Olbia. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> On the appearance of
                        the praetor P. Manlius Volso with his army, they sailed round to the other
                        side of the island and devastated the district of Caralita, after which they
                        returned to Africa with every description of plunder. Several Roman priests
                        died this year and others were appointed in their place. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> C. Servilius was made pontiff in place of T. Otacilius
                        Crassus. Tiberius Sempronius Longus, son of Tiberius, was appointed augur in
                        place of T. Otacilius Crassus, Tiberius Sempronius Longus, son of Tiberius,
                        was similarly appointed one of the Keepers of the Sacred Books in place of
                        Ti. Sempronius Longus, son of Tiberius. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        The deaths took place also of M. Marcius, the Rex Sacrorum, and M. Aemilius
                        Papus, the Curio Maximus; these vacancies were not filled up during the
                        year. The censors appointed this year were L. Veturius Philo and P. Licinius
                        Crassus, the Pontifex Maximus. Licinius Crassus had not been either consul
                        or praetor before he was made censor, he went straight from the aedileship
                        to the censorship. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> These censors,
                        however, did not revise the roll of senators, nor did they transact any
                        public business whatever; the death of L. Veturius put an end to their
                        censorship, for Licinius at once resigned office. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> The curule aediles, L. Veturius and P. Licinius Varus,
                        celebrated the Roman Games for one day. The plebeian aediles, Q. Catius and
                        L. Porcius Licinius, devoted the money derived from fines to the casting of
                        bronze statues for the temple of Ceres; they also celebrated the Plebeian
                        Games with great splendour, considering the resources available at the time.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of the year C. Laelius
                        arrived in Rome, thirty-four days after leaving Tarraco. His entrance into
                        the City with his train of prisoners was watched by a great crowd of
                        spectators. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The next day he appeared
                        before the senate and reported that Carthage, the capital city of Spain, had
                        been captured in a single day, whilst several revolted cities had been
                        recovered and new ones received into alliance. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The information gained from the prisoners tallied with
                        that conveyed in the despatches of M. Valerius Messalla. What produced the
                        greatest impression on the senate was the threatened march of Hasdrubal into
                        Italy, which could hardly hold its ground against Hannibal and his arms.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When Laelius was brought before the
                        Assembly he repeated the statements already made in the senate. A day of
                        solemn thanksgiving for P. Scipio's victories was decreed, and C. Laelius
                        was ordered to return as soon as possible to Spain with the ships he had
                        brought over. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Following many authorities,
                        I have referred the capture of New Carthage to this year, though I am quite
                        aware that some writers place it in the following year. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> This, however, appears improbable, as Scipio could
                        hardly have spent a whole year in Spain without doing anything. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The new consuls entered office on March 15th, and
                        on the same day the senate assigned them their province. They were both to
                        command in Italy; Tarentum was to be the objective for Fabius; Fulvius was
                        to operate in Lucania and Bruttium. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> M.
                        Claudius Marcellus had his command extended for a year The praetors balloted
                        for their provinces; C. Hostilius Tubulus obtained the City jurisdiction; L.
                        Venturius Philo the alien jurisdiction together with Gaul; Capua fell to T.
                        Quinctius Crispinus, and Sardinia to C. Aurunculeius. The following was the
                        distribution of the armies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two
                        legions which M. Valerius Laevinus had in Sicily were assigned to Fulvius,
                        those which C. Calpurnius had commanded in Etruria were transferred to Q.
                        Fabius; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> C. Calpurnius was to remain in
                        Etruria and the City force was to form his command; T. Quinctius was to
                        retain the army which Quintus Fulvius had had; C. Hostilius was to take over
                        his province and army from the propraetor C. Laetorius who was at the time
                        at Ariminum. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The legions who had been
                        serving with the consul were assigned to M. Marcellus. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> M. Valerius and L. Cincius had their term in Sicily
                        extended, and the army of Cannae was placed under their command; they were
                        required to bring it up to full strength out of any that remained of Cn.
                        Fulvius' legions. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These were hunted up
                        and sent by the consuls into Sicily, where they were subjected to the same
                        humiliating conditions as the defeated of Cannae and those belonging to Cn.
                        Fulvius' army who had already been sent to Sicily as a punishment by the
                        senate. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The legions with which P. Manlius
                        Vulso had held Sardinia were placed under C. Aurunculeius and remained in
                        the island. P. Sulpicius retained his command for another year with
                        instructions to employ the same legion and fleet against Macedonia which he
                        had previously had. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Orders were issued
                        for thirty quinqueremes to be despatched from Sicily to the consul at
                        Tarentum, the rest of the fleet was <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> to
                        sail to Africa and ravage the coast, under the command of M. Valerius
                        Laevinus, or if he did not go himself he was to send either L . Cincius or
                        M. Valerius Messalla. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> There were no
                        changes in Spain except that Scipio and Silanus had their commands extended,
                        not for a year but until such time as they should be recalled by the senate.
                        Such were the distribution of the provinces and the military commands for
                        the year. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the public attention was fixed on
                        more important matters an old controversy was revived on the occasion of the
                        election of a Curio Maximus, in place of M. Aemilius. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> There was one candidate, a plebeian, C. Mamilius
                        Atellus, and the patricians contended that no votes ought to be counted for
                        him, as none but a patrician had ever yet held that dignity. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes, on being appealed to, referred the
                        matter to the senate, the senate left it to the decision of the people. C.
                        Mamilius Atellus was accordingly the first plebeian to be elected Curio
                        Maximus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> P. Licinius, the Pontifex
                        Maximus, compelled C. Valerius Flaccus to be consecrated, against his will,
                        a Flamen of Jupiter. C. Laetorius was appointed one of the Keepers of the
                        Sacred Books in place of Q. Mucius Scaevola, deceased. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Had not the bad repute into which Valerius had fallen
                        given place to a good and honourable character, I should have preferred to
                        keep silence as to the cause of his forcible consecration. It was in
                        consequence of his careless and dissolute life as a young man, which had
                        estranged his own brother Lucius and his other relations, that the Pontifex
                        Maximus made him a Flamen. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When his
                        thoughts became wholly occupied with the performance of his sacred duties he
                        threw off his former character so completely that amongst all the young men
                        in Rome, none held a higher place in the esteem and approbation of the
                        leading patricians, whether personal friends or strangers to him. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Encouraged by this general feeling he gained
                        sufficient self-confidence to revive a custom which, owing to the low
                        character of former Flamens, had long fallen into disuse; he took his seat
                        in the senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as he appeared L.
                        Licinius the praetor had him removed. He claimed it as the ancient privilege
                        of the priesthood and pleaded that it was conferred together with the toga
                        praetexta and curule chair as belonging to the Flamen's office. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The praetor refused to rest the question upon
                        obsolete precedents drawn from the annalists and appealed to recent usage.
                        No Flamen of Jupiter, he argued, had exercised that right within the memory
                        of their fathers or their grandfathers. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The tribunes, when appealed to, gave it as their opinion that as it was
                        through the supineness and negligence of individual Flamens that the
                        practice had fallen into abeyance, the priesthood ought not to be deprived
                        of its rights. They led the Flamen into the senate amid the warm approval of
                        the House and without any opposition even from the praetor, though every one
                        felt that Flaccus had gained his seat more through the purity and integrity
                        of his life than through any right inherent in his office. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Before the consuls left for their
                        provinces they raised two legions in the City to supply the necessary drafts
                        for the armies. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The old City army was
                        made over by the consul Fulvius to his brother Caius for service in Etruria,
                        the legions which were in Etruria being sent to Rome. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The consul Fabius ordered his son Quintus to take to M.
                        Valerius, the proconsul in Sicily, the remains, so far as they had been got
                        together, of the army of Fulvius. They amounted to 4344 men. He was at the
                        same time to receive from the proconsul two legions and thirty quinqueremes.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The withdrawal of these legions from
                        the island did not weaken the occupying force in either numbers or
                        efficiency, for besides the two old legions which had now been brought up to
                            <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> full strength, the proconsul had a
                        large body of Numidian deserters, mounted and unmounted, and he also
                        enlisted those Sicilians who had served with Epicydes and the Carthaginians,
                        and were seasoned soldiers. By strengthening each of the Roman legions with
                        these foreign auxiliaries he gave them the appearance of two complete
                        armies. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> One of these he placed under L.
                        Cincius, for the protection of that part of the island which had constituted
                        the kingdom of Hiero; the other he retained under his own command for the
                        defence of the rest of Sicily. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> He also
                        broke up his fleet of seventy ships so as to make it available for the
                        defence of the entire coast-line of the island. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> Escorted by Muttines' cavalry he made a tour of the
                        island in order to inspect the land and note which parts were cultivated and
                        which were uncultivated, and commend or rebuke the owners accordingly.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Owing to his care and attention there
                        was so large a yield of corn that he was able to send some to Rome, and also
                        accumulate a store at Catina to furnish supplies for the army which was to
                        pass the summer at Tarentum. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The deportation of the soldiers to Sicily,
                        most of whom belonged to the Latin and the allied nationalities, very nearly
                        caused a great rising; so often do small occasions involve serious
                        consequences. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Meetings were held amongst
                        the Latins and the allied communities in which they complained loudly that
                        for ten years they had been drained by levies and war-taxes; every year they
                        fought only to sustain a great defeat, those who were not killed in battle
                        were carried off by sickness. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A
                        fellow-citizen who was enlisted by the Romans was more lost to them than one
                        who had been made prisoner by the Carthaginians, for the latter was sent
                        back to his home without ransom, the former was sent out of Italy into what
                        was really exile rather than military service. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> There the men who had fought at Cannae had been for
                        eight years wearing out their lives, and there they would die before the
                        enemy, who had never been stronger than he was today, quitted Italian soil.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If the old soldiers were not to
                        return, and fresh ones were always being enlisted, there would soon be
                        nobody left. They would be compelled therefore, before they reached the last
                        stage of depopulation and famine, to refuse to Rome what the necessities of
                        their situation would very soon make it impossible to grant. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> If the Romans saw that this was the unanimous
                        determination of their allies, they would assuredly begin to think about
                        making peace with Carthage. Otherwise Italy would never be free from war as
                        long as Hannibal was alive. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such was the
                        general tone of the meetings. There were at the time thirty colonies
                        belonging to Rome. Twelve of these announced to the consuls through their
                        representatives in Rome that they had no means from which to furnish either
                        men or money. The colonies in question were Ardea, Nepete, Sutrium, Alba,
                        Carseoli, Sora, Suessa, Cercei, Setia, Cales, Narnia and Interamna. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls, startled by this
                        unprecedented step, wanted to frighten them out of such a detestable course,
                        and thought that they would succeed better by uncompromising sternness than
                        by adopting gentle methods. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "You
                        colonists," they said, "have dared to address us, the consuls, in language
                        which we cannot bring ourselves to repeat openly in the senate, for it is
                        not simply a refusal of military obligations, but an open revolt against
                        Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> You must go back to your respective
                        colonies at once, while your treason is still confined to words, and consult
                        your people. You are not Capuans or Tarentines, but Romans, from Rome you
                        sprang, from Rome you have been planted in colonies on land taken from the
                        enemy, in order that you may augment her dominion. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Whatever duties children owe to their parents, you owe
                        to Rome, if indeed you feel a spark of affection for her or cherish any
                        memories of your mother country. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> So you
                        must begin your deliberations afresh, for what you are now so recklessly
                        contemplating means the betrayal of the sovereignty of Rome and the
                        surrender of victory into the hands of Hannibal." <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Such were the arguments which each of the consuls
                        advanced at considerable length, but they produced no impression. The envoys
                        said that there was no reply for them to take home, nor was there any other
                        policy for their senate to consider since there was not a man left for
                        conscription nor any money for his pay. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        As the consuls saw that their determination was unshaken they brought the
                        matter before the senate. Here such general consternation and alarm were
                        felt that most of the senators declared that the empire was doomed, other
                        colonies would take the same course, as would also the allies; all had
                        agreed together to betray the City of Rome to Hannibal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls spoke in reassuring terms to
                        the senate. They declared that the other colonies were as loyal and dutiful
                        as ever, and even those colonies which had forgotten their duty would learn
                        to respect the empire if representatives of the government were sent amongst
                        them, with words of admonishment and rebuke, not of supplication or
                        entreaty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate left it to the
                        consuls to take such action as they deemed best in the interests of the
                        State. After sounding the temper of the other colonies, they summoned their
                        delegates to Rome and questioned them as to whether they had soldiers in
                        readiness in accordance with the terms of their constitution. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> M. Sextilius of Fregellae, acting as spokesman
                        for the eighteen colonies, replied that the stipulated number of soldiers
                        were ready for service; if more were needed they would furnish more, and do
                        their utmost to carry out the wishes and commands of the Roman people.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They had no insufficiency of
                        resources, they had more than a sufficiency of loyalty and goodwill.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls told them in reply that
                        they felt they could not praise their conduct as they deserved unless the
                        senate as a body thanked them, and with this, bade them follow them into the
                        House. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A resolution was adopted by the
                        senate and read to them, couched in the most complimentary and laudatory
                        terms possible. The consuls were then charged to introduce them to the
                        Assembly and, among the other splendid services which they had rendered to
                        them and their ancestors, to make special mention of this fresh obligation
                        which they had conferred on the Republic. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Though so many generations have passed away, their names ought not to be
                        passed over in silence nor their due meed of praise withheld. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Signia, Norba, Saticula, Fregellae, Lucerium,
                        Venusia, Brundisium, Hadria, Formae and Ariminum; on the Tyrrhenian Sea,
                        Pontia, Paestum, Cosa; and the inland colonies, Beneventum, Aesernum,
                        Spoletum, Placentia and Cremona-these were the colonies by whose aid and
                        succour the dominion of Rome was upheld, it was these who were publicly
                        thanked in the senate and before the Assembly. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The senate forbade all mention of the other colonies
                        who had proved false to the empire; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the
                        consuls were to ignore their representatives, neither retaining them nor
                        dismissing them nor addressing them, but leaving them severely alone. This
                        silent rebuke seemed most in accordance with the dignity of the Roman
                        people. The other preparations for war now occupied the attention of the
                        consuls. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was decided that the
                        "vicesimary gold" which was kept as a reserve for extreme emergencies in the
                        secret treasury should now be brought out. Four thousand pounds of gold were
                        produced. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Of this 550 pounds were given
                        to each of the consuls and to the proconsuls M. Marcellus and P. Sulpicius.
                        A similar amount was given to the praetor L. Veturius, who had drawn in the
                        lottery the province of Gaul, and a special grant of 100 pounds was placed
                        in the hands of the consul Fabius, to be carried into the citadel of
                        Tarentum. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The rest was made use of in
                        purchasing, for cash at contract prices, clothing for the army in Spain,
                        whose successful operations were enhancing their own and their general's
                        reputation. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was further decided that before the
                        consul left the City certain portents should be expiated. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Various places had been struck by lightning: the statue
                        of Jupiter on the Alban Mount and a tree near his temple, a grove at Ostia,
                        the city wall and temple of Fortune at Capua and the wall and one of the
                        gates at Sinuessa. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some people asserted
                        that the water at Alba had run blood and that in the sanctuary of the temple
                        of Fors Fortuna in Rome a statuette in the diadem of the goddess had fallen
                        of itself on to her hand. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was
                        confidently believed that at Privernum an ox had spoken and that a vulture
                        had flown down on to a booth in the crowded forum. At Sinuessa it was
                        reported that a child was born of doubtful sex, these are commonly called
                        androgyni-a word like many others <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                        borrowed from the Greek, a language which readily admits compound words-also
                        that it had rained milk and that a boy had been born with an elephant's
                        head. These portents were expiated by sacrifices of full-grown victims, and
                        a day was appointed for special intercessions at all the shrines. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> It was further decreed that the praetor C.
                        Hostilius should vow and celebrate the Games of Apollo in strict accordance
                        with the practice of recent years. During this interval the consul Q.
                        Fulvius convened the Assembly for the election of censors. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Two men were elected, neither of whom had attained the
                        dignity of consul-M. Cornelius Cethegus and P. Sempronius Tuditanus. A
                        measure was adopted by the plebs, with the sanction of the senate,
                        authorising these censors to let the territory of Capua to individual
                        occupiers. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The revision of the senatorial
                        roll was delayed through a difference between them as to who ought to be
                        chosen as leader of the senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        selection had fallen to Sempronius; Cornelius, however, insisted that they
                        ought to follow the traditional usage in accordance with which the man who
                        had been the first of <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> all his surviving
                        contemporaries to be appointed censor was always chosen as leader of the
                        senate and in this case it was T. Manlius Torquatus. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Sempronius replied that the gods who had given him by
                        lot the right of choosing had also given him the right to make a free
                        choice; he should therefore act on his own discretion and choose Q. Fabius
                        Maximus, the man whom he claimed as foremost of all the Romans, a claim he
                        would make good before Hannibal himself. After a lengthy argument his
                        colleague gave way and Sempronius selected Q. Fabius Maximus as leader of
                        the senate. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The revision of the roll was
                        then proceeded with, eight names being struck off, amongst them that of M.
                        Caecilius Metellus, the author of the infamous proposal to abandon Italy
                        after Cannae. For the same reason some were struck out of the equestrian
                        order, but there were very few on whom the taint of that disgrace rested.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> All those who had belonged to the
                        cavalry of the legions of Cannae, which were in Italy at the time-and there
                        was a considerable number of them-were deprived of their regulation horses.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> This punishment was made still
                        heavier by an extension of their compulsory service. The years they had
                        served with the horses furnished by the State were not to count, they were
                        to serve their ten years from that date with their own horses. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> A large number of men were discovered who ought
                        to have served, and all those who had reached the age of seventeen at the
                        commencement of the war and had not done any military service were degraded
                        to the aerarii. The censors next signed contracts for the rebuilding of the
                        places round the Forum which had been destroyed by fire. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> These comprised seven shops, the fish market and the
                        Hall of Vestal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After despatching their business in Rome
                        the consuls started for the war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fulvius
                        was the first to leave and went on in advance to Capua. After a few days
                        Fabius followed, and in a personal interview with his colleague strongly
                        urged him, as he had Marcellus by letter, to do his utmost to keep Hannibal
                        on the defensive while he himself was attacking Tarentum. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He pointed out that the enemy had now been driven back
                        on all sides, and if he were deprived of that city there would be no
                        position where he could make a stand, no sure place for retreat, there would
                        be no longer anything to keep him in Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> He also sent a message to the commandant of the garrison which Laevinus
                        had stationed in Regium as a check against the Bruttii. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> This was a force of 8000 men, the majority drawn, as
                        stated above, from Agathyrna in Sicily, and all accustomed to live by
                        rapine; their numbers had been swelled by deserters from Bruttium, who were
                        quite their equals in recklessness and love of desperate adventures.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Fabius ordered the commandant to take
                        this force into Bruttium and lay waste the country and then attack the city
                        of Caulonia. They carried out their orders with alacrity and zest, and after
                        plundering and scattering the peasants, they made a furious attack on the
                        citadel. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul's letter and his own
                        belief that no Roman general was so good a match for Hannibal as himself
                        stirred Marcellus into action. As soon as there was plenty of forage in the
                        fields he broke up his winter quarters and confronted Hannibal at Canusium.
                        The Carthaginian was trying to induce the Canusians to revolt, but as soon
                        as he heard of the approach of Marcellus, he moved away. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As the country was open, affording no cover for an
                        ambuscade, he began to withdraw into a more wooded district. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Marcellus followed at his heels, fixed his camp
                        close to Hannibal's, and the moment he had completed his entrenchments he
                        led his legions out to battle. Hannibal saw no necessity for risking a
                        general engagement, and sent out detached troops of cavalry and bodies of
                        slingers to skirmish. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He was, however,
                        drawn into the battle which he had tried to avoid, for after he had been
                        marching all night, Marcellus caught him up in level and open country, and
                        prevented him from fortifying his camp by attacking the entrenching parties
                        on all sides. A pitched battled ensued in which the whole strength of both
                        armies was engaged, and at the approach of nightfall they separated on equal
                        terms. Both the camps, separated by only a small interval, were hastily
                        fortified before dark. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as it
                        began to grow light on the morrow Marcellus marched his men on to the field
                        and Hannibal accepted the challenge. He said much to encourage his men,
                        bidding them remember Thrasymenus and Cannae, and tame the insolence of
                        their foe, who was incessantly pressing them and following on their heels,
                        preventing them from fortifying their camp, giving them no breathing space,
                        no time to look round. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Day after day two
                        objects met their eyes at the same time, the rising sun and the Roman
                        battle-line on the plain. If the enemy got away with heavy loss after one
                        battle, he would conduct his operations more quietly and deliberately.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Animated by their general's words and
                        exasperated at the defiant way in which the enemy challenged and provoked
                        them, they began the battle with great spirit. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> After more than two hours' fighting the allied
                        contingent on the Roman right including the special levies, began to give
                        way. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> As soon as Marcellus saw this he
                        brought the 10th legion up to the front. They were slow in coming up, and as
                        the others were becoming unsteady and falling back, the whole line was
                        gradually thrown into disorder and ultimately routed. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Their fears got the better of them and they took to
                        flight. 2700 Romans and allies fell in the battle and during the pursuit;
                        amongst them were four centurions and two military tribunes, M. Licinius and
                        M. Helvius. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Four standards were lost out
                        of the wing which began the fight, and two from the legion which came up in
                        support. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they were once more in camp,
                        Marcellus addressed such an impassioned and stinging remonstrance to his men
                        that they suffered more from the words of their angry general than in the
                        adverse struggle which they had kept up the livelong day. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> "As matters are," he said, "I am devoutly thankful to
                        heaven that the enemy did not actually attack the camp while you in your
                        panic were dashing into the gates and over the rampart; you would most
                        certainly have abandoned your camp in the same wild terror in which you
                        deserted the field. What is the meaning of this panic, this terror?
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> What has suddenly come to you that you
                        should forget who you are and with whom you are fighting? These surely are
                        precisely the same enemies as those whom you spent last summer in defeating
                        and pursuing, whom you have been closely following up these last few days,
                        whilst they fled before you night and day, whom you have worn out in
                        skirmishes, whom as late as yesterday you prevented from either advancing or
                        encamping. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I pass over incidents for which
                        you may possibly take credit to yourselves and will only mention one
                        circumstance which ought to fill you with shame and remorse. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Last night, as you know, you drew off from the
                        field after holding your own against the enemy. How has the situation
                        changed during the night or throughout the day? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Have your forces been weakened or his strengthened? But
                        really, I do not seem to myself to be speaking to my army or to Roman
                        soldiers, it is only your bodies and weapons that are the same. Do you
                        imagine if you had had the spirit of Romans that the enemy would have seen
                        your backs or captured a single standard from either maniple or cohort?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So far he has prided himself upon the
                        Roman legions he has cut up, you have been the first to confer upon him
                        today the glory of having put a Roman army to flight." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then there arose a general cry of
                        supplication; the men begged him to pardon them for that day's work, and to
                        make use of his soldiers' courage whenever and wherever he would. "Very
                        well, soldiers," he said, "I will make proof of it and lead you to battle
                        tomorrow, so that you may win the pardon you crave as victors rather as
                        vanquished." <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He ordered the cohorts who
                        had lost their standards to be put on barley rations, and the centurions of
                        the maniples whose standards were lost were ordered to stand away from their
                        fellows without their military cloaks and girdles and with their swords
                        drawn. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> All the troops, mounted and
                        unmounted, were ordered to assemble under arms the following day. They were
                        then dismissed and all acknowledged that they had been justly and deservedly
                        censured, and that in the whole army there was not one who had that day
                        shown himself a man except their commander. They felt bound to make
                        satisfaction to him either by their deaths or by a brilliant victory.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The next morning they appeared
                        equipped and armed according to orders. The general expressed his approval
                        and announced that those who had been the first to flee and the cohorts
                        which had lost their standards would be placed in the forefront of the
                        battle. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He went on to say that all must
                        fight and conquer, and that they must, one and all, do their utmost to
                        prevent the rumour of yesterday's flight from reaching Rome before the news
                        of that day's victory. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They were then
                        ordered to strengthen themselves with food, so that if the fight was
                        prolonged they might hold out. After all had been said and done to raise
                        their courage, they marched to battle. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this was reported to Hannibal, he
                        remarked, "Evidently we have to do with an enemy who cannot endure either
                        good fortune or bad. If he is victorious he follows up the vanquished in
                        fierce pursuit; if he is defeated he renews the struggle with his
                        conquerors." <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then he ordered the advance
                        to be sounded, and led his men on to the field. The fighting was much hotter
                        than on the previous day; the Carthaginians did their utmost to maintain the
                        prestige they had gained, the Romans were equally determined to wipe out the
                        disgrace of their defeat. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The contingents
                        who had formed the Roman left and the cohorts who had lost their standards
                        were fighting in the front line, and the twentieth legion was stationed on
                        their right. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> L. Cornelius Lentulus and C:
                        Claudius Nero commanded the wings; Marcellus remained in the centre to
                        encourage his men and mark how they bore themselves in battle. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal's front line consisted of his Spanish
                        troops, the flower of his army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After a
                        long and undecided struggle he ordered the elephants to be brought up into
                        the fighting line, in the hope that they would create confusion and panic
                        among the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first they threw the
                        front ranks into disorder, trampling some underfoot and scattering those
                        round in wild alarm. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> One flank was thus
                        exposed, and the rout would have spread much farther had not C. Decimius
                        Flavus, one of the military tribunes, snatched the standard of the foremost
                        maniple of hastati and called on them to follow him. He took them to where
                        the animals trotting close to one another were creating the greatest tumult,
                        and told his men to hurl their javelins at them. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Owing to the short distance and the huge mark presented
                        by the beasts, crowded as they were together, every missile went home. They
                        were not all hit, but those in whose flanks the javelins were sticking
                        turned the uninjured ones to flight, for these animals cannot be depended
                        upon. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Not only the men who first attacked
                        them, but every soldier within reach hurled his javelin at them as they
                        galloped back into the Carthaginian ranks, where they caused much more
                        destruction than they had caused amongst the enemy. They dashed about much
                        more recklessly and did far greater damage when driven by their fears, than
                        when directed by their drivers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Where the
                        line was broken by their charge, the Roman standards at once advanced, and
                        the broken and demoralised enemy was put to rout without much fighting.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Marcellus sent his cavalry after the
                        fugitives, and the pursuit did not slacken till they had been driven in wild
                        panic to their camp. To add to their confusion and terror two of the
                        elephants had fallen and blocked up the camp gate, and the men had to
                        scramble into their camp over fosse and rampart. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> It was here that they suffered the heaviest loss; 8000
                        men were killed and five elephants. The victory was anything but a bloodless
                        one for the Romans; out of the two legions some 1700 men were killed and
                        1300 of the allied contingents, besides a very large number of wounded in
                        both divisions. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The following night
                        Hannibal shifted his camp. Marcellus, though anxious to follow him, was
                        unable to do so owing to the enormous number of wounded. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Reconnoitring parties who were sent out to watch his
                        movements reported that he had taken the direction of Bruttium. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time the Hirpini, the Lucani
                        and the Vulcientes surrendered to the consul Q. Fulvius, and delivered up
                        the garrisons which Hannibal had placed in their cities. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He accepted their submission graciously, and only
                        reproached them for the mistake they had made in the past. This led the
                        Bruttians to hope that similar indulgence might be shown to them, and they
                        sent the two men who were of highest rank amongst them. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Vivius and his brother Paccius, to ask for favourable
                        terms of surrender. The consul Q. Fabius carried by storm the town of
                        Manduria, in the country of the Sallentines. 3000 prisoners were secured and
                        a considerable amount of plunder. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From
                        there he marched to Tarentum, and fixed his camp at the very mouth of the
                        harbour. Some of the ships which Laevinus had had for the purpose of keeping
                        the sea open for supplies he loaded with the engines and apparatus necessary
                        for battering the walls; others he made use of for carrying artillery and
                        stores and projectiles of every kind. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Only
                        the transports which were propelled by oars were there made use of, so that
                        whilst some of the troops could bring up their engines and scaling ladders
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> close to the walls, others could
                        beat off the defenders from the walls by attacking them at a distance from
                        the ships. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These vessels were so fitted up
                        that they could attack the city from the open sea without any interference
                        from the enemy, as the Carthaginian fleet had sailed across to Corcyra to
                        assist Philip in his campaign against the Aetolians. The force besieging
                        Caulo, hearing of Hannibal's approach and fearing a surprise, withdrew to a
                        position on the hills which was safe from any immediate attack. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While Fabius was besieging Tarentum an
                        incident, of slight importance in itself, helped him to achieve a great
                        success. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Tarentines had been furnished
                        by Hannibal with a garrison of Bruttian troops. One of their officers was
                        deeply in love with a young woman who had a brother in Fabius' army. She had
                        written to tell him of the intimacy that had sprung up between her and a
                        stranger who was rich and held a high position amongst his countrymen.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The brother was led to hope that
                        through his sister's means her lover might be led on to any lengths, and he
                        communicated his anticipations to the consul. The idea did not seem at all
                        an unreasonable one, and he received instructions to cross the lines and
                        enter Tarentum as a deserter. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After being
                        introduced to the officer by his sister and getting on friendly terms with
                        him, he cautiously sounded his disposition without betraying his real
                        object. When he had satisfied himself as to the weakness of his character he
                        called in his sister's aid, and through her coaxing and blandishments the
                        man was persuaded to betray the position which he was in charge of.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the time and method of carrying
                        out the project were arranged, a soldier was despatched from the city at
                        night to make his way through the outposts and report to the consul what had
                        been done and what arrangements had been made. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At the first watch Fabius gave the signal
                        for action to the troops in the citadel and those who were guarding the
                        harbour, and then marched right round the harbour and took up his position
                        without being observed on the east side of the town. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Then he ordered the trumpets to sound at the same
                        moment from the citadel, the harbour and the ships which had been brought up
                        from the open sea. The greatest shouting and uproar was designedly raised in
                        just those parts where there was least danger of an attack. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> The consul meanwhile kept his men perfectly
                        quiet. Democrates, who had formerly commanded the fleet, happened to be in
                        charge of that part of the defences. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        Finding all quiet round him whilst elsewhere there was shouting and tumult
                        as though the city had been taken, he feared to remain where he was in case
                        the consul should storm the place and break in somewhere else. So he led his
                        men up to the citadel from which the most alarming noise proceeded.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> From the time that had elapsed and
                        the silence which followed the excited shouts and calls to arms, Fabius
                        judged that the garrison had withdrawn from that part of the fortifications.
                        He at once ordered the scaling ladders to be carried to that part of the
                        walls where he understood from the traitor that the Bruttii were mounting
                        guard. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> With their aid and connivance that
                        section of the fortifications was carried, and the Romans made their way
                        into the town after breaking down the nearest gate to allow the main body of
                        their comrades to march in. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Raising their
                        battle shout they went on to the forum; which they reached about sunrise
                        without meeting a single armed enemy. All the defenders who had been engaged
                        at the citadel and the harbour now combined to attack them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The fighting in the forum commenced with
                        an impetuosity which was not sustained. The Tarentine was no match for the
                        Roman either in courage or weapons or military training or bodily strength
                        and vigour. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They hurled their javelins,
                        and that was all; almost before they came to close quarters they turned and
                        fled through the streets, seeking shelter in their own homes and in their
                        friends' houses. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Two of their leaders,
                        Nico and Democrates, fell fighting bravely; Philemenus, who had been the
                        prime agent in delivering the city up to Hannibal, rode at full speed out of
                        the battle, but though his riderless horse was recognised soon afterwards
                        whilst straying about the city, his body was nowhere found. It was commonly
                        believed that he had been pitched headlong from his horse down an
                        unprotected well. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Carthalo the commandant
                        of the garrison, had laid down his arms and was going to <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> the consul to remind him of the old tie of hospitality
                        between their fathers when he was killed by a soldier who met him.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Those found with arms and those who
                        had none were massacred indiscriminately, Carthaginians and Tarentines met
                        the same fate. Many even of the Bruttians were killed in different parts of
                        the town, either by mistake or to satisfy an old-standing hate, or to
                        suppress any rumour of its capture through treachery, by making it appear as
                        though it had been taken by storm. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After
                        the carnage followed the sack of the city. It is said that 30,000 slaves
                        were captured together with an enormous quantity of silver plate and
                        bullion, 83 pounds' weight of gold and a collection of statues and pictures
                        almost equal to that which had adorned Syracuse. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Fabius, however, showed a nobler spirit than Marcellus
                        had exhibited in Sicily; he kept his hands off that kind of spoil. When his
                        secretary asked him what he wished to have done with some colossal
                        statues-they were deities, each represented in his appropriate dress and in
                        a fighting attitude-he ordered them to be left to the Tarentines who had
                        felt their wrath. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The wall which separated
                        the city from the citadel was completely demolished. </p>
                    <p> Hannibal had in the meanwhile received the surrender of the force which was
                        investing Caulo. As soon as he heard that Tarentum was being attacked he
                        hurried to its relief, marching night and day. On receiving the news of its
                        capture, he remarked, "The Romans too have their Hannibal, we have lost
                        Tarentum by the same practices by which we gained it." <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> To prevent his retirement from appearing like a
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> flight he encamped at a distance of
                        about five miles from the city, and after staying there for a few days he
                        fell back on Metapontum. From this place he sent two of the townsmen with a
                        letter to Fabius at Tarentum. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It was
                        written by the civic authorities, and stated that they were prepared to
                        surrender Metapontum and its Carthaginian garrison if the consul would
                        pledge his word that they should not suffer for their conduct in the past.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Fabius believed the letter to be
                        genuine and handed the bearers a reply addressed to their chiefs, fixing the
                        date of his arrival at Metapontum. This was taken to Hannibal. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Naturally delighted to find that even Fabius was
                        not proof against his stratagems, he disposed his force in ambuscade not far
                        from Metapontum. Before leaving Tarentum Fabius consulted the sacred
                        chickens, and on two occasions they gave an unfavourable omen. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> He also consulted the gods of sacrifice, and
                        after they had inspected the victim the augurs warned him to be on his guard
                        against plots and ambuscades on the part of the enemy. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> As he did not come at the appointed time, the
                        Metapontines were again sent to him to hasten his movements, and were
                        promptly arrested. Terrified at the prospect of examination under torture,
                        they disclosed the plot. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> P. Scipio had spent the whole winter in
                        winning over the various Spanish tribes, either by bribes or by restoring
                        those of their countrymen who had been taken as hostages or prisoners. At
                        the commencement of summer Edesco, a famous Spanish chieftain, came to visit
                        him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His wife and children were in the
                        hands of the Romans, but that was not the only reason why he came. He was
                        influenced by the change which Fortune apparently was bringing about over
                        the whole of Spain in favour of Rome as against Carthage. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The same motive actuated Indibilis and Mandonius, who
                        were beyond question the most powerful chiefs in Spain. They abandoned
                        Hasdrubal, with the whole of their contingent, and withdrew to the hills
                        above his camp and keeping along the ridge of mountains made their way
                        safely to the Roman headquarters. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When
                        Hasdrubal saw that the enemy were receiving such accessions of strength
                        whilst his own forces were shrinking in equal proportion, he realised that
                        unless he made some bold move, the wastage would continue, so he made up his
                        mind to seize the first opportunity of fighting. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio was still more anxious for a battle; his
                        confidence had grown with success, and he was unwilling to wait till the
                        hostile armies had formed a junction, preferring to engage each separately
                        rather than all united. In case, however, he might have to fight with their
                        combined armies, he had augmented his strength by a somewhat ingenious
                        method. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As the whole of the Spanish coast
                        was now clear of the enemy's ships, he had no further use for his own fleet,
                        and after beaching the vessels at Tarraco he brought up the crews to
                        reinforce his land army. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of arms and
                        armament he had more than enough, what with those taken in the capture of
                        New Carthage, and those which the large body of artisans had fabricated for
                        him subsequently. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Laelius, in whose
                        absence he would not undertake anything of importance, had now returned from
                        Rome, so in the early days of spring he left Tarraco with his composite army
                        and marched straight for the enemy. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The country through which he passed was
                        everywhere peaceful; each tribe as he approached gave him a friendly
                        reception and escorted him to their frontiers. On his route he was met by
                        Indibilis and Mandonius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The former,
                        speaking for himself and his companion, addressed Scipio in grave and
                        dignified language, very unlike the rough and heedless speech of barbarians.
                        Instead of claiming credit for having seized the first opportunity of going
                        over to the side of Rome he rather pleaded that he had no alternative.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He was quite aware, he said, that the
                        name of deserter was an object of loathing to the old friends and of
                        suspicion to the new ones, nor did he find fault with this way of looking at
                        it as long as the twofold odium attached not merely to the name but to the
                        motive. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then after dwelling on the
                        services they had both rendered to the Carthaginian generals and the
                        rapacity and insolence which the latter had exhibited and the innumerable
                        wrongs inflicted on them and their fellow-countrymen, he continued:
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> "Hitherto we have been associated
                        with them so far as our bodily presence is concerned, but our hearts and
                        minds have long been where we believe justice and right are cherished.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Now we come as suppliants to the gods
                        who cannot permit violence and injustice, and we implore you, Scipio, not to
                        regard our change of sides, as either a crime or a merit; put us to the test
                        from this day forward, and as you find us, so judge and appraise our
                        conduct." <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The Roman general replied that
                        this was just what he intended to do; he should not regard as deserters men
                        who did not consider an alliance binding where no law, human or divine, was
                        respected. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Thereupon their wives and
                        children were brought out and restored to them amid tears of joy. For that
                        day they were the guests of the Romans, on the morrow a definite treaty of
                        alliance was concluded, and they were sent off to bring up their troops.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> On their return they shared the Roman
                        camp and acted as guides until they reached the enemy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first army they came to was the one
                        commanded by Hasdrubal, which was encamped near the city of Baecula.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Cavalry outposts were stationed in
                        front of the camp. The advance guard of the Roman column with the velites
                        and skirmishers, at once attacked these outposts without changing their
                        order of march or stopping to entrench themselves, and the contempt they
                        showed for their enemy showed clearly the difference in the temper of the
                        two armies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The cavalry were driven in
                        hasty flight back to their camp, and the Roman standards were carried almost
                        to the gates. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That day's skirmish only
                        served to whet the courage of the Romans, and, impatient for battle, they
                        formed their camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the night Hasdrubal
                        withdrew his force to a hill, the summit of which formed a broad table-land.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His rear was protected by a river, in
                        front and on either side the hill sloped down precipitously, forming a kind
                        of steep bank, which surrounded the whole position. Below there was another
                        level stretch of ground which also fell away abruptly, and was equally
                        difficult of ascent. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When, on the morrow,
                        Hasdrubal saw the Roman battle-line standing in front of their camp, he sent
                        his Numidian cavalry and the Balearic and African light infantry on to this
                        lower ground. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio rode along the ranks
                        and pointed to the enemy standing in full view, who, he said, having given
                        up all hope of success on level ground were clinging to the hills, trusting
                        to the strength of their position and not to their arms or their courage.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the walls of New Carthage were
                        higher still, and yet Roman soldiers had surmounted them; neither hills, nor
                        citadel, nor the sea itself had stayed the advance of their arms. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> What use would the heights which the enemy had
                        seized be to them except to compel them to leap down cliffs and precipices
                        in their flight? Even that way of escape he should close to them. He then
                        told off two cohorts, one to hold the entrance of the valley through which
                        the river ran, the other to block the road which led from the city along the
                        slope of the hill into the country. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                        attack was commenced by the light-armed troops who had repulsed the outposts
                        the day before, and who were led by Scipio in person. At first their only
                        difficulty was the rough ground over which they were marching, but when they
                        came within range of the infantry stationed on the <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> lower plateau, all kinds of missiles were showered upon
                        them, to which they replied with showers of stones, with which the ground
                        was strewn, and which not only the soldiers but the camp followers who were
                        with them flung at the enemy. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Difficult
                        as the climb was, and almost buried as they were beneath stones and javelins
                        and darts, they went steadily on, thanks to their training in escalade and
                        their grim determination. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As soon as they
                        reached level ground and could plant their feet firmly, their superior mode
                        of fighting told. The light and active enemy, accustomed to fighting and
                        skirmishing at a distance, when he could evade the missiles, was quite
                        incapable of holding his own in a hand-to-hand fight, and he was hurled back
                        with heavy loss on to the main body posted on the higher ground. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Scipio ordered the victors to make a frontal
                        attack on the enemy's centre, while he divided the remainder of his force
                        between himself and Laelius. Laelius was ordered to work round the right of
                        the hill till he could find an easier ascent; he himself, making a short
                        detour to the left, attacked the enemy's flank. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Shouts were now resounding on all sides, and the enemy
                        tried to wheel their wings round to face the new attack; the consequence was
                        their lines got into confusion. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> At this
                        moment Laelius came up and the enemy fell back to avoid being assailed from
                        the rear; this led to their front being broken, and an opportunity was
                        afforded for the Roman centre to gain the plateau, which <milestone n="18??"
                            unit="section"/> they could not have reached over such difficult ground,
                        had the leading ranks of the Carthaginians kept their formation and the
                        elephants remained in the fighting line. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        The carnage was now spreading over the field, for Scipio, who had brought
                        his left against the enemy's right, was cutting up his exposed flank.
                            <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> There was no longer even a chance of
                        flight, for the roads in both directions were blocked by the Roman
                        detachments. Hasdrubal and his principal officers had in their flight closed
                        the gate of their camp, and to make matters still worse, the elephants were
                        galloping wildly about, and were dreaded by the Carthaginians as much as by
                        the Romans. The enemies' losses amounted to 8000 men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal had secured the war-chest before
                        the battle, and after sending on the elephants in advance and collecting all
                        the fugitives that he could, he directed his march along the Tagus towards
                        the Pyrenees. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Scipio took possession of
                        the enemy's camp, and gave up all the plunder, with the exception of the
                        prisoners, to his troops. On counting the prisoners he found that they
                        amounted to 10,000 infantry and 2000 cavalry. The Spanish prisoners were all
                        released and sent to their homes; the Africans were ordered to be sold by
                        the quaestor. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All the Spaniards, those who
                        had previously surrendered and those who had been made prisoners the day
                        before, now crowded round him, and with one accord saluted him as "King."
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He ordered silence to be proclaimed,
                        and then told them that the title he valued most was the one his soldiers
                        had given him, the title of "Imperator." "The name of king," he said, "so
                        great elsewhere, is insupportable to Roman ears. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> If a kingly mind is in your eyes the noblest thing in
                        human nature, you may attribute it to me in thought, but you must avoid the
                        use of the word." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Even the barbarians
                        appreciated the greatness of a man who stood so high that he could look down
                        on a title the splendour of which dazzled other men's eyes. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Presents were then distributed amongst the Spanish
                        princes and chieftains, and Scipio invited Indibilis to choose 300 horses
                        out of the large number captured. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Whilst
                        the quaestor was putting up the Africans to sale, he found amongst them a
                        remarkably handsome youth, and hearing that he was of royal blood, he sent
                        him to Scipio. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio questioned him as to
                        who he was, what country he belonged to, and why at his tender age he was in
                        camp. He told him that he was a Numidian, and his people called him Massiva.
                        Left an orphan by his father, he had been brought up by his maternal
                        grandfather Gala, king of the Numidians. His uncle Masinissa had come with
                        his cavalry to assist the Carthaginians, and he had accompanied him into
                        Spain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Masinissa had always forbidden him
                        to take part in the fighting because he was so young, but that day he had,
                        unknown to his uncle, secured arms and a horse and gone into action, but his
                        horse fell and threw him, and so he had been made prisoner. Scipio ordered
                        the Numidian to be kept under guard, and when he had transacted all the
                        necessary business he left the tribunal and resumed to his tent. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Here he sent for his prisoner and asked him
                        whether he would like to return to Masinissa. The boy replied amid tears of
                        joy that he should only be too glad to do so. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio then presented him with a gold ring, a tunic
                        with a wide purple border, a Spanish cloak with a gold clasp, and a
                        beautifully caparisoned horse. He then ordered an escort of cavalry to
                        accompany him as far as he wanted to go, and dismissed him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A council of war was then held. Some of
                        those present urged the immediate pursuit of Hasdrubal, but Scipio thought
                        it hazardous in case Mago and the other Hasdrubal should join forces with
                        him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He contented himself with sending a
                        division to occupy the passes of the Pyrenees, and spent the remainder of
                        the summer in receiving the submission of the Spanish tribes. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> A few days after the battle of Baecula, when
                        Scipio had descended from the pass of Castulo on his return to Tarraco, the
                        two Carthaginian generals, Hasdrubal Gisgo and Mago, came from Further Spain
                        to join forces with Hasdrubal. They were too late to prevent his defeat, but
                        their arrival was very timely in enabling them to concert measures for the
                        prosecution of the war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When they came to
                        compare notes as to the feeling in the different provinces, Hasdrubal Gisgo
                        considered that as the distant coast of Spain between Gades and the ocean
                        still knew nothing of the Romans, it was so far faithful to Carthage.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The other Hasdrubal and Mago were
                        agreed as to the influence which Scipio's generous treatment had had upon
                        the feelings of all states and individuals alike, and they were convinced
                        that the desertions could not be checked until all the Spanish soldiery had
                        either been removed to the furthest corners of Spain or transported into
                        Gaul. They decided therefore, without waiting for the sanction of the
                        senate, that Hasdrubal must proceed to Italy, the focus of the war where the
                        decisive conflict would be fought. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In this
                        way he would remove all the Spanish soldiers out of Spain far beyond the
                        spell of Scipio's name. </p>
                    <p> His army, weakened as it was by desertions and by the losses in the recent
                        disastrous battle, had to be brought up to its full strength. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Mago was to hand over his own army to Hasdrubal
                        Gisgo, and cross over to the Balearic Isles with an ample supply of money to
                        hire mercenaries among the islanders. Hasdrubal Gisgo was to make his way
                        into the interior of Lusitania and avoid any collision with the Romans.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A force of 3000 horse, selected from
                        all their cavalry, was to be made up for Masinissa, with which he was to
                        traverse Western Spain, ready to assist the friendly tribes and carry
                        devastation amongst the towns and territory of those who were hostile. After
                        drawing up this plan of operations the three generals separated to carry out
                        their several tasks. This was the course of events during the year in Spain.
                        Scipio's reputation was rising day by day in Rome. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Fabius too, though he had taken Tarentum by treachery
                        rather than by valour, added to his prestige by its capture. Fulvius'
                        laurels were fading. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Marcellus was even
                        the object of general censure, owing to the defeat which he had suffered and
                        still more because he had quartered his army in Venusia in the height of the
                        summer whilst Hannibal was marching where he pleased in Italy. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> He had an enemy in the person of C. Publicius
                        Bibulus, a tribune of the plebs. Immediately after Marcellus met with his
                        defeat, this man blackened his character and stirred up a bitter feeling
                        against him by the harangues which he was constantly delivering to the
                        plebs, and now he was actually working to get him deprived of his command.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Claudius' friends obtained permission
                        for him to leave his second in command at Venusia, and come home to clear
                        himself of the charges brought against him, and they also prevented any
                        attempt to deprive him of his command in his absence. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> It so happened that when Marcellus reached Rome to
                        avert the threatened disgrace, Fulvius also arrived to conduct the
                        elections. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The question of depriving Marcellus of his
                        command was debated in the Circus Flaminius before an enormous gathering in
                        which all orders of the State were represented. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The tribune of the plebs launched his accusations, not
                        only against Marcellus, but against the nobility as a whole. It was due to
                        their crooked policy and lack of energy, he said, that Hannibal had for ten
                        years been holding Italy as his province; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        he had, in fact, passed more of his life there than in Carthage. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The Roman people were now reaping the fruits of
                        the extension of Marcellus' command, his army after its double defeat was
                        now passing the summer comfortably housed in Venusia. Marcellus made such a
                        crushing reply to the tribune's speech by simply recounting all that he had
                        done that not only was the proposal to deprive him of his command rejected,
                        but the next day all the centuries with absolute unanimity elected him
                        consul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> T. Quinctius Crispinus, who was
                        praetor at the time, was assigned to him as his colleague. The next day came
                        the election of praetors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Those elected
                        were P. Licinius Crassus Dives, the Pontifex Maximus, P. Licinius Varus,
                        Sextus Julius Caesar and Q. Claudius. In the middle of the elections
                        considerable anxiety was created by the intelligence that Etruria had
                        revolted. C. Calpurnius, who was acting in that province as propraetor, had
                        written to say that the movement was started at Arretium. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Marcellus, the consul elect, was hastily despatched
                        thither to ascertain the position of affairs, and if he thought it
                        sufficiently serious to require the presence of his army he was to transfer
                        his operations from Apulia to Etruria. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        Etruscans were sufficiently intimidated by these measures to keep quiet.
                        Envoys came from Tarentum to ask for terms of peace under which they might
                        retain their liberties and their laws. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        senate directed them to come again as soon as Fabius arrived in Rome. The
                        Roman Games and the Plebeian Games were celebrated this year, each for one
                        day. The curule aediles were L. Cornelius Caudinus and Servius Sulpicius
                        Galba; the plebeian aediles, C. Servilius and Q. Caecilius Metellus.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was asserted that Servilius had no
                        legal right to be either tribune of the plebs or aedile, because there was
                        sufficient evidence that his father, who was supposed to have been killed by
                        the Boii near Mutina ten years previously when acting as agrarian
                        commissioner, was really alive and a prisoner in the hands of the enemy.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now the eleventh year of the Punic
                        War when M. Marcellus and T. Quinctius Crispinus entered upon their duties
                        as consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Reckoning the consulship to
                        which Marcellus had been elected, but in which, owing to some flaw in his
                        election, he did not act, this was the fifth time he had held the office.
                        Italy was assigned to both consuls as their province and the two armies
                        which the previous consuls had had, and a third which Marcellus had
                        commanded and which <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> was at the time in
                        Venusia, were all placed at their disposal so that they could select which
                        of the three they chose. The remaining one would then be given to the
                        commander to whom Tarentum and the Sallentini should be allotted. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The other spheres were allocated as follows: P.
                        Licinius Varus was placed in charge of the city jurisdiction, P. Licinius
                        Crassus the Pontifex Maximus had the jurisdiction over aliens and also
                        wherever the senate might determine. Sicily was allotted to Sextus Julius
                        Caesar, Tarentum to Q. Claudius the Flamen. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Q. Fulvius Flaccus had his command extended for a year and was to hold
                        the district of Capua, which T. Quinctius had previously held as praetor,
                        with one legion. C. Hostilius Tubulus also had his command extended, he was
                        to succeed C. Calpurnius as propraetor with two legions in Etruria.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A similar extension of command was
                        granted to L. Veturius Philo, who was to remain in Gaul as propraetor with
                        the two legions he had previously commanded. The same order was made in the
                        case of C. Aurunculeius, who had administered Sardinia as praetor; the fifty
                        ships which P. Scipio was to send from Spain were assigned to him for the
                        protection of his province. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> P. Scipio and
                        M. Silanus were confirmed in their commands for another year. Out of the
                        ships which Scipio had brought with him from Italy or captured from the
                        Carthaginians-eighty in all-he was instructed to send fifty to Sardinia, as
                        there were rumours of extensive naval preparations at Carthage. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> It was said that they were fitting out 200 ships
                        to menace the whole of the Italian, Sicilian and Sardinian coasts. In Sicily
                        it was arranged that the army of Cannae should be given to Sextus Caesar
                        whilst M. Valerius Laevinus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> whose command
                        had also been extended, was to retain the fleet of seventy ships which was
                        stationed off Sicily, and augment it with the thirty vessels which had lain
                        at Tarentum during the past year. This fleet of one hundred ships he was to
                        employ, if he thought good, in harrying the African seaboard. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> P. Sulpicius was to continue to hold Macedonia
                        and Greece in check with the fleet which he had. There was no change in the
                        case of the two legions which were quartered in the City. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The consuls were commissioned to raise fresh troops
                        where it was necessary, in order to bring up the legions to their proper
                        strength. Thus one-and-twenty legions were under arms to defend the Roman
                        empire. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> P. Licinius Varus, the City
                        praetor, was charged with the task of refitting the thirty old warships
                        which were laid up at Ostia, and manning with their full complement twenty
                        new ones, so that he might have a fleet of fifty ships for the protection of
                        that part of the coast which was nearest to Rome. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> C. Calpurnius received strict orders not to move his
                        army from Arretium before the arrival of Tubulus who was to succeed him;
                        Tubulus was also enjoined to be especially on his guard in case any
                        revolutionary projects were formed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The praetors left for their provinces, but
                        the consuls were detained by religious matters; several portents had been
                        announced, and the omens drawn from the sacrificial victims were mostly
                        unfavourable. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> News came from Campania that
                        two temples in Capua-those of Fortune and Mars-as well as several sepulchral
                        monuments had been struck by lightning. To such an extent does a depraved
                        superstition see the work of the gods in the most insignificant trifles,
                        that it was seriously reported that rats had gnawed the gold in the temple
                        of Jupiter in Cumae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Casinum a swarm of
                        bees had settled in the forum; at Ostia a gate and part of the wall had been
                        struck by lightning; at Caere a vulture had flown into the temple of
                        Jupiter, and at Vulsinii the waters of the lake had run with blood.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In consequence of these portents a day
                        of special intercession was ordered. For several days full-grown victims had
                        been sacrificed without giving any propitious indications, and it was long
                        before the "peace of the gods" could be secured. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> It was on the heads of the consuls that the direful
                        mischance prognosticated by these portents fell, the State remained
                        unharmed. The Games of Apollo had been celebrated for the first time in the
                        consulship of Q. Fulvius and Appius Claudius under the superintendence of
                        the City praetor, P. Cornelius Sulla. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Subsequently all the City praetors celebrated them in turn, but they used to
                        vow them for one year only, and there was no fixed day for their
                        celebration. This year a serious epidemic attacked both the City and the
                        country districts, but it resulted more frequently in protracted than in
                        fatal illness. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In consequence of this
                        epidemic special intercessions were appointed at all the chapels throughout
                        the City, and P. Licinius Varus, the City praetor, was instructed to propose
                        a measure to the people providing that the Games of Apollo should always be
                        celebrated on the same day. He was the first to celebrate them under this
                        rule, and the day fixed for their celebration was July 5th, which was
                        henceforth observed as the day. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Day by day the reports from Arretium
                        became more serious and caused increasing anxiety to the senate. Written
                        instructions were sent to C. Hostilius, bidding him lose no time in taking
                        hostages from the townspeople, and C. Terentius Varro was sent with powers
                        to receive them from him and conduct them to Rome. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as he arrived, Hostilius ordered one of his
                        legions which was encamped before the city to enter it in military order,
                        and he then disposed the men in suitable positions. This done, he summoned
                        the senators into the forum and ordered them to give hostages for their good
                        behaviour. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They asked for forty-eight
                        hours for consideration, but he insisted upon their producing the hostages
                        at once, and threatened in case of refusal to seize all their children the
                        next day. He then issued orders to the military tribunes and prefects of
                        allies and centurions to keep a strict watch on the gates, and to allow no
                        one to leave the city during the night. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        There was too much slackness and delay in carrying out these instructions;
                        before the guards were posted at the gates seven of the principal senators
                        with their children slipped out before it was dark. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Early on the morrow, when the senators began to
                        assemble in the forum, the absence of these men was discovered, and their
                        property was sold. The rest of the senators offered their own children to
                        the number of one hundred and twenty; the offer was accepted, and they were
                        entrusted to C. Terentius to be conveyed to Rome. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The report he gave to the senate made matters look
                        still more serious. It seemed as though a rising throughout Etruria was
                        imminent. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> C. Terentius was accordingly
                        ordered to proceed to Arretium with one of the two City legions and occupy
                        the place in force, C. Hostilius with the rest of the army was to traverse
                        the entire province and see that no opening was afforded for revolutionary
                        disturbances. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When C. Terentius and his
                        legion reached Arretium, he demanded the keys of the gates. The magistrates
                        replied that they could not find them, but he was convinced that they had
                        been deliberately carried off and not lost through carelessness, so he had
                        fresh locks fitted on all the gates, and took especial precautions to have
                        everything under his own control. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                        earnestly impressed upon Hostilius the need of vigilance, and warned him
                        that all hope of Etruria remaining quiet depended upon his taking such
                        precautions as to make any movement of disaffection impossible. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was an animated debate in the senate
                        as to the treatment to be meted out to the Tarentines. Fabius was present,
                        and stood up for those whom he had subjugated; others took the opposite
                        line, the majority regarded their guilt as equal to that of Capua and
                        deserving equally severe punishment. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At
                        last a resolution was adopted embodying the proposal of Manlius Acilius,
                        viz. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that the town should be garrisoned
                        and the entire population confined within their walls until Italy was in a
                        less disturbed state, when the whole question could be reconsidered. An
                        equally warm discussion arose in connection with M. Livius who had commanded
                        the force in the citadel. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some were for
                        passing a formal vote of censure on him for having, through his negligence,
                        allowed the place to be betrayed to the enemy. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Others considered that he ought to be rewarded for
                        having successfully defended the citadel for five years, and having done
                        more than any one else to effect the recapture of Tarentum. A third party,
                        taking a middle course, urged that it was for the censors, not the senate,
                        to take cognisance of his action. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This
                        view was supported by Fabius, who remarked that he quite admitted what
                        Livius' friends were constantly asserting in that House, that it was owing
                        to his efforts that Tarentum had been retaken, for there would have been no
                        recapture had it not previously been lost. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        One of the consuls, T. Quinctius Crispinus, left with reinforcements for the
                        army in Lucania which Q. Fulvius Flaccus had commanded. Marcellus was
                        detained by religious difficulties which one after another presented
                        themselves. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the war with the Gauls he
                        had vowed during the battle of Clastidium a temple to Honos and Virtus, but
                        he was prevented from dedicating it by the pontiffs. They said that one
                        shrine could not be lawfully dedicated to two deities, because in case it
                        were struck by lightning, or some other portent occurred in it, there would
                        be a difficulty about the expiation, since it could not be known which deity
                        was to be propitiated; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> one victim could
                        not be sacrificed to two deities except in the case of certain specified
                        deities. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A second temple was hastily
                        built to Virtus, but this was not dedicated by Marcellus. At last he started
                        with reinforcements for the army which he had left the previous year at
                        Venusia. Seeing how Tarentum had enhanced Fabius' reputation, Crispinus
                        determined to attempt the capture of Locri in Bruttium. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He had sent to Sicily for all kinds of artillery and
                        military engines, and had also collected a number of ships to attack that
                        part of the city which faced the sea. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As,
                        however, Hannibal had brought up his army to Lacinium, he abandoned the
                        siege, and hearing that his colleague had moved out by Venusia, he was
                        anxious to join forces with him. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> With
                        this view he marched back into Apulia, and the two consuls encamped within
                        three miles of each other in a place between Venusia and Bantia. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> As all was now quiet at Locri Hannibal moved up
                        into their neighbourhood. But the consuls were quite sanguine of success;
                        they drew out their armies for battle almost every day, feeling perfectly
                        certain that if the enemy would try his chance against two consular armies,
                        the war would be brought to a close. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal had already fought two battles
                        with Marcellus during the past year, in one he had been victorious, the
                        other he lost. After this experience he felt that if he had to meet him
                        again there was as much ground for fear as for hope, and he was therefore
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> far from feeling himself equal to
                        the two consuls together. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He decided to
                        employ his old tactics and looked out for a position suitable for an
                        ambuscade. Both sides, however, confined themselves to skirmishes, with
                        varying success, and the consuls thought that as the summer was being spun
                        out in this way there was no reason why the siege of Locri should not be
                        resumed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So they sent written instructions
                        to L. Cincius to take his fleet from Sicily to Locri, and as the walls of
                        that city <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> were open to a land attack
                        also, they ordered a portion of the army which was garrisoning Tarentum to
                        be marched there. These plans were disclosed to Hannibal by some people from
                        Thurium, and he sent a force to block the road from Tarentum. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> 3000 cavalry and 2000 infantry were concealed
                        under a hill above Petelia. The Romans, marching on without reconnoitring,
                        fell into the trap, and 2000 were killed and 1500 taken prisoners. The rest
                        fled through the fields and woods back to Tarentum. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Between the Carthaginian camp and that of the Romans
                        there was a wooded hill which neither side had taken possession of, for the
                        Romans did not know what that side of it was like which fronted the enemy,
                        and Hannibal regarded it as better adapted for an ambuscade than for a camp.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He accordingly sent a force of
                        Numidians during the night to conceal themselves in the wood, and there they
                        remained the following day without stirring from their position, so that
                        neither they nor their arms were visible. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        It was being everywhere remarked in the Roman camp that the hill ought to be
                        seized and strengthened with defences, for if Hannibal seized it they would
                        have the enemy, so to speak, over their heads. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The idea impressed Marcellus, and he said to his
                        colleague: "Why do we not go with a few horsemen and examine the place?
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When we have seen it for ourselves we
                        shall know better what to do." Crispinus assented, and they started with 220
                        mounted men, 40 of whom were from Fregellae, the rest were Etruscans.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They were accompanied by two military
                        tribunes, M. Marcellus, a son of the consul, and A. Manlius, and also by two
                        prefects of allies, L. Arrenius and Manius Aulius. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Some writers assert that whilst Marcellus was
                        sacrificing on that day, the liver of the first victim was found to have no
                        head; in the second all the usual parts were present, but the head appeared
                        abnormally large. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The haruspex was
                        seriously alarmed at finding after misshaped and stunted parts such an
                        excess of growth. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus, however, was seized with such a
                        keen desire of engaging Hannibal that he never thought that their respective
                        camps were near enough to each other. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As
                        he was crossing the rampart on his way to the hill he signalled to the
                        soldiers to be at their posts, ready to get the baggage together and follow
                        him in case he decided that the hill which he was going to reconnoitre was
                        suitable for a camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was a narrow
                        stretch of level ground in front of the camp, and from there a road led up
                        to the hill which was open and visible from all sides. The Numidians posted
                        a vidette to keep a look out, not in the least anticipating such a serious
                        encounter as followed, but simply in the hope of intercepting any who had
                        strayed too far from their camp after wood or fodder. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> This man gave the signal for them to rise from their
                        concealment. Those who were in front of the Romans further up the hill did
                        not show themselves until those who were to close the road behind them had
                        worked round their rear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then they sprang
                        up on all sides, and with a loud shout charged down. Though the consuls were
                        hemmed in, unable to force their way to the hill which was occupied, and
                        with their retreat cut off by those in their rear, still the conflict might
                        have <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> kept up for a longer time if the
                        Etruscans, who were the first to flee, had not created a panic among the
                        rest. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Fregellans, however, though
                        abandoned by the Etruscans, maintained the conflict as long as the consuls
                        were unwounded and able to cheer them on and take their part in the
                        fighting. But when both the consuls were wounded, when they saw Marcellus
                        fall dying from his horse, run through with a lance, then the little band of
                        survivors fled in company with Crispinus, who had been hit by two darts, and
                        young Marcellus, who was himself wounded. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Aulus Manlius was killed, and Manius Aulius; the other prefect of allies,
                        Arrenius, was taken prisoner. Five of the consuls' lictors fell into the
                        hands of the enemy, the rest were either killed or escaped with the consul.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Forty-three of the cavalry fell either
                        in the battle or the pursuit, eighteen were made prisoners. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> There was great excitement in the camp, and they
                        were hurriedly preparing to go to the consuls' assistance when they saw one
                        consul and the son of the other coming back wounded with the scanty remnant
                        who had survived the disastrous expedition. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> The death of Marcellus was to be deplored for many reasons, especially
                        because, with an imprudence not to be expected at his age-he was more than
                        sixty-and altogether out of keeping with the caution of a veteran general,
                        he had flung into headlong danger not only himself but his colleague as
                        well, and almost the entire commonwealth. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        I should make too long a digression about one solitary fact, if I were to go
                        through all the accounts of the death of Marcellus. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> I will only cite one authority, Coelius. He gives three
                        different versions of what happened, one handed down by tradition, another
                        copied from the funeral oration delivered by his son who was on the spot,
                        and a third which Coelius gives as the ascertained result of his own
                        researches. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Amidst the variations of the
                        story, however, most authorities agree that he left the camp to reconnoitre
                        the position, and all agree that he was ambushed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal felt convinced that the enemy
                        would be thoroughly cowed by the death of one consul and the disablement of
                        the other, and he determined not to lose the opportunity thus afforded him.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He at once transferred his camp to the
                        hill where the action had been fought, and here he interred the body of
                        Marcellus, which had been found. Crispinus, unnerved by the death of his
                        colleague and his own wound, left his position in the dead of night and
                        fixed his camp on the first mountains he came to, in a lofty position
                        protected on every side. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And now the two
                        commanders showed great wariness, the one trying to deceive his opponent,
                        the other taking every precaution against him. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When the body of Marcellus was discovered, Hannibal
                        took possession of his rings. Fearing that the signet might be used for
                        purposes of forgery, Crispinus sent couriers to all the cities round,
                        warning them that his colleague was killed and his ring in the possession of
                        the enemy, so that they were not to trust any missives sent in the name of
                        Marcellus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Soon after the consul's
                        messenger had arrived at Salapia, a despatch was received from Hannibal
                        purporting to come from Marcellus, and stating that he would come to Salapia
                        the night after they received the letter, and the soldiers of the garrison
                        were to hold themselves in readiness in case their services should be
                        required. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Salapians saw through the
                        ruse, and supposed that he was seeking an opportunity for punishing them,
                        not only for their desertion of the Carthaginian cause, but also for the
                        slaughter of his cavalry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They sent back
                        the messenger, who was a Roman deserter, that he might not be cognisant of
                        the measures which they decided to take, and then made their dispositions.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The townsmen took their places on the
                        walls and other commanding positions, the patrols and sentries for the night
                        were strengthened and kept a most careful look out, and the pick of the
                        garrison were formed up near the gate to which the enemy were expected to
                        come. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Hannibal approached the city about the
                        fourth watch. The head of the column was formed of Roman deserters; they
                        carried Roman weapons, their armour was Roman, and they were all speaking
                        Latin. When they reached the gate, they called up the sentinels and told
                        them to open the gate as the consul was there. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The sentinels, pretending to be just wakened up,
                        bustled about in hurry and confusion and began slowly and laboriously to
                        open the gate. It was closed by a portcullis, and by means of levers and
                        ropes they raised it just high enough for a man to pass upright under it.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The passage was hardly sufficiently
                        clear when the deserters rushed through the gate, each trying who should be
                        first. About 600 were inside, when suddenly the rope which held it was let
                        go, and the portcullis fell with a great crash. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The Salapians attacked the deserters, who were marching
                        carelessly along with their shields hung from their shoulders, as though
                        friends; others on the gate tower and the walls kept off the enemy outside
                        with stones and long poles and javelins. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        So Hannibal, finding himself caught in his own trap, drew off and proceeded
                        to raise the siege of Locri. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Cincius was
                        making a most determined attack upon the place with siege works and
                        artillery of every kind which he had brought from Sicily, and Mago was
                        beginning to despair of holding the place when his hopes were suddenly
                        revived by the news of Marcellus' death. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Then came a messenger with the tidings that Hannibal had sent his Numidian
                        cavalry on in advance, and was following as rapidly as he could with his
                        infantry. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> As soon as the signal was given
                        from the look-out of the approach of the Numidians, Mago flung the city gate
                        open and made a vigorous sortie. Owing to the suddenness of his attack which
                        was quite unlooked for, rather than to his fighting strength, the battle was
                        for some time an even one, but <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> when the
                        Numidians came up, such a panic seized the Romans that they abandoned the
                        siege works and the engines with which they were battering the walls, and
                        fled in disorder to the sea and to their ships. Thus by the arrival of
                        Hannibal, the siege of Locri was raised. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as Crispinus found that Hannibal
                        had withdrawn to Bruttium he ordered M. Marcellus to take the army which his
                        late colleague had commanded back to Venusia. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Though hardly able to bear the motion of the litter
                        owing to his serious wounds, he started with his legions for Capua.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In a despatch which he sent to the
                        senate, after alluding to his colleague's death and the critical condition
                        he himself was in, he explained that he could not go to Rome for the
                        elections because he did not think he could bear the fatigue of the journey,
                        and also because he was anxious about Tarentum in case Hannibal should leave
                        Bruttium and direct his armies against it. He also requested that some men
                        of wisdom and experience might be sent to him, as it was necessary for him
                        to confer with them as to the policy of the Republic. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The reading of this despatch evoked a feeling of deep
                        regret at the death of the one consul and serious apprehensions for the life
                        of the other. In accordance with his wish they sent young Q. Fabius to the
                        army at Venusia, and three representatives to the consul, viz. Sextus Julius
                        Caesar, L. Licinius Pollio and L. Cincius Alimentus who had returned from
                        Sicily a few days previously. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their
                        instructions were to tell the consul that if he could not come to Rome to
                        conduct the elections, he was to nominate a Dictator in Roman territory for
                        the purpose. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If the consul had gone to
                        Tarentum, the praetor Q. Claudius was required to withdraw the legions
                        stationed there, and march with them into that district in which he could
                        protect the greatest number of cities belonging to the allies of Rome.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During the summer M. Valerius sailed
                        across to Africa with a fleet of a hundred vessels. Landing his men near the
                        city of Clupea, he ravaged the country far and wide without meeting with any
                        resistance. The news of the approach of a Carthaginian fleet caused the
                        pillagers to return in haste to their ships. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> This fleet consisted of eighty-three ships, and the Roman commander
                        successfully engaged it not far from Clupea. After capturing eighteen ships
                        and putting the rest to flight, he returned to Lilybaeum with a great
                        quantity of booty. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the course of the
                        summer Philip lent armed assistance to the Achaeans, who had implored his
                        aid against Machanidas, tyrant of the Lacedaemonians, and against the
                        Aetolians. Machanidas was harassing them with a border warfare, and the
                        Aetolians had crossed the narrow sea between Naupactus and Patrae-the local
                        name of the latter is Rhion-and were making forays in Achaia. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> There were rumours also of an intention on the
                        part of Attalus, king of Asia, to visit Europe, as the Aetolians had at the
                        last meeting of their national council made him one of their two supreme
                        magistrates. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This being the position of affairs, Philip
                        moved southward into Greece. The Aetolians under the command of Pyrrhias,
                        who had been elected Attalus' colleague, met Philip at the city of Lamia.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were supported by a contingent
                        furnished by Attalus, and also by about 1000 men whom P. Sulpicius had sent
                        from his fleet. Philip won two battles against Pyrrhias, and in each battle
                        the enemy lost not less than 1000 men. From that time the Aetolians were
                        afraid to meet him in the field and remained inside the walls of Lamia.
                        Philip accordingly marched his army to Phalara. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> This place lies on the Maliac Gulf, and was formerly
                        the seat of a considerable population, owing to its splendid harbour, the
                        safe anchorages in the neighbourhood, and other maritime and commercial
                        advantages. Whilst he was here he was visited by embassies from Ptolemy king
                        of Egypt, and from Rhodes and Athens and Chios, with the view of bringing
                        about a reconciliation between him and the Aetolians. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Amynandor, king of the Athamanians, a neighbour of the
                        Aetolians. was also acting on their behalf as peacemaker. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But the general concern was not so much for the
                        Aetolians, who were more warlike than the rest of the Greeks, as for the
                        liberty of Greece, which would be seriously endangered if Philip and his
                        kingdom took an active part in Greek politics. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The question of peace was held over for discussion in
                        the meeting of the Achaean League. The place and time for this meeting were
                        settled, and in the meantime a thirty days' armistice was arranged.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From Phalara the king proceeded
                        through Thessaly and Boeotia to Chalcis in Euboea, in order to prevent
                        Attalus, who he understood was sailing thither, from landing on the island.
                        Leaving a force there in case Attalus should sail across in the meantime, he
                        went on with a small body of cavalry and light infantry to Argos. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Here the presidency of the Heraean and Nemean
                        Games was conferred upon him by the popular vote, on the ground that the
                        kings of Macedon trace their origin to Argos. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as the Heraean Games were over he went off to
                        Aegium to the meeting of the League which had been fixed some time
                        previously. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The discussion turned upon the question
                        of putting a stop to the war with the Aetolians, so that neither the Romans
                        nor Attalus might have any reason for entering Greece. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But everything was upset by the Aetolians almost before
                        the armistice had expired, after they learnt that Attalus had reached Aegina
                        and that a Roman fleet was anchored off Naupactus. They had been invited to
                        attend the meeting of the League, and the deputations who had been trying to
                        secure peace at Phalara were also present. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> They began by complaining of certain trivial infringements of the
                        armistice, and ended by declaring that hostilities could never cease until
                        the Achaeans restored Pylos to the Messenians, and Atintania was given back
                        to Rome, and the Ardiaei to Scerdilaedus and Pleuratus. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Philip was naturally indignant at those whom he had
                        defeated proposing terms of peace to him, their conqueror. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> He reminded the assembly that when the question of
                        peace was referred to him and an armistice was granted, it was not with any
                        expectation that the Aetolians would remain quiet, but solely in order that
                        all the allies might bear him witness that whilst he was seeking a basis for
                        peace, the other side were determined to find a pretext for war. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Since there was no chance of peace being
                        established, he dismissed the council and returned to Argos, as the time for
                        the Nemean Games was approaching and he wished to add to their popularity by
                        his presence. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He left a force of 4000 men
                        to protect the Achaeans, and at the same time took over from them five ships
                        of war. He intended to add these to the fleet recently sent from Carthage;
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> with these vessels and the ships
                        which Prusias was despatching from Bithynia he had made up his mind to offer
                        battle to the Romans who were masters of the sea in that part of the world.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the king was preoccupied with the
                        preparations for the Games, and was allowing himself more recreation than
                        was possible in a time of active warfare, P. Sulpicius, setting sail from
                        Naupactus, brought up his fleet between Sicyon and Corinth, and spread
                        devastation far and wide over that wonderfully fertile land. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> This news brought Philip away from the Games. He
                        hurried off with his cavalry, leaving the infantry to follow, and caught the
                        Romans whilst they were dispersed through the fields in all directions,
                        laden with plunder, and utterly unsuspicious of danger. They were driven to
                        their ships, and the Roman fleet returned to Naupactus, far from happy at
                        the result of their raid. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Philip returned
                        to see the close of the Games, and their splendour was enhanced by the news
                        of his victory, for whatever its importance it was still a victory over the
                        Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What added to the universal
                        enjoyment of the festival was the way in which he gratified the people by
                        laying aside his diadem and purple robe and the rest of his royal state so
                        as to be, as far as appearance went, on a level with the rest. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Nothing is more grateful than this to the
                        citizens of a free State. He would indeed have given them every reason to
                        hope that their liberties would remain unimpaired if he had not sullied and
                        disgraced all by his insufferable debauchery. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Accompanied by one or two boon companions, he ranged as
                        he pleased through homes and families, day and night, and by stooping to the
                        status of a private citizen he attracted less notice and was therefore under
                        less restraint. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The liberty with which he
                        had cheated others he turned in his own case to unbridled licence, and he
                        did not always effect his purpose by money or blandishments but even
                        resorted to criminal violence. It was a dangerous thing for husbands and
                        fathers to place obstacles in the way of the king's lusts by any untimely
                        scruples on their part. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A lady called
                        Polycratia, the wife of Aratus, one of the leading men amongst the Achaeans,
                        was taken away from her husband and carried off to Macedon under a promise
                        from the king to marry her. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the midst
                        of these debaucheries the sacred festival of the Nemean Games came to a
                        close. A few days afterwards Philip marched to Dymae to expel the Aetolian
                        garrison which the Eleans had invited and admitted into their city.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here the king was met by the Achaeans
                        under Cycliadas their captain general, who were burning with resentment
                        against the Eleans for having deserted the Achaean League, and furious
                        against the Aetolians for having, as they believed, brought the arms of Rome
                        against them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The combined force left
                        Dymae and crossed the Larisus, which separates the territory of Elia from
                        that of Dymae. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first day of their advance in the
                        enemy's country was spent in plunder and destruction. The next day they
                        marched in battle array towards the city, the cavalry having been sent
                        forward to provoke the Aetolians to fight, which they were perfectly ready
                        to do. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The invaders were unaware that
                        Sulpicius had sailed across from Naupactus to Cyllene with fifteen ships and
                        landed 4000 men who had entered Elis in the night. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as they recognised the standards and arms of
                        Rome amongst the Aetolians and Eleans, the unlooked-for sight filled them
                        with great alarm. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At first the king wanted
                        to retire his men, but they were already engaged with the Aetolians and
                        Trallians-an Illyrian tribe-and as he saw that they were being hard pressed,
                        he charged the Roman cohort with his cavalry. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> His horse was wounded by a javelin and fell, throwing
                        the king over its head, and a fierce contest began, on both sides, the
                        Romans making desperate efforts to reach him and his own men doing their
                        best to protect him. Compelled as he was to fight on foot amongst mounted
                        men, he showed conspicuous courage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        struggle became at length an unequal one, many were falling round him and
                        many were wounded, and he was seized by his own men and placed on another
                        horse on which he fled. That day he fixed his camp about five miles from
                        Elis; the following day he led the whole of his force to a fortified place
                        called Pyrgon. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This was a fort belonging
                        to the Eleans, and he had been informed that a large number of peasants with
                        their cattle had taken refuge there through fear of being plundered.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Destitute as they were of organisation
                        and arms, the mere fact of his approach filled them with terror and they
                        were all made prisoners. This booty was some compensation for his
                        humiliating defeat at Elis. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Whilst he was
                        distributing the spoil and the captives-there were 4000 prisoners and 20,000
                        head of cattle large and small-a messenger arrived from Macedonia stating
                        that a certain Eropus had taken Lychnidos after bribing the commandant of
                        the garrison, that he was in possession of some villages belonging to the
                        Dassaretii and was also making the Dardanians restless. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Philip at once abandoned hostilities with the Aetolians
                        and prepared to return home. He left a force of 2500 of all arms under the
                        command of Menippus and Polyphantas to protect his allies, and taking his
                        route through Achaia <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> and Boeotia, and
                        across Euboea, he arrived at Demetrias in Thessaly on the tenth day after
                        his departure from Dymae. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There he was met by still more alarming
                        tidings; the Dardanians were pouring into Macedonia and were already in
                        occupation of the Orestides district, they had even descended into the
                        Argestaean Plain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The report was current
                        that Philip had been killed; the rumour was due to the fact that in the
                        encounter with the plundering parties from the Roman fleet at Sicyon, his
                        horse flung him against a tree and one of the horns of his helmet was broken
                        off by a projecting branch. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This was
                        afterwards picked up by an Aetolian and taken to Scerdilaedus, who
                        recognised it. Hence the rumour. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the
                        king had left Achaia Sulpicius sailed to Aegina and Scipio in Spain joined
                        forces with Attalus. The Achaeans in conjunction with the Aetolians and
                        Eleans fought a successful action not far from Messene. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Attalus and Sulpicius went into winter quarters in
                        Aegina. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At the close of this year the
                        consul T. Quinctius died of his wounds, having previously nominated T.
                        Manlius Torquatus Dictator to conduct the elections. Some say he died in
                        Tarentum, others, in Campania. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This
                        accident of two consuls being killed in a quite unimportant action had never
                        occurred in any previous war, and it left the republic, so to speak, in a
                        state of orphanhood. The Dictator named C. Servilius, who was curule aedile
                        at the time, his Master of the Horse. On the first day of their session the
                        senate instructed the Dictator to celebrate the Great Games. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> M. Aemilius, who was city praetor at the time,
                        had celebrated them in the consulship of C. Flaminius and Cnaeus Servilius,
                        and had made a vow that they should be celebrated in five years' time. The
                        Dictator celebrated them accordingly, and made a vow that they should be
                        repeated at the following lustrum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Meanwhile, as the two consular armies had no generals and were in such close
                        proximity to the enemy, both senate and people were anxious that all other
                        business should be postponed, and consuls elected as soon as possible.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was felt that, above all, men
                        ought to be elected whose courage and skill would be proof against the wiles
                        of the Carthaginian, for all through the war the hot and hasty temperament
                        of different commanders had proved disastrous, and in that very year the
                        consuls had been led by their eagerness to come to grips with the enemy into
                        snares of which they did not suspect the existence. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The gods, however, out of pity for the name of Rome,
                        spared the unoffending armies and visited the rashness of the consuls on
                        their own heads. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the patricians began to look round
                        and see who would make the best consuls, one man stood out conspicuously-C.
                        Claudius Nero. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The question was, who was
                        to be his colleague? He was regarded as a man of exceptional ability but too
                        impulsive and venturesome for such a war as the present one, or such an
                        enemy as Hannibal, and they felt that his impetuous temperament needed to be
                        restrained by a cool and prudent colleague. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Their thoughts turned to M. Livius. He had been consul several years
                        previously, and after laying down his consulship had been impeached before
                        the Assembly and found guilty. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This
                        disgrace he felt so keenly that he removed into the country, and for many
                        years was a stranger to the City and to all public gatherings. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> It was about eight years after his condemnation
                        that the consuls M. Claudius Marcellus and M. Valerius Laevinus brought him
                        back to the City, but his squalid garments, his neglected hair and beard,
                        his whole appearance showed pretty clearly that he had not forgotten the
                        humiliation. The censors L. Veturius and P. Licinius made him trim his hair
                        and beard and lay aside his squalid garments and take his place in the
                        senate and discharge other public duties. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Even then he contented himself with a simple "aye" or "no" to the question
                        before the House, and in the event of a division <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> with a silent vote, until the case of his kinsman
                        Marcus Livius Macatus came up, when the attack upon his relative's fair fame
                        compelled him to rise in his place and address the House. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The voice which after so long an interval was once more
                        heard was listened to with deep attention, and the senators remarked to one
                        another that the people had wronged an innocent man to the great detriment
                        of the commonwealth, which in the stress of a grievous war had been unable
                        to avail itself of the help and counsel of such a man as that. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Neither Q. Fabius nor M. Valerius Laevinus could
                        be assigned to C. Nero as his colleague because it was illegal for two
                        patricians to be elected, and the same difficulty existed in the case of T.
                        Manlius, who had moreover already refused a consulship and would continue to
                        refuse it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If they gave him M. Livius as
                        colleague, they felt that they would have a splendid pair of consuls. This
                        suggestion put forward by the senators was approved by the great body of the
                        people. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There was only one among all the
                        citizens who rejected it and that was the man on whom the honour was to be
                        conferred. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He accused them of
                        inconsistency. "When he appeared in mourning garments at his trial they felt
                        no pity for him, now, in spite of his refusal, they would have him put on
                        the white robe of the candidate. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They
                        heaped penalties and honours on the same man. If they thought that he was a
                        good citizen, why had they condemned him as a criminal? If they had found
                        him to be a criminal, why were they entrusting him with a second consulship
                        after he had misused the first?" <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                        senators severely censured him for complaining and protesting in this way,
                        and reminded him of M. Furius Camillus who after being recalled from exile
                        restored his country to its ancient seat. "We ought to treat our country,"
                        they told him, "like our parents, and disarm its severity by patience and
                        submission." <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> By their united efforts they
                        succeeded in making him consul with C. Claudius Nero. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Three days later came the election of
                        praetors. Those elected were L. Porcius Licinius, C. Mamilius and the two
                        Catos, C. Hostilius and A. Hostilius. When the elections were over and the
                        Games concluded, the Dictator and the Master of the Horse resigned office.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> C. Terentius Varro was sent into
                        Etruria as propraetor to relieve C. Hostilius, who was to take over the
                        command of the army at Tarentum which the consul T. Quinctius had had. L.
                        Manlius was to go to Greece and find out what was going on there. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> As the Olympian Games were to be held this
                        summer, and as a very large gathering would be there, he was, if he could
                        get through the enemy's forces, to be present at them and <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> inform those Sicilians who had fled there from the war
                        and any citizens of Tarentum who had been banished by Hannibal that they
                        might return home and rest assured that the Roman people would restore to
                        them all that they possessed before the war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> As the coming year seemed to be fraught with most serious dangers, and
                        the State was for the moment without consuls, all eyes were turned to the
                        consuls-elect, and it was universally hoped that they would lose no time in
                        balloting for their provinces and deciding what enemy each of them would
                        have to meet. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the initiative of Q.
                        Fabius Maximus a resolution was earned in the senate insisting upon their
                        becoming reconciled to each other. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Their
                        quarrel was only too notorious, and was embittered by Livius' resentment at
                        the insulting treatment he had received, for he felt that his honour had
                        been sullied by his prosecution. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This made
                        him all the more implacable; he said that there was no need for any
                        reconciliation, each would act with greater energy and alertness if he knew
                        that failure to do so would give his enemy an advantage. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> However, the senate successfully exerted their
                        authority, and they were induced to lay aside their private differences and
                        conduct the affairs of State with one mind and one policy. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Their provinces were not contiguous as in former years,
                        but widely separated, at the extremities of Italy. One was to act against
                        Hannibal in Bruttium and Lucania, the other in Gaul against Hasdrubal, who
                        was reported to be now nearing the Alps. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        The consul to whose lot Gaul should fall was to choose either the army which
                        was in Gaul or the one in Etruria, and would receive in addition the army of
                        the City. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The one to whom Bruttium fell
                        was to raise fresh legions in the City and select one of the two consular
                        armies of the previous year. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The other
                        one Q. Fabius was to take over as proconsul, in which capacity he was to act
                        for the year. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> C. Hostilius, who had
                        already been removed from Etruria to Tarentum, was now again to change from
                        Tarentum to Capua. One legion was given him, the one which Fulvius had
                        commanded. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal's appearance in Italy was looked
                        forward to with daily increasing anxiety. The first news came from the
                        Massilians, who reported that he had passed into Gaul, and <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> that there was widespread excitement amongst
                        the natives owing to a rumour that he had brought a large amount of gold for
                        the payment of auxiliary troops. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        Massilian envoys were accompanied on their return by Sextus Antistius and M.
                        Raecius, who were sent to make further investigations. These reported that
                        they had sent emissaries, accompanied by some Massilians who had friends
                        amongst, the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> Gaulish chieftains, to gain
                        information and that they had definitely ascertained that Hasdrubal intended
                        to cross the Alps the next spring with an enormous army. The only thing that
                        kept him from advancing at once was that the Alps were insurmountable in
                        winter. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> P. Aelius Paetus was appointed and
                        consecrated augur in place of M. Marcellus, and Cnaeus Cornelius Dolabella
                        was consecrated "King of Sacrifices" in place of M. Marcius, who had been
                        dead for two years. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The lustrum was closed
                        by the censors P. Sempronius Tuditanus and M. Cornelius Cethegus. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The census returns gave the number of citizens as
                        137,108, a considerably smaller number than the one before the beginning of
                        the war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For the first time since Hannibal
                        had invaded Italy the comitium is stated to have been covered over and the
                        Roman Games were celebrated for one day by the curule aediles Q. Metellus
                        and C. Servilius. The Plebeian Games also were celebrated for two days by
                        the plebeian aediles C. Mamilius and M. Caecilius Metellus. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> They also gave three statues to the temple of Ceres,
                        and a banquet was held in honour of Jupiter on the occasion of the Games.
                        The consuls then entered upon office; C. Claudius Nero for the first time,
                        M. Livius for the second. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As they had
                        balloted for their provinces they ordered the praetors to ballot for theirs.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The urban jurisdiction fell to C.
                        Hostilius, and the jurisdiction over aliens was also committed to him in
                        order that three praetors might be available for foreign service. A.
                        Hostilius was allotted to Sardinia, C. Mamilius to Sicily and L. Porcius to
                        Gaul. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The total military strength
                        amounted to twenty-three legions and were thus distributed: each of the
                        consuls had two; four were in Spain; each of the three praetors had two in
                        Sardinia, Sicily and Gaul respectively; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        C. Terentius had two in Etruria; Quintus Fulvius had two in Bruttium; Q.
                        Claudius had two in the neighbourhood of Tarentum and the Sallentine
                        district; C. Hostilius Tubulus had one at Capua; and two were raised in the
                        City for home defence. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The people
                        appointed the military tribunes for the first four legions; the consuls
                        commissioned the rest. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Prior to the departure of the consuls
                        religious observances were kept up for nine days owing to the fall of a
                        shower of stones at Veii. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As usual, no
                        sooner was one portent announced than reports were brought in of others. At
                        Menturnae the temple of Jupiter and the sacred grove of Marica were struck
                        with lightning, as were also the wall of Atella and one of the gates.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The people of Menturnae reported a
                        second and more appalling portent; a stream of blood had flowed in at their
                        gate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Capua a wolf had entered the gate
                        by night and mauled one of the watch. These portents were expiated by the
                        sacrifice of full-grown victims, and special intercessions for the whole of
                        one day were ordered by the pontiffs. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Subsequently a second nine days' observance was ordered in consequence of a
                        shower of stones which fell in the Armilustrum. No sooner were men's fears
                        allayed by these expiatory rites than a fresh report came, this time from
                        Frusino, to the effect that a child had been born there in size and
                        appearance equal to one four years old, and what was still more startling,
                        like the case at Sinuessa two years previously, it was impossible to say
                        whether it was male or female. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        diviners who had been summoned from Etruria said that this was a dreadful
                        portent, and the thing must be banished from Roman soil, kept from any
                        contact with the earth, and buried in the sea. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They enclosed it alive in a box, took it out to sea,
                        and dropped it overboard. </p>
                    <p> The pontiffs also decreed that three bands of maidens, each consisting of
                        nine, should go through the City singing a hymn. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This hymn was composed by the poet Livius, and while
                        they were practicing it in the temple of Jupiter Stator, the shrine of Queen
                        Juno on the Aventine was struck by lightning. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The diviners were consulted, and they declared that
                        this portent concerned the matrons and that the goddess must be appeased by
                        a gift. The curule aediles issued an edict summoning to the Capitol all the
                        matrons whose homes were in Rome or within a distance of ten miles. When
                        they were assembled they selected twenty-five of their number to receive
                        their offerings; these they contributed out of their dowries. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> From the sum thus collected a golden basin was
                        made and carried as an oblation to the Aventine, where the matrons offered a
                        pure and chaste sacrifice. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Immediately
                        afterwards the Keepers of the Sacred Books gave notice of a day for further
                        sacrificial rites in honour of this deity. The following was the order of
                        their observance. Two white heifers were led from the temple of Apollo
                        through the Carmental Gate into the City; after them were borne two images
                        of the goddess, made of cypress wood. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Then twenty-seven maidens, vested in long robes, walked in procession
                        singing a hymn in her honour, which was perhaps admired in those rude days,
                        but which would be considered very uncouth and unpleasing if it were recited
                        now. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After the train of maidens came the
                        ten Keepers of the Sacred Books wearing the toga praetexta, and with laurel
                        wreaths round their brows. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> From the
                        Carmental Gate the procession marched along the Vicus Jugarius into the
                        Forum, where it stopped. Here the girls, all holding a cord, commenced a
                        solemn dance while they sang, beating time with their feet to the sound of
                        their voices. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> They then resumed their
                        course along the Vicus Tuscus and the Velabrum, through the Forum Boarium,
                        and up the Clivus Publicius till they reached the temple of Juno. Here the
                        two heifers were sacrificed by the Ten Keepers, and the cypress images were
                        carried into the shrine. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the deities had been duly appeased,
                        the consuls proceeded with the levy and conducted it with a rigour and
                        exactitude such as no one could remember in former years. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The appearance of a fresh enemy in Italy redoubled the
                        apprehensions generally felt as to the issue of the war, and at the same
                        time there was a smaller population from which to obtain the men required.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Even the maritime colonies which were
                        declared to have been solemnly and formally exempted from military service
                        were called upon to furnish <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> soldiers,
                        and on their refusal a day was fixed on which they were to appear before the
                        senate and state, each for themselves, the grounds on which they claimed
                        exemption. On the appointed day representatives attended from Ostia, Alsium,
                        Antium, Anxur, Menturnae, Sinuessa, and from Sena on the upper sea.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Each community produced its title to
                        exemption, but as the enemy was in Italy, the claim was disallowed in the
                        case of all but two-Antium and Ostia-and in the case of these, the men of
                        military age were compelled <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> to take an
                        oath that they would not sleep outside their walls for more than thirty
                        nights as long as the enemy was in Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Everybody was of opinion that the consuls ought to take the field at the
                        earliest possible moment; for Hasdrubal must be met on his descent from the
                        Alps, otherwise he might foment a rising amongst the Cisalpine Gauls and in
                        Etruria, and Hannibal must be kept fully employed, so as to prevent his
                        leaving Bruttium and meeting his brother. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Still Livius delayed. He did not feel confidence in the troops assigned to
                        him, and complained that his colleague had his choice of three splendid
                        armies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He also suggested the recall to
                        the standards of the volunteer slaves. The senate gave the consuls full
                        powers to obtain reinforcements in any way they thought best, to select what
                        men they wanted from all the armies and to exchange and transfer troops from
                        one province to another as <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> they thought
                        best in the interest of the State. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                        consuls acted in perfect harmony in carrying out all these measures. The
                        volunteer slaves were incorporated in the nineteenth and twentieth legions.
                        Some authorities assert that Publius Scipio sent M. Livius strong
                        reinforcements from Spain including 8000 Gauls and Spaniards, 2000
                        legionaries, and 1000 Numidian and Spanish horse, and that this force was
                        transported to Italy by M. Lucretius. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It
                        is further stated that C. Mamilius sent 3000 bowmen and slingers from
                        Sicily. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The excitement and alarm in Rome were
                        heightened by a despatch from L. Porcius, the propraetor commanding in Gaul.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He announced that Hasdrubal had left
                        his winter quarters and was actually crossing the Alps. He was to be joined
                        by a force of 8000 men raised and equipped amongst the Ligurians, unless a
                        Roman army were sent into Liguria to occupy the attention of the Gauls.
                        Porcius added that he would himself advance as far as he safely could with
                        such a weak army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The receipt of this
                        despatch made the consuls hurry on the enlistment, and on its completion
                        they left for their provinces at an earlier date than they had fixed. Their
                        intention was that each of them should keep his enemy in his own province
                        and not allow the brothers to unite or concentrate their forces. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> They were materially assisted by a miscalculation
                        which Hannibal made. He quite expected his brother to cross the Alps during
                        the summer, but remembering his own experience in the passage first of the
                        Rhone and then of the Alps, and how for five months he had had to carry on
                        an exhausting struggle against man and against <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> nature, he had no idea that Hasdrubal's passage would
                        be as easy and rapid as it really was. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Owing to this mistake he was too late in moving out of his winter quarters.
                        Hasdrubal, however, had a more expeditious march and met with fewer
                        difficulties than either he or anyone else expected. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Not only did the Arverni and the other Gallic and
                        Alpine tribes give him a friendly reception, but they followed his standard.
                        He was, moreover, marching mainly over roads made by his brother where
                        before there were none, and as the Alps had now been traversed to and fro
                        for twelve years he found the natives less savage. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Previously they had never visited strange lands nor
                        been accustomed to seeing strangers in their own country; they had held no
                        intercourse with the rest of the world. Not knowing at first the destination
                        of the Carthaginian general, they imagined that he wanted their rocks and
                        strongholds and intended to carry off their men and cattle as plunder.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then when they heard about the Punic
                        War with which Italy had been alight for twelve years, they quite understood
                        that the Alps were only a passage from one country to another, and that the
                        struggle lay between two mighty cities, separated by a vast stretch of sea
                        and land, which were contending for power and dominion. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> This was the reason why the Alps lay open to Hasdrubal.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But whatever advantage he gained by
                        the rapidity of his march was forfeited by the <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> time he wasted at Placentia, where he commenced a
                        fruitless investment instead of attempting a direct assault. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Lying as it did in flat open country he thought
                        that the town would be taken without difficulty, and that the capture of
                        such an important colony would deter the others from offering any
                        resistance. Not only was his own advance hampered by this investment, but he
                        also retarded Hannibal's movements, who, on learning of <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> his brother's unexpectedly rapid march, had quitted his
                        winter quarters, for Hannibal knew what a slow business sieges usually are
                        and had not forgotten his own unsuccessful attempt on that very colony after
                        his victory at the Trebia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls left for the front, each by a
                        separate route, and their departure was watched with feelings of painful
                        anxiety. Men realised that the republic had two wars on its hands
                        simultaneously; they recalled the disasters which followed upon Hannibal's
                        appearance in Italy, and wondered what gods would be so propitious to the
                        City and the empire as to grant victory over two enemies at once in widely
                        distant fields. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Up till now heaven had
                        preserved it by balancing victories against defeats. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When the cause of Rome had been brought to the ground
                        in Italy at Thrasymenus and at Cannae, the successes in Spain raised it up
                        once more; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> when reverse after reverse had
                        been sustained in Spain and the State lost its two generals and the greater
                        part of both their armies, the many successes achieved in Italy and Sicily
                        stayed the collapse of the battered republic, whilst the distance at which
                        that unsuccessful war was waged <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> in the
                        remotest corner of the world afforded in itself a breathing space. Now they
                        had two wars on hand, both in Italy; two generals who bore illustrious names
                        were closing round Rome; the whole weight of the peril, the whole burden of
                        the conflict had settled down on one spot. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The one who was first victorious would in a few days unite his forces with
                        the other. Such were the gloomy forebodings, and they were deepened by the
                        recollections of the past year made so mournful by the death of both
                        consuls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In this depressed and anxious
                        mood the population escorted the consuls to the gates of the City, as they
                        left for their respective provinces. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There
                        is an utterance recorded of M. Livius which shows his bitter feeling towards
                        his fellow-citizens. When on his departure Q. Fabius warned him against
                        giving battle before he knew the sort of enemy he had to meet, Livius is
                        said to have replied that he would fight as soon as he caught sight of the
                        enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When asked why he was in such a
                        hurry he said: "Either I shall win special distinction from conquering such
                        an enemy or a well-earned if not very honourable pleasure from the defeat of
                        my fellow-citizens." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Before the consul
                        Claudius Nero arrived in his province, Hannibal, who was marching just
                        outside the frontiers of the territory of Larinum on his way to the
                        Sallentini, was attacked by C. Hostilius Tubulus. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> His light infantry created considerable disorder
                        amongst the enemy, who were not prepared for action; 4000 of them were
                        slain, and nine standards captured. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Q.
                        Claudius had quartered his troops in various cities in the Sallentine
                        district, and on hearing of the enemy's approach he quitted his winter
                        quarters and took the field against him. Not wishing to meet both armies at
                        once, Hannibal left the neighbourhood by night, and withdrew into Bruttium.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Claudius marched back into the
                        Sallentine territory, and Hostilius while on his way to Capua met the consul
                        Claudius Nero near Venusia. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Here a corps
                        d'elite was selected from both armies, consisting of 40,000 infantry and
                        2500 cavalry, which the consul intended to employ against Hannibal. The rest
                        of the troops Hostilius was ordered to take to Capua and then hand them over
                        to Q. Fulvius the proconsul. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal assembled the whole of his force,
                        those in winter quarters and those on garrison duty in Bruttium, and marched
                        to Grumentum in Lucania, with the intention of recovering the towns whose
                        inhabitants had been led by their fears to go over to Rome. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The Roman consul marched to the same place from
                        Venusia, making careful reconnaissances as he advanced, and fixed his camp
                        about a mile and a half from the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The rampart of the Carthaginian camp seemed to be almost touching the walls
                        of Grumentum; there was really half a mile between them. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Between the two hostile camps the ground was level; on
                        the Carthaginian left and the Roman right stretched a line of bare hills
                        which did not arouse any suspicion on either side, as they were quite devoid
                        of vegetation and afforded no hollows where an ambuscade could be concealed.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the plain between the camps small
                        skirmishes took place between the advanced posts, the one object of the
                        Roman evidently being to prevent the retirement of the enemy; Hannibal, who
                        was anxious to get away, marched on to the field with his whole force
                        marshalled for battle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul,
                        adopting his enemy's tactics with all the more chance of success since there
                        could be no fears of an ambuscade on such open ground, told off five cohorts
                        strengthened with five maniples of Roman troops to mount the hill by night
                        and take their station in the dip on the other side. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He placed T. Claudius Asellus a military tribune and P.
                        Claudius a prefect of allies in command of the party, and gave them
                        instructions as to the moment when they were to rise from ambush and attack
                        the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At dawn of the following day he
                        led out the whole of his force, horse and foot, to battle. Soon after
                        Hannibal, too, gave the signal for action, and his camp rang with the shouts
                        of his men as they ran to arms. Scrambling through the gates of the camp,
                        mounted and unmounted men each trying to be first they raced over the plain
                        in scattered groups towards the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        When the consul saw them in this disorder he ordered C. Aurunculeius,
                        military tribune of the third legion, to send the cavalry attached to his
                        legion at full gallop against the enemy, for, as he said, they were
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> scattered over the plain like a
                        flock of sheep and could be ridden down and trampled under foot before they
                        could close their ranks. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal had not left his camp, when he
                        heard the noise of the battle. He lost not a moment in leading his force
                        against the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Roman cavalry had
                        already created a panic amongst the foremost of their assailants, the first
                        legion and the allied contingent on the left wing were coming into action,
                        the enemy in no sort of formation were fighting with infantry or cavalry as
                        they happened to meet them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As their
                        reinforcements and supports came up the fighting became more general, and
                        Hannibal would have succeeded in getting his men into order in spite of the
                        confusion and panic-a task <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> almost
                        impossible for any but veteran troops under a veteran commander-if they had
                        not heard in their rear the shouts of the cohorts and maniples running down
                        the hill, and saw themselves in danger of being cut off from their camp.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The panic spread and flight became
                        general in all parts of the field. The nearness of their camp made their
                        flight easy, and for this reason their losses were comparatively small,
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> considering that the cavalry were
                        pressing on their rear and the cohorts charging along an easy road down the
                        hill were attacking their flank Still, over 8000 men were killed and 700
                        made <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> prisoners, nine standards were
                        captured, and of the elephants which had proved useless in the confusion and
                        hurry of the fight four were killed and two captured. About 500 Roman and
                        allies fell. The next day the Carthaginians remained quiet. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The Roman general marched in battle order on to the
                        field, but when he saw that no standards were advancing from the opposing
                        camp he ordered his men to gather the spoils of the slain and collect the
                        bodies of their comrades and bury them in one common grave. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Then for several days in succession he marched up so
                        close to the gates that it seemed as though he were going to attack the
                        camp, until Hannibal made up his mind to depart. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Leaving numerous fires burning and tents standing on
                        the side of the camp facing the Romans, and a few Numidians who were to show
                        themselves on the rampart and at the gates, he set out with the intention of
                        marching into Apulia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as it grew
                        light, the Roman army approached the rampart and the Numidians made
                        themselves visible on the ramparts and at the gates. After deceiving their
                        enemy for some time they rode off at full speed to join their comrades.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the consul found that the camp
                        was silent and that even the few who had been patrolling it at dawn were
                        nowhere visible, he sent two troopers into the camp to reconnoitre. They
                        brought back word that they had examined it and found it safe everywhere, on
                        which he ordered the troops to enter. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He
                        waited while the soldiers secured the plunder, and then the signal was given
                        to retire; long before nightfall he had his soldiers back in camp.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Very early next morning he started in
                        pursuit and, guided by the local information supplied to him and the traces
                        of their retreat, he succeeded, by making forced marches, in coming up with
                        the enemy not far from Venusia. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There a
                        second irregular action took place in which the Carthaginians lost 2000 men.
                        After this Hannibal decided to give no further opportunity of fighting and,
                        in a series of night marches over the mountains, made for Metapontum.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Hanno was in command of the garrison
                        here, and he was sent with a few troops into Bruttium to raise a fresh army
                        there. The rest of his force Hannibal incorporated with his own, and
                        retracing his steps reached Venusia, and from there went on to Canusium.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Nero never lost touch with him, and
                        while he was following him to Metapontum he sent Q. Fulvius into Lucania, so
                        that that country might not be left without a defending force. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After Hasdrubal had raised the siege of
                        Placentia, he sent off four Gaulish and two Numidian troopers with
                        despatches to Hannibal. They had passed through the midst of the enemy, and
                        almost traversed the length of Italy, and were following Hannibal's retreat
                        to Metapontum when they missed the road and were brought to Tarentum.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here they were caught by a Roman
                        foraging party dispersed amongst the fields, and conducted to the propraetor
                        Q. Claudius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first they tried to
                        mislead him by evasive answers, but the fear of torture compelled them to
                        confess the truth, and they informed him that they were the bearers of
                        despatches from Hasdrubal to Hannibal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        They and the despatches, with seals intact, were handed over to L.
                        Verginius, one of the military tribunes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        He was furnished with an escort of two troops of Samnite cavalry, and
                        ordered to conduct the six troopers to the consul Claudius Nero. After the
                        despatches had been translated to him, and the prisoners had been examined,
                        the consul saw that the regulation which confined <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> each consul to the province and the army and the enemy
                        which had been designated for him by the senate would not in the present
                        instance be beneficial to the republic. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                        would have to venture upon a startling innovation, and though at the outset
                        it might create as much alarm among his own countrymen as amongst the enemy,
                        it would, when carried through, turn their great fear into great rejoicing.
                        Hasdrubal's despatches he sent on to the senate together with one from
                        himself explaining his project. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As
                        Hasdrubal had written to say that he would meet his brother in Umbria, he
                        advised the senators to recall the Roman legion from Capua, raise troops in
                        Rome, and with this City force oppose the enemy at Narnia. This was what he
                        wrote to the senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But he also sent
                        couriers into the districts through which he intended to march-Larinum,
                        Marrucina, Frentanum and Praetutia-to warn the inhabitants to collect all
                        the supplies from the towns and the country districts and have them in
                        readiness on the line of march to feed the troops. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> They were also to bring their horses and other draught
                        animals so that there might be an ample supply of vehicles for the men who
                        fell out through fatigue. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Out of the
                        whole of his army he selected a force of 6000 infantry and 1000 cavalry, the
                        flower of the Roman and allied contingents, and gave out that he intended to
                        seize the nearest city in Lucania with its Carthaginian garrison, so that
                        all should be ready to march. Starting by night, he turned off in the
                        direction of Picenum. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Leaving Q. Catius,
                        his second in command, in charge of the camp he marched as rapidly as he
                        could to join his colleague. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The excitement and alarm in Rome were
                        quite as great as they had been two years previously, when the Carthaginian
                        camp was visible from the walls and gates of the City. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> People could not make up their minds whether the
                        consul's daring march was more to be lauded or censured, and it was evident
                        that they would await the result before pronouncing for or against it-a most
                        unfair way of judging. "The camp." they said, "is left, near an enemy like
                        Hannibal, with no general, with an army from which its main strength, the
                        flower of its soldiery, has been withdrawn. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Pretending to march into Lucania, the consul has taken the road to
                        Picenum and Gaul, leaving the safety of his camp dependent upon the
                        ignorance of the enemy as to what direction he and his division have taken.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What will happen if they find that
                        out, if Hannibal with his whole army decides to start in pursuit of Nero
                        with his 6000 men, or attacks the camp, left as it is to be plundered,
                        without defence, without a general with full powers or one who can take the
                        auspices?" <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The former disasters in this
                        war, the recollection of the two consuls killed the previous year, filled
                        them with dread. "All those things," it was said, "happened when the enemy
                        had only one commander and one army in Italy; now there are two distinct
                        wars going on, two immense armies, and practically two Hannibals in Italy,
                        for Hasdrubal too is a son of Hamilcar and is quite as able and energetic a
                        commander as his brother. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He has been
                        trained in war against Rome for many years in Spain, and distinguished
                        himself by the double victory in which he annihilated two Roman armies and
                        their illustrious captains. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the
                        rapidity of his march from Spain, and the way in which he has roused the
                        tribes of Gaul to arms, he can boast of far greater success than even
                        Hannibal himself, for he got <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> together an
                        army in those very districts in which his brother lost the greater part of
                        his force by cold and hunger, the most miserable of all deaths." <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Those who were acquainted with recent events in
                        Spain went on to say that he would meet in Nero a general who was no
                        stranger to him, for he was the general whom Hasdrubal, when intercepted in
                        a narrow pass, had duped and baffled as though he were a child by making
                        illusory proposals for peace. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In this way
                        they exaggerated the strength of the enemy and depreciated their own, their
                        fears made them look on the darkest side of everything. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Nero had placed a sufficient distance
                        between himself and the enemy to make it safe for him to reveal his design,
                        he made a brief address to his men. "No commander," he said, "has ever
                        formed a project apparently more risky but really less so than mine.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I am leading you to certain victory.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> My colleague did not enter upon this
                        campaign until he had obtained from the senate such a force of infantry and
                        cavalry as he deemed sufficient, a force indeed more numerous and better
                        equipped than if he were advancing against Hannibal himself. However small
                        the addition you are now making to it, it will be enough to turn the scale.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When once the news spreads on the
                        battle-field-and I will take care that it does not spread sooner-that a
                        second consul has arrived with a second army, it will make victory no longer
                        doubtful. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Rumour decides battles; slight
                        impulses sway men's hopes and fears; if we are successful you yourselves
                        will reap almost all the glory of it, for it is always the last weight added
                        that has the credit of turning the balance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> You see for yourselves what admiring and enthusiastic crowds welcome you
                        as you march along." And indeed they did advance amidst vows and prayers and
                        blessings from the lines of men and women who were gathered everywhere out
                        of the fields and homesteads. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were
                        called the defenders of the republic, the vindicators of the City and
                        sovereignty of Rome; upon their swords and strong right hands depended all
                        security and liberty for the people and their children. The bystanders
                        prayed to all the gods and goddesses to grant them a safe and prosperous
                        march, a successful battle and an early victory over their foes. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> As they were now following them with anxious
                        hearts, so they prayed that they might fulfil the vows which they were
                        making when they went forth with joy to meet them flushed with the pride of
                        victory. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then they invited the soldiers to
                        take what they had brought for them, each begging and <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> entreating them to take from his hands rather than from
                        any one else's what would be of use to them and their draught animals, and
                        loading them with presents of all sorts. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        The soldiers showed the utmost moderation and refused to accept anything
                        that was not absolutely necessary. They did not interrupt their march or
                        leave the ranks or even halt to take food; day and night they went steadily
                        on, hardly allowing themselves the rest which nature demanded. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> The consul sent messages in advance to announce
                        his coming to his colleague, and to enquire whether it would be better to
                        come secretly or openly, by night or by day, and also whether they were to
                        occupy the same camp or separate ones. It was thought better that he should
                        come by night. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul Livius had issued a secret
                        order by means of the tessera that the tribunes should take in the tribunes
                        who were coming; the centurions, the centurions; the cavalry, their mounted
                        comrades; and the legionaries, the infantry. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> It was not desirable to extend the camp, his object was to keep the enemy
                        in ignorance of the other consul's arrival. The crowding together of a
                        larger number of men in the restricted space afforded by the tents was
                        rendered all the easier because Claudius' army, in their hurried march, had
                        brought hardly anything with them except their arms. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> On the march, however, their numbers had been augmented
                        by volunteers, partly old soldiers who had served their time and partly
                        young men who were anxious to join. Claudius enlisted those whose appearance
                        and strength seemed to qualify them for service. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Livius' camp was in the neighbourhood of Sena, and
                        Hasdrubal was about half a mile distant. When he found that he was nearing
                        the place, the consul halted where he was screened by the mountains, so as
                        not to enter the camp before night. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then
                        the men entered in silence and were conducted to the tents, each by a man of
                        his own rank, where they received the warmest of welcomes and most
                        hospitable entertainment. Next day a council of war was held, at which the
                        praetor L. Porcius Licinus was present. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        His camp was now contiguous with that of the consuls; before their arrival
                        he had adopted every possible device to baffle the Carthaginian by marching
                        along the heights and seizing the passes, so as to check his advance, and
                        also by harassing his columns whilst on the march. Many of those present at
                        the council were in favour of postponing battle in order that Nero might
                        recruit his troops worn out with the length of the march and want of sleep,
                        and also might have a few days for getting to know his enemy. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Nero tried to dissuade them from this course, and
                        earnestly implored them not to endanger the success of his plan after he had
                        made it perfectly safe by the rapidity of his march. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Hannibal's activity, he argued, was so to speak
                        paralysed by a mistake which he would not be long in rectifying; he had
                        neither attacked the camp in the absence of its commander, nor had he made
                        up his mind to follow him on his march. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Before he moved, it was possible to destroy Hasdrubal's army and march back
                        into Apulia. "To give the enemy time by putting off the engagement would be
                        to betray their camp in Apulia to Hannibal and give him a clear road into
                        Gaul, so that he would be able to form a junction with Hasdrubal when and
                        where he pleased. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The signal for action
                        must be given at once, and we must march on to the field and profit by the
                        mistakes which both our enemies are making, the distant one and the one
                        close at hand. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That one does not know
                        that he has to deal with a smaller army than he supposes, this one is not
                        aware that he has to meet a larger and stronger one than he imagines."
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As soon as the council broke up, the
                        red ensign was displayed and the army at once took the field. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The enemy were already standing in front
                        of their camp, in battle order. But there was a pause. Hasdrubal had ridden
                        to the front with a handful of cavalry, when he noticed in the hostile ranks
                        some well-worn shields which he had not seen before, and some unusually lean
                        horses; the numbers, too, seemed greater than usual. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Suspecting the truth he hastily withdrew his troops
                        into camp and sent men down to the river from which the Romans obtained
                        water, to catch if they could some of the watering parties and see whether
                        they were especially sunburnt, as is generally the case after a long march.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He ordered, at the same time, mounted
                        patrols to ride round the consul's camp and observe whether the lines had
                        been extended in any direction and to notice at the same time whether the
                        bugle-call was sounded once or twice in the camp. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> They reported that both the camps-M. Livius' camp and
                        that of L. Porcius-were just as they had been, no addition had been made,
                        and this misled him. But they also informed him that the bugle-call was
                        sounded once in the praetor's camp and twice in the consul's, and this
                        perturbed the veteran commander, familiar as he was with the habits of the
                        Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He concluded that both the consuls
                        were there and was anxiously wondering how the one consul had got away from
                        Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Least of all could he suspect
                        what had actually occurred, namely that Hannibal had been so completely
                        outwitted that he did not know the whereabouts of the commander and the army
                        whose camp had been so close to his own. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        As his brother had not ventured to follow the consul, he felt quite certain
                        that he had sustained a serious defeat, and he felt the gravest
                        apprehensions lest he should have come too late to save a desperate
                        situation, and lest the Romans should enjoy the same good fortune in Italy
                        which they had met with in Spain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then
                        again he was convinced that his letter had never reached Hannibal, but had
                        been intercepted by the consul who then hastened to crush him. Amidst these
                        gloomy forebodings he ordered the camp fires to be extinguished, and gave
                        the signal at the first watch for all the baggage to be collected in
                        silence. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The army then left the camp. In
                        the hurry and confusion of the night march the guides, who had not been kept
                        under very close observation, slipped away; one hid himself in a place
                        selected beforehand, the other swam across the Metaurus at a spot well known
                        to him. The column deprived of its guides marched on aimlessly across
                        country, and many, worn out by sleeplessness flung themselves down to rest,
                        those who remained with the standards becoming fewer and fewer. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Until daylight showed him his route, Hasdrubal
                        ordered the head of the column to advance cautiously, but finding that owing
                        to the bends and turns of the river he had made little progress, he made
                        arrangements for crossing it as soon as daybreak should show him a
                        convenient place. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But he was unable to
                        find one, for the further he marched from the sea, the higher were the banks
                        which confined the stream, and by thus wasting the day he gave his enemy
                        time to follow him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nero with the whole of the cavalry was the
                        first to come up, then Porcius followed with the light infantry. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> They began to harass their wearied enemy by
                        repeated charges on all sides, until Hasdrubal stopped a march which began
                        to resemble a flight, and decided to form camp on a hill which commanded the
                        river. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At this juncture Livius appeared
                        with the heavy infantry, not in order of march, but deployed and armed for
                        immediate battle. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All their forces were
                        now massed together, and the line was formed; Claudius Nero taking command
                        of the right wing, Livius of the left, while the centre was assigned to the
                        praetor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When Hasdrubal saw that he must
                        give up all idea of entrenching himself and prepare to fight, he stationed
                        the elephants in the front, the Gauls near them on the left to oppose
                        Claudius, not so much because he trusted them as because he hoped they would
                        frighten the enemy, while on the right, where he commanded in person, he
                        posted the Spaniards in whom as veteran troops he placed most confidence.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Ligurians were stationed in the
                        centre behind the elephants. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His formation
                        was greater in depth than length and the Gauls were covered by a hill which
                        extended across their front. That part of the line which Hasdrubal and his
                        Spaniards held engaged the Roman left; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the
                        whole of the Roman right was shut out from the fighting, the hill in front
                        prevented them from making either a frontal or a flank attack. The struggle
                        between Livius and Hasdrubal was a fierce one, and both sides lost heavily.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Here were the two captains, the
                        greater part of the Roman infantry and cavalry, the Spaniards who were
                        veteran soldiers and used to the Roman methods of fighting, and also the
                        Ligurians, a people hardened by warfare. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        To this part of the field the elephants too had been driven, and at their
                        first onset they threw the front ranks into confusion and forced the
                        standards to give way. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then as the
                        fighting became hotter and the noise and shouting more furious, it became
                        impossible to control them, they rushed about between the two armies as
                        though they did not know to which side they belonged, just like ships
                        drifting rudderless. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Nero made fruitless
                        efforts to scale the hill in front of him, calling out repeatedly to his
                        men, "Why have we made so long a march at such break-neck speed? <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> "When he found it impossible to reach the enemy
                        in that direction, he detached some cohorts from his right wing where he saw
                        that they were more likely to stand on guard than to take any part in the
                        fighting, led them past the rear of his division and to the surprise of his
                        own men as much as of the enemy commenced an attack upon the enemy's flank.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So rapidly was this maneuver
                        executed, that almost as soon as they showed themselves on the flank, they
                        were attacking the rear of the enemy. Thus attacked on every side, front,
                        flank and rear, Spaniards and Ligurians alike were simply massacred where
                        they stood. At last the carnage reached the Gauls. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Here there was very little fighting, for a great many
                        had fallen <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> out during the night and
                        were lying asleep everywhere in the fields, and those who were still with
                        the standards were worn out by the long march and want of sleep, and being
                        quite unable to stand fatigue could hardly sustain the weight of their
                        armour. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> It was now mid-day, and the heat
                        and thirst made them gasp for breath, until they were cut down or made
                        prisoners without offering any resistance. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> More elephants were killed by their
                        drivers than by the enemy. They had a carpenter's chisel and a mallet, and
                        when the maddened beasts rushed among their own side the driver placed the
                        chisel between the ears just where the head is joined to the neck and drove
                        it home with all his might. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was the
                        quickest method that had been discovered of putting these huge animals to
                        death when there was no hope of controlling them, and Hasdrubal was the
                        first to introduce it. Often had this commander distinguished himself in
                        other battles, but never more than in this one. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He kept up the spirits of his men as they fought by
                        words of encouragement and by sharing their dangers; when, weary and
                        dispirited, they would no longer fight, he rekindled their courage by his
                        entreaties and reproaches; he rallied those in flight and often revived the
                        battle where it had been abandoned. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At
                        last when the fortune of the day was decisively with the enemy he refused to
                        survive that great army which had followed him, drawn by the magic of his
                        name, and setting spurs to his horse dashed against a Roman cohort.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There he fell fighting-a death worthy
                        of Hamilcar's son and Hannibal's brother. Never during the whole of the war
                        had so many of the enemy perished in a single battle. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The death of the commander and the destruction of his
                        army were regarded as an adequate repayment for the disaster of Cannae.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> 56,000 of the enemy were killed, 5400
                        taken prisoners, and a great quantity of plunder was secured, especially of
                        gold and silver. Above 3000 Romans who had been captured by the enemy were
                        recovered, and this was some consolation for the losses incurred in the
                        battle. For the victory was by no means a bloodless one; about 8000 Romans
                        and allies were killed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So satiated were
                        the victors with bloodshed and carnage that when it was reported to Livius
                        on the following day that the Cisalpine Gauls and Ligurians who had taken no
                        part in the battle or had escaped from the field were marching off in a body
                        without general or standards or any one to give the word <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> of command, and that a single squadron of cavalry could
                        wipe out the whole lot, the consul replied: "Let some survive to carry the
                        news of their defeat and our victory." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The night after the battle Nero started
                        off at a more rapid pace than he had come, and in six days reached his camp
                        and was once more in touch with Hannibal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        His march was not watched by the same crowds as before, because no
                        messengers preceded him, but his return was welcomed with such extravagant
                        delight that people were almost beside themselves for joy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As to the state of feeling in Rome, it is impossible to
                        describe it, or to picture the anxiety with which the citizens waited for
                        the result of the battle or the enthusiasm which the report of the victory
                        aroused. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Never from the day when the news
                        came that Nero had commenced his march had any senator left the House, or
                        the people the Forum from sunrise to sunset. The matrons, as they could give
                        no active help, betook themselves to prayers and intercessions; they
                        thronged all the shrines and assailed the gods with supplications and vows.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst the citizens were in this state
                        of anxious suspense, a vague rumour was started to the effect that two
                        troopers belonging to Narnia had gone <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        from the battle-field to the camp there which was holding the road to Umbria
                        with the announcement that the enemy had been cut to pieces. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> People listened to the rumour, but they could not
                        take it in, the news was too great, too joyful for them to realise or to
                        accept as true, and the very speed at which it had travelled made it less
                        credible, for the battle was reported as having taken place only two days
                        previously. Then followed a despatch from L. Manlius Acidinus, reporting the
                        arrival of the two troopers in his camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        When this despatch was carried through the Forum to the praetor's tribunal
                        the senators left their seats, and such was the excitement of the people as
                        they pushed and struggled round the door of the senate-house that the
                        courier could not get near it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was
                        dragged away by the crowd, who demanded with loud shouts that the despatch
                        should be read from the rostra before it was read in the senate-house.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At last the magistrates succeeded in
                        forcing back and restraining the populace, and it became possible for all to
                        share in the joyous news they were so impatient to learn. The despatch was
                        read first in the senate-house, and then in the Assembly. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> It was listened to with different feelings according to
                        each man's temperament; some regarded the news as absolutely true, others
                        would not believe it till they had the consul's despatch and the report of
                        the envoys. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Word was brought that the envoys were
                        approaching. Everybody young and old alike ran out to meet them, each eager
                        to drink in the good tidings with eyes and <milestone n="2??" unit="section"
                        /> ears, and the crowd extended as far as the Mulvian bridge. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The envoys were L. Veturius Philo, P. Licinius
                        Varus and Q. Caecilius Metellus. They made their way to the Forum surrounded
                        by a crowd which represented every class of the population, and besieged by
                        questions on all sides as to what had really happened. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> No sooner did any one hear that the army of the enemy
                        and its commander had been slain whilst the consuls and their army were
                        safe, than he hastened to make others sharers of his joy. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The senate-house was reached with difficulty, and with
                        much greater difficulty was the crowd prevented from invading the space
                        reserved for the senators. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here the
                        despatch was read, and then the envoys were conducted to the Assembly. After
                        the despatch was read, L. Veturius gave fuller details and his narrative was
                        received with bursts of applause, which finally swelled into universal
                        cheers, the Assembly being hardly able to contain itself for joy. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Some ran to the temples to give thanks to heaven,
                        others hurried home that their wives and children might hear the good news.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The senate decreed a three days'
                        thanksgiving "because the consuls, M. Livius and C. Claudius Nero, had
                        preserved their own armies in safety and destroyed the army of the enemy and
                        its commander." C. Hostilius, the praetor, issued the order for its
                        observance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The services were attended by
                        men and women alike, the temples were crowded all through the three days,
                        and the matrons in their most splendid robes, accompanied by their children,
                        offered their thanksgivings to the gods, as free from anxiety and fear as
                        though the war were over. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This victory
                        also relieved the financial position. People ventured to do business just as
                        in a time of peace, buying and selling, lending and repaying loans.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After Nero had returned to camp he
                        gave orders for Hasdrubal's head, which he had kept and brought with him, to
                        be thrown in front of the enemies' outpost, and the African prisoners to be
                        exhibited just as they were in chains. Two of them were released with orders
                        to go to Hannibal and report all that had happened. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Stunned by the blow which had fallen on his country and
                        on his family, it is said that Hannibal declared that he recognised the doom
                        which awaited Carthage. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He broke up his
                        camp, and decided to concentrate in Bruttium, the remotest corner of Italy,
                        all his supporters whom he could no longer protect, whilst scattered in the
                        different cities. The whole population of Metapontum had to leave their
                        homes together with all the Lucanians who acknowledged his supremacy, and
                        were transported into Bruttian territory. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
