<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six -
                    27</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to
                                thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="1089" xml:id="p.1089"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXVII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Cneius Fulvius, pro-consul, defeated by Hannibal and slain; the consul,
                        Claudius Marcellus, engages him with better success. Hannibal, raising his
                        camp, retires; Marcellus pursues, and forces him to an engagement. They
                        fight twice; in the first battle, Hannibal gains the advantage; in the
                        second, Marcellus. Tarentum betrayed to Fabius Maximus, the consul. Scipio
                        engages with Hasdrubal, the son of Hamilcar, at Baetula, in Spain, and
                        defeats him. Among other prisoners, a youth of royal race and exquisite
                        beauty is taken; Scipio sets him free, and sends him, enriched with
                        magnificent presents, to his uncle Masinissa. Marcellus and Quintus
                        Crispinus, consuls, drawn into an ambuscade by Hannibal; Marcellus is slain,
                        Crispinus escapes. Operations by Publius Sulpicius, praetor, against Philip
                        and the Achaeans. A census held; the number of citizens found to amount to
                        one hundred and thirty-seven thousand one hundred and eight: from which it
                        appears how great a loss they had sustained by the number of unsuccessful
                        battles they had of late been engaged in. Hasdrubal, who had crossed the
                        Alps with a reinforcement for Hannibal, defeated by the consuls, Marcus
                        Livius and Claudius Nero, and slain; with him fell fifty-six thousand men.
                    </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> SUCH was the state of affairs in Spain. In
                    Italy, the consul Marcellus, after regaining Salapia, which was betrayed into
                    his hands, took Maronea and Meles from the Samnites by force. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As many as three thousand of the soldiers of Hannibal,
                    which were left as a garrison, were here surprised and overpowered. The booty,
                    and there was a considerable quantity of it, was given up to the troops. Also,
                    two hundred and forty thousand pecks of wheat, with a hundred and ten thousand
                    peeks of barley, were found here. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The joy,
                    however, thus occasioned, was by no means so great as a disaster sustained a few
                    days afterwards, not far from the town Herdonea. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Cneius Fulvius, the consul, was lying encamped there, in the hope of
                    regaining <pb n="1090" xml:id="p.1090"/> Herdonea, which had revolted from the
                    Romans after the defeat at Cannae, his position being neither sufficiently
                    secure, from the nature of the place, nor strengthened by guards. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The natural negligence of the general was now
                    increased by the hope that their attachment to the Carthaginians was shaken,
                    when they had heard that Hannibal, after the loss of Salapia, had retired from
                    that neighbourhood into Bruttium. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Intelligence
                    of all these circumstances being conveyed to Hannibal by secret messengers from
                    Herdonea, at once excited an anxious desire to retain possession of a city in
                    alliance with him, and inspired a hope of attacking the enemy when unprepared.
                    With a lightly equipped force he hastened to Herdonea by forced marches, so as
                    almost to anticipate the report of his approach; and in order to strike greater
                    terror into the enemy, came up with his troops in battle-array. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman, equal to him in courage, but inferior in
                    strength, hastily drawing out his troops, engaged him. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The fifth legion and the left wing of the allied infantry
                    commenced the battle with spirit. But Hannibal ordered his cavalry, on a signal
                    given, to ride round, as soon as the foot forces had their eyes and thoughts
                    occupied with the contest before <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> them, and
                    one half of them to attack the camp of the enemy, the other half to fall upon
                    their rear, while busily engaged in fighting. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    He himself, sarcastically alluding to the similarity of the name Fulvius, as he
                    had defeated Cneius Fulvius, the praetor, two years ago, in the same country,
                    expressed his confidence that the issue of the battle would be similar.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Nor was this expectation vain; for after
                    many of the Romans had fallen in the close contest, and in the engagement with
                    the infantry, notwithstanding which they still preserved their ranks and stood
                    their ground; the alarm occasioned by the cavalry on their rear, and the enemy's
                    shout, which was heard at the same time from their camp, first put to flight the
                    sixth legion, which being posted in the second line, was first thrown into
                    confusion by the Numidians; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and then the
                    fifth legion, and those who were posted in the van. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Some fled precipitately, others were slain in the middle
                    space, where also Cneius Fulvius himself, with eleven military tribunes, fell.
                    Who can state with certainty how many thousands of the Romans and their allies
                    were slain in this battle, when I find in some accounts that thirteen, in others
                    that not more than seven, thousand were slain? <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> The <pb n="1091" xml:id="p.1091"/> conquerors got possession of the camp and
                    the spoil. Finding that Herdonea would have revolted to the Romans, and was not
                    likely to continue faithful to him if he departed thence, he removed all its
                    inhabitants to Metapontum and Thurium, and burnt it. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> He put to death the chief men who were found to have held
                    secret conferences with Fulvius. Such of the Romans as escaped this dreadful
                    carnage, fled half-armed, by different roads, into Samnium, to the consul
                    Marcellus. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus, who was not much discouraged at
                    this so great a disaster, sent a letter to the senate at Rome, with an account
                    of the loss of the general and army at Herdonea; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> observing, however, <quote> that he who, after the battle of Cannae, had
                        humbled Hannibal when elated with victory, was now marching against him, and
                        that he would cause that his present joy and exultation should not continue
                        long. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Rome, indeed, the grief occasioned by what
                    had occurred, and the fears entertained for the future, were excessive.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul passing out of Samnium into
                    Lucania, pitched his camp at Numistro, on a plain within view of Hannibal, who
                    occupied a hill. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He added also another
                    demonstration of his confidence; for he was the first to lead out his troops to
                    battle, nor did Hannibal decline fighting when he saw the standards carried out
                    from the gates. However, they drew up their forces so that the right wing of the
                    Carthaginians was extended up the hill, while the left wing of the Romans was
                    contiguous to the town. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For a long time
                    neither side had any advantage; but the battle having continued from the third
                    hour till night, and the first lines, which consisted, on the part of the
                    Romans, of the first legion and the right wing of the allied infantry, on the
                    part <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> of Hannibal, of the Spanish soldiers,
                    the balearic slingers, and the elephants, which were driven into the field after
                    the commencement of the battle, being fatigued with fighting, the first legion
                    was relieved by the third, and the right wing of allied infantry by the left;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> while on the part of the enemy fresh
                    troops took up the battle in place of those who were tired. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> A new and desperate conflict suddenly arose, instead of
                    that which was so feebly maintained, their minds and bodies being unimpaired by
                    fatigue; but night separated the combatants while the victory was undecided. The
                    following day the Romans stood drawn up for battle from sunrise till <pb
                        n="1092" xml:id="p.1092"/> late in the day; but none of the enemy coming out
                    against them, they gathered the spoils at their leisure, and collecting the
                    bodies of their own troops into a heap, burnt them. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The following night Hannibal decamped in silence, and moved
                    off into Apulia. As soon as daylight discovered the flight of the enemy,
                    Marcellus, leaving his wounded under the protection of a small garrison at
                    Numistro, in command of which he placed Lucius Furius Purpureo, a military
                    tribune, commenced a close pursuit of Hannibal, and overtook him at Venusia.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Here, during several days, parties of
                    troops sallying from the outposts, battles took place between foot and horse
                    promiscuously, rather irregular than important, but which for the most part were
                    favourable to the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The armies were
                    marched thence through Apulia without any engagement worth recording; for
                    Hannibal marched by night, seeking an opportunity for ambuscade, but Marcellus
                    never followed him except in broad daylight, and after having explored the
                    country. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time, while Flaccus was detained
                    at Capua in selling the property of the nobles, and letting out the lands which
                    had been forfeited, all of which he let for a rent to be paid in corn, lest
                    occasions for exercising severity towards the Campanians should be wanting, a
                    new piece of iniquity, which had been ripening in secret, was brought out in
                    evidence. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had compelled his soldiers,
                    withdrawn from the houses, to build for themselves huts after the military
                    manner, near the gates and walls; at once, that the houses of the city might be
                    let and occupied together with the land, and also through fear, lest the
                    excessive luxury of the city should enervate his troops as it had those of
                    Hannibal. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Now most of these were formed of
                    hurdles or boards, others of reeds interwoven, all being covered with straw, as
                    if combustible materials had been employed on purpose. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> A hundred and seventy Campanians, headed by the Blosii who
                    were brothers, had formed a conspiracy to set fire to all these at one hour of
                    the night; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but information of the conspiracy
                    having been given by one of the slaves of the Blosii, the gates were suddenly
                    closed by the command of the proconsul, and after the soldiers had been
                    assembled under arms, on a signal given, all who were implicated in the guilt
                    were seized, and, after a rigorous examination, were condemned and executed.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The <pb n="1093" xml:id="p.1093"/>
                    informers were rewarded with liberty and ten thousand <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses</hi> each. The people of Nuceria and Acerra, who complained that they
                    had no where to dwell, Acerra being partly burnt, and Nuceria demolished,
                    Fulvius sent to Rome to the senate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Permission
                    was given to the people of Acerra to rebuild what had been destroyed by fire.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The people of Nuceria were removed to
                    Atella, as they preferred; the people of Atella being ordered to migrate to
                    Calatia. Among the many and important events, sometimes prosperous, sometimes
                    adverse, which occupied men's thoughts, not even the citadel of Tarentum was
                    forgotten. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcus Ogulnius and Publius
                    Aquillius went into Etruria as commissioners to buy up corn to be conveyed to
                    Tarentum; and one thousand men out of the city troops, an equal number of Romans
                    and allies, were sent to the same place, together with the corn, for its
                    protection. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The summer was now on the close, and the time
                    for the election of consuls drew nigh; but a letter from Marcellus, in which he
                    stated, that it would not be for the interest of the state that he should depart
                    a single step from Hannibal, whom he was <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    severely pressing while retreating before him and evading an engagement, had
                    excited anxiety, lest they must either recall the consul from the war at that
                    time when he was most actively employed, or consuls should not be appointed for
                    the year. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The best course appeared to be to
                    recall in preference the consul Valerius from Sicily, although he was out of
                    Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A letter was sent to him by Lucius
                    Manlius, the city praetor, by order of the senate, together with the letter of
                    Marcus Marcellus, the consul, that he might learn from it what reason the senate
                    had for recalling him from his province rather than his colleague. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Much about this time ambassadors came to Rome from
                    king Syphax with accounts of the successful battles which he had fought with the
                    Carthaginians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They assured the senate that
                    there was no people to whom the king was more hostile than the Carthaginians,
                    and none to whom he was more friendly than the Romans. They said, that <quote>
                        he had before sent ambassadors into Spain, to Cneius and Publius Cornelius,
                        the Roman generals, but that he was now desirous to solicit the friendship
                        of the Romans, as it were, from the fountain-head itself. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate not only returned a gracious answer
                    to the ambassadors, but also sent as ambassadors to the king, with presents,
                    Lucius Genucius, Publius Pœtelius, and Publius Popillius. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The presents <pb n="1094" xml:id="p.1094"/> they carried
                    were a purple gown and vest, an ivory chair, and a bowl formed out of five
                    pounds of gold. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They received orders to
                    proceed forthwith to other petty princes of Africa, carrying with them as
                    presents for them gowns bordered with purple, and golden bowls weighing three
                    pounds each. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Marcus Atilius and Manius
                    Acilius were also sent as ambassadors to Alexandria, to king Ptolemy and queen
                    Cleopatra, to revive and renew the treaty of friendship with them, carrying with
                    them as presents a gown and purple tunic, with an ivory chair for the king, and
                    an embroidered gown and a purple vest for the queen. During the summer in which
                    these transactions took place, many prodigies were reported from the country and
                    cities in the neighbourhood; at Tusculum it was said that a lamb was yeaned with
                    its dug full of milk; that the roof of the temple of Jupiter was struck with
                    lightning and almost stripped of its entire covering. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Much about the same time it was reported that the ground in
                    front of the gate at Anagnia was struck, and that it continued burning for a day
                    and a night without any thing to feed the fire; <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> that at Compitum, in the territory of Anagnia, the birds had deserted their
                    nests in the trees in the grove of Diana; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    that snakes of amazing size had leaped up, like fishes sporting, in the sea at
                    Tarricina, not far from the port; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> at
                    Tarquinii, that a pig was produced with a human face; that in the territory of
                    Capena, at the grove of Feronia, four statues had sweated blood profusely for a
                    day and a night. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> These prodigies were
                    expiated with victims of the greater kind, according to a decree of the
                    pontiffs, and a supplication was fixed to be performed for one day at Rome at
                    all the shrines, and another in the territory of Capena at the grove of Feronia. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius, the consul, having been
                    summoned by letter, gave the command of the province and his army to Cincius the
                    praetor, sent Marcus Valerius Messala, commander of the fleet, with half of the
                    ships to Africa, at the same time to plunder the country and observe what
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the Carthaginians were doing, and what
                    preparations they were making, and then set out himself with ten ships for Rome;
                    where, having arrived in safety, he immediately convened the senate. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Here he made a recital of his services. That <quote>
                        after hostilities had been carried on, and severe losses often sustained,
                        both by sea and land, through a period of almost sixty years, he had
                        completely terminated the business of the province. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> That <pb n="1095" xml:id="p.1095"/> there was not one
                        Carthaginian in Sicily, nor one Sicilian absent of those who through fear
                        had been compelled to go into exile and live abroad; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> that all of them were brought back to their cities and
                        fields, and were employed in ploughing and sowing; <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> that the land which was deserted was now again
                        inhabited, not only yielding its fruits to its cultivators, but forming a
                        most certain resource for the supply of provisions to the Roman people in
                        peace and war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After this, Mutines and such others as had
                    rendered any services to the Roman people were introduced into the senate, and
                    all received honorary rewards in fulfilment of the consul's engagement.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Mutines was also made a Roman citizen, a
                    proposition to that effect having been made to the commons by a plebeian
                    tribune, on the authority of the senate. While these things were going on at
                    Rome, Marcus Valerius Messala, arriving on the coast of Africa before daylight,
                    made a sudden descent on the territory of Utica; <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> and after ravaging it to a great extent, and taking many prisoners, together
                    with booty of every kind, he returned to his ships and sailed over to Sicily. He
                    returned to Lilybaeum on the thirteenth day from the time he left it. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> From the prisoners, on examination, the following
                    facts were discovered, and all communicated in writing to the consul Laevinus in
                    order, so that he might know in what state the affairs of Africa were.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That "five thousand Numidians, with
                    Masinissa, the son of Gala, a youth of extraordinary spirit, were at Carthage,
                    and that other troops were hiring throughout all Africa, to be passed over into
                    Spain to Hasdrubal; in order that he might, as soon as possible, pass over into
                    Italy, with as large a force as could be collected, and form a junction with
                    Hannibal. That the Carthaginians considered their success dependent on this
                    measure. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That a very large fleet <milestone
                        n="13??" unit="section"/> was also in preparation for the recovery of
                    Sicily, which they believed would sail thither in a short time. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> The recital of these facts had such an effect upon
                    the senate, that they resolved that the consul ought not to wait for the
                    election, but that a dictator should be appointed to hold it, and that the
                    consul should immediately return to his province. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> A difference of opinion delayed this, for the consul
                    declared that he should nominate as dictator Marcus Valerius Messala, who then
                    commanded the fleet in Sicily; but the fathers denied that a person could be
                    appointed dictator who was not in the Roman territory, and this was limited by
                    Italy. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Marcus <pb n="1096" xml:id="p.1096"/>
                    Lucretius, a plebeian tribune, having taken the sense of the senate upon the
                    question, it was decreed, <quote> that the consul, before he quitted the city,
                        should put the question to the people, as to whom they wished to be
                        appointed dictator, and that he should nominate whomsoever they directed. If
                        the consul were unwilling that the praetor should put the question, and if
                        even he were unwilling to do it, that then the tribunes should make the
                        proposition to the commons. </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The consul refusing to submit to the people
                    what lay in his own power, and forbidding the praetor to do so, the plebeian
                    tribunes put the question, and the commons ordered that Quintus Fulvius, who was
                    then at Capua, should be nominated dictator. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    But on the night preceding the day on which the assembly of the people was to be
                    held for that purpose, the consul went off privately into Sicily; and the
                    fathers, thus deserted, decreed that a letter should be sent to Marcus Claudius,
                    in order that he might come to the support of the state, which had been
                    abandoned by his colleague, and appoint him dictator whom the commons had
                    ordered. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Thus Quintus Fulvius was appointed
                    dictator by Marcus Claudius, the consul, and in conformity with the same order
                    of the people, Publius Licinius Crassus, chief pontiff, was appointed master of
                    the horse by Quintus Fulvius, the dictator. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the dictator had arrived at Rome, he
                    sent Cneius Sempronius Blaesus, who had acted under him as lieutenant-general at
                    Capua, into the province of Etruria, to take the command of the army there, in
                    the room of the praetor, Caius Calpurnius, whom he had summoned by letter to
                    take the command of Capua and his own army. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                    fixed the first day he could for the election; which, however, could not be
                    brought to a conclusion, in consequence of a dispute which arose between the
                    tribunes and the dictator. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The junior century
                    of the Galerian tribe, to whose lot it fell to give their votes first, had named
                    Quintus Fulvius and Quintus Fabius as consuls; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    and the other centuries, on being called upon to vote according to their course,
                    would have inclined the same way, had not the plebeian tribunes, Caius and
                    Lucius Arennius, interposed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They said,
                        <quote> that it was hardly constitutional that a chief magistrate should be
                        continued in office; but that it was a precedent still more shocking, that
                        the very person who held the election should be appointed. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That, therefore, if the dictator should allow his own
                        name to appear, <pb n="1097" xml:id="p.1097"/> they would interpose against
                        the election; but if the names of any other persons besides himself were put
                        up, they should not impede it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The dictator defended the election by the
                    authority of the fathers, the order of the common, and precedents. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> For, <quote> in the consulate of Cneius Servilius,
                        when the other consul, Caius Flaminius, had fallen at Trasimenus, it was
                        proposed to the people on the authority of the fathers, and the people had
                        ordered, that as long as the war continued in Italy, it should be lawful for
                        the people to elect to the consulship whomsoever they pleased, out of those
                        persons who had been consuls, and as often as they pleased. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> That he had a precedent of ancient date, which was to
                        the point, in the case of Lucius Posthumius Megellus, who, while he was
                        interrex, had been created consul with Caius Junius Bubulcus, at an election
                        over which he himself presided; and a precedent of recent date, in Quintus
                        Fabius, who certainly would never have allowed himself to be re-elected, had
                        it not been for the good of the state. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the contest had been continued for a
                    long time, by arguments of this kind, at length the tribunes and the dictator
                    came to an agreement, that they should abide by what the senate should decide.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The fathers were of opinion, that such
                    was then the condition of the <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> state, that
                    it was necessary that its affairs should be conducted by old and experienced
                    generals, who were skilled in the art of war; and, therefore, that no delay
                    should take place in the election. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    tribunes then withdrew their opposition, and the election was held. Quintus
                    Fabius Maximus was declared consul for the fifth time, and Quintus Fulvius
                    Flaccus for the fourth. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The praetors were
                    then created; Lucius Veturius Philo, Titus Quintus Crispinus, Caius Hostilius
                    Tubulus, and Caius Aurunculeius. The magistrates for the year being appointed,
                    Quintus Fulvius resigned the dictatorship. At the end of this summer, a
                    Carthaginian fleet of forty ships, under the command of Hamilcar, passed over to
                    Sardinia. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> At first it laid waste the
                    territory of Olbia, and then Publius Manlius Vulso, with his army, making his
                    appearance, it sailed round thence to the other side of the island, and
                    devastating the territory of Caralis, returned to Africa with booty of every
                    kind. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Several Roman priests died this year,
                    and others were substituted. Caius Servilius was appointed pontiff, in the place
                    of Titus Otacilius Crassus. Tiberius Sempronius Longus, son of Tiberius, was
                    appointed as augur, in the place of Titus <pb n="1098" xml:id="p.1098"/>
                    Otacilius Crassus; and Tiberius Sempronius Longus, son of Tiberius, was
                    appointed decemvir for the performance of sacred rites, in the room of Tiberius
                    Sempronius Longus, son of Caius. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Marcius, king of the sacred rites, and Marcus Aemilius Papus, chief curio, died;
                    but no priests were appointed to succeed them this year. The censors this year
                    were Lucius Veturius Philo, and Publius Licinius Crassus, chief pontiff.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Licinius Crassus had neither been consul
                    nor praetor before he was appointed censor, he stepped from the aedileship to
                    the censorship. These censors neither chose a senate, nor transacted any public
                    business. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> the death of Lucius Veturius
                    prevented it; on this Licinius also gave up his office. The curule aediles,
                    Lucius Veturius and Publius Licinius Varus, repeated the Roman games during one
                    day. The plebeian aediles, Quintus Catius and Lucius Porcius Licinius, furnished
                    brazen statues for the temple of Ceres, out of the money arising from fines, and
                    exhibited games with great pomp and splendour, considering the circumstances of
                    the times. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of this year, Caius Laelius, the
                    lieutenant-general of Scipio, came to Rome on the thirty-fourth day after he set
                    out from Tarraco, and entering the city accompanied by a train of captives, drew
                    together a great concourse of people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The next
                    day, on being brought into the senate, he stated that Carthage, the capital of
                    Spain, had been captured in one day, that several cities which had revolted were
                    regained, and that fresh ones had been received into alliance. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> From the prisoners, information was gained, corresponding
                    for the most part with what was contained in the letter of Marcus Valerius
                    Messala. What produced the greatest effect upon the fathers, was the march of
                    Hasdrubal into Italy, which was with difficulty resisting Hannibal and his
                    forces. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Laelius also, who was brought before
                    the general assembly, gave a particular statement of the same things. The senate
                    decreed a supplication for one day, on account of the successes of Publius
                    Scipio, and ordered Caius Laelius to return as soon as possible to Spain, with
                    the ships he had brought with him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I have laid
                    the taking of Carthage in this year, on the authority of many writers, although
                    aware that some have stated that it was <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    taken the following year, because it appeared to me hardly probable that Scipio
                    should have spent an entire year in Spain in doing nothing. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius Maximus for the fifth time, and Quintus
                    Fulvius Flaccus for the fourth, <pb n="1099" xml:id="p.1099"/> having entered on
                    their offices of consuls on the ides of March, on the same day, Italy was
                    decreed as the province of both, their command, however, was distributed to
                    separate districts. Fabius was appointed to carry on the war at Tarentum;
                    Fulvius in Lucania and Bruttium. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Claudius was continued in command for the year. The praetors thin cast lots for
                    their provinces. Caius Hostilius Tubulus obtained the city jurisdiction; Lucius
                    Veturius Philo the foreign, with Gaul; Titus Quinctius Crispinus, Capua; Caius
                    Aurunculeius, Sardinia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The troops were thus
                    distributed through the provinces: Fulvius received the two legions which Marcus
                    Valerius Laevinus had in Sicily; Quintus Fabius, those which Caius Calpurnius
                    had commanded in Etruria. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The city troops
                    were to succeed those in Etruria; Caius Calpurnius commanding the same province
                    and the army. Titus Quinctius was to take the command of Capua, and the army
                    which had served under Quintus Fulvius there. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Veturius was to succeed Caius Laetorius, propraetor, in his province and
                    the command of the army, which was then at Ariminum. Marcus Marcellus had the
                    legions with which he had been successful when consul. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> To Marcus Valerius together with Lucius Cincius, for these
                    also were continued in command in Sicily, the troops which had fought at Cannae
                    were given, with orders to recruit them out of the surviving soldiers of the
                    legions of Cneius Fulvius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These were
                    collected and sent by the consuls into Sicily, and the same ignominious
                    condition of service was added, under which the troops which had fought at
                    Cannae served, and to those troops belonging to the army of Cneius Fulvius, the
                    praetor, which had been sent thither by the senate through displeasure
                    occasioned by a similar flight. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Caius
                    Aurunculeius was appointed to command, in Sardinia, the same legions with which
                    Publius Manlius Vulso had occupied that province. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Sulpicius was continued in command for the year,
                    with orders to hold Macedonia with the same legion and fleet. Orders were given
                    to send thirty quinqueremes from Sicily to Tarentum, to the consul Fabius.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> With the rest of the ships, orders were
                    given that Marcus Valerius Laevinus should either pass over himself into Africa
                    to ravage the country, or send either Lucius Cincius or Marcus Valerius Messala.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> With regard to Spain, no alteration was
                    made, except that Scipio and Silanus were continued in command, not for the
                    year, but until they <pb n="1100" xml:id="p.1100"/> should be recalled by the
                    senate. In such manner were the provinces and the commands of the armies
                    distributed for this year. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Amid concerns of greater importance, an old
                    dispute was revived at the election of a chief curio, when a priest was
                    appointed to succeed Marcus Aemilius; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the
                    patricians denying that Caius Mamilius Vitulus, who was a plebeian candidate,
                    ought to be allowed to stand, because no one before his time had held that
                    priesthood who was not a patrician. The tribunes, on being appealed to, referred
                    the matter to the senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate left it
                    to the decision of the people. Thus Caius Mamilius Vitulus was the first
                    plebeian created chief curio. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Publius
                    Licinius, chief pontiff, compelled Caius Valerius Flaccus to be inaugurated
                    flamen of Jupiter, against his will. Caius Valerius Laetorius was created
                    decemvir for the performance of sacred rites, in the room of Quintus Mucius
                    Scaevola, deceased. I should willingly have passed over in silence the reason of
                    a flamen's being compelled to be inaugurated, had he not become a good, from
                    having been a bad character. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In consequence of
                    having spent his youth in idleness and debauchery, vices for which he had
                    incurred the displeasure of his own brother, Lucius Flaccus, and the rest of his
                    kinsmen, Caius Flaccus was chosen flamen by Publius Licinius, chief pontiff.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as his mind became occupied with
                    the care of the sacred rites and ceremonies, he soon so completely divested
                    himself of his former habits, that no one among all the youth was more esteemed,
                    or enjoyed in a greater degree the approbation of the chief of the patricians,
                    whether relations or aliens. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Being raised by
                    this general good character to a proper confidence in himself, he claimed to be
                    admitted into the senate; a thing intermitted for many years, on account of the
                    worthlessness of former flamens. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On entering
                    the senate, Lucius Licinius, the praetor, led him out; on which the flamen
                    appealed to the tribunes of the people. He demanded back the ancient privilege
                    of his priesthood, which was given, together with the purple-bordered robe, and
                    the curule chair, to the office of flamen. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    praetor wished the question to rest not on the precedents contained in the
                    annals, which were obsolete from their antiquity, but on the usual practice in
                    all the cases of most recent date; urging, that no flamen of Jupiter, in the
                    memory of their fathers or their grandfathers, had taken up that privilege.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The tribunes <pb n="1101" xml:id="p.1101"
                    /> giving it as their opinion, that justice required, that as the obliteration
                    of the privilege was occasioned by the negligence of the flamens, the
                    consequences ought to fall upon the flamens themselves, and not upon the office,
                    led the flamen into the senate, with the general approbation of the fathers, and
                    without any opposition, even from the praetor himself; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> while all were of opinion that the flamen had obtained his
                    object more from the purity of his life, than any right appertaining to the
                    priesthood. The consuls, before they departed to their provinces, raised two
                    legions for the city, and as many soldiers as were necessary to make up the
                    numbers of the other armies. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The consul
                    Fulvius appointed his brother, Caius Fulvius Flaccus, lieutenant-general, to
                    march the old city army into Etruria, and to bring to Rome the legions which
                    were in Etruria. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And the consul Fabius
                    ordered his son, Quintus Fabius Maximus, to lead the remains of the army of
                    Fulvius, which had been collected, amounting to three thousand three hundred and
                    thirty-six, into Sicily to Marcus Valerius, the proconsul, and to receive from
                    him two legions and thirty quinqueremes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                    withdrawing of these legions from the island did not at all diminish the force
                    employed for the protection of that province, either in effect or appearance;
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> for though, in addition to two veteran
                    legions which were most effectively reinforced, he had a great number of
                    Numidian deserters, both horse and foot, he raised also a body of Sicilian
                    troops, consisting of men who had served in the armies of Epicydes and the
                    Carthaginians, and were experienced in war. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Having added these foreign auxiliaries to each of the Roman legions, he
                    preserved the appearance of two armies. With one he ordered Lucius Cinctius to
                    protect that portion of the island which had formed the kingdom of Hiero, with
                    the other he himself guarded the rest of the island, which was formerly divided
                    by the boundary of the Roman and Carthaginian dominions. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> He divided also the fleet of seventy ships, in order that
                    it might protect the sea-coast, through the entire extent of its shores.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> He himself went through the island with
                    the cavalry of Mutines to inspect the lands, observe those which were cultivated
                    and those which were not, and, accordingly, either praise or reprove the owners.
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> By this diligence so large a quantity of
                    corn was produced, that he both sent some to Rome, and collected at Catana corn
                    which might serve as a <pb n="1102" xml:id="p.1102"/> supply for the army, which
                    was about to pass the summer at Tarentum. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the transportation of the soldiers into
                    Sicily, and they consisted chiefly of Latins and allies, had very nearly caused
                    a serious commotion; from such trifling circumstances do events of great
                    importance frequently arise. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A murmuring arose
                    among the Latins and allies at their meetings. They said, that <quote> they had
                        been drained by levies and contributions for ten years. That almost every
                        year they fought with the most disastrous consequences. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> That some of them were slain in the field, others were
                        carried off by disease. That a countryman of theirs who was enlisted by the
                        Romans, was more lost to them than one who was taken prisoner by the
                        Carthaginians; for the latter was sent back to his country by the enemy
                        without ransom, while the former was sent beyond the limits of Italy, into
                        exile rather than military service. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That
                        the troops which fought at Cannae were growing old there, for eight years,
                        and would die there before the enemy, who was now more than ever flourishing
                        and vigorous, would depart from Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If
                        the old soldiers did not return to their country, and fresh ones were
                        enlisted, that in a short time there would be no one left. That, therefore,
                        they must refuse to the Roman people, before they came to utter desolation
                        and want, what shortly their very condition would refuse. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> If the Romans saw their allies unanimous on this point,
                        that they would then certainly think of making peace with the Carthaginians;
                        otherwise, Italy would never be without war while Hannibal was alive.
                    </quote> Thus they discoursed in their meetings. The Roman people had at that
                    time thirty colonies. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Twelve of these, for
                    they all had embassies at Rome, told the consuls that they had not whence to
                    furnish either men or money. The twelve were, Ardea, Nepete, Sutrium, Alba,
                    Carseoli, Cora, Suessa, Cerceii, Setia, Cales, Narnia, Interamna. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls, astonished at this new proceeding, were
                    desirous to deter them from so hateful a measure; and, considering that they
                    could effect this better by censure and remonstrance than by mild means, said
                    that <quote> they had dared to say to the consuls what the consuls could not
                        bring their minds to declare in the senate; for that this was not a refusal
                        to perform military service, but an open defection from the Roman people.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They desired, therefore, that they <pb
                            n="1103" xml:id="p.1103"/> would return to their colonies speedily, and
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> that, considering the subject as
                        untouched, as they had only spoken of, but not attempted, so impious a
                        business, they would consult with their countrymen. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> That they would warn them that they were not Campanians
                        or Tarentines, but Romans; that from thence they derived their origin, and
                        thence were sent out into colonies and lands captured from the enemy, for
                        the purpose of increasing the population. That they owed to the Romans what
                        children owed to parents, if they possessed any natural affection, or any
                        gratitude towards their mother country. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        That they should, therefore, consider the matter afresh; for that certainly
                        what they then so rashly meditated, was the betraying the Roman empire, and
                        putting the victory in the hands of Hannibal. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The consuls having spent a long time in
                    exchanging arguments of this kind, the ambassadors, who were not at all moved by
                    what they said, declared, that <quote> they had nothing which they could carry
                        home, nor had their senate any thing fresh to devise, having neither men to
                        be enlisted, nor money to be furnished for pay. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The consuls, seeing that they were
                    inflexible, laid the matter before the senate; where the alarm excited in the
                    minds of all was so great, that <quote> the greater part declared it was all
                        over with the empire; that the rest of the colonies would take the same
                        course, and that all the allies had conspired to betray the city of Rome to
                        Hannibal. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls endeavoured to encourage and
                    console the senate, telling them that <quote> the other colonies would maintain
                        their allegiance, and continue in their former state of dutiful obedience,
                        and that those very colonies who had renounced their allegiance, would be
                        inspired with respect for the empire, if ambassadors were sent round to them
                        to reprove and not entreat them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate having given them permission to do
                    and to act as they might conceive best for the state; after sounding the
                    intentions of the other colonies, the consuls summoned their ambassadors, and
                    asked them whether they had their soldiers ready according to the roll?
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Marcus Sextilius of Fregellae replied, in
                    behalf of the eighteen colonies, that <quote> they both had their soldiers ready
                        according to the roll, and if more were wanting would furnish more, and
                        would perform with all diligence whatever else the Roman people commanded
                        and wished; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that to do this they wanted
                        not means, and of inclination they had more than enough. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1104" xml:id="p.1104"/> The consuls, having first told them that any
                    praises bestowed by themselves alone seemed too little for their deserts, unless
                    the whole body of the fathers should thank them in the senate-house, led them
                    before the senate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate, having voted an
                    address to them conceived in the most honourable terms, charged the consuls to
                    take them before the assembly of the people; and, among the many other
                    distinguished services rendered to themselves and their ancestors, to make
                    mention also of this recent obligation conferred upon the state. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Nor even at the present day, after the lapse of so
                    many ages, let their names be passed over in silence, nor let them be defrauded
                    of the praise due to them. They were the people of Signia, Norba, Saticulum,
                    Brundusium, Fregellae, Luceria, Venusia, Adria, Firma, Ariminum; on the other
                    sea, Pontia, Paestum, and Cosa; and in the inland parts, Beneventum, Aesernia,
                    Spoletum, Placentia, and Cremona. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By the
                    support of these colonies the empire of the Roman people then stood; and the
                    thanks both of the senate and the people were given to them. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> As to the twelve other colonies which refused obedience,
                    the fathers forbade that their names should be mentioned, that their ambassadors
                    should either be dismissed or retained, or be addressed by the consuls.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Such a tacit reproof appeared most
                    consistent with the dignity of the Roman people. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> While the consuls were getting in readiness all the other
                    things which were necessary for the war, it was resolved that the vicesimary
                    gold, which was preserved in the most sacred part of the treasury as a resource
                    in cases of extreme exigency, should be drawn out. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> There were drawn out as many as four thousand pounds of
                    gold, from which five hundred pounds each were given to the consuls, to Marcus
                    Marcellus and Publius Sulpicius, proconsuls, and Lucius Veturnius, the praetor,
                    who had by lot obtained Gaul as his province; and in addition, one hundred
                    pounds of gold were given to the consul Fabius, as an extraordinary grant to be
                    carried into the citadel of Tarentum. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    rest they employed in contracts, for ready money, for clothing for the army
                    which was carrying on the war in Spain, to their own and their general's glory. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was resolved also, that the prodigies
                    should be expiated before the consuls set out from the city. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> In the Alban mount, the statue of Jupiter and a tree near
                    the temple were struck by lightning; at Ostia, a grove; at Capua, a wall and <pb
                        n="1105" xml:id="p.1105"/> the temple of Fortune; at Sinuessa, a wall and a
                    gate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some also asserted, that water at Alba
                    had flowed tinged with blood. That at Rome, within the cell of Fors Fortuna, an
                    image, which was in the crown of the goddess, had fallen spontaneously from her
                    head into her hands. At Privernum, it was satisfactorily established that an ox
                    spoke, and that a vulture flew down into a shop, while the forum was crowded.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And that a child was born at Sinuessa, of
                    ambiguous sex, between a male and female, such as are commonly called
                    Androgynes, a term derived from the Greek language, which is better adapted, as
                    for most other purposes, so for the composition of words; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> also that it rained milk, and that a boy was born with the
                    head of an elephant. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These prodigies were then
                    expiated with victims of the larger kind, and a supplication at every shrine,
                    and an offering up of prayers, was proclaimed for one day. It was also decreed,
                    that Caius Hostilius, the praetor, should vow and perform the games in honour of
                    Apollo as they had of late years been vowed and performed. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> During the same time, Quintus Fulvius, the consul, held an
                    election for the creation of censors. Marcus Cornelius Cethegus, and Publius
                    Sempronius Tuditanus, both of whom had not yet been consuls, were created
                    censors. The question was put to the people on the authority of the fathers, and
                    the people ordered that these censors should let to farm the Campanian lands.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The choosing of the senate was delayed by
                    a dispute which arose between the censors about the selection of a chief of the
                    senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The choice belonged to Sempronius; but
                    Cornelius contended that the custom handed down by their fathers must <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> be followed, which was, that they should choose
                    him as chief of the senate who was first censor of those who were then alive;
                    this was Titus Manlius Torquatus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Sempronius
                    rejoined, that to whom the gods had given the lot of choosing, to him the same
                    gods had given the right of exercising his discretion freely. That he would act
                    in this affair according to his own free will, and would choose Quintus Fabius
                    Maximus, whom he would prove to be the first ma in the Roman state, even in the
                    judgment of Hannibal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After a long verbal
                    dispute, his colleague giving up the point, Quintus Fabius Maximus, the consul,
                    was chosen, by Sempronius, chief of the senate. Another senate was then chosen,
                    and eight names were passed over; among which was that of <pb n="1106"
                        xml:id="p.1106"/> Lucius Caecilius Metellus, disrespected as the adviser of
                    the abandonment of Italy, after the defeat at Cannae. In censuring those of the
                    equestrian order, the same ground was acted upon, but there were very few to
                    whom that disgrace belonged. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> All of the
                    equestrian order belonging to the legions who had fought at Cannae, and were
                    then in Sicily, were deprived of their horses. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> To this severe punishment they added another relating to time, which was,
                    that the past campaigns which they had served on horses furnished at the public
                    expense should not be reckoned to them, but that they should serve ten campaigns
                    on horses furnished at their own expense. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    They also searched for, and discovered, a great number of those who ought to
                    have served in the cavalry; and all those who were seventeen years old at the
                    beginning of the war, and had not served, they disfranchised. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> They then contracted for the restoration of the seven
                    shops, the shambles, and the royal palace, situated round the forum, and which
                    had been consumed by fire. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having finished every thing which was to be
                    done at Rome, the consuls set out for the war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Fulvius first went in advance to Capua; in a few days Fabius followed. He had
                    implored his colleague in person, and Marcellus by a letter, to use the most
                    vigorous measures to detain Hannibal, while he was making an attack upon
                    Tarentum. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That when that city was taken from
                    the enemy, who had been repulsed on all sides, and had no place where he might
                    make a stand or look back upon as a safe retreat, he would not then have even a
                    pretext for remaining in Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He also sent a
                    messenger to Rhegium, to the prefect of the garrison, which had been placed
                    there by the consul Laevinus, against the Bruttians, and consisted of eight
                    thousand men, the greater part of whom had been brought from Agathyrna in
                    Sicily, as has been before mentioned, and were men who had been accustomed to
                    live by rapine. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To these were added fugitives
                    of the Bruttians, natives of that country, equal to them in daring, and under an
                    equal necessity of braving every thing. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This
                    band he ordered to be marched, first, to lay waste the Bruttian territory, and
                    then to attack the city Caulonia. After having executed the order, not only with
                    alacrity, but avidity, and having pillaged and put to flight the cultivators of
                    the land, they attacked the city with the utmost vigour. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Marcellus, <pb n="1107" xml:id="p.1107"/> incited by the
                    letter of the consul, and because he had made up his mind that no Roman general
                    was so good a match for Hannibal as himself, set out from his winter quartets as
                    soon as there was plenty of forage in the fields, and met Hannibal at Canusium.
                    The Carthaginian was then endeavouring to induce the Canusians to revolt, but as
                    soon as he heard that Marcellus was approaching, he decamped thence. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The country was open, without any covers adapted for
                    an ambuscade; he therefore began to retire thence into woody districts.
                    Marcellus closely pursued him, pitched his camp close to his, and when he had
                    completed his works, led out his troops into the field. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal engaged in slight skirmishes, and sent out single
                    troops of horse and the spearmen from his infantry, not considering it necessary
                    to hazard a general battle. He was, however, drawn on to a contest of that kind
                    which he was avoiding. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal had decamped
                    by night, but was overtaken by Marcellus in a plain and open country. Then,
                    while encamping, Marcellus, by attacking the workmen on all hands, prevented the
                    completion of his works. Thus a pitched battle ensued, and all their forces were
                    brought into action; but night coming on, they retired from an equal contest.
                    They then hastily fortified their camps, which were a small space apart, before
                    night. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The next day, as soon as it was light,
                    Marcellus led out his troops into the field; nor did Hannibal decline the
                    challenge, but exhorted his soldiers at great length, desiring them <quote>to
                        remember Trasimenus and Cannae, and thus quell the proud spirit of their
                        enemies.</quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He said, <quote> the enemy pressed upon him,
                        and trod upon their heels; that he did not allow them to pass unmolested,
                        pitch their camp, or even take breath and look around them; that every day,
                        the rising sun and the Roman troops in battle-array were to be seen together
                        on the plains. But if in one battle he should retire from the field, not
                        without loss of blood, he would then prosecute the war more steadily and
                        quietly. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Fired by these exhortations, and at the same
                    time wearied with the presumption of the enemy, who daily pressed upon them and
                    provoked them to an engagement, they commenced the battle with spirit.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The battle continued for more than two
                    hours, when the right wing of the allies and the chosen band began to give way
                    on the part of the Romans; which Marcellus perceiving, led the eighteenth legion
                    to the front. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> While some were retiring in <pb
                        n="1108" xml:id="p.1108"/> confusion, and others were coming up reluctantly,
                    the whole line was thrown into disorder, and afterwards completely routed; while
                    their fears getting the better of their sense of shame, they turned their backs.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> In the battle and in the flight there
                    fell as many as two thousand seven hundred of citizens and allies; among which
                    were four Roman centurions, and two military tribunes, Marcus Licinius and
                    Marcus Helvius. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Four military standards were
                    lost by the wing which first fled, and two belonging to the legion which came up
                    in place of the retiring allies. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus, on his return to the camp,
                    delivered an address to his soldiers so severe and acrimonious, that the words
                    of their exasperated general were more painful to them than what they had
                    suffered in the unsuccessful battle during the whole day. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>I praise and thank the immortal gods,</quote> said he, <quote> that in
                        such an affair the victorious enemy did not assault our very camp, when you
                        were hurrying into the rampart and the gates with such consternation. There
                        can be no doubt but you would have abandoned the camp with the same
                        cowardice with which you gave up the battle. What panic is this? What
                        terror? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> What sudden forgetfulness of who
                        you are, and who the persons with whom you were fighting, took possession of
                        your minds? Surely these are the same enemies in conquering and pursuing
                        whom when conquered you spent the preceding summer; whom latterly you have
                        been closely pursuing while they fled before you night and day; <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> whom you have wearied by partial battles; whom
                        yesterday you would not allow either to march or encamp. I pass over those
                        things in which you might be allowed to glory; I will mention a circumstance
                        which of itself ought to fill you with shame and remorse. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Yesterday you separated from the enemy on equal terms.
                        What alteration has last night, what has this day, produced? <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Have your forces been diminished by them, or
                        theirs increased? I verily do not seem to be talking to my own troops, or to
                        Roman soldiers. The bodies only and the arms are the same. Had you possessed
                        the same spirit, would the enemy have seen your backs? Would he have carried
                        off a standard from any company or cohort? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Hitherto he was wont to boast of having cut to pieces the Roman legions, but
                        yesterday you gave him the glory, for the first time, of having put to
                        flight an army. </quote> On this, the <pb n="1109" xml:id="p.1109"/>
                    soldiers began to call upon him to pardon them for that day, and entreat that he
                    would now, whenever he pleased, make trial of the courage of his soldiers.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>I will indeed make trial of you,</quote> said he, <quote> and to-morrow I
                        will lead you into the field, that in the character of conquerors, rather
                        than conquered men, you may obtain the pardon you seek. </quote> To the
                    cohorts which had lost their standards, he ordered that barley should be given.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The centurions of the Campanians, whose
                    standards were lost, he left to stand without their girdles and with their
                    swords drawn; and gave orders that all, both horse and foot, should be ready
                    under arms on the following day. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus the
                    assembly was dismissed; the soldiers confessing that they had been justly and
                    deservedly rebuked; and that there was no one in the whole Roman army who had
                    acquitted himself like a man, except the general, to whom they were bound to
                    make atonement, either by their death or a glorious victory. The next day they
                    appeared in readiness, according to the order, armed and equipped. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The general praised them, and gave out, that <quote>
                        he should lead into the first line those who had commenced the flight on the
                        preceding day, and those cohorts which had lost their standards. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> He now charged them all to fight and conquer,
                        and exert every efforts one and all, that the intelligence of yesterday's
                        flight might not arrive at Rome before that of this day's victory. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They were then ordered to refresh themselves
                    with food, in order that, if the fight should continue longer than might be
                    expected, their strength might not fail. After every thing had been done and
                    said, by which the courage of the soldiers might be roused, they advanced into
                    the field. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, on receiving intelligence of this,
                    said, <quote> surely the enemy we have to do with can neither bear good nor bad
                        fortune. If he is victorious, he fiercely pursues the vanquished. If
                        conquered, he renews the contest with the victors. </quote> He then ordered
                    the signal to be given, and led out his forces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The battle was fought on both sides with much more spirit than the day
                    before. The Carthaginians exerting themselves to the utmost, to keep the glory
                    they had acquired yesterday; the Romans, to remove their disgrace. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> On the side of the Romans, the left wing, and the
                    cohorts which had lost their standards, fought in the first line, and the
                    twentieth legion was drawn up on the right wing. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Lucius Cornelius <pb n="1110" xml:id="p.1110"/> Lentulus and Caius Claudius
                    Nero, lieutenant-generals, commanded the wings, Marcellus gave vigour to the
                    centre by his presence, as an encourager and a witness. On the part of Hannibal,
                    the Spaniards, who were the flower of his whole army, occupied the front line.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the battle had continued doubtful
                    for a long time, Hannibal ordered the elephants to be advanced into the front
                    line, if by that means any confusion or panic could be created. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At first, they threw the troops into confusion and broke
                    their ranks, and treading some under foot, and dispersing others who were round
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> them by the alarm they created, had made
                    an opening in one part of the Roman line; and the flight would have spread more
                    widely had not Caius Decimus Flavius, a military tribune, seizing the standard
                    of the first maniple of the spearmen, ordered that maniple to follow him.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He led them to the spot where the
                    elephants, collected in a body, were creating the greatest confusion, and
                    ordered them to discharge their javelins at them. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> As there was no difficulty in hitting such bulky bodies at
                    a short distance, and where so many were crowded together, all their javelins
                    stuck in them. But as they were not all wounded, so those in whose hides the
                    javelins stuck, as that race of animals is not to be depended on, betaking
                    themselves to flight, drove away those also which were untouched. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> At that moment not only one maniple, but all the
                    soldiers who could but overtake the body of retreating elephants, threw their
                    javelins at them, each man exerting himself to his utmost. With so much greater
                    impetuosity did the animals rush upon their own men, and so much greater a
                    carnage did they make amongst them than they had made amongst their enemies, in
                    proportion as the violence with which they are impelled, and the consternation
                    produced in them when under the influence of fear, is greater than when they are
                    ruled by their masters seated on their backs. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman infantry bore their standards against the line of the enemy when
                    thrown <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> into disorder by the elephants which
                    had crossed over to them, and, thus scattered and confused, put them to flight
                    without any great opposition. Marcellus then sent his cavalry after them as they
                    fled; nor did they desist from the pursuit till they were driven in
                    consternation to their camp. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For in addition
                    to the other causes which had occasioned terror and dismay, two elephants had
                    fallen just in <pb n="1111" xml:id="p.1111"/> the gate, and the soldiers were
                    compelled to rush into the camp over the ditch and rampart. Here the greatest
                    slaughter of the enemy occurred. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> There fell
                    as many as eight thousand men and five elephants. Nor did the Romans gain a
                    bloodless victory; about seventeen hundred of the two legions, and thirteen
                    hundred of the allies, were slain; a great number of the Romans and allies were
                    wounded. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The following night Hannibal
                    decamped. The great number of the wounded prevented Marcellus from following
                    him, as he desired. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The spies who were sent to watch his movements
                    brought word back the next day that Hannibal was making for Bruttium. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Much about the same time the Hirpinians, Lucanians,
                    and Volcentes surrendered themselves to the consul, Quintus Fulvius, delivering
                    up the garrisons of Hannibal which they had in their cities. They were mildly
                    received by the consul, with only a verbal reproof for their past error.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the Bruttians also similar hopes of
                    pardon were held out, when two brothers, Vibius and Pactius, by far the most
                    illustrious persons of that nation, came from them to solicit the same terms of
                    surrender which had been given to the Lucanians. Quintus Fabius, the consul,
                    took by storm Manduria, a town in the territory of Sallentum, where as many as
                    four thousand men were made prisoners, and much booty taken besides. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Proceeding thence to Tarentum, he pitched his camp in
                    the very mouth of the harbour: of the ships which Livius had employed for
                    protecting convoys, some he loaded with engines and implements for attacking
                    walls, others he furnished with machines for discharging missiles, and with
                    stones and missiles of every kind; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> not only
                    those which were impelled with oars, but the storeships also, in order that some
                    might carry the engines and ladders to the <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    walls, while others might wound the defenders of the walls by discharging
                    missiles from the ships at a distance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These
                    ships were fitted up and prepared to attack the town from the open sea; and the
                    sea was free from the Carthaginian fleet, which had crossed over to Corcyra on
                    account of Philip's preparing to attack the Aetolians. Meanwhile, those who were
                    attacking Caulon, in the territory of Bruttium, fearful lest they should be
                    overpowered, had retired on the approach of Hannibal to an eminence, secure from
                    an immediate attack. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While <pb n="1112"
                        xml:id="p.1112"/> Fabius was besieging Tarentum, he received assistance in
                    the accomplishment of that great object by a circumstance which, in the mere
                    mention, is unimportant. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Tarentum was occupied
                    by a garrison of Bruttians, given them by Hannibal; the commander of that
                    garrison was desperately in love with a girl, whose brother was in the army of
                    the consul Fabius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Being informed, by a
                    letter from his sister, of the new acquaintance she had formed with a wealthy
                    stranger and one so honoured among his countrymen, and conceiving a hope that
                    the lover, by means of his sister, might be induced to any thing she pleased, he
                    acquainted the consul with the hopes he had formed. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> His reasoning appeared not altogether unfounded, and he was
                    desired to go to Tarentum as a deserter; and having gained the confidence of the
                    prefect by means of his sister, he began by sounding his disposition in a covert
                    manner, and then, having sufficiently ascertained his weakness, induced him, by
                    the aid of female fascinations, to the betrayal of that custody of the place to
                    which he was appointed. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After the method to
                    be pursued and the time for putting the plan into effect had been agreed upon, a
                    soldier, who was sent out of the city by night clandestinely, through the
                    intervals between the guards, related to the consul what had been done, and what
                    had been agreed upon to be done. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At the first
                    watch, Fabius, on a signal given to those who were in the citadel, and those who
                    had the custody of the harbour, went himself round the harbour, and took up a
                    position in concealment, on the side of the city which faced the east.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then the trumpets began to sound at once
                    from the citadel, the harbour, and the ships which had been brought to the shore
                    from the open sea, and a shout was purposely raised, accompanied with the
                    greatest confusion, in whatever quarter there was the least danger. Meanwhile,
                    the consul kept his men in silence. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Democrates, therefore, who had formerly commanded the fleet, and happened to be
                    in command in that quarter, seeing that all was quiet around him, while other
                    parts of the city resounded with such a din that sometimes a shout like that of
                    a captured city was raised, and fearing lest, while he hesitated, the consul
                    should make some attack and <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> advance his
                    standards, led his party over to the citadel, from which the most alarming noise
                    proceeded. Fabius, concluding that the guard was withdrawn, both from the time
                    which had <pb n="1113" xml:id="p.1113"/> elapsed and from the silence <milestone
                        n="17??" unit="section"/> which prevailed, for not a voice met the ear from
                    a quarter where a little while ago the noise and bustle of men resounded,
                    rousing and calling each other to arms, ordered the ladders to be carried to
                    that part of the wall where the person who had contrived the plot or betraying
                    the city, had informed him that the Bruttian cohort kept guard. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> The wall was first captured in that quarter, the
                    Bruttians aiding and receiving the Romans; and here they got over into the city:
                    after which the nearest gate was broken open in order that the troops might
                    enter in a large body. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Then raising a shout,
                    they proceeded to the forum, where they arrived much about daybreak, without
                    meeting a single armed man; and drew upon themselves the attention of all the
                    troops in every quarter, which were fighting at the citadel and at the harbour. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A battle was fought in the entrance of the
                    forum, with greater impetuosity than perseverance. The Tarentines were not equal
                    to the Romans in spirit, in their arms, in tactics, in activity or strength of
                    body. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly, having just discharged
                    their javelins, they turned their backs almost before they had joined battle,
                    and escaped in different directions through the streets of the city, with which
                    they were acquainted, to their own houses and those of their friends. Two of
                    their leaders, Nico and Democrates, fell while fighting bravely. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Philomenus, who was the author of the plot for
                    betraying the city to Hannibal, rode away from the battle at full speed. Shortly
                    after, his horse, which was loose and straying through the city, was recognised,
                    but his body could not be found any where. It was generally believed that he had
                    pitched headlong from his horse into an open well. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Carthalo, the praefect of the Carthaginian garrison, while
                    coming to <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> the consul unarmed, to put him in
                    mind of a connexion of hospitality which subsisted between their fathers, was
                    put to death by a soldier who met him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    rest were put to the sword on all hands, armed and unarmed indiscriminately,
                    Carthaginians and Tarentines without distinction. Many of the Bruttians also
                    were slain either by mistake or on account of an old grudge entertained against
                    them, or else with a view to the report that the city was betrayed; in order
                    that Tarentum might rather appear to have been captured by force of arms.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The troops then ran off in all directions
                    from the slaughter, to <pb n="1114" xml:id="p.1114"/> plunder the city. Thirty
                    thousand slaves are said to have been captured; an immense quantity of silver,
                    wrought and coined; eighty-three thousand pounds of gold; of statues and
                    pictures so many that they almost equalled the decorations of Syracuse.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But Fabius, with more magnanimity than
                    Marcellus, abstained from booty of that kind. When his secretary asked him what
                    he wished to be done with the statues of their gods, which are of immense size
                    and represented as fighting, each having his peculiar habit, he gave orders that
                    their angry gods should be left in the possession of the Tarentines. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> After this, the wall which separated the city from
                    the citadel was razed and demolished. While things were going on thus at
                    Tarentum, Hannibal, to whom the troops engaged in the siege of Caulonia had
                    surrendered themselves, hearing of the siege of Tarentum, marched with the
                    greatest expedition both night and day; but hearing that the city was taken, as
                    he was hastening to bring assistance to it, he exclaimed, <quote> the Romans too
                        have their Hannibal. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> We have lost
                        Tarentum by the same arts by which we took it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> However, that he might not appear to have
                    turned his army in the manner of a fugitive, he encamped where he had halted,
                    about five miles from the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After staying
                    there a few days, he retired to Metapontum, from which place he sent two
                    Metapontines with letters from the principal men in the state to Fabius at
                    Tarentum, to the effect, that they would accept of his promise that their past
                    conduct should be unpunished, on condition of their betraying Metapontum
                    together with the Carthaginian garrison into his hands. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Fabius, who supposed that the communication they brought
                    was genuine, appointed a day on which he would go to Metapontum, and gave the
                    letters to the nobles, which were put into the hands of Hannibal. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> He, forsooth, delighted at the success of his
                    stratagem, which showed that not even Fabius was proof against his cunning,
                    planted an ambuscade not far from Metapontum. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    But when Fabius was taking the auspices, before he took his departure from
                    Tarentum, the birds more than once refused approval. Also, on consulting the
                    gods after sacrificing a victim, the aruspex forewarned him to be on his guard
                    against hostile treachery and ambuscade. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    After the day fixed for his arrival had passed without his coming, the
                    Metapontines were sent again to encourage him, delaying, but they were instantly
                    seized, and, from ap- <pb n="1115" xml:id="p.1115"/> prehension of a severer
                    mode of examination, disclosed the plot. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the summer during which
                    these events occurred, after Publius Scipio had employed the whole of the winter
                    in Spain in regaining the affections of the barbarians, partly by presents, and
                    partly by sending home their hostages and prisoners, Edesco, a man distinguished
                    among the Spanish commanders, came to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His
                    wife land children were in the hands of the Romans; but besides this motive, he
                    was influenced by that apparently fortuitous turn in the state of feeling which
                    had converted the whole of Spain from the Carthaginian to the Roman cause.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The same motive induced Indibilis and
                    Mandonius, who were undoubtedly the principal men in all Spain, to desert
                    Hasdrubal and withdraw with the whole body of their countrymen to the eminences
                    which overhung his camp, from which they had a safe retreat along a chain of
                    hills to the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, perceiving
                    that the strength of the enemy was increasing by such large accessions, while
                    his own was diminishing, and that events would continue to flow in the same
                    course they had taken, unless by a bold effort he effected some alteration,
                    resolved to come to an engagement as soon as possible. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio was still more eager for a battle, as well from hope
                    which the success attending his operations had increased, as because he
                    preferred, before the junction of the enemy's forces, to fight with one general
                    and one army, rather than with their united troops. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> However, in case he should be obliged to fight with more
                    armies than one at the same time, he had with some ingenuity augmented his
                    forces; for seeing that there was no necessity for ships, as the whole coast of
                    Spain was clear of Carthaginian fleets, he hauled his ships on shore at Tarraco
                    and added his mariners to his land forces. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                    had plenty of arms for them, both those which had been captured at Carthage, and
                    those which he had caused to be made after its capture, so large a number of
                    workmen having been employed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With these
                    forces, setting out from Tarraco at the commencement of the spring, for Laelius
                    had now returned from Rome, without whom he wished nothing of very great
                    importance to be attempted, Scipio marched against the enemy. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Indibilis and Mandonius, with their forces, met him while
                    on his march; passing through every place without molestation, his allies
                    receiving him courteously, and <pb n="1116" xml:id="p.1116"/> escorting him as
                    he passed the boundaries of each district. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Indibilis, who spoke for both, addressed him by no means stupidly and
                    imprudently like a barbarian, but with a modest gravity, rather excusing the
                    change as necessary, than glorying that the present opportunity had been eagerly
                    seized as the first which had occurred. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>For he well knew,</quote> he said, <quote> that the name of a deserter
                        was an object of execration to former allies, and of suspicion to new ones;
                        nor did he blame the conduct of mankind in this respect, provided, however,
                        that the cause, and not the name, occasioned the twofold hatred. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He then recounted the services they had
                    rendered the Carthaginian generals, and on the other hand their rapacity and
                    insolence, together with the injuries of every kind committed against themselves
                    and their countrymen. <quote>On this account,</quote> he said, <quote> his
                        person only up to that time had been with them, his heart had long since
                        been on that side where he believed that right and justice were respected.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That people sought for refuge, as
                        suppliants, even with the gods when they could not endure the oppression and
                        injustice of men. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> What he had to entreat
                        of Scipio was, that their passing over to him might neither be the occasion
                        of a charge of fraud nor a ground for respect, but that he would estimate
                        their services according to what sort of men he should find them to be from
                        experience from that day. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The Roman replied, that <quote> he would do
                        so in every particular; nor would he consider those men as deserters who did
                        not look upon an alliance as binding where no law, divine or human, was
                        unviolated. </quote> Their wives and children were then brought before them
                    and restored to them; on which occasion they wept for joy. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> On that day they were conducted to a lodging; on the
                    following they were received as allies, by a treaty, after which they were sent
                    to bring up their forces. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> From that time they
                    had their tents in the same camp with the Romans, until under their guidance
                    they had reached the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The army of Hasdrubal, which was the nearest
                    of the Carthaginian armies, lay near the city Baecula. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Before his camp he had outposts of cavalry. On these the
                    light-armed, those who fought before the standards and those who composed the
                    vanguard, as they came up from their march, and before they chose the ground for
                    their camp, commenced an attack in so contemptuous a manner, that it was
                    perfectly evi- <pb n="1117" xml:id="p.1117"/> dent what degree of spirit each
                    party possessed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The cavalry were driven into
                    their camp in disorderly flight, and the Roman standards were advanced almost
                    within their very gates. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their minds on that
                    day having only been excited to a contest, the Romans pitched their camp.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At night Hasdrubal withdrew his forces to
                    an eminence, on the summit of which extended a level plain. There was a river on
                    the rear, in front and on either side a kind of steep bank completely surrounded
                    its extremity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Beneath this and lower down was
                    another plain of gentle declivity, which was also surrounded by a similar ridge
                    equally difficult of ascent. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Into this lower
                    plain Hasdrubal, the next day, when he saw the troops of the enemy drawn up
                    before their camp, sent his Numidian cavalry and light-armed Baleares. Scipio
                    riding out to the companies and battalions, pointed out to them, that "the enemy
                    having abandoned, beforehand, all hope of being able to withstand them on level
                    ground, had resorted to hills; where they stood in view, relying on the strength
                    of their position, and not on their valour and arms. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> But the walls of Carthage, which the Roman soldiers had
                    scaled, were still higher. That neither hills, nor a citadel, nor even the sea
                    itself, had formed an impediment to their arms. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> That the heights which the enemy had occupied would only have the effect of
                    making it necessary for them to leap down crags and precipices in their flight,
                    but he would even cut off that kind of retreat. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> He accordingly gave orders to two cohorts, that one of them should occupy the
                    entrance of the valley down which the river ran, and that the other should block
                    up the road which led from the city into the country, over the side of the hill.
                    He himself led the light troops, which the day before had driven in the advanced
                    guard of the enemy, against the light-armed troops which were stationed on the
                    lower ridge. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At first they marched through
                    rugged ground, impeded by nothing except the road; afterwards, when they came
                    within reach of the darts, an immense quantity of weapon of every description
                    was showered upon them; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> while on their part,
                    not only the soldiers, but a multitude of servants mingled with the troops,
                    threw stones furnished by the place, which were spread about in every part, and
                    for the most part convenient as missiles. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But
                    though the ascent was difficult, and they were almost overwhelmed with stones
                    and darts, yet from their practice in approaching walls and their inflexibility
                    of <pb n="1118" xml:id="p.1118"/> mind, the foremost succeeded in getting up.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> These, as soon as they got upon some
                    level ground and could stand with firm footing, compelled the enemy, who were
                    light-armed troops adapted for skirmishing, and could defend themselves at a
                    distance, where an elusive kind of fight is carried on by the discharge of
                    missiles, but yet wanted steadiness for a close action, to fly from their
                    position; and, killing a great many, drove them to the troops which stood above
                    them on the higher eminence. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Upon this
                    Scipio, having ordered the victorious troops to mount up and attack the centre
                    of the enemy, divided the rest of his forces with Laelius; whom he directed to
                    go round the hill to the right till he could find a way of easier ascent, while
                    he himself, making a small circuit to the left, charged the enemy in flank.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> In consequence of this their line was
                    first thrown into confusion, while they endeavoured to wheel round and face
                    about their ranks towards the shouts which resounded from every quarter around
                    them. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> During this confusion Laelius also came
                    up, and while the enemy were retreating, that they might not be exposed to
                    wounds from behind, their front line became disjoined, and a space was left for
                    the Roman centre to mount up; <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> who, from the
                    disadvantage of the ground, never could have done so had their ranks stood
                    unbroken with the elephants stationed in front. <milestone n="19" unit="section"
                    /> While the troops of the enemy were being slain on all sides, Scipio, who with
                    his left wing had charged the right of the enemy, was chiefly employed in
                    attacking their naked flank. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> And now there
                    was not even room to fly; for parties of the Roman troops had blocked up the
                    roads on both sides, right and left, and the gate of the camp was closed by the
                    flight of the general and principal officers; added to which was the fright of
                    the elephants, who, when in consternation, were as much feared by them as the
                    enemy were. There were, therefore, slain as many as eight thousand men. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, having seized upon the treasure
                    before he engaged, now sent the elephants in advance, and collecting as many of
                    the flying troops as he could, directed his course along the river Tagus to the
                    Pyrenees. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Scipio, having got possession of the
                    enemy's camp, and giving up all the booty to the soldiers, except the persons of
                    free condition, found, on counting the prisoners, ten thousand foot and two
                    thousand horse. Of these, all who were Spaniards he sent home without ransom;
                    the Africans he ordered the quaestor to sell. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    After this, <pb n="1119" xml:id="p.1119"/> a multitude of Spaniards, consisting
                    of those who had surrendered to him before and those whom he had captured the
                    preceding day, crowding around, one and all saluted him as king; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> when Scipio, after the herald had obtained silence,
                    declared that <quote> in his estimation the most honourable title was that of
                        general, which his soldiers had conferred upon him. That the name of king,
                        which was in other countries revered, could not be endured at Rome.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That they might tacitly consider his
                        spirit as kingly, if they thought that the highest excellence which could be
                        attributed to the human mind, but that they must abstain from the use of the
                        term. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Even barbarians were sensible of the greatness
                    of mind which could from such an elevation despise a name, at the greatness of
                    which the rest of mankind were overawed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Presents were then distributed to the petty princes and leading men of the
                    Spaniards, and out of the great quantity of horses which were captured, he
                    desired Indibilis to select those he liked best to the number of three hundred.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While the quaestor was selling the
                    Africans, according to the command of the general, he found among them a
                    full-grown youth remarkably handsome; and hearing that he was of royal blood, he
                    sent him to Scipio. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On being asked by Scipio
                        <quote>who he was, of what country, and why at that age he was in the
                        camp?</quote> he replied, <quote> that he was a Numidian, that his
                        countrymen called him Massiva; that being left an orphan by his father, he
                        was educated by his maternal grandfather, Gala, the king of the Numidians.
                        That he had passed over into Spain with his uncle Masinissa, who had lately
                        come with a body of cavalry to assist the Carthaginians. That having been
                        prohibited by Masinissa on account of his youth, he had never before been in
                        battle. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That the day on which the battle
                        took place with the Romans, he had clandestinely taken a horse and arms,
                        and, without the knowledge of his uncle, gone out into the field, where his
                        horse falling forward, he was thrown headlong, and taken prisoner by the
                        Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Scipio, having ordered that the Numidian
                    should be taken care of, completed the business which remained to be done on the
                    tribunal, and returning to his pavilion, asked him, when he had been called to
                    him, whether he wished to return to Masinissa? <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> Upon his replying, with tears of joy, that he did indeed desire it, he
                    presented the youth with a gold ring, a vest with a broad purple <pb n="1120"
                        xml:id="p.1120"/> border, a Spanish cloak with a gold clasp, and a horse
                    completely caparisoned, and then dismissed him, ordering a party of horse to
                    escort him as far as he chose. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A council was then held respecting the war;
                    when some advised that he should endeavour to overtake Hasdrubal forthwith.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But thinking that hazardous, lest Mago and
                    the other Hasdrubal should unite their forces with his, he sent a body of troops
                    to occupy the pass of the Pyrenees, and employed the remainder of the summer in
                    receiving the states of Spain into his alliance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> A few days after the battle of Baecula, when Scipio on his return to Tarraco
                    had now cleared the pass of Castulo, the generals, Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, and
                    Mago came from the farther Spain and joined Hasdrubal; a late assistance after
                    the defeat he had sustained, though their arrival was somewhat seasonable, for
                    counsel with respect to the further prosecution of the war. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They then consulted together as to what was the feeling of
                    the Spaniards in the quarters where their several provinces were situated, when
                    Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, alone gave it as his opinion, that the remotest tract
                    of Spain which borders on the ocean and Gades, was, as yet, unacquainted with
                    the Romans, and might therefore be somewhat friendly to the Carthaginians.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Between the other Hasdrubal and Mago it
                    was agreed, that <quote> Scipio by his good offices had gained the affections of
                        all, both publicly and privately; and that there would be no end of
                        desertions till all the Spanish soldiers were removed to the remotest parts
                        of Spain, or were marched over into Gaul. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        That, therefore, though the Carthaginian senate had not decreed it,
                        Hasdrubal must, nevertheless, march into Italy, the principal seat and
                        object of the war; and thus at the same time lead away all the Spanish
                        soldiers out of Spain far from the name of Scipio. That the army, which had
                        been diminished by desertions and defeats, should be recruited by Spanish
                        soldiers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That Mago, having delivered over
                        his army to Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, should himself pass over to the
                        Baleares with a large sum of money to hire auxiliaries; that Hasdrubal, son
                        of Gisgo, should retire with the army into the remotest part of Lusitania,
                        and avoid an encounter with the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        That a body of three thousand horse should be made up for Masinissa, the
                        flower of the whole cavalry; and that he, shifting about from place to place
                        throughout hither <pb n="1121" xml:id="p.1121"/> Spain, should succour their
                        allies and commit depredations upon the towns and lands of their enemies.
                    </quote> Having adopted these resolutions, the generals departed to put in
                    execution what they had resolved on. Such were the transactions in Spain of this
                    year. At Rome the reputation of Scipio increased daily. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The capture of Tarentum, though elected by artifice more
                    than valour, was considered honourable to Fabius. The fame of Fulvius was on the
                    wane. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Marcellus was even under an ill report,
                    not only because he had failed in his first battle, but further, because while
                    Hannibal was going wherever he pleased throughout Italy, he had led his troops
                    to Venusia in the midst of summer to lodge in houses. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Caius Publicius Bibulus, a tribune of the people, was
                    hostile to him. This man, ever since the time of his first battle which had
                    failed, had in constant harangues made Claudius obnoxious and odious to the
                    people; and now his object was to deprive him of his command. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The connexions of Marcellus, however, then obtained leave
                    that Marcellus, leaving a lieutenant-general at Venusia, should return to Rome
                    to clear himself of the charges which his enemies were urging, and that the
                    question of depriving him of his command should not be agitated during his
                    absence. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It happened that nearly at the same
                    time, Marcellus, and Quintius Fulvius the consul, came to Rome, the former to
                    exonerate himself from ignominy, the latter on account of the elections. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The question touching Marcellus's command was
                    debated in the Flaminian circus, in the presence of an immense concourse of
                    plebeians and persons of every rank. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    plebeian tribune accused, not only Marcellus, but the nobility generally.
                        <quote>It was owing,</quote> he said, <quote> to their dishonesty and
                        dilatory conduct, that Hannibal occupied Italy, as though it were his
                        province, for now ten years; that he had passed more of his life there than
                        at Carthage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That the Roman people were
                        enjoying the fruits of the prolonged command of Marcellus; that his army,
                        after having been twice defeated, was now spending the summer at Venusia
                        lodged in houses. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcellus so completely destroyed the effect
                    of this harangue of the tribune, by the recital of the services he had rendered,
                    that not only the bill for depriving him of his command was thrown out, but the
                    following day he was created consul by the votes of all the centuries with
                    wonderful unanimity. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1122" xml:id="p.1122"/> Titus Quinctius Crispinus, who was then praetor,
                    was joined with him as his colleague. The next day Publius Licinius Crassus
                    Dives, then chief pontiff, Publius Licinius Varus, Sextus Julius Caesar, and
                    Quintus Claudius Flamen were created praetors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    At the very time of the election, the public were thrown into a state of anxiety
                    relative to the defection of Etruria. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Caius
                    Calpurnius, who held that province as propraetor, had written word that the
                    Arretians had originated such a scheme. Accordingly Marcellus, consul elect, was
                    immediately sent thither to look into the affair, and if it should appear to him
                    of sufficient consequence, to send for his army and transfer the war from Apulia
                    to Etruria. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Tuscans, checked by the alarm
                    thus occasioned, desisted. To the ambassadors of Tarentum, who solicited a
                    treaty of peace securing to them their liberty and the enjoyment of their own
                    laws, the senate answered, that they might return when the consul Fabius came to
                    Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Roman and plebeian games were this
                    year repeated each for one day. The curule aediles were, Lucius Cornelius
                    Caudinus and Servius Sulpicius Galba; the plebeian aediles, Caius Servilius and
                    Quintus Caecilius Metellus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was asserted
                    that Servilius was not qualified to be plebeian tribune or aedile, because it
                    was satisfactorily established that his father, who, for ten years, was supposed
                    to have been killed by the Boii in the neighbourhood of Mutina, when acting as
                    triumvir for the distribution of lands, was alive and in the hands of the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the eleventh year of the Punic war, Marcus
                    Marcellus, for the fifth time, reckoning in the consulate in which he did not
                    act in consequence of an informality in his creation, and Titus Quinctius
                    Crispinus entered upon the office of consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    To both the consuls the province of Italy was decreed, with both the consular
                    armies of the former year; (the third was then at Venusia, being that which
                    Marcus Marcellus had commanded.) <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That out of
                    the three armies the consuls might choose whichever two they liked, and that the
                    third should be delivered to him to whose lot the province of Tarentum and the
                    territory of Sallentum fell. The other provinces were thus distributed among the
                    praetors: Publius Licinius Varus had the city jurisdiction, Publius Licinius
                    Crassus, chief pontiff, the foreign, and wherever the senate thought proper.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Sextus Julius Caesar had Sicily, and
                    Quintus Claudius <pb n="1123" xml:id="p.1123"/> Flamen, Tarentum. Quintus
                    Fulvius Flaccus was to continue in command for a year, and hold the province of
                    Capua, which had been held by Titus Quinctius, with one legion. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Caius Hostilius Tubulus was also continued in command, with
                    orders to go into Etruria, in the capacity of propraetor, and succeed Caius
                    Calpurnius in the command of the two legions there. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Veturius Philo was also continued in command, to
                    hold in the capacity of proprietor the same province of Gaul with the same two
                    legions with which he had held it as praetor. The senate decreed the same with
                    respect to Caius Aurunculeius, who, as praetor, had held the province of
                    Sardinia with two legions, which it did in the case of Lucius Veturius, and the
                    question of the continuation of his command was proposed to the people.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He had in addition, for the protection of
                    the province, fifty ships which Publius Scipio had sent from Spain. To Publius
                    Scipio and Marcus Silanus, their present province of Spain and their present
                    armies were assigned. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of the eighty ships
                    which he had with him, some taken from Italy and others captured at Carthage,
                    Scipio was ordered to send fifty to Sardinia, in consequence of a report that
                    great naval preparations were making at Carthage that year; and that the
                    intention of the Carthaginians was to blockade the whole coasts of Italy,
                    Sicily, and Sardinia with two hundred ships. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    In Sicily also the following distribution was made: to Sextus Caesar the troops
                    of Cannae were assigned; Marcus Valerius Laevinus, who was also continued in
                    command, was to have the fleet of seventy ships which was at Sicily, adding to
                    it the thirty ships which the preceding year were stationed at Tarentum.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> With this fleet of a hundred ships he was
                    ordered to pass over into Africa, if he thought proper, and collect booty.
                    Publius Sulpicius was also continued in command for a year, to hold the province
                    of Macedonia and Greece, with the same fleet. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    No alteration was made with regard to the two legions which were at Rome.
                    Permission was given to the consuls to enlist as many troops as were necessary
                    to complete the numbers. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This year the Roman
                    empire was defended by twenty-one legions. Publius Licinius Varus, the city
                    praetor, was also commissioned to repair the thirty old men of war which lay at
                    Ostia, and to man twenty new ones with full complements, in order that he might
                    defend the sea-coast in the neighbour- <pb n="1124" xml:id="p.1124"/> hood of
                    Rome with a fleet of fifty ships. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Caius
                    Calpurnius was ordered not to move his army from Arretium till his successor had
                    arrived. Both he and Tubulus were ordered to be particularly careful, lest any
                    new plots should be formed in that quarter. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The praetors set out for their provinces. The
                    consuls were detained by religious affairs; for receiving intelligence of
                    several prodigies, they could not easily obtain a favourable appearance from the
                    victims. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was reported from Campania, that
                    two temples, those of Fortune and Mars, and several sepulchres, had been struck
                    by lightning. From Cumae, so does superstition connect the deities with the most
                    trifling circumstances, that mice had gnawed some gold in the temple of Jupiter.
                    That an immense swarm of bees had settled in the forum at Casinum. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> That at Ostia a wall and gate had been struck by
                    lightning. At Caere, that a vulture had flown into the temple of Jupiter.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That blood had flowed from a lake at
                    Volsinii. On account of these prodigies, a supplication was performed for one
                    day. For several days, victims of the larger kind were sacrificed without any
                    favourable appearance, and for a long time the good will of the gods could not
                    be obtained. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The fatal event indicated by
                    these portents pointed to the persons of the consuls, the state being
                    unaffected. The Apollinarian games were first celebrated by Publius Cornelius
                    Sulla, the city praetor, in the consulate of Quintus Fulvius and Appius
                    Claudius; from that time all the city praetors in succession had performed them;
                    but they vowed them for one year only, and fixed no day for their performance.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This year a grievous pestilence attacked
                    the city and the country; it showed itself, however, in protracted rather than
                    fatal diseases. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On account of this pestilence
                    a supplication was performed in every street throughout the city; and Publius
                    Licinius Varus, the city proctor, was ordered to propose to the people a law to
                    the effect, that a vow should be made to perform these games on a stated day for
                    ever. He himself was the first who vowed them in this manner, and he celebrated
                    them on the third day of the nones of July, a day which was henceforth kept
                    sacred. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The reports respecting the people of Arretium
                    became daily more serious, and the anxiety of the fathers increased. A letter
                    was therefore written to Caius Hostilius, directing him not to delay taking
                    hostages from that people; and Caius <pb n="1125" xml:id="p.1125"/> Terentius
                    Varro was sent, with a command, to receive from him the hostages and convey them
                    to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On hi arrival, Hostilius immediately
                    ordered one legion, which was encamped before the city, to march into it; and
                    having posted guards in suitable places, he summoned the senate into the forum
                    and demanded hostages of them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the senate's
                    requesting a delay of two days to consider the matter, he declared that they
                    must themselves give them forthwith, or he would the next day take all the
                    children of the senators. After this the military tribunes, the praefects of the
                    allies, and the centurions, were ordered to keep watch at the gates, that no one
                    might go out by night. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This duty was not
                    performed with sufficient care and attention, for seven of the principal
                    senators, with their children, escaped before night, and before the guards were
                    posted at the gates. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next day, as soon as
                    it was light, the senate began to be summoned into the forum, when they were
                    missed and their goods were sold. From the rest of the senators one hundred and
                    twenty hostages, consisting of their own children, were taken and delivered over
                    to Caius Terentius to be conveyed to Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Before the senate he made every thing more suspected than before. Considering,
                    therefore, that there was imminent danger of a commotion in Tuscany, they
                    ordered Caius Terentius himself to lead one of the city legions to Arretium, and
                    to employ it for the protection of the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    It was also resolved, that Caius Hostilius, with the other army, should traverse
                    the whole province, and use precautions, that no opportunity might be afforded
                    to those who were desirous of altering the state of things. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> On his arrival at Arretium with the legion, Terentius asked
                    the magistrates for the keys of the gates, when they declared they could not be
                    found; but he, believing that they had been put out of the way with some bad
                    intention rather than lost through negligence, took upon himself to have fresh
                    locks put upon all the gates, and used diligent care to keep every thing in his
                    own power. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He earnestly cautioned Hostilius to
                    rest his hope in this; that the Tuscans would remain quiet, if he should take
                    care that not a step could be taken. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The case of the Tarentines was then warmly
                    debated in the senate, Fabius being present, and himself defending those whom he
                    had subdued by force of arms, while others <pb n="1126" xml:id="p.1126"/>
                    entertained an angry feeling towards them; the greater part comparing them with
                    the Campanians in guilt and punishment. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A
                    decree of the senate was passed conformably to the opinion of Manius Acilius,
                    that the town should be guarded by a garrison, and that all the Tarentines
                    should be kept within their walls; and further, that the question touching their
                    conduct should be hereafter laid before the senate afresh, when the state of
                    Italy should be more tranquil. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The case of
                    Marcus Livius, prefect of the citadel of Tarentum, was also debated with no less
                    warmth; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> some proposing a vote of censure
                    against the prefect on the ground that Tarentum was betrayed to the enemy
                    through his negligence, others proposing rewards for having defended the citadel
                    for five years, and because Tarentum had been recovered chiefly by his single
                    efforts; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> while some, adopting an intermediate
                    course, declared that it appertained to the censors, and not to the senate, to
                    take cognizance of his case; and of this latter opinion was Fabius, who added,
                    however, <quote> that he admitted that the recovery of Tarentum was owing to the
                        efforts of Livius, as his friends openly boasted in the senate, but
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> that there would have been no
                        necessity for its recovery, had it not been lost. </quote> One of the
                    consuls, Titus Quinctius Crispinus, set out for Lucania, with soma troops to
                    make up the numbers, to take the command of the army which had served under
                    Quintus Fulvius Flaccus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcellus was
                    detained by a succession of religious scruples, which presented themselves to
                    his mind. One of which was, that when in the Gallic war at Clastidium he had
                    vowed a temple to Honour and Valour, its dedication was impeded by the pontiffs.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> who said, that one shrine could not with
                    propriety be dedicated to two deities; because if it should be struck with
                    lightning or any kind of portent should happen in it, the expiation would be
                    attended with difficulty, as it could not be ascertained to which deity
                    sacrifice ought to be made; nor could one victim be lawfully offered to two
                    deities, unless in particular cases. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly another temple to Virtue was erected with all speed. Nevertheless,
                    these temples were not dedicated by Marcellus himself. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Then at length he set out, with the troops raised to fill
                    up the numbers, to the army he had left the preceding year at Venusia.
                    Crispinus, who endeavoured to reduce Locri in Bruttium by a siege, because he
                    considered that the affair of Tarentum had <pb n="1127" xml:id="p.1127"/> added
                    greatly to the fame of Fabius, had sent for every kind of engine and machine
                    from Sicily; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> he also sent for ships from the
                    same place to attack that part of the city which lay towards the sea. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> But this siege was raised by Hannibal's bringing his
                    forces to Lacinium, and in consequence of a report, that his colleague, with
                    whom he wished to effect a junction, had now led his army from Venusia.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He therefore returned from Bruttium into
                    Apulia, and the consuls took up a position in two separate camps, distant from
                    each other less than three miles, between Venusia and Bantia. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal, after diverting the war from Locri, returned also
                    into the same quarter. Here the consuls, who were both of sanguine temperament,
                    almost daily went out and drew up their troops for action, confidently hoping,
                    that if the enemy would hazard an engagement with two consular armies united,
                    they might put an end to the war. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As Hannibal, who gained one and lost the other
                    of the two battles which he fought the preceding year with Marcellus, would have
                    equal grounds for hope and fear, should he encounter the same general again; so
                    was he far from thinking himself a match for the two consuls together.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Directing his attention, therefore, wholly
                    to his own peculiar arts, he looked out for an opportunity for planting an
                    ambuscade. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Slight battles, however, were
                    fought between the two camps with varying success. But the consuls, thinking it
                    probable that the summer would be spun out in engagements of this kind, and
                    being of opinion that the siege of Locri might be going on notwithstanding,
                    wrote to Lucius Cincius to pass over to Locri with his fleet from Sicily.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And that the walls might be besieged by
                    land also, they ordered one half of the army, which formed the garrison of
                    Tarentum, to be marched thither. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal
                    having found from certain Thurians that these things would be done, sent a body
                    of troops to lie in ambush on the road leading from Tarentum. There, under the
                    hill of Petelia, three thousand cavalry and two thousand foot were placed in
                    concealment. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Romans, who proceeded without
                    exploring their way, having fallen into the ambuscade, as many as two thousand
                    soldiers were slain, and about twelve hundred made prisoners. The others, who
                    were scattered in flight through the fields and forests, returned to Tarentum.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There was a rising ground covered with
                    wood situated between the Punic and Roman camps, <pb n="1128" xml:id="p.1128"/>
                    which was occupied at first by neither party, because the Romans were
                    unacquainted with its nature on that side which faced the enemy's camp, while
                    Hannibal had supposed it better adapted for an ambuscade than a camp. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly, he had sent thither, by night, several
                    troops of Numidians, concealing them in the midst of the wood. Not one of them
                    stirred from his position by day, lest their arms or themselves should be
                    observed from a distance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There was a general
                    murmur in the Roman camp, that this eminence ought to be occupied and secured by
                    a fort, lest if it should be seized by Hannibal they should have the enemy, as
                    it were, immediately over their heads. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Marcellus was moved by this consideration, and observed to his colleague,
                        <quote> Why not go ourselves with a few horsemen and reconnoitre? <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The matter being examined with our own eyes,
                        will make our measures more certain. </quote> Crispinus consenting, they set
                    out with two hundred and twenty horsemen, of which forty were Fregellans, the
                    rest Tuscans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Marcus Marcellus, the consul's
                    son, and Aulus Manlius, military tribunes, together with two prefects of the
                    allies, Lucius Arennius and Manius Aulius, accompanied them. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Some historians have recorded, that Marcellus had offered
                    sacrifices on that day, and that in the first victim slain, the liver was found
                    without its head; in the second, that all the usual parts were present, and that
                    there was also an excrescence in the head. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    That the aruspex was not, indeed, pleased that the entrails should first have
                    appeared mutilated and foul, and then too exuberant. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the consul Marcellus was influenced by so
                    ardent a desire of engaging with Hannibal, that he never thought their camps
                    close enough. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At that time also, as he quitted
                    the rampart, he gave orders that the troops should be ready when occasion
                    required, in order that if the hill, which they were going to examine, were
                    thought convenient, they might collect their baggage and follow them. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Before the camp there was a small plain; the road
                    thence to the hill was open and exposed to view on all sides. A watchman who was
                    stationed, not under the expectation of so important an event, but in order that
                    they might be able to intercept any stragglers who had gone too far from the
                    camp in search of wood or forage, gave a signal to the Numidians to rise
                    simultaneously one and all from their concealment. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Those who were to rise from the very summit of the hill,
                    and meet the <pb n="1129" xml:id="p.1129"/> enemy, did not show themselves until
                    those whose business it was to intercept their passage in the rear, had gone
                    round. Then they all sprang up from every side, and, raising a shout, commenced
                    an attack. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although the consuls were in such a
                    position in the valley that they could neither make good their way up the hill,
                    which was occupied by the enemy, nor retreat, as they were intercepted in the
                    rear, yet the contest might have been continued longer had not a retreat,
                    commenced by the Tuscans, dismayed the rest of the troops. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Fregellans, however, did not give over fighting, though
                    deserted by the Tuscans, while the consuls, uninjured, kept up the battle by
                    encouraging their men and fighting themselves. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But when they saw both the consuls wounded, and Marcellus transfixed with a
                    lance and falling lifeless from his horse, then they too, and but a very few
                    survived, betook themselves to flight, together with Crispinus the consul, who
                    had received two javelin wounds, and young Marcellus, who was himself also
                    wounded. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Aulus Manlius, a military tribune,
                    was slain, and of the two prefects of allies, Manius Aulius was slain, Lucius
                    Arennius made prisoner. Five of the consul's lictors fell into the enemy's hands
                    alive, the rest were either slain or fled with the consul. Forty-three horsemen
                    fell in the battle or in the flight, and eighteen were taken alive. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> An alarm had been excited in the camp, and the troops
                    were hastening to go and succour the consuls, when <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> they saw one of the consuls and the son of the other
                    wounded, and the scanty remains of this unfortunate expedition returning to the
                    camp. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The death of Marcellus was an event to
                    be deplored, as well from other circumstances which attended it, as because that
                    in a manner unbecoming his years, for he was then more than sixty, and
                    inconsistently with the prudence of a veteran general, he had so improvidently
                    plunged into ruin himself, his colleague, and almost the whole commonwealth.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> I should launch out into too many
                    digressions for a single event, were I to relate all the various accounts which
                    authors give respecting the death of Marcellus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> To pass over others Lucius Caelius gives three narratives ranged under
                    different heads; one as it is handed down by tradition; a second, written in the
                    panegyric of his son, who was engaged in the affair; a third, which he himself
                    vouched for, being the result of his own investigation. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The accounts, however, though varying <pb n="1130"
                        xml:id="p.1130"/> in other points, agree for the most part in the fact, that
                    he went out of the camp for the purpose of viewing the ground; and all state
                    that he was cut off by an ambuscade. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, concluding that the enemy were
                    greatly dismayed by one of their consuls being slain and the other wounded, that
                    he might not be wanting on any opportunity presenting itself, immediately
                    transferred his camp to the eminence on which the battle had been fought.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here he found the body of Marcellus, and
                    interred it. Crispinus, disheartened by the death of his colleague and his own
                    wound, set out during the silence of the following night, and encamped upon the
                    nearest mountains he could reach, in a position elevated and secured on all
                    sides. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here the two generals exerted their
                    sagacity, the one in effecting, the other in guarding against, a deception.
                    Hannibal got possession of the ring of Marcellus, together with his body.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Crispinus, fearing lest any artifice
                    should be practised by the Carthaginian's employing this signet as the means of
                    deception, had sent round messengers to the neighbouring states, informing them,
                    that <quote> his colleague had been slain, and that the enemy were in possession
                        of his seal, and that they must not give credit to any letters written in
                        the name of Marcellus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This message of the consul arrived at Salapia
                    a little before a letter was brought from Hannibal, written in the name of
                    Marcellus, to the effect, that <quote> he should come to Salapia on the night
                        which followed that day; that the soldiers in the garrison should hold
                        themselves in readiness, in case he might want to employ them on any
                        service. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Salapians were aware of the fraud, and
                    concluding that an opportunity for punishing them was sought by Hannibal, from
                    resentment, not only on account of their defection, but also because they slew
                    his <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> horsemen, sent his messenger, who was a
                    deserter from the Romans, back again, in order that the soldiers might do what
                    was thought necessary, without his being privy to it, and then placed the
                    townsmen in parties to keep guard along the walls, and in convenient parts of
                    the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The guards and watches they formed
                    with extraordinary care for that night, and on each side of the gate at which
                    they supposed the enemy would come, they opposed to them the choicest of the
                    troops in the garrison. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> About the fourth
                    watch, Hannibal approached the city. His vanguard was composed of Roman
                    deserters, with <pb n="1131" xml:id="p.1131"/> Roman arms. These, all of whom
                    spoke the Latin language, when they reached the gate, called up the guards, and
                    ordered the gate to be opened, for the consul had arrived. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The guards, as if awakened at their call, began to be in a
                    hurry and bustle, and exert themselves in opening the gate, which was closed by
                    letting down the portcullis; some raised this with levers, others drew it up
                    with ropes to such a height that the men could come in without stooping.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The opening was scarcely wide enough,
                    when the deserters eagerly rushed through the gate, and after about six hundred
                    had got in, the rope being let go by which it was suspended, the portcullis fell
                    with a loud noise. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some of the Salapians fell
                    upon the deserters, who were carrying their arms carelessly suspended upon their
                    shoulders, as is customary after a march, as if among friends; others frightened
                    away the enemy by discharging stones, pikes, and javelins from the tower
                    adjoining the gate and from the walls. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Thus
                    Hannibal withdrew, having been caught by his own stratagem, and proceeded to
                    raise the siege of Locri, which Cincius was carrying on with the greatest
                    vigour, with works and engines of every kind, which were brought from Sicily.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Mago, who by that time almost despaired
                    of retaining and defending the town, derived his first gleam of hope on the
                    death of Marcellus being reported. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> This was
                    followed by a message, that Hannibal had despatched his Numidian cavalry in
                    advance, and was himself following them with all possible speed with a body of
                    infantry. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> As soon, therefore, as he was
                    informed, by a signal displayed from the watch-towers, that the Numidians were
                    drawing near, suddenly throwing open the gate he sallied out boldly upon the
                    enemy, and at first, more because he had done it unexpectedly than from the
                    equality of his strength, the contest was doubtful; <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> but afterwards, when the Numidians came up, the Romans were
                    so dismayed that they fled on all hands to the sea and their ships, leaving
                    their works and the engines with which they battered the walls. Thus the siege
                    of Locri was raised by the approach of Hannibal. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Crispinus found that Hannibal had gone
                    into Bruttium, he ordered Marcus Marcellus, a military tribune, to march the
                    army, which his colleague had commanded, to Venusia. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Having set out himself with his own legions for Capua,
                    though scarcely able to endure the motion of the <pb n="1132" xml:id="p.1132"/>
                    litter, from the severity of his wounds, he sent a letter to Rome stating the
                    death of his colleague, and in how great danger he himself was. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He said, "it was impossible for him to go to Rome to hold
                    the election, both because he did not think he could bear the fatigue of the
                    journey, and because he was anxious about Tarentum, lest Hannibal should direct
                    his course thither from Bruttium. That it was expedient that commissioners
                    should be sent to him, men of sound judgment, with whom he might communicate,
                    when he pleased, respecting the commonwealth. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The reading of this letter excited great grief for the death of one of the
                    consuls, and apprehension for the safety of the other. They therefore sent
                    Quintus Fabius the younger to Venusia to the army; and to the consul three
                    commissioners, Sextus Julius Caesar, Lucius Licinius Pollio, and Lucius Cincius
                    Alimentus, though but a few days before he had returned from Sicily. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> These were directed to convey a message to the
                    consul, to the effect, that if he could not himself go to Rome to hold the
                    election, he should nominate a dictator within the Roman territory for that
                    purpose. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If the consul should have gone to
                    Tarentum, that it was the pleasure of the senate that Marcus Claudius, the
                    praetor, should march off his legions to that quarter in which he could protect
                    the greatest number of the cities of the allies. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> The same summer Marcus Valerius crossed over from Sicily into Africa with a
                    fleet of a hundred ships, and making a descent near the city Clupea, devastated
                    the country to a wide extent, scarcely meeting with a single person in arms.
                    Afterwards the troops employed in making these depredations were hastily led
                    back to their ships, and a report had suddenly reached them that a Carthaginian
                    fleet was drawing near. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It consisted of
                    eighty-three ships. With these the Romans fought successfully, not far from the
                    city Clupea, and after taking eighteen and putting the rest to flight, returned
                    to Lilybaeum with a great deal of booty gained both by land and sea. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The same summer also Philip gave assistance to the
                    suppliant Achaeans. They were harassed by Machanidas, tyrant of the
                    Lacedaemonians, with a war in their immediate neighbourhood; and the Aetolians,
                    having passed over an army in ships through the strait which runs between
                    Naupactus and Patrae, called by the neighbouring people Rhion, had devastated
                    their country. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was reported also, that
                    Attalus, king of Asia, <pb n="1133" xml:id="p.1133"/> would pass over into
                    Europe, because the Aetolians, in their last council, had offered to him the
                    office of chief magistrate of their nation. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, when marching down into Greece, for
                    these reasons, was met at the city Lamia by the Aetolians, under the command of
                    Pyrrhias, who had been created praetor that year jointly with Attalus, who was
                    absent. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They had with them also auxiliaries
                    from Attalus, and about a thousand men sent from the Roman fleet by Publius
                    Sulpicius. Against this general and these forces, Philip fought twice
                    successfully, and slew full a thousand of his enemies in each battle. Whence, as
                    the Aetolians were compelled by fear to keep themselves under the walls of
                    Lamia, Philip led back his army to Phalara. This place is situated in the Malian
                    bay, and was formerly thickly inhabited on account of its excellent harbour, the
                    safe anchorage in its neighbourhood, and other conveniences of sea and land.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hither came ambassadors from Ptolemy, king
                    of Egypt, the Rhodians, Athenians, and Chians, to put a stop to hostilities
                    between the Aetolians and Philip. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    Aetolians also called in one of their neighbours as a mediator, Amynander, king
                    of the Athamanians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But all these were less
                    concerned for the Aetolians, whose arrogance of disposition exceeded that of any
                    other nation of Greece, than lest Philip and his empire, which was likely to
                    prove injurious to the cause of liberty, should be intermixed with the affairs
                    of Greece. The deliberations concerning a peace were put off, to a council of
                    the Achaeans, for which a place and certain day were fixed upon; for the mean
                    time a true of thirty days was obtained. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    king, setting out thence, went through Thessaly and Bœotia to Chalcis in Eubœa,
                    to prevent Attalus, who he <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> heard was about
                    to come to Eubœa with a fleet, from entering the harbours and approaching the
                    coasts. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Leaving a force to oppose Attalus, in
                    case he should cross over in the mean time, he set out thence with a small body
                    of cavalry and light-armed troops, and came to Argos. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Here the superintendence of the Heraean and Nemaean games
                    having been conferred upon him by the suffrages of the people, because the kings
                    of the Macedonians trace their origin from that state, after completing the
                    Heraean games, he set out directly after the celebration for Aegium, to the
                    council of allies, fixed some time before. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Here measures were proposed <pb n="1134" xml:id="p.1134"/> for putting an end to
                    the Aetolian war, in order that neither the Romans nor Attalus might have a
                    pretext for entering Greece; but they were all upset by the Aetolians, before
                    the period of the truce had <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> scarcely
                    expired, after they heard that Attalus had arrived at Aegina, and that a Roman
                    fleet was stationed at Naupactus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For when
                    called into the council of the Achaeans, where the same embassies were present
                    which had negotiated for peace at Phalara, they at first complained of some
                    trifling acts committed during the period of the truce, contrary to the faith of
                    the convention; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> but at last they asserted,
                    that it was impossible the war could be terminated unless the Achaeans gave back
                    Pylus to the Messenians, unless Atintania was restored to the Romans, and
                    Ardyaea to Scerdilaedus and Pleuratus. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But
                    Philip, conceiving it an indignity that the vanquished should presumptuously
                    dictate terms to him the victor, said, <quote> that he did not before either
                        listen to proposals for peace, or agree to a truce, from any hope he
                        entertained that the Aetolians would remain quiet, but in order that he
                        might have all the allies as witnesses that he was desirous of peace, and
                        that they were the occasion of this war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Thus, without effecting a peace, he dismissed
                    the council; and leaving four thousand troops for the protection of the
                    Achaeans, and receiving five men of war, with which, if he could <milestone
                        n="16??" unit="section"/> have joined them to the fleet of the Carthaginians
                    lately sent to him, and the ships which were coming from Bithynia, from king
                    Prusias, he had resolved to challenge the Romans, who had long been masters of
                    the sea in that quarter, to a naval battle, the king himself went back from the
                    congress to Argos; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> for now the time for
                    celebrating the Nemaean games was approaching, which he wished to be celebrated
                    in his presence. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the king was occupied with the
                    exhibition of the games, and was indulging himself during the days devoted to
                    festivity with more freedom than in time of war, Publius Sulpicius, setting out
                    from Naupactus, brought his fleet to the shore, between Sicyon and Corinth, and
                    devastated without restraint a country of the most renowned fertility.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Intelligence of this proceeding called
                    Philip away from the games. He set out hastily with his cavalry, ordering his
                    infantry to follow him closely; and attacking the Romans as they were scattered
                    through the fields and loaded with booty, like men who feared nothing of the
                    kind, drove them to their ships. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1135" xml:id="p.1135"/> The Roman fleet returned to Naupactus by no means
                    pleased with their booty. The fame of a victory gained by Philip over the
                    Romans, of whatever magnitude, increased the celebrity of the remaining part of
                    the games. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The festival was celebrated with
                    extraordinary mirth, the more so as the king, in order to please the people,
                    took the diadem off his head, and laid aside his purple robe with the other
                    royal apparel, and placed himself, with regard to appearance, on an equality
                    with the rest, than which nothing is more gratifying to free states. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> By this conduct he would have afforded the strongest
                    hopes of the enjoyment of liberty, had he not debased and marred all by his
                    intolerable lust; for he ranged night and day through the houses of married
                    people with one or two companions, and in proportion as he was less conspicuous
                    by lowering his dignity to a private level, the less restraint lie felt;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> thus converting that empty show of
                    liberty, which he had made to others, into a cover for the gratification of his
                    own unbounded desires. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For neither did he
                    obtain his object in all cases by money or seductive arts, but he also employed
                    violence in the accomplishment of his flagitious purposes; and it was dangerous
                    both to husbands and parents to have presented any impediment to the
                    gratification of royal lust, by an unseasonable strictness. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> From one man, Aratus, of the highest rank among the
                    Achaeans, his wife, named Polycratia, was taken away and conveyed into Macedonia
                    under the hope of a matrimonial connexion with royalty. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> After passing the time appointed for the celebration of the
                    Nemaean games, and a few days more, in the commission of these profligate acts,
                    he set out for Dymae to expel the garrison of the Aetolians, which had been
                    invited by the Eleans, and received into the town. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Cycliadas, who had the chief direction of affairs, met the
                    king at Dymae, together with the Achaeans, who were inflamed with hatred against
                    the Eleans, because they had disunited themselves from the rest of the Achaeans,
                    and were incensed against the Aetolians, because they considered that they had
                    stirred up a Roman war against them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Setting
                    out from Dymae, and uniting their forces, they passed the river Larissus, which
                    separates the Elean from the Dymaean territory. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first day on which they entered upon the
                    enemy's confines, they employed in plundering. The following day they <pb
                        n="1136" xml:id="p.1136"/> approached the city in battle-array, having sent
                    their cavalry in advance, in order that, by riding up to the gates, they might
                    provoke the Aetolians to make a sally, a measure to which they were naturally
                    inclined. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were not aware that Sulpicius
                    had passed over from Naupactus to Cyllene with fifteen ships, and landing four
                    thousand armed men, had entered Elis during the dead of night, that his troops
                    might not be seen. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, when they
                    recognised the Roman standards and arms among the Aetolians, so unexpected an
                    event occasioned the greatest terror; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and at
                    first the king had wished to withdraw his troops; but afterwards, an engagement
                    having taken place between the Aetolians and Trallians, a tribe of Illyrians,
                    when he saw his men hard pressed, the king himself with his cavalry charged a
                    Roman cohort. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here his horse being pierced
                    with a javelin threw the king, who fell over his head; when a conflict ensued,
                    which was desperate on both sides; the Romans making a furious attack upon the
                    king, and the royal party protecting him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His
                    own conduct was highly meritorious, when though on foot he was obliged to fight
                    among horsemen. Afterwards, when the contest was unequal, many were falling and
                    being wounded around him, he was snatched away by his soldiers, and, being
                    placed upon another horse, fled from the field. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> On that day he pitched his camp five miles from the city of the Eleans, and
                    the next day led out all his forces to a fort called Pyrgus, whither he had
                    heard that a multitude of rustics had resorted through fear of being plundered.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This unorganized and unarmed multitude he
                    took immediately on his approach, from the first effects of alarm; and by this
                    capture compensated for the disgrace sustained at Elis. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> While engaged in distributing the spoil and captives, and
                    there were four thousand men and as many as twenty thousand head of cattle of
                    every kind, intelligence reached him from Macedonia that one Eropus had gained
                    possession of Lychnidus by bribing the praefect of the citadel and garrison;
                    that he held also certain towns of the Dassaretians, and that he was
                    endeavouring to incite the Dardanians to arms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Desisting from the Achaean war, therefore, but still leaving two thousand
                    five hundred armed troops of every description under the generals Menippus and
                    Polyphantas for the protection of his allies, he <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> set out <pb n="1137" xml:id="p.1137"/> from Dymae, and
                    passing through Achaea, Bœotia, and Eubœa, arrived on the tenth day at Demetrias
                    in Thessaly. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Here he was met by other messengers with
                    intelligence of still greater commotions; that the Dardanians, having poured
                    into Macedonia, were in possession of Orestis, and had descended into the
                    Argestaean plain; and that there was a general report among the barbarians that
                    Philip was slain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In that expedition in which
                    he fought with the plundering party near Sicyon, being carried by the fury of
                    his horse against a tree, he broke off the extremity of one of the horns of his
                    helmet against a projecting branch; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> which
                    being found by a certain Aetolian and carried into Aetolia to Scerdilaedus, who
                    knew it to be the ornament of his helmet, spread the report that the king was
                    killed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the king had departed from
                    Achaea, Sulpicius, going to Aegina with his fleet, formed a junction with
                    Attalus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Achaeans fought successfully with
                    the Aetolians and Eleans not far from Messene. King Attalus and Publius
                    Sulpicius wintered at Aegina. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the close of
                    this year Titus Quinctius Crispinus, the consul, after having nominated Titus
                    Manlius Torquatus dictator for the purpose of holding the election and
                    celebrating the games, died of his wound. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some
                    say that he died at Tarentum, others in Campania. The death of the two consuls,
                    who were slain without having fought any memorable battle, a coincidence which
                    had never occurred in any former war, had left the commonwealth in a manner
                    orphan. The dictator, Manlius, appointed as his master of the horse Caius
                    Servilius, then curule aedile. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the first
                    day of its meeting the senate ordered the dictator to celebrate the great games
                    which Marcus Aemilius, the city praetor, had celebrated in the consulship of
                    Caius Flaminius and Cneius Servilius, and had vowed to be repeated after five
                    years. The dictator then both performed the games and vowed them for the
                    following lustrum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But as the two consular
                    armies without commanders were so near the enemy, disregarding every thing else,
                    one especial care engrossed the fathers and the people, that of creating the
                    consuls as soon as possible; and that they might create those in preference
                    whose valour was least in danger from Carthaginian treachery; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> since, through the whole period of the war, the precipitate
                    and hot tempers of their generals had been detrimental, and this very year the
                    consuls had fallen <pb n="1138" xml:id="p.1138"/> into a snare for which they
                    were not prepared, in consequence of their excessive eagerness to engage the
                    enemy, but the immortal gods, in pity to <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                    the Roman name, had spared the unoffending armies, and doomed the consuls to
                    expiate their temerity with their own lives. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the fathers' looking round to see whom they
                    should appoint as consuls, Caius Claudius Nero appeared preeminently. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> They then looked out for a colleague for him, and
                    although they considered him a man of the highest talents, they also were of
                    opinion that he was of a more forward and vehement disposition than the
                    circumstances of the war, or the enemy, Hannibal, <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> required, they resolved that it would be right to qualify
                    the impetuosity of his temper by uniting with him a cool and prudent colleague.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The person fixed upon was Marcus Livius,
                    who, many years ago, was, on the expiration of his consulship, condemned in a
                    trial before the people; a disgrace which he took so much to heart, that he
                    retired into the country, and for many years absented himself from the city, and
                    avoided all public assemblies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Much about the
                    eighth year after his condemnation, Marcus Claudius Marcellus and Marcus
                    Valerius Laevinus, the consuls, had brought him back into the city; but he
                    appeared in a squalid dress, his hair and beard allowed to grow, and exhibiting
                    in his countenance and attire the deep impression of the disgrace he had
                    sustained. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Lucius Veturius and Publius
                    Licinius, the censors, compelled him to have his beard and hair trimmed, to lay
                    aside his squalid garb, to come into the senate, and discharge other public
                    duties. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But even then he either gave his
                    assent by a single word, or signified his vote by walking to one side of the
                    house, till the trial of Marcus Livius Macatus, a kinsman of his, whose
                    character was at stake, obliged him to deliver his sentiments in the senate upon
                    his legs. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On being heard in the senate on this
                    occasion, after so long an interval, he drew the eyes of all upon him, and gave
                    occasion to conversations to the following effect: <quote> That the people had
                        injuriously disgraced a man who was undeserving of it, and that it had been
                        greatly detrimental to the state that, in so important a war, it had not had
                        the benefit of the services and counsels of such a man. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> That neither Quintus Fabius nor Marcus Valerius
                        Laevinus could be given to Caius Nero as colleagues, because it was not
                        allowed for two patricians to <pb n="1139" xml:id="p.1139"/> be elected.
                        That the same cause precluded Titus Manlius, besides that he had refused a
                        consulship when offered to him, and would refuse it. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> That they would have two most distinguished consuls if
                        they should add Marcus Livius as a colleague to Caius Claudius. </quote> Nor
                    did the people despise a proposal, the mention of which originated with the
                    fathers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The only person in the state who
                    objected to the measure was the man to whom the honour was offered, who accused
                    his <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> countrymen of inconstancy, saying,
                        <quote> that, having withheld their pity from him when arrayed in a mourning
                        garment and a criminal, they now forced upon him the white gown against his
                        will; that honours and punishments were heaped upon the same person.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If they esteemed him a good man, why
                        had they thus passed a sentence of condemnation upon him as a wicked and
                        guilty one? If they had proved him a guilty man, why should they thus trust
                        him with a second consulate after having improperly committed to him the
                        first? </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> While thus remonstrating and complaining, the
                    fathers rebuked him, putting him in mind, that <quote> Marcus Furius too, being
                        recalled from exile, had reinstated his country when shaken from her very
                        base. That we ought to soothe the anger of our country as we would that of
                        parents, by patience and resignation. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> All exerting themselves to the utmost, they
                    succeeded in uniting Marcus Livius in the consulate with Caius Claudius. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The third day afterwards the election of
                    praetors was held. The praetors created were, Lucius Porcius Licinus, Caius
                    Mamilius, Aulus Hostilius Cato, and Caius Hostilius Cato. The election
                    completed, and the games celebrated, the dictator and master of the horse
                    abdicated their offices. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Caius Terentius Varro
                    was sent as proprietor into Etruria, in order that Caius Hostilius might quit
                    that province and go to Tarentum to that army which Titus Quinctius, the consul,
                    had commanded, and that Lucius Manlius might go as ambassador across the sea,
                    and observe what was going on there; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and at
                    the same time, as the games at Olympia, which were attended by the greatest
                    concourse of persons of any solemnity in Greece, were about to take place that
                    summer, that if he could without danger from the enemy, he might <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> go to that assembly, in order that any Sicilians
                    who might be there, having been driven away by the war, or any Tarentine citi-
                        <pb n="1140" xml:id="p.1140"/> zens banished by Hannibal, might return to
                    their homes, and be informed that the Roman people would restore to them every
                    thing which they had possessed before the war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    As a year of the most dangerous character seemed to threaten them, and there
                    were no consuls to direct the government, all men fixed their attention on the
                    consuls elect, wishing them to draw lots for their provinces, as soon as
                    possible, and determine beforehand what province and what enemy each should
                    have. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate also took measures, at the
                    instance of Quintus Fabius Maximus, to effect a reconciliation between them.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For the enmity between them was notorious;
                    and in the case of Livius his misfortunes rendered it more inveterate and
                    acrimonious, as he considered that in that situation he had been treated with
                    contempt. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was, therefore, the more
                    inexorable, and said, <quote> that there was no need of a reconciliation, for
                        that they would use greater diligence and activity in every thing they did
                        for fear lest they should give their colleague, who was an enemy, an
                        opportunity of advancing himself at their expense. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> However, the authority of the senate
                    prevailed; and, laying aside their private differences, they conducted the
                    affairs of the state in friendship and unanimity. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Their provinces were not districts bordering upon each
                    other, as in former years, but quite separate, in the remotest confines of
                    Italy. To one was decreed Bruttium and Lucania, to act against Hannibal; to the
                    other Gaul, to act against Hasdrubal, who, it was reported, was now approaching
                    the Alps; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and that he to whose lot Gaul fell
                    should choose whichever he pleased of the two armies, one of which was in Gaul,
                    the other in Etruria, and receive the city legions in addition; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> and that he to whose lot Bruttium fell, should,
                    after enlisting fresh legions for the city, take the army of whichever of the
                    consuls of the former year he pleased. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That
                    Quintus Fulvius, proconsul, should take the army which was left by the consul,
                    and that his command should last for a year. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    To Caius Hostilius, to whom they had given the province of Tarentum in exchange
                    for Etruria, they gave Capua instead of Tarentum, with one legion which Fulvius
                    had commanded the preceding year. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The anxiety respecting the approach of
                    Hasdrubal to Italy increased daily. At first, ambassadors from the Massilians
                    had brought word that he had passed over into Gaul, <pb n="1141" xml:id="p.1141"
                    /> and that <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the expectations of the Gauls
                    were raised by his coming, as he was reported to have brought a large quantity
                    of gold for the purpose of hiring auxiliaries. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Afterwards, Sextus Antistius and Marcus Raecius, who were sent from Rome,
                    together with these persons, as ambassadors, to look into the affair, had
                    brought word back that they had sent persons with Massilian guides, who, through
                    the medium of Gallic chieftains connected with them by hospitality, might bring
                    back all ascertained particulars; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that they
                    found that Hasdrubal, who had already collected an immense army, would cross the
                    Alps the ensuing spring; and that the only cause which delayed him there was,
                    that the passage of the Alps was closed by winter. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Aelius Paetus was created and inaugurated in the
                    office of augur in the room of Marcus Marcellus, and Cneius Cornelius Dolabella
                    was inaugurated king of <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the sacred rites in
                    the room of Marcus Marcius, who had died two years before. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> This same year, for the first time since Hannibal came into
                    Italy, the lustrum was closed by the censors Publius Sempronius Tuditanus and
                    Marcus Cornelius Cethegus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The citizens
                    numbered in the census were one hundred and thirty-seven thousand one hundred
                    and eight, a number considerably smaller than before the war. This year it is
                    recorded that the Comitium was covered, and that the Roman games were repeated
                    once by the curule aediles, Quintus Metellus and Caius Servilius; and that the
                    plebeian games were repeated twice by Quintus Mamilius and Marcus Caecilius
                    Metellus, plebeian aediles. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The same persons
                    also gave three statues for the temple of Ceres, and there was a feast in honour
                    of Jupiter on occasion of the games. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After
                    this Caius Claudius Nero and Marcus Livius a second time entered upon their
                    consulate; and as they had already, while consuls elect, drawn lots for their
                    provinces, they ordered the praetors to draw lots for theirs. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Caius Hostilius had the city jurisdiction, to which the
                    foreign was added, in order that three praetors might go out to the provinces.
                    Aulus Hostilius had Sardinia, Caius Mamilius, Sicily, Lucius Porcius, Gaul.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The total amount of legions employed in
                    the provinces was twenty-three, which were so distributed that the consuls might
                    have two each; Spain, four; the three praetors in Sicily, Sardinia, and Gaul,
                    two each; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Caius Terentius, two in Etruria;
                    Quintus Fulvius, two in Bruttium; Quintus Clau- <pb n="1142" xml:id="p.1142"/>
                    dius two in the neighbourhood of Tarentum and the territory of Sallentum; Caius
                    Hostilius Tubulus, one at Capua; and two were ordered to be enlisted for the
                    city. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> For the first four legions the people
                    elected tribunes, the consuls sent those for the rest. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the consuls set out, the nine days'
                    sacred rite was performed, as a shower of stones had fallen from the sky at
                    Veii. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the mention of one prodigy, others
                    also were reported, as usual. At Minturnae, that the temple of Jupiter and the
                    grove of Marica, and at Atella also that a wall and gate, had been struck by
                    lightning. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The people of Minturnae added what
                    was more alarming, that a stream of blood had flowed at their gate. At Capua, a
                    wolf, which had entered at the gate by night, had torn a watchman. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> These prodigies were expiated with victims of the
                    larger kind, and a supplication for one day was made, according to a decree of
                    the pontiffs. The nine days' sacred rite was then performed again, because a
                    shower of stones had been seen to fall in the armilustrum. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> After the people's minds had been freed from superstitious
                    fears, they were again disturbed by intelligence that an infant had been born at
                    Frusino as large as a child of four years old, and not so much an object of
                    wonder from its size, as that it was born without any certain mark of
                    distinction whether it was male or female, which was the case two years before
                    at Sinuessa. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Aruspices, called in from
                    Etruria, declared this to be indeed a foul and ill-omened prodigy, which ought
                    to be removed out of the Roman territory, and, being kept far from coming in
                    contact with the earth, to be plunged into the deep. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They shut it up alive in a chest, and carrying it away,
                    threw it into the sea. The pontiffs also decreed, that thrice nine virgins
                    should go through the city singing a hymn. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    While in the temple of Jupiter Stator they were learning this hymn, which was
                    composed by the poet Livius, the temple of Juno Regina, on the Aventine, was
                    struck by lightning; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and the aruspices, on
                    being consulted, having replied that that prodigy appertained to the matrons,
                    and that the goddess must be appeased by a present, such of the matrons as dwelt
                    within the city and within the tenth milestone from it, were summoned to the
                    Capitol by an edict of the curule aediles; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    when they themselves chose twenty-five out of their own body, to whom they paid
                    a contribution out <pb n="1143" xml:id="p.1143"/> of their dowries, from which a
                    golden basin was made, as a present, and carried to the Aventine, where a
                    sacrifice was performed by the matrons in a pure and chaste manner. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Immediately a day was given out by the decemviri for
                    another sacrifice to the same goddess, which was performed in the following
                    order: two white heifers were led from the temple of Apollo into the city
                    through the Carmental gate; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> after these, two
                    cypress images of Juno Regina were carried; after these went seven and twenty
                    virgins, arrayed in white vestments, and singing in honour of Juno Regina a
                    hymn, which to the uncultivated minds of that time might appear to have merit,
                    but if repeated now would seem inelegant and uncouth. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The train of virgins was followed by the decemvirs, crowned
                    with laurel, and in purple-bordered robes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    From the gate they proceeded by the Jugarian street into the forum: in the forum
                    the procession stopped, and the virgins, linked together by a cord passed
                    through their hands, moved on, beating time with their feet to the music of
                    their voices. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> They then proceeded by the
                    Tuscan street and the Velabrum, through the cattle market, up the Publician
                    hill, and to the temple of Juno Regina; where two victims were immolated by the
                    decemviri, and the cypress images carried into the temple. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the deities were appeased in due form,
                    the consuls made the levy with greater diligence and strictness than any one
                    remembered it to have been made in former years; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> for the war was now doubly formidable, in consequence of the advance of a new
                    enemy into Italy, while the number of the youth from which they could enlist
                    soldiers was diminished. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They therefore
                    resolved to compel the settlers upon the seacoast, who were said to possess an
                    exemption from service solemnly granted, to furnish soldiers; and on their
                    refusing to do so, appointed that they should severally lay before the senate,
                    on a certain day, the grounds on which they claimed exemption. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> On the appointed day the following people tame to the
                    senate: the people of Ostia, Alsia, Antium, Anxur, Minturnae, and Sinuessa, and,
                    on the upper sea, Sena. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After each people had
                    stated their grounds of exemption, the exemption of none was allowed, as the
                    enemy was in Italy, except those of Antium and Ostia, and of these colonies the
                    young men were bound by oath that they would not lodge without the walls of
                    their colony, while the enemy was in <pb n="1144" xml:id="p.1144"/> Italy, more
                    than thirty days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Although it was the opinion
                    of all that the consuls ought to proceed to the war as soon as possible, (for
                    Hasdrubal ought to be met on his descent from the Alps, lest he might seduce the
                    Cisalpine Gauls and Etruria, which was anxiously looking forward to a
                    revolution; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> while it was necessary to occupy
                    Hannibal with a war in his own quarters, lest he should emerge from Bruttium,
                    and advance to meet his brother;) yet Livius delayed, not having sufficient
                    confidence in the armies destined for his provinces. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He said his colleague had his option to take which he
                    pleased out of two excellent consular armies, and a third which Quintus Claudius
                    commanded at Tarentum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He also made mention of
                    recalling the volunteer slaves to their standards. The senate gave the consuls
                    unrestricted liberty of filling up their numbers from what source they pleased,
                    of selecting out of all the armies such as they liked, and of exchanging and
                    removing from one province to another, as they thought conducive <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> to the good of the state. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> In all these affairs the consuls acted with the most
                    perfect harmony. The volunteer slaves were enlisted into the nineteenth and
                    twentieth legions. Some authors state that very efficient auxiliaries were sent
                    out of Spain also to Marcus Livius by Publius Scipio; namely, eight thousand
                    Spaniards and Gauls, two thousand legionary soldiers, a thousand horse of
                    Numidians and Spaniards together. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That Marcus
                    Lucretius brought these forces in ships, and that Caius Mamilius sent as many as
                    four thousand bowmen and slingers out of Sicily. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A letter which was brought out of Gaul from
                    Lucius Porcius, the praetor, increased the alarm at Rome. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It stated that Hasdrubal had quitted his winter quarters,
                    and was now crossing the Alps; that eight thousand Ligurians had been enlisted
                    and armed, which would join him when he had crossed over into Italy, unless some
                    general were sent into Liguria to engage them with a war. That he would himself
                    advance as far as he thought it safe with his small forces. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This letter obliged the consuls hastily to conclude the
                    levy, and go earlier than they had determined into their provinces, with the
                    intention that each should keep his enemy in his own province, and not allow
                    them to form a junction or concentrate their forces. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This object was much aided by an opinion possessed by
                    Hannibal; for although he felt assured that his brother <pb n="1145"
                        xml:id="p.1145"/> would cross over into Italy that summer, yet when he
                    recollected what difficulties he had himself experienced through a period of
                    five months, first in crossing the Rhone, then the Alps, contending against men,
                    and the nature of the ground, he was far from expecting that his transit would
                    be so easy and expeditious, <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and this was the
                    cause of his moving more slowly from his winter quarters. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But all things were done by Hasdrubal with less delay and
                    trouble than he himself or any others expected. For the Arverni, and after them
                    the other Gallic and Alpine nations in succession, not only gave him a friendly
                    reception, but followed him to the war; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and
                    not only had roads been formed during the passage of his brother in most of the
                    countries through which he marched, and which were before impassable, but also
                    as the Alps had been passable for a period of twelve years, he marched through
                    tribes of less ferocious dispositions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For
                    before that time, being never visited by foreigners, nor accustomed, themselves,
                    to see a stranger in their country, they were unsociable to the whole human
                    race. And at first, not knowing whither the Carthaginian was going, they had
                    imagined that their own rocks and forts, and the plunder of their cattle and
                    people, were his objects; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but afterwards, the
                    report of the Punic war with which Italy was being desolated for now ten years,
                    had convinced them that the Alps were only a passage, and that two very powerful
                    nations, separated from each other by a vast tract of sea and land, were
                    contending for empire and power. These were the causes which opened the Alps to
                    Hasdrubal. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But the advantage which he gained
                    by the celerity of his <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> march he lost by his
                    delay at Placentia, while he carried on a fruitless siege, rather than an
                    assault. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He had supposed that it would be
                    easy to take by storm a town situated on a plain; and the celebrity of the
                    colony induced him to believe that by destroying it he should strike great
                    terror into the rest. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This siege not only
                    impeded his own progress, but had the effect of restraining Hannibal, who was
                    just on the point of quitting his winter quarters, after hearing of his passage,
                    which was so much quicker than he expected; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    for he not only revolved in his mind how tedious was the siege of towns, but
                    also how ineffectual was his attempt upon that same colony, when returning
                    victorious from the Trebia. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, on departing from the city in
                    different <pb n="1146" xml:id="p.1146"/> directions, had drawn the attention of
                    the public, as it were, to two wars at once, while they called to mind the
                    disasters which Hannibal's first coming had brought upon Italy, and at the same
                    time, tortured with anxiety, asked themselves what deities would be so
                    propitious to the city and empire as that the commonwealth should be victorious
                    in both quarters at once. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hitherto they had
                    been enabled to hold out to the present time by compensating for their
                    misfortunes by their successes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the Roman
                    power was laid prostrate at the Trasimenus and at Cannae in Italy, their
                    successes in Spain had raised it up from its fallen condition. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Afterwards, when in Spain one disaster after another had in
                    a great measure destroyed two armies, with the loss of two distinguished
                    generals, the many successes in Italy and Sicily had, as it were, afforded a
                    haven for the shattered state; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and the mere
                    interval of space, as one war was going on in the remotest quarter of the world,
                    gave them time to recover their breath. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Whereas now two wars were received into Italy; two generals of the highest
                    renown were besetting the Roman city; while the whole weight of the danger and
                    the entire burden pressed upon one point. Whichever of these generals should be
                    first victorious, he would in a few days unite his camp with the other.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The preceding year also, saddened by the
                    deaths of two consuls, filled them with alarm. Such were the anxious feelings
                    with which the people escorted the consuls on their departure to their
                    provinces. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is recorded that Marcus Livius,
                    still teeming with resentment against his countrymen, when setting out to the
                    war, replied to Fabius, who warned him not rashly to come to an action till he
                    had made himself acquainted with the character of his enemy, that as soon as
                    ever he had got sight of the troops of the enemy he would engage them.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When asked what was his reason for such
                    haste, he said, <quote> I shall either obtain the highest glory from conquering
                        the enemy, or the greatest joy from the defeat of my countrymen, a joy which
                        they have deserved, though it would not become me. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Before the consul Claudius arrived in his
                    province, Caius Hostilius Tubulus, attacking Hannibal with his light cohorts
                    while marching his army through the extreme borders of the territory of Larinum
                    into that of Sallentum, caused terrible confusion in his unmarshalled troops;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> he killed as many as four thousand, and
                        <pb n="1147" xml:id="p.1147"/> captured nine military standards. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Quintus Claudius, who had his camps distributed
                    through the towns of the Sallentine territory, had quitted his winter quarters
                    on hearing of the enemy; and Hannibal, fearing on that account lest he should
                    have to engage with two armies at once, decamped by night, and retired from the
                    Tarentine to the Bruttian territory. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Claudius
                    turned his army to the Sallentine territory. Hostilius, on his way to Capua, met
                    the consul Claudius at Venusia. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Here forty
                    thousand infantry and two thousand five hundred horse were selected from both
                    armies, with which the consul might carry on the war against Hannibal. The rest
                    of the troops Hostilius was directed to march to Capua to deliver them over to
                    Quintus Fulvius, proconsul. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, having drawn together his forces
                    from all quarters, both those which he had in winter quarters, and those which
                    he had in the garrisons of the Bruttian territory, came to Grumentum in Lucania,
                    with the hope of regaining the towns which through fear had revolted to the
                    Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To the same place the Roman consul
                    proceeded from Venusia, exploring the way as he went, and pitched his camp about
                    fifteen hundred paces from the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    rampart of the Carthaginians seemed almost united with the walls of Grumentum,
                    though five hundred paces intervened. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Between
                    the Carthaginian and Roman camps lay a plain; and overhanging the left wing of
                    the Carthaginians and the right of the Romans were some naked hills, which were
                    not objects of suspicion to either party, as they had no wood upon them, nor any
                    hiding-places for an ambuscade. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the plain
                    which lay between them skirmishes hardly worth mentioning took place between
                    parties sallying from the outposts. It was evident that what the Roman aimed at
                    was to prevent the enemy from going off, while Hannibal, who was desirous of
                    escaping thence, came down with all his forces, and formed in order of battle.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Upon this the consul, imitating the crafty
                    character of his enemy, ordered five cohorts, with the addition of five
                    maniples, to pass the summit by night and sit down in the valleys on the
                    opposite side; a measure to which he was prompted the more strongly in
                    proportion as he felt that there could exist no suspicion of an ambuscade in
                    hills so uncovered. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of the time for rising up
                    from their retreat and of falling upon the enemy he informed Tiberius Claudius
                    Asellus, <pb n="1148" xml:id="p.1148"/> a military tribune, and Publius
                    Claudius, praefect of the allies, whom he sent with them. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The general himself, at break of day, drew out all his
                    forces, both foot and horse, for battle. Shortly after, the signal for battle
                    was given out by Hannibal, and a noise was raised in the camp, from the troops
                    running hastily to arms; then both horse and foot eagerly rushed through the
                    gates, and spreading themselves over the plain, hastened to the enemy.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul perceiving them thus
                    disordered, gave orders to Caius Aurunculeius, a military tribune of the third
                    legion, to send out the cavalry of the legion to charge the enemy with all
                    possible vehemence, for that the enemy had spread themselves <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> like cattle in such disorder throughout the whole plain,
                    that they might be knocked down and trampled under foot before they could be
                    formed. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal had not yet gone out of the camp,
                    when he heard the shout of his troops engaged; and thus roused by the alarm, he
                    hastily led his forces against the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Already had the Roman horse spread terror through the Carthaginian van; the
                    first legion also of the infantry and the right wing were commencing the action,
                    while the troops of the Carthaginians, in disorder, engaged just as chance threw
                    each in the way of horse or foot. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The battle
                    became more general by reinforcements, and the number of those who ran out to
                    the combat. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal, amid the terror and
                    confusion, would have drawn up his troops while fighting, (which would not have
                    been an easy task unless to a veteran general with veteran soldiers,) had not
                    the shouts of the cohorts and maniples, running down from the hills, which was
                    heard in their rear, created an alarm lest they should be cut off from their
                    camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After this they were seized with a
                    panic, and a flight commenced in every part; but the number slain was less,
                    because the nearness of the camp offered to the terrified troops a shorter
                    distance to fly. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the cavalry hung upon
                    their rear, and the cohorts, running down the declivities of the hills by an
                    unobstructed and easy path, charged them transversely in flank. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> However, above eight thousand men were slain, above seven
                    hundred made prisoners, and eight military standards taken. Of the elephants
                    also, which had been of no use in such a sudden and irregular action, four were
                    killed and two captured. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The conquerors lost
                    about five hundred Romans and allies. The following day the Car- <pb n="1149"
                        xml:id="p.1149"/> thaginian remained quiet. The Roman having led out his
                    troops into the field, when he saw that no one came out to meet him, gave orders
                    that the spoils of those of the enemy who were slain should be collected, and
                    that the bodies of his own men should be gathered into one place and buried.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After this, for several days following in
                    succession, he came up so near the enemy's gates that he almost seemed to be
                    carrying in his standards. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But at length
                    Hannibal at the third watch, leaving a number of fires and tents in that part of
                    the camp which faced the enemy, and also a few Numidians who might show
                    themselves in the rampart and the gates, decamped and proceeded towards Apulia.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as it dawned, the Roman army came
                    up to the trenches, and the Numidians, according to the plan concerted, took
                    care to show themselves for a little time on the rampart and in the gates; and
                    having deceived the enemy for some time, rode off at full speed, and overtook
                    their friends on their march. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The consul,
                    when all was silence in the camp, and he could now no where see even the few who
                    at break of day had walked up and down, sent two horsemen in advance to
                    reconnoitre; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and after he had ascertained
                    that all was safe enough, ordered his troops to march in; <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> and after staying there only while his men distributed
                    themselves for plunder, sounded a retreat and led back his forces long before
                    night. The next day he set out as soon as it was light, and following the rumour
                    and the track of the enemy by forced marches, came up with them not far from
                    Venusia. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Here also an irregular battle took
                    place, in which two thousand of the Carthaginians were slain. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> The Carthaginian quitting this place made for Metapontum,
                    marching by night and over mountainous districts in order to avoid a battle.
                    Thence Hanno, who commanded the garrison of that place, was sent into Bruttium
                    with a small party to raise a fresh army. Hannibal, after adding his forces to
                    his own, went back to Venusia by the same route by which he came, and proceeded
                    thence to Canusium. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Nero had never quitted
                    the enemy's steps, and when he himself went to Metapontum, had sent for Quintus
                    Fulvius into Lucania, lest that region should be left without protection. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile four Gallic horsemen and two
                    Numidians, who were sent to Hannibal with a letter from Hasdrubal, after he had
                    retired from the siege of Placentia, having <pb n="1150" xml:id="p.1150"/>
                    traversed nearly the whole length of Italy through the midst of enemies, while
                    following Hannibal as he was retiring to Metapontum, were taken to Tarentum by
                    mistaking the roads; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> where they were seized by
                    some Roman foragers, who were straggling through the fields, and brought before
                    the propraetor, Caius Claudius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first they
                    endeavoured to baffle him by evasive answers, but threats of applying torture
                    being held out to them, they were compelled to confess the truth; when they
                    fully admitted that they were the bearers of a letter from Hasdrubal to
                    Hannibal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were delivered into the custody
                    of Lucius Virginius, a military tribune, together with the letter sealed as it
                    was, to be conveyed to the consul Claudius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At
                    the same time two troops of Samnites were sent with them as an escort. Having
                    made their way to the consul, the letter was read by means of an interpreter,
                    and the captives were interrogated; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> when
                    Claudius, coming to the conclusion that the predicament of the state was not
                    such as that her generals should carry on the war, each within the limits of his
                    own province, and with his own troops, according to the customary <milestone
                        n="7??" unit="section"/> plans of warfare, and with an enemy marked out for
                    him by the senate, but that some unlooked for and unexpected enterprise must be
                    attempted, which, in its commencement, might cause no less dread among their
                    countrymen than their enemies, but which, when accomplished, might convert their
                    great fear into great joy, sent the letter of Hasdrubal to Rome to the senate;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and at the same time informed the
                    conscript fathers what his intentions were; and recommended that, as Hasdrubal
                    had written to his brother that he should meet him in Umbria, they should send
                    for the legion from Capua to Rome, enlist troops at Rome, and oppose the city
                    forces to the enemy at Narnia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such was his
                    letter to the senate. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Messengers were sent in
                    advance through the territory of Larinum, Marrucia, Frentana, and Praetutia,
                    where he was about to march his army, with orders that they should all bring
                    down from their farms and towns to the road-side provisions ready dressed for
                    the soldiers to eat; and that they should bring out horses and other beasts of
                    burden, so that those who were tired might have plenty of conveyances.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He then selected the choicest troops out
                    of the whole army of the Romans and allies, to the amount of six thousand
                    infantry and one thousand horse; and gave out that he intended to seize <pb
                        n="1151" xml:id="p.1151"/> on the nearest town in Lucania and the
                    Carthaginian garrison in it, and that they should all be in readiness to march.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Setting out by night he turned off
                    towards Picenum, and making his marches as long as possible, led his troops to
                    join his colleague, having left Quintus Catius, lieutenant-general, in command
                    of the camp. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Rome the alarm and consternation were not
                    less than they had been two years before, when the Carthaginian camp was pitched
                    over against the Roman walls and gates; nor could people make up their minds
                    whether they should commend, or censure, this so bold march of the consul.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was evident that the light in which it
                    would be viewed would depend upon its success; than which nothing can be more
                    unfair. They said, <quote> that the camp was left near to the enemy, Hannibal,
                        without a general, and with an army from which all the flower and vigour had
                        been withdrawn; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that the consul had
                        pretended an expedition into Lucania, when he was in reality going to
                        Picenum and Gaul, leaving his camp secured only by the ignorance of the
                        enemy, who were not aware that the general and part of his army were away.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What would be the consequence if that
                        should be discovered, and Hannibal should think proper either to pursue Nero
                        with his whole army, who had gone off with only six thousand armed men, or
                        to assault the camp, which was left as a prey for him, without strength,
                        without command, without auspices? </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The disasters already experienced in the war,
                    the deaths of two consuls the preceding year, augmented their fears. Besides,
                    all these events had occurred <quote> when there was only one general and one
                        army of the enemy in Italy; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> whereas now
                        they had two Punic wars, two immense armies, and in a manner two Hannibals
                        in Italy, inasmuch as Hasdrubal was descended from the same father,
                        Hamilcar, was a general equally enterprising, having been trained in a Roman
                        war during so many years in Spain, and rendered famous by a double victory,
                        having annihilated two armies with two most renowned generals. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> For he could glory even more than Hannibal
                        himself, on account of the celerity with which he had effected his passage
                        out of Spain, and his success in stirring up the Gallic nations to arms,
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> inasmuch as he had collected an army
                        in those very regions in which Hannibal lost the major part of his soldiers
                        by famine and cold, the most <pb n="1152" xml:id="p.1152"/> miserable modes
                        of death. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Those who were experienced in the events which
                    had occurred in Spain, added, that <quote> he would not have to engage with
                        Caius Nero, the general, as an unknown person, whom, when accidentally
                        caught in a difficult defile, he had eluded and baffled like a little child,
                        by drawing up fallacious terms of peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Under the dictation of fear, which always
                    puts the worst construction upon things, they magnified all the advantages which
                    the enemy possessed, and undervalued their own. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Nero had got such a distance from the
                    enemy that his plan might be disclosed without danger, he briefly addressed his
                    soldiers, observing, that <quote> there never was a measure adopted by any
                        general which was in appearance more daring than this, but in reality more
                        safe. That he was leading them on to certain victory. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> For as his colleague had not set out <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> to prosecute the war which he conducted, until forces
                        both of horse and foot had been assigned to him by the senate to his own
                        satisfaction, and those greater and better equipped than if he had been
                        going against Hannibal himself, that they would, by joining him, however
                        small the quantity of force which they might add, completely turn the scale.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That when it was only heard in the
                        field of battle (and he would take care that it should not be heard before)
                        that another consul and another army had arrived, it would insure the
                        victory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That rumour decided war; and that
                        the most inconsiderable incidents had power to excite hope and fear in the
                        mind. That they would themselves reap almost the entire glory which would be
                        obtained if they succeeded, for it was invariably the case that the last
                        addition which is made is supposed to have effected the whole. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> That they themselves saw with what multitudes,
                        what admiration, and what good wishes of men their march was attended. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And, by Hercules, they marched amid vows,
                    prayers, and commendations, all the roads being lined with ranks of men and
                    women, who had flocked there from all parts of the country. They called them the
                    safeguards of the state, the protectors of the city and empire of Rome. They
                    said that the safety and liberty of themselves and their children were treasured
                    up in their arms and right hands. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They prayed
                    to all the gods and goddesses to grant them a prosperous march, a successful
                    battle, and a speedy victory over their enemies; and that they might be <pb
                        n="1153" xml:id="p.1153"/> bound to pay the vows which they had undertaken
                    in their behalf; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> so that as now they attended
                    them off with anxiety, so after a few days' interval they might joyfully go out
                    to meet them exulting in victory. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then they
                    severally and earnestly invited them to accept, offered them, and wearied them
                    with entreaties, to take from them in preference to another, whatever might be
                    requisite for themselves or their cattle. They generously gave them every thing
                    in abundance, while the soldiers vied with each other in moderation, taking care
                    not to accept any thing beyond what was necessary for use. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They did not make any delay nor quit their ranks when
                    taking food; they continued the march day and night, scarcely giving as much to
                    rest as was necessary to the requirements of the body. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Messengers were also despatched in advance to his
                    colleague, to inform him of his approach, and to ask whether he wished that he
                    should come secretly or openly, by day or night, whether they should lodge in
                    the same or different camps. It appeared most advisable that they should come
                    into the camp secretly by night. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A private signal was sent through the camp by
                    the consul Livius, that each tribune should receive a tribune, each centurion a
                    centurion, each horseman a horseman, each foot-soldier a foot-soldier;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for it was not expedient that the camp
                    should be enlarged, lest the enemy should discover the arrival of the other
                    consul, while the crowding together of several persons, who would have their
                    tents in a confined place, would be attended with less inconvenience, because
                    the army of Claudius had brought with them on their expedition scarcely any
                    thing except their arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Claudius, on the very
                    march, had augmented his numbers by volunteers; for not only veteran soldiers,
                    who had completed their period of service, but young men also offered themselves
                    without solicitation; and, as they vied with each other in giving in their
                    names, he had enlisted those whose personal appearance and bodily strength
                    seemed fit for military service. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The camp of
                    the other consul was near Sena, and Hasdrubal's position was about five hundred
                    paces from it. Nero, therefore, when he was now drawing near, halted under cover
                    of the mountains, in order that he might not enter the camp before night.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having entered when all was still, they
                    were severally conducted into their tents by the men of their own description,
                        <pb n="1154" xml:id="p.1154"/> where they were hospitably entertained with
                    the utmost joy on the part of all. The next day a council was held, at which
                    Lucius Porcius Licinus, the praetor, was present. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He had his camp joined to that of the consuls, and before
                    their arrival, by leading, his army along the heights, sometimes occupying
                    narrow defiles that he might intercept his passage, at other times harassing his
                    troops while marching by attacking their flank or rear, he had baffled the enemy
                    by all the arts of war. This man was, on the present occasion, one of the
                    council. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Many inclined to the opinion that an
                    engagement should be deferred till Nero had recruited his soldiers, who were
                    weary with marching and watching, and had employed a few days in acquiring a
                    knowledge of his enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nero urged, not only
                    by persuasion, but with the most earnest entreaties, <quote> that they would not
                        render rash by delay that measure of his which despatch had made safe.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That Hannibal, who lay in a state of
                        torpid inactivity in consequence of a delusion which would not continue
                        long, had neither attacked his camp, left as it was without a leader, nor
                        had directed his course in pursuit of him. That the army of Hasdrubal might
                        be annihilated, and he might retire into Apulia before he stirred a step.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The man who by delay gave time to the
                        enemy both betrayed that camp to Hannibal, and opened a way to him into
                        Gaul, so that he might effect a junction with Hasdrubal at his leisure, and
                        when he pleased. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That they ought to give
                        the signal for battle instantly, and march out into the field, and take
                        advantage of the delusion of their enemies present and absent, while neither
                        those were aware that they had fewer, nor these that they had more and
                        stronger forces to encounter. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On the breaking up of the council the signal
                    for battle was displayed, and the troops immediately led into the field. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians were already standing before
                    their camp in battle-array. This circumstance delayed the battle: Hasdrubal, who
                    had advanced before the line with a few horsemen, remarked some old shields
                    among the enemy, which he had not seen before, and some horses leaner than the
                    rest; their numbers also appeared greater than usual. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Suspecting, therefore, what was really the case, he hastily
                    sounded a retreat, and sent a party to the river from which they got their
                    water, where some of them might be intercepted, and notice taken whether there
                    were perchance any there whose com- <pb n="1155" xml:id="p.1155"/> plexions were
                    more than ordinarily sun-burnt, as from a recent march. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time he ordered a party to ride round the camp
                    at a distance, and note whether the rampart was extended in any part, and also
                    observe whether the signal sounded once or twice. Having received a report of
                    all these particulars, the fact of the camp's not being enlarged led him into
                    error. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There were now two camps, as there were
                    before the other consul arrived, one belonging to Marcus Livius, the other to
                    Lucius Porcius, and to neither of them had any addition been made to give more
                    room for the tents. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the veteran general,
                    who was accustomed to a Roman enemy, was much struck by their reporting that the
                    signal sounded once in the praetor's camp, and twice in the consul's; there must
                    therefore be two consuls, and felt the most painful anxiety as to the manner in
                    which the other had got away from Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Least of all could he suspect, what was really the case, that he had got away
                    from Hannibal by deceiving him to such an extent, as that he knew not where the
                    general was, and where the army whose camp stood opposite to his own. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Surely, he concluded, deterred by a defeat of no
                    ordinary kind, he has not dared to pursue him; and he began to entertain the
                    most serious fears that he had himself come too late with assistance, now that
                    affairs were desperate, and lest the same good fortune attended the Roman arms
                    in Italy which they had experienced in Spain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes he imagined that his letter could not have reached him, and that, it
                    having been intercepted, the consul had hastened to overpower him. Thus anxious
                    and perplexed, having put out the fires, he issued a signal at the first watch
                    to collect the baggage in silence, and gave orders to march. In the hurry and
                    confusion occasioned by a march by night, their guides were not watched with
                    sufficient care and attention. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> One of them
                    stopped in a lace of concealment which he had beforehand fixed upon in hi mind,
                    the other swam across the river Metaurus, at a ford with which he was
                    acquainted. The troops, thus deserted by their guides, at first wandered up and
                    down through the fields; and some of them, overpowered with sleep, and fatigued
                    with watching, stretched themselves on the ground here and there, leaving their
                    standards thinly attended. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal gave
                    orders to march along the bank of the river until the light should discover the
                    road; but, pursuing a circuitous and un- <pb n="1156" xml:id="p.1156"/> certain
                    course along the turnings and windings of that tortuous river, with the
                    intention of crossing it as soon as the first light should discover a place
                    convenient for the purpose, he made but little progress; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> but wasting the day in a fruitless attempt to discover a
                    ford, for the further he went from the sea the higher he found the banks which
                    kept the river in its course, he gave the enemy time to overtake him. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> First Nero arrived with the whole body of his
                    cavalry; then Porcius came up with him, with the light infantry. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And while these were harassing his weary troops on
                    every side, and charging them, and the Carthaginian, stopping his march, which
                    resembled a flight, was desirous of encamping on an eminence, on the bank of the
                    river, Livius came up with all his <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> foot
                    forces, not after the manner of troops on march, but armed and marshalled for
                    immediate action. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When they had united all
                    their forces, and the line was drawn out, Claudius took the direction of the
                    battle in the right wing, Livius in the left; the management of the centre was
                    given to the praetor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, when he saw
                    that an engagement was inevitable, giving over the fortification of a camp,
                    placed his elephants in the front line, before the standards; on either side
                    these he placed in the left wing the Gauls to oppose Claudius, not so much from
                    any confidence he reposed in them, as because he believed them to be dreaded by
                    the enemy; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the right wing he took to himself
                    against M. Livius, together with the Spaniards, in whom, as being veteran
                    troops, he placed his greatest hopes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Behind
                    the elephants, in the centre, the Ligurians were posted; but his line was rather
                    long than deep. The Gauls were covered by a hill, which extended in front.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That part of the line which was occupied
                    by the Spaniards, engaged the left wing of the Romans, the whole of whose right
                    wing, extending beyond the line of battle, was unengaged. The hill before them
                    prevented their making an attack either in front or flank. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Between Livius and Hasdrubal a furious contest arose, and
                    the slaughter on both sides was dreadful. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Here were both the generals, here the major part of the Roman horse and
                    infantry, here the Spaniards, veteran troops, and experienced in the Roman
                    manner of fighting, and the Ligurians, a nation inured to war. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The elephants were also driven to the same part, which, on
                    the first onset, disordered the van, and had now <pb n="1157" xml:id="p.1157"/>
                    even dislodged the standards; but afterwards, the contest growing hotter, and
                    the shout increasing, they became less submissive to their riders, and ranged to
                    and fro between the two lines, as if not knowing to which side they belonged,
                    like ships floating about without rudders. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Claudius, when he had striven in vain to advance up the hill, repeatedly calling
                    out to his soldiers, <quote>To what purpose then have we performed so long a
                        march with such expedition?</quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> when he found it impossible to make his way
                    to the enemy in that quarter, withdrawing several cohorts from the right wing,
                    where he saw they would occupy an inactive station, rather than join in the
                    fight, led them round the rear of the line, and, to the surprise not only of the
                    enemy but his own party, charged their right flank; <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> and such was their rapidity, that after showing themselves
                    on their flank, they almost immediately made an attack on their rear. Thus on
                    all sides, in front, flank, and rear, the Spaniards and Ligurians were cut to
                    pieces; and now the carnage had even reached the Gauls. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Here the least opposition was found; for a great number
                        <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> of them had quitted their standards,
                    having slunk off during the night, and laid themselves down to sleep up and down
                    the fields, while even those who were present, being tired with marching and
                    watching, for their bodies are most intolerant of fatigue, could scarcely carry
                    their arms upon their shoulders. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> And now it
                    was midday, and thirst and heat gave them over to the enemy to be killed or
                    captured in multitudes. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> More elephants were killed by their guides
                    than by the enemy. They used to have with them a workman's knife, with a mallet.
                    When these beasts began to grow furious, and attack their own party, the rider,
                    placing this knife between the ears, just on the joint by which the neck is
                    connected with the head, used to drive it in, striking it with all the force he
                    could. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was found to be the most
                    expeditious mode of putting these bulky animals to death, when they had
                    destroyed all hope of governing them. This method was first practised by
                    Hasdrubal, a general whose conduct both frequently on other occasions, and
                    especially in this battle, deserved to be recorded. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> By encouraging the men when fighting, and sharing equally
                    in every danger, he kept up the battle. Sometimes by entreating, at other times
                    by rebuking, the troops, when tired and indisposed to fight from <pb n="1158"
                        xml:id="p.1158"/> weariness and over-exertion, he rekindled their spirits.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He called back the flying, and restored
                    the battle in many places when it had been given up. At length, when fortune
                    decidedly declared for the Romans, lest he should survive so great an army which
                    had been collected under the influence of his name, he put spurs to his horse
                    and rushed upon a Roman cohort, where he fell fighting, as was worthy of the son
                    of Hamilcar and the brother of Hannibal. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At no
                    time during that war were so many of the enemy slain in one battle; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> so that a defeat equal to that sustained at Cannae,
                    whether in respect of the loss of the general or the troops, was considered to
                    have been retorted upon him. Fifty-six thousand of the enemy were slain, five
                    thousand four hundred captured. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The other
                    booty was great, both of every other kind, and also of gold and silver. In
                    addition to the rest, there were recovered above four thousand Roman citizens,
                    who had been taken by the enemy, which formed some consolation for the soldiers
                    lost in that battle. For the victory was by no means bloodless. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Much about eight thousand of the Romans and the allies were
                    slain; and so completely were even the victors satiated with blood and
                    slaughter, that the next day, when Livius the consul received intelligence that
                    the Cisalpine Gauls and Ligurians, who had either not been present at the battle
                    or had made their escape from the carnage, were marching off in one body without
                    a certain leader, without standards, without any discipline or subordination;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that if one squadron of horse were sent
                    against them they might be all destroyed, he replied, <quote>Let some survive to
                        bear the news of the enemy's losses and of our valour.</quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nero set out on the night following the
                    battle, and marching at a more rapid rate than when he came, arrived at his camp
                    before the enemy on the sixth day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As he was
                    not preceded by a messenger, fewer people attended him on his march; but the joy
                    felt was so great, that they were almost insane with delight. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Neither state of feeling at Rome can be well described or
                    told, whether that in which the citizens were when in doubtful expectation of
                    the issue, or when they received the intelligence of victory. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Every day, from the time that news arrived that the consul
                    Claudius had set out, from sunrise to sunset, none of the senators ever quitted
                    the senate-house, or did the people depart from the forum. The <pb n="1159"
                        xml:id="p.1159"/> matrons, as they had themselves no means of affording
                    assistance, had recourse to prayers and entreaties, and going about to all the
                    temples, wearied the gods with vows and supplications. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> While the city was in this state of solicitude and
                    suspense, a vague report first arrived that two Narnian horsemen had come from
                    the field of battle into the camp which stood as a defence in the entrance to
                    Umbria, with intelligence that the enemy were cut to pieces. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At first they rather heard than credited this news, as
                    being too great and too joyful for the mind to take in, or obtain a firm belief.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Even the very rapidity with which it had
                    arrived formed an obstacle to its reception; for it was stated that the battle
                    took place two days before. After this a letter was brought which had been sent
                    by Lucius Manlius Acidinus, from his camp, on the subject of the arrival of the
                    Narnian horsemen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This letter being conveyed
                    through the forum to the tribunal of the praetor, drew the senators out of the
                    senate-house; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and with such eagerness and
                    hurry did the people crowd to the doors of the senate-house, that the messenger
                    could not approach, but was dragged off by persons who asked him questions, and
                    demanded vociferously that the letter should be read on the rostrum before it
                    was read in the senate. At length they were put back and restrained by the
                    magistrates; and thus the joy was gradually dispensed to their overpowered
                    spirits. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The letter was read first in the
                    senate, and then in the assembly of the people. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> The effect was various, according to the difference in the cast of men's
                    minds, some thinking that there were already sure grounds for rejoicing, while
                    others would place no confidence in the news, till they listened to ambassadors,
                    or a letter from the consuls. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this, news came that the ambassadors
                    themselves were on the point of arriving. Then, indeed, people of all ages ran
                    to meet them, each man being eager to be the first to <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> receive an assurance of such joyful tidings, by the
                    evidence of his eyes and ears. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> One continued
                    train extended as far as the Mulvian bridge. The ambassadors, Lucius Veturius
                    Philo, Publius Licinius Varus, and Quintus Caecilius Metellus, made their way
                    into the forum, surrounded by a crowd of persons of every description; when some
                    asked the ambassadors them-selves, others their attendants, what had been done;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and, as <pb n="1160" xml:id="p.1160"/>
                    soon as each had heard that the army and general of the enemy had been cut off,
                    that the Roman legions were safe, and the consuls unhurt, he immediately
                    imparted the joyful intelligence to others, imparting to them the joy he felt
                    himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having with difficulty made their way
                    into the senate-house, and the crowd with still more difficulty being removed,
                    that they might not mix with the fathers, the letter was read in the senate;
                    after which the ambassadors were brought into the general assembly. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Lucius Veturius Philo, after reading the letter
                    himself, gave a more explicit account of all that had occurred, amidst great
                    approbation, and at last of general shouting from the assembly, while their
                    minds could scarcely contain their joy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They
                    then ran off in various directions, some to the different temples of the gods,
                    to return thanks, others to their homes, to impart the joyful intelligence to
                    their wives and children. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The senate decreed a
                    supplication for three days, because Marcus Livius and Caius Claudius, the
                    consuls, had cut off the general and legions of the enemy, their own army being
                    safe. This supplication Caius Hostilius, the praetor, proclaimed in the
                    assembly, and was celebrated both by men and women. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> During the whole three days all the temples were uniformly
                    crowded, whilst the matrons, dressed in their richest robes, and accompanied by
                    their children, just as though the war had been brought to a conclusion, and
                    free from every apprehension, offered thanksgivings to the immortal gods.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This victory produced an alteration also
                    in the condition of the state, so that immediately from this event, just as
                    though it had been a time of peace, men were not afraid to do business with each
                    other, buying, selling, lending, and paying borrowed money. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Caius Claudius, the consul, on his return to his camp,
                    ordered the head of Hasdrubal, which he had carefully kept and brought with him,
                    to be thrown before the advanced guards of the enemy, and the African prisoners
                    to be shown to them bound just as they were. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Two of these also he unbound, and bid them go to Hannibal and tell him what had
                    occurred. Hannibal, smitten by such severe distress, at once public and
                    domestic, is said to have declared that he recognised the destiny of Carthage;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and decamping thence with the intention
                    of drawing together into Bruttium, the remotest corner of Italy, all his <pb
                        n="1161" xml:id="p.1161"/> auxiliaries which he could not protect when
                    widely scattered, removed into Bruttium the whole state of the Metapontines,
                    summoned away from their former habitations, and also such of the Lucanians as
                    were under his authority. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
