<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab urbe condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 8-10 - 19s</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books VIII-X With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1926: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19s" type="book">
                <head>Summary of Book XIX</head>
                <p> CAECILIUS METELLUS, after a prosperous campaign against the Carthaginians,
                    triumphed brilliantly, having thirteen of the enemy's generals and a hundred and
                    twenty elephants in his procession. <name>The</name> consul Claudius Pulcher
                    having set out in opposition to the auspices—he ordered the chickens to be
                    drowned, when they would not feed <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        According to Cicero, <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>de</reg> Natura Deoreum, </hi> ii. 7, Claudius had the fowls thrown
                        into water, <quote>that they might drink, since they would not eat.</quote>
                    </note> —fought an unsuccessful naval engagement with the Carthaginians, and on
                    being recalled by the senate and directed to name a dictator, named Claudius
                    Glicia, a man of the basest sort, who afterwards, when he had been forced to
                    abdicate the office, witnessed the games in his purple—bordered toga.
                        <name>Aulus</name> Atilius Calatinus was the first dictator to lead an army
                    out of Italy. <name>An</name>
                    <pb n="p.559"/> exchange of prisoners with the Carthaginians was effected.
                        <reg>colonies</reg> were founded at Fregenae <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Near the coast about due W. of Rome.</note> and in the
                    Sallentine country at Brundisium. <name>The</name> lustrum was closed by the
                    censors. 241,212 citizens were registered. <reg>claudia</reg> , the sister of
                    Publius Claudius, who had been defeated after making light of the auspices,
                    being jostled by the crowd while returning from the games, exclaimed, <quote>
                        <reg>o</reg> that my brother were alive to command another fleet! </quote>
                    <reg>for</reg> this she was fined. <reg>then</reg> for the first time two
                    praetors were elected. <name>Caecilius</name> Metellus, the pontifex maximus,
                    kept Aulus Postumius, the consul, in the City, since he was also the flamen of
                    Mars, when he desired to go forth to war, nor would he suffer him to forsake his
                    sacred functions. <reg>after</reg> a number of generals had gained successes
                    against the Carthaginians, Gaius Lutatius crowned the victory by defeating the
                    Carthaginian fleet off the Aegatian Islands. <name>The</name> Carthaginians sued
                    for peace and it was granted them. <reg>when</reg> the temple of Vesta was
                    burning, Caecilius Metellus, the pontifex maximus, rescued the sacred objects
                    from the flames. <reg>two</reg> tribes were added, the Velina and the Quirina.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
