<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 26</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="book">
                <head>The Fate of Capua</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The new consuls, Cn, Fulvius Centimalus
                        and P. Sulpicius Galba, entered upon office on the 15th of March, and at
                        once convened a meeting of the senate in the Capitol to discuss questions of
                        State, the conduct of the war and the distribution of the provinces and the
                        armies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The retiring consuls-Q. Fulvius
                        and Appius Claudius-retained their commands and were instructed to prosecute
                        the siege of Capua unremittingly until they had effected its capture. The
                        recovery of this city was the main concern of the Romans now. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> What determined them was not only the bitter
                        resentment which its defection had evoked, a feeling which <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> was never more justified in the case of any
                        city, but also the certainty they felt that, as in its revolt it had drawn
                        many communities with it, owing to its greatness and strength, so its
                        recapture would create amongst these communities a feeling of respect for
                        the power whose sovereignty they had formerly acknowledged. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The praetors of the past year, M. Junius in Etruria and
                        P. Sempronius in Gaul, had their commands extended and were each to retain
                        the two legions they had. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> M. Marcellus was
                        to act as proconsul and finish the war in Sicily with the army which he had.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If he needed reinforcements he was to
                        take them from the troops which P. Cornelius was commanding in Sicily, but
                        none were to be selected from those who had been forbidden by the <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> senate to take a furlough or return home before
                        the end of the war. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The province of Sicily
                        was assigned to C. Sulpicius, and he was to take over the two legions which
                        were with P. Cornelius; any reinforcements he needed were to be supplied
                        from the army of Cn. Fulvius which had been so disgracefully routed and cut
                        up the previous year in Apulia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        soldiers who had so disgraced themselves were placed under the same
                        conditions with regard to length of service as the survivors of Cannae. As
                        an additional brand of ignominy the men of both these armies were forbidden
                        to winter in towns or to construct winter quarters for themselves within ten
                        miles of any town. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The two legions which
                        Q. Mucius had commanded in Sardinia were given to L. Cornelius, and any
                        additional force he might require was to be raised by the consuls.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> T. Otacilius and M. Valerius were
                        ordered to cruise off the coasts of Sicily and Greece respectively with the
                        fleets and soldiers they had previously commanded. The former had a hundred
                        ships with two legions on board; the latter, fifty ships and one legion.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The total strength of the Roman
                        armies engaged on land and sea this year amounted to twenty-five legions.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .At the beginning of the year a despatch
                        from L. Marcius was laid before the senate. The senators fully appreciated
                        the successful way in which he had conducted his operations, but a good many
                        of them were indignant at the honorific title he had assumed. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The superscription of the letter was "The
                        propraetor to the senate," though the imperium had not been conferred upon
                        him by an order of the people nor with the sanction of the senate. An evil
                        precedent had been set, they said, when a commander was chosen by his army,
                        and the solemn procedure at elections, after the auspices were duly taken,
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> was transferred to camps and
                        provinces far away from the magistrates and the laws, and left to the
                        caprice of the soldiers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some thought the
                        senate ought to take the matter up, but it was thought better to adjourn the
                        consideration of it until the horsemen who had brought the despatch had left
                        the City. With regard to the food and clothing of the army, they ordered a
                        reply to be sent to the effect that both these matters would be attended to
                        by the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They refused, however, to
                        allow the despatch to be addressed "To the propraetor L. Marcius," lest it
                        should appear that the question which was to be discussed had been
                        prejudged. After the messengers had been dismissed the consuls gave this
                        question priority over everything else, and it was unanimously agreed that
                        the tribunes should consult the plebs as soon as possible as to whom they
                        wished to have sent <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> to Spain with the
                        imperium as commander-in-chief to take over the army which Cn. Scipio had
                        commanded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The tribunes undertook to do
                        so, and due notice of the question was given to the Assembly. But the
                        citizens were preoccupied with a controversy of a very different nature. C.
                        Sempronius Blaesus had fixed a day for bringing Cn. Fulvius to trial for
                        losing his army in Apulia, and made a very bitter attack upon him beforehand
                        in the Assembly. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "Many commanders," he
                        said, "have through rashness and inexperience led their armies into most
                        dangerous positions, but Cn. Fulvius is the only one who has demoralised his
                        army by every form of vice before betraying them. They may with perfect
                        truth be said to have been destroyed before they saw the enemy; they owed
                        their defeat to their own commander, not to Hannibal. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "Now no man, when he is going to vote,
                        takes sufficient trouble to find out what sort of a man it is to whom he is
                        entrusting the supreme command of the army. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> Think of the difference between Tiberius Sempronius and Cn. Fulvius.
                        Tiberius Sempronius had an army of slaves given to him, but in a short time,
                        thanks to the discipline he maintained and the wise use he made of his
                        authority, there was not a man amongst them who when he was in the field of
                        battle gave a thought to his birth or his condition. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Those men were a protection to our allies and a terror
                        to our enemies. They snatched, as though from the very jaws of Hannibal,
                        cities like Cumae and Beneventum and restored them to Rome. Cn. Fulvius, on
                        the other hand, had an army of Roman citizens, born of respectable parents,
                        brought up as free men, and he infected them with the vices of slaves, and
                        made them such that they were <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> insolent
                        and riotous amongst our allies, weaklings and cowards in face of the enemy;
                        they could not stand even the war-cry of the Carthaginians, let alone their
                        charge. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Good heavens! no wonder the
                        soldiers gave ground, when their commander was the first to run away; the
                        wonder is that any stood their ground and fell, and that all did not
                        accompany Cn. Fulvius in his panic and flight. C. Flaminius, L. Paulus, L.
                        Postumius, and the two Scipios, Cnaeus and Publius, all chose to fall in
                        battle rather than desert their armies, when they were hemmed in by the foe.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Cn. Fulvius came back to Rome as the
                        all-but solitary herald of the annihilation of his army. After the army had
                        fled from the field of Cannae it was deported to Sicily, not to return till
                        the enemy had evacuated Italy, and a similar decree was recently passed in
                        the case of Fulvius' legions. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> But, shame
                        to relate, the commander himself remained unpunished after his flight from a
                        battle brought on by his own headstrong folly; he is free to pass the rest
                        of his life where he passed it in youth-in stews and brothels-whilst his
                        soldiers, whose only fault is that they copied their commander, are
                        practically sent into exile and have to undergo a service of disgrace.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> So unequal are the liberties enjoyed
                        in Rome by the rich and the poor, the men of rank and the men of the
                        people." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In his defence Fulvius threw all the blame
                        upon his men. They clamoured, he said, for battle, and he led them out, not
                        at the moment, for it was late in the day, but on the following morning.
                        Though they were drawn up on favourable ground, at an early hour they found
                        either the terror of the enemy's name or the strength of his attack too much
                        for them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they were all flying in
                        disorder he was swept away by the rush as Varro was at Cannae and as many
                        other commanders have been at different times. What help would he have given
                        to the republic by staying there alone? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        unless indeed his death would have warded off other national disasters. His
                        failure was not due to lack of supplies, or to incautiously taking up a
                        position on unfavourable ground; he had not been ambushed through
                        insufficient reconnoitring; he had been beaten in a fair fight on an open
                        field. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Men's tempers, on whichever side
                        they were, were beyond his control, a man's natural disposition made him
                        either brave or cowardly. The speeches of the prosecutor and the defendant
                        occupied two days, on the third day the witnesses were produced. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Besides all the other serious charges brought
                        against him, a great many men stated on oath that the panic and flight began
                        with the praetor, and that when the soldiers found that they were left to
                        themselves, and thought that their commander had good ground for fear, they
                        too turned their backs and fled. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        prosecutor had in the first instance asked for a fine, but the evidence
                        which had been given roused the anger of the people to such an extent that
                        they insisted upon a capital charge being laid. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> This led to a fresh contest. As the prosecutor during
                        the first two days had limited the penalty to a fine and only on the third
                        day made the charge a capital one, the defendant appealed to the other
                        tribunes, but they refused to interfere with their colleague. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> It was open to him by ancient custom to proceed
                        either by statute law or by customary precedent, whichever he preferred,
                        until he had obtained judgment, whether the penalty were a capital or a
                        pecuniary one. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On this Sempronius
                        announced that he should prosecute C. Fulvius on the charge of treason and
                        requested the City praetor to convene the Assembly for the purpose on the
                        appointed day. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then the accused tried
                        another way of escape. His brother Quintus was in high favour with the
                        people at the time, owing to his former successes and the general conviction
                        that he would soon take Capua, and the defendant hoped that he might be
                        present at his trial. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Quintus wrote to
                        the senate for their permission, appealing to their compassion and begging
                        to be allowed to defend his brother's life, but they told him in reply that
                        it would militate against the interests of the State for him to leave Capua.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Just before the day of trial Cn.
                        Fulvius went into exile at Tarquinii. The plebs affirmed by resolution his
                        legal status as exile and all the consequences it involved. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the whole stress of the war bore
                        on Capua. The blockade was proving more effective than direct assault; the
                        common people and the slaves could not endure the famine, nor could they
                        send messengers to Hannibal owing to the strict watch which was kept.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At last a Numidian was found who
                        promised to get through with the despatches, and he succeeded. He escaped
                        through the Roman lines by night, and this encouraged the Capuans to attempt
                        sorties in all directions while they still had some strength left.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Numerous cavalry encounters took place
                        in which they generally had the advantage, but their infantry got the worst
                        of it. The gratification which the Romans derived from their infantry
                        successes was considerably damped by their finding themselves beaten in any
                        arm by an enemy whom they had invested and almost conquered. At length they
                        devised a clever plan by which they could make up for their inferiority in
                        the mounted arm. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Young men of exceptional
                        speed and agility were selected from all the legions and supplied with
                        bucklers somewhat shorter than those used by the cavalry. Each was furnished
                        with seven javelins, four feet long and tipped with iron heads similar to
                        those on the darts of the velites. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        troopers each took one of these upon his horse and trained them to ride
                        behind and leap down briskly at a given signal. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as their daily training had given them
                        sufficient confidence, the cavalry advanced against the Capuans, who were
                        drawn up on the level ground between the Roman camp and the city walls.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as they came within range the
                        signal was given and the velites sprang down to the ground. The line of
                        infantry thus formed made a sudden attack on the Capuan horse; shower after
                        shower of javelins was flung at the men and horses all along the line.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A great many were wounded, and the
                        novel and unexpected form of attack created widespread consternation. Seeing
                        the enemy shaken the Roman cavalry charged home, and in the rout that
                        followed they drove them with much loss right up to their gates. From that
                        time the Romans had the superiority in their cavalry also. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The velites were subsequently incorporated in the
                        legions. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This plan of combining infantry
                        and cavalry in one force is said to have originated with one of the
                        centurions-Q. Navius, and he received special honour from his commander in
                        consequence. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the position of affairs at Capua.
                        During this time Hannibal was drawn in two directions; he was anxious to get
                        possession of the citadel of Tarentum and he was equally anxious to retain
                        his hold on Capua. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Regard for Capua
                        however carried the day, for he saw that it was the spot to which all eyes
                        were turned, of friends and foes alike, and its fate would show
                        conclusively, one way or the other, the consequences of defection from Rome.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Leaving therefore his baggage and
                        heavy-armed troops in Bruttium, he hurried into Campania with a force of
                        horse and foot selected for their capacity for rapid marching. Swift as his
                        advance was, however, three and thirty elephants followed him. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> He took up his position in a secluded valley at
                        the back of Mount Tifata which overlooked Capua. On his march he captured
                        the fortified post of Calatia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then
                        turned his attention to the besiegers of Capua, and sent a message to the
                        city telling them at what time he intended to attack the Roman lines, so
                        that they might be ready to make a sortie and pour in full strength out of
                        all their gates. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The investing force was
                        thrown into a state of great alarm, for while Hannibal was delivering his
                        assault on one side, the whole of the forces of Capua, mounted and
                        unmounted, supported by the Punic garrison under Bostar and Hanno were
                        making a vigorous sortie on the other. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Realising their critical position and the danger of leaving a portion of
                        their lines unprotected by concentrating their defence in any one direction,
                        the Romans divided their force; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Appius
                        Claudius confronted the Capuans, Fulvius was opposed to Hannibal; the
                        propraetor C. Nero with the cavalry of the six legions held the road to
                        Suessula, and C. Fulvius Flaccus with the cavalry of the allies took up a
                        position towards the Volturnus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There was
                        not only the usual shouting and uproar when the battle commenced; the din of
                        horses and men and arms was aggravated by the non-combatant population of
                        Capua. They crowded on to the walls, and by clashing brazen vessels
                        together, as people do in the dead of the night when there is an eclipse of
                        the moon, they made such a dreadful noise that it even distracted the
                        attention of the combatants. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Appius had no difficulty in driving the
                        Capuans from his earthworks, but Fulvius had to meet a much heavier attack
                        from Hannibal and his Carthaginians on the other side. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Here the sixth legion gave way and a cohort of
                        Spaniards with three elephants succeeded in getting up to the breastwork.
                        They had penetrated the Roman line, and whilst they saw their chance of
                        breaking through into the camp they saw also the danger of being cut off
                        from their supports. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When Fulvius saw the
                        disorder of the legion and the danger which threatened the camp, he called
                        upon Q. Navius and other centurions of the first rank to charge the enemy's
                        cohort which was fighting just under the breastwork. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> "It is a most critical moment," he told them; "either
                        you must allow the enemy to go on, in which case they will break into the
                        camp with less difficulty than they found in breaking through the closed
                        ranks of the legion, or you must dispose of them whilst they are still below
                        the breastwork. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> It will not be a hard
                        fight; they are a small body, cut off from their support; and the very fact
                        of the Roman line being broken will be an advantage if both sections close
                        on the enemy's flanks, who would then be hemmed and exposed to a double
                        attack." <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> On hearing this Navius took the
                        standard of the second maniple of hastati from the bearer and advanced with
                        it against the enemy, threatening at the same time to throw it into their
                        midst if his men did not promptly follow him and take their share in the
                        fighting. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He was a huge man and his
                        armour set him off, and as he lifted the standard high in the air, he
                        attracted all eyes. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But when he was close
                        to the Spaniards they hurled their javelins at him from all sides, and
                        almost the whole of their line turned their attention to this one man.
                        Neither the number of the enemy, however, nor the force of their missiles
                        were able to check the gallant fellow's onset. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Atilius now brought up the leading
                        maniple of the sixth legion against the Spanish cohort; L. Porcius Licinius
                        and T. Popilius, who were in command of the camp, were keeping up a fierce
                        struggle in front of the breastwork, and killed some of the elephants whilst
                        they were actually clambering over it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Their bodies rolled down into the fosse and filled it up, making a bridge
                        for the passage of the enemy, and a terrible carnage began over the
                        prostrate elephants. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the other side of
                        the camp the Capuans and their Punic garrison had by this time been
                        repulsed, and the fighting went on right up to the city gate which leads to
                        the Volturnus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The efforts of the Romans
                        to break in were frustrated not so much by the arms of the defenders as by
                        the ballistae and scorpions which were mounted over the gate and kept the
                        assailants at a distance by the missiles they discharged. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> A further check was given them by a wound received by
                        Appius Claudius; he was struck by a heavy javelin in the upper part of the
                        chest under the left shoulder, whilst he was riding along the front
                        encouraging his men. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A great many of the
                        enemy were however killed outside the gate; the rest were driven in hasty
                        flight into the city. When Hannibal saw the destruction of his Spanish
                        cohort and the energy with which the Romans were defending their lines, he
                        gave up the attack and recalled the standards. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The retiring column of infantry was followed by the
                        cavalry who were to protect the rear in case the enemy harassed their
                        retreat. The legions were burning to pursue them, but Fulvius ordered the
                        "retire" to be sounded, as he considered that he had gained quite enough in
                        making both the Capuans and Hannibal himself realise how little he could do
                        in their defence. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Some authors who describe this battle say
                        that 8000 of Hannibal's men were killed that day and 3000 Capuans, and that
                        15 standards were taken from the Carthaginians and 18 from the Capuans.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In other accounts I find that the
                        affair was nothing like so serious, there was more excitement and confusion
                        than actual fighting. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> According to these
                        writers the Numidians and Spaniards broke unexpectedly into the Roman lines
                        with the elephants, and these animals, trotting all over the camp, upset the
                        tents and created terrible uproar and panic during which the baggage animals
                        broke their tethers and bolted. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To add to
                        the confusion Hannibal sent some men got up as Italians, who could speak
                        Latin, to tell the defenders in the name of the consul that as the camp was
                        lost each man must do his best to escape to the nearest mountains.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The trick was, however, soon detected
                        and frustrated with heavy loss to the enemy, and the elephants were driven
                        out of the camp with firebrands. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In any
                        case, however it began or ended, this was the last battle fought before
                        Capua surrendered. The "medix tuticus," the supreme magistrate of Capua,
                        happened for that year to be Seppius Loesius, a man of humble birth and
                        slender fortune. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The story goes that
                        owing to a portent which had occurred in his mother's household she
                        consulted a soothsayer on behalf of her little boy, and he told her that the
                        highest official position in Capua would come to her son. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> As she was not aware of anything which would justify
                        such expectations she replied, "You are indeed describing a desperate state
                        of things in Capua when you say that such an honour will come to my son."
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Her jesting reply to what was a true
                        prediction turned out itself to be true, for it was only when famine and
                        sword were pressing them sorely and all hope of further resistance was
                        disappearing that Loesius accepted the post. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> He was the last Capuan to hold it, and he only did so
                        under protest; Capua, he declared, was abandoned and betrayed by all her
                        foremost citizens. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Finding that his enemy could not be drawn
                        into an engagement and that it was impossible to break through their lines
                        and relieve Capua, Hannibal decided to abandon his attempt and <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> march away from the place, for he was afraid of
                        being cut off from his supplies by the new consuls. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He was anxiously turning over in his mind the question
                        of his future movements when the idea occurred to him of marching upon Rome,
                        the head and guiding spirit of the whole war. He had always set his heart
                        upon this, and men blamed him for letting the opportunity slip, immediately
                        after the battle of Cannae; he himself admitted that he had made a mistake
                        in not doing so. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He was not without hope
                        of seizing some part of the City in the confusion caused by his unexpected
                        appearance, and if Rome were in danger, he expected that both the consuls-or
                        at all events, one of them-would at once quit their hold on Capua.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then, as they would be weakened by
                        their forces being divided, they would give either him or the Capuans the
                        opportunity of fighting a successful action. One thing made him anxious, the
                        possibility of the Capuans surrendering as soon as he had withdrawn.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Amongst his men there was a Numidian
                        who was ready for any desperate enterprise, and he induced this man, by the
                        offer of a reward, to carry a despatch and enter the Roman lines in the
                        guise of a deserter, then steal away on the opposite side and enter Capua.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He wrote in a very encouraging strain,
                        and pointed out that his departure would be the means of saving them, as it
                        would draw off the Roman generals from their attack on Capua to defend Rome.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were not to be despondent, a few
                        days' patience would completely break up the siege. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He then ordered the boats which were on the Volturnus
                        to be seized and brought up to a fort which he had previously constructed to
                        secure the passage of the river. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He was
                        informed that there was a sufficient number of them to admit of his entire
                        army being taken across in one night. Ten days' rations were supplied to the
                        men; they marched down to the river, and all his legions were across before
                        day-break. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fulvius Flaccus was informed by deserters
                        of this project before it was put into execution, and at once sent
                        intelligence of it to the senate. The news was received with varying
                        feelings as men's temperaments differed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Naturally, at such a crisis, a meeting of the senate was instantly convened.
                        Publius Cornelius Asina was for recalling all the generals and armies from
                        every part of Italy for the defence of the City, regardless of Capua or any
                        other object they had in view. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fabius
                        Maximus considered that it would be a disgrace for them to quit their hold
                        on Capua and allow themselves to be scared by Hannibal and marched up and
                        down at his beck and menaces. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "Do you
                        suppose," he asked the senators, "that the man who did not venture to
                        approach the City after his victory at Cannae, really hopes to capture it
                        now that he has been driven away from Capua? <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> His object in coming here is not to attack Rome but to raise the siege of
                        Capua. The army which is now in the City will be sufficient for our defence,
                        for it will be aided by Jupiter and the other gods who have witnessed
                        Hannibal's violation of treaty engagements." <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> P. Valerius Flaccus advocated a middle course, which was ultimately
                        adopted. He recommended that a despatch should be sent to the generals
                        commanding at Capua, telling them what defensive force the City possessed.
                        They themselves would know what troops Hannibal was bringing and how large
                        an army was required to maintain the siege of Capua. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> If one of the generals commanding could be sent with a
                        part of the army to Rome without interfering with the effective conduct of
                        the siege by the other general, Claudius and Fulvius might arrange
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> which of them should continue the
                        investment of Capua and which should go to Rome to prevent their own city
                        from being invested. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When this decision of
                        the senate reached Capua, the proconsul Q. Fulvius, whose colleague had been
                        obliged to leave for Rome owing to his wound, selected a force out of the
                        three armies and crossed the Volturnus with 15,000 infantry and 1000
                        cavalry. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When he had definitely
                        ascertained that Hannibal was advancing by the Latin Road, he sent men on in
                        advance through the burghs situated on the Appian Way and also to some lying
                        near it, to warn the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> inhabitants to
                        have supplies stored in readiness in their towns and to bring them in from
                        the outlying fields to the line of march. They were further to call in their
                        fighting men to defend their homes, and each municipality was to provide for
                        its own protection. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After crossing the Volturnus Hannibal
                        fixed his camp a short distance from the river, and the next day he marched
                        past Cales into the Sidicine territory. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        One day was devoted to laying waste the district, and then he proceeded
                        along the Latin Road through the lands of Suessa, Allifae, and Casinum up to
                        the walls of the last-mentioned place. Here he remained encamped for two
                        days and ravaged the whole of the surrounding country. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> From there he went on past Interamna and Aquinum into
                        the territory of Fregellae as far as the Liris. Here he found that the
                        bridge had been destroyed by the people of Fregellae in order to delay his
                        advance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fulvius too had been delayed at
                        the Volturnus, owing to Hannibal having burnt his boats, and he had
                        considerable difficulty in procuring rafts for the transport of his troops,
                        owing to the lack of timber. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When,
                        however, he had once crossed, the remainder of his march was uninterrupted,
                        as he found ample supplies of provisions waiting for him in each city he
                        came to, and also put out by the side of the road in the country districts.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His men, too, in their eagerness urged
                        one another to march more quickly, for they were going to defend their
                        homes. A messenger who had travelled from Fregellae for a day and a night
                        without stopping created great alarm in Rome, and the excitement was
                        increased by people running about the City with wildly exaggerated accounts
                        of the news he had brought. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The wailing
                        cry of the matrons was heard everywhere, not only in private houses but even
                        in the temples. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Here they knelt and swept
                        the temple-floors with their dishevelled hair and lifted up their hands to
                        heaven in piteous entreaty to the gods that they would deliver the City of
                        Rome out of the hands of the enemy and preserve its mothers and children
                        from injury and outrage. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The senators
                        remained in session in the Forum so as to be at hand should the magistrates
                        wish to consult them. Some received orders and went off to execute their
                        commissions, others offered their services in case they could be of use
                        anywhere. Troops were posted at the Capitol, on the walls, round about the
                        City and even as far as the Alban Mount and the fortress of Aesula. In the
                        midst of all this excitement word was brought that the proconsul Q. Fulvius
                        was on his way from Capua with an army. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        As proconsul he could not hold command in the City, the senate therefore
                        passed a decree conferring upon him consular powers. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> After completely destroying the territory of Fregellae
                        in revenge for the destruction of the bridge over the Liris, Hannibal
                        continued his march through the districts of Frusinum, Ferentinum and
                        Anagnia into the neighbourhood of Labicum. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> He then crossed Algidus and marched on Tusculum, but he was refused
                        admittance, so he turned to the right below Tusculum towards Gabii, and
                        still descending, came into the district of Pupinia where he encamped, eight
                        miles from Rome. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The nearer his approach
                        the greater was the slaughter of those who were fleeing to the City at the
                        hands of the Numidians who rode in front of the main body. Many, too, of all
                        ages and conditions were made prisoners. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the midst of this turmoil and
                        excitement Fulvius Flaccus entered Rome with his army. He passed through the
                        Porta Capena and marched right through the City past the Cavinae and the
                        Esquiliae, and out again through the Colline Gate, entrenching himself on
                        ground between the Colline and Esquiline Gates. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Here the plebeian aediles furnished him with
                        provisions. The consuls, attended by the senate, visited him in his camp,
                        and a council was held to consider what measures the supreme interests of
                        the republic demanded. It was decided that the consuls should form
                        entrenched camps in the vicinity of the Colline and Esquiline Gates, the
                        City praetor taking command of the Citadel and the Capitol, and that the
                        senate should remain in permanent session in the Forum in case any sudden
                        emergency should need to be provided against. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Hannibal had now moved his camp to the Anio at a
                        distance of three miles from the City. From this position, he advanced with
                        a body of 2000 cavalry towards the Colline Gate as far as the temple of
                        Hercules, and from that point he rode up and made as close an inspection as
                        he could of the walls and the situation of the City. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Flaccus was furious with indignation at this calm and
                        leisurely proceeding and sent some cavalry with orders to clear the enemy
                        and drive them back to their camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There
                        were some 1200 Numidian deserters stationed on the Aventine at the time, and
                        the consuls sent orders to them to ride through the City to the Esquiliae,
                        as they considered none more fitted to fight amongst the hollows and garden
                        walls and sepulchres and enclosed paths all around that part of the City.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When those on guard at the Citadel and
                        the Capitol saw them trotting down the Publician hill they shouted out that
                        the Aventine was taken. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This caused so
                        much confusion and panic that, had not the Carthaginian camp been outside
                        the City, the terrified population would have poured out of the gates. As it
                        was, they took refuge in the houses and various buildings, and seeing some
                        of their own people walking in the streets, they took them for enemies and
                        attacked them with stones and missiles. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It
                        was impossible to calm the excitement or to rectify the mistake, as the
                        streets were packed with crowds of country people with their cattle, whom
                        the sudden danger had driven into the City. The cavalry action was
                        successful and the enemy were driven off. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        It became necessary, however, to quell the disturbances which, without the
                        slightest reason, were breaking out in many quarters, and the senate decided
                        that all who had been Dictators, consuls or censors should be invested with
                        the imperium until the enemy had retired from the walls. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> During the remainder of the day and throughout the
                        night, many such disturbances arose and were promptly repressed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following day Hannibal crossed the
                        Anio and led out the whole of his force to battle; Flaccus and the consuls
                        did not decline the challenge. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When both
                        sides were drawn up to decide an action in which Rome was the victor's
                        prize, a tremendous hailstorm threw the two armies into such disorder that
                        they had difficulty in holding their arms. They retired to their respective
                        camps, fearing everything rather than their enemy. The following day, when
                        the armies were drawn up in the same position, a similar storm separated
                        them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On each occasion, after they were
                        once more in camp, the weather cleared up in an extraordinary way.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians looked upon the
                        occasion as preternatural, and the story runs that Hannibal was heard to say
                        that at one time he lacked the will, at another the opportunity, of becoming
                        master of Rome. His hopes were further damped by two incidents, one of some
                        importance, the other less so. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The more
                        important was his receiving information that while he was actually in arms
                        near the walls of Rome a force had marched out fully equipped, under their
                        standards, to reinforce the army in Spain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The other incident, which he learnt from a prisoner, was the sale by auction
                        of the spot on which he had fixed his camp, and the fact that, in spite of
                        his occupation of it, there was no abatement in the price. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> That any one should have been found in Rome to buy the
                        ground which he was holding in possession as spoil of war, seemed to
                        Hannibal such an insulting piece of arrogance that he instantly summoned a
                        crier and made him give notice of the sale of the silversmiths' shops round
                        the Forum of Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These incidents led to his withdrawal from
                        Rome, and he retired as far as the river Tutia, six miles distant from the
                        City. From there he marched to the grove of Feronia and the temple, which
                        was celebrated in those days for its wealth. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> The people of Capena and other cities round used to bring their
                        first-fruits and other offerings, according to their ability, and they had
                        also embellished it with a considerable quantity of gold and silver. Now the
                        temple was despoiled of all its treasures. Great heaps of metal, where the
                        soldiers, struck by remorse, had thrown pieces of uncoined brass, were found
                        there after Hannibal's departure. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> All
                        writers are agreed as to the plundering of this temple. Coelius tell us that
                        Hannibal diverted his march to it while he was going from Eretum to Rome,
                        after marching from Amiternum by Reate and Cutiliae. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> According to this writer, on leaving Capua, Hannibal
                        entered Samnium, and from there passed to the Peligni; then, marching past
                        the town of Sulmo, he crossed the frontiers of the Marrucini and then
                        advanced through the Alban territory to the country of the Marsi, and from
                        there to Amiternum and the hamlet of Foruli. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> There can be no uncertainty as to the route he took,
                        for the traces of that great commander and his large army could not have
                        been lost in so short a space of time; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        the only point at issue is whether that was the route he took when he
                        marched to Rome or whether he followed it on his return to Campania. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The energy with which the Romans pressed
                        the siege of Capua was far greater than that which Hannibal exhibited in its
                        defence, for he hurried away through Lucania to Bruttium in the hope of
                        surprising Regium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Though the siege was in
                        no way relaxed during Fulvius' absence, his return made a sensible
                        difference in the conduct of operations, and it was a matter of general
                        surprise that Hannibal had not returned at the same time. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The Capuans gradually learnt through their
                        conversations with the besiegers that they were abandoned and left to
                        themselves, and that the Carthaginians had given up all hope of saving
                        Capua. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In accordance with a resolution of
                        the senate, the proconsul issued an edict which was published in the
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> city, that any Campanian burgher who
                        went over to the Romans before a certain day would be amnestied. Not a
                        single man went over; their fears prevented them from trusting the Romans,
                        for they had in their revolt committed crimes too great for any hope of
                        pardon. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But whilst no one would provide
                        for his own safety by going over to the enemy, there was <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> nothing done for the public safety in the way of wise
                        or prudent counsel. The nobility had deserted their public duties; it was
                        impossible to get together a meeting of the senate. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The supreme magistracy was held by a man who conferred
                        no honour on his office; on the contrary, his unfitness detracted from its
                        authority and power. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> None of the nobility
                        were to be seen in the forum, or indeed anywhere in public; they shut
                        themselves up at home waiting for their country's downfall and their own
                        destruction. All responsibility was thrown upon the commandants of the Punic
                        garrison, Bostar and Hanno, and they were much more <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> concerned for their own safety than for that of their
                        supporters in the city. A communication was drawn up for the purpose of
                        forwarding it to Hannibal, in which he was directly charged with
                        surrendering Capua into the enemy's hands and exposing his garrison to every
                        kind of torture. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He had gone off, so the
                        despatch hinted, to be out of the way, lest Capua should be taken before his
                        eyes, The Romans could not be drawn off from besieging Capua even when an
                        attack was threatened on their city; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> so
                        much more determination did the Romans show as enemies, than the
                        Carthaginians as friends. If Hannibal would return to Capua and turn the
                        whole tide of war in that direction, then the garrison were prepared to make
                        an attack on the besiegers. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He had not
                        crossed the Alps to make war with Regium or Tarentum; where the legions of
                        Rome were, there ought the armies of Carthage to be. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> That was how he had conquered at Cannae, and at
                        Thrasymenus, by meeting the enemy face to face, army to army, and trying his
                        fortune in battle. </p>
                    <p> This was the main drift of the despatch. It was handed to some Numidians who
                        had undertaken to carry it on promise of a reward. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> They had come into Fulvius' camp as deserters,
                        intending to seize a favourable opportunity of slipping away, and the famine
                        from which Capua had long been suffering was a very good reason why they
                        should desert. A Campanian woman, however, the mistress of one of these
                        deserters, suddenly appeared in the camp and informed the Roman commander
                        that the Numidians had come in as part of a pre-arranged plot, <milestone
                            n="16??" unit="section"/> and were really carrying a despatch to
                        Hannibal, and that she was prepared to prove it, as one of them had
                        disclosed the affair to her. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> When this
                        man was brought forward, he at first stoutly denied all knowledge of the
                        woman, but gradually he gave way before the truth, especially when he saw
                        that instruments of torture were being sent for and got ready, and at last
                        made a complete confession. The despatch was produced, and further evidence
                        came to light, as it was found that other Numidians were at large in the
                        Roman camp under the guise of deserters. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        Above seventy of them were arrested and together with the recent arrivals
                        were all scourged, and their hands were cut off, after which they were sent
                        back to Capua. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The sight of this terrible
                        punishment broke the spirit of the Capuans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The people went in a body to the senate
                        house and insisted on Loesius summoning the senate. They openly threatened
                        the nobles who had so long absented themselves from the senate, that they
                        would go round to their houses and drag them all by main force into the
                        streets. These threats resulted in a full meeting of the senate. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The general opinion was in favour of sending a
                        deputation to the Roman commander, but Vibius Virrius, the prime author of
                        the revolt from Rome, when asked his opinion, told those who were talking
                        about a deputation and terms of peace and surrender that they <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> were forgetting what they would have done had
                        they had the Romans in their power, or what, as circumstances now were, they
                        would have to suffer. "Why! <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> ," he
                        exclaimed, "do you imagine that our surrender now will be like the one we
                        made in old days when, in order to get help against the Samnites, we
                        surrendered ourselves and all that belonged to us to Rome? Have you already
                        forgotten at what a critical moment for Rome we revolted from her?
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> How we put to death with every torture
                        and indignity the garrison which we could easily have sent away? What
                        numerous and desperate sorties we have made against our besiegers, how we
                        have assaulted their lines and called Hannibal in to crush them? <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Have you forgotten this last act of ours when we
                        sent him to attack Rome ? </p>
                    <p> "Now look at the other side, consider their determined hostility to us and
                        see if you have anything to hope for. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Though there was a foreign enemy on Italian soil, and that enemy Hannibal,
                        though the flames of war were being kindled in every quarter, they neglected
                        everything, even Hannibal himself, and sent both the consuls, each with an
                        army, to Capua. For two years now have they hemmed us in with their lines of
                        circumvallation, and are wearing us down with famine. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> They have endured as much as we have in the extremity
                        of peril, the utmost severity of toil; often have they been slaughtered
                        about their entrenchments, and all but driven out of them. But I pass over
                        these things; the labours and dangers of a siege are an old and common
                        experience. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But to show their rage and
                        implacable hatred against us I will remind you of these incidents: Hannibal
                        assaulted their lines with an enormous force of infantry and cavalry, and
                        partly captured them, but they did not raise the siege; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> he crossed the Volturnus and desolated the district of
                        Calenum with fire; the sufferings of their allies failed to call off the
                        Romans; he ordered a general advance on Rome itself, they disregarded the
                        threatening storm; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> he crossed the Anio
                        and encamped within three miles of the City, and at last rode up to its
                        walls and gates and made as though he would take their city from them if
                        they did not loose their hold on Capua; they did not loose their hold. When
                        wild beasts are mad with rage you can still divert their blind fury by
                        approaching their lairs and young ones which they will hasten to defend.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Romans were not diverted from
                        Capua by the prospect of their city being besieged, or by the terrified
                        cries of their wives and children which could almost be heard here, or by
                        the threatened desecration of their hearths and altars, of the shrines of
                        their gods and the tombs of their ancestors. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> So eager are they to visit us with punishment, so
                        greedily do they thirst for our blood. And, perhaps, rightly; we should have
                        done the same had fortune favoured us. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> "Heaven, however, has ordered otherwise,
                        and so, though I am bound to meet my death in any case, I can, whilst I am
                        still free, escape the insults and the tortures which the enemy is preparing
                        for me, I can dispose of myself by a death as peaceful as it is honourable.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I refuse to look upon Appius Claudius
                        and Q. Fulvius exulting in all the insolence of victory; I refuse to be
                        dragged in chains through the streets of Rome to grace their triumph, and
                        then in the dungeon or bound to the stake, with my back torn with the
                        scourge, pass under the headsman's axe. I will not see my city plundered and
                        burnt, and the matrons and maidens and noble boys of Capua ravished and
                        outraged. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Alba, the mother city of Rome,
                        was rased by the Romans to its foundations in order that no memorial of
                        their origin and of the stock whence they sprung might survive; much less
                        can I believe that they will spare Capua which they hate more bitterly than
                        they hate Carthage. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> So, for those of you
                        who intend to meet your fate before you witness all these horrors I have
                        prepared a banquet today at my house. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        When you have taken your fill of food and wine, the same goblet that is
                        handed to me will be passed round to you. That draught will free our bodies
                        from torture, our spirits from insult, our eyes and ears from seeing and
                        hearing all the suffering and outrage which await the vanquished. Men will
                        be in readiness to place our lifeless bodies on a vast pile which will be
                        kindled in the court-yard of the house. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        This is the only path to death which is honourable and worthy of free men.
                        Even the enemy will admire our courage, and Hannibal will know that the
                        allies whom he has abandoned and betrayed were, after all, brave men." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This speech of Virrius was received with
                        approbation by many who had not the courage to carry out what they approved
                        of. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The majority of the senators were not
                        without hope that the clemency of the Roman people so often experienced in
                        former wars would be once more extended to them, and they determined to send
                        envoys to make a formal surrender of Capua. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> About seven-and-twenty accompanied Virrius home and banqueted with him.
                        When they had as far as possible deadened their feelings with wine against
                        the sense of impending evil, they all partook of the poisoned cup.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then they rose from table and grasped
                        each other's hands and took a last embrace of one another, weeping for their
                        own and their country's doom. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some
                        remained that they might be cremated together on the same funeral pyre,
                        others departed for their homes. The congestion of the veins caused by the
                        food and wine they had taken made the action of the poison somewhat slow,
                        and most of them lingered through the whole night and part of the following
                        day. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All however, expired before the gates
                        were opened to the enemy. The following day, the gate called "the Gate of
                        Jupiter," opposite the Roman camp, was opened by the proconsul's order.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> One legion was admitted through it and
                        two squadrons of allied cavalry, with C. Fulvius in command. First he took
                        care that all the weapons of war in Capua were brought to him; then, after
                        stationing guards at all the gates to prevent any exit or escape, he
                        arrested the Punic garrison and ordered the senate to go to the Roman
                        commanders. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On their arrival in the camp
                        they were manacled, and ordered to send word for all the gold and silver
                        they possessed to be brought to the quaestors. This amounted to 2072 pounds
                        of gold and 31,200 pounds of silver. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Twenty-five senators were sent to be kept in custody at Cales, and
                        twenty-eight who were proved to have been mainly instrumental in bringing
                        about the revolt were sent to Teanum </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As to the punishment to be meted out to
                        the senators of Capua, Claudius and Fulvius were anything but unanimous.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Claudius was prepared to grant them
                        pardon, but Fulvius took a much sterner line. Appius Claudius wished to
                        refer the whole question to the senate at Rome. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He maintained that it was but right that the senators
                        should have an opportunity of investigating all the circumstances and
                        finding out whether the Capuans had made any of the allies or the Latins or
                        the municipal burghs privy to their designs, and if so, whether any of these
                        had given them assistance in the war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Fulvius, on the other hand, declared that the very last thing they ought to
                        do was to harass their faithful allies by vague charges and put them at the
                        mercy of informers who were perfectly indifferent as to what they said or
                        what they did. Any such investigation therefore he should stifle. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> After this interchange of views they parted,
                        Appius feeling no doubt that in spite of his violent language his comrade
                        would, in such an important matter, await instructions from Rome. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Fulvius, determined to forestall any such
                        obstacle to his designs, dismissed the council and ordered the military
                        tribunes and the officers of the allies to select 2000 horsemen and warn
                        them to be in readiness by the time the third watch was sounded. Starting
                        with this force in the night, he reached Teanum at day-break and rode
                        straight into the forum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A crowd had
                        collected at the first entry of the cavalry, and Fulvius ordered the chief
                        magistrate of the district to be summoned, and on his appearance commanded
                        him to produce the Capuans who were in his custody. They were all brought
                        forward and then scourged and beheaded. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Then putting spurs to his horse he rode to Cales. When he had taken his seat
                        on the tribunal and the Capuans who had been brought out were being bound to
                        the stake, a mounted messenger arrived post-haste from Rome and handed
                        Fulvius a despatch from the praetor C. Calpurnius containing the decree of
                        the senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The spectators guessed the
                        nature of the contents, and those standing round the tribunal expressed
                        their belief-a belief which soon found expression throughout the
                        Assembly-that the whole question of the treatment of the Capuan prisoners
                        was to be left to the senate. Fulvius thought so too; he took the letter and
                        without opening it placed it in his breast and then ordered his marshal to
                        tell the lictor to carry out the law. Thus, those who were at Cales were
                        also executed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Now he read the despatch
                        and the decree of the senate. But it was too late to prevent a deed
                        accomplished, which had been hurried on as quickly as possible in order that
                        it might not be prevented. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Just as
                        Fulvius was leaving the tribunal a Capuan named Taurea Vibellius strode
                        through the middle of the crowd and addressed him by name. Fulvius resumed
                        his seat, wondering what the man wanted. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        "Order me too," he cried, to be put to death so that you may boast of having
                        caused the death of a braver man than yourself." <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Fulvius declared that the man was certainly out of his
                        mind, and added that even if he wished to kill him he was prevented from
                        doing so by the decree of the senate. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Then Vibellius exclaimed, "Now that my native city has been taken, my
                        friends and relations lost to me, my wife and children slain by my own hand
                        to save them from insult and outrage, and since even the opportunity of
                        dying as my fellow-countrymen here have died is refused me, let me seek in
                        courage a release from the life which has become so hateful to me."
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> With these words he drew out a sword
                        which he had concealed in his garment, and plunging it into his heart fell
                        dying at the general's feet. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the execution of the Capuans and most
                        of the other steps taken were carried out by the instructions of Fulvius
                        alone, some authors assert that Appius Claudius died immediately after the
                        surrender of Capua. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> According to this
                        account, Taurea did not come voluntarily to Cales, nor did he perish by his
                        own hand; when he had been tied to the stake along with the others he
                        shouted repeatedly, and as owing to the noise they could not hear what he
                        was saying, Fulvius ordered silence. Then Taurea said, as I have already
                        related, that he was being done to death by a man who was far from being his
                        equal in courage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At these words, the
                        marshal, on the proconsul's order gave this direction to the lictor:
                        "Lictor, let this brave man have more of the rod, and execute the law upon
                        him first of all." <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some authors assert
                        that the decree of the senate was read before the men were beheaded, but
                        there was a proviso in it to the effect that if he thought fit, he might
                        refer the question to the senate, and Fulvius took this to mean that he was
                        at liberty to decide as to what would be the best course in the interests of
                        the republic. After Fulvius returned to Capua, he received the submission of
                        Atella and Calatia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here too the
                        ringleaders in the revolt were punished; seventy of the leading senators
                        were put to death, and three hundred Campanian nobles thrown into prison.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Others who were distributed amongst
                        the various Latin cities to be kept in custody perished from various causes;
                        the rest of the population of Capua were sold as slaves. The question now
                        was what was to be done with the city and its territory. Some were of
                        opinion that a city so strong, so near to Rome and so hostile to it, ought
                        to be utterly destroyed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Utilitarian
                        considerations however prevailed. The territory was generally allowed to be
                        the first in Italy in point of productiveness, and the only reason why the
                        city was spared was that there might be a place for the tillers of the soil
                        to live in. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A motley throng of peasants,
                        freedmen, small tradesmen and artisans were told off to occupy the place;
                        the whole of the territory with the buildings on it became the property of
                        the Roman State. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was settled that Capua
                        itself should be simply a lodgment and a shelter, a city merely in name;
                        there was to be no corporate life, no senate, no council of the plebs, no
                        magistrates; the population were without any right of public assembly or
                        self-government; they had no common interest and were incapable of taking
                        any common action. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The administration of
                        justice was in the hands of a praetor who was to be sent annually from Rome.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In this way matters were arranged at
                        Capua in pursuance of a policy which commends itself from every point of
                        view. Sternly and swiftly was punishment meted out to those who had been
                        most guilty, the civic population was scattered far and wide with no hope of
                        return, the unoffending walls and houses were spared from the ravages of
                        fire and demolition. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The preservation of
                        the city, whilst it was a material advantage to Rome, afforded to the
                        friendly communities a striking proof of her lenity; the whole of Campania
                        and all the surrounding nationalities would have been horror-struck at the
                        destruction of such a famous and wealthy city. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The enemy, on the other hand, was made to realise the
                        power of Rome to punish those who were faithless to her, and the
                        powerlessness of Hannibal to protect those who had gone over to him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now that the senate was relieved from its
                        anxiety about Capua, it was able to turn its attention to Spain. A force of
                        6000 infantry and 300 cavalry was placed at Nero's disposal, and he selected
                        it from the two legions he had had with him at Capua; an equal number of
                        infantry and 600 cavalry were to be furnished by the allies. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> He embarked his army at Puteoli and landed at
                        Tarraco. Here he hauled his ships ashore and furnished the crews with arms,
                        thus augmenting his strength. With this composite force he marched to the
                        Ebro and took over the army there from Ti. Fonteius and L. Marcius.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then advanced against the enemy.
                        Hasdrubal-Hamilcar's son-was encamped at the Lapides Atri (the "Black
                        Boulders"). This is a place in the Auretanian country between the towns of
                        Iliturgis and Mentissa. Nero occupied the two exits of the pass. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, finding himself shut in, sent a herald
                        to promise in his name that he would deport the whole of his army from Spain
                        if he were allowed to leave his position. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The Roman general was glad to accept the offer, and Hasdrubal asked for an
                        interview the following day. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At this
                        conference they were to draw up in writing the terms upon which the various
                        citadels were to be handed over, and the date at which the garrisons were to
                        be withdrawn, on the understanding that they should take with them all their
                        goods and chattels. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His request was granted, and Hasdrubal
                        ordered the most heavily armed portion of his army to get out of the pass as
                        best they could as soon as darkness set in. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> He was careful to see that not very many went out that night, as a small
                        body would make but little noise and be more likely to escape observation.
                        They would also find their way more easily through the narrow and difficult
                        foot-paths. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The next day he kept the
                        appointment, but so much time was taken up in discussing and writing down a
                        number of things which had nothing to do with the matters they had agreed to
                        discuss, that the whole day was lost and the business adjourned till the
                        morrow. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So another opportunity was
                        afforded him of sending off a fresh body of troops by night. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The discussion was not brought to a close the
                        next day, and so it went on; several days were occupied in discussing terms,
                        and the nights in despatching the Carthaginians secretly from their camp.
                        When the greater part of the army had escaped, Hasdrubal no longer kept to
                        the conditions which he had himself proposed, and there was less and less
                        desire to come to terms as his sincerity diminished with his fears.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Almost the entire force of infantry
                        had now got out of the defile when, at daybreak, a dense fog covered the
                        valley and the whole of the surrounding country. No sooner did Hasdrubal
                        become aware of this than he sent a message to Nero begging that the
                        interview might be put off for that day as it was a day on which the
                        Carthaginians were forbidden by their religion to transact any important
                        business. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Even this did not arouse any
                        suspicion of trickery. On learning that he would be excused for that day,
                        Hasdrubal promptly left his camp with the cavalry and elephants, and by
                        keeping his movements secret, emerged into safety. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> About ten o'clock the sun dispersed the mist, and the
                        Romans saw that the hostile camp was deserted. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Then, recognising at last the trick which the
                        Carthaginian had played upon him and how he had been befooled, Nero
                        hurriedly prepared to follow him and force him to an engagement. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> The enemy, however, declined battle; only a few
                        skirmishes took place between the Carthaginian rear and the Roman advanced
                        guard. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Spanish tribes who had revolted after
                        the defeat of the two Scipios showed no signs of returning to their
                        allegiance; there were not, however, any fresh instances. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> After the recovery of Capua the public interest both in
                        senate and people centered in Spain quite as much as in Italy; and it was
                        decided that the army serving there should be increased and a
                        commander-in-chief appointed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was,
                        however, much uncertainty felt as to whom they ought to appoint. Two
                        consummate generals had fallen within thirty days of each other, and the
                        selection of a man to take their place demanded exceptional care. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Various names were proposed, and at last it was
                        arranged that the matter should be left to the people, and a proconsul for
                        Spain formally elected. The consuls fixed a day for the election. They were
                        in hopes that those who felt themselves qualified for such an important
                        command would become candidates. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                        were, however, disappointed, and the disappointment renewed the grief of the
                        people, as they thought of the defeats they had sustained and the generals
                        they had lost. The citizens were depressed, almost in despair, nevertheless
                        they went out to the Campus Martius on the day fixed for the election.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All turned their eyes to the
                        magistrates and watched the expression of the leaders of the republic as
                        they looked enquiringly at one another. Everywhere men were saying that the
                        State was in such a hopeless condition that no one dared to accept the
                        command in Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Suddenly, Publius
                        Cornelius Scipio, the son of the Scipio who had fallen in Spain, a young man
                        barely twenty-four years old, took his stand upon a slight eminence where he
                        could be seen and heard, and announced himself as a candidate. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> All eyes were turned towards him, and the
                        delighted cheers with which his announcement was received were at once
                        interpreted as an omen of his future good fortune and success. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> On proceeding to vote, not only the centuries but
                        even the individual voters were unanimous to a man in favour of entrusting
                        P. Scipio with the supreme command in Spain. When, however, the election was
                        decided and their enthusiasm had had time to cool down, there was a
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> sudden silence as the people began
                        to reflect on what they had done, and ask themselves whether their personal
                        affection for him might not have got the better of their judgment. What gave
                        them the greatest concern was his youth. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Some, too, recalled with dread the fortune that had attended his house, and
                        regarded as ominous of evil even the name of the man who was quitting two
                        bereaved families in order to carry on a campaign round the tombs of his
                        uncle and his father. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Seeing how the step which they had taken
                        so impetuously now filled them with anxiety, Scipio called the voters
                        together and spoke to them about his age and the command which they had
                        entrusted to him, and the war which he had to conduct. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He spoke in such lofty and glowing words that he evoked
                        their enthusiasm once more, and inspired them with more hopeful confidence
                        than is usually called out by faith in men's promises or by reasonable
                        anticipations of success. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio won
                        people's admiration not only by the sterling qualities which he possessed,
                        but also by his cleverness in displaying them, a cleverness which he had
                        developed from early youth. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In his public
                        life he generally spoke and acted as though he were guided either by visions
                        of the night or by some divine inspiration, whether it was that he was
                        really open to superstitious influences or that he claimed oracular sanction
                        for his commands and counsels in order to secure prompt adoption. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He sought to create this impression on men's
                        minds from the beginning, from the day when he assumed the toga virilis, for
                        he never undertook any important business, either public or private, without
                        first going to the Capitol, where he sat for some time in the temple in
                        privacy and alone. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This custom, which he
                        kept up all through his life, gave rise to a widespread belief, whether
                        designedly upon his part or not, that he was of divine origin, and the story
                        was told of him <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> which was commonly
                        related of Alexander-a story as silly as it was fabulous-that he was
                        begotten by an enormous serpent which had been often seen in his mother's
                        bedroom, but on any one's approach, suddenly uncoiled itself and
                        disappeared. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The belief in these marvels
                        was never scoffed at by him; on the contrary, it was strengthened by
                        deliberate policy on his part in refusing to deny or to admit that anything
                        of the kind ever occurred. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There were many
                        other traits in this young man's character, some of which were genuine,
                        others the result of studied acting, which created a greater admiration for
                        him than usually falls to the lot of man. </p>
                    <p> It was the confidence with which he had in this way inspired his
                        fellow-citizens that led them to entrust to him, young as he was, a task of
                        enormous difficulty, and a command which involved the gravest
                        responsibilities. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The force which he had
                        formed out of the old army in Spain, and that which sailed from Puteoli with
                        C. Nero, were further reinforced by 10,000 infantry and 1000 cavalry. M.
                        Junius Silanus was appointed as his second in command. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Setting sail from the mouth of the Tiber with a fleet
                        of thirty vessels, all quinqueremes, he coasted along the Etruscan shore,
                        crossed the Gulf of Gaul, and after rounding the Pyrenaean Promontory
                        brought up at Emporiae, a Greek city, founded by settlers from Phocaea.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Here he disembarked his troops and
                        proceeded overland to Tarraco, leaving orders for his fleet to follow his
                        movements. At Tarraco he was met by deputations which had been sent from all
                        the friendly tribes as soon as they knew of his coming. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The vessels were hauled ashore, and the four Massilian
                        triremes which had acted as convoy were sent home. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The deputations informed Scipio of the unsettlement
                        amongst their tribes due to the varying fortunes of the war. He replied in a
                        bold and assured tone, full of self-confidence, but no expression savouring
                        of presumption or arrogance escaped him, everything he said was marked by
                        perfect dignity and sincerity. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tarraco was now his headquarters. From
                        there he paid visits to the friendly tribes, and also inspected the winter
                        quarters of the army. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He praised them
                        warmly for having maintained their hold on the province after sustaining two
                        such terrible blows, and also for keeping the enemy to the south of the
                        Ebro, thereby depriving them of any advantages from their victories, and
                        also affording protection to their own friends. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Marcius, whom he kept with him, he treated with so much
                        honour that it was perfectly obvious that Scipio had not the slightest fear
                        of his reputation being dimmed by anybody. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Soon afterwards Silanus succeeded Nero and the new troops were sent into
                        winter quarters. After making all the necessary visits and inspections and
                        completing the preparations for the next campaign Scipio returned to
                        Tarraco. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His reputation was quite as great
                        among the enemy as among his own countrymen; there was amongst the former a
                        foreboding, a vague sense of fear which was all the stronger because no
                        reason for it could be given. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        Carthaginian armies withdrew into their respective winter-quarters:
                        Hasdrubal, the son of Gisgo, to Gades on the coast, Mago into the interior
                        above the forest of Castulo, Hasdrubal, the son of Hamilcar, near the Ebro
                        in the neighbourhood of Saguntum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This
                        summer, marked by two important events, the recovery of Capua and the
                        despatch of Scipio to Spain, was drawing to a close when a Carthaginian
                        fleet was sent from Sicily to Tarentum to intercept supplies from the Roman
                        garrison in the citadel. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It certainly
                        succeeded in blocking all access to the citadel from the sea, but the longer
                        it remained the greater was the scarcity amongst the townspeople as compared
                        with that amongst the Romans in the citadel. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> For though the coast was clear and open access was secured to the harbour
                        by the Carthaginian fleet, it was impossible to convey to the population of
                        the city as much corn as was consumed by the crowd of sailors, drawn from
                        every class, on board the fleet. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        garrison in the citadel, on the other hand, being only a small body, were
                        able to exist on what they had previously laid in, without any external
                        supply. At length the ships were sent away, and their departure was hailed
                        with more delight than their arrival had been. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But the scarcity was not in the slightest degree
                        lessened, for when their protection was withdrawn, corn could not be brought
                        in at all. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Towards the end of this summer M.
                        Marcellus left Sicily for Rome. On his arrival in the City he was granted an
                        audience of the senate in the Temple of Bellona. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> After giving a report of his campaign and gently
                        protesting on his own behalf and on that of his soldiers against not being
                        allowed to bring them home, though he had completely pacified the province,
                        he requested to be allowed to enter the City in triumph. After a lengthy
                        debate his request was refused. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the one
                        hand, it was argued, it was most inconsistent to refuse him a triumph now
                        that he was on the spot after the way in which the news of his successes in
                        Sicily had been received, and public thanksgivings and special rites ordered
                        while he was still in his province. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Against this it was alleged that as the senate had ordered him to hand over
                        his army to his successor, it was a proof that a state of war still existed
                        in the province, and he could not enjoy a triumph since he had not brought
                        the war to a close, nor was his army present to testify as to whether he
                        deserved a triumph or not. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They decided
                        upon a middle course, he was to be allowed an ovation. The tribunes of the
                        plebs were authorised by the senate to propose as an ordinance to the people
                        "that for the day <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> on which he entered
                        the City in ovation M. Marcellus should retain his command." </p>
                    <p> The day previous to this he celebrated his triumph on the Alban Mount.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From there he marched into the City in
                        ovation. An enormous quantity of spoil was carried before him together with
                        a model of Syracuse at the time of its capture. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Catapults and ballistae and all the engines of war
                        taken from the city were exhibited in the procession, as were also the works
                        of art which had been accumulated in royal profusion during the long years
                        of peace. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These included a number of
                        articles in silver and bronze, pieces of furniture, costly garments and many
                        famous statues with which Syracuse, like all the principal cities of Greece,
                        had been adorned. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To signalise his
                        victories over the Carthaginians eight elephants were led in the procession.
                        Not the least conspicuous feature of the spectacle was the sight of Sosis
                        the Syracusan and Moericus the Spaniard who marched in front wearing golden
                        crowns. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The former had guided the
                        nocturnal entry into Syracuse, the latter had been the agent in the
                        surrender of Nasos and its garrison. Each of these men received the full
                        Roman citizenship and 500 jugera of land. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Sosis was to take his allotment in that part of the Syracusan territory
                        which had belonged to the king or to those who had taken up arms against
                        Rome, and he was allowed to choose any house in Syracuse which had been the
                        property of those who had been put to death under the laws of war.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A further order was made that
                        Moericus and the Spaniards should have assigned to them a city and lands in
                        Sicily out of the possessions of those who had revolted from Rome.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> M. Cornelius was commissioned to
                        select the city and territory for them, where he thought best, and 400
                        jugera in the same district were also decreed as a gift to Belligenes
                        through whose instrumentality Moericus had been induced to change sides.
                        After Marcellus' departure from Sicily a Carthaginian fleet landed a force
                        of 8000 infantry and 3000 Numidian horse. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        The cities of Murgentia and Ergetium revolted to them, and their example was
                        followed by Hybla and Macella and some other less important places.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Muttines and his Numidians were also
                        roaming all through the island and laying waste the fields of Rome's allies
                        with fire. To add to these troubles the Roman army bitterly resented not
                        being withdrawn from the province with their commander and also not being
                        allowed to winter in the towns. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        Consequently they were very remiss in their military duties; in fact it was
                        only the absence of a leader that prevented them from breaking out into open
                        mutiny. In spite of these difficulties the praetor M. Cornelius succeeded by
                        remonstrances and reassurances in calming the temper of his men, and then
                        reduced all the revolted cities to submission. In pursuance of the senate's
                        orders he selected Murgentia, one of those cities, for the settlement of
                        Moericus and his Spaniards. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As both the consuls had Apulia for their
                        province, and as there was less danger from Hannibal and his Carthaginians,
                        they received instructions to ballot for Apulia and Macedonia. Macedonia
                        fell to Sulpicius, and he superseded Laevinus. Fulvius was recalled to
                        conduct the consular elections in Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The Veturian century of juniors was the first to vote, and they declared for
                        T. Manlius Torquatus and T. Otacilius, the latter being at the time absent
                        from Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The voters began to press round
                        Manlius to congratulate him, regarding his election as a certainty, but he
                        at once proceeded, surrounded by a large crowd, to the consul's tribunal and
                        begged to be allowed to make a brief speech and also asked that the century
                        which had voted might be recalled. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When
                        all were on the tiptoe of expectation to learn what he wanted, he began by
                        excusing himself <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> on the score of his
                        eyesight. "A man must have little sense <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        of shame," he continued "whether he be pilot of a ship or commander of an
                        army, who asks that the lives and fortunes of others should be committed to
                        him when, in all he does, he has to depend upon other people's eyes.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If, therefore, you approve, order the
                        Veturian century of juniors to cast their vote again, and to remember,
                        whilst they are choosing their consuls, the war in Italy and the critical
                        position of the republic. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Your ears can
                        hardly yet have recovered from the uproar and confusion caused by the enemy
                        a few months ago, when he brought the flames of war almost up to the very
                        walls of Rome." The century replied with a general shout that they had not
                        changed their minds, they should vote as before. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Then Torquatus said, "I shall not be able to tolerate
                        your manners and conduct, nor will you submit to my authority. Go back and
                        vote again, and bear in mind that the Carthaginians are carrying war in
                        Italy, and that their leader is Hannibal." <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> Then the century, swayed by the speaker's personal authority and by the
                        murmurs of admiration which they heard all around them, begged the consul to
                        call up the Veturian century of seniors, as they wished to consult their
                        elders and be guided by their advice in the choice of consuls. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> They were accordingly called up and an interval
                        was allowed for the two bodies to consult privately in the ovile. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> The seniors maintained that the choice really
                        lay between three men, two of them already full of honours-Q. Fabius and M.
                        Marcellus-and, if they particularly wished a new man to be appointed consul
                        to act against the Carthaginians, M. Valerius Laevinus, who had conducted
                        operations against Philip both by sea and land with conspicuous success. So
                        they discussed the claims of these three, and after the seniors had
                        withdrawn the juniors proceeded to vote. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        They gave their vote in favour of M. Marcellus Claudius, resplendent with
                        the glory of his conquest of Sicily, and, as the second consul, M. Valerius.
                        Neither of them had put in a personal appearance. The other centuries all
                        followed the leading century. People nowadays may laugh at the admirers of
                        antiquity. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> I for my part do not believe
                        it possible, even if there ever existed a commonwealth of wise men such as
                        philosophers dream of but have never really known, that there could be an
                        aristocracy more grave or more temperate in their desire for power or a
                        people with purer manners and a higher moral tone. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> That a century of juniors should have been anxious to
                        consult their seniors as to whom they were to place in supreme authority is
                        a thing hardly credible in these days, when we see in what contempt children
                        hold the authority of their parents. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then followed the election of praetors.
                        The successful candidates were P. Manlius Vulso, L. Manlius Acidinus, C.
                        Laetorius and L. Cincius Alimentus. When the elections were over news came
                        of the death of T. Otacilius in Sicily. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                        was the man whom the people would have given to T. Manlius as his colleague
                        in the consulship, if the order of the proceedings had not been interrupted.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Games of Apollo had been exhibited
                        the previous year, and when the question of their repetition the next year
                        was moved by the praetor Calpurnius, the senate passed a decree that they
                        should be observed for all time. Some portents were observed this year and
                        duly reported. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The statue of victory which
                        stood on the roof of the temple of Concord was struck by lightning and
                        thrown down on to the statues of Victory which stood above the facade in
                        front of the pediment, and here it was caught and prevented from falling
                        lower. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At Anagnia and Fregellae the walls
                        and gates were reported to have been struck. In the forum of Subertum
                        streams of blood had flowed for a whole day. At Eretium there was a shower
                        of stones and at Reate a mule had produced offspring. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> These portents were expiated by sacrifices of
                        full-grown victims; a day was appointed for special intercessions and the
                        people were ordered to join in solemn rites for nine days. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Some members of the national priesthood died this year,
                        and others were appointed in their stead. Manlius Aemilius Numida, one of
                        the Keepers of the Sacred Books, was succeeded by M. Aemilius Lepidus. C.
                        Livius was appointed pontiff in the room of M. Pomponius Matho, and M.
                        Servilius, augur, in the place of Spurius Carvilius Maximus. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The death of the pontiff T. Otacilius Crassus did
                        not occur before the close of the year, so no one was appointed in his
                        place. C. Claudius, one of the Flamens of Jupiter, was guilty of
                        irregularity in laying the selected parts of the victim on the altar and
                        consequently resigned his office. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Valerius Laevinus had been holding
                        private interviews with some of the leading Aetolians with the view of
                        ascertaining their political leanings. It was arranged that a meeting of
                        their national council should be convened to meet him, and thither he
                        proceeded with some fast-sailing vessels. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        He commenced his address to the assembly by alluding to the captures of
                        Syracuse and Capua as instances of the success which had attended the arms
                        of Rome in Sicily and Italy, and then proceeded: "It is the practice of the
                        Romans, a practice handed down from their ancestors, to cultivate the
                        friendship of other nations; some of them they have received into
                        citizenship on the same footing as themselves; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> others they have allowed to remain under such
                        favourable conditions that they preferred alliance to full citizenship.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> You, Aetolians, will be held in all
                        the greater honour because you will have been the first of all the oversea
                        nations to establish friendly relations with us. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Philip and the Macedonians you find to be troublesome
                        neighbours; I have already dealt a fatal blow to their ambitions and
                        aggressiveness, and I shall reduce them to such a pass that they will not
                        only evacuate those cities which they have wrested from you, but will have
                        enough to do to defend Macedonia itself. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The Acarnanians, too, whose secession from your league you feel so keenly, I
                        shall bring back to the old terms by which your rights and suzerainty over
                        them were guaranteed." <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These assertions
                        and promises of the Roman commander were supported by Scopas, the chief
                        magistrate of Aetolia at the time, and by Dorimachus, a leading man amongst
                        them, both of whom from their official position spoke with authority. They
                        were less reserved, and adopted a more confident tone as they extolled the
                        power and greatness of Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> What weighed
                        most, however, with the Assembly was the hope of becoming masters of
                        Acarnania. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The terms on which they were to become the
                        friends and allies of Rome were reduced to writing and an additional clause
                        was inserted that if it was their will and pleasure the Eleans and
                        Lacedaemonians as well as Attalus, Pleuratus and Scerdilaedus might be
                        included in the treaty. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Attalus was king
                        of Pergamum in Asia Minor; Pleuratus, king of the Thracians; Scerdilaedus,
                        king of the Illyrians. The Aetolians were at once to commence war with
                        Philip on land, and the Roman general would assist them with not less than
                        twenty-five quinqueremes. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                        territories, buildings and walls of all the cities as far as Corcyra were to
                        become the property of the Aetolians, all the other booty was to go to the
                        Romans, who were also to be responsible for Acarnania passing under the
                        dominion of the Aetolians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Should the
                        Aetolians make peace with Philip, one of the conditions was to be that he
                        would abstain from hostilities against Rome and her allies and dependencies.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Similarly, if the Romans made a
                        treaty with him it was to be a provision that he should not be allowed to
                        make war upon the Aetolians and their allies. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> These were the agreed conditions, and after a lapse of
                        two years, copies of the treaty were deposited by the Aetolians at Olympia,
                        and by the Romans in the Capitol, in order that the sacred memorials round
                        them might be a perpetual witness to their obligation. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> The reason for this delay was that the Aetolian envoys
                        had been detained for a considerable time in Rome. No time, however, was
                        lost in commencing hostilities, and Laevinus attacked Zacynthus. This is a
                        small island adjacent to Aetolia, and it contains one city of the same name
                        as the island; this city, with the exception of its citadel, Laevinus
                        captured. He also took two cities belonging to the Acarnanians-Oeniadae and
                        Nasos-and handed them over to the Aetolians. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> After this he withdrew to Corcyra, feeling satisfied
                        that Philip had enough on his hands with the war on his frontiers to prevent
                        him from thinking about Italy and the Carthaginians and his compact with
                        Hannibal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip was wintering in Pella when the
                        news of the defection of the Aetolians reached him. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He had intended to march into Greece at the beginning
                        of the spring, and with the view of keeping the Illyrians and the cities
                        adjacent to his western frontier quiet he made a sudden invasion into the
                        territories of Oricum and Apollonia. The men of Apollonia came out to give
                        battle, but he drove them back in great panic to their walls. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> After devastating the neighbouring district of
                        Illyria, he turned swiftly into Pelagonia and captured Sintia, a city of the
                        Dardani, which gave them easy access into Macedonia. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> After these rapid incursions he turned his attention to
                        the war which the Aetolians, in conjunction with the Romans, were commencing
                        against him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marching through Pelagonia,
                        Lyncus and Bottiaea he descended into Thessaly, whose population he hoped to
                        rouse to joint action with him against the Aetolians. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Leaving Perseus with a force of 4000 men to hold the
                        pass into Thessaly against them he returned to Macedonia, before engaging in
                        the more serious contest, and from there marched into Thrace to attack the
                        Maedi. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This tribe were in the habit of
                        making incursions into Macedonia whenever they found the king occupied with
                        some distant war and his kingdom unprotected. To break their aggressiveness
                        he devastated their country, and attacked Iamphoryna, their chief city and
                        stronghold. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When Scopas heard that the king had gone
                        into Thessaly, and was engaged in hostilities there, he called up all the
                        fighting men of Aetolia and prepared to invade Acarnania. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The Acarnanians were inferior to their enemy in
                        strength; they were also aware that Oeniadae and Nasos were lost, and above
                        all, that the arms of Rome were turned against them. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Under these circumstances they entered upon the
                        struggle more in a spirit of rage and despair than with prudence and method.
                        Their wives and children and all men over sixty years of age were sent into
                        the adjoining country of Epirus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> All who
                        were between fifteen and sixty bound themselves by oath not to return home
                        unless they were victorious, and if any one left the field, <milestone
                            n="12??" unit="section"/> defeated, no man should receive him into any
                        city or house or admit him to his table or his hearth. They drew up a form
                        of words, invoking a terrible curse upon any of their countrymen who should
                        prove recreants, and <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> a most solemn
                        appeal to their hosts, the Epirotes, to respect their oath. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> They also begged them to bury those of their
                        countrymen who fell in battle in one common grave and place over it this
                        inscription: "Here lie the Acarnanians who met their death whilst fighting
                        for their country against the violence and injustice of the Aetolians."
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In this determined and desperate
                        mood, they fixed their camp on the extreme limit of their borders and
                        awaited the enemy. Messengers were despatched to Philip to announce their
                        critical situation, and in spite of his recapture of Iamphoryna and other
                        successes in Thrace he was compelled to abandon his northern campaign and go
                        to their assistance. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Rumours of the oath
                        which the Acarnanians had taken arrested the advance of the Aetolians; the
                        news of Philip's approach compelled them to withdraw into the interior of
                        their country. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Philip had made a forced
                        march to prevent the Acarnanians from being crushed, but he did not advance
                        beyond Dium, and on learning that the Aetolians had retired he returned to
                        Pella. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of spring Laevinus set
                        sail from Corcyra and after rounding the promontory of Leucata reached
                        Naupactus. He announced that he was going on to attack Anticyra, so that
                        Scopas and the Aetolians might be ready for him there. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Anticyra is situated in Locris, on the left hand as you
                        enter the Corinthian Gulf, and is only a short distance either by sea or
                        land from Naupactus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In three days the
                        attack began in both directions; the naval attack was the heavier one
                        because the ships were furnished with artillery and engines of every kind,
                        and it was the Romans who were delivering the attack on this side. In a few
                        days the place surrendered and was made over to the Aetolians; the booty in
                        accordance with the treaty became the property of the Romans. During the
                        siege a despatch was handed to Laevinus informing him that he had been made
                        consul, and that P. Sulpicius was coming to succeed him. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst he was there he was overtaken by a tedious
                        illness, and consequently arrived in Rome much later than was expected.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> M. Marcellus entered upon his
                        consulship on March 15, and in order to comply with traditional usage
                        summoned a meeting of the senate on the same day. The meeting was a purely
                        formal one; he announced that in his colleague's absence he should not
                        submit any proposals either in respect of the policy of the State or the
                        assignment of provinces. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "I am quite
                        aware," he told the senators, "that there are a large body of Sicilians
                        quartered in the country houses of my detractors round the City. I have no
                        intention of preventing them from publishing here in Rome the charges which
                        have been got up by my enemies; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> on the
                        contrary, I was prepared to give them an immediate opportunity of appearing
                        before the senate had they not pretended to be afraid of speaking about a
                        consul in his colleague's absence. When, however, my colleague has come I
                        shall not allow any business to be discussed before the Sicilians have been
                        brought into the senate house. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> M.
                        Cornelius has issued what is practically a formal summons throughout the
                        island in order that as many as possible might come to Rome to lay their
                        complaints against me. He has filled the City with letters containing false
                        information about a state of war existing in Sicily, solely that he may
                        tarnish my reputation." <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul's
                        speech won for him the reputation of being a man of moderation and
                        self-control. The senate adjourned, and it seemed as though there would be a
                        total suspension of business pending the other consul's arrival. As usual,
                        idleness led to discontent and grumbling. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The plebs were loud in their complaints about the way the war dragged on,
                        the devastation of the land round the City wherever Hannibal and his army
                        moved, the exhaustion of Italy by the constant levies, the almost annual
                        destruction of their armies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And now the
                        new consuls were both of them fond of war, far too enterprising and
                        ambitious, quite capable, even in a time of peace and quiet, of getting up a
                        war, and now that war was actually going on all the less likely to allow the
                        citizens any respite or breathing space. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> All this talk was suddenly interrupted by
                        a fire which broke out in the night in several places round the Forum on the
                        eve of the Quinquatrus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Seven shops which
                        were afterwards replaced by five were burning at the same time, as well as
                        the offices where the New Banks now stand. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Soon after, private buildings-the Basilicae did not yet exist-the Lautumiae,
                        the Fish Market and the Hall of Vesta were alight. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> It was with the utmost difficulty that the Temple of
                        Vesta was saved, mainly through the exertions of thirteen slaves, who were
                        afterwards manumitted at the public cost. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The fire raged all through the next day and there was not the smallest doubt
                        that it was the work of incendiaries, for fires started simultaneously in
                        several different places. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate
                        accordingly authorised the consul to give public notice that whoever
                        disclosed the names of those through whose agency the conflagration had been
                        started should, if he were a freeman, receive a reward, if a slave, his
                        liberty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Tempted by the offer of a reward,
                        a slave belonging to the Capuan family of the Calavii, called Manus, gave
                        information to the effect that his masters, together with five young Capuan
                        nobles, whose fathers had been beheaded by Q. Fulvius, had caused the fire
                        and were prepared to commit every description of crime if they were not
                        arrested. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They and their slaves were at
                        once apprehended. At first they endeavoured to throw suspicion upon the
                        informer and his statement. It was asserted that after being beaten by his
                        master, the day before he gave information, he had run away and had made out
                        of an occurrence which was really accidental the foundation of a false
                        charge. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When, however, the accused and
                        accuser were brought face to face and the slaves were examined under
                        torture, they all confessed. The masters as well as the slaves who had been
                        their accessories were all executed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        informer was rewarded with his liberty and 20,000 ases. </p>
                    <p> When Laevinus was passing Capua on his way to Rome he was surrounded by a
                        crowd of the inhabitants who implored him with tears to allow them to go to
                        Rome and try if they could not awaken the compassion of the senate and
                        persuade them not to allow Q. Flaccus to ruin them utterly and efface their
                        name. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Flaccus declared that he had no
                        personal feeling against the Capuans, it was as public enemies that he
                        regarded them, and should continue to do so as long as he knew that they
                        maintained their present attitude towards Rome. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> He had shut them up, he said, within their walls,
                        because if they got out anywhere they would prowl about the country like
                        wild beasts, and mangle and murder whatever came in their way. Some had
                        deserted to Hannibal, others had gone off to burn down Rome. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The consul would see in the half-burnt Forum the
                        result of their crime. They had tried to destroy the temple of Vesta, with
                        its perpetual fire, and the image which was <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> concealed in the sacred shrine-that image which Fate
                        had decreed to be the pledge and guarantee of Roman dominion. He considered
                        that it would be anything but safe to give the Capuans a chance of entering
                        the City. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After hearing this Laevinus
                        made the Capuans take an oath to Flaccus that they would return within five
                        days after receiving the reply of the senate. Then he ordered them to follow
                        him to Rome. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Surrounded by this crowd and
                        by a number of Sicilians who had also met him, he entered the City. It
                        seemed just as though he were bringing in a body of accusers against the two
                        commanders who had distinguished themselves by the <milestone n="17??"
                            unit="section"/> destruction of two famous cities and who would now have
                        to defend themselves against those they had vanquished. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first questions, however, which the
                        two consuls brought before the senate were those relating to foreign policy
                        and the allocation of the various commands. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Laevinus made his report on the situation in Macedonia and Greece, and
                        the unrest amongst the Aetolians, the Acarnanians and the Locrians. He also
                        gave details as to his own military and naval movements, and stated that he
                        had driven Philip, who was meditating an attack on the Aetolians, back into
                        the interior of his kingdom. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The legion
                        could now be safely withdrawn, as the fleet was sufficient to protect Italy
                        from any attempt on the part of the king. After this statement about himself
                        and the province of which he had had charge, he and his colleague raised the
                        question of the various commands. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        senate made the following dispositions. One consul was to operate in Italy
                        against Hannibal; the other was to succeed T. Otacilius in command of the
                        fleet and also to administer Sicily with L. Cincius as praetor. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> They were to take over the armies in Etruria and
                        Gaul, each of which comprised two legions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The two City legions which the consul Sulpicius had commanded the previous
                        year were sent to Gaul, and the consul who was to act in Italy was to
                        appoint to the command in Gaul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> C.
                        Calpurnius had his office of propraetor extended for a year, and was sent
                        into Etruria, Q. Fulvius also received a year's extension of his command at
                        Capua. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The composite force of citizens and
                        allies was reduced, one strong legion being formed out of the two; this
                        consisted of 5000 infantry and 300 cavalry, those who had served longest
                        being sent home. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The army of the allies
                        was reduced to 7000 infantry and 300 cavalry, the same rule being observed
                        as to the release of the veterans who had seen the longest service. In the
                        case of the retiring consul, Cn. Fulvius, no change was made; he retained
                        his army and his province, Apulia, for another year. His late colleague, P.
                        Sulpicius, received orders to disband his entire army with the exception of
                        the naval force. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Similarly the army which
                        M. Cornelius had commanded was to be sent home from Sicily. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The men of Cannae, who practically represented
                        two legions, were still to remain in the island, under the command of the
                        praetor L. Cincius. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> L. Cornelius had
                        commanded the same number of legions the previous year in Sardinia, and
                        these were now transferred to the praetor P. Manlius Vulso. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The consuls received instructions to see that in
                        raising the City legions, none were enrolled who had been in the army of M.
                        Valerius, or in that of Q. Fulvius. So the total number of Roman legions in
                        active service that year was not to exceed one-and-twenty. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the senate had finished making the
                        appointments, the consuls were ordered to ballot for their commands. Sicily
                        and the fleet fell to Marcellus, Italy and the campaign against Hannibal to
                        Laevinus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This result utterly appalled the
                        Sicilians, to whom it seemed as though all the horrors of the capture of
                        Syracuse were to be repeated. They were standing in full view of the
                        consuls, waiting anxiously for the result of the balloting, and when they
                        saw how it was decided, they broke out into loud laments and cries of
                        distress, which drew the eyes of all upon them for the moment, and became
                        the subject of much comment afterwards. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Clothing themselves in mourning garb they visited the houses of the senators
                        and assured each of them in turn that if Marcellus went back to Sicily with
                        the power and authority of a consul they would every one of them abandon his
                        city and quit the island for ever. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had,
                        they said, before shown himself vindictive and implacable towards them; what
                        would he do now, furious as he was at the Sicilians who had come to Rome to
                        complain of him? It would be better for the island to be buried beneath the
                        fires of Aetna or plunged in the depths of the sea than to be given up to
                        such an enemy to wreak his rage and vengeance on it. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> These remonstrances of the Sicilians were made to
                        individual nobles in their own homes, and gave rise to lively discussions,
                        in which sympathy with the sufferers and hostile sentiments towards
                        Marcellus were freely expressed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At last
                        they reached the senate. The consuls were requested to consult that body as
                        to the advisability of a rearrangement of the provinces. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> In addressing the House Marcellus said that had the
                        Sicilians been already admitted to an audience he would have taken a
                        different line, but as matters stood, he did not wish it to be open to any
                        one to say that they were afraid to lay their complaints against the man in
                        whose power they would shortly be placed. If, therefore, it made no
                        difference to his colleague he was prepared to exchange provinces with him.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He begged the senate not to make any
                        order, for since it would have been unfair to him for his colleague to have
                        chosen his province without recourse to the ballot, how much more unfair and
                        even humiliating to him would it be now to have the province which had
                        fallen to him formally transferred to his colleague! <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> After indicating their wish, without embodying it in a
                        decree, the senate adjourned, and the consuls themselves arranged to
                        exchange provinces. Marcellus was being hurried on by his destiny to meet
                        Hannibal, in order that, as he was the first Roman general to win <milestone
                            n="10??" unit="section"/> the distinction of a successful action with
                        him after so many disastrous ones, so he would be the last to contribute to
                        the Carthaginian's reputation by his own fall, and that just at the time
                        when the war was going most favourably for the Romans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the exchange of provinces had been
                        decided, the Sicilians were introduced into the senate. After expatiating at
                        some length upon the unbroken loyalty of Hiero to Rome, and claiming the
                        credit of it for the people rather than for the king, they proceeded: "There
                        were many reasons for the hatred we felt towards Hieronymus and afterwards
                        towards Hippocrates and Epicydes, but the principal one was their abandoning
                        Rome for Hannibal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was this that led
                        some of the foremost of our younger men to assassinate Hieronymus close to
                        the senate-house, and also induced some seventy who belonged to our noblest
                        houses to form a plot for the destruction of Epicydes and Hippocrates.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As Marcellus failed to support them by
                        bringing up his army to Syracuse at the time he promised, the plot was
                        disclosed by an informer, and they were all put to death by the tyrants.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcellus was really responsible for
                        the tyranny, owing to his ruthless sacking of Leontium. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> From that time the Syracusan leaders never ceased to go
                        over to Marcellus and undertake to deliver up the city to him whenever he
                        wished. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He would rather have taken it by
                        storm, but when all his attempts by sea and land failed, and he saw that the
                        thing was impossible, he chose as agents of the surrender an artisan called
                        Sosis and the Spaniard Moericus, rather than let the leaders of the city,
                        who had so often offered in vain to do so, undertake the task. No doubt he
                        considered that he would thus have more justification for plundering and
                        massacring the friends of Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Even if
                        the revolt to Hannibal had been the act of senate and people and not simply
                        of Hieronymus; if it had been the government of Syracuse who closed the
                        gates against Marcellus, and not the tyrants Hippocrates and Epicydes who
                        had ousted the government; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> if we had
                        warred against Rome in the spirit and temper of the Carthaginians, what
                        greater severity could Marcellus have shown towards us than that which he
                        actually practiced, unless he had blotted Syracuse out from the face of the
                        earth? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At all events, nothing has been
                        left to us beyond our walls and our houses stripped of everything, and the
                        defaced and despoiled temples of our gods, from which even the gods
                        themselves and their votive offerings have been carried off. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Many have been deprived of their land, so that
                        they have not even the bare soil on which to support themselves, and all who
                        belong to them, with the remains of their wrecked fortunes. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> We beg and entreat you, senators, if you cannot
                        order all that we have lost to be restored to us, at least to insist upon
                        the restitution of what can be found and identified." After they had stated
                        their grievances, Laevinus ordered them to withdraw, that their position
                        might be discussed. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> "Let them stop,"
                        exclaimed Marcellus, "that I may make my reply in their presence, since we
                        who conduct war on your behalf, senators, must do so on condition of those
                        whom we have vanquished coming forward as our accusers. Two cities have been
                        taken this year: let Capua call Fabius to account, and Syracuse, Marcellus."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they had been brought back into the
                        senate-house, Marcellus made the following speech: "I have not so far
                        forgotten, senators, the majesty of Rome or the dignity of my office as to
                        stoop to defend myself, as consul, against the charges of these Greeks, if
                        they concerned me alone. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The question is
                        not so much what I have done as what they ought to have suffered. Had they
                        not been enemies it is a matter of indifference whether I maltreated
                        Syracuse now or in Hiero's lifetime. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But
                        if they have proved false to us, opened their gates to the enemy, threatened
                        our envoys with drawn swords, shut their city and walls against us and
                        called in a Carthaginian army to protect them against us, who is there who
                        can feel any indignation at their having suffered hostile violence after
                        having practiced it? I declined the offers of their leaders to deliver up
                        the city, and looked upon Sosis and the Spaniard Moericus as much more
                        suitable persons to be trusted in a matter of such importance. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> As you make their humble station in life a
                        reproach to others, you do not yourselves belong to the lowest class in
                        Syracuse, and yet who amongst you promised to open your gates and admit my
                        armed force into your city? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those who did
                        this are the objects of your hatred and execration; not even in this place
                        do you shrink from insulting them, showing thereby how far you yourselves
                        were from contemplating anything of the kind. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That low social position, senators, which these men
                        make a ground of reproach, proves most clearly that I discouraged no man who
                        was willing to render effectual help to the commonwealth. Before commencing
                        the siege of Syracuse, I made various attempts at a peaceful settlement,
                        first by sending envoys and then by personal interviews with the leaders.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was only when I found that no
                        reverence for the persons of my envoys protected them from violence and that
                        I was unable to get any reply from the leaders with whom I conferred at
                        their gates, that I took action and finally took the city by storm, after a
                        vast expenditure of toil and exertion by sea and land. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As to the incidents attending its capture, these men
                        would be more justified in laying their complaints before Hannibal and his
                        vanquished Carthaginians than before the senate of the people who vanquished
                        them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If, senators, I had intended to
                        conceal my spoliation of Syracuse I should never have adorned the City of
                        Rome with its spoils. With regard to what I, as conqueror, took away or
                        bestowed in individual cases, I am quite satisfied that I acted in
                        accordance with the laws of war, according to the deserts of each
                        individual. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Whether you approve of my
                        action or not is a question that concerns the State more than it concerns
                        me. I only did my duty, but it will be a serious matter for the republic, if
                        by rescinding my acts you make other generals in the future more remiss in
                        doing their duty. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And since you have
                        heard what both the Sicilians and I have had to say in each other's
                        presence, we will leave the House together in order that the senate may be
                        able to discuss the matter more freely in my absence." The Sicilians were
                        accordingly dismissed; Marcellus proceeded to the Capitol to enrol troops.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The other consul, Laevinus, then consulted
                        the senate as to what reply was to be given to the petition of the
                        Sicilians. There was a long debate and great divergence of opinion.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Many of those present supported the
                        view expressed by T. Manlius Torquatus. They were of opinion that
                        hostilities ought to have been directed against the tyrants, who were the
                        common enemies of Syracuse and of Rome. The city ought to have been allowed
                        to surrender, not taken by storm, and when surrendered it ought to have had
                        its own laws and liberties guaranteed to it, instead of being ruined by war
                        after it had been worn out by a deplorable servitude under its tyrants.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The struggle between the tyrants and
                        the Roman general in which Syracuse was the prize of victory had resulted in
                        the utter destruction of a most famous and beautiful city, the granary and
                        treasury of the Roman people. The commonwealth had frequently experienced
                        its generosity, especially in the present Punic war, and the City had been
                        embellished by its munificent gifts. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If
                        Hiero, that loyal supporter of the power of Rome, could rise from the dead,
                        with what face would any one dare to show him either Rome or Syracuse? In
                        the one-his own city-he would see universal spoliation and a large part of
                        it burnt, and as he approached the other he would see just outside its
                        walls, almost within its gates, the spoils of his country. This was the line
                        of argument urged by those who sought to create a feeling against the consul
                        and evoke sympathy for the Sicilians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        majority, however, did not take such an <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        unfavourable view of his conduct, and a decree was passed confirming the
                        acts of Marcellus both during the war and after his victory, and declaring
                        that the senate would for the future make the interests of the Syracusans
                        their charge and would instruct Laevinus to safeguard the property of the
                        citizens so far as he could without inflicting any loss on the State.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Two senators were sent to the Capitol
                        to request the consul to come back, and after the Sicilians had again been
                        brought in, the decree was read to them. Some kind words were addressed to
                        the envoys and they were dismissed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Before
                        they left the House they flung themselves on their knees before Marcellus
                        and implored him to forgive them for what they had said in their anxiety to
                        gain sympathy and relief in their distress. They also begged him to take
                        them and their city under his protection, and look upon them as his clients.
                        The consul promised that he would do so, and after a few gracious words
                        dismissed them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Capuans were then admitted to an
                        audience. Their case was a harder one, and their appeal for mercy was all
                        the stronger. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They could not deny that
                        they deserved punishment, and there were no tyrants on whom they could throw
                        the blame, but they considered that they had paid an adequate penalty after
                        so many of their senators had been carried off by poison, and so many had
                        died under the axe. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some of their nobles,
                        they said, were still living, who had not been driven by the consciousness
                        of guilt into doing away with themselves, nor had the victor in his wrath
                        condemned them to death. These men begged that they and their families might
                        be set at liberty, and some portion of their goods restored to them.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were for the most part Roman
                        citizens, connected with Roman families by intermarriage. After the envoys
                        had withdrawn, there was some doubt as to whether they ought to summon Q.
                        Fulvius from Capua-the consul Claudius had died soon after its capture-in
                        order that the matter might be debated in the presence of the general whose
                        proceedings were being called in question. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        This had just been done in the case of Marcellus and the Sicilians. When,
                        however, some senators were seen sitting in the House who had been through
                        the whole of the siege-M. Atilius Regulus and Caius the brother of Flaccus,
                        both on his staff, and Q. Minucius and L. Veturius Philo, who had been
                        members of Claudius' staff-they would not have Q. Fulvius recalled, nor the
                        hearing of the Capuans adjourned. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Amongst
                        those who had been at Capua, the man whose opinion carried most weight was
                        M. Atilius, and he was asked what course he would advise. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He replied: "I believe I was present at the military
                        council which met after the fall of Capua, when the consuls made enquiry as
                        to which of the Capuans had assisted our republic. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> They discovered only two, and those were women. One was
                        Vestia Oppia of Atella, who was living in Capua and who offered sacrifices
                        daily for the welfare and triumph of Rome; the other was Cluvia Pacula, at
                        one time a woman of loose character, who secretly supplied the starving
                        prisoners with food. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The rest of the
                        Capuans were just as hostile to us as the Carthaginians themselves, and
                        those whom Q. Fulvius executed were selected rather on account of their
                        higher rank than of their greater guilt. I do not quite see how the senate
                        is competent to deal with the Capuans, who are Roman citizens, without an
                        order of the people. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the revolt of
                        the Satricans, the course adopted by our ancestors was for a tribune of the
                        plebs, M. Antistius, to bring the matter first before the Assembly, and a
                        resolution was passed empowering the senate to decide what should be done to
                        them. I therefore advise that we arrange with the tribunes of the plebs for
                        one or more of them to propose a resolution to that body empowering us to
                        settle the fate o f the Capuans." <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> L.
                        Atilius, tribune of the plebs, was authorised by the senate to put the
                        question in the following terms: <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> "Whereas
                        the inhabitants of Capua, Atella and Calatia, and also the dwellers in the
                        valley of the Sabatus have yielded themselves to the proconsul Fulvius to be
                        at the arbitrament and disposal of the people of Rome, and whereas they have
                        surrendered divers persons together with <milestone n="13??" unit="section"
                        /> themselves, as also their land and city with all things therein, sacred
                        and profane, together with their goods and chattels and whatsoever else they
                        had in possession, I demand of you Quirites to know what it is your will and
                        pleasure shall be done in regard of all these persons and things?"
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The resolution of the Assembly ran
                        thus: "What the senate, or the greater part of those who are present, shall,
                        on oath, decree and determine, that we will and order shall be done." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The plebs having thus resolved, the senate
                        made the following orders: First they restored their liberty and property to
                        Oppia and Cluvia; if they wished to ask the senate for a further reward,
                        they were to come to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Separate
                        decrees were made in the case of each of the Capuan families; it is not
                        worth while giving a complete enumeration. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Some were to have their property confiscated, they themselves with their
                        wives and children were to be sold, with the exception of those of their
                        daughters who had married outside the territory before they passed under the
                        power of Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Others were to be thrown
                        into chains, and their fate settled afterwards. In the case of the rest, the
                        question whether their property should be confiscated or not depended upon
                        the amount at which they were assessed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Where property was restored it was to include all the captured live stock
                        except the horses, all the slaves except the adult males, and everything
                        which was not attached to the soil. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was
                        further decreed that the populations of Capua, Atella, Calatia and the
                        valley of the Sabatus should all retain their <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> liberty, except those who themselves, or whose parents
                        had been with the enemy, but none of them could become a Roman citizen or a
                        member of the Latin League. None of those who had been in Capua during the
                        siege could remain in the city or its neighbourhood beyond a certain date; a
                        place of residence was assigned to them beyond the Tiber at some distance
                        from it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those who had not been in Capua
                        during the war, nor in any revolted Campanian city, were to be settled to
                        the north of the Liris in the direction of Rome; <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> those who had gone over to the side of Rome before
                        Hannibal came to Capua were to be removed to this side of the Volturnus, and
                        no one was to possess any land or building within fifteen miles of the sea.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Those who had been deported beyond
                        the Tiber were forbidden to acquire or to hold either for themselves or
                        their posterity landed property anywhere except in the territories of Veii,
                        Sutrium and Nepete, and in no case was such holding to exceed fifty jugera.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The property of all the senators and
                        of all who had held any magistracy in Capua, Atella and Calatia was ordered
                        to be sold in Capua, and those persons whom it had been decided to sell into
                        slavery were sent to Rome and sold there. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        The disposal of the images and bronze statues which were alleged to have
                        been taken from the enemy, and the question which of them were sacred and
                        which profane, were referred to the Pontifical College. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> After hearing these decrees. the Capuans were dismissed
                        in a much more sorrowful state of mind than that in which they had come. It
                        was no longer Q. Fulvius' cruelty to them, but the injustice of the gods and
                        their accursed fate that they denounced. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the departure of the Sicilian and
                        Capuan envoys, the enrolment of the new legions was completed. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Then came the question of providing the fleet
                        with its proper complement of rowers. There was not a sufficient number of
                        men available, nor was there any money at the time in the treasury with
                        which to procure them or to pay them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In
                        view of this state of things the consuls issued an order requiring private
                        individuals to furnish seamen in proportion to their income and their rank,
                        as they had done on a previous occasion, and also to supply them with thirty
                        days' provision and pay. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This order
                        excited such a widespread feeling of indignation and resentment that if the
                        people had had a leader they would have risen in insurrection. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls, they said, after ruining the
                        Sicilians and Capuans, had seized upon the Roman plebs as their next victim
                        to mangle and destroy. "After being drained by the war-tax," they
                        complained, "for so many years, we have nothing left but the bare and wasted
                        soil. Our houses have been burnt by the enemy, our slaves who tilled our
                        fields have been appropriated by the State, first buying them for a few
                        coppers to make soldiers of them, and now requisitioning them for seamen.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whatever silver or gold we had has
                        been taken to pay the rowers and furnish the annual war-tax. No resort to
                        force, no exercise of authority can compel us to give what we do not
                        possess. Let the consuls sell our goods, then let them glut their rage on
                        our bodies which are all we have left; nothing remains with which we can
                        even ransom ourselves." <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Language of this
                        kind was used not only in private conversation, but openly in the Forum,
                        before the very eyes of the consuls. A vast crowd had gathered round the
                        tribunal, uttering angry cries, and the consuls were powerless to allay the
                        agitation either by fair speeches or by threats. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Ultimately they announced that they would give them
                        three days to think the matter over, and they themselves devoted that time
                        to seeing whether they could not find some way out of the difficulty.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The next day they called the senate
                        together to consider the matter, and many arguments were advanced to prove
                        that the plebs were acting fairly and reasonably in their protest. At last
                        the discussion came round to this point, that whether fair or unfair the
                        burden must fall on the individual citizens. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> From what source, it was asked, could they procure
                        seamen and sailors, when there was no money in the treasury, and how could
                        they keep their hold on Sicily, or render the shores of Italy safe against
                        any attempt by Philip, if they had no fleet? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As there seemed to be no solution of the
                        difficulty and a kind of mental torpor appeared to beset the senate, the
                        consul Laevinus came to the rescue. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "As
                        the magistrates," he said, "take precedence of the senate and the senate of
                        the people in honour and dignity; so they ought to lead the way in
                        discharging unpleasant and difficult tasks. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> If, in laying any obligation on an inferior, you have first decided that
                        it is binding on you and those connected with you, you will find that all
                        are more ready to obey you. They do not feel an expense to be burdensome
                        when they see each of their leaders bearing more than his due share of it.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We want the Roman people to have
                        fleets and to equip them, we want each citizen to furnish rowers and not to
                        shirk his duty; then let us impose the burden on ourselves first of all.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Let us, every one of us, bring our
                        gold and silver and bronze money, tomorrow, to the treasury, only reserving
                        the rings for ourselves, our wives and our children, and the bullae for our
                        boys. Those who have wives and daughters may keep an ounce of gold for each
                        of them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With regard to silver, those who
                        have occupied curule chairs should keep the plating on their horse-trappings
                        and two pounds of silver that they may have a dish and saltcellar for the
                        gods. All the other senators should keep only one pound of silver.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the case of bronze coin let us
                        retain 5000 ases for each household. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All
                        the rest of our gold and silver and money let us place in the hands of the
                        commissioners of the treasury. No formal resolution should be passed; our
                        contributions must be strictly voluntary; and our mutual rivalry to assist
                        the commonwealth may stir up the equestrian order to emulate us, and after
                        them, the plebs. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This is the only course
                        which we consuls have been able to devise after our lengthy discussion, and
                        we beg you to adopt it with the help of the gods. As long as the
                        commonwealth is safe, each man's property is safe under its protection, but
                        if you desert it, it will be in vain that you try to keep what you have."
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These suggestions were so favourably
                        received that the consuls were even thanked for them. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> No sooner did the senate adjourn, than they each
                        brought their gold and silver and bronze to the treasury, and they were so
                        eager to be among the first to have their names inscribed in the public
                        register that the commissioners were not able to take over the amounts or
                        the clerks to enter them fast enough. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        equestrian order showed quite as much zeal as the senate, and the plebs were
                        not behind the equestrian order. In this way, without any formal order or
                        compulsion by the magistrates, the full complement of rowers was made up,
                        and the State put in a position to pay them. As the preparations for war
                        were now complete the consuls started for their respective provinces. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At no period of the war were the
                        Carthaginians and the Romans alike subjected to greater vicissitudes of
                        fortune, or to more rapid alternations of hope and fear. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> In the provinces, the disasters in Spain on the one
                        hand and the successes in Sicily on the other filled the Romans with mingled
                        feelings of sorrow and joy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In Italy the
                        loss of Tarentum was felt to be a grievous blow, but the unexpected stand by
                        the garrison in the citadel made all hearts glad, and the sudden panic at
                        the prospect of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> Rome being besieged and
                        stormed gave way to universal rejoicings when Capua was taken a few days
                        later. In the campaign overseas a kind of balance was struck. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Philip began hostilities at an inopportune moment
                        for Rome, but in the new alliance with the Aetolians and Attalus, king of
                        Pergamum, it seemed as though Fortune were giving a pledge of Rome's
                        dominion in the East. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians,
                        again, felt that the capture of Tarentum was a set-off against the loss of
                        Capua, and though they prided themselves on having marched unopposed up to
                        the walls of Rome they were mortified at the futility of their enterprise,
                        and humiliated by <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the contempt shown for
                        them when a Roman army marched out on its way to Spain whilst they were
                        actually lying under the very walls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Even
                        in Spain itself, where the destruction of two great generals with their
                        armies had raised their hopes of finally expelling the Romans and finishing
                        the war, the higher their hopes had been, the greater the disgust they felt
                        at their victory being robbed of all its importance by L. Marcius, who was
                        not even a regular general. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So whilst
                        Fortune was holding the scales evenly and everything was in suspense, both
                        sides felt the same hopes and fears as though the war were only just
                        beginning. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal's principal cause of anxiety was
                        the effect produced by the fall of Capua. It was generally felt that the
                        Romans had shown greater determination in attacking than he had in defending
                        the place, and this alienated many of the Italian communities from him.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He could not occupy them all with
                        garrisons unless he was prepared to weaken his army by detaching numerous
                        small units from it; a course at that time highly inexpedient. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> On the other hand he did not dare to withdraw any
                        of his garrisons and so leave the loyalty of his allies to depend upon their
                        hopes and fears. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His temperament, prone as
                        it was to rapacity and cruelty, led him to plunder the places which he was
                        unable to defend, in order that they might be left to the enemy waste and
                        barren. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This evil policy had evil results
                        for him, for it aroused horror and loathing not only amongst the actual
                        sufferers but amongst all who heard of them. The Roman consul was not slow
                        in sounding the feelings of those cities where any hope of recovering them
                        had shown itself. Amongst these was the city of Salapia. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Two of its most prominent citizens were Dasius and
                        Blattius. Dasius was friendly to Hannibal; Blattius favoured the interests
                        of Rome as far as he safely could, and had sent secret messages to Marcellus
                        holding out hopes that the city might be surrendered. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> But the thing could not be carried through without the
                        help of Dasius. For a long time he hesitated, but at last he addressed
                        himself to Dasius, not so much in the hope of success as because no better
                        plan presented itself. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Dasius was opposed
                        to the project, and by way of injuring his political rival disclosed the
                        affair to Hannibal. Hannibal summoned them both before his tribunal.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they appeared, he was occupied
                        with business, intending to go into their case as soon as he was at liberty,
                        and the two men, accuser and accused, stood waiting, apart from the crowd.
                        Whilst thus waiting Blattius approached Dasius on the subject of the
                        surrender. At this open and barefaced conduct, Dasius called out that the
                        surrender of the city was being mooted under the very eyes of Hannibal.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal and those round him felt
                        that the very audacity of the thing made the charge improbable, and regarded
                        it as due to spite and jealousy, since it was easy to invent such an
                        accusation in the absence of witnesses. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        They were accordingly dismissed. Blattius, however, did not desist from his
                        venturesome project. He was perpetually urging the matter and showing what a
                        beneficial thing it would be for them both and for their city. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> At last he succeeded in effecting the surrender
                        of the city with its garrison of 5000 Numidians. But the surrender could
                        only be effected with a heavy loss of life. The garrison were by far the
                        finest cavalry in the Carthaginian army, and although they were taken by
                        surprise and could make no use of their horses in the city, they seized
                        their arms in the confusion and attempted to cut their way out. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> When they found escape impossible they fought to
                        the last man. Not more than fifty fell into the hands of the enemy alive.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The loss of this troop of horse was a
                        heavier blow to Hannibal than the loss of Salapia; never from that time was
                        the Carthaginian superior in cavalry, hitherto by far his most efficient
                        arm. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this period the privations of the
                        Roman garrison in the citadel of Tarentum had become almost insupportable;
                        the men and their commandant M. Livius placed all their hopes in the arrival
                        of supplies sent from Sicily. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To secure a
                        safe passage for these along the coast of Italy, a squadron of about twenty
                        vessels was stationed at Regium. The fleet and the transports were under the
                        command of D. Quinctius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was a man of
                        humble birth, but his many deeds of gallantry had gained him a high military
                        reputation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had only five ships to
                        begin with, the largest of these-two triremes-had been assigned to him by
                        Marcellus; subsequently, owing to the effective use he made of these, three
                        quinqueremes were <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> added to his command,
                        and at last, by compelling the allied cities, Regium, Velliea and Paestum to
                        furnish the ships which they were bound by treaty to supply, he made up the
                        above-mentioned squadron of twenty vessels. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> As this fleet was setting out from Regium, and was opposite Sapriportis,
                        a place about fifteen miles from Tarentum, it fell in with a Tarentine
                        fleet, also of twenty ships, under the command of Democrates. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The Roman commander, not anticipating a fight,
                        had all sail set; he had, however, got together his full complement of
                        rowers while he was in the neighbourhood of Croton and Sybaris, and his
                        fleet was excellently equipped and manned, considering the size of the
                        vessels. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It so happened that the wind
                        completely died down just as the enemy came into sight, and there was ample
                        time to lower the sails and get the rowers and soldiers into readiness for
                        the approaching conflict. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Seldom have two
                        regular fleets gone into action with such determination as these small
                        flotillas, for they were fighting for larger issues than their own success.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Tarentines hoped that as they had
                        already recovered their city from the Romans after the lapse of nearly a
                        century, so they might now rescue their citadel, by cutting off the enemy's
                        supplies after they had deprived them of the mastery of the sea. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The Romans were eager to show, by retaining
                        their hold on the citadel, that Tarentum had not been lost in fair fight.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but by a foul and treacherous stroke.
                        So, when the signal was given on each side, they rowed with their prows
                        straight at each other; there was no backing or maneuvering, nor did they
                        let go of any ship when once they had grappled and boarded. They fought at
                        such close quarters that they not only discharged missiles, but even used
                        their swords in hand-to-hand fighting. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        The prows were locked together and remained so while the hinder part of the
                        vessel was pushed about by the oars of hostile ships. The vessels were so
                        crowded together that hardly any missile failed to reach its aim or fell
                        into the water. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> They pressed forward
                        front to front like a line of infantry, and the combatants made their way
                        from ship to ship. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Conspicuous amongst
                        all was the fight between the two ships which had led their respective lines
                        and were the first to engage. </p>
                    <p> Quinctius himself was in the Roman ship, and in the Tarentine vessel was a
                        man named Nico Perco, who hated the Romans for private as well as public
                        grounds, and who was equally hated by them, for he was one of the party who
                        betrayed Tarentum to Hannibal. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Whilst
                        Quinctius was fighting and encouraging his men, Nico took him unawares and
                        ran him through with his spear. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> He fell
                        headlong over the prow, and the victorious Tarentine springing on to the
                        ship dislodged the enemy, who were thrown into confusion by the loss of
                        their leader. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The foreship was now in the
                        hands of the Tarentines, and the Romans in a compact body were with
                        difficulty defending the hinder part of the vessel, when another of the
                        hostile triremes suddenly appeared astern. Between the two the Roman ship
                        was captured. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The sight of the admiral's
                        ship in the enemy's hands created a panic, and the remainder of the fleet
                        fled in all directions; some were sunk, others were hurriedly rowed to land
                        and were seized by the people of Thurium and Metapontum. Very few of the
                        transports which were following with supplies fell into the enemy's hands;
                        the rest, shifting their sails to meet the changing winds, were carried out
                        to sea. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> An affair took place at Tarentum
                        during this time which led to a very different result. <milestone n="21"
                            unit="section"/> A foraging force of 4000 Tarentines were dispersed
                        through the fields, and Livius, the Roman commandant, who was always looking
                        out for a chance of striking a blow, sent C. Persius, an able and energetic
                        officer, with 2500 men from the citadel to attack them. <milestone n="22"
                            unit="section"/> He fell upon them while they were dispersed in
                        scattered groups all through the fields, and after inflicting great and
                        widespread slaughter, drove the few who escaped in headlong flight through
                        their half-opened gates into the town. So matters were equalised as far as
                        Tarentum was concerned; the Romans were victorious by land, and the
                        Tarentines by sea. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> Both were alike
                        disappointed in their hopes of obtaining the corn which had been within
                        their view. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laevinus' arrival in Sicily had been
                        looked forward to by all the friendly cities, both those who had been old
                        allies of Rome, and those who had recently joined her. His first and most
                        important task was the settlement of the affairs of Syracuse, which, as
                        peace had only quite recently been established, were still in confusion.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he had accomplished this task he
                        marched to Agrigentum, where the embers of war were still smouldering, and a
                        Carthaginian garrison still in occupation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Fortune favoured his enterprise. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hanno was
                        in command, but the Carthaginians placed their chief reliance on Muttines
                        and his Numidians. He was scouring the island from end to end and carrying
                        off plunder from the friends of Rome; neither force nor stratagem could keep
                        him from entering Agrigentum and leaving it on his raids whenever he chose.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His reputation as a dashing officer
                        was beginning to eclipse that of the commandant himself, and at last created
                        so much jealousy that even the successes he gained were unwelcome to Hanno,
                        because of the man who gained them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It
                        ended in his giving the command of the cavalry to his own son in the hope
                        that by depriving Muttines of his post he would also destroy his influence
                        with the Numidians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It had just the
                        opposite effect, for the ill-feeling created only made Muttines more
                        popular, and he showed his resentment at the injustice done to him by at
                        once entering into secret negotiations with Laevinus for the surrender of
                        the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When his emissaries had come to
                        an understanding with the consul and arranged the plan of operations, the
                        Numidians seized the gate leading to the sea after driving off or massacring
                        the men on guard, and admitted a Roman force which was in readiness into the
                        city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As they were marching in serried
                        ranks into the forum and the heart of the city, amidst great confusion,
                        Hanno, thinking it was only a riotous disturbance caused by the Numidians,
                        such as had often happened before, went to allay the tumult. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> When, however, he saw in the distance a larger
                        body of troops than the Numidians amounted to, and when the well-known
                        battle shout of the Romans reached his ears, he at once took to flight
                        before a missile could reach him. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Escaping with Epicydes through a gate on the other side of the city, and
                        attended by a small escort, he reached the shore. Here they were fortunate
                        enough to find a small ship, in which they sailed across to Africa,
                        abandoning Sicily, for which they had fought through so many years, to their
                        victorious enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The mixed population of
                        Sicilians and Carthaginians whom they had left behind, made no attempt at
                        resistance, but rushed away in wild flight, and, as the exits were all
                        closed, they were slaughtered round the gates. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> When he had gained possession of the place, Laevinus
                        ordered the men who had been at the head of affairs in Agrigentum to be
                        scourged and beheaded; the rest of the population he sold with the plunder,
                        and sent all the money to Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When the fate of the Agrigentines became
                        generally known throughout Sicily, all the cities at once declared for Rome.
                        In a short time twenty towns were clandestinely surrendered and six taken by
                        storm, and as many as forty voluntarily surrendered on terms. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> The consul meted out rewards and punishments to
                        the chief men in these cities, according to each man's deserts, and now that
                        the Sicilians had at last laid arms aside he obliged them to turn their
                        attention to agriculture. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> That fertile
                        island was not only capable of supporting its own population, but had on
                        many occasions relieved the scarcity in Rome, and the consul intended that
                        it should do so again if necessary. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        Agathyrna had become the seat of a motley population, numbering some 4000
                        men, made up of all sorts of characters-refugees, insolvent debtors-most of
                        them had committed capital offences at the time when they were living in
                        their own cities and under their own laws and afterwards when similarity of
                        fortunes arising from various causes had drawn them together at Agathyrna.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Laevinus did not think it safe to
                        leave these men behind in the island, as a material for fresh disturbances,
                        whilst things were settling down under the newly established peace. The
                        Regians too would find a body so experienced in brigandage as they were,
                        very useful; accordingly Laevinus transported them all to Italy. As far as
                        Sicily was concerned, the state of war was put an end to this year. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the commencement of spring P. Scipio
                        issued orders for the allied contingents to muster at Tarraco. He then
                        launched his ships and led the fleet and transports to the mouth of the
                        Ebro, where he had also ordered the legions to concentrate from their winter
                        quarters. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He then left Tarraco, with an
                        allied contingent of 5000 men for the army. On his arrival he felt that he
                        ought to address some words of encouragement to his men, especially to the
                        veterans who had gone through such terrible disasters. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He accordingly ordered a parade and addressed the
                        troops in the following words: "No commander before my time, who was new to
                        his troops, has been in a position to express well-deserved thanks to his
                        men before he made use of their services. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Fortune laid me under obligations to you before I saw my province or my
                        camp, first because of the devoted affection you showed towards my father
                        and my uncle during their <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> lifetime and
                        after their death, and then again, because of the courage with which you
                        kept your hold on the province when it was apparently lost after their
                        terrible defeat, and so retained it unimpaired for Rome and for me their
                        successor. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It must be our aim and object
                        now with the help of heaven not so much to maintain our own footing in Spain
                        as to prevent the Carthaginians from maintaining theirs. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> We must not remain stationary here, defending the bank
                        of the Ebro against the enemy's passage of the river; we must cross over
                        ourselves and shift the seat of war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To
                        some of you at least, I fear that this plan may seem too large and bold when
                        you remember the defeats we have lately sustained, and when you think of my
                        youth. No man is less likely to forget those fatal battles in Spain than I
                        am, for my father and my uncle were killed within thirty days of each other,
                        so that my family was visited by one death upon another. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "But though I am almost heart-broken at
                        the orphanhood and desolation of our house, the good fortune and courage of
                        our race forbid me to despair of the State. It has been our lot and destiny
                        to conquer in all great wars only after we have been defeated. Not to
                        mention the earlier wars-Porsena and the Gauls and the Samnites-I will take
                        these two Punic wars. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> How many fleets and
                        generals and armies were lost in the first war! And what about this war?
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In all our defeats I was either
                        present in person, or where I was not, I felt them more keenly than any one.
                        The Trebia, Lake Thrasymenus, Cannae-what are they but records of Roman
                        consuls and their armies cut to pieces? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Add to these the defection of Italy, of the greatest part of Sicily, of
                        Sardinia, and then the crowning terror and panic-the Carthaginian camp
                        pitched between the Anio and the walls of Rome, and the sight of the
                        victorious Hannibal almost within our gates. In the midst of this utter
                        collapse one thing stood unshaken and unimpaired, the courage of the Roman
                        people; it and it alone raised up and sustained all that lay prostrate in
                        the dust. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> You, my soldiers, under the
                        conduct and auspices of my father were the first to retrieve the defeat of
                        Cannae by barring the way to Hasdrubal when he was marching to the Alps and
                        Italy. Had he joined forces with his brother the name of Rome would have
                        perished; this success of yours held us up under those defeats. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Now, by the goodness of heaven, everything is
                        going in our favour; the situation in Italy and Sicily is becoming better
                        and more hopeful day by day. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In Sicily,
                        Syracuse and Agrigentum have been captured, the enemy has been everywhere
                        expelled and the whole of the island acknowledges the sovereignty of Rome.
                        In Italy, Arpi has been recovered and Capua taken, Hannibal in his hurried
                        flight has traversed the whole breadth of Italy from Rome to the furthest
                        corners of Bruttium, and his one prayer is that he may be allowed to make a
                        safe retreat and get away from the land of his enemies. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> At a time when one defeat followed close on the heels
                        of another, and heaven itself seemed to be fighting on Hannibal's side, you,
                        my soldiers, together with my two parents-let me honour them both with the
                        same appellation-upheld in this country the tottering fortunes of Rome.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> What then can be more foolish than
                        for you to fail in courage now when all is going on prosperously and happily
                        there? As to recent events, I could wish that they had caused as little pain
                        to me as to you. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> "The immortal gods who watch over the
                        fortunes of the dominions of Rome, and who moved the electors in their
                        centuries to insist with one voice upon the supreme command being given to
                        me-the gods, I say, are assuring us through auguries and auspices and even
                        through visions of the night that all will go successfully and happily with
                        us. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> My own heart too, hitherto my truest
                        prophet, presages that Spain will be ours and that ere long all who bear the
                        name of Carthage will be driven away from this soil and will cover sea and
                        land in their shameful flight. What my breast thus divines is confirmed by
                        solid reasoning from facts. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Owing to the
                        maltreatment they have received their allies are sending envoys to us to
                        appeal for protection. Their three generals are at variance, almost in
                        active opposition to each other, and after breaking up their army into three
                        separate divisions have marched away into different parts of the country.
                            <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> The same misfortune has overtaken
                        them which was so disastrous to us, they are being deserted by their allies
                        as we were by the Celtiberians, and the army which proved so fatal to my
                        father and my uncle they have split up into separate bodies. Their domestic
                        quarrel will not let them act in unison, and now that they are divided they
                        will not be able to withstand us. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                        Welcome, soldiers, the omen of the name I bear, be loyal to a Scipio who is
                        the offspring of your late commander, the scion of a stock which has been
                        cut down. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> Come on then, my veterans, and
                        lead a new army and a new commander across the Ebro into the lands which you
                        have so often traversed and where you have given so many proofs of your
                        prowess and your courage. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> You recognise a
                        likeness to my father and my uncle in figure, face, and expression, I will
                        soon show you that I am like them also in character and fidelity and
                        courage, so that each of <milestone n="25??" unit="section"/> you may say
                        that the Scipio who was his old commander has either come to life again or
                        reappeared in his son." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After kindling the spirits of his men by
                        this speech, he crossed the Ebro with 25,000 infantry and 2500 cavalry,
                        leaving M. Silanus in charge of the country north of the Ebro with 3000
                        infantry and 300 cavalry. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As the
                        Carthaginian armies had all taken different routes, some of his staff urged
                        him to attack the one which was nearest, but he thought that if he did that
                        there would be a danger of their all concentrating against him, and he would
                        be no match for the three together. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                        decided to begin with an attack on New Carthage, a city not only rich in its
                        own resources, but also with the enemy's war-stores, their arms, their
                        war-chest and hostages drawn from every part of Spain. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> It possessed an additional advantage in its situation,
                        as it afforded a convenient base for the invasion of Africa, and commanded a
                        harbour capable of holding any fleet however large, and, as far as I know,
                        the only one of the kind on that part of the coast which abuts on our sea.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No one knew of his intended march
                        except C. Laelius, who was sent round with his fleet and instructed to
                        regulate the pace of his vessels so that he might enter the harbour at the
                        same time that the army showed itself. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Seven days after leaving the Ebro, the land and sea forces reached New
                        Carthage simultaneously. The Roman camp was fixed opposite the north side of
                        the city, and to guard against attacks from the rear was strengthened by a
                        double rampart; the front was protected by the nature of the ground.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The following is the situation of New
                        Carthage. There is a bay about half-way down the coast of Spain, opening to
                        the south-west and stretching inland about two-and-a-half miles. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> A small island at the mouth of the harbour forms
                        a breakwater and shelters it from all winds, except those from the
                        south-west. From the innermost part of the bay stretches a promontory on the
                        slopes of which the city stands, surrounded on the east; and south by the
                        sea. On the west it is enclosed by a shallow sheet of water which extends
                        northward and varies in depth with the rise and fall of the tide. A neck of
                        land about a quarter of a mile in length connects the city with the
                        mainland. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Roman commander did not
                        throw an earthwork across this isthmus, though it would have cost him very
                        little trouble to do so; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> whether it was
                        that he wished to impress the enemy with his confidence in his strength, or
                        because he wished to have an unimpeded retirement in his frequent advances
                        against the city. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the necessary intrenchments were
                        completed he drew up the vessels in the harbour as though he were going to
                        blockade the place by sea. Then he was rowed round the fleet and warned the
                        captains to be careful in keeping a look-out by night, as an enemy when
                        first besieged makes counter-attacks in all directions. On his return to
                        camp he explained to his soldiers his plan of operations and his reasons for
                        beginning the campaign with an attack upon a solitary city in preference to
                        anything else. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After they were mustered on
                        parade he made the following speech to them: "Soldiers, if any one supposes
                        that you have been brought here for the sole purpose of attacking this city,
                        he is making more account of the work before you than of the advantage you
                        will reap from it. You are going, it is true, to attack the walls of a
                        single city, but in the capture of this one city you will have secured the
                        whole of Spain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here are the hostages
                        taken from all the nobles and kings and tribes, and when once these are in
                        your power, everything which the Carthaginians now hold will be given up to
                        you. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here is the enemy's war-chest,
                        without which they cannot keep up the war, seeing that they have to pay
                        their mercenaries, and the money will be of the utmost service to us in
                        gaining over the barbarians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here are
                        their artillery, their armoury, the whole of their engines of war, which
                        will at once provide you with all you want, and leave the enemy destitute of
                        all he needs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And what is more, we shall
                        become masters, not only of a most wealthy and beautiful city, but also of a
                        most commodious harbour, from which all that is requisite for the purposes
                        of war, both by sea and land, will be supplied. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Great as our gains will be, the deprivations which the
                        enemy suffers will be still greater. Here is their stronghold, their
                        granary, their treasure, their arsenal-everything is stored here. Here is
                        their direct route from Africa. This is their only naval base between the
                        Pyrenees and Gades; from this Africa threatens the whole of Spain.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But I see that you are all perfectly
                        ready; let us pass over to the assault on New Carthage, with our full
                        strength and a courage that knows no fear." The men all shouted with one
                        voice, that they would carry out his orders, and he marched them up to the
                        city. Then he ordered a general attack to be made by the army and the fleet.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Mago, the Carthaginian commander, saw
                        that an attack was being prepared both by land and sea, he made the
                        following disposition of his forces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two
                        thousand townsmen were posted in the direction of the Roman camp; the
                        citadel was occupied by 500 soldiers; 500 more were stationed in the higher
                        part of the city, towards the east. The rest of the townsmen were ordered to
                        be in readiness to meet any sudden emergency and to hasten in whatever
                        direction the shouting of the enemy might summon them. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Then the gate was thrown open and those who had been
                        drawn up in the street leading to their enemy's camp were sent forward.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans, at the direction of their
                        general, retired a short distance in order to be nearer to the supports
                        which were to be sent up. At first the lines stood confronting each other in
                        equal strength; but as the successive reinforcements came up they not only
                        turned the enemy to flight, but pressed upon them so closely as they fled in
                        disorder that if the "retire" had not sounded they would in all probability
                        have burst into the city pell-mell with the fugitives. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The confusion and terror of the battlefield spread
                        right through the city; many of the pickets fled from their stations
                        panic-struck; the defenders of the walls leaped down the shortest way they
                        could and deserted the fortifications. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Scipio had taken his stand on an eminence which they called Mercury's Hill,
                        and from here he became aware that the walls were in many places without
                        defenders. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He at once called out the whole
                        force in the camp to the attack, and ordered the scaling ladders to be
                        brought up. Covered by the shields of three powerful young men-for missiles
                        of every description were flying from the battlements-he went up close to
                        the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> walls, encouraging his men, giving
                        the necessary orders, and, what did most to stimulate their efforts,
                        observing with his own eyes each man's courage or cowardice. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> So they rushed on, regardless of missiles and
                        wounds, and neither the walls nor the men upon them could prevent them from
                        striving who should be the first to mount. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> At the same time the ships commenced an attack upon that part of the city
                        which faced the sea. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Here, however, there
                        was too much noise and confusion to admit of a regular assault, for what
                        with bringing up the vessels and hauling out the scaling ladders, and
                        clambering ashore as quickly as they could, the men only got in one
                        another's way through their hurry and eagerness. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst this was going on the Carthaginian
                        general had manned the walls with his regular soldiers, and they were amply
                        supplied with missiles, great heaps of which had been stored in readiness.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But neither the men, nor their
                        missiles, nor anything else proved such a sure defence as the walls
                        themselves. Very few of the ladders were long enough to reach to the top of
                        the wall, and the longer the ladders the weaker they were. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The consequence was that whilst each man who reached
                        the top was unable to get on to the wall, the others who came up behind him
                        were unable to advance and the ladder was broken by the mere weight of men.
                        Some who were on ladders which stood the strain grew dizzy from the height
                        and fell to the ground. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As men and ladders
                        were crashing down in all directions and the spirits and courage of the
                        enemy were rising with their success, the signal was sounded for retiring.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This led the besieged to hope that
                        they would not only gain a respite from their hard and wearisome struggle
                        for the time being, but would also be safe for the future, as they believed
                        that the city could not be taken by escalade and storm, whilst the
                        construction of siege works would be a difficult matter and would allow time
                        for succours to be sent. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The noise and
                        tumult of this first attempt had hardly subsided when Scipio ordered fresh
                        troops to take the ladders from those who were exhausted and wounded and
                        make a more determined attack upon the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> He had ascertained from the fishermen of Tarraco, who were in the habit
                        of crossing these waters in light skiffs and when these ran aground of
                        wading ashore through the shallows, that it was easy at low water to
                        approach the walls on foot. It was now reported to him that the tide was on
                        the ebb; and he at once took about 500 men with him and marched down to the
                        water. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was about midday, and not only
                        was the falling tide drawing the water seaward, but a strong northerly wind
                        which had sprung up was driving it in the same direction, and the lagoon had
                        become so shallow that in some places it was waist-deep and in others only
                        reached to the knee. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This state of things,
                        which Scipio had ascertained by careful investigation and reasoning, he
                        ascribed to the direct intervention of the gods, who he said were turning
                        the sea into a highway for the Romans, and by withdrawing its waters were
                        opening up a path which had never before been trodden by mortal feet. He
                        bade his men follow the guidance of Neptune and make their way through the
                        middle of the lagoon up to the walls. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Those who were making the attack on the
                        land side were in very great difficulties. Not only were they baffled by the
                        height of the walls, but as they approached them they were open to showers
                        of missiles on both hands, so that their sides were more exposed than their
                        front. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the other direction, however,
                        the 500 found their passage through the lake and their ascent from there to
                        the foot of the walls an easy matter. No fortifications had been constructed
                        on this side, as it was considered to be sufficiently protected by the lake
                        and by the nature of the ground, nor were there any outposts or pickets on
                        guard against any attack, as all were intent on rendering assistance where
                        danger was actually visible. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They entered
                        the city without meeting any opposition, and at once marched full speed to
                        the gate round which all the fighting had gathered. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> All had their attention absorbed in the struggle; even
                        the eyes and ears of the combatants, as of those who <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> were watching and cheering them on, were so riveted on
                        the fighting that not a single man was aware that the city behind him was
                        captured until the missiles began to fall upon them from the rear.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now that they had the enemy in front
                        and rear they gave up the defence, the walls were seized, the gate was
                        battered from both sides, smashed to pieces, and carried out of the way to
                        allow a free passage to the troops. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A
                        large number surmounted the walls and inflicted heavy slaughter on the
                        townsmen, but those who entered through the gate marched in unbroken ranks
                        through the heart of the city into the forum. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> From this point Scipio saw the enemy retreating in two
                        directions; one body was making for a hill to the east of the city, which
                        was being held by a detachment of 500 men; the others were going to the
                        citadel where Mago, together with the men who had been driven from the
                        walls, had taken refuge. Sending a force to storm the hill, he led the rest
                        of his troops against the citadel. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        hill was taken at the first charge, and Mago, seeing that the whole of the
                        city was in occupation of the enemy, and that his own position was hopeless,
                        surrendered the citadel and its defenders. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> Until the citadel was surrendered the carnage went on everywhere
                        throughout the city, no adult male who was met with was spared, but on its
                        surrender the signal was given and an end put to the slaughter. The victors
                        then turned their attention to the plunder, of which there was a vast amount
                        of every kind. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As many as 10,000 freemen were made
                        prisoners. Those who were citizens were set free and Scipio gave them back
                        their city and all the property which the war had left them. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> There were some 2000 artisans; these Scipio
                        allotted to the public service, and held out to them hopes of recovering
                        their liberty if they did their best in the tasks which the war demanded.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The rest of the able-bodied population
                        and the sturdiest of the slaves he assigned to the fleet to make up the
                        complement of rowers. He also augmented his fleet by five vessels which he
                        had seized. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Besides all this population
                        there were the Spanish hostages; these he treated with as much consideration
                        as though they had been children of the allies of Rome. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> An enormous amount of munitions of war was also
                        secured; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> 120 catapults of the largest size
                        and 281 smaller ones, 23 of the heavier ballistae and 52 lighter ones,
                        together with an immense number of scorpions of various calibre, as well as
                        missiles and other arms. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> 73 military
                        standards were also captured. A vast quantity of gold and silver was brought
                        to the general, including 287 golden bowls, almost all of which were at
                        least a pound in weight, 18,300 pounds of silver plate and coinage, the
                        former comprising a large number of vessels. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> This was all weighed and counted and then made over to the quaestor C.
                        Flaminius, as were also 10,000 bushels of wheat and 270 pecks of barley.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the harbour 63 transports were
                        captured, some of them with their cargoes of corn and arms, as well as
                        bronze, iron, sails, esparto grass, and other articles required for the
                        fleet. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Amidst such an enormous supply of
                        military and naval stores, the actual city itself was regarded as the least
                        important capture of all. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Leaving C. Laelius with the marines in
                        charge of the city, Scipio led his legions the same day back into camp. They
                        were well-nigh worn out; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> they had fought
                        in the open field, had undergone much toil and danger in the capture of the
                        city, and after capturing it had sustained a conflict on unfavourable ground
                        with those who had taken refuge in the citadel. So he gave them one day's
                        respite from all military duties and ordered them to seek refreshment and
                        rest. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The next day he issued orders for
                        all the soldiers and marines to appear on parade that he might address them.
                        First he offered up a thanksgiving to the immortal gods because they had not
                        only made him master in a single day of the wealthiest city in all Spain,
                        but had also brought together beforehand into the place all the resources of
                        Africa and Spain, so that whilst nothing was left to the enemy he and his
                        men had a superabundance of everything. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Then he praised the courage of his troops, whom, he said, nothing had
                        daunted, neither the sortie of the enemy, nor the height of the walls, nor
                        the untried depth of the lagoon, nor the fort on the hill, nor the unusual
                        strength of the citadel. Nothing had prevented them from surmounting every
                        obstacle and forcing their way everywhere. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Though every man amongst them deserved all the rewards he could give, the
                        glory of the mural crown belonged especially to him who was the first to
                        scale the wall, and the man who considered that he deserved it should claim
                        it. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two men came forward, Q. Tiberilius, a
                        centurion of the fourth legion, and Sextus Digitius, one of the marines. The
                        contention between them was not so heated as the excitement with which each
                        body advocated the claim of its own representative. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> C. Laelius, the commander of the fleet, supported the
                        marine, M. Sempronius Tuditanus took the part of his legionaries. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> As the dispute was almost becoming a mutiny,
                        Scipio announced that he would allow three arbitrators to be named who
                        should investigate the case and take evidence and give their decision as to
                        which had been the first to scale the wall and enter the town. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> C. Laelius and M. Sempronius were named by their
                        respective parties, and Scipio added the name of P. Cornelius Caudinus, who
                        belonged to neither party, and bade the three sit at once and try the case
                        judicially. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As they proceeded, the
                        dispute became hotter than ever, for the two men whose dignity and authority
                        had helped to restrain the excitement were now withdrawn to the tribunal. At
                        last Laelius left his colleagues and stepped down in front of the tribunal
                        to Scipio and pointed out to him that the proceedings were being carried on
                        in defiance of all order and self-restraint, and the men were almost coming
                        to blows. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And even if there were no
                        resort to violence the precedent that was being set was none the less
                        detestable, since men were trying to win the reward of valour by falsehood
                        and perjury. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On the one side were the
                        soldiers of the legion, on the other those of the fleet, all alike ready to
                        swear by all the gods to what they wanted rather than to what they knew to
                        be true, and prepared to involve in the guilt of perjury not themselves
                        only, but the military standards, the eagles and their solemn oath of
                        allegiance. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Laelius added that he was
                        making these representations to him at the wish of P. Cornelius and M.
                        Sempronius. Scipio approved of the step Laelius had taken and summoned the
                        troops to assembly. He then announced that he had definitely ascertained
                        that Q. Tiberilius and Sextius Digitius had both surmounted the wall at the
                        same moment, and he should honour their bravery by presenting them each with
                        a mural crown. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then he bestowed rewards
                        upon the rest according to each man's merit. C. Laelius, the commander of
                        the fleet, was singled out for special distinction, and in the praises which
                        he lavished upon him he placed him on an equality with himself, finally
                        presenting him with a golden crown and thirty oxen. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this he ordered the hostages from
                        the various Spanish states to be summoned into his presence. It is difficult
                        to give their number, for I find in one place 300 mentioned and in another
                        3724. There is a similar discrepancy amongst the authorities on other
                        points. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One author asserts that the
                        Carthaginian garrison amounted to 10,000 men, another puts it at 7000,
                        whilst a third estimates it as not more than 2000. In one place you will
                        find that there were 10,000 prisoners, in another the number is said to have
                        exceeded 25,000. If I followed the Greek author Silenus <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> I should give the number of scorpions large and small
                        as 60; according to Valerius Antias there were 6000 large ones and 13,000
                        small ones; so wildly do men invent. It is even a matter of dispute who were
                        in command. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Most authorities agree that
                        Laelius was in command of the fleet, but there are some who say that it was
                        M. Junius Silanus. Antias tells us that Arines was the Carthaginian
                        commandant when the garrison surrendered, other writers say it was Mago.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor are authors agreed as to the
                        number of ships that were captured, or the weight of gold and silver, or the
                        amount of money that was brought into the treasury. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> If we are to make a choice, the numbers midway between
                        these extremes are probably nearest the truth. When the hostages appeared
                        Scipio began by reassuring them and dispelling their fears. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They had, he told them, passed under the power of Rome,
                        and the Romans preferred to hold men by the bonds of kindness rather than by
                        those of fear. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They would rather have
                        foreign nations united to them on terms of alliance and mutual good faith
                        than kept down in hard and hopeless servitude. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He then ascertained the names of the States from which
                        they came and made an inventory of the number belonging to each State.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Messengers were then despatched to
                        their homes, bidding their friends to come and take charge of those who
                        belonged to them-where envoys from any of these States happened to be
                        present he restored their own relations to them on the spot; the care of the
                        rest he entrusted to C. Flaminius the quaestor, with injunctions to show
                        them all kindness and protection. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Whilst
                        he was thus engaged a high-born lady, wife of Mandonius the brother of
                        Indibilis, chief of the Ilergetes, came forward from the crowd of hostages
                        and flinging herself in tears at the general's feet implored him to impress
                        more strongly on their guards the duty of treating the women with tenderness
                        and consideration. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scipio assured her
                        that nothing would be wanting in this respect. Then she continued: "We do
                        not set great store on those things, for what is there that is not good
                        enough for the condition that we are in? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        I am too old to fear the injury to which our sex is exposed, but it is for
                        others that I am anxious as I look at these young girls." Round her stood
                        the daughters of Indibilis and other maidens of equal rank in the flower of
                        their youthful beauty, and they all looked up to her as a mother. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Scipio replied: "For the sake of the discipline
                        which I in common with all Romans uphold, I should take care that nothing
                        which is anywhere held sacred be violated amongst us; <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> your virtue and nobility of soul, which even in
                        misfortune is not forgetful of matronly decorum, make me now still more
                        careful in this matter." <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He then
                        delivered them into the charge of a man of tried integrity, with strict
                        injunctions to protect their innocence and modesty as carefully as though
                        they were the wives and mothers of his own guests. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Soon afterwards an adult maiden who had
                        been captured was brought to him by the soldiers, a girl of such exceptional
                        beauty that she attracted the eyes of all wherever she moved. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> On enquiring as to her country and parentage,
                        Scipio learnt, amongst other things, that she had been betrothed to a young
                        Celtiberian noble named Aluccius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He at
                        once sent for her parents and also for her betrothed, who, he learnt, was
                        pining to death through love of her. On the arrival of the latter Scipio
                        addressed him in more studied terms than a father would use. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> "A young man myself," he said, "I am addressing
                        myself to a young man, so we may lay aside all reserve. When your betrothed
                        had been taken by my soldiers and brought to me, I was informed that she was
                        very dear to you, and her beauty made me believe it. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Were I allowed the pleasures suitable to my age,
                        especially those of chaste and lawful love, instead of being preoccupied
                        with affairs of state, I should wish that I might be forgiven for loving too
                        ardently. Now I have the power to indulge another's love, namely yours.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Your betrothed has received the same
                        respectful treatment since she has been in my power that she would have met
                        with from her own parents. She has been reserved for you, in order that she
                        might be given to you as a gift inviolate and worthy of us both. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> In return for that boon I stipulate for this one
                        reward-that you will be a friend to Rome. If you believe me to be an upright
                        and honourable man such as the nations here found my father and uncle to be,
                        you may rest assured that there are many in Rome like us, and you may be
                        perfectly <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> certain that nowhere in the
                        world can any people be named whom you would less wish to have as a foe to
                        you and yours, or whom you would more desire as a friend." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The young man was overcome with
                        bashfulness and joy. He grasped Scipio's hand, and besought all the gods to
                        recompense him, for it was quite impossible for him to make any return
                        adequate to his own feelings, or the kindness Scipio had shown him. Then the
                        girl's parents and relatives were called. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        They had brought a large amount of gold for her ransom, and when she was
                        freely given back to them, they begged Scipio to accept it as a gift from
                        them; his doing so, they declared, would evoke as much gratitude as the
                        restoration of the maiden unhurt. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As they
                        urged their request with great importunity, Scipio said that he would accept
                        it, and ordered it to be laid at his feet. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> Calling Aluccius, he said to him: "In addition to the dowry which you are
                        to receive from your future father-in-law you will now receive this from me
                        as a wedding present." He then told him to take up the gold and keep it.
                        Delighted with the present and the honourable treatment he had received, the
                        young man resumed home, and filled the ears of his countrymen with
                        justly-earned praises of Scipio. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A young
                        man had come among them, he declared, in all ways like the gods, winning his
                        way everywhere by his generosity and goodness of heart as much as by the
                        might of his arms. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He began to enlist a
                        body of his retainers, and in a few days returned to Scipio with a picked
                        force of 1400 mounted men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio kept Laelius with him to advise as
                        to the disposal of the prisoners, the hostages and the booty, and when all
                        had <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> been arranged, he assigned him one
                        of the captured quinqueremes, and placing on board Mago and some fifteen
                        senators who had been made prisoners with him, he sent Laelius to Rome to
                        report his victory. He had himself decided to spend a few days in New
                        Carthage, and he employed this time in exercising his military and naval
                        forces. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the first day the legions,
                        fully equipped, went through various evolutions over a space of four miles;
                        the second day was employed in rubbing up and sharpening their weapons in
                        front of their tents; the third day they engaged in regular battle.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> practice with single-sticks and darts,
                        the points of which were muffled with balls of cork or lead; the fourth day
                        they rested, and on the fifth they were again exercised under arms. This
                        alternation of exercise and rest was kept up as long as they remained in
                        Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The rowers and marines put out
                        to sea when the weather was <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> calm and
                        tested the speed and handiness of their ships in a sham fight. These
                        maneuvers going on outside the city on land and sea sharpened the men both
                        physically and mentally for war; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the city
                        itself resounded with the din of warlike constructions carried on by the
                        artisans of every kind who were kept together in the Government workshops.
                        The general devoted his attention equally to everything. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> At one time he was present with the fleet watching a
                        naval encounter; at another he was exercising his legions; then he would be
                        giving some hours to an inspection of the work which was going on in the
                        shops and in the arsenal and dockyards, where the vast number of artisans
                        were vying with each other as to who could work the hardest. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> After starting these various undertakings and
                        seeing that the damaged portions of the walls were repaired, he started for
                        Tarraco, leaving a detachment in the city for its protection. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> On his way he was met by numerous delegations;
                        some of them he dismissed, after giving his reply while still on the march;
                        others he put off till he reached Tarraco, where he had given notice to all
                        the allies, old and new, to meet him. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Almost all the tribes south of the Ebro obeyed the summons, as did many also
                        from the northern province. The Carthaginian generals did their best to
                        suppress any rumours of the fall of New Carthage, then when the facts came
                        out too clearly to be either suppressed or perverted, they tried to minimise
                        its importance. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It was by a sudden ruse,
                        almost by stealth, they said, that one city out of the whole of Spain had
                        been filched from them in a single day; a young swaggerer elated with this
                        trifling success had in the intoxication of his delight made believe that it
                        was a great victory. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But when he learnt
                        that three generals and three victorious armies were bearing down upon him
                        he would be painfully reminded of the deaths which had already visited his
                        family. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> This was what they told people
                        generally, but they themselves were perfectly aware how much their strength
                        was in every way weakened by the loss of New Carthage. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
