<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six - 26</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp> literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by </resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>

                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1849</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXVI.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Hannibal encamps on the banks of the Anio, within three miles of Rome.
                        Attended by two thousand horsemen, he advances close to the Colline gate to
                        take a view of the walls and situation of the city. On two suc- cessive days
                        the hostile armies are hindered from engaging by the severity of the
                        weather. Capua taken by Quintus Fulvius and Appius Claudius; the chief
                        nobles die, voluntarily, by poison. Quintus Fulvius having con- demned the
                        principal senators to death, at the moment they are actually tied to the
                        stakes, receives despatches from Rome, commanding him to spare their lives,
                        which he postpones reading until the sentence is executed. Publius Scipio,
                        offering himself for the service, is sent to command in Spain; takes New
                        Carthage in one clay. Successes in Sicily. Treaty of friendship with the
                        Aetolians. War with Philip, king of Macedonia, and the Acarnanians. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THE consuls, Cneius Fulvius Centumalus and
                    Publius Sulpicius Galba, having entered on their office on the ides of March,
                    assembled the senate in the Capitol, and took the opinion of the fathers on the
                    state of the republic, the manner of conducting the war, and on what related to
                    the provinces and the armies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius
                    and Appius Claudius, the consuls of the former year, were continued in command;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and the armies which they before had were
                    assigned to them, it being added that they should not withdraw from Capua, which
                    they were besieging, till they had taken it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans were now solicitously intent upon this object, not from resentment so
                    much, which was never juster against any city, as from the consideration that as
                    this city, so celebrated and powerful, had by its defection drawn away several
                    states, so when reduced it would bring back their minds to respect for <pb
                        n="1018" xml:id="p.1018"/> the former supreme government. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Two praetors also of the former year, Marcus Junius and
                    Publius Sempronius, were each continued in command of the two legions which they
                    had under them, the former in Etruria, the latter in Gaul. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Marcus Marcellus also was continued in command, that he
                    might, as proconsul, finish the war in Sicily with the army he had there.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If he wanted recruits he was to take them
                    from the legions which Publius Cornelius, the propraetor, commanded in Sicily,
                    provided he did not choose any soldier who <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    was of the number of those whom the senate had refused to allow to be
                    discharged, or to return home till the war was put an end to. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> To Caius Sulpicius, to whose lot Sicily had fallen, the two
                    legions which Publius Cornelius had commanded were assigned, to be recruited
                    from the army of Cneius Fulvius, which had been shamefully beaten, and had
                    experienced a dreadful loss the year before in Apulia. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> To soldiers of this description the senate had assigned the
                    same period of service as to those who fought at Cannae; and as an additional
                    mark of ignominy upon both, they were not allowed to winter in towns, or to
                    build huts for wintering within the distance of ten miles from any town.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To Lucius Cornelius, in Sardinia, the two
                    legions which Quintus Mucius had commanded were assigned; if recruits were
                    wanted, the consuls were ordered to enlist them. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> To Titus Otacilius and Marcus Valerius was allotted the
                    protection of the coasts of Sicily and Greece, with the legions and fleets which
                    they had commanded. The Greek coast had fifty ships with one legion; the
                    Sicilian, a hundred ships with two legions. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Twenty-three legions were employed by the Romans in carrying on the war this
                    year by land and sea. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the year, on a letter from
                    Lucius Marcius being laid before the senate, they considered his achievements as
                    most glorious; but the title of honour which he assumed (for though he was
                    neither invested with the command by the order of the people, nor by the
                    direction of the fathers, his letter ran in this form, <quote>The proprietor to
                        the senate</quote> ) gave offence to a great many. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It was considered as an injurious precedent for generals to
                    be chosen by the armies, and for the solemn ceremony of elections, held under
                    auspices, to be transferred to camps and provinces, and (far from the control of
                    the laws and magistrates) to military thoughtlessness. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> And though some gave it as their opinion, that the <pb
                        n="1019" xml:id="p.1019"/> sense of the senate should be taken on the
                    matter, yet it was thought more advisable that the discussion should be
                    postponed till after the departure of the horsemen who brought the letter from
                    Marcius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was resolved, that an answer
                    should be returned respecting the corn and clothing of the army, stating, that
                    the senate would direct its attention to both those matters; but that the letter
                    should not be addressed to Lucius Marcius, proprietor, lest he should consider
                    that as already determined which was the very point they reserved for
                    discussion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the horsemen were dismissed,
                    it was the first thing the consuls brought before the senate; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and the opinions of all to a man coincided, that the
                    plebeian tribunes should be instructed to consult the commons with all possible
                    speed, as to whom they might resolve to send into Spain to take the command of
                    that army which had been under the conduct of Cneius Scipio. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The plebeian tribunes were instructed accordingly, and the
                    question was published. But another contest had pre-engaged the minds of the
                    people: Caius Sempronius Blaesus, having brought Cneius Fulvius to trial for the
                    loss of the army in Apulia, harassed him with invectives in the public
                    assemblies: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Many generals,</quote> he reiterated, <quote> had by indiscretion and
                        ignorance brought their armies into most perilous situations, but none, save
                        Cneius Fulvius, had corrupted his legions by every species of excess before
                        he betrayed them to the enemy; it might therefore with truth be said, that
                        they were lost before they saw the enemy, and that they were defeated, not
                        by Hannibal, but by their own general. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> No
                        man, when he gave his vote, took sufficient pains in ascertaining who it was
                        to whom he was intrusting an army. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> What a
                        difference was there between this man and Tiberius Sempronius! The latter,
                        having been intrusted with an army of slaves, had in a short time brought it
                        to pass, by discipline and authority, that not one of them in the field of
                        battle remembered his condition and birth, but they became a protection to
                        our allies and a terror to our enemies. They had snatched, as it were, from
                        the very jaws of Hannibal, and restored to the Roman people, Cumae,
                        Beneventum, and other towns. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But Cneius
                        Fulvius had infected with the vices peculiar to slaves, an army of Roman
                        citizens, of honourable parentage and liberal education; and had thus made
                        them insolent and turbulent among their allies, inefficient and dastardly
                        among their ene- <pb n="1020" xml:id="p.1020"/> mies, unable to sustain, not
                        only the charge, but the shout of the Carthaginians. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> But, by Hercules, it was no wonder that the troops did
                        not stand their ground in the battle, when their general was the first to
                        fly; with him, the greater wonder was, that any had fallen at their posts,
                        and that they were not all the companions of Cneius Fulvius in his
                        consternation and his flight. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Caius
                        Flaminius, Lucius Paullus, Lucius Posthumius, Cneius and Publius Scipio, had
                        preferred falling in the battle to abandoning their armies when in the power
                        of the enemy. But Cneius Fulvius was almost the only man who returned to
                        Rome to report the annihilation of his army. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> It was a shameful crime that the army of Cannae should
                        be transported into Sicily, because they fled from the field of battle, and
                        not be allowed to return till the enemy has quitted Italy; that the same
                        decree should have been lately passed with respect to the legions of Cneius
                        Fulvius; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> while Cneius Fulvius himself has
                        no punishment inflicted upon him for running away, in a battle brought about
                        by his own indiscretion; that he himself should be permitted to pass his old
                        age in stews and brothels, where he passed his youth, while his troops,
                        whose only crime was that they resembled their general, should be sent away
                        in a manner into banishment, and suffer an ignominious service. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> So unequally, </quote> he said, <quote> was
                        liberty shared at Rome by the rich and the poor, by the ennobled and the
                        common people. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The accused shifted the blame from himself to
                    his soldiers; he said, <quote> that in consequence of their having in the most
                        turbulent manner demanded battle, they were led into the field, not on the
                        day they desired, for it was then evening, but on the following; that they
                        were drawn up at a suitable time and on favourable ground; but either the
                        reputation or the strength of the enemy was such, that they were unable to
                        stand their ground. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they all fled
                        precipitately, he himself also was carried away with the crowd, as had
                        happened to Varro at the battle of Cannae, and to many other generals.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> How could he, by his sole resistance,
                        benefit the republic, unless his death would remedy the public disasters?
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that he was not defeated in
                        consequence of a failure in his provisions; that he had not, from want of
                        caution, been drawn into a disadvantageous position; that he had not been
                        cut off by an ambuscade in consequence of not having ex- <pb n="1021"
                            xml:id="p.1021"/> plored his route, but had been vanquished by open
                        force, and by arms, in a regular engagement. He had not in his power the
                        minds of his own troops, or those of the enemy. Courage and cowardice were
                        the result of each man's natural constitution. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He was twice accused, and the penalty was laid
                    at a fine. On the third accusation, at which witnesses were produced, he was not
                    only overwhelmed with an infinity of disgraceful charges, but a great many
                    asserted on oath, that the flight and <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> panic
                    commenced with the praetor, that the troops being deserted by him, and
                    concluding that the fears of their general were not unfounded, turned their
                    backs; when so strong a feeling of indignation was excited, that the assembly
                    clamorously rejoined that he ought to be tried capitally. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> This gave rise to a new controversy; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> for when the tribune, who had twice prosecuted him as for a
                    finable offence, now, on the third occasion, declared that he prosecuted him
                    capitally; the tribunes of the commons being appealed to, said, <quote> they
                        would not prevent their colleague from proceeding, as he was permitted
                        according to the custom of their ancestors, in the manner he himself
                        preferred, whether according to the laws or to custom, until he had obtained
                        judgment against a private individual, convicting him either of a capital or
                        finable offence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Upon this, Sempronius said, that he charged
                    Cneius Fulvius with the crime of treason; and requested Caius Calpurnius, the
                    city praetor, to appoint a day for the comitia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Another ground of hope was then tried by the accused, viz. if his brother,
                    Quintus Fulvius, could be present at his trial, who was at that time flourishing
                    in the fame of his past achievements and in the near expectation of taking
                    Capua. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Fulvius wrote to the senate,
                    requesting the favour in terms calculated to excite compassion, in order to save
                    the life of his brother; but the fathers replied, that the interest of the state
                    would not admit of his leaving Capua. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Cneius
                    Fulvius, therefore, before the day appointed for the comitia arrived, went into
                    exile to Tarquinii, and the commons resolved that it was a legal exile. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile all the strength of the war was
                    directed against Capua. It was, however, more strictly blockaded than besieged.
                    The slaves and populace could neither endure the famine, nor send messengers to
                    Hannibal through guards so <pb n="1022" xml:id="p.1022"/> closely stationed.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A Numidian was at length found, who, on
                    undertaking to make his way with it, was charged with a letter; and going out by
                    night, through the midst of the Roman camp, in order to fulfil his promise, he
                    inspired the Campanians with confidence to try the effect of a sally from every
                    quarter, while they had any strength remaining. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> In the many encounters which followed, their cavalry were generally
                    successful, but their infantry were beaten: however, it was by no means so
                    joyful to conquer, as it was miserable to be worsted in any respect by a
                    besieged and almost subdued enemy. A plan was at length adopted, by which their
                    deficiency in strength might be compensated by stratagem. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Young men were selected from all the legions, who, from the
                    vigour and activity of their bodies, excelled in swiftness; these were supplied
                    with bucklers shorter than those worn by horsemen, and seven javelins each, four
                    feet in length, and pointed with steel in the same manner as the spears used by
                    light-armed troops. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The cavalry taking one of
                    these each upon their horses, accustomed them to ride behind them, and to leap
                    down nimbly when the signal was given. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When,
                    by daily practice, they appeared to be able to do this in an orderly manner,
                    they advanced into the plain between the camp and the walls, against the cavalry
                    of the Campanians, who stood there prepared for action. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As soon as they came within a dart's cast, on a signal
                    given, the light troops leaped down, when a line of infantry formed out of the
                    body of horse suddenly rushed upon the cavalry of the enemy, and discharged
                    their javelins one after another with great rapidity; which being thrown in
                    great numbers upon men and horses indiscriminately, wounded a great many.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The sudden and unsuspected nature of the
                    attack, however, occasioned still greater terror; and the cavalry charging them,
                    thus panic-struck, chased them with great slaughter as far as their gates.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From that time the Roman cavalry had the
                    superiority; and it was established that there should be velites in the legions.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It is said that Quintus Navius was the
                    person who advised the mixing of infantry with cavalry, and that he received
                    honour from the general on that account. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While affairs were in this state at Capua,
                    Hannibal was perplexed between two objects, the gaining possession of <pb
                        n="1023" xml:id="p.1023"/> the citadel of Tarentum, and the retaining of
                    Capua. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His concern for Capua, however,
                    prevailed, on which he saw that the attention of every body, allies and enemies,
                    was fixed; and whose fate would be regarded as a proof of the consequences
                    resulting from defection from the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Leaving, therefore, a great part of his baggage among the Bruttians, and all his
                    heavier armed troops, he took with him a body of infantry and cavalry, the best
                    he could select for marching expeditiously, and bent his course into Campania.
                    Rapidly as he marched he was followed by thirty-three elephants. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> He took up his position in a retired valley behind
                    Mount Tifata, which overhung Capua. Having at his coming taken possession of
                    fort Galatia, the garrison of which he dislodged by force, he then directed his
                    efforts against those who were besieging Capua. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Having sent forward messengers to Capua stating the time at which he would
                    attack the Roman camp, in order that they also, having gotten themselves in
                    readiness for a sally, might at the same time pour forth from all their gates,
                    he occasioned the greatest possible terror; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    for on one side he himself attacked them suddenly, and on the other side all the
                    Campanians sallied forth, both foot and horse, joined by the Carthaginian
                    garrison under the command of Bostar and Hanno. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> The Romans, lest in so perilous an affair they should leave any part
                    unprotected, by running together to any one place, thus divided their forces:
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius was opposed to the
                    Campanians; Fulvius to Hannibal; Caius Nero, the propraetor, with the cavalry of
                    the sixth legion, placed himself in the road leading to Suessula; and Caius
                    Fulvius Flaccus, the lieutenant-general, with the allied cavalry, on the side
                    opposite the river Vulturnus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The battle
                    commenced not only with the usual clamour and tumult, but in addition to the din
                    of men, horses, and arms, a multitude of Campanians, unable to bear arms, being
                    distributed along the walls, raised such a shout together with the clangour of
                    brazen vessels, similar to that which is usually made in the dead of night when
                    the moon is eclipsed, that it diverted the attention even of the combatants.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Appius easily repulsed the Campanians
                    from the rampart. On the other side Hannibal and the Carthaginians, forming a
                    larger force, pressed hard on Fulvius. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There
                    the sixth legion gave way; which being repulsed, a cohort of Spaniards with
                    three ele- <pb n="1024" xml:id="p.1024"/> phants made their way up to the
                    rampart. They had broken through the centre of the Roman line, and were in a
                    state of anxious and perilous suspense, whether to force their way into the
                    camp, or be cut off from their own army. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When
                    Fulvius saw the disorder of the legion, and the danger the camp was in, he
                    exhorted Quintus Navius, and the other principal centurions, to charge the
                    cohort of the enemy which was fighting under the rampart; he said, <quote> that
                        the state of things was most critical; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        that either they must retire before them, in which case they would burst
                        into the camp with less difficulty than they had experienced in breaking
                        through a dense line of troops, or they must cut them to pieces under the
                        rampart: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> nor would it require a great
                        effort; for they were few, and cut off from their own troops, and if the
                        line which appeared broken, now while the Romans were dispirited, should
                        turn upon the enemy on both sides, they would become enclosed in the midst;
                        and exposed to a twofold attack. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Navius, on hearing these words of the
                    general, snatched the standard of the second company of spearmen from the
                    standard-bearer, and advanced with it against the enemy, threatening that he
                    would throw it into the midst of them unless the soldiers promptly followed him
                    and took part in the fight. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He was of
                    gigantic stature, and his arms set him off; the standard also, raised aloft,
                    attracted the gaze both of his countrymen and the enemy. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> When, however, he had reached the standards of the
                    Spaniards, javelins were poured upon him from all sides, and almost the whole
                    line was turned against him; but neither the number of his enemies nor the force
                    of the weapons could repel the onset of this hero. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Atilius, the lieutenant-general, also
                    caused the standard of the first company of principes of the same legion to be
                    borne against a cohort of the Spaniards. Lucius Portius Licinus and Titus
                    Popilius, the lieutenant-generals, who had the command of the camp, fought
                    valiantly in defence of the rampart, and slew the elephants while in the very
                    act of crossing it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The carcasses of these
                    filling up the ditch, afforded a passage for the enemy as effectually as if
                    earth had been thrown in, or a bridge erected over it; and a horrid carnage took
                    place amid the carcasses of the elephants which lay prostrate. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> On the other side of the camp, the Campanians, with the
                    Carthaginian garrison, had by this time been repulsed, <pb n="1025"
                        xml:id="p.1025"/> and the battle was carried on immediately under the gate
                    of Capua leading to Vulturnus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor did the
                    armed men contribute so much in resisting the Romans, who endeavoured to force
                    their way in, as the gate itself, which, being furnished with balistas and
                    scorpions, kept the enemy at bay by the missiles discharged from it. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The ardour of the Romans was also damped by the
                    general, Appius Claudius, receiving a wound; he was struck by a javelin in the
                    upper part of his breast, beneath the left shoulder, while encouraging his men
                    before the front line. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A great number,
                    however, of the enemy were slain before the gate, and the rest were driven in
                    disorder into the city. When Hannibal saw the destruction of the cohort of
                    Spaniards, and that the camp of the enemy was defended with the utmost vigour,
                    giving up the assault, he began to withdraw his standards, making his infantry
                    face about, but throwing out his cavalry in the rear lest the enemy should
                    pursue them closely. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The ardour of the legions
                    to pursue the enemy was excessive, but Flaccus ordered a retreat to be sounded,
                    considering that enough had been achieved to convince the Campanians, and
                    Hannibal himself, how unable he was to afford them protection. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Some who have undertaken to give accounts of this battle,
                    record that eight thousand of the army of Hannibal, and three thousand
                    Campanians, were slain; that fifteen military standards were taken from the
                    Carthaginians, and eighteen from the Campanians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> In other authors I find the battle to have been by no means so important, and
                    that there was more of panic than fighting; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    that a party of Numidians and Spaniards suddenly bursting into the Roman camp
                    with some elephants, the elephants, as they made their way through the midst of
                    the camp, threw down their tents with a great noise, and caused the beasts of
                    burden to break their halters and run away. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    That in addition to the confusion occasioned, a stratagem was employed; Hannibal
                    having sent in some persons acquainted with the Latin language, for he had some
                    such with him, who might command the soldiers, in the name of <milestone
                        n="12??" unit="section"/> the consuls, to escape every one as fast as he
                    could to the neighbouring mountains, since the camp was lost; but that the
                    imposture was soon discovered, and frustrated with a great slaughter of the
                    enemy; that the elephants were driven out of the camp by fire. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> However commenced, and however terminated, this was the
                    last battle which <pb n="1026" xml:id="p.1026"/> was fought before the surrender
                    of Capua. Seppius Lesius was Medixtuticus, or chief magistrate of Capua, that
                    year, a man of obscure origin and slender fortune. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> It is reported that his mother, when formerly expiating a
                    prodigy which had occurred in the family in behalf of this boy, who was an
                    orphan, received an answer from the aruspex, stating, that <quote>the highest
                        office would come to him;</quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and that not recognising, at Capua, any
                    ground for such a hope, exclaimed, <quote> the state of the Campanians must be
                        desperate indeed, when the highest office shall come to my son. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But even this expression, in which the
                    response was turned into ridicule, turned to be true, for those persons whose
                    birth allowed them to aspire to high offices, refusing to accept them when the
                    city was oppressed by sword and famine, and when all hope was lost, Lesius, who
                    complained that Capua <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> was deserted and
                    betrayed by its nobles, accepted the office of chief magistrate, being the last
                    Campanian who held it. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But Hannibal, when he saw that the enemy could
                    not be drawn into another engagement, nor a passage be forced through their camp
                    into Capua, resolved to remove his camp from that <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> place and leave the attempt unaccomplished, fearful lest
                    the new consuls might cut off his supplies of provision. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> While anxiously deliberating on the point to which he
                    should next direct his course, an impulse suddenly entered his mind to make an
                    attack on Rome, the very source of the war. That the opportunity of
                    accomplishing this ever coveted object, which occurred after the battle of
                    Cannae, had been neglected, and was generally censured by others, he himself did
                    not deny. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He thought that there was some hope
                    that he might be able to get possession of some part of the city, in consequence
                    of the panic and confusion which his unexpected approach would occasion, and
                    that if Rome were in danger, either both the Roman generals, or at least one of
                    them, would immediately leave Capua; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and if
                    they divided their forces, both generals being thus rendered weaker, would
                    afford a favourable opportunity either to himself or the Campanians of gaining
                    some advantage. One consideration only disquieted him, and that was, lest on his
                    departure the Campanians should immediately surrender. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> By means of presents he induced a Numidian, who was ready
                    to attempt any thing, however daring, to take charge of a letter; and, entering
                    the Ro- <pb n="1027" xml:id="p.1027"/> man camp under the disguise of a
                    deserter, to pass out privately on the other side and go to Capua. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> As to the letter, it was full of encouragement. It
                    stated, that <quote> his departure, which would be beneficial to them, would
                        have the effect of drawing off the Roman generals and armies from the siege
                        of Capua to the defence of Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That they
                        must not allow their spirits to sink; that by a few days' patience they
                        would rid themselves entirely of the siege. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then ordered the ships on the Vulturnus to
                    be seized, and rowed up to the fort which he had before erected for his
                    protection. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And when he was informed that
                    there were as many as were necessary to convey his army across in one night,
                    after providing a stock of provisions for ten days, he led his legions down to
                    the river by night, and passed them over before daylight. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fulvius Flaccus, who had discovered from
                    deserters that this would happen, before it took place, having written to Rome
                    to the senate to apprize them of it, men's minds were variously affected by it
                    according to the disposition of each. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As might
                    be expected in so alarming an emergency, the senate was immediately assembled,
                    when Publius Cornelius, surnamed Asina, was for recalling all the generals and
                    armies from every part of Italy to protect the city, disregarding Capua and
                    every other concern. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fabius Maximus thought
                    that it would be highly disgraceful to retire from Capua, and allow themselves
                    to be terrified and driven about at the nod and menaces of Hannibal. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Was it probable that he, who, though victorious at Cannae, nevertheless
                        dared not approach the city, now, after having been repulsed from Capua, had
                        conceived hopes of making himself master of Rome? <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> It was not to besiege Rome, but to raise the siege of
                        Capua that he was coming. Jupiter, the witness of treaties violated by
                        Hannibal, and the other deities, would defend the city of Rome with that
                        army which is now at the city. </quote> To these opposite opinions, that of
                    Publius Valerius Flaccus, which recommended a middle course, was preferred.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Regardful of both objects, he thought that
                    a letter should be written to the generals at Capua, informing them of the force
                    they had at the city for its protection, and stating, that as to the number of
                    forces which Hannibal was bringing with him, or how large an army was necessary
                    to carry on the siege of Capua, they themselves knew. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> If one of the generals and a part of <pb n="1028"
                        xml:id="p.1028"/> the army could be sent to Rome, and at the same time Capua
                    could be efficiently besieged by the remaining general and army, that then
                    Claudius and Fulvius should settle between themselves <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> which should continue the siege of Capua, and which should
                    come to Rome to protect their capital from being besieged. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> This decree of the senate having been conveyed to Capua,
                    Quintus Fulvius, the proconsul, who was to go to Rome, as his colleague was ill
                    from his wound, crossed the Vulturnus with a body of troops, to the number of
                    fifteen thousand infantry and a thousand horse, selected from the three armies.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then having ascertained that Hannibal
                    intended to proceed along the Latin road, he sent persons before him to the
                    towns on and near the Appian way, Setia, Cora, and Lanuvium, with directions
                    that they should <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> not only have provisions
                    ready in their towns, but should bring them down to the road from the fields
                    which lay out of the way, and that they should draw together into their towns
                    troops for their defence, in order that each state might be under its own
                    protection. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the day he crossed the Vulturnus, Hannibal
                    pitched his camp at a small distance from the river. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The next day, passing by Cales, he reached the Sidicinian
                    territory, and having spent a day there in devastating the country, he led his
                    troops along the Latin way through the territory of Suessa, Allifae, and
                    Casinum. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Under the walls of Casinum he
                    remained encamped for two days, ravaging the country all around; thence passing
                    by Interamna and Aquinum, he came into the Fregellan territory, to the river
                    Liris, where he found the bridge broken down by the Fregellans in order to
                    impede his progress. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fulvius also was detained
                    at the Vulturnus, in consequence of Hannibal's having burnt the ships, and the
                    difficulty he had in procuring rafts to convey his troops across that river from
                    the great scarcity of materials. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The army
                    having been conveyed across by rafts, the remainder of the march of Fulvius was
                    uninterrupted, a liberal supply of provisions having been prepared for him, not
                    only in all the towns, but also on the sides of the road; while his men, who
                    were all activity, exhorted each other to quicken their pace, remembering that
                    they were going to defend their country. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A
                    messenger from Fregella, who had travelled a day and a night without
                    intermission, arriving at Rome, caused the <pb n="1029" xml:id="p.1029"/>
                    greatest consternation; and the whole city was thrown into a state of alarm by
                    the running up and down of persons who made vague additions to what they heard,
                    and thus increased the confusion which the original intelligence created.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The lamentations of women were not only
                    heard from private houses, but the matrons from every quarter, rushing into the
                    public <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> streets, ran up and down around the
                    shrines of the gods, sweeping the altars with their dishevelled hair, throwing
                    themselves upon their knees and stretching their uplifted hands to heaven and
                    the gods, imploring them to rescue the city of Rome out of the hands of their
                    enemies, and preserve the Roman mothers and their children from harm. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The senate sat in the forum near the magistrates, in
                    case they should wish to consult them. Some were receiving orders and departing
                    to their own department of duty; others were offering themselves wherever there
                    might be occasion for their aid. Troops were posted in the citadel, in the
                    Capitol, upon the walls around the city, and also on the Alban mount, and the
                    fort of Aesula. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During this confusion,
                    intelligence was brought that Quintus Fulvius, the proconsul, had set out from
                    Capua with an army; when the senate decreed that Quintus Fulvius should have
                    equal authority with the consuls, lest on entering the city his power should
                    cease. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hannibal, having most destructively
                    ravaged the Fregellan territory, on account of the bridge having been broken
                    down, came into the territory of the Lavici, passing through those of Frusino,
                    Ferentinum, and Anagnia; thence passing through Algidum he directed his course
                    to Tusculum; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but not being received within
                    the walls, he went down to the right below Tusculum to Gabii; and marching his
                    army down thence into the territory of the Pupinian tribe, he pitched his camp
                    eight miles from the city. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The nearer the
                    enemy carve, the greater was the number of fugitives slain by the Numidians who
                    preceded him, and the greater the number of prisoners made of every rank and
                    age. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this confusion, Fulvius Flaccus entered
                    the city with his troops through the Capuan gate, passed through the midst of
                    the city, and through Carinae, to Esquiliae; and going out thence, pitched his
                    camp between the Esquiline and Colline gates. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The plebeian aediles brought a supply of provisions there. The consuls and the
                    senate came to the camp, <pb n="1030" xml:id="p.1030"/> and a consultation was
                    held on the state of the republic. It was resolved that the consuls should
                    encamp in the neighbourhood of the Colline and Esquiline gates; that Caius
                    Calpurnius, the city praetor, should have the command of the Capitol and the
                    citadel; and that a full senate should be continually assembled in the forum, in
                    case it should be necessary to consult them amidst such sudden emergencies.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, Hannibal advanced his camp to
                    the Anio, three miles from the city, and fixing his position there, he advanced
                    with two thousand horse from the Colline gate as far as the temple of Hercules,
                    and riding up, took as near a view as he could of the walls and site of the
                    city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Flaccus, indignant that he should do
                    this so freely, and so much at his ease, sent out a party of cavalry, with
                    orders to displace and drive back to their camp the cavalry of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the fight had begun, the consuls
                    ordered the Numidian deserters who were on the Aventine, to the number of twelve
                    hundred, to march through the midst of the city to the Esquiliae, judging that
                    no troops were better calculated to fight among the hollows, the garden walls,
                    and tombs, or in the enclosed roads which were on all sides. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But some persons, seeing them from the citadel and Capitol
                    as they filed off on horseback down the Publician hill, cried out that the
                    Aventine was taken. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This circumstance
                    occasioned such confusion and terror, that if the Carthaginian camp had not been
                    without the city, the whole multitude, such was their alarm, would have rushed
                    out. They then fled for refuge into their houses and upon the roofs, where they
                    threw stones and weapons on their own soldiers as they passed along the streets,
                    taking them for enemies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor could the tumult
                    be repressed, or the mistake explained, as the streets were thronged with crowds
                    of rustics and cattle, which the sudden alarm had driven into the city.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The battle between the cavalry was
                    successful, and the enemy were driven away; and as it was necessary to repress
                    the tumults which were arising in several quarters without any cause, it was
                    resolved that all who had been dictators, consuls, or censors, should be
                    invested with authority till such time as the enemy had retired from the walls.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During the remainder of the day and the
                    following night, several tumults arose without any foundation, and were
                    repressed. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day Hannibal, crossing the Anio, drew
                    out <pb n="1031" xml:id="p.1031"/> all his forces in order of battle; nor did
                    Flaccus and the consuls decline to fight. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When
                    the troops on both sides were drawn up to try the issue of a battle, in which
                    Rome was to be the prize of the victors, a violent shower of rain mingled with
                    hail created such disorder in both the lines, that the troops, scarcely able to
                    hold their arms, retired to their camps, less through fear of the enemy than of
                    any thing else. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the following day,
                    likewise, a similar tempest separated the armies marshalled on the same ground;
                    but after they had retired to their camps the weather became wonderfully serene
                    and tranquil. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians considered
                    this circumstance as a Divine interposition, and it is reported that Hannibal
                    was heard to say, <quote> That sometimes he wanted the will to make himself
                        master of Rome, at other times the opportunity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Two other circumstances also, one
                    inconsiderable, the other important, diminished his hopes. The important one
                    was, that while he lay with his armed troops near the walls of the city, he was
                    informed that troops had marched out of it with colours flying, as a
                    reinforcement for Spain; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that of less
                    importance was, that he was informed by one of his prisoners, that the very
                    ground on which his camp stood was sold at this very time, without any
                    diminution in its price. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Indeed, so great an
                    insult and indignity did it appear to him that a purchaser should be found at
                    Rome for the very soil which he held and possessed by right of conquest, that he
                    immediately called a crier, and ordered that the silversmiths' shops, which at
                    that time stood around the Roman forum, should be put up for sale. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Induced by these circumstances he retired to the
                    river Tutia, six miles from the city, whence he proceeded to the grove of
                    Feronia, where was a temple at that time celebrated for its riches. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The Capenatians and other states in the
                    neighbourhood, by bringing here their first- fruits and other offerings
                    according to their abilities, kept it decorated with abundance of gold and
                    silver. Of all these offerings the temple was now despoiled. After the departure
                    of Hannibal, vast heaps of brass were found there, as the soldiers, from a
                    religious feeling, had thrown in pieces of uncoined brass. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The spoliation of this temple is undoubted by historians;
                    but Caelius asserts, that Hannibal, in his progress to Rome, turned out of his
                    way to it from Eretum. According to him his route commenced with Amiternum,
                    Caetilii, <pb n="1032" xml:id="p.1032"/> and Reate. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> He came from Campania into Samnium, and thence into
                    Pelignia; then passing the town Sulmio, he entered the territory of the
                    Marrucini; thence through the Alban territory he came to that of the Marsi, from
                    which he came to Amiternum and the village of Foruli. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Nor is this diversity of opinion a proof that the traces of
                    so great an army could be confounded in the lapse of so brief a period.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That he went that way is evident. The
                    only question is, whether he took this route to the city, or returned by it from
                    the city into Campania? </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With regard to Capua, Hannibal did not evince
                    such obstinate perseverance in raising the siege of it as the Romans did in
                    pressing it; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for quitting Lucania, he came
                    into the Bruttian territory, and marched to the strait and Rhegium with such
                    rapidity, that he was very near taking the place by surprise, in consequence of
                    the suddenness of his arrival. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Though the
                    siege had been urged with undiminished vigour during his absence, yet Capua felt
                    the return of Flaccus; and astonishment was excited that Hannibal had not
                    returned with him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Afterwards they learnt, by
                    conversations, that they were abandoned and deserted, and that the Carthaginians
                    had given up all hopes of retaining Capua. In addition to this a proclamation
                    was made by the proconsul, agreeably to a decree of the senate, <milestone
                        n="5??" unit="section"/> and published among the enemy, that any Campanian
                    citizen who came over before a stated day should be indemnified. No one,
                    however, came over, as they were held together by fear more than fidelity; for
                    the crimes they had committed during their revolt were too great to admit of
                    pardon. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As none of them passed over to the
                    enemy, consulting their own individual interest, so no measure of safety was
                    taken with regard to the general body. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    nobility had deserted the state, nor could they be induced to meet in the
                    senate, while the office of chief magistrate was <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> filled by a man who had not derived honour to himself from
                    his office, but stripped the office of its influence and authority by his own
                    unworthiness. Now none of the nobles made their appearance even in the forum, or
                    any public place, but shut themselves up in their houses, in daily expectation
                    of the downfal of their city, and their own destruction together. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The chief responsibility in every thing devolved upon
                    Bostar and Hanno, the praefects of the Punic garrison, who were anxious on ac-
                        <pb n="1033" xml:id="p.1033"/> count of their own danger, and not that of
                    their allies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They addressed a letter to
                    Hannibal, in terms, not only of freedom, but severity, charging him with <quote>
                        delivering, not only Capua into the hands of the enemy, but with
                        treacherously abandoning themselves also, and their troops, to every species
                        of tor- ture; </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> they told him <quote> he had gone off to the
                        Bruttians, in order to get out of the way, as it were, lest Capua should be
                        taken before his eyes; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> while, by
                        Hercules, the Romans, on the contrary, could not be drawn off from the siege
                        of Capua, even by an attack upon their city. So much more constant were the
                        Romans in their enmity than the Carthaginians in their friendship.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If he would return to Capua and
                        direct the whole operations of the war to that point, that both themselves
                        and the Campanians would be prepared for a sally. That they had crossed the
                        Alps not to carry on a war with the people of Rhegium nor Tarentum.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> That where the Roman legions were,
                        there the armies of the Carthaginians ought to be. Thus it was that
                        victories had been gained at Cannae and Trasimenus; by uniting, by pitching
                        their camp close to that of the enemy, by trying their fortune. </quote> A
                    letter to this effect was given to some Numidians who had already engaged to
                    render their services for a stated reward. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    These men came into the camp to Flaccus under pretence of being deserters, with
                    the intention of quitting it by seizing an opportunity; and the famine, which
                    had so long existed at Capua, afforded a pretext for desertion which no one
                    could suspect. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But a Campanian woman, the
                    paramour of one of the deserters, unexpectedly entered the camp, and informed
                    the Roman general that the Numidians had come over according to a preconcerted
                    plan of treachery, and were the bearers of letters to Hannibal; that she was
                    prepared to convict one of the party of that fact, as he had discovered it to
                    her. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> On being brought forward, he at first
                    pretended, with considerable pertinacity, that he did not know the woman; but
                    afterwards, gradually succumbing to the force of truth, when he saw the
                    instruments of torture called for and preparing, he confessed that it was so.
                    The letters were produced, and a discovery was made of an additional fact,
                    before concealed, that other Numidians were strolling about in the Roman camp,
                    under pretence of being deserters. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Above
                    seventy of these were arrested, and, with the late deserters, scourged with
                    rods; and after their hands had <pb n="1034" xml:id="p.1034"/> been cut off,
                    were driven back to Capua. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The sight of so
                    severe a punishment broke the spirit of the Campanians. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The people, rushing in crowds to the
                    senate-house, compelled Lesius to assemble a senate, and openly threatened the
                    nobles, who had now for a long time absented themselves from the public
                    deliberations, that unless they attended the meeting of the senate, they would
                    go round to their houses and drag them all before the public by force. The fear
                    of this procured the magistrate a full senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Here, while the rest contended for sending ambassadors to the Roman generals,
                    Vibius Virrius, who had been the instigator of the revolt from the Romans, on
                    being asked his opinion, observed, that <quote> those persons who spoke of
                        sending ambassadors, and of peace, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> and a
                        surrender, did not bear in mind either what they would do if they had the
                        Romans in their power, or what they themselves must expect to suffer. What!
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> do you think, </quote> says he,
                        <quote> that your surrender will be like that in which formerly we placed
                        ourselves and every thing belonging to us at the disposal of the Romans, in
                        order that we might obtain assistance from them against the Samnites?
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Have you already forgotten at what a
                        juncture we revolted from the Romans, and what were their circumstances?
                        Have you forgotten how at the time of the revolt we put to death, with
                        torture and indignity, their garrison, which might have been sent out? How
                        often, and with determined hostility, we have sallied out against them when
                        besieging us, and assaulted their camp? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        How we invited Hannibal to come and cut them off? And how most recently we
                        sent him hence to lay siege to Rome? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But
                        come, retrace on the other hand what they have done in hostility towards us,
                        that you may learn therefrom what you have to hope for. When a foreign enemy
                        was in Italy, and that enemy Hannibal; when the flame of war was kindled in
                        every quarter; disregarding every other object, disregarding even Hannibal
                        himself, they sent two consuls with two consular armies to lay siege to
                        Capua. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This is the second year, that,
                        surrounded with lines and shut up within our walls, they consume us by
                        famine, having suffered in like manner with ourselves the extremest dangers
                        and the severest hardships, having frequently had their troops slain near
                        their rampart and trenches, and at last having been almost deprived of their
                        camp. But I pass over these matters. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It
                        has <pb n="1035" xml:id="p.1035"/> been usual, even from of old, to suffer
                        dangers and hardships in besieging an enemy's city. The following is a proof
                        of their animosity and bitter hatred. Hannibal assaulted their camp with an
                        immense force of horse and foot, and took a part of it. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> By so great a danger they were not in the least
                        diverted from the siege. Crossing the Vulturnus, he laid waste the territory
                        of Cales with fire. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such calamities
                        inflicted upon their allies had no effect in calling them off. He ordered
                        his troops to march in hostile array to the very city of Rome. They despised
                        the tempest which threatened them in this case also. Crossing the Anio, he
                        pitched his camp three miles from the city, and lastly, came up to the very
                        walls and gates. He gave them to understand that he would take their city
                        from them, unless they gave up Capua. But they did not give it up. Wild
                        beasts, impelled by headlong fury and rage, you may divert from their object
                        to bring assistance to those belonging to them, if you attempt to approach
                        their dens and their young. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Romans
                        could not be diverted from Capua by the blockade of Rome, by their wives and
                        children, whose lamentations could almost be heard from this place, by their
                        altars, their hearths, <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> the temples of
                        their gods, and the sepulchres of their ancestors profaned and violated.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So great was their avidity to bring
                        us to punishment, so insatiable their thirst for drinking our blood. Nor,
                        perhaps, without reason. We too would have done the same had the opportunity
                        been afforded us. Since, however, the gods have thought proper to determine
                        it otherwise, though I ought not to shrink from death, while I am free,
                        while I am master of myself, I have it in my power, by a death not only
                        honourable but mild, to escape the tortures and indignities which the enemy
                        hope to inflict upon me. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I will not see
                        Appius Claudius and Quintus Fulvius in the pride and insolence of victory,
                        nor will I be dragged in chains through Rome as a spectacle in a triumph,
                        that afterwards in a dungeon, or tied to a stake, after my back has been
                        lacerated with stripes, I may place my neck under a Roman axe. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> I will neither see my native city demolished and
                        burnt, nor the matrons, virgins, and freeborn youths of Campania dragged to
                        constupration. Alba, from which they themselves derived their origin, they
                        demolished from her foundations, that there might remain no trace of their
                        rise and extraction; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> much less can I
                        believe they <pb n="1036" xml:id="p.1036"/> will spare Capua, towards which
                        they bear a more rancorous hatred than towards Carthage. For such of you,
                        therefore, as have a mind to yield to fate, before they behold such horrors,
                        a banquet is furnished and prepared at my house. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> When satiated with wine and food, the same cup which
                        shall have been given to me shall be handed round to them. That potion will
                        rescue our bodies from torture, our minds from insult, our eyes and ears
                        from seeing and hearing all those cruelties and indignities which await the
                        vanquished. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> There will be persons in
                        readiness who will throw our lifeless bodies upon a large pile kindled in
                        the court-yard of the house. This is the only free and honourable way to
                        death. Our very enemies will admire our courage, and Hannibal will learn
                        that those whom he deserted and betrayed were brave allies. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> More of those who heard this speech of Virrius
                    approved of the proposal contained in it, than had strength of mind to execute
                    what they approved. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The greater part of the
                    senate being not without hopes that the Romans, whose clemency they had
                    frequently had proof of in many wars, would be exorable by them also, decreed
                    and sent ambassadors to surrender Capua to the Romans. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> About twenty-seven senators, following Vibius Virrius to
                    his home, partook of the banquet with him; and after having, as far as they
                    could, withdrawn their minds, by means of wine, from the perception of the
                    impending evil, all took the poison. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They then
                    rose from the banquet, after giving each other their right hands, and taking a
                    last embrace, mingling their tears for their own and their country's fate; some
                    of them remained, that they might be burned upon the same pile, and the rest
                    retired to their homes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their veins being
                    filled in consequence of what they had eaten, and the wine they drank, rendered
                    the poison less efficacious in expediting death; and accordingly, though the
                    greater part of them languished the whole of that night and part of the
                    following day, all of them, however, breathed their last before the gates were
                    opened to the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The following day the
                    gate of Jupiter, which faced the Roman camp, was opened by order of the
                    proconsul, when one legion and two squadrons of allies marched in at it, under
                    the command of Caius Fulvius, lieutenant-general. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> When he had taken care that all the arms and weapons to be
                    found in Capua should be brought to him; having placed <pb n="1037"
                        xml:id="p.1037"/> guards at all the gates to prevent any one's going or
                    being sent out, he seized the Carthaginian garrison, and ordered the Campanian
                    senators to go into the camp to the Roman generals. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> On their arrival they were all immediately thrown into
                    chains, and ordered to lay before the quaestor an account of all the gold and
                    silver they had. There were seventy pounds of gold, and three thousand two
                    hundred of silver. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Twenty-five of the senators
                    were sent to Cales, to be kept in custody, and twenty-eight to Teanum; these
                    being the persons by whose advice principally it appeared that the revolt from
                    the Romans had taken place. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fulvius and Claudius were far from being
                    agreed as to the punishment of the Campanian senators. Claudius was disposed to
                    grant their prayer for pardon, but Fulvius was more inclined to severity.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Appius, therefore, was for referring the
                    entire disposal of the question to the Roman senate. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He thought it right also, that the fathers should have the
                    opportunity of asking them whether any of the Latin confederates, or of the
                    municipal towns, had taken part in these designs, and whether they had derived
                    any assistance from them in the war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fulvius,
                    on the contrary, urged that they ought by no means to run the hazard of having
                    the minds of faithful allies harassed by doubtful accusations, and subjected to
                    informers who never cared at all what they did or what they said. For this
                    reason he said that he should prevent and put a stop to any such inquiry.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After this conversation they separated;
                    Appius not doubting but that his colleague, though he expressed himself so
                    warmly, would, nevertheless, wait for a letter from Rome, in an affair of such
                    magnitude. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But Fulvius, fearing that his
                    designs would be frustrated by that very means, dismissed his council, and
                    commanded the military tribunes and the praefects of the allies to give notice
                    to two thousand chosen horsemen to be in readiness at the third trumpet.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Setting out for Teanum with this body of
                    cavalry, he entered the gate at break of day, and proceeded direct to the forum;
                    and a number of people having flocked together at the first entrance of the
                    horsemen, he ordered the Sidicinian magistrate to be summoned; when he desired
                    him to bring forth the Campanians whom he had in custody. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> These were all accordingly brought forth, scourged, and
                    beheaded. He then proceeded at full speed to Cales; where, <pb n="1038"
                        xml:id="p.1038"/> when he had taken his seat on the tribunal, and while the
                    Campanians, who had been brought forth, were being bound to the stake, an
                    express arrived from Rome, and delivered to him a letter from Caius Calpurnius,
                    the praetor, and a decree of the senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A
                    murmur immediately pervaded the whole assembly, beginning at the tribunal, that
                    the entire question respecting the Campanians was referred to the decision of
                    the fathers; and Fulvius, suspecting this to be the case, took the letter, and
                    without opening it put it into his bosom, and then commanded the crier to order
                    the lictor to do his duty. Thus punishment was inflicted on those also who were
                    at Cales. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The letter was then read, together
                    with the decree of the senate, when it was too late to prevent the business
                    which was already executed, and which had been accelerated by every means to
                    prevent its being obstructed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When Fulvius
                    was now rising from his seat, Jubellius Taurea, a Campanian, making his way
                    through the middle of the city and the crowd, called upon him by name;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and when Flaccus, who wondered greatly
                    what he could want, had resumed his seat, he said, <quote> Order me also to be
                        put to death, that you may be able to boast, that a much braver man than
                        yourself has been put to death by you. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Fulvius at first said, that the man could not
                    certainly be in his senses; then, that he was restrained by a decree of the
                    senate, even though he might wish it; when Jubellius exclaimed: <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Since, after the capture of my country, and the loss of my relations and
                        friends, after having killed, with my own hand, my wife and children to
                        prevent their suffering any indignity, I am not allowed even to die in the
                        same manner as these my countrymen, let a rescue be sought in courage from
                        this hated existence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> So saying, he thrust a sword, which he had
                    concealed under his garment, right through his breast, and fell lifeless at the
                    general's feet. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Because not only what related to the
                    punishment of the Campanians, but most of the other particulars of this affair,
                    were transacted according to the judgment of Flaccus alone, some authors affirm
                    that Appius Claudius died about the time of the surrender of Capua; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> and that this same Taurea neither came to Cales
                    voluntarily nor died by his own hand; but that while he was being tied to the
                    stake among the rest, Flaccus, who could not distinctly hear what he vociferated
                    from the noise which was made, ordered silence; when Taurea <pb n="1039"
                        xml:id="p.1039"/> said the things which have been before related: <quote>
                        that he, a man of the greatest courage, was being put to death by one who
                        was by no means his equal in respect to valour. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That immediately on his saying this, the
                    herald, by command of the proconsul, pronounced this order: <quote>Lictor, apply
                        the rods to this man of courage, and execute the law upon him first.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some authors also relate, that he read the
                    decree of the senate before he beheaded them, but that as there was a clause in
                    it, to the effect, that if he thought proper he should refer the entire question
                    to the senate, he construed it that the decision as to what was most for the
                    interest of the state was left to himself. He returned from Cales to Capua.
                    Atella and Calatia surrendered themselves, and were received. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Here also the principal promoters of the revolt were
                    punished. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thus eighty principal members of the
                    senate were put to death; and about three hundred of the Campanian nobles thrown
                    into prison. The rest were distributed through the several cities of the Latin
                    confederacy, to be kept in custody; where they perished in various ways. The
                    rest of the Campanian citizens were sold. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    remaining subject of deliberation related to the city and its territory. Some
                    were of opinion that a city so eminently powerful, so near, and so hostile,
                    ought to be demolished. But immediate utility prevailed; for on account of the
                    land, which was evidently superior to any in Italy from the variety and
                    exuberance of its produce, the city was preserved that it might become a
                    settlement of husbandmen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For the purpose of
                    peopling the city, a number of sojourners, freed-men, dealers, and artificers,
                    were retained; but all the land and buildings were made the property of the
                    Roman state. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was resolved, however, that
                    Capua should only be inhabited and peopled as a city; that there should be no
                    body- politic, nor assembly of the senate or people, nor magistrates. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> For it was thought that a multitude not possessing
                    any public council, without a ruling power, and unconnected by the participation
                    of any common rights, would be incapable of combination. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They resolved to send a prefect annually from Rome to
                    administer justice. Thus were matters adjusted at Capua, upon a plan in every
                    respect worthy of commendation. Punishment was inflicted upon the most guilty
                    with rigour and despatch; the populace dispersed beyond all hope of return; no
                    rage vented in fire and ruins upon the unoffending <pb n="1040" xml:id="p.1040"
                    /> houses and walls. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Together also with
                    advantage, a reputation for clemency was obtained among the allies, by the
                    preservation of a city of the greatest celebrity and opulence; the demolition of
                    which, all Campania, and all the people dwelling in the neighbourhood of
                    Campania, would have bewailed; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> while their
                    enemies were compelled to admit the ability of the Romans to punish their
                    faithless allies, and how little assistance could be derived from Hannibal
                    towards the defence of those whom he had taken under his protection. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman senate having gone through every
                    thing which required their attention relative to Capua, decreed to Caius Nero
                    six thousand foot and three hundred horse, whichever he should himself choose
                    out of those two legions which he had commanded at Capua, with an equal number
                    of infantry, and eight hundred horse of the Latin confederacy. This army Nero
                    embarked at Puteoli, and conveyed over into Spain. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Having arrived at Tarraco with his ships, landed his
                    troops, hauled his ships ashore, and armed his mariners to augment his numbers,
                    he proceeded to the river Iberus, and received the army from Titus Fonteius and
                    Lucius Marcius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then marched towards the
                    enemy. Hasdrubal, son of Hamilcar, was encamped at the black stones in
                    Ausetania, a place situated between the towns Illiturgi and Mentissa. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The entrance of this defile Nero seized; and
                    Hasdrubal, to prevent his being shut up in it, sent a herald to engage that, if
                    he were allowed to depart thence, he would convey the whole of his army out of
                    Spain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman general having received this
                    proposition gladly, Hasdrubal requested the next day for a conference, when the
                    Romans might draw up conditions relative <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> to
                    the surrender of the citadels of the towns, and the appointment of a day on
                    which the garrisons might be withdrawn, and the Carthaginians might remove every
                    thing belonging to them without imposition. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Having obtained his point in this respect, Hasdrubal gave orders that as soon as
                    it was dark, and during the whole of the night afterwards, the heaviest part of
                    his force should get out of the defile by whatever way they could. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The strictest care was taken that many should not go
                    out that night, that the very fewness of their numbers might both be more
                    adapted to elude the notice of the enemy from their silence, and to an escape
                    through confined and rugged paths. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Next day
                    they met for the confer- <pb n="1041" xml:id="p.1041"/> ence; but that day
                    having been spent, on purpose, in speaking and writing about a variety of
                    subjects, which were not to this point, the conference was put off to the next
                    day. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The addition of the following night gave
                    him time to send still more out; nor was the business concluded the next day.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thus several days were spent in openly
                    discussing conditions, and as many nights in privately sending the Carthaginian
                    troops out of their camp; and after the greater part of the army had been sent
                    out, he did not even keep to those terms which he had himself proposed; and his
                    sincerity decreasing with his fears, they became less and less agreed.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> By this time nearly all the infantry had
                    cleared the defile, when at daybreak a dense mist enveloped the whole defile and
                    the neighbouring plains; which Hasdrubal perceiving, sent to Nero to put off the
                    conference to the following day, as the Carthaginians held that day sacred from
                    the transaction of any serious business. Not even then was the cheat suspected.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal having gained the indulgence he
                    sought for that day also, immediately quitted his camp with his cavalry and
                    elephants, and without creating any alarm escaped to a place of safety.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> About the fourth hour the mist, being
                    dispelled by the sun, left the atmosphere clear, when the Romans saw that the
                    camp of the enemy was deserted. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then at
                    length Claudius, recognising the Carthaginian perfidy, and perceiving that he
                    had been caught by trickery, immediately began to pursue the enemy as they moved
                    off, prepared to give battle; but they declined fighting. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> Some skirmishes, however, took place between the rear of
                    the Carthaginians and the advanced guard of the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the time in which these events
                    occurred, neither did those states of Spain which had revolted after the defeat
                    that was sustained, return to the Romans, nor did any others desert them.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At Rome, the attention of the senate and
                    people, after the recovery of Capua, was not fixed in a greater degree upon
                    Italy than upon Spain. They resolved that the army there should be augmented and
                    a general sent. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were not, however, so
                    clear as to the person whom they should send, as that, where two generals had
                    fallen within the space of thirty days, he who was to supply the place of them
                    should be selected with unusual care. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some
                    naming one person, and others another, they at length came to the resolution
                    that the <pb n="1042" xml:id="p.1042"/> people should assemble for the purpose
                    of electing a proconsul for Spain; and the consuls fixed a day for the election.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At first they waited in expectation that
                    those persons who might think themselves qualified for so momentous a command
                    would give in their names; but this expectation being disappointed, their grief
                    was renewed for the calamity they had suffered, and their regret for the
                    generals they had lost. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The people thus
                    afflicted, and almost at their wits' end, came down, however, to the Campus
                    Martius on the day of the election; where, turning towards the magistrates, they
                    looked round at the countenances of their most eminent men, who were earnestly
                    gazing at each other; and murmured bitterly, that their affairs were in so
                    ruinous a state, and the condition of the commonwealth so desperate, that no one
                    dared undertake the command in Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When
                    suddenly Publius Cornelius, son of Publius who had fallen in Spain, who was
                    about twenty-four years of age, declaring himself a candidate, took his station
                    on an eminence from which he could be seen by all. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The eyes of the whole assembly were directed towards him,
                    and by acclamations and expressions of approbation, a prosperous and happy
                    command were at once augured to him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Orders
                    were then given that they should proceed to vote, when not only every century,
                    but every individual to a man, decided that Publius Scipio should be invested
                    with the command in Spain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But after the
                    business had been concluded, and the ardour and impetuosity of their zeal had
                    subsided, a sudden silence ensued, and a secret reflection on what they had
                    done; whether their partiality had not got the better of their judgment?
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They chiefly regretted his youth; but
                    some were terrified at the fortune which attended his house and his name; for
                    while the two families to which he belonged were in mourning, he was going into
                    a province where he must carry on his operations between the tombs of his father
                    and his uncle. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perceiving the solicitude and anxiety which
                    people felt, after performing the business with so much ardour, he summoned an
                    assembly, in which he discoursed in so noble and high-minded a manner, on his
                    years, the command intrusted to him, and the war which he had <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> to carry on, as to rekindle and renew the ardour which had
                    subsided, and inspire the people with more confident hopes than the reliance
                    placed on <pb n="1043" xml:id="p.1043"/> human professions, or reasoning on the
                    promising appearance of affairs, usually engenders. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> For Scipio was not only deserving of admiration for his
                    real virtues, but also for his peculiar address in displaying them, to which he
                    had been formed from his earliest years; effecting <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> many things with the multitude, either by feigning
                    nocturnal visions or as with a mind divinely inspired; whether it was that he
                    was himself, too, endued with a superstitious turn of mind, or that they might
                    execute his commands and adopt his plans without hesitation, as if they
                    proceeded from the responses of an oracle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    With the intention of preparing men's minds for this from the beginning, he
                    never at any time from his first assumption of the manly gown transacted any
                    business, public or private, without first going to the Capitol, entering the
                    temple, and taking his seat there; where he generally passed a considerable time
                    in secret and alone. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This practice, which was
                    adhered to through the whole of his life, occasioned in some persons a belief in
                    a notion which generally prevailed, whether designedly or undesignedly
                    propagated, that he was a man of divine extraction; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> and revived a report equally absurd and fabulous with that
                    formerly spread respecting Alexander the Great, that he was begotten by a huge
                    serpent, whose monstrous form was frequently observed in the bedchamber of his
                    mother, but which, on any one's coming in, suddenly unfolding his coils, glided
                    out of sight. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The belief in these miraculous
                    accounts was never ridiculed by him, but rather increased by his address;
                    neither positively denying any such thing nor openly affirming it. There were
                    also many other things, some real and others counterfeit, which exceeded in the
                    case of this young man the usual measure of <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    human admiration, in reliance on which the state intrusted him with an affair of
                    so much difficulty, and with so important a command, at an age by no means ripe
                    for it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To the forces in Spain, consisting of
                    the remains of the old army, and those which had been conveyed over from Puteoli
                    by Claudius Nero, ten thousand infantry and a thousand horse were added; and
                    Marcus Junius Silanus, the proprietor, was sent to assist in the management of
                    affairs. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thus with a fleet of thirty ships,
                    all of which were quinqueremes, he set sail from the mouth of the Tiber, and
                    coasting along the shore of the Tuscan Sea, the Alps, and the Gallic Gulf, and
                    then doubling the promontory of the Pyrenees, landed his troops at Emporiae, a
                        <pb n="1044" xml:id="p.1044"/> Greek city, which also derived its origin
                    from Phocaea. Ordering his ships to attend him, he marched by land to Tarraco;
                    where he held a congress of deputies from all the allies; for embassies had
                    poured forth from every province on the news of his arrival. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Here he ordered his ships to be hauled on shore, having
                    sent back the four triremes of the Massilians, which had, in compliment to him,
                    attended him from their home.. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After that, he
                    began to give answers to the embassies of the several states, which had been in
                    suspense on account of the many vicissitudes of the war; <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> and this with so great dignity, arising from the great
                    confidence he had in his own talents, that no presumptuous expression ever
                    escaped him; and in every thing he said there appeared at once the greatest
                    majesty and sincerity. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Setting out from Tarraco, he visited the
                    states of his allies and the winter quarters of his army; and bestowed the
                    highest commendations upon the soldiers, because, though they had received two
                    such disastrous blows in succession, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> they
                    had retained possession of the province, and not allowing the enemy to reap any
                    advantage from their successes, had excluded them entirely from the territory on
                    this side of the Iberus, and honourably protected their allies. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Marcius he kept with him, and treated him with such
                    respect, that it was perfectly evident there was nothing he feared less than
                    lest any one should stand in the way of his own glory. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Silanus then took the place of Nero, and the fresh troops
                    were led into winter quarters. Scipio having in good time visited every place
                    where his presence was necessary, and completed every thing which was to be
                    done, returned to Tarraco. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The reputation of
                    Scipio among his enemies was not inferior to that which he enjoyed among his
                    allies and countrymen. They felt also a kind of presentiment of what was to
                    come, which occasioned the greater apprehension, the less they could account for
                    their fears, which had arisen without any cause. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> They had retired to their winter quarters in different directions. Hasdrubal,
                    son of Gisgo, had gone quite to the ocean and Gades; Mago into the midland parts
                    chiefly above the forest of Castulo; Hasdrubal, son of Hamilcar, wintered in the
                    neighbourhood of Saguntum, close upon the Iberus. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> At the close of the summer in which Capua was recovered and
                    Scipio entered Spain, a Carthaginian fleet, which had been fetched from Sicily
                    to Tarentum, to cut off the supplies <pb n="1045" xml:id="p.1045"/> of the Roman
                    garrison in the citadel of that place, had blocked up all the approaches to the
                    citadel from the sea; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but by lying there too
                    long, they caused a greater scarcity of provisions to their friends than to
                    their enemies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For so much corn could not be
                    brought in for the townsmen, along the coasts which were friendly to them, and
                    through the ports which were kept open through the protection afforded by the
                    Carthaginian fleet, as the fleet itself consumed, which had on board a crowd
                    made up of every description of persons. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So
                    that the garrison of the citadel, which was small in number, could be supported
                    from the stock they had previously laid in without importing any, while that
                    which they imported was not sufficient for the supply of the Tarentines and the
                    fleet. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At length the fleet was sent away with
                    greater satisfaction than it was received. The scarcity of provisions, however,
                    was not much relieved by it; because when the protection by sea was removed corn
                    could not be brought in. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of the same summer, Marcus
                    Marcellus arriving at the city from his province of Sicily, an audience of the
                    senate was given him by Caius Calpurnius, the praetor, in the temple of Bellona.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here, after discoursing on the services he
                    had performed, and complaining in gentle terms, not on his own account more than
                    that of his soldiers, that after having completely reduced the province, he had
                    not been allowed to bring home his army, he requested that he might be allowed
                    to enter the city in triumph; this he did not obtain. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> A long debate took place on the question, whether it was
                    less consistent to deny a triumph on his return to him, in whose name, when
                    absent, a supplication had been decreed and honours paid to the immortal gods,
                    for successes obtained under his conduct; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> or,
                    when they had ordered him to deliver over his army to a successor, which would
                    not have been decreed unless there were still war in the province, to allow him
                    to triumph, as if the war had been terminated, when the army, the evidence of
                    the triumph being deserved or undeserved, were absent. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> As a middle course between the two opinions, it was
                    resolved that he should enter the city in ovation. The plebeian tribunes, by
                    direction of the senate, proposed to the people, that Marcus Marcellus should be
                    invested with command during the day on which he should enter the city in
                    ovation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The day before he entered the city he
                    triumphed on the Alban mount; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> after which he
                    entered the city in ovation, <pb n="1046" xml:id="p.1046"/> having a great
                    quantity of spoils carried before him, together with a model of the capture of
                    Syracuse. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The catapultas and balistas, and
                    every other instrument of war were carried; likewise the rich ornaments laid up
                    by its kings during a long continuance of peace; a quantity of wrought silver
                    and brass, and other articles, with precious garments, and a number of
                    celebrated <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> statues, with which Syracuse had
                    been adorned in such a manner as to rank among the chief Grecian cities in that
                    respect. Eight elephants were also led as an emblem of victory over the
                    Carthaginians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Sosis, the Syracusan, and
                    Mericus, the Spaniard, who preceded him with golden crowns, formed not the least
                    interesting part of the spectacle; under the guidance of one of whom the Romans
                    had entered Syracuse by night, while the other had betrayed to them the island
                    and the garrison in it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To both of them the
                    freedom of the city was given, and five hundred acres of land each. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Sosis was to have his portion in the Syracusan
                    territory, out of the lands which had belonged either to the kings or the
                    enemies of the Roman people, together with a house at Syracuse, which had
                    belonged to any one of those persons who had been punished according to the laws
                    of war. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Mericus and the Spaniards who had
                    come over with him were ordered to have a city and lands assigned to them in
                    Sicily, which had belonged to some of those who had revolted from the Romans. It
                    was given in charge to Marcus Cornelius to assign them the city and lands
                    wherever he thought proper. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> In the same
                    country, four hundred acres of land were decreed to Belligenes, by whose means
                    Mericus had been persuaded to come over. After the departure of Marcellus from
                    Sicily, a Carthaginian fleet landed eight thousand infantry and three thousand
                    Numidian cavalry. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> To these the Murgantian
                    territories revolted; Hybla, Macella, and certain other towns of less note
                    followed their defection. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The Numidians also,
                    headed by Mutines, ranging without restraint through the whole of Sicily,
                    ravaged with fire the lands of the allies of the Romans. In addition to these
                    unfortunate circumstances, the Roman soldiers, incensed partly because they had
                    not been taken from the province with their general, and partly because they had
                    been forbidden to winter in towns, discharged their duties negligently, and
                    wanted a a leader more than inclination for a mutiny. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> Amid these difficulties Marcus Cornelius, the praetor,
                    sometimes by soothing, at other times by reproving them, pacified the minds <pb
                        n="1047" xml:id="p.1047"/> of the soldiers; and reduced to obedience all the
                    states which had revolted; out of which he gave Murgantia to those Spaniards who
                    were entitled to a city and land, in conformity with the decree of the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As both the consuls had Apulia for their
                    province, and as there was now less to be apprehended from Hannibal and the
                    Carthaginians, they were directed to draw lots for the provinces of Apulia and
                    Macedonia. Macedonia fell to the lot of Sulpicius, who succeeded Laevinus.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fulvius having been called to Rome on
                    account of the election, held an assembly to elect new consuls; when the junior
                    Veturian century, which had the right of voting first, named Titus Manlius
                    Torquatus and Titus Otacilius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A crowd
                    collecting round Manlius, who was present, to congratulate him, and it being
                    certain that the people would concur in his election, he went, surrounded as he
                    was with a multitude of persons, to the tribunal of the consul, and requested
                    that he would listen to a few words from him; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    and that he would order the century which had voted to be recalled. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> While all present were waiting impatiently to hear
                    what it was he was going to ask, he alleged as an excuse the weakness of his
                    eyes; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> observing, that 'a pilot or a general
                    might fairly be charged with presumption who should request that the lives and
                    fortunes of others might be intrusted to him, when in every thing which was to
                    be done he must make use of other people's eyes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Therefore he requested, that, if it seemed good to him, he would order the
                    junior Veturian century to come and vote again; and to recollect, while electing
                    consuls, the war which they had in Italy, and the present exigencies of the
                    state. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That their ears had scarcely yet ceased
                    to ring with the noise and tumult raised by the enemy, when but a few months ago
                    they nearly scaled the walls of Rome." <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This
                    speech was followed by the century's shouting out, one and all, that <quote>
                        they would not in the least alter their vote, but would name the same
                        persons for consuls; </quote> when Torquatus replied, <quote> neither shall
                        I as consul be able to put up with your conduct, nor will you be satisfied
                        with my government. Go back and vote again, and consider that you have a
                        Punic war in Italy, and that the leader of your enemies is Hannibal. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Upon this the century, moved by the authority
                    of the man and the shouts of admirers around, besought the consul <pb n="1048"
                        xml:id="p.1048"/> to summon the elder Veturian century; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> for they were desirous of conferring with persons older
                    than themselves, and to name the consuls in accordance with their advice. The
                    elder Veturian century having been summoned, time was allowed them to confer
                    with the others by themselves in the <hi rend="italics">ovile.</hi>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The elders said that there were three persons
                    whom they ought to deliberate about electing, two of them having already served
                    all the offices of honour, namely, Quintus Fabius and Marcus Marcellus; and if
                    they wished so particularly to elect some fresh person as consul to act against
                    the Carthaginians, that Marcus Valerius Laevinus had carried on operations
                    against king Philip by sea and land with signal success. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Thus, three persons having been proposed to them to
                    deliberate about, the seniors were dismissed, and the juniors proceeded to vote.
                    They named as consuls, Marcus Claudius Marcellus, then glorious with the
                    conquest of Sicily, and Marcus Valerius, both in their absence. All the
                    centuries followed the recommendation of that which voted first. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Let men now ridicule the admirers of antiquity. Even
                    if there existed a republic of wise men, which the learned rather imagine than
                    know of; for my own part I cannot persuade myself that there could possibly be a
                    nobility of sounder judgment, and more moderate in their desire of power, or a
                    people better moralled. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Indeed that a century
                    of juniors should have been willing to consult their elders, as to the persons
                    to whom they should intrust a command by their vote, is rendered scarcely
                    probable by the contempt and levity with which the parental authority is treated
                    by children in the present age. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The assembly for the election of praetors was
                    then held, at which Publius Manlius Vulso, Lucius Manlius Acidinus, Caius
                    Laetorius, and Lucius Cincius Alimentus were elected. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It happened that just as the elections were concluded, news
                    was brought that Titus Otacilius, whom it seemed the people would have made
                    consul in his absence, with Titus Manlius, had not the course of the elections
                    been interrupted, had died in Sicily. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    games in honour of Apollo had been performed the preceding year, and on the
                    motion of Calpurnius, the praetor, that they should be performed this year also,
                    the senate decreed that they should be vowed every year for the time to come.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The same year several prodigies were seen
                    and reported. At the temple of Concord, a statue of Victory, <pb n="1049"
                        xml:id="p.1049"/> which stood on the roof, having been struck by lightning
                    and thrown down, stuck among the figures of Victory, which were among the
                    ornaments under the eaves, and did not fall to the ground from thence.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both from Anagnia and Fregellae it was
                    reported that a wall and some gates had been struck by lightning. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> That in the forum of Sudertum streams of blood had
                    continued flowing through a whole day; at Eretum, that there had been a shower
                    of stones; and at Reate, that a mule had brought forth. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> These prodigies were expiated with victims of the larger
                    sort, the people were commanded to offer up prayers for one day, and perform the
                    nine days' sacred rite. Several of the public priests died off this year, and
                    fresh ones were appointed. In the room of Manius Aemilius Numida, decemvir for
                    sacred rites, Marcus Aemilius Lepidus was appointed; in the room of Manius
                    Pomponius Matho, the pontiff, Caius Livius; in the room of Spurius Carvilius
                    Maximus, the augur, Marcus Servilius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As Titus
                    Otacilius Crassus, a pontiff, died after the year was concluded, no person was
                    nominated to succeed him. Caius Claudius, flamen of Jupiter, retired from his
                    office, because he had distributed the entrails improperly. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same time Marcus Valerius Laevinus,
                    having first sounded the intentions of the leading men by means of secret
                    conferences, came with some light ships to a council of the Aetolians, which had
                    been previously appointed to meet for this very purpose. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Here having proudly pointed to the capture of Syracuse and
                    Capua, as proofs of the success of the Roman arms in Sicily and Italy, he added,
                    that "it was a custom with the Romans, handed down to them from their ancestors,
                    to respect their allies; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> some of whom they had
                    received into their state, and had admitted to the same privileges they enjoyed
                    themselves, while others they treated so favourably that they chose rather to be
                    allies than citizens. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That the Aetolians would
                    be honoured by them so much the more, because they were the first of the nations
                    across the sea which had entered into friendship with them. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> That Philip and the Macedonians were troublesome neighbours
                    to them, but that he had broken their strength and spirits already, and would
                    still further reduce them to that degree, that they should not only evacuate the
                    cities which they had violently taken from the Aetolians, but have Macedonia
                    itself disturbed <pb n="1050" xml:id="p.1050"/> with war. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> And that as to the Acarnanians, whose separation from their
                    body was a source of grief to the Aetolians, he would place them again under
                    their ancient system of jurisdiction and dominion. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> These assertions and promises of the Roman general, Scopas,
                    who was at that time praetor of the nation, and Dorymachus, a leading man among
                    the Aetolians, confirmed on their own authority, extolling the power and
                    greatness of the Roman people with less reserve, and with greater force of
                    conviction. However, the hope of recovering Acarnania principally moved them.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The terms, therefore, were reduced to
                    writing, on which they should enter into alliance and friendship <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> with the Roman people, and it was added, that
                        <quote> if it were agreeable to them and they wished it, the Eleans and
                        Lacedaemonians, with Attalus, Pleuratus, and Scerdilaedas, should be
                        included on the same conditions. </quote> Attalus was king of Asia; the
                    latter, kings of the Thracians and Illyrians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The conditions were, that <quote> the Aetolians should immediately make war on
                        Philip by land, in which the Romans should assist, with not less than twenty
                        quinqueremes. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That the site and
                        buildings, together with the walls and lands, of all the cities as far as
                        Corcyra, should become the property of the Aetolians, every other kind of
                        booty, of the Romans. That the Romans should endeavour to put the Aetolians
                        in possession of Acarnania. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If the
                        Aetolians should make peace with Philip, they should insert a stipulation
                        that the peace should stand good only on condition that they abstained from
                        hostilities against the Romans, their allies, and the states subject to
                        them. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In like manner, if the Romans
                        should form an alliance with the king, that they should provide that he
                        should not have liberty to make war upon the Aetolians and their allies. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Such were the terms agreed upon; and copies
                    of them having been made, they were laid up two years afterwards by the
                    Aetolians at Olympia, and by the Romans in the Capitol, that they might be
                    attested by these consecrated records. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The
                    delay had been occasioned by the Aetolian ambassadors' having been detained at
                    Rome. This, however, did not form an impediment to the war's proceeding. Both
                    the Aetolians immediately commenced war against Philip, and Laevinus taking, all
                    but the citadel, Zacynthus, a small island near to Aetolia, and having one city
                    of the same name with the island; and also taking $Aeniadae and <pb n="1051"
                        xml:id="p.1051"/> Nasus from the Acarnanians, annexed them to the Aetolians;
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> and also considering that Philip was
                    sufficiently engaged in war with his neighbours to prevent his thinking of
                    Italy, the Carthaginians, and his compact with Hannibal, he retired to Corcyra. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To Philip intelligence of the defection of the
                    Aetolians was brought while in winter quarters at Pella. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As he was about to march an army into Greece at the
                    beginning of the spring, he undertook a sudden expedition into the territories
                    of Oricum and Apollonia, in order that Macedonia might not be molested by the
                    Illyrians, and the cities bordering upon them, in consequence of the terror he
                    would thus strike them with in turn. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    Apollonians came out to oppose him, but he drove them, terrified and dismayed,
                    within their walls. After devastating the adjacent parts of Illyricum he turned
                    his course into Pelagonia, with the same expedition. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He then took Sintia, a town of the Dardanians, which would
                    have afforded them a passage into Macedonia. Having with the greatest despatch
                    performed these achievements, not forgetting the war made upon him by the
                    Aetolians and Romans in conjunction, he marched down into Thessaly through
                    Pelagonia, Lyncus, and Bottiaea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He trusted
                    that people might be induced to take part with him in the war against the
                    Aetolians, and, therefore, leaving Perseus with four thousand armed men at the
                    gorge, which <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> formed the entrance into
                    Thessaly, to prevent the Aetolians from passing it, before he should be occupied
                    with more important business, he marched his army into Macedonia, and thence
                    into Thrace and Maedica. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This nation had been
                    accustomed to make incursions into Macedonia when they perceived the king
                    engaged in a foreign war, and the kingdom left unprotected. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, he began to devastate the lands in the
                    neighbourhood of Phragandae, and to lay siege to the city Jamphorina, the
                    capital and chief fortress of Maedica. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scopas,
                    on hearing that the king had gone into Thrace, and was engaged in a war there,
                    armed all the Aetolian youths, and prepared to invade Acarnania. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The Acarnanian nation, unequal to their enemy in
                    point of strength, and seeing that they had lost Aeniadae and Nasus, and
                    moreover that the Roman arms were threatening them, prepare the war rather with
                    rage than prudence. Having sent their wives, children, and those who were above
                    sixty years old. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1052" xml:id="p.1052"/> into the neighbouring parts of Epirus, all who
                    were between the ages of fifteen and sixty, bound each other by an oath not to
                    return unless victorious. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That no one might
                    receive into his city or house, or admit to his table or hearth, such as should
                    retire from the field vanquished, they drew up a form of direful execration
                    against their countrymen who should do so; and the most solemn entreaty they
                    could devise, to friendly states. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At the same
                    time they entreated the Epirotes to bury in one tomb such of their men as should
                    fall in the encounter, adding this inscription over their remains: <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> HERE LIE THE ACARNANIANS, WHO DIED WHILE FIGHTING IN
                    DE- FENCE OF THEIR COUNTRY, AGAINST THE VIOLENCE AND IN- JUSTICE OF THE
                    AeTOLIANS. Having worked up their courage to the highest pitch by these means,
                    they fixed their camp at the extreme borders of their country in the way of the
                    enemy; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and sending messengers to Philip to
                    inform him of the critical situation in which they stood, they obliged him to
                    suspend the war in which he was engaged, though he had gained possession of
                    Jamphorina by surrender, and had succeeded in other respects. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> The ardour of the Aetolians was damped, in the first
                    instance, by the news of the combination formed by the Acarnanians; but
                    afterwards the intelligence of Philip's approach compelled them even to retreat
                    into the interior of the country. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Nor did
                    Philip proceed farther than Dium, though he had marched with great expedition to
                    prevent the Acarnanians being overpowered; and when he had received information
                    that the Aetolians had returned out of Acarnania, he also returned to Pella. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laevinus set sail from Corcyra in the
                    beginning of the spring, and doubling the promontory Leucate, arrived at
                    Naupactus; when he gave notice that he should go thence to Anticyra, in order
                    that Scopas and the Aetolians might be ready there to join him. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Anticyra is situated in Locris, on the left hand as you
                    enter the Corinthian Gulf. The distance between Naupactus and this place is
                    short both by sea and land. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In about three
                    days after, the attack upon this place commenced on both elements. The attack
                    from the sea produced the greatest effect, because there were on board the ships
                    engines and machines of every description, and because the Romans besieged from
                    that quarter. In a few days, therefore, the town surrendered, and was delivered
                    over to the <pb n="1053" xml:id="p.1053"/> Aetolians; the booty, according to
                    compact, was given up to the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Laevinus
                    then received a letter informing him, that he had been elected consul in his
                    absence, and that Publius Sulpicius was coming as his successor. He arrived at
                    Rome later than he was generally expected, being detained by a lingering
                    illness. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcus Marcellus, having entered upon
                    the consulship on the ides of March, assembled the senate on that day merely for
                    form's sake. He declared, that <quote> in the absence of his colleague he would
                        not enter into any question relative to the state or the provinces. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He said, <quote> he well knew there were
                        crowds of Sicilians in the neighbourhood of the city at the country-houses
                        of those who maligned him, whom he was so far from wishing to prevent from
                        openly publishing, at Rome, the charges which had been circulated and got up
                        against him by his enemies, that did they not pretend that they entertained
                        some fear of speaking of a consul in the absence of his colleague, he would
                        forthwith have given them a hearing of the senate. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> That when his colleague had arrived, he would not allow
                        any business to be transacted before the Sicilians were brought before the
                        senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That Marcus Cornelius had in a
                        manner held a levy throughout all Sicily, in order that as many as possible
                        might come to Rome to prefer complaints against him; that the same person
                        had filled the city with letters containing false representations that there
                        was still war in Sicily, in order to detract from his merit. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul, having acquired on that day the
                    reputation of having a well-regulated mind, dismissed the senate; and it
                    appeared that there would be almost a total suspension of every kind of business
                    till the other consul returned to the city. The want of employment, as usual,
                    produced expressions of discontent among the people. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> They complained of the length of the war; that the lands
                    around the city were devastated wherever Hannibal had marched his hostile
                    troops; that Italy was exhausted by levies, and that almost every year their
                    armies were cut to pieces; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that the consuls
                    elected were both of them fond of war, men over-enterprising and impetuous, who
                    would probably stir up war in a time of profound peace, and therefore were the
                    less likely to allow the state to breathe in time of war. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A fire which broke out in several places at
                    once in the neighbourhood of the forum, on the night before the festival <pb
                        n="1054" xml:id="p.1054"/> of Minerva, interrupted these discourses.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Seven shops, where five were afterwards
                    erected, and the banks, which are now called the new banks, were all on fire at
                    once. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Afterwards the private dwellings caught,
                    for there were no public halls there then, the prisons called the Quarry, the
                    fish-market, and the royal palace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The temple
                    of Vesta was with difficulty saved, principally by the exertions of thirteen
                    slaves, who were redeemed at the public expense and manumitted. The fire
                    continued for a day and a night. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was
                    evident to every body that it was caused by human contrivance, because the
                    flames burst forth in several places at once, and those at a distance from each
                    other. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul, therefore, on the
                    recommendation of the senate, publicly notified, that whoever should make known
                    by whose act the conflagration was kindled, should be rewarded; if a free-man,
                    with money, if a slave, with liberty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Induced
                    by this reward, a slave of the Campanian family, the Calavii, named Mannus, gave
                    information that <quote> his masters, with five noble Campanian youths, whose
                        parents had been executed by Fulvius, were the authors of the fire, and that
                        they would commit various other acts of the same kind if they were not
                        seized. </quote> Upon this they were seized, as well as their slaves.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At first, the informer and his evidence
                    were disparaged; for that "he had run away from his masters the day before in
                    consequence of a whipping, and that from an event which had happened by mere
                    chance, he had fabricated this charge, from resentment and wantonness.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But when they were charged by their
                    accusers face to face, and the ministers of their villanies began to be examined
                    in the middle of the forum, they all confessed; and punishment was inflicted
                    upon the masters and their accessory slaves. The informer received his liberty
                    and twenty thousand <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consul Laevinus, while passing by Capua,
                    was surrounded by a multitude of Campanians, who besought him, with tears, that
                    they might be permitted to go to Rome to the senate, so that if they could at
                    length be in any degree moved by compassion, they might not carry their
                    resentment so far as to destroy them utterly, nor suffer the very name of the
                    Campanian nation to be obliterated by Quintus Flaccus. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Flaccus declared, that <quote> he had individually no
                        quarrel with the Campanians, but that he did entertain an enmity towards
                        them on public grounds, and because they were foes, and should continue to
                        do so as <pb n="1055" xml:id="p.1055"/> long as he felt assured that they
                        had the same feelings towards the Roman people; for that there was no nation
                        or people on earth more inveterate against the Roman name. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> That his reason for keeping them shut up within their
                        walls was, that if any of these got out any where they roamed through the
                        country like wild beasts, tearing and massacring whatever fell in their way.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That some of them had deserted to
                        Hannibal, others had gone and set fire to Rome; that the consul would find
                        the traces of the villany of the Campanians in the half-burnt forum.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> That the temple of Vesta, the eternal
                        fire, and the fatal pledge for the continuance of the Roman empire deposited
                        in the shrine, had been the objects of their attack. That in his opinion it
                        was extremely unsafe for any Campanians to be allowed to enter the walls of
                        Rome. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Laevinus ordered the Campanians to follow him
                    to Rome, after Flaccus had bound them by an oath to return to Capua on the fifth
                    day after receiving an answer from the senate. <milestone n="16" unit="section"
                    /> Surrounded by this crowd, and followed also by the Sicilians and Aetolians,
                    who came out to meet him, he went to Rome; taking with him into the city as
                    accusers of two men who had acquired the greatest celebrity by the overthrow of
                    two most renowned cities, those whom they had vanquished in war. <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> Both the consuls, however, first proposed to the
                    senate the consideration of the state of the commonwealth, and the arrangements
                    respecting the provinces. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On this occasion Laevinus reported the state
                    of Macedonia and Greece, of the Aetolians, Acarnanians, and Locrians, and the
                    services he had himself performed there on sea and land. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> That <quote> Philip, who was bringing an army against the
                        Aetolians, had been driven back by him into Macedonia, and compelled to
                        retire into the heart of his kingdom. That the legion might therefore be
                        withdrawn from that quarter, and that the fleet was sufficient to keep the
                        king out of Italy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Thus much he said respecting himself and the
                    province where he had commanded. The consuls jointly proposed the consideration
                    of the provinces, when the senate decreed, that, <quote> Italy and the war with
                        Hannibal should form the province of one of the consuls; that the other
                        should have the command of the fleet which Titus Otacilius had commanded,
                        and the province of Sicily, in conjunction with Lucius Cincius, the praetor. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The two armies decreed to them were those in
                        <pb n="1056" xml:id="p.1056"/> Etruria and Gaul, consisting of four legions.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That the two city legions of the former
                    year should be sent into Etruria, and the two which Sulpicius, the consul, had
                    commanded, into Gaul; that he should have the command of Gaul, and the legions
                    there whom the consul, who had the province of Italy, should appoint. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Caius Calpurnius, having his command continued to him
                    for a year after the expiration of his praetorship, was sent into Etruria.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To Quintus Fulvius also the province of
                    Capua was decreed, with his command continued for a year. The army of citizens
                    and allies was ordered to be reduced, so that, out of two, <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> one legion should be formed consisting of five thousand
                    foot and three hundred horse, those being discharged who had served the greatest
                    number of campaigns. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That of the allies there
                    should be left seven thousand infantry and three hundred horse, the same rule
                    being observed with regard to the periods of their service in discharg- ing the
                    old soldiers. With Cneius Fulvius, the consul of the former year, no change was
                    made touching his province of Apulia nor his army; only he was continued in
                    command for a year. Publius Sulpicius, his colleague, was ordered to discharge
                    the whole of his army excepting the marines. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It was ordered also, that the army which Marcus Cornelius had commanded, should
                    be sent out of Sicily as soon as the consul arrived in his province. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The soldiers which had fought at Cannae, amounting
                    to two legions, were assigned to Lucius Cincius, the praetor, for the occupation
                    of Sicily. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As many legions were assigned to
                    Publius Manlius Vulso, the praetor, for Sardinia, being those which Lucius
                    Cornelius had commanded in that province the former year. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls were directed so to raise legions for the
                    service of the city, as not to enlist any one who had served in the armies of
                    Marcus Claudius, Marcus Valerius, or Quintus Fulvius, so that the Roman legions
                    might not exceed twenty-one that year. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the senate had passed these decrees, the
                    consuls drew lots for their provinces. Sicily and the fleet fell to the lot of
                    Marcellus; Italy, with the war against Hannibal, to Laevinus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This result so terrified the Sicilians, who were standing
                    in sight of the consuls waiting the determination of the lots, that their bitter
                    lamentations and mournful cries both drew upon them the eyes of all at the time,
                    and afterwards furnished matter for conversation. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> For they went round to <pb n="1057" xml:id="p.1057"/> the
                    several senators in mourning garments, affirming, that <quote> they would not
                        only abandon, each of them, his native country, but all Sicily, if Marcellus
                        should again go thither with command. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That
                        he had formerly been implacable toward them for no demerit of theirs; what
                        would he do now, when exasperated that they had come to Rome to complain of
                        him? That it would be better for that island to be overwhelmed with the
                        fires of Aetna, or sunk in the sea, than to be delivered up, as it were, for
                        execution to an enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These complaints of the Sicilians, having been
                    carried round to the houses of the nobility, and frequently canvassed in
                    conversations, which were prompted partly by compassion for the Sicilians and
                    partly by dislike for Marcellus, at length reached the senate also. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls were requested to take the sense of the
                    senate on an exchange of provinces. Marcellus said, that <quote> if the
                        Sicilians had already had an audience of the senate, his opinion perhaps
                        might have been different, but as the case now stood, lest any one should be
                        able <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> to say that they were prevented by
                        fear from freely venting their complaints respecting him, to whose power
                        they were presently about to be subject, he was willing, if it made no
                        difference to his colleague, to exchange provinces with him. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> That he deprecated a premature decision on the
                        part of the senate; for since it would be unjust that his colleague should
                        have the power of selecting his province without drawing lots, how much
                        greater injustice would it be, nay, rather indignity, for his lot to be
                        transferred to him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly the senate, having rather shown
                    than decreed what they wished, adjourned. An exchange of provinces was made by
                    the consuls of themselves; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> fate hurrying on
                    Marcellus to encounter Hannibal, that he might be the last of the Roman
                    generals, who, by his fall, when the affairs of the war were most prosperous,
                    might add to the glory of that man, from whom he derived the reputation of
                    having been the first Roman general who defeated him. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the provinces had been exchanged, the
                    Sicilians, on being introduced into the senate, discoursed largely on the
                    constant fidelity of king Hiero to the Roman people, converting it into a public
                    merit. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They said, <quote> that the tyrants,
                        Hieronymus, and, after him, Hippocrates and Epicydes, had been objects of
                        detestation to them, both on other accounts and especially on account of
                        their deserting the Romans to take <pb n="1058" xml:id="p.1058"/> part with
                        Hannibal. For this cause Hieronymus was put to death by the principal young
                        men among them, almost with the public concurrence, and a conspiracy was
                        formed to murder Epicydes and Hippocrates, by seventy of the most
                        distinguished of their youth; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but being
                        left without support in consequence of the delay of Marcellus, who neglected
                        to bring up his troops to Syracuse at the time agreed upon, they were all,
                        on an indictment that was made, put to death by the tyrants. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> That Marcellus, by the cruelty exercised in the
                        sacking of Leontini, had given occasion to the tyranny of Hippocrates and
                        Epicydes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From that time the leading men
                        among the Syracusans never ceased going over to Marcellus, and promising him
                        that they would deliver the city to him whenever he pleased; <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> but that he, in the first instance, was disposed
                        rather to take it by force, and afterwards, finding it impossible to effect
                        his object by sea or land, after trying every means, he preferred having
                        Syracuse delivered to him by Sosis, a brazier, and Mericus, a Spaniard, to
                        receiving it from the principal men of Syracuse, who had so often offered it
                        to him voluntarily to no purpose; doubtless in order that he might with a
                        fairer pretext butcher and plunder the most ancient allies of the Roman
                        people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If it had not been Hieronymus who
                        revolted to Hannibal, but the people and senate of Syracuse; if the body of
                        the Syracusan people, and not their tyrants, Hippocrates and Epicydes, who
                        held them in thraldrom, had closed the gates against Marcellus; <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> if they had carried on war with the Roman people
                        with the animosity of Carthaginians, what more could Marcellus have done in
                        hostility than he did, without levelling Syracuse with the ground?
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nothing indeed was left at Syracuse
                        except the walls and gutted houses of her city, the temples of her gods
                        broken open and plundered; her very gods and their ornaments having been
                        carried away. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> From many their possessions
                        also were taken away, so that they were unable to support themselves and
                        their families, even from the naked soil, the only remains of their
                        plundered property. They entreated the conscript fathers, that they would
                        order, if not all, at least such of their property as could be found and
                        identified, to be restored to the owners. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After they had made these complaints,
                    Laevinus ordered them to withdraw from the senate-house, that the senate might
                    deliberate <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> on their requests, when
                    Marcellus exclaimed, <quote> Nay, rather let <pb n="1059" xml:id="p.1059"/> them
                        stay here, that I may reply to their charges in their presence, since we
                        conduct your wars for you, conscript fathers, on the condition of having as
                        our accusers those whom we have conquered with our arms. Of the two cities
                        which have been captured this year, let Capua arraign Fulvius, and Syracuse
                        Marcellus. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The deputies having been brought back into the
                    senate-house, the consul said: <quote> I am not so unmindful of the dignity of
                        the Roman people and of the office I fill as consul, conscript fathers, as
                        to make a defence against charges brought by Greeks, had the inquiry related
                        only to my own delinquency. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But it is not
                        so much what I have done, as what they deserved to suffer, which comes into
                        dispute. For if they were not our enemies, there was no difference between
                        sacking Syracuse then, and when Hiero was alive. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> But if, on the other hand, they have renounced their
                        connexion with us, attacked our ambassadors sword in hand, shut us out of
                        their city and walls, and defended themselves against us with an army of
                        Carthaginians, who can feel indignant that they should suffer the
                        hostilities they have offered? I turned away from the leading men of the
                        Syracusans, when they were desirous of delivering up the city to me, and
                        esteemed Sosis and Mericus as more proper persons for so important an
                        affair. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now you are not the meanest of the
                        Syracusans, who reproach others with the meanness of their condition.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But who is there among you, who has
                        promised that he would open the gates to me, and receive my armed troops
                        within the city? You hate and execrate those who did so; and not even here
                        can you abstain from speaking with insult of them; so far is it from being
                        the case that you would yourselves have done any thing of the kind.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The very meanness of the condition of
                        those persons, conscript fathers, with which these men reproach them, forms
                        the strongest proof that I did not turn away from any man who was willing to
                        render a service to our state. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Before I
                        began the siege of Syracuse I attempted a peace, at one time by sending
                        ambassadors, at another time by going to confer with them; and after that
                        they refrained not from laying violent hands on my ambassadors, nor would
                        give me an answer when I held an interview with their chief men at their
                        gates, then, at length, after suffering many hard- ships by sea and land, I
                        took Syracuse by force of arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of <pb
                            n="1060" xml:id="p.1060"/> what befell them after their city was
                        captured they would complain with more justice to Hannibal, the
                        Carthaginians, and those who were vanquished with them, than to the senate
                        of the victorious people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If, conscript
                        fathers, I had intended to conceal the fact that I had despoiled Syracuse, I
                        should never have decorated the city of Rome with her spoils. As to what
                        things I either took from individuals or bestowed upon them, as conqueror, I
                        feel assured that I have acted agreeably to the laws of war, and the deserts
                        of each. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That you should confirm what I
                        have done, conscript fathers, certainly concerns the commonwealth more than
                        myself, since I have discharged my duty faithfully; but it is the duty of
                        the state to take care, lest, by rescinding my acts, they should render
                        other commanders for the time to come less zealous. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> And since, conscript fathers, you have heard both what
                        the Sicilians and I had to say, in the presence of each other, we will go
                        out of the senate-house together, in order that in my absence the senate may
                        deliberate more freely. </quote> Accordingly, the Sicilians having been
                    dismissed, he himself also went away to the Capitol to levy soldiers. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The other consul then proposed to the fathers
                    the consideration of the requests of the Sicilians, when a long debate took
                    place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A great part of the senate acquiesced
                    in an opinion which originated with Titus Manlius Torquatus, <quote> that the
                        war ought to have been carried on against the tyrants, the enemies both of
                        the Syracusans and the Roman people; that the city ought to have been
                        recovered, not captured; and, when recovered, should have been firmly
                        established under its ancient laws and liberty, and not distressed by war,
                        when worn out with a wretched state of bondage. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> That in the contest between the tyrants and the Roman
                        general, that most beautiful and celebrated city, formerly the granary and
                        treasury of the Roman people, which was held up as the reward of the victor,
                        had been destroyed; a city by whose munificence and bounty the commonwealth
                        had been assisted and adorned on many occasions, and lastly, during this
                        very Punic war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Should king Hiero, that
                        most faithful friend of the Roman empire, rise from the shades, with what
                        face could either Syracuse or Rome be shown to him, when, after beholding
                        his half-demolished and plundered native city, he should see, on entering
                        Rome, the spoils of his country in the <pb n="1061" xml:id="p.1061"/>
                        vestibule, as it were, of the city, and almost in the very gates? </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although these and other similar things were
                    said, to throw odium upon the consul and excite compassion for the Sicilians,
                    yet the fathers, out of regard for Marcellus, passed a milder decree, to the
                    effect, <quote> that what Marcellus had done while prosecuting the war, and when
                        victorious, should be confirmed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That for
                        the time to come, the senate would look to the affairs of Syracuse, and
                        would give it in charge to the consul Laevinus, to consult the interest of
                        that state, so far as it could be done without detriment to the
                        commonwealth. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Two senators having been sent to the Capitol
                    to request the consul to return to the senate-house, and the Sicilians having
                    been called in, the decree of the senate was read. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The deputies were addressed in terms of kindness, and
                    dismissed; when they threw themselves at the knees of the consul, Marcellus,
                    beseeching him to pardon them for what they had said for the purpose of exciting
                    compassion, and procuring relief from their calamities, and to receive
                    themselves and the city of Syracuse under his protection and patronage; after
                    which, the consul addressed them kindly and dismissed them. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An audience of the senate was then granted to
                    the Campanians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Their speech was more
                    calculated to excite compassion, but their case less favourable; for neither
                    could they deny that they deserved the punishment they had suffered, nor were
                    there any tyrants to whom they could transfer their guilt. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But they trusted that sufficient atonement had been made by
                    the death of so many of their senators by poison and the hands of the
                    executioner. They said, <quote> that a few only of their nobles remained, being
                        such as were not induced by the consciousness of their demerit to adopt any
                        desperate measure respecting themselves, and had not been condemned to death
                        through the resentment of their conquerors. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> That these implored the restoration of their liberty, and some portion of
                        their goods for themselves and families, being citizens of Rome, and most of
                        them connected with the Romans by affinity and now too near relationship, in
                        consequence of intermarriages which had taken place for a long period. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After this they were removed from the
                    senate-house, when for a short time doubts were entertained whether it would be
                    right or not to send for Quintus Fulvius from Capua, (for Claudius, the
                    proconsul, died after the capture of that place,) that the <pb n="1062"
                        xml:id="p.1062"/> question might be canvassed in the presence of the general
                    who had been concerned, as was done in the affair between Marcellus and the
                    Sicilians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But afterwards, when they saw in
                    the senate Marcus Atilius, and Caius Fulvius, the brother of Flaccus, his
                    lieutenant-generals, and Quintus Minucius, and Lucius Veturius Philo, who were
                    also his lieutenant-ge- nerals, who had been present at every transaction; and
                    being unwilling that Fulvius should be recalled from Capua, or the Campanians
                    put <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> off, Marcus Atilius Regulus, who
                    possessed the greatest weight of any of those present who had been at Capua,
                    being asked his opinion, thus spoke: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> I believe I assisted at the council held by the consuls after the
                        capture of Capua, when inquiry was made whether any of the Campanians had
                        deserved well of our state; and it was found that two women had done so;
                        Vestia Oppia, a native of Atella and an inhabitant of Capua, and Faucula
                        Cluvia, formerly a common woman. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        former had daily offered sacrifice for the safety and success of the Roman
                        people, and the latter had clandestinely supplied the starving prisoners
                        with food. The sentiments of all the rest of the Campanians towards us had
                        been the same, </quote> he said, <quote> as those of the Carthaginians; and
                        those who had been decapitated by Fulvius, were the most conspicuous in
                        rank, but not in guilt. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I do not see,
                    </quote> said he, <quote> how the senate can decide respecting the Campanians
                        who are Roman citizens, without an order of the people. And the course
                        adopted by our ancestors, in the case of the Satricani when they had
                        revolted, was, that Marcus Antistius, the plebeian tribune, should first
                        propose and the commons make an order, that the senate should have the power
                        of pronouncing judgment upon the Satricani. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> I therefore give it as my opinion, that application should be made to the
                        plebeian tribunes, that one or more of them should propose to the people a
                        bill, by which we may be empowered to determine in the case of the
                        Campanians. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Lucius Atilius, plebeian tribune, proposed to
                    the people, on the recommendation of the senate, a bill to the following effect:
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Concerning all the Campanians, Atellanians, Calatinians, and
                        Sabatinians, who have surrendered themselves to the proconsul Fulvius, and
                        have placed themselves under the authority and dominion of the Roman people;
                        also concerning what things they have surrendered, together with their
                        persons, both lands and city, <pb n="1063" xml:id="p.1063"/> divine or
                        human, together with their utensils and whatsoever else they have
                        surrendered; concerning these things, Roman citizens, I ask you what it is
                        your pleasure should be done. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The commons thus ordered: <quote> Whatsoever
                        the senate on oath, or the majority of those present, may determine, that we
                        will and order. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate having taken the matter into their
                    consideration in conformity with this order of the people, first restored to
                    Oppia and Cluvia their goods and liberty; directing, that if they wished to
                    solicit any other rewards from the senate, they should come to Rome. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Separate decrees were passed respecting each of the
                    Campanian families, all of which it is not worth while to enumerate. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The goods of some were to be confiscated; themselves,
                    their children, and their wives were to be sold, excepting such of their
                    daughters as had married before they came into the power of the Roman people.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Others were ordered to be thrown into
                    chains, and their cases to be considered at a future time. They made the amount
                    of income the ground on which they decided, whether the goods of the rest of the
                    Campanians should be confiscated or not. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                    voted, that all the cattle taken except the horses, all the slaves except adult
                    males, and every thing which did not belong to the soil, should be restored to
                    the owners. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They ordered that all the
                    Campanians, Atellanians, Calatinians, and Sabatinians, except such as were
                    themselves, or whose parents were, among the enemy, should be free, with a
                    proviso, that none of them should become a Roman citizen or a Latin confederate;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and that none of those who had been at
                    Capua while the gates were shut should remain in the city or territory of Capua
                    after a certain day. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That a place should be
                    assigned to them to inhabit beyond the Tiber, but not contiguous to it. That
                    those who had neither been in Capua nor in any Campanian city which had revolted
                    from the Romans during the war, should inhabit a place on this side the river
                    Liris towards Rome; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and that those who had
                    come over to the Romans before Hannibal arrived at Capua, should be removed to a
                    place on this side the Vulturnus, with a proviso, that none of them should have
                    either land or house within fifteen miles of the sea. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> That such of them as were removed to a place beyond the
                    Tiber, should neither themselves nor their posterity acquire or possess any
                    property any <pb n="1064" xml:id="p.1064"/> where, except in the Veientian,
                    Sutrian, or Nepetian territories; and, except on condition, that no one should
                    possess a greater extent of land than fifty acres. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> That the goods of all the senators, and such as had been
                    magistrates at Capua, Calatia, and Atella, should be sold at Capua; but that the
                    free persons who were decreed to be exposed to sale, should be sent to Rome and
                    sold there. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As to the images and brazen
                    statues, which were said to have been taken from the enemy, whether sacred or
                    profane, they referred them to the college of pontiffs. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> They sent the Campanians away, considerably more grieved
                    than they were when they came, in consequence of these decrees; and now they no
                    longer complained of the severity of Quintus Fulvius towards them, but of the
                    malignity of the gods and their own accursed fortune. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Sicilians and Campanians were
                    dismissed, a levy was made; and after the troops had been enlisted for the army,
                    they then began to consider about making up the number of rowers; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> but as there was neither a sufficient supply of men
                    for that purpose, nor any money at that time in the treasury by which <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> they might be purchased or paid, the consuls issued
                    an edict, that private persons should furnish rowers in proportion to their
                    income and rank, as had been done before, with pay and provisions for thirty
                    days. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So great was the murmuring and
                    indignation of the people, on account of this edict, that a leader, rather than
                    matter, was wanting for an insurrection. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It
                    was said, that <quote> the consuls, after having ruined the Sicilians and
                        Campanians, had undertaken to destroy and lacerate the Roman commons; that,
                        drained as they had been for so many years by taxes, they had nothing left
                        but wasted and naked lands. That the enemy had burned their houses, and the
                        state had taken away their slaves, who were the cultivators of their lands,
                        at one time by purchasing them at a low rate for soldiers, at another by
                        commanding a supply of rowers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If any one
                        had any silver or brass it was taken away from him, for the payment of
                        rowers or for annual taxes. That no force could compel and no command oblige
                        them to give what they had not got. That they might sell their goods and
                        then vent their cruelty on their persons, which were all that remained to
                        them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That they had nothing even left from
                        which they could be redeemed. </quote> These complaints were uttered not in
                    secret, but publicly in the forum, <pb n="1065" xml:id="p.1065"/> and before the
                    eyes of the consuls themselves, by an immense crowd which surrounded them;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> nor could the consuls appease them now by
                    coercing nor by soothing them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Upon this they
                    said that three days should be allowed them to consider of the matter; which
                    interval the consuls employed in examining and planning. The following day they
                    assembled the senate to consider of raising a supply of rowers; and after
                    arguing at great length that the people's refusal was fair, they brought their
                    discourse to this point, that whether it were just or unjust, this burden must
                    be borne by private individuals. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For from
                    what source could they procure rowers, when there was no money in the treasury?
                    and how, without fleets, could Sicily be kept in subjection, or Philip be
                    prevented from entering Italy, or the shores of Italy be protected? </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In this perplexing state of affairs, when all
                    deliberation was at a stand, and a kind of torpor had seized on men's minds,
                    Laevinus, the consul, observed, that "as the magistrates <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> were more honoured than the senators, and the senators than
                    the people, so also ought they to be the first in taking upon themselves every
                    thing that was burdensome and arduous. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If you
                    would enjoin any duty on an inferior, and would first submit yourself and those
                    belonging to you to the obligation, you will find everybody else more ready to
                    obey; nor is an expense thought heavy, when the people see every one of their
                    principal men taking upon himself more than his proportion of it. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Are we then desirous that the Roman people should
                    have and equip a fleet? that private individuals should without repugnance
                    furnish rowers? Let us first execute the command ourselves. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Let us, senators, bring into the treasury to-morrow all our
                    gold, silver, and coined brass, each reserving rings for himself, his wife, and
                    children, and a bulla for his son; and he who has a wife or daughters, an ounce
                    weight of gold for each. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Let those who have
                    sat in a curule chair have the ornaments of a horse, and a pound weight of
                    silver, that they may have a salt-cellar and a dish for the service of the gods.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Let the rest of us, senators, reserve for
                    each father of a family, a pound weight only of silver and five thousand coined
                        <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All the rest of our gold, silver, and coined
                    brass, let us immediately carry to the triumviri for banking affairs, no decree
                    of the senate having been previously <pb n="1066" xml:id="p.1066"/> made; that
                    our voluntary contributions, and our emulation in assisting the state, may
                    excite the minds, first, of the equestrian order to emulate us, and after them
                    of the rest of the community. This is the only course which we, your consuls,
                    after much conversation on the subject, have been able to discover. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Adopt it, then, and may the gods prosper the measure.
                    If the state is preserved, she can easily secure the property of her individual
                    members, but by betraying the public interests you would in vain preserve your
                    own. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This proposition was received with such
                    entire approbation, that thanks were spontaneously returned to the consuls.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The senate was then adjourned, when every
                    one of the members brought his gold, silver, and brass into the treasury, with
                    such emulation excited, that they were desirous that their names should appear
                    among the first on the public tables; so that neither the triumviri were
                    sufficient for receiving nor the notaries for entering them. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The unanimity displayed by the senate was imitated by the
                    equestrian order, and that of the equestrian order by the commons. Thus, without
                    any edict, or coercion of the magistrates, the state neither wanted rowers to
                    make up the numbers, nor money to pay them; and after every thing had been got
                    in readiness for the war, the consuls set out for their provinces. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nor was there ever any period of the war, when
                    both the Carthaginians and the Romans, plunged alike in vicissitudes, were in a
                    state of more anxious suspense between hope and fear. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For on the side of the Romans, with respect to their
                    provinces, their failure in Spain on the one hand, and their successes in Sicily
                    on the other, had blended joy and sorrow; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and
                    in Italy, the loss of Tarentum was an injury and a source of grief to them,
                    while the unexpected preservation of the citadel with the garrison was matter of
                    joy to them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The sudden terror and panic
                    occasioned by the siege and attack of Rome, was turned into joy by the capture
                    of Capua, a few days after. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their affairs
                    beyond sea also were equalized by a kind of compensation. Philip had become
                    their enemy at a juncture somewhat unseasonable; but then the Aetolians, and
                    Attalus, king of Asia, were added to their allies; fortune now, in a manner,
                    promising to the Romans the empire of the east. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> The Carthaginians also set the loss of Capua against the capture of Tarentum;
                    and as they consi- <pb n="1067" xml:id="p.1067"/> dered it as glorious to them
                    to have reached the walls of Rome without opposition, so they were chagrined at
                    the failure of their attempt; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and they felt
                    ashamed that they had been held in such contempt, that while they lay under the
                    walls of Rome, a Roman army was marched out for Spain at an opposite gate.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With regard also to Spain itself, the
                    greater the reason was to hope that the war there was terminated, and that the
                    Romans were driven from the country, after the destruction of two such renowned
                    generals and their armies, so much the greater was the indignation felt, that
                    the victory had been rendered void and fruitless by Lucius Marcius, a general
                    irregularly appointed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus fortune balancing
                    events against each other, all was suspense and uncertainty on both sides; their
                    hopes and their fears being as strong as though they were now first commencing
                    the war. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> What grieved Hannibal more than anything was
                    the fact, that Capua having been more perseveringly besieged by the Romans than
                    defended by him, had turned from him the regard of many of the states of Italy;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and it was not only impossible for him to
                    retain possession of all these by means of garrisons, unless he could make up
                    his mind to tear his army into a number of small portions, which at that time
                    was most inexpedient; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but he could not, by
                    withdrawing the garrisons, leave the fidelity of his allies open to the
                    influence of hope, or subject to that of fear. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    His disposition, which was strongly inclined to avarice and cruelty, induced him
                    to plunder the places he could not keep possession of, that they might be left
                    for the enemy in a state of desolation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This
                    resolution was equally horrid in principle and in its issue; for not only were
                    the affections of those who suffered such harsh treatment alienated from him,
                    but also of the other states; for the warning affected a greater number than did
                    the calamity. Nor did the Roman consul fail to sound the inclinations of the
                    cities, whenever any prospect of success presented itself. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Dasius and Blasius were the principal men in Salapia;
                    Dasius was the friend of Hannibal; Blasius, as far as he could do it with
                    safety, promoted the Roman interest; and, by means of secret messengers, had
                    given Marcellus hopes of having the place betrayed to him; but the business
                    could not be accomplished without the assistance of Dasius. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> After much and long hesitation, and <pb n="1068"
                        xml:id="p.1068"/> even then more for the want of a better plan than from any
                    hope of success, he addressed himself to Dasius; but he, being both adverse to
                    the measure and also hostile to his rival in the government, discovered the
                    affair to Hannibal. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Both parties were
                    summoned, and while Hannibal was transacting some business on his tribunal,
                    intending presently to take cognizance of the case of Blasius, and the accuser
                    and the accused were standing apart from the crowd, which was put back, Blasius
                    solicited Dasius on the subject of surrendering the city; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> when he exclaimed, as if the case were now clearly proved,
                    that he was being treated with about the betrayal of the city, even before the
                    eyes of Hannibal. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The more audacious the
                    proceeding was, the less probable did it appear to Hannibal and those who were
                    present. They considered that the charge was undoubtedly a matter of rivalry and
                    animosity, and that it had been brought because it was of such a nature that,
                    not admitting of being proved by witnesses, it could the more easily be
                    fabricated. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly the parties were
                    dismissed. But Blasius, notwithstanding, desisted not from his bold undertaking,
                    till by continually harping upon the same subject, and proving how conducive
                    such a measure would be to themselves and their country, he carried his point
                    that the Punic garrison, consisting of five hundred Numidians, and Salapia,
                    should be delivered up to Marcellus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Nor
                    could it be betrayed without much bloodshed, consisting of the bravest of the
                    cavalry in the whole Punic army. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Accordingly,
                    though the event was unexpected, and their horses were of no use to them in the
                    city, yet hastily taking arms, during the confusion, they endeavoured to force
                    their way out; and not being able to escape, they fell fighting to the last, not
                    more than fifty of them falling into the hands of the enemy alive. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> The loss of this body of cavalry was considerably
                    more detrimental to Hannibal than that of Salapia, for the Carthaginian was
                    never afterwards superior in cavalry, in which he had before been most
                    effective. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this time the scarcity of provisions in
                    the citadel of Tarentum was almost intolerable; the Roman garrison there, and
                    Marcus Livius, the prefect of the garrison and the citadel, placing all their
                    dependence in the supplies sent from Sicily; that these might safely pass along
                    the coast of Italy, a <pb n="1069" xml:id="p.1069"/> fleet of about twenty ships
                    was stationed at Rhegium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Decius Quinctius, a
                    man of obscure birth, but who had acquired great renown as a soldier, on account
                    of many acts of bravery, had charge of the fleet and the convoys. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> At first he had five ships, the largest of which were
                    two triremes, given to him by Marcellus; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but
                    afterwards, in consequence of his spirited conduct on many occasions, three
                    quinqueremes were added to his number; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> at
                    last, by exacting from the allied states of Rhegium, Velia, and Paestum, the
                    ships they were bound to furnish according to treaty, he made up a fleet of
                    twenty ships, as was before stated. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This fleet
                    setting out from Rhegium, was met at Sacriportus, about fifteen miles from the
                    city, by Democrates, with an equal number of Tarentine ships. It happened that
                    the Roman was then coming with his sails up, not expecting an approaching
                    contest; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but in the neighbourhood of Croto and
                    Sybaris, he had supplied his ships with rowers, and had his fleet excellently
                    equipped and armed for the size of his vessels; <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> and it also happened, that just at the time when the enemy were in sight, the
                    wind completely fell, so that there was sufficient time to furl their sails, and
                    get their rowers and soldiers in readiness for the approaching action. Rarely
                    elsewhere have regular fleets engaged with so much spirit, for they fought for
                    what was of greater importance than the fleets themselves. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The Tarentines, in order that, having recovered their city
                    from the Romans after the lapse of almost a century, they might also rescue
                    their citadel; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> hoping also to cut off the
                    supplies of their enemy, if by a naval battle they could deprive them of the
                    dominion of the sea. The Romans, that, by keeping possession of the citadel,
                    they might prove that Tarentum was lost not by the strength and valour of their
                    enemies, but by treachery and stealth. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, the signal having been given on both sides, they charged each other
                    with the beaks of their ships, and neither did they draw back their own, nor
                    allow the ships of the enemy with which they were engaged to separate from them,
                    having thrown their grappling irons; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and thus
                    the battle was carried on in such close quarters, that they fought not only with
                    missile weapons, but in a manner foot to foot even with their swords. The prows
                    joined together remained stationary, while the sterns were moved round by the
                    force of their adversaries' oars. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The ships
                    were crowded together in so small a com- <pb n="1070" xml:id="p.1070"/> pass,
                    that scarcely one weapon fell into the sea without taking effect. They pressed
                    front against front like lines of troops engaging on land, and the combatants
                    could pass from one ship to another. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But the
                    contest between two ships which had engaged each other in the van, was
                    remarkable above the rest. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In the Roman ship
                    was Quinctius himself, in the Tarentine, Nico, surnamed Perco, who hated, and
                    was hated by, the Romans, not only on public grounds, but also personally, for
                    he belonged to that faction which had betrayed Tarentum to Hannibal. This man
                    transfixed Quinctius with a spear while off his guard, and engaged at once in
                    fighting and encouraging his men, and he immediately fell headlong with his arms
                    over the prow. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The victorious Tarentine
                    promptly boarded the ship, which was all in confusion from the loss of the
                    commander, <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> and when he had driven the enemy
                    back, and the Tarentines had got possession of the prow, the Romans, who had
                    formed themselves into a compact body, with difficulty defending the stern,
                    suddenly another trireme of the enemy appeared at the stern. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> Thus the Roman ship, enclosed between the two, was
                    captured. Upon this a panic spread among the rest, seeing the commander's ship
                    captured, and flying in every direction, some were sunk in the deep and some
                    rowed hastily to land, where, shortly after, they became a prey to the Thurians
                    and Metapontines. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Of the storeships which
                    followed, laden with provisions, a very few fell into the hands of the enemy;
                    the rest, shifting their sails from one side to another with the changing winds,
                    escaped into the open sea. An affair took place at Tarentum at this time, which
                    was attended with widely different success; <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    for a party of four thousand men had gone out to forage, and while they were
                    dispersed, and roaming through the country, Livius, the commander of the citadel
                    and the <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/> Roman garrison, who was anxious to
                    seize every opportunity of striking a blow, sent out of the citadel Caius
                    Persius, an active officer, with two thousand soldiers, who attacked them
                    suddenly when widely dispersed and straggling about the fields; <milestone
                        n="22" unit="section"/> and after slaying them for a long time on all hands,
                    drove the few that remained of so many into the city, to which they fled in
                    alarm and confusion, and where they rushed in at the doors of the gates, which
                    were half-opened that the city might not be taken in the same attack. <milestone
                        n="23" unit="section"/> In this manner affairs were equally balanced <pb
                        n="1071" xml:id="p.1071"/> at Tarentum, the Romans being victorious by land,
                    and the Tarentines by sea. Both parties were equally disappointed in their hope
                    of receiving provisions, after they were within sight. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were ocucrring, the consul,
                    Laevinus, after a great part of the year had elapsed, having arrived in Sicily,
                    where he had been expected by both the old and new allies, considered it his
                    first and principal duty to adjust the affairs of Syracuse, which were still in
                    a state of disorder, the peace being but recent. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> He then marched his legions to Agrigentum, the seat of the remaining part of
                    the war, which was occupied by a strong garrison of Carthaginians; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> and here fortune favoured his attempt. Hanno was
                    commander-in- chief of the Carthaginians, but their whole reliance was placed
                    upon Mutines and the Numidians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Mutines,
                    scouring the whole of Sicily, employed himself in carrying off spoil from the
                    allies of the Romans; nor could he by force or stratagem be cut off from
                    Agrigentum, or prevented from sallying from it whenever he pleased. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The renown which he gained by this conduct, as it
                    began now to eclipse the fame of the commander-in-chief, was at last converted
                    into a source of jealousy; so that even now his successes were not as acceptable
                    as they ought to have been, on account of the person who gained them. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> For these reasons Hanno at last gave his commission
                    to his own son, concluding that by taking away his command he should also
                    deprive him of the influence he possessed with the Numidians. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> But the result was very different; for their former
                    attachment to him was increased by the envy incurred by him. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Nor did he brook the affront put upon him by this injurious
                    treatment, but immediately sent secret messengers to Laevinus, to treat about
                    delivering up Agrigentum. After an agreement had been entered into by means of
                    these persons, and the mode of carrying it into execution concerted, the Nu-
                    midians seized on a gate which leads towards the sea, having driven the guards
                    from it, or put them to the sword, and then received into the city a party of
                    Romans sent for that purpose; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and when these
                    troops were now marching into the heart of the city and the forum with a great
                    noise, Hanno, concluding that it was nothing more than a disturbance and
                    secession of the Numidians, such as had happened before, advanced to quell <pb
                        n="1072" xml:id="p.1072"/> the mutiny; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    but observing at a distance that the numbers were greater than those of the
                    Numidians, and hearing the Roman shout, which was far from being new to him, he
                    betook himself to flight before he came within reach of their weapons.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Passing out of the town at a gate in the
                    opposite quarter, and taking Epicydes to accompany him, he reached the sea with
                    a few attendants; and having very seasonably met with a small vessel, they
                    abandoned to the enemy Sicily, for which they had contended for so many years,
                    and crossed over into Africa. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The remaining
                    multitude of Carthaginians and Sicilians fled with headlong haste, but as every
                    passage by which they could escape was blockaded up, they were cut to pieces
                    near the gates. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On gaining possession of the
                    town, Laevinus scourged and beheaded those who took the lead in the affairs of
                    Agrigentum. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The rest, together with the
                    booty, he sold. All the money he sent to Rome. Accounts of the sufferings of the
                    Agrigentines spreading through all Sicily, all the states suddenly turned to the
                    Romans. In a short time twenty towns were betrayed to them, and six taken by
                    storm. As many as forty put themselves under their protection, by voluntary
                    surrender. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The consul having rewarded and
                    punished the leading men of these states, according to their several deserts,
                    and compelled the Sicilians, now that they had at length laid aside arms, to
                    turn their attention to the cultivation of their lands, <milestone n="16??"
                        unit="section"/> in order that the island might by its produce not only
                    maintain its inhabitants, but, as it had frequently done on many former
                    occasions, add to the supplies of Rome and Italy, he returned into Italy, taking
                    with him a disorderly multitude from Agathyrna. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                    /> These were as many as four thousand men, made up of a mixed assemblage of
                    every description of persons, exiles, bankrupts, the greater part of them
                    felons, who had supported themselves by rapine and robbery, both when they lived
                    in their native towns, under the restraint of the laws, and also after that a
                    coincidence in their fortunes, brought about by causes different in each case,
                    had congregated them at Agathyrna. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> These men
                    Laevinus thought it hardly safe to leave in the island, when an unwonted
                    tranquillity was growing up, as the materials of fresh disturbances; and
                    besides, they were likely to be useful to the Rhegians, who were in want of a
                    band of men <pb n="1073" xml:id="p.1073"/> habituated to robbery, for the
                    purpose of committing depredations upon the Bruttian territory. Thus, so far as
                    related to Sicily, the war was this year terminated. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Spain, in the beginning of spring, Publius
                    Scipio, having launched his ships, and summoned the auxiliary troops of his
                    allies to Tarraco by an edict, ordered his fleet and transports to proceed
                    thence to the mouth of the Iberus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He also
                    ordered his legions to quit their winter quarters, and meet at the same place;
                    and then set out from Tarraco, with five thousand of the allies, to join the
                    army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On his arrival at the camp he considered
                    it right to harangue his soldiers, particularly the old ones who had survived
                    such dreadful disasters; and therefore, calling an assembly, he thus addressed
                    them: <quote> Never was there a new commander before myself who could, with
                        justice and good reason, give thanks to his soldiers before he had availed
                        himself of their services. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fortune laid me
                        under obligations to you before I set eyes on my province or your camp;
                        first, on account of the respect you have shown to my father and uncle, both
                        in their lifetime and since their death; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        and secondly, because by your valour you have recovered and preserved
                        entire, for the Roman people, and me their successor, the possession of the
                        province which had been lost in consequence of so dreadful a calamity.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But since, now, by the favour of the
                        gods, our purpose and endeavour is not that we may remain in Spain
                        ourselves, but that the Carthaginians may not; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> and not to stand on the bank of the Iberus, and hinder
                        the enemy from crossing that river, but cross it first ourselves, and carry
                        the war to the other side, I fear lest to some among you the enterprise
                        should appear too important and daring, considering your late misfortunes,
                        which are fresh in your recollection, and my years. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> There is no person from whose mind the memory of the
                        defeats sustained in Spain could be obliterated with more difficulty than
                        from mine; inasmuch as there my father and uncle were both slain within the
                        space of thirty days, so that one death after another was accumulated on my
                        family. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But as the orphanhood and
                        desolation of my own family depresses my mind, so both the good fortune and
                        valour of our nation forbid me to despair of the safety of the state. It has
                        happened to us by a kind of fatality, that in all important wars we have
                        been victorious, after having been defeated. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> I pass <pb n="1074" xml:id="p.1074"/> over those wars
                        of ancient date with Porsena, the Gauls, and Samnites. I will begin with the
                        Punic wars. How many fleets, generals, and armies were lost in the former
                        war? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Why should I mention what has
                        occurred in this present war? I have either been myself present at all the
                        defeats sustained, or have felt more than any other those from which I was
                        absent. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> What else are the Trebia, the
                        Trasimenus, and Cannas, but monuments of Roman armies and consuls slain? Add
                        to these the defection of Italy, of the greater part of Sicily and Sardinia,
                        and the last terror and panic, the Carthaginian camp pitched between the
                        Anio and the walls of Rome, and the victorious Hannibal seen almost in our
                        gates. Amid this general ruin, the courage of the Roman people alone stood
                        unabated and unshaken. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> When every thing
                        lay prostrate on the ground, it was this that raised and supported the
                        state. You, first of all, my soldiers, under the conduct and auspices of my
                        father, opposed Hasdrubal on his way to the Alps and Italy, after the defeat
                        of Cannae, who, had he formed a junction with his brother, the Roman name
                        would now have been extinct. These successes formed a counterpoise to those
                        defeats. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Now, by the favour of the gods,
                        every thing in Italy and Sicily is going on prosperously and successfully,
                        every day affording matter of fresh joy, and presenting things in a better
                        light. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In Sicily, Syracuse and Agrigentum
                        have been captured, the enemy entirely expelled the island, and the province
                        placed again under the dominion of the Romans. In Italy, Arpi has been
                        recovered and Capua taken. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Hannibal has
                        been driven into the remotest corner of Bruttium, having fled thither all
                        the way from Rome, in the utmost confusion; and now he asks the gods no
                        greater boon than that he might be allowed to retire in safety, and quit the
                        territory of his enemy. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> What then, my
                        soldiers, could be more preposterous than that you, who here supported the
                        tottering fortune of the Roman people, together with my parents, (for they
                        may be equally associated in the honour of that epithet,) when calamities
                        crowded one upon another in quick succession, and even the gods themselves,
                        in a manner, took part with Hannibal, should now sink in spirits when every
                        thing is going on happily and prosperously? <milestone n="18" unit="section"
                        /> Even with regard to the events which have recently occurred, I could wish
                        that they had passed with as little grief <pb n="1075" xml:id="p.1075"/> to
                        me as to you. At the present time the immortal gods who preside over the
                        destinies of the Roman empire, who inspired all the centuries to order the
                        command to be given to me, those same gods, I say, by auguries and auspices,
                        and even by nightly visions, portend entire success and joy. <milestone
                            n="19" unit="section"/> My own mind also, which has hitherto been to me
                        the truest prophet, presages that Spain will be ours; that the whole
                        Carthaginian name will in a short time be banished from this land, and will
                        fill both sea and land with ignominious flight. <milestone n="20"
                            unit="section"/> What my mind presages spontaneously, is also supported
                        by sound reasoning. Their allies, annoyed by them, are by ambassadors
                        imploring our protection; their three generals, having differed so far as
                        almost to have abandoned each other, have divided their army into three
                        parts, which they have drawn off into regions as remote as possible from
                        each other. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> The same fortune now
                        threatens them which lately afflicted us; for they are both deserted by
                        their allies, as formerly we were by the Celtiberians, and they have divided
                        their forces, which occasioned the ruin of my father and uncle. <milestone
                            n="22" unit="section"/> Neither will their intestine differences allow
                        them to unite, nor will they be able to cope with us singly. Only do you, my
                        soldiers, favour the name of the Scipios, favour the offspring of your
                        generals, a scion springing up from the trunks which have been cut down.
                            <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> Come then, veterans, lead your new
                        commander and your new army across the Iberus, lead us across into a country
                        which you have often traversed, with many a deed of valour. <milestone
                            n="24" unit="section"/> I will soon bring it to pass that, as you now
                        trace in me a likeness to my father and uncle in my features, countenance,
                        and figure, I will so restore a copy of their genius, honour, and courage,
                        to <milestone n="25??" unit="section"/> you, that every man of you shall say
                        that his commander, Scipio, has either returned to life, or has been born
                        again. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having animated his troops with this harangue,
                    and leaving Marcus Silanus with three thousand infantry and three hundred horse,
                    for the protection of that district, he crossed the Iberus with all the rest of
                    his troops, consisting of twenty-five thousand infantry and two thousand five
                    hundred horse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Though certain persons there
                    endeavoured to persuade him that, as the Carthaginian armies had retired from
                    each other into three such distant quarters, he should attack the nearest of
                    them; yet concluding that if he did so there was danger lest he should cause
                    them to concentrate all <pb n="1076" xml:id="p.1076"/> their forces, and he
                    alone should not be a match for so many, he determined for <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> the present to make an attack upon New Carthage, a city not
                    only possessing great wealth of its own, but also full of every kind of military
                    store belonging to the enemy; there were their arms, their money, and the
                    hostages from every part of Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was,
                    besides, conveniently situated, not only for a passage into Africa, but also
                    near a port sufficiently capacious for a fleet of any magnitude, and, for aught
                    I know, the only one on the coast of Spain which is washed by our sea. No one
                    but Caius Laelius knew whither he was going. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    He was sent round with the fleet, and ordered so to regulate the sailing of his
                    ships, that the army might come in view and the fleet enter the harbour at the
                    same time. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Both the fleet and army arrived at
                    the same time at New Carthage, on the seventh day after leaving the Iberus. The
                    camp was pitched over against that part of the city which looks to the north.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A rampart was thrown up as a defence on
                    the rear of it, for the front was secured by the nature of the ground. Now the
                    situation of New Carthage is as follows: at about the middle of the coast of
                    Spain is a bay facing for the most part the south-west, about two thousand five
                    hundred paces in depth, and a little more in breadth. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> In the mouth of this bay is a small island forming a
                    barrier towards the sea, and protecting the harbour from every wind except the
                    south-west. From the bottom of the bay there runs out a peninsula, which forms
                    the eminence on which the city is built; which is washed in the east and south
                    by the sea, and on the west is enclosed by a lake which extends a little way
                    also towards the north, of variable depth according as the sea overflows or
                    ebbs. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> An isthmus of about two hundred paces
                    broad connects the city with the continent, on which, though it would have been
                    a work of so little labour, the Roman general did not raise a rampart;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> whether his object was to make a display
                    of his confidence to the enemy from motives of pride, or that he might have free
                    regress when frequently advancing to the walls of the city. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having completed the other requisite works, he
                    drew up his ships in the harbour, that he might exhibit to the enemy the
                    appearance of a blockade by sea also; he then went round the fleet, and having
                    warned the commanders of the ships to be particularly careful in keeping the
                    night-watches, because an enemy, when besieged, usually tried every effort <pb
                        n="1077" xml:id="p.1077"/> and in every quarter at first, he returned into
                    his camp; and in order to explain to his soldiers the reason why he had adopted
                    the plan of commencing the war with the siege of a city, in preference to any
                    other, and also by exhortations to inspire them with hopes of making themselves
                    masters of it, he summoned them to an assembly, and thus addressed them:
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Soldiers, if any one among you suppose that you have been brought here
                        to attack a single city, that man takes a more exact account of your present
                        labour than of its profitable result from it. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> For you will in truth attack the walls of a single
                        city, but in that single city you will have made yourselves masters of all
                        Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here are the hostages of all her
                        most distinguished kings and states; and as soon as you shall have gained
                        possession of these, they will immediately deliver into your hands every
                        thing which is now subject to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Here is the whole of the enemy's treasure, without
                        which they cannot carry on the war, as they are keeping mercenary troops,
                        and which will be most serviceable to us in conciliating the affections of
                        the barbarians. Here are their engines, their arms, their tackle, and every
                        requisite in war; which will at once supply you, and leave the enemy
                        destitute. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Besides, we shall gain
                        possession of a city, not only of the greatest beauty and wealth, but also
                        most convenient as having an excellent harbour, by means of which we may be
                        supplied with every requisite for carrying on the war both by sea and land.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Great as are the advantages we shall
                        thus gain, we shall deprive our enemies of much greater. This is their
                        citadel, their granary, their treasury, their magazine, their receptacle for
                        every thing. Hence there is a direct passage into Africa; this is the only
                        station for a fleet between the Pyrenees and Gades; this gives to Africa the
                        command of all Spain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But as I perceive
                        you are arrayed and marshalled, let us pass on to the assault of New
                        Carthage, with our whole strength, and with undaunted courage. </quote> Upon
                    this, they all with one accord cried out that it should be done; and he led them
                    to Carthage, and ordered that the assault should be made both by sea and land. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the other side, Mago, the Carthaginian
                    general, perceiving that a siege was being prepared for both by sea and land,
                    himself also disposed his forces thus: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> he
                    placed two thousand of the townsmen to oppose the enemy, on the side <pb
                        n="1078" xml:id="p.1078"/> facing the Roman camp; he occupied the citadel
                    with five hundred soldiers, and stationed five hundred on a rising ground,
                    facing the east; the rest of his troops he ordered, intent on every thing that
                    occurred, to hasten with assistance wherever the shout, or any sudden emergency,
                    might call them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then, throwing open the gate,
                    he sent out those he had drawn up in the street leading to the camp of the
                    enemy. The Romans, according to the direction of their general, retired a
                    little, in order that they might be nearer to the reserved troops which were to
                    be sent to their assistance during the engagement. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> At first they stood with pretty equal force, but afterwards
                    the reserved troops, sent from time to time from the camp, not only obliged the
                    enemy to turn their backs, but followed them up so close when flying in
                    disorder, that had not a retreat been sounded, they seemed as though they would
                    have rushed into the city together with the fugitives. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The consternation in the field was not greater than in
                    every part of the city; many of the outposts were abandoned in panic and flight;
                    and the walls were deserted, as they leaped down each in the part nearest him.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Scipio, who had gone out to an eminence
                    called Mercury's hill, perceiving that the walls were abandoned by their
                    defenders in many parts, ordered all his men to be called out of his camp and
                    advance to take the city, and orders them to bring the scaling-ladders.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The general himself, covered by the
                    shields of three stout young men, (for now an immense number of missiles of
                    every description were let fly from the walls,) came up to the city, cheered
                    them on, and gave the requisite orders; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and,
                    what was of the utmost importance in exciting the courage of his men, he
                    appeared among them a witness and spectator of the valour or cowardice of each.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly, they rushed forward, amidst
                    wounds and weapons; nor could the walls, or the armed troops which stood upon
                    them, repel them from eagerly mounting them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    At the same time an attack was commenced by the fleet upon that part of the city
                    which was washed by the sea. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But here the
                    alarm occasioned was greater than the force which could be employed; for while
                    they were bringing the boats to shore, and hastily landing the ladders and the
                    men, each man pressing forward to gain the land the shortest way, they hindered
                    one another by their very haste and eagerness. <pb n="1079" xml:id="p.1079"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time, the Carthaginians had now
                    filled the walls again with armed men, who were supplied with a great quantity
                    of missiles from the immense stores which they had laid up. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But neither men nor missiles, nor any thing else, so
                    effectually defended them as the walls themselves; for very few of the ladders
                    were equal to the height of them, and all those which were longer than the rest
                    were proportionably weaker. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, those
                    who were highest being unable to mount from them, and being followed,
                    nevertheless, by others, they broke from the mere weight upon them. Some, though
                    the ladders stood, a dizziness having come over their eyes in consequence of the
                    height, fell to the ground. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And as men and
                    ladders were every where tumbling down, while the boldness and alacrity of the
                    enemy were increased by the mere success, the signal for retreat was sounded;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> which afforded hopes to the besieged, not
                    only of present rest after such a laborious contest, but also for the future, as
                    it appeared their city could not be taken by scalade and siege. To raise works
                    they considered would be attended with difficulty, and would give time to their
                    generals to bring them assistance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Scarcely
                    had the first tumult subsided, when Scipio ordered other fresh and unfatigued
                    troops to take the ladders from those who were tired and wounded, and assault
                    the city with increased vigour. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having
                    received intelligence that the tide was ebbing, and having before been informed
                    by some fishermen of Tarraco who used to pass through the lake, sometimes in
                    light boats, and, when these ran aground, by wading, that it afforded an easy
                    passage to the wall for footmen, he led some armed men thither in person.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was about mid-day, and besides that the
                    water was being drawn off naturally, in consequence of the tide receding, a
                    brisk north wind rising impelled the water in the lake, which was already in
                    motion, in the same direction as the tide, and rendered it so shallow, that in
                    some parts the water reached only to the navel, while in others it scarcely rose
                    above the knees. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio, referring this
                    discovery, which he had made by his own diligence and penetration, to the gods
                    and to miracle, which had turned the course of the sea, withdrawn it from the
                    lake, and opened ways never before trodden by human feet to afford a passage to
                    the Romans, ordered them to follow Neptune as their guide, and <pb n="1080"
                        xml:id="p.1080"/> passing through the middle of the lake, make good their
                    way to the walls. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Those who renewed the assault by land
                    experienced great difficulty; for they were baffled not only by the height of
                    the walls, but also because they exposed the Romans, as they approached them, to
                    the missiles of the enemy from different quarters, so that their sides were
                    endangered more than the fronts of their bodies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> But in the other quarter five hundred passed without difficulty through the
                    lake, and then mounted the wall, for neither was it defended by any
                    fortifications, because there they thought the city was sufficiently protected
                    by the nature of the place and the lake, nor were there any outposts or guards
                    stationed there, because all were engaged in bringing succour to that quarter in
                    which the danger appeared. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Having entered the
                    city without opposition, they proceeded direct, with all possible speed, to that
                    gate near which the contest was concentrated; and so intently occupied with this
                    were not only the minds, but the eyes and ears of all, both of those <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> who were engaged in fighting, and of those who were
                    looking on and encouraging the combatants, that no one perceived <milestone
                        n="5??" unit="section"/> that the city had been captured in their rear till
                    the weapons fell upon their backs, and they had an enemy on both sides of them.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then, the defenders having been thrown
                    into confusion through fear, both the walls were captured, and the gate began to
                    be broken open both from within and from without; and presently, the doors
                    having been broken to pieces by blows, in order that the way might not be
                    obstructed, the troops rushed in. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A great
                    number had also got over the walls, but these employed themselves in putting the
                    townsmen to the sword; those which entered by the gate, forming a regular body,
                    with officers and in ranks, advanced through the midst of the city into the
                    forum. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio then perceiving that the enemy
                    fled in two different directions, some to the eminence which lay eastward, which
                    was occupied by a garrison of five hundred men, others to the citadel, into
                    which Mago himself also had fled for refuge, together with almost all the troops
                    which had been driven from the walls, sent part of his forces to storm the hill,
                    and part he led in person against the citadel. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Not only was the hill captured at the first assault, but Mago also, after making
                    an effort to defend <pb n="1081" xml:id="p.1081"/> it, when he saw every place
                    filled with the enemy, and that there was no hope, surrendered himself and the
                    citadel, with the garrison. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Until the citadel
                    was surrendered, the massacre was continued in every quarter throughout the
                    city; nor did they spare any one they met who had arrived at puberty: but after
                    that, on a signal given, a stop was put to the carnage, and the victors turned
                    their attention to the plunder, of which there was an immense quantity of every
                    description. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Of males of free condition, as many as ten
                    thousand were captured. Of these he allowed to depart such as were citizens of
                    New Carthage; and restored to them their city, and all their property which the
                    war had left them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The artisans amounted to
                    two thousand, whom he assigned to the Roman people as their property; holding
                    out to them a hope of speedy emancipation, provided they should address
                    themselves strenuously to the service of the war. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Of the rest of the mass of inhabitants, the young men and
                    able-bodied slaves he assigned for the service of the fleet, to fill up the
                    numbers of the rowers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had also augmented
                    his fleet with five ships which he had captured. Besides this multitude, there
                    remained the Spanish hostages, to whom as much attention was paid as if they had
                    been children of allies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> An immense quantity
                    of military stores was also taken; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> one hundred
                    and twenty catapults of the larger size, two hundred and eighty-one of the
                    smaller; twenty-three balistae of the larger size, fifty-two of the smaller; an
                    immense number of scorpions of the larger and smaller size, and also of arms and
                    missile weapons; and seventy-four military standards. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Of gold and silver, an immense quantity was brought to the
                    general; there were two hundred and seventy-six golden bowls, almost all of them
                    weighing a pound; of silver, wrought and coined, eighteen thousand three hundred
                    pounds' weight; and of silver vessels an immense number. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> All these were weighed and reckoned to the quaestor, Caius
                    Flaminius. There were twenty thousand pecks of wheat, and two hundred and
                    seventy of barley. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> One hundred and thirteen
                    ships of burden were boarded and captured in the harbour, some of them with
                    their cargoes, consisting of corn and arms, besides brass, iron, sails, spartum,
                    and other naval materials, of use in equipping a fleet; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> so that amid such large military stores which were
                    captured, Car- thage itself was of the least consideration. <pb n="1082"
                        xml:id="p.1082"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having ordered Caius Laelius with the marines
                    to guard the city, Scipio led back his legions to the camp the same day in
                    person; and as his soldiers were tired, as they had in one day gone through
                    every kind of military labour; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for they had
                    engaged the enemy in the field, and had undergone very great fatigue and danger
                    in taking the city; and after they had taken it had fought, and that on
                    disadvantageous ground, with those who had fled to the citadel, he ordered them
                    to attend to themselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The next day, having
                    assembled the land and naval forces, he, in the first place, ascribed praise and
                    thanks to the immortal gods, who had not only in one day made him master of the
                    wealthiest city in Spain, but had previously collected in it the riches of
                    almost all Africa and Spain; so that while his enemy had nothing left, he and
                    his army had a superabundance of every thing. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He then commended in the highest terms the valour of his soldiers, because that
                    neither the sally of the enemy, nor the height of the walls, nor the unexplored
                    fords of the lake, nor the fort standing upon a high hill, nor the citadel,
                    though most strongly fortified, had deterred them from surmounting and breaking
                    through every thing. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Therefore, though all
                    credit was due to them all, he said that the man who first mounted the wall
                    ought to be distinguished above the rest, by being honoured with a mural crown;
                    and he desired that he who thought himself worthy of that reward would claim it.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two persons laid claim to it, Quintus
                    Trebellius, a centurion of the fourth legion, and Sextus Digitius, a marine. Nor
                    did these contest so fiercely as each excited the zeal of his own body of men.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Caius Laelius, admiral of the fleet,
                    patronized the marines, and Marcus Sempronius Tuditanus, the legionary troops.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As this contest began almost to assume the
                    character of a mutiny, Scipio having notified that he should appoint three
                    delegates, who, after making themselves acquainted with the case, and examining
                    the witnesses, might decide <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> which had been
                    the first to scale the wall and enter the town, added Publius Cornelius
                    Caudinus, a middle party, to Laelius and Sempronius, the advocates of the two
                    parties, and ordered these three delegates to sit and determine the cause.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But as the contest was now carried on
                    with increased warmth, because those high characters, who had acted more as
                    moderators of the zeal of both than as advocates of any particular <pb n="1083"
                        xml:id="p.1083"/> party, were withdrawn, Caius Laelius, leaving the council,
                    went up to the tribunal of Scipio and informed him, <quote> that the contest was
                        proceeding without bounds or moderation, and that they had almost come to
                        blows. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But still, though no violence
                        should take place, that the proceedings formed a most hateful precedent; for
                        that the honours due to valour were being sought by fraud and perjury.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That on one side stood the legionary
                        troops, on the other the marines, ready to swear by all the gods what they
                        wished, rather than what they knew, to be true, and to involve in the guilt
                        of perjury not only themselves and their own persons, but the military
                        standards, the eagles, and their solemn oath of allegiance. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> That he laid these matters before him, in
                        accordance with the opinion of Publius Cornelius and Marcus Sempronius.
                    </quote> Scipio, after highly praising Laelius, summoned an assembly, and then
                    declared, <quote> that he had ascertained satisfactorily that Quintus Trebellius
                        and Sextus Digitius had mounted the wall at the same time, and that he
                        presented them both with mural crowns in consideration of their valour.
                    </quote> He then gave presents to the rest, according to the merit and valour of
                    each. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Above all he honoured Caius Laelius,
                    the admiral of the fleet, by the placing him upon an equality with himself, and
                    bestowing upon him every kind of commendation, and also by presenting him with a
                    golden crown and thirty oxen. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He then ordered the Spanish hostages to be
                    summoned. What the number of these was I feel reluctant to state, because in
                    some authors I find that it was about three hundred, in others seven hundred and
                    twenty-five. There is the same difference between authors with regard to the
                    other particulars. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One writes that the Punic
                    garrison consisted of ten thousand, another of seven, a third of not more than
                    two thousand. In some you may find that ten thousand persons were captured, in
                    others above twenty-five thousand. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I should
                    have stated the number of scorpions captured, both of the greater and smaller
                    size, at sixty, if I had followed the Greek author, Silenus; if Valerius Antius,
                    of the larger at six thousand, of the smaller at thirteen; so great is the
                    extent of falsehood. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor are they agreed even
                    respecting the commanders; most say that Laelius commanded the fleet, but some
                    say Marcus Junius Silanus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Valerius Antius
                    says, that Arines commanded the Punic garrison, and was given up to the Romans;
                        <pb n="1084" xml:id="p.1084"/> other writers say it was Mago. They are not
                    agreed respecting the number of the ships taken, respecting the weight of gold
                    and silver, and of the money brought into the public treasury. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> If we must assent to some of their statements, the medium
                    is nearest to the truth. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> However, Scipio
                    having summoned the hostages, first bid them all keep up their spirits,
                    observing, <quote> that they had fallen into the hands of the Roman <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> people, who chose to bind men to them by
                        benefits rather than by fear, and keep foreign nations attached to them by
                        honour and friendship, rather than subject them to a gloomy servitude. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then receiving the names of the states to
                    which they belonged, he took an account of the captives, distinguishing the
                    number belonging to each people, and sent messengers to their homes, to desire
                    that they would come and take back their respective friends. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> If ambassadors from any of the states happened to be
                    present, he delivered their countrymen to them in person, and assigned to them
                    the quaestor, Caius Flaminius, the charge of kindly taking care of the rest.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, there advanced from the midst
                    of the crowd of hostages a woman in years, the wife of Mandonius, who was the
                    brother of Indibilis, the chieftain of the Illergetians; she threw herself
                    weeping at the general's feet, and began to implore him to give particularly
                    strict injunctions to their guardians with respect to the care and treatment of
                    females. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scipio replied, that nothing
                    certainly should be wanting; when the woman rejoined: "We do not much value such
                    things, for what is not good enough for such a condition? A care of a different
                    kind disquiets me, when beholding the age of these females; for I am myself no
                    longer exposed to the danger peculiar to females. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Around her stood the daughters of Indibilis, in the bloom
                    of youth and beauty, with others of equal rank, all of whom looked up to her as
                    a parent. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Scipio then said: <quote> Out of
                        regard for that discipline which I myself and the Roman nation maintain, I
                        should take care that nothing, which is any where held sacred, should be
                        violated among us. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In the present case,
                        your virtue and your rank cause me to observe it more strictly; for not even
                        in the midst of misfortunes have you forgotten the delicacy becoming
                        matrons. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He then delivered them over to a man of tried
                    virtue, ordering him to treat them with no less respect and modesty than the
                    wives and mothers of guests. <pb n="1085" xml:id="p.1085"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The soldiers then brought to him a female
                    captive, a grown-up virgin, of such exquisite beauty, that whichever way she
                    walked she attracted the eyes of every body. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, on making inquiries as to her country and parentage, heard, among other
                    particulars, that she was betrothed to a young prince of the Celtiberians, named
                    Allucius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He immediately, therefore, summoned
                    from their abode her parents and lover, and having heard in the mean time that
                    the latter was desperately enamoured of her, as soon as he arrived he addressed
                    him in a more studied manner than her parents. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>A young man myself,</quote> said he, <quote> I address myself to a young
                        man, and therefore there need be the less reserve in this conversation.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As soon as your intended bride, having
                        been captured by my soldiers, was brought into my presence, and I was
                        informed that she was endeared to you, which her beauty rendered probable;
                        considering that I should myself wish that my affection for my intended
                        bride, though excessive, should meet with indulgence, could I enjoy the
                        pleasures suited to my age, (particularly in an honourable and lawful love,)
                        and were not my mind engrossed by public affairs, I indulge as far as I can
                        your passion. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Your mistress, while under
                        my protection, has received as much respect as under the roof of her own
                        parents, your father-in-law and mother-in-law. She has been kept in perfect
                        safety for you, that she might be presented to you pure, a gift worthy of me
                        and of you. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This only reward I bargain for
                        in return for the service I have rendered you, that you would be a friend to
                        the Roman people; and if you believe that I am a true man, as these nations
                        knew my father and uncle to have been heretofore, that you would feel
                        assured that in the Roman state there are many like us; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> and that no nation in the world at the present time can
                        be mentioned, with which you ought to be less disposed that you, or those
                        belonging to you, should be at enmity, or with which you would rather be in
                        friendship. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The young man, overcome at once with joy and
                    modesty, clung to Scipio's right hand, and invoked all the gods to recompense
                    him in his behalf, since he himself was far from possessing means proportioned
                    either to his own wishes or Scipio's deserts. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    He then addressed himself to the parents and relatives of the damsel, who, on
                    receiving her back without any reward, whom they had brought <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> a very large weight of gold to redeem, entreated Scipio to
                    ac- <pb n="1086" xml:id="p.1086"/> cept it from them as a present to himself;
                    affirming, that if he would do so, they should feel as grateful for it as they
                    did for the restoration of their daughter inviolate. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> As they were so earnest in their entreaties, Scipio
                    promised to accept it, and ordered it to be laid at his feet. Then calling
                    Allucius to him, he said: <quote> To the dowry which you are about to receive
                        from your father-in-law, let these marriage presents also from me be added;
                    </quote> bidding him take away the gold and keep it for himself. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Delighted with these presents and honours, he was
                    dismissed to his home, where he inspired his countrymen with the deserved
                    praises of Scipio, observing, <quote> that a most godlike youth had come among
                        them, who conquered every thing, not only by arms, but by kindness and
                        generosity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Accordingly, making a levy among his
                    dependants, he returned to Scipio after a few days, with fourteen hundred chosen
                    horsemen. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio kept Laelius with him until he had
                    disposed of the captives, hostages, and booty, in accordance with his advice;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> but when all these matters were
                    satisfactorily arranged, he gave him a quinquereme; and selecting from the
                    captives Mago, and about fifteen senators who had been made prisoners at the
                    same time with him, put them on board, and sent him to Rome with the news of his
                    victory. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He himself employed the few days he
                    had resolved to stay at Carthage, in exercising his naval and land forces.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the first day the legions under arms
                    performed evolutions through a space of four miles; on the second day he ordered
                    them to repair and clean their arms before their tents; on the third day they
                    engaged in imitation of a regular battle with wooden swords, throwing javelins
                    with the points covered with balls; on the fourth day they rested; on the fifth
                    they again performed evolutions under arms. This succession of exercise and rest
                    they kept up as long as they staid at Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The rowers and mariners, pushing out to sea when the weather was calm, made
                    trial of the manageableness of their ships by mock sea-fights. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Such exercises, both by sea and land, without the city
                    prepared their minds and bodies for war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    city itself was all bustle with warlike preparations, artificers of every
                    description being collected together in a public workshop. The general went
                    round to all the works with equal attention. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    At one time he was employed in the dock-yard with his fleet, at <pb n="1087"
                        xml:id="p.1087"/> another he exercised with the legions; sometimes he would
                    devote his time to the inspection of the works, which were every day carried on
                    with the greatest eagerness by a multitude of artificers both in the workshops,
                    and in the armoury and docks. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having put these
                    preparations in a train, repaired the walls in a part where they had been
                    shattered, and placed bodies of troops to guard the city, he set out for
                    Tarraco; and on his way thither was visited by a number of embassies, some of
                    which he dismissed, having given them answers on his journey, others he
                    postponed till his arrival at Tarraco; at which place he had appointed a meeting
                    of all his new and old allies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here
                    ambassadors from almost all the people dwelling on this side the Iberus, and
                    from many dwelling in the farther Spain, met. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The Carthaginian generals at first industriously suppressed the rumour of the
                    capture of Carthage; but afterwards, when it became too notorious to be
                    concealed or dissembled, they disparaged its importance by their language.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They said, that <quote> by an unexpected
                        attack, and in a manner by stealth, in one day, one city of Spain had been
                        snatched out of their hands; that a presumptuous youth, elated with the
                        acquisition of this, so inconsiderable an advantage, had, by the
                        extravagance of his joy, given it the air of an important victory; but that
                        as soon as he should hear that three generals and three victorious armies of
                        his enemies were approaching, the deaths which had taken place in his family
                        would occur to his recollection. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Such was the tone in which they spoke of this
                    affair to the people, though <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> they were, at
                    the same time, far from ignorant how much their strength had been diminished, in
                    every respect, by the loss of Carthage. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
