<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab urbe condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 8-10 - 18s</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books VIII-X With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1926: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18s" type="book">
                <head>Summary of Book XVIII</head>
                <p> ATILIUS REGULUS in Africa slew a serpent of portentous size with the loss of
                    many of his soldiers. <reg>having</reg> fought several successful battles with
                    the Carthaginians, and finding that owing to his good fortune in the prosecution
                    of the war the senate was not disposed to send anyone to succeed him, he wrote
                    to the senate and complained of this very thing, alleging, amongst other reasons
                    for desiring a successor, that his little farm had been deserted by the
                    labourers hired to work it. <reg>afterwards</reg> , on Fortune's seeking to
                    exhibit in the case of Regulus an <pb n="p.557"/> example of both extremes, the
                    Carthaginians sent for Xanthippus, a general of the Lacedaemonians, who defeated
                    Regulus in battle and made him prisoner. <reg>after</reg> that all the Roman
                    generals gained victories on land and sea; but these were marred by the wreck of
                    fleets. <name>Tiberius</name> Coruncanius was the first to be chosen pontifex
                    maximus from the plebs. <reg>manius</reg> Valerius Maximus and Publius
                    Sempronius Sophus, when as censors they were passing on the senate, removed
                    sixteen from that order. <reg>they</reg> closed the lustrum and the number of
                    citizens returned was 297,797. Regulus being sent by the Carthaginians to the
                    senate to treat for peace, or, failing that, for an exchange of prisoners, and
                    being bound by an oath to return to Carthage, if the Romans would not exchange,
                    advised the senate to grant neither request, and having loyally returned, was
                    tortured to death by the Carthaginians. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Regulus story inspired Horace to write his finest
                        ode ( <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>carm</reg> . </hi> III. 5). </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
