<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader status="new">
    	<fileDesc>
    		<titleStmt>
    			<title type="work">Fragments</title>
    			<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    			<author n="Petr.">Petronius</author>
    			<editor role="editor">Michael Heseltine</editor>
    			<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder> </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
    		 <sourceDesc>
    			<biblStruct>
                	<monogr>
                		<author>Petronius Arbiter</author>
                		<title>Petronius</title>
                		<editor role="editor" n="Heseltine">Michael Heseltine</editor>                        
                		<imprint>
                			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                			<publisher>William Heinemann</publisher>
                			<date>1913</date>
                		</imprint>
                	</monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <state delim="." unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            	<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>--><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader><text xml:lang="en"><body>
        		<div type="section" n="1"><head>I
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Servius on Virgil, Aeneid III,</hi> 57: <quote>The sacred hunger
        				for gold.</quote>
        				<quote>Sacred</quote> means <quote>accursed.</quote> This expression is derived from
        				a Gallic custom. For whenever the people of Massilia were burdened with pestilence,
        				one of the poor would volunteer to be fed for an entire year out of public funds on
        				food of special purity. After this period he would be decked with sacred herbs and
        				sacred robes, and would be led through the whole state while people cursed him, in
        				order that the sufferings of the whole state might fall upon him, and so he would be
        				cast out. This account has been given in Petronius.</p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="2"><head>II
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Servius on Virgil, Aeneid XII,</hi> 159, <hi rend="italics">on the
        				feminine gender of nouns ending in -tor:</hi> But if they are not derived from a
        				verb they are common in gender. For in these cases both the masculine and the
        				feminine end alike in -tor, for example, senator, a male or female senator,
        				balneator, a male or female bath attendant, though Petronius makes an exception in
        				speaking of<hi rend="italics">a <quote>bath-woman</quote></hi> (<hi rend="italics">balneatricem</hi>).</p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="3"><head>III
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Pseud-Acro on Horace, Epodes</hi> 5, 48: <quote>Canidia biting her
        				thumb</quote>: He expressed the appearance and movements of Canidia in a rage.
        				Petronius, wishing to portray a furious person, says <quote>
        					<hi rend="italics">biting his thumb to the quick.</hi>
        				</quote></p>
        		</div>
            <pb id="p.327"/>
        		<div type="section" n="4"><head>IV
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Sidonius Apollinaris Carmen XXIII, 145, 155:</hi> Why should I
        				hymn you, tuneful Latin writers, thou of Arpinum, thou of Patavium, thou of
        				Mantua?<note>The writers are Cicero, Livy, Virgil.</note> And thou, Arbiter, who
        				in the gardens of the men of Massilia findest a home on the hallowed tree-trunk as
        				the peer of Hellespontine Priapus?</p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="5"><head>V
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Priscian Institutiones VIII, 16 and XI, 29</hi> (<hi
        				rend="italics">pp. 881, 567 ed. Hertz</hi>) <hi rend="italics">among the
        					examples by which he shows that the past participles of deponent verbs have a
        					passive meaning:</hi> Petronius, <quote><hi rend="italics">the soul locked</hi>
        						(<hi rend="italics">amplexam</hi>) <hi rend="italics">in our
        							bosoms.</hi></quote></p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="5b"><head>V<hi rend="super">b</hi>
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Boethius on Victorinus's translation of Porphyry, Dialogue II (p.
        				45 ed. Basle):</hi> I shall be very glad to do it, he said. But since <hi
        					rend="italics">the morning sun,</hi> in Petronius's words, <hi rend="italics">has now smiled upon the roofs,</hi> let us get up, and if there is any other
        				point, it shall be treated later with more careful attention.</p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="6"><head>VI
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius Mythologiae I</hi> (<hi rend="italics">p.</hi> 22 <hi
        				rend="italics">ed. Muncker</hi>): You do not know . . . how women dread satire.
        				Lawyers may retreat and scholars may not utter a syllable before the flood of a
        				woman's words, the rhetorician may be dumb and the herald may stop his cries; satire
        				alone can put a limit to their madness, though it be Petronius's <hi rend="italics">Albucia</hi> who is hot.</p>
        		</div>
        		<pb id="p.329"/>
        		<div type="section" n="7"><head>VII
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius Mythologiae III, 8 (p. 124), (where he remarked that
        				essence of myrrh is very strong):</hi> hence too Petronius Arbiter says <hi
        					rend="italics">that he drank a cup of myrrh in order to excite his passion.</hi></p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="8"><head>VIII
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius in his Treatise on the Contents of Virgil's works (p.
        				156):</hi> For we have already explained above the application of the myth of
        				Cerberus with Three Heads to quarrels and litigation in the courts. Hence too
        				Petronius says of <hi rend="italics">Euscios, <quote>The barrister was a Cerberus of
        					the courts.</quote></hi></p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="9"><head>
        			<hi rend="italics">IX</hi>
        		
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius in his Explanation of Old Words, 42 (p.</hi> 565 <hi
        				rend="italics">in Mercer's edition): Ferculum</hi> means a dish of flesh. Hence
        				too Petronius Arbiter says, <quote>
        					<hi rend="italics">After the dish offlesh (ferculum) was brought in.</hi>
        				</quote></p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="10"><head>X
        			<p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius ibid. 46 (p. 565): Valgia</hi> really means the
        				twisting of the lips which occurs in vomiting. As Petronius also says, <quote><hi
        					rend="italics">With lips twisted as in a vomit</hi> (<hi rend="italics">valgiter</hi>).</quote></p>
        		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="11"><head>XI
            <p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius ibid. 52 (p. 566): Alucinare</hi> means to dream
                falsely, and is derived from <hi rend="italics">alucitae,</hi> which we call <hi
                    rend="italics">conopes</hi> (mosquitoes). As Petronius Arbiter says,<quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">For the mosquitoes (alucitae) were troubling my
                    companion.</hi>
                </quote></p>
            </div>
            	<pb id="p.331"/>
        		<div type="section" n="12"><head>XII
            <p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius ibid. 60 (p. 567): Manubiae</hi> means the ornaments of
                kings. Hence Petronius Arbiter also says, <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">So many kingly ornaments (manubiae) found in the possession
                        of a runaway.</hi>
                </quote></p>
            </div>
        		<div type="section" n="13"><head>XIII
            <p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius ibid. 61 (p. 567): Aumatium</hi> means a private place
                in a public spot such as theatres or the circus. Hence Petronius Arbiter also says, <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">I hurled myself into the privy-place (aumatium).</hi>
                </quote></p>
            		</div>
        		<div type="section" n="14"><head>XIV
            <p><hi rend="italics">Isidorus Origines V, 26, 7: Dolus</hi><note><hi rend="italics">Dolus</hi> originally meant <hi rend="italics">a device</hi> without moral
                    connotation; hence the legal term for <hi rend="italics">fraud was dolus
                    malus,</hi> and the use of <hi rend="italics">dolus</hi> alone in a bad sense is
                    later.</note> is the mental cunning on the part of the deceiver: for he does one
                thing and pretends another. Petronius takes a different view when he says,
                        <quote><hi rend="italics">What is a wrong (dolus), gentlemen? It occurs
                        whenever anything offensive to the law is done. You understand what a wrong
                        is: now take damage</hi>. . .</quote></p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="15"><head>XV
            <p><hi rend="italics">Glossary of St. Dionysius:</hi> The spring-board is a kind of
                game. Petronius, <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">Now lifted high at the will of the spring-board.</hi>
                </quote></p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="16"><head>XVI
            <p><hi rend="italics">From the Glossary of St. Dionysius:</hi> Petronius, <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">'It was quite certainly their usual plan to go through the
                        Grotto of Naples only with backs bent double.</hi>
            </quote></p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="17"><head>XVII
            <p>
                <hi rend="italics">Another Glossary:</hi>
            </p>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">Suppes suppumpis, that is with feet bent backwards.</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">Tullia, mediator (?) or princess.</hi>
                </l>
            </quote>
            	</div>
            <pb id="p.333"/>
        		<div type="section" n="18"><head>XVIII
            <p><hi rend="italics">Nicolaus Perottus in the Cornucopia (p. 200, 26 in the Aldine
                    Edition of 1513):</hi> Cosmus too was a superb perfumer, and ointments are
                called Cosmian after him. The same writer (Juvenal 8, 86) says, <quote>and let him
                    be plunged deep in a bronze vase of Cosmus.</quote> Petronius, <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">Bring us, he said, an alabaster box of Cosmus ointment.</hi>
                    </quote></p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="19"><head>XIX
            <p>
                <hi rend="italics">Terentianus Maurus on Metre:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We see that Horace nowhere employed verse of this rhythm continuously, but the
                learned Arbiter uses it often in his works. You will remember these lines, which we
                are used to sing: <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">The maidens of Memphis, made ready for the rites of the Gods.
                        The boy coloured deep as the night with speaking gestures.</hi>
                </quote></p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Marius Victorinus III, 17 (Keil, Grammatici, II,</hi> 138):</p>
            <p>We know that the lyric poets inserted some lines of this rhythm and form in their
                works, as we find too in Arbiter, for example: <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">The maidens of Memphis, made ready for the rites of the
                    Gods,</hi>
                </quote> and again<quote><hi rend="italics">Coloured deep as the night,</hi>
                    [dancing] <hi rend="italics">Egyptian dances.</hi></quote></p>
            	</div>
            <pb id="p.335"/>
        		<div type="section" n="20"><head>XX
            <p>
                <hi rend="italics">Terentianus Maurus on Metre:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the analysis, which we will explain, will give us the metre in which they say
                that Anacreon wrote his sweet old songs. We find that Petronius, as well as many
                others, used this metre, when he says that this same lyric poet sang in words
                harmonious to the Muses. But I will explain with what kind of caesura this verse is
                written. In the line <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">Iuverunt segetes meum laborem</hi>
                </quote> (<quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">The cornfields have lightened my labour</hi>
                </quote>), the word <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">iuverunt</hi>
                </quote> is the beginning of a hexameter: the remaining words <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">segetes meum laborem</hi>
                </quote> are in the same metre as</p>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">"triplici vides ut ortu</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">Triviae rotetur ignis</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">volucrique Phoebus axe</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">rapidum pererret orbem"</hi>
                </l>
            </quote>
            <p>(<quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">You see how the fire of Trivia spins round from her threefold
                            rising,<note>I.e. as the new, the full, or the waning moon.</note> and
                        Phoebus on his winged wheel traverses the hurrying globe</hi>
            </quote>.)</p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="21"><head>XXI
            <p><hi rend="italics">Diomede on Grammar III (Keilp. 518):</hi> Hence arises the caesura
                which Arbiter employed thus:</p>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">"Anus recocta vino</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italics">trementibus labellis"</hi>
                </l>
            </quote>
            <p>(<quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">An old woman soaked in wine, with trembling lips</hi>
            </quote>)</p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="22"><head>XXII
            <p><hi rend="italics">Servius on the Grammar of Donatus (Keil p. 432, 22):</hi> Again,
                he uses <quote>Quirites</quote> (<quote>Roman citizens</quote>) only in the plural
                number. But we read in Horace the accusative <quote>hunc Quiritem</quote>
                    (<quote>this Roman citizen</quote>) making<pb id="p.337"/> the nominative
                    <quote>hic Quiris.</quote> Again, the same Horace says <quote>Quis te
                Quiritem?</quote> and there the nominative will be <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">hic Quirites,</hi>
                </quote> as Petronius says.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Pompeius in his Commentary on the Art of Donatus</hi> (<hi
                    rend="italics">Keil p. 167, 9</hi>): No one says <quote>this Roman
                citizen,</quote> but <quote>these Roman citizens,</quote> although we find the
                former in books. Read Petronius, and you will find this use of the nominative
                singular. And Petronius says <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">Hic Quirites</hi>
                </quote> (<quote><hi rend="italics">this Roman citizen</hi>).</quote></p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="23"><head>XXIII
            <p><hi rend="italics">A Grammarian on Nouns of uncertain gender (Keil p. 578, 23):</hi>
                Fretum (<quote>a strait</quote>) is of the neuter gender, and its plural is freta,
                as Petronius says<quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">Freta Nereidum</hi>
                </quote> (<quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">The straits of the Nereids</hi>
                </quote>).</p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="24"><head>XXIV
            <p><hi rend="italics">Hieronymus in his Letter to Demetriades CXXX, 19</hi> (<hi
                    rend="italics">Vallarsius p.</hi> 995): Boys with hair curled and crimped and
                skins smelling like foreign musk-rats, about whom Arbiter wrote the line, <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">To smell good always is not to smell good,</hi>
                </quote><note>The line occurs in Martial 2, 12, 4. The reference to Petronius may be
                    due to a confusion with ch. 2,1. 1.</note> showing how the virgin may avoid
                    certain plagues and poisons of modesty.</p>
            	</div>
        		<div type="section" n="25"><head>XXV
            <p><hi rend="italics">Fulgentius Mythologiae II, 6 (p. 80, on Prometheus):</hi> Although
                Nicagoras. . . represents his yielding his liver to a vulture, as an allegorical
                picture of envy. Hence too Petronius Arbiter says: <quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">The vulture who explores our inmost liver, and drags out our
                        heart and inmost nerves, is not the bird of whom our dainty poets talk, but
                        those diseases of the soul, envy and wantonness.</hi>
                </quote></p>
            	</div>
            <pb/>
        	
        	</body></text></TEI>