<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Behalf of Marcus Tullius</title>
				<title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius, Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
				<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
				<author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
				<editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor> <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>  </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>  <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
						<title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B. A.</title>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
							<date>1856</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

	 <encodingDesc>
	  <refsDecl n="CTS">
	   <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
	    <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
	   </cRefPattern>
	  </refsDecl>
	  <refsDecl>
	   <refState unit="section"/>
	  </refsDecl>
	   
	   <!--<refsDecl>
	     <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
	     <refState unit="section"/>
	   </refsDecl>
	   <refsDecl>
	     <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
	     <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
	     <refState unit="section"/>
	   </refsDecl>
	   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
	     <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
	     <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
	     <refState unit="section"/>
	   </refsDecl>
	   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
	     <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
	     <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
	     <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
	     <refState unit="section"/>
	   </refsDecl>
	   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
	     <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
	     <refState unit="speech"/>
	   </refsDecl>-->
</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English</language>
				<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
				<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>

		<revisionDesc>
		  <change when="2016-03-09" who="Lisa Cerrato">Incorporated initial changes; minor edits; added missing section numbers and indicated perseus responsibiity</change>
		 <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
     <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		  <change when="2014-07" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
		 <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">Revision 1.9  reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
		 <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.7  fixed typo in while to in which</change>
		 <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.6  fixing gap tags against source</change>
		 <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">Revision 1.5  cleaned up log keyword</change>
		 <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">Revision 1.4  cleaned up log keyword</change>
		 <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">Revision 1.2  fixing place tags - AD</change>
		 <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">Revision 1.1 more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
		 <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">Revision 1.8 fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
		 <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">Revision 1.7 fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
		 <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">Revision 1.6 fixed date tags</change>
		 <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">Revision 1.5 places/dates now actually tagged</change>
		 <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.4 changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
		 <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.3 changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
		 <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">Revision 1.2 removed stray item tags</change>
		 <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Revision 1.1 Converted to XML</change>
		 <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.19 Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
		 <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.18 changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
		 <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">Revision 1.17 div1s missing type attributes</change>
		 <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.16 changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
		 <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Revision 1.15 Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
		 <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.14 changed ought to he to ought to be in first
     oration against Cataline</change><change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">Revision 1.13 really fix language ids</change>
		 <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">Revision 1.12 fix language codes</change>
		 <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Revision 1.11 Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
		 <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">Revision 1.10 fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
		 <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">Revision 1.9 replace the
     refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
		 <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">Revision 1.8 revised and proofread again</change>
		 <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Revision 1.7 Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
		 <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Revision 1.6 Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
		 <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Revision 1.5 Fixed refsDecl</change>
		 <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Revision 1.4 Fixed typo.</change> 
		 <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Revision 1.3 Fixed typo.</change>
		 <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Revision 1.2 Added sections.</change>
		 <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Revision 1.1 Added to repository.</change>
		  <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="eng">
   
   <body>
     <div type="translation" subtype="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi006.perseus-eng2">
					<head>THE FRAGMENTS WHICH REMAIN OF THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO ON BEHALF OF MARCUS TULLIUS.</head>
					  <div type="commentary" resp="ed">
						<note anchored="true">This Oration is in a very imperfect and corrupt state. It is only lately
       that even what we have of it has been discovered in the North of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. It has been edited with great care by C. Beier, who has, however, gone
       rather beyond the province of an editor in filling up lacunae of several lines at a time to
       complete what he considers must have been Cicero's meaning. Those additions of his I have
       generally thought it better to omit from the translation, as they rest on no authority, and
       as this work professes only to be a translation of Cicero himself.</note>
					
						<head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
						<p>Marcus Tullius had a farm, and a man of the name of Publius Fabius had bought another farm
       bordering on it. On the farm of Tullius there was a large field which Fabius coveted greatly,
       and as he could not obtain it by bargain, or by any legal process, (though he does seem to
       have tried this latter expedient,) he arms a gang of slaves, and sends them to take
       possession of the land, they murder Tullius's slaves, and demolish and burn the villa which
       he had there. After all this, Tullius prosecutes Fabius for the damage done. So that, as it
       seems, this speech ought rather to be called a speech against Publius Fabius than a speech on
       behalf of Marcus Tullius. </p></div>
				
					<milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus">
					<p>Formerly, O judges, I had determined to conduct this cause in a different manner, thinking
      that our adversaries would deny that their household was implicated in such a violent and
      atrocious murder. Accordingly, I came with a mind free from care and anxiety, because I was
      aware that I could easily prove that by witnesses. But now, when it has been confessed, not
      only by that most honourable man, Lucius Quinctius, 
      <add>but when Publius Fabius himself has not hesitated to admit the facts which are the
       subject of this trial, I come forward to plead this cause in quite a different manner from
       that in which I was originally prepared to argue it. For then</add> my anxiety was to be able
      to prove what I asserted had been done. Now all my speech is to be directed to this point, to
      prevent our adversaries from being in a better position, merely because they have admitted
      what they could not possibly deny though they greatly wished to do so. 
					</p></div> <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus">
				  <p>Therefore, as matters stood at first your decision was more difficult, but my
      defence was easy. For I originally rested my whole case on the evidence; 
      <add>now I rest it on the confession of my adversary; and to oppose his audacity in acts of
       violence, his impudence in a court of justice, may fairly be considered as the task of your
       power, not of my abilities.—</add> For what is easier than to decide on the case of
      a man who confesses the fact? But it is difficult for me to speak with sufficient force of
      that which cannot be by language made out worse than it is in reality, and cannot be made more
      plain by my speech than it is by the confession of the parties actually concerned.
				  </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus">
					<p><milestone unit="para"/>As, therefore, on account of the reasons which I have stated, my system of defence must be
      changed, <add>I must also forget for a little time, in the case of Publius Fabius, that lenity of mine
       which I practiced at the previous trial, when I restrained myself from using any arguments
       which might have the appearance of attacking him, so much that I seemed to be defending his
       reputation</add> with no less care than the cause of Marcus Tullius. Now, since Quinctius has
      thought it not foreign to the subject to introduce so many statements, false for the most part
      and most wickedly invented, concerning the life and habits and character of Marcus Tullius,
      Fabius must pardon me for many reasons, if I do not now appear to spare his character so much,
      or to show the same regard for it now as I did previously.
					</p>
				  </div><milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus">
				  <p><add>At the former trial I kept all my stings sheathed; but
       since, in that same previous trial,</add> he thought it a part of his duty to show no
      forbearance whatever to his adversary, how ought I to act, I, a Tullius for another Tullius, a
      man kindred to me in disposition not less than in name? And it seems to me, O judges, that I
      have more need to feel anxious as to whether my conduct will be approved in having said
      nothing against him before, than blamed for the reply I now make to him. 
				  </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus">
				  <p> But I both did at that time what I ought to have done, and I shall do now
      what I am forced to do. For when it was a dispute about money matters, because we said that
      Marcus Tullius had sustained damage, it appeared foreign to my character to say anything of
      the reputation of Quintus Fabius; not because the case did not open the door to such
      statements. What is my conduct then? Although the cause does require it, still, unless when he
      absolutely compels me against my will, I am not inclined to condescend to speak ill of him.
      Now that I am speaking under compulsion, if I say anything strong, still I will do even that
      with decency and moderation, and only in such a way that, as he could not consider me hostile
      to him at the former trial, so he may now know that I am a faithful and trustworthy friend to
      Marcus Tullius.
				  </p>
				  </div><milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus">
	   <p><milestone unit="para"/>One thing, O Lucius Quinctius, I should wish to obtain from you, which, although I desire
      because it is useful for me, still I request of you because it is reasonable and
      just,—that you would regulate the time that you take to yourself for speaking, so as
      to leave the judges some time for coming to a decision. For the time before, there was no end
      to your speech in his defence; night alone set bounds to your oration. Now, if you please, do
      not do the same; this I beg of you. Nor do I beg it on this account, because I think it
      desirable for me that you should pass over some topics, or that you should fail to state them
      with sufficient elegance, and at sufficient length; but because I do think it enough for you
      to state each fact only once. And if you do that, I have no fear that the whole day will be
      taken up in talking.
     	</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus">
					<p><milestone unit="para"/>The subject of this trial which comes before you, O judges, is, What is the pecuniary amount
      of the damage inflicted on Marcus Tullius by the malice of the household of Quintus Fabius, by
      men armed and banded together in a violent manner. Those damages we have taxed; the valuation
      is yours; the decision given is that the amends shall be fourfold.
	  </p></div>
   <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus">
      <p>As all laws and all legal proceedings which seem at all harsh and severe have originated in
      the dishonesty and injustice of wicked men, so this form of procedure also has been
      established within these few years on account of the evil habits and excessive licentiousness
      of men. For when many families were said to be wandering armed about the distant fields and
      pasture lands, and to be committing murders, and as that fact appeared to concern not merely
      the estates of individuals, but the main interests of the republic, Marcus Lucullus, who often
      presided as judge with the greatest equity and wisdom, first planned this tribunal, and had
      regard to this object, that all men should so restrain their households that they should not
      only not go about armed to inflict damage on any one, but, even if they were attacked, should
      defend themselves by law, rather than by arms; </p></div>
				 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p> and though he
      knew that the Aquilian law <note anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="lat">Lex Aquilia</foreign>
       provided for the damages which any one was to pay to the owner, in the case of his having
       unlawfully killed any slave or quadruped. Actions under this law were limited to damage done
       by actual contact, though the subject of them was extended afterwards. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 313, in voc. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Damni injuria
        Actio</foreign>.</note>about damage existed, still he thought, that, as in the time of our
      ancestors both men's estates and their desires were less, and as their families, not being
      very numerous, were restrained by fear of important consequences, it very seldom happened that
      a man would be killed, and it was thought a nefarious and unprecedented atrocity; and
      therefore, that there was at that time no need of a system of judicial procedure with
      reference to bodies of men collected in a violent manner and armed; (for he thought that if
      any one established a law or a tribunal for matters which were not usual, he seemed not so
      much to forbid them as to put people in mind of them.) </p>
				 </div>
   <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus">
				  <p>In these times, when after a long civil war our manners
      had so far degenerated that men used arms with less scruple, he thought it necessary to
      establish a system of judicial procedure, with reference to the whole of a man's household, in
      the formula, “Which was said to have been done by the household,” and to
      assign judges, </p></div>
				    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus">
				      <p>in order that the matter might be decided as speedily as possible; and to affix
      a severe punishment, in order that audacity might be repressed by fear, and to take away that
      outlet, “Damage unjustly caused.”</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para"/>That which in other causes ought to have weight, and which has weight by the Aquilian law,
      namely, that damage had been caused by armed slaves in a violent manner, <gap reason="lost"/></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>
      Men must decide themselves when they could lawfully take arms, collect a band, and put men to
      death. When an action was assigned, this alone was to be the point at issue,
      “whether it appeared that damage had been inflicted by the malice of the household,
      by men collected and armed acting in a violent manner,” and the word
      “unjustly” was not to be added; he thought that he had put an end to the
      audacity of wicked men when he had left them no hope of being able to make any defence.
       </p></div>
   <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>Since, then, you have now heard what this judicial procedure is, and with what intention it
      was established, now listen, while I briefly explain to you the case itself, and its attendant
      circumstances. </p></div>
				 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus">
					<p><milestone unit="para"/>Marcus Tullius had a farm, inherited from his father, in the territory of 
					  <placeName key="tgn,6005942">Thurium</placeName>, O judges, which he was never sorry to have, till he
      got a neighbor who preferred extending the boundaries of his estate by arms, to defending them
      by law. For Publius Fabius lately purchased a farm of Caius Claudius, a senator,—a
      farm bordering on that of Marcus Tullius,—dear enough, for nearly half as much again
      (though in a wretched state of cultivation, and with all the buildings burnt down) as Claudius
      himself had given for it when it was in a good and highly ornamented condition, though he had
      paid an extravagant price for it. <gap reason="lost"/>
      </p></div>
				 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p>I will add this also, which is very important to the
      matter. When the commander-in-chief died, though he wished to invest a sum of money, got I
      know not how, in a farm, he did not so invest it, but he squandered it. 
      <add>I do not very greatly wonder that, hampered as he was by his own folly, he wished to
       extricate himself how he could. But this I cannot marvel at sufficiently, this I am indignant
       at, that he strives</add> to remedy his own folly at the expense of his neighbours, and that
      he endeavoured to pacify his own ill-temper by the injury of Tullius. </p></div>
				   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p>
				     <milestone unit="para"/>There is in that farm a field of two hundred acres, which is called the Popilian field, O
      judges, which had always belonged to Marcus Tullius, and which even his father had possessed. <add>That new neighbour of his, full of wicked hope, and the more confident because Marcus
       Tullius was away, began to wish for this field, as it appeared to him</add> to lie very
      conveniently for him, and to be a convenient addition to his own farm. And at first, because
      he repented of the whole business and of his purchase, he advertised the farm for sale. But he
      had had a partner in the purchase, Cnaeus Acerronius a most excellent man. <add>He was at
        <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, when on a sudden messengers came to Marcus
       Tullius from his villa, to say that Publius Fabius had advertised that neighbouring farm of
       his for sale, offering a much larger quantity of land than he and Cnaeus Acerronius had
       lately purchased.</add>
      </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>He applies to the man. He, arrogantly enough, answers just
      what he chooses. And he had not yet pointed out the boundaries. Tullius sends letters to his
      agent and to his bailiff, <add>to go to the procurator of Caius Claudius, in order that he
       might point out the boundaries to purchasers in their presence. But he</add>
      <gap reason="lost"/> refused to do this. He pointed out the boundaries to Acerronius while they
      were absent; but still he did not give them up this Popilian field. Acerronius excused himself
      from the whole business as well as he could, <add>and as soon as he could; and he immediately revoked any agreement which he had with
       Fabius, (for he preferred losing his money to losing his character,)</add>
      </p>
      </div><milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p>and dissolved partnership with such a man, being only
      slightly scorched. Fabius in the meantime brings on the farm picked men of great courage and
      strength, and prepares arms such as were suitable and fit for each of them; so that any one
      might see that those men were equipped, not for any farming work, but for battle and murder.
       </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p>In a short time they murdered two men of Quintus Catius
      Aemilianus, an honourable man, whom you all are acquainted with. They did many other things;
      they wandered about everywhere armed; they occupied all the fields and roads in an hostile
      manner, so that they seemed not obscurely but evidently to be aware of what business they were
      equipped for. In the meantime Tullius came to <placeName key="tgn,6005942">Thurium</placeName>. Then that worthy father of a family, that noble Asiaticus, that new
      farmer and grazier, while he was walking in the farm, notices in this very Popilian field a
      moderate-sized building, and a slave of Marcus Tullius, named Philinus. </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>“What business have you,” says he, “in my
      field?” The slave answered modestly and sensibly, that his master was at the villa;
      that he could talk to him if he wanted anything. Fabius asks Acerronius (for he happened to be
      there at the time) to go with him to Tullius. They go. Tullius was at the villa. Fabius says
      that either he will bring an action against Tullius, or that Tullius must bring one against
      him. Tullius answers that he will bring one, and that he will exchange securities with Fabius
      at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. Fabius agrees to this condition. Presently
      he departs. 
      </p></div>
   <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>The next night, when it was near day-break, the slaves of Publius Fabius come armed and in
      crowds to that house which I have already mentioned, which was in the Popilian field. They
      make themselves an entrance by force. They attack the slaves of Marcus Tullius, men of great
      value, unawares, which was very easy to do; and as these were few in number and offered no
      resistance, they, being a numerous body well armed and prepared, murdered them. And they
      behaved with such rancour and cruelty that they left them all with their throats cut, lest, if
      they left any one only half dead and still breathing, they should get the less credit. And
      besides this, they demolish the house and villa. </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>Philinus,
      whom I have already mentioned, and who had himself escaped from the massacre severely wounded,
      immediately reports this atrocious, this infamous, this unexpected attack to Marcus Tullius.
      Tullius immediately sends round to his friends, of whom in that neighbourhood he had a
      numerous and honourable body. </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>The matter appears scandalous
      and infamous to them all. <gap reason="lost"/>
      </p></div>
   <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus">
					<p>Listen, I entreat you, to the evidence of honest men touching those affairs which I am
      speaking of those things which my witnesses state, our adversary confesses that they state
      truly. Those things which my witnesses do not state, because they have not seen them and do
      not know them, those things our adversary himself states. Our witnesses say that they saw the
      men lying dead; that they saw blood in many places; that they saw the building demolished.
      They say nothing further. What says Fabius? He denies none of these things. What then further
      does he add? </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p>He says that his own household of slaves did
      it. How? By men armed, with violence. With what intention? That that might be done which was
      done. What is that? That the men of Marcus Tullius might be slain. If, then, they contrived
      all these circumstances with this intention, so that men assembled in one place, and armed
      themselves, and then marched with fixed resolution to an appointed place, chose a suitable
      time, and committed a massacre,—if they intended all this and planned it, and
      effected it,—can you separate that intention, that design, and that act from malice?
       </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>But those words “with malice” are added
      in this form of procedure with reference to the man who does the deed, not to him to whom it
      is done. And that you may understand this, O judges, attend, I beg of you, carefully. And, in
      truth, you will not doubt that this is the case. 
					</p></div>
   <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>If the trial were assigned to proceed on this ground, that the fact to be proved was,
      “That it had been done by the household,” then if any household itself had
      been unwilling to appear personally in the slaughter, and had either compelled or hired the
      assistance of other men, whether slaves or free men, all this trial, and the severe justice of
      the praetor, would be at an end. For no one can decide that, if the household were not present
      at a transaction, in that transaction the household itself committed damage with men armed, in
      a violent manner. Therefore, because that could be done, and done easily too, on that account
      it was not thought sufficient for investigation to be made as to what the household itself had
      done, but as to this point also, “What had been done by the malice of the
      household.” </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>For when the household itself does
      anything, men being collected together and armed, in a violent manner, and inflicts damage on
      any one, that must be done by malice. But when it forms a plan to procure such a thing to be
      done, the household itself does not do it, but it is done by its malice. And so by the
      addition of the words “by malice” the cause of both plaintiff and
      defendant is made more comprehensive. For whichever point he can prove, whether that the
      household itself did him the damage, or that it was done by the contrivance and assistance of
      that household, he must gain his cause. 
       </p></div>
   <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>You see that the praetors in these last years have interposed between me and Marcus Claudius
      with the insertion of this clause,—“From which, O Marcus Tullius, Marcus
      Claudius, or his household, or his agent, was driven by violence.” find what follows
      is according to the formula in the terms in which the praetor's interdict ran, and in which
      the securities were drawn up. If I were to defend myself before a judge in this
      way,—to confess that I had driven men out by violence— to deny that there
      was malice in it,—who would listen to me? No one, I suppose; because, if I drove out
      Marcus Claudius by violence, I drove him out by malice; for malice is a necessary ingredient
      in violence; and it is sufficient for Claudius to prove either point,—either that he
      was driven out with violence by me myself, or that I contrived a plan to have him driven out
      with violence. </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>More, therefore, is granted to Claudius when
      the interdict runs thus, “from which he was driven by violence, by my
      malice,” than if it had merely said, “whence he was driven by me by
      violence.” For, in this latter case, unless I had myself driven him out, I should
      gain my cause. In the former case, when the word “malice” is added,
      whether I had merely originated the design, or had myself driven him out, it is inevitable
      that it should be decided that he had been violently driven out by me with malice. 
     </p></div>
   <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/> The case in this trial, O judges, is exactly like this, and, indeed, identical with it. For
      I ask of you, O Quinctius, if the point in question were, “What appeared to be the
      pecuniary amount of the damage done by the household of Publius Fabius, by armed men, to
      Marcus Tullius,” what would you have to say? Nothing, I suppose; for you confess
      everything, both that the household of Publius Fabius did this, and that they did it violently
      with armed men. As to the addition, “with malice,” do you think that that
      avails you, that by which all your defence is cut off and excluded? </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>for, if that addition had not been made, and if you had chosen to urge, in
      your defence, that your household had not done this, you would have gained your cause if you
      had been able to prove this. Now, whether you had chosen to use that defence, or this one
      which you are using, you must inevitably be convicted; unless we think that a man is brought
      before the court who has formed a plan, but that one who has actually done an action is not;
      since a design may be supposed to exist without any act being done, but an act cannot exist
      without a design. Or, because the act is such that it could not be done without a secret
      design, without the aid of the darkness of night, without violence, without injury to another,
      without arms, without murder, without wickedness, is it on that account to be decided to have
      been done without malice? Or, will you suppose that the pleading has been rendered more
      difficult for me in the very case in which the praetor intended that a scandalous plea in
      defence should be taken from him? </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p> Here, now, they do seem
      to me to be men of very extraordinary talent, when they seize themselves on the very thing
      which was granted to me to be used against them; when they use rocks and reefs as a harbour
      and an anchorage. For they wish the word “malice” to be kept in the shade;
      by which they would be caught and detected, not only since they have done the things
      themselves which they admit having done, but even if they had done them by the agency of
      others. </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>I say that malice exists not in one action alone, (which would be enough for me,) nor in the
      whole case, only, (which would also be enough for me,) but separately in every single item of
      the whole business. They form a plan for coming, upon the slaves of Marcus Tullius: they do
      that with malice. They take arms: they do that with malice. They choose a time suitable for
      laying an ambush and for concealing their design: they do that with malice. They break open
      the house with violence: in the violence itself there is malice. They murder men, they
      demolish buildings: it is not possible for a man to be murdered intentionally, or for damage
      to be done to another intentionally, without malice. Therefore, if every part of the business
      is such that the malice is inherent in each separate part, will you decide that the entire
      business and the whole transaction is untainted with malice? 
     </p></div>
   <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus">
     	<p>What will Quinctius say to this? Surely he has nothing to say, no one point, I will not say
      on which he is able to stand, but on which he even imagines that he is able. For, first of
      all, he advanced this argument, that nothing can be done by the malice of a household. By this
      topic he was tending not merely to defend Fabius, but to put an end utterly to all judicial
      proceedings of this sort. For if that is brought before the court with reference to a
      household, which a household is absolutely incapacitated from doing, there is evidently no
      trial at all; all must inevitably be acquitted for the same reason. </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>If this were the only case, (it would be well, indeed, if it were,) but if it
      were, the only case, still you, O judges, being such as you are, ought to be unwilling that an
      affair of the greatest importance, affecting not only the welfare of the entire republic but
      also the fortunes of individuals—that a most dignified tribunal, one established
      with the greatest deliberation, and for the weightiest reasons, should appear to be put an end
      to by you. But this is not the only thing at stake. <gap reason="lost"/> the decision in this
      case is waited for with so much anxiety as shows that it is expected to rule not one case
      only, but all cases. <gap reason="lost"/>
					 <add>
					  <milestone unit="para"/>Shall I say that violence was done by the household of Publius Fabius? Our adversaries do
        not deny it. That damage was done to Marcus Tullius? You grant that—I have carried
        one point. That this violence was done by armed men? You do not deny that—I have
        carried a second point. You deny that it was done with malice; on this point we join issue.
         <gap reason="lost"/> Nor, indeed, do I see any need of looking for arguments by which that
        trivial and insignificant defence of his may be refuted and done away with.
      </add>
      </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus">
       <p> And yet I must speak to the statements which Quinctius has
      made; not that they have anything to do with the matter, but that it may not be thought that
      anything has been granted by me, merely because it has been overlooked. 
      </p></div>
   <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>You say that inquiry ought to be instituted whether the men of Marcus Tullius were slain
      wrongfully or no. This is the first inquiry that I make about the matter,—whether
      that matter has come before the court or not. If it has not come, why then need we say
      anything about it, or why need they ask any questions about it? But if it has, what was your
      object in making such a long speech to the praetor, to beg him to add to the formula the word
      “wrongfully,” and because you had not succeeded, to appeal to the tribunes
      of the people, and here before the court to complain of the injustice of the praetor because
      he did not add the word “wrongfully.” </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p>When you were requesting this of the praetor,—when you were appealing to the
      tribunes, you said that you ought to have an opportunity given to you of persuading the
      judges, if you could, that damage had not been done to Marcus Tullius wrongfully. Though,
      therefore, you wish that to be added to the formula of the trial, in order to be allowed to
      speak to that point before the judges; though it was not added, do you nevertheless speak to
      it as if you had gained the very thing which was refused to you?</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus"><p><milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
			But the same words which Metellus used in making his decree, the others, whom you appealed
      to, likewise used. Was not this the language of them all,—that although that which a
      household was said to have done by means of men armed and collected in a violent manner, could
      not possibly be done rightly, still they would add nothing, And they ware right, O judges. For
      if, when there is a refuge open to them, still slaves commit these wickednesses with the
      greatest audacity, and masters avow them with the greatest shamelessness, what do you think
      would be the case if the praetor were to decide that it is possible that such murders should
      be committed lawfully? Does it make any difference whether the magistrates establish a defence
      for a crime, or give people power and liberty to commit crime? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p>
      In truth, O judges, the magistrates are not influenced by the extent or the
      damage, to assign a trial in this formula. For if it were the case, the magistrates would not
      give recuperators rather than a judex, <note anchored="true">We are not acquainted with the
       difference between the <foreign xml:lang="lat">judex</foreign> and the <foreign xml:lang="lat">recuperatores</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 529, v.
        <foreign xml:lang="lat">Judex</foreign> in init.</note> —not an action against the
      whole family, but against the one who was proceeded against by name; nor would the damages be
      estimated at fourfold, but at double; and to the word “damage” would be
      added the word “wrongfully.” Nor, indeed, does the magistrate who has
      assigned this trial depart from the provisions of the Aquilian law about other damage, in
      cases in which nothing is at issue except the damage. And to this point the praetor ought to
      turn his attention. </p>
					</div>
   <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>In this trial, you see the question is about violence; you see the question is about armed
      men; you see that the demolition of houses, the ravaging of lands, the murders of men, fire,
      plunder, and massacre are brought before the court. And do you wonder that those who assigned
      this trial thought it sufficient that it should be inquired whether these cruel, and
      scandalous, and atrocious actions had been done or not; not whether they had been done rightly
      or wrongfully? The praetors, then, have not departed from the Aquilian law which was passed
      about damage; but they appointed a very severe course of proceeding in the case of armed men
      acting with violence. Not that they thought that no inquiry was ever to be made as to the
      right or the wrong; but they did not think it fit that they who preferred to manage their
      business by arms rather than by law should argue the question of right and wrong. </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p>Nor did they refuse to add the word “wrongfully”
      because they would not add it in other cases; but they did not think that it was possible for
      slaves to take arms and collect a band rightfully. Nor did they refuse because they thought,
      that if this addition were made, it would be possible to persuade such men as these judges
      that it had not been wrongfully done, but because they would not appear to put a shield in the
      hands of those men in a court of justice, whom they had summoned before the court for talking
      those arms which they did take. 
      </p></div>
   <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>The same prohibitory law about violence existed in the time of our ancestors which exists
      now. “From which you, or your household, or your agent have this year driven him, or
      his household, or his agent, by violence.” Then there is added, with reference to
      the man who is being proceeded against, “When he was the owner;” and this
      further addition also, “Of what he possessed, having acquired it neither by
      violence, nor secretly, nor as a present.” </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p>The man
      who is said to have driven another away by violence has many pleas of defence allowed him,
      (and if he can prove any one of them to the satisfaction of the judge, then, even if he
      confesses that he drove him out by violence, he must gain his cause,) either that he who has
      been driven out was not the owner, or that he had got possession from him himself by violence,
      or by stealth, or as a present. Our ancestors left so many pleas of defence, by which he might
      gain his cause, even to the man who confessed himself guilty of violence. 
      </p></div>
   <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>Come, now, let us consider another prohibitory law, which has also been now established on
      account of the iniquity of the times, and the excessive licentiousness of men. <gap reason="lost"/>
      </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus">
     <p>And he read me the law out of the Twelve Tables, which permits a man to kill a thief by
      night, and even by day if he defends himself with a weapon; and an ancient law out of the
      sacred laws, which allows any one to be put to death with impunity who has assaulted a tribune
      of the people. I imagine I need say no more about the laws.
     </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus">
				  <p><milestone unit="para"/>And now I, for the first time in this affair, ask this question: —What connection
      the reading of these laws had with this trial? Had the slaves of Marcus Tullius assaulted any
      tribune of the people? I think not. Had they come by night to the house of Publius Fabius to
      steal? Not even that. Had they come by day to steal, and then had they defended themselves
      with a weapon? It cannot be affirmed. Therefore, according to those laws which you have read,
      certainly that man's household had no right to slay the slaves of Marcus Tullius. 
      </p></div>
   <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus">
    	<p><milestone unit="para"/>“Oh,” says he, “I did not read it because of its bearing on
      that subject, but that you might understand this, that it did not appear to our ancestors to
      be anything so utterly intolerable for a man to be slain.” But, in the first place
      those very laws which you read, (to say nothing of other points,) prove how utterly our
      ancestors disapproved of any man being slain unless it was absolutely unavoidable. First of
      all, there is that holy law which armed men petitioned for, that unarmed men might be free
      from danger. Wherefore it was only reasonable for them to wish the person of that magistrate
      to be hedged round with the protection of the laws, by whom the laws themselves are protected.
       </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus"><p>The Twelve Tables forbid a thief— that is to say,
      a plunderer and a robber—to be slain by day, even when you catch him, a self-evident
      enemy, within your walls. “Unless he defends himself with a weapon,” says
      the law; not even if he has come with a weapon; unless he uses it, and resists; “you
      shall not kill him. If he resists, <foreign xml:lang="lat">endoplorato</foreign>,” that
      is to say, raise an outcry, that people may hear you and come to your aid. What can be added
      more to this merciful view of the case, when they did not allow that it might be lawful for a
      man to defend his own life in his own house without witnesses and umpires? 
       </p></div>
   <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>Who is there who ought more to be pardoned, (since you bring me back to the Twelve Tables,)
      than a man who without being aware of it kills another? No one, I think. For this is a silent
      law of humanity, that punishment for intentions, but not for fortune, may be exacted of a man.
      Still our ancestors did not pardon even this. For there is a law in the Twelve Tables,
      “If a weapon escapes from the hand” <gap reason="lost"/>
     </p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p>
       If any one slays a thief, he slays him wrongfully. Why? Because there is no law established
      by which he may do so. What? suppose he defended himself with a weapon? Then he did not slay
      him wrongfully. Why so? Because there is a law<gap reason="lost"/>
      </p></div>
   <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus"><p> Still it would have been done by violence. <gap reason="lost"/> Still in that
      very spot which belonged to you, you not only could not lawfully slay the slaves of Marcus
      Tullius, but even if you had demolished the house without his knowledge, or by violence,
      because he had built it in your land and defended his act on the ground of its being his, it
      would be decided to have been done by violence, or secretly. Now, do you yourself decide how
      true it is, that, when your household had no power to throw down a few tiles with impunity, he
      had power to commit an extensive massacre without violating the law. If, now that that
      building has been demolished, I myself were this day to prosecute him on the ground
      “that it was done by violence, or secretly,” you must inevitably either
      make restitution according to the sentence of an arbitrator, or you must be condemned in the
      amount of your security. Now, will you be able to make it seem reasonable to such men as these
      judges, that, though you had no power of your own right to demolish the building, because it
      was, as you maintain, on your land, you had power of your own right to slay the men who were
      in that edifice? </p></div>
   <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus">
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>“But my slave is not to be found, who was seen with your slaves. But my cottage
      was burnt by your slaves.” What reply am I to make to this? I have proved that it
      was false. Still I will admit it. What comes next? Does it follow from this that the household
      of Marcus Tullius ought to be murdered? Scarcely, in truth, that they ought to be flogged,
      scarcely, that they ought to be severely reprimanded. But granting that you were ever so
      severe; the matter could be tried in the usual course of law, by an everyday sort of trial.
      What was the need of violence? what was the need of armed men, of slaughter, and of bloodshed?
       </p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus">
					<p><milestone unit="para"/>“But perhaps they would have proceeded to attack me.” This, in their
      desperate case, is neither a speech nor a defence, but a mere guess, a sort of divination.
      Were they coming to attack him? Whom? Fabius. With what intention? To kill him. Why? to gain
      what? how did you find it out? And that I may set forth a plain case as briefly as possible,
      is it possible to doubt, O judges, which side seems to have been the attacking
      party?— 
					</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus">
					 <p>Those who came to the house, or those who remained in the house? Those who were slain, or those, of whose number not one man was
      wounded? Those who had no imaginable reason for acting so, or those who confess that they did
      act so? But suppose I were to believe that you were afraid of being attacked, who ever laid
      down such a principle as this, or who could have this granted him without extreme danger to
      the whole body of citizens, that he might lawfully kill a man, if he only said that he was
      afraid of being hereafter killed by him? [The rest of this oration is lost.] </p>
				</div>
  </div>
  </body>
			</text>

			</TEI>
