<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 35</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="book">
                <head>Antiochus in Greece</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the opening months of the year in which
                        the above events occurred several unimportant engagements took place in
                        Spain between Sextus Digitius, the praetor, and the numerous cantons which
                        after the departure of M. Cato had recommenced hostilities. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> These were on the whole so costly to the Romans that
                        the force which the praetor handed over to his successor was hardly half
                        what he had received. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There would
                        undoubtedly have been a general rising throughout Spain had not the other
                        praetor, P. Cornelius Scipio, fought several successful actions beyond the
                        Ebro and so cowed the natives that no less than fifty towns went over to
                        him. This was whilst he was praetor. As pro-praetor he inflicted a severe
                        defeat on the Lusitanians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They had
                        devastated Further Spain and were on <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                        their way home with an immense quantity of plunder when he attacked them on
                        the march and fought from the third hour of the day to the eighth without
                        arriving at any decision. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He was inferior
                        in numbers, but in everything else he had the advantage, for he was with
                        close and serried ranks attacking a long column hampered by many herds of
                        cattle, and his soldiers were fresh while the enemy were wearied with their
                        long march. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They had started in the third
                        hour of the night on a march which was prolonged through three hours of
                        daylight and they were forced to accept battle without taking any rest.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So it was only in the first stage of
                        the battle that they showed any spirit or energy. At first they threw the
                        Romans into some disorder, but soon the fighting became even. In the crisis
                        of the struggle the praetor vowed that he would celebrate Games to Jupiter
                        if he should rout and destroy the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        At length the Roman attack became more insistent and the Lusitanians began
                        to give ground. Finally they broke and fled, and in the hot pursuit which
                        followed as many as 12,000 of the enemy were killed, 540 prisoners taken,
                        nearly all mounted troops, and 134 standards captured. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The losses in the Roman army amounted to 73. The scene
                        of the action was not far from the city of Ilipa, and P. Cornelius led his
                        victorious army, enriched with spoil, to that place. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The whole of the booty was laid out in front of the
                        city and the owners were allowed to claim their property. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The rest was made over to the quaestor to be sold and
                        the proceeds distributed to the soldiers. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> C. Flaminius had not left Rome when these
                        things happened in Spain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Naturally he and
                        his friends talked much more about the defeats than about the successes, and
                        as a widespread war had broken out in his province and he was going to take
                        over from Sex. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Digitius a miserable
                        remnant of an army, and that utterly demoralised, he had tried to induce the
                        senate to assign to him one of the City legions. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> From this and from the force which the senate had
                        empowered him to raise he could select 6200 infantry and 300 cavalry, and
                        with that legion-for there was not much to be expected from Digitius'
                        army-he said he could manage very well. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The senior members of the House said that their decisions must not depend
                        upon rumours started <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> by private
                        individuals in the interest of particular magistrates, and that no
                        importance should be attached to anything but the despatches of the praetors
                        from their provinces or the reports which their officers brought home.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If there was a sudden rising in Spain
                        they considered that emergency troops ought to be promptly raised by the
                        praetor outside Italy. What they had in their minds was that these troops
                        should be raised in Spain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias
                        asserts that C. Flaminius went to Sicily to enlist men, and that whilst on
                        his way from there to Spain he was carried by a storm to Africa, where he
                        administered the military oath to soldiers who had belonged to the
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> army of P. Africanus. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Italy, too, the Ligurian war was
                        growing more serious. Pisae was now surrounded by 40,000 men, and their
                        numbers were being swelled daily by crowds who were attracted by the love of
                        fighting and the hope of plunder. Minucius arrived in Arretium on the day
                        which he had appointed for the assembling of his soldiers. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> From there he marched in close order to Pisae, and
                        though the enemy had moved their camp across the river to a position not
                        more than a mile distant from the place, he succeeded in entering the city,
                        which his arrival undoubtedly saved. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        day following he, too, crossed the river and fixed his camp about half a
                        mile distant from that of the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From
                        this position he sent out skirmishers, and so protected the land of the
                        friendly tribes from depredation. As his troops were new levies, drawn from
                        various classes and not yet sufficiently acquainted with each other to feel
                        mutual confidence, he did not venture to challenge a regular engagement.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Ligurians, relying on their
                        numbers, marched out and offered battle, prepared for a decisive conflict,
                        and even detached bodies to go in all directions beyond their frontiers to
                        secure plunder. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they had collected a
                        vast quantity of cattle and other booty an armed escort was ready to take it
                        to their forts and villages. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the Ligurian operations were confined
                        to Pisae the other consul led his army through the furthest limits of
                        Liguria into the country of the Boii. Here totally different tactics were
                        pursued; it was the consul who offered battle and the enemy who declined it.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As they met with no opposition the
                        Romans dispersed on plundering forays, the Boii preferring to let their
                        property be carried off with impunity rather than risk a battle in its
                        defence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After the whole country had been
                        laid waste with fire and sword the consul left the enemy's territory and
                        marched in the direction of Mutina, taking as little precaution against
                        attack as though he were in a friendly country. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When the Boii found that their enemy had withdrawn from
                        their frontiers, they followed noiselessly, looking out for a suitable place
                        for a surprise attack. Passing by the Roman camp in the night, they seized a
                        pass through which the Romans would have to go. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> This movement did not escape observation, and the
                        consul, who had been in the habit of marching in the dead of the night,
                        decided to wait for daylight so that the dangers incident to a tumultuary
                        battle might not be augmented by darkness. Though it was quite light when he
                        started, he sent on a squadron of cavalry to reconnoitre. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> On receiving their report as to the strength and
                        position of the enemy he ordered the whole of the baggage to be collected
                        together, and the triarii were told off to surround it with a breastwork.
                        With the rest of his army in battle formation he advanced against the enemy.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Gauls did the same when they found
                        that their stratagem was exposed and that they would have to fight an open
                        and regular battle. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The action began about eight o'clock. The
                        left wing of the allied cavalry and the "special" corps were fighting in the
                        front line, and two generals of consular rank-M. Marcellus and Tiberius
                        Sempronius; the latter had been consul the previous year-were in command of
                        them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul Merula was at one moment
                        at the front and at another holding back the legions who were in reserve,
                        lest in their eagerness they should go forward before the signal was given.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Two military tribunes, Q. Minucius and
                        P. Minucius, received orders to take the cavalry of these two legions
                        outside the line and when the signal was given to deliver an attack from the
                        open. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whilst the consul was making these
                        dispositions a message came from Ti. Sempronius Longus informing him that
                        the special corps were not able <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> to
                        withstand the onslaught of the Gauls, a great many had been killed, and the
                        survivors, wearied out and dispirited, had lost all heart for fighting. He
                        asked the consul, therefore, if he approved, to send up one of the legions
                        before they were humiliated by defeat. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        second legion was sent up and the special corps was withdrawn. The battle
                        was now restored, as the legion came up with its men fresh and its maniples
                        complete. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As the left division was
                        withdrawn from the fighting the right came up into the front line. The hot
                        sun was blazing down on the Gauls, who were incapable of standing the heat;
                        nevertheless they sustained the attacks of the Roman army in mass formation,
                        leaning against each other or on their shields. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> On perceiving this the consul ordered C. Livius
                        Salinator, the allied cavalry leader, to send his men at a hard gallop
                        against them, and the cavalry of the legions to act as supports. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> This hurricane of cavalry confused, disordered,
                        and finally broke up the Gaulish lines, but they did not turn to flee.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Their officers began to stop any
                        attempt at flight by striking the waverers with their spears and forcing
                        them back into their ranks, but the cavalry, riding in amongst them, did not
                        allow them to do this. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consul urged
                        his men on; only a little more effort was needed, he said; victory was
                        within their grasp, they saw how disordered and demoralised the enemy were,
                        and they must press the attack. If they allowed them to re-form their ranks,
                        the battle would begin all over again with doubtful result. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> He ordered the standard-bearers to advance, and
                        with one united effort they at last forced the enemy to give way. When once
                        the Gauls were scattered in flight the cavalry of the legions was sent in
                        pursuit. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Fourteen thousand of the Boii
                        were killed in that day's fighting, 1902 taken prisoners, as well as 721 of
                        their cavalry, including three officers; 212 standards were also captured
                        and 63 military wagons. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Nor was the
                        victory a bloodless one for the Romans; they and the allied contingents
                        together lost over 5000 men, including 23 centurions, four praefects of
                        allies and three military tribunes in the second legion-M. Genucius, Q.
                        Marcius and M. Marcius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Despatches from the two consuls arrived in
                        Rome almost on the same day. The one from L. Cornelius contained his report
                        of the battle at Mutina; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that from Q.
                        Minucius, at Pisae, stated that the conduct of the elections had fallen to
                        his lot, but the whole position in Liguria was so uncertain that it was
                        impossible for him to leave without bringing ruin on the friendly tribes and
                        injury to the interests of the republic. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        He suggested that if the senate thought proper they should send word to his
                        colleague, who had practically brought the war in Gaul to a close,
                        requesting him to return to Rome for the elections. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> If Cornelius objected on the ground that it was not
                        part of his allotted duties, he was ready to do whatever the senate decided
                        upon. But he begged them to give long and careful consideration to the
                        question whether it would be more in the interest of the State that an
                        interrex should be appointed than that he should leave his province in such
                        a condition. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate instructed C.
                        Scribonius to send two commissioners of senatorial rank to L. Cornelius to
                        show him the despatch which his colleague had sent to <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> the senate, and to inform him that unless he came to
                        Rome for the election of the new magistrates the senate would consent to the
                        appointment of an interrex rather than call away Q. Minucius from a war
                        which had hardly begun. The commissioners brought back word that L.
                        Cornelius would come to Rome for the election of the new magistrates.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The despatch which he had sent after
                        his engagement with the Boii gave rise to a debate in the senate. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> M. Claudius had written unofficially to the
                        majority of the senators stating that it was the good fortune of Rome and
                        the valour of the soldiers that they had to thank for any success that had
                        been gained. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> All the consul had done was
                        to lose a large number of his men and let the enemy slip out of his hands
                        when he had the chance of annihilating them. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> His losses were mainly due to the delay in bringing up
                        the reserves to relieve the first line, who were being overpowered. The
                        enemy were able to escape because he was too late in giving the order to the
                        legionary cavalry, and so prevented them from following up the fugitives.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate agreed that no hasty decision
                        should be come to on this matter and the debate was adjourned for a fuller
                        meeting of the House. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was another
                        pressing question to be dealt with. The citizens were suffering from
                        money-lenders, and though numerous laws had been made in restraint of
                        avarice they were evaded through the fraudulent transferring of the bills to
                        subjects of the allied States who were not bound by these laws. In this way
                        debtors were being overwhelmed by unlimited interest. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> After a discussion as to the best method of checking
                        this practice it was decided to fix a date, and all members of the allied
                        States who had after that date lent money to Roman citizens were required to
                        make a return of the amounts so lent, and the debtor was to be at liberty to
                        choose under which laws the creditor might exercise his rights. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The appointed day was that of the Feralia, which
                        had just been celebrated. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From the returns
                        sent in it was found that the debts contracted under this fraudulent system
                        amounted to a considerable sum, and M. Sempronius, one of the tribunes of
                        the plebs, was authorised by the senate to propose a measure, which the
                        plebs adopted, providing that debts contracted with members of the Latin and
                        allied communities should come under the same <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> laws as those contracted with Roman citizens. These
                        were the main military and political events in Italy. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> In Spain the war was by no means so serious as rumour
                        represented. C. Flaminius in Hither Spain took the fortified town of Inlucia
                        in the country of the Oretani. He then with drew his troops into winter
                        quarters, and during the winter several unimportant actions were fought to
                        repel raiding parties, who resembled banditti rather than hostile troops. He
                        was not always successful, however, and sustained losses. More important
                        operations were carried on by M. Fulvius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        He fought a pitched battle near Toletum with a combined force of Vaccaci,
                        Vettones and Celtiberians, defeated and routed them and took Hilernus their
                        king prisoner. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the date of the elections was
                        approaching, and L. Cornelius, after handing over his command to M.
                        Claudius, went to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After expatiating
                        in the senate upon his services and the state in which he had left the
                        province, he took the senators to task for not having paid due honour to the
                        immortal gods, now that such a serious war had been terminated by a single
                        victorious battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then asked the House
                        to decree a public thanksgiving, and at the same time a triumph for him.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before the question was put, however,
                        Q. Metellus, who had filled the offices of consul and dictator, said that
                        the despatch which L. Cornelius had sent to the senate and the letter which
                        M. Marcellus had sent to most of the senators were in conflict with one
                        another, and the discussion of this question had been adjourned in order
                        that it might take place when the writers of these letters were present.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He had been expecting, therefore, that
                        the consul, who knew that his lieutenant had made statements reflecting on
                        him, would bring him with him when he had to come to Rome, especially as the
                        army ought really to have been handed over to Tiberius Sempronius, who had
                        the imperium, and not to a staff officer. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        It seemed now as if the man had been purposely kept out of the way who could
                        have repeated his written statements face <milestone n="7??" unit="section"
                        /> to face with his opponent and established them if possible, while any
                        groundless charge he made could have been disproved until at last the truth
                        had been clearly ascertained. He gave it as his opinion, therefore, that
                        none of the decrees which the consul asked for should, for the present at
                        all events, be made. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As the consul still
                        persisted in asking the senate to decree a public thanksgiving and
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> authorise him to ride in triumph
                        through the City, two of the tribunes of the plebs, M. Titinius and C.
                        Titinius, said that they would exercise their right of veto if a resolution
                        of the senate were passed to that effect. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The censors who had been elected during
                        the previous year were Sextus Aelius Paetus and C. Cornelius Cethegus.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Cornelius closed the lustrum. The
                        assessment returns gave the number of citizens as 243,704. There was an
                        enormous rainfall that year and the low-lying parts of the City were
                        inundated by the Tiber. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Near the Porta
                        Flumentana some buildings collapsed and fell in ruins. The Porta
                        Coelimontana was struck by lightning and the wall adjacent was struck in
                        several places. At Aricia and Lanuvium and on the Aventine there were
                        showers of stones. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was reported from
                        Capua that a huge swarm of wasps flew into the forum and settled in the
                        temple of Mars, and that they were carefully collected and burnt. In
                        consequence of these portents the Keepers of the Sacred Books were ordered
                        to consult them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Sacrifices were offered
                        for nine days, public intercessions were appointed and the City underwent
                        lustration. During this time M. Porcius Cato dedicated the chapel of
                        Victoria Virgo near the temple of Victory, which he had vowed two years
                        previously. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> During the year a Latin colony
                        was settled at the Castrum Frentinum in the territory of Thurium. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The commissioners who superintended the
                        colonisation were A. Manlius Volso, L. Apustius Fullo and Q. Aelius Tubero,
                        the latter of whom had brought in the bill for its settlement. The colonists
                        comprised 3000 infantry and 300 cavalry, a small number in proportion to the
                        amount of land available. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thirty jugera
                        might have been allotted to each infantryman and 60 to each of the cavalry,
                        but on the advice of Apustius a third of the land was reserved, which could,
                        were it desired, be assigned to fresh colonists. The infantry received 20
                        jugera and the cavalry 40 each. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year was now drawing to a close and
                        the canvassing for the consular elections was keener than had ever been
                        known before. There were many strong candidates, both patrician and
                        plebeian, in the field. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The patrician
                        candidates were P. Cornelius, the son of Cneius Scipio, who had lately
                        returned from his province in Spain with a brilliant record; L. Quinctius
                        Flamininus, who had commanded the fleet off Greece, and Cn. Manlius Volso.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The plebeian candidates were C.
                        Laelius, Cn. Domitius, C. Livius Salinator and Manius Acilius. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> But all men's eyes were turned to Quinctius and
                        Cornelius, for as they were both patricians they were competing for the same
                        place and they each possessed strong recommendations, for each had covered
                        himself with military glory. But it was the brothers of the two candidates
                        who most of all made the contest such an exciting one, for they were the two
                        most brilliant commanders of their day. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Scipio had the more splendid reputation, but its very splendour exposed him
                        all the more to jealousy; Quinctius' reputation was of more recent growth,
                        as his triumph had been celebrated during the year. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Moreover, the former had been continually before the
                        public eye for nearly ten years, a circumstance which tends to diminish the
                        reverence felt for great men as people become surfeited with their praises.
                        He had been made consul for the second time after his final defeat of
                        Hannibal, and also censor. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the case of
                        Quinctius, all his claims to popular favour were founded upon his recent
                        successes; since his triumph he had not sought for nor received anything
                        from the people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He said that he was
                        canvassing for his own brother, not for a step-brother; for one who had as
                        lieutenant shared with him the management of the war; whilst he commanded on
                        land his brother commanded at sea. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By
                        these arguments he succeeded in beating his competitor, though his
                        competitor was supported by his brother Africanus, by the house of the
                        Cornelii-it was a Cornelius who was conducting the election-and by the
                        splendid testimonial which the senate gave when they pronounced Africanus to
                        be the best man among all the citizens and most worthy to receive the Mater
                        Idaea on her arrival from Pessinus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> L.
                        Quinctius and Cneius Domitius Ahenobarbus were the two elected, so that even
                        in the case of the plebeian candidate C. Laelius, Scipio, who had been
                        working for him, was unable to secure his return. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The next day the praetors were elected. The successful
                        candidates were L. Scribonius Libo, M. Fulvius Centumalus, A. Atilius
                        Serranus, M. Baebius Tamphilus, L. Valerius Tappo and Q. Salonius Sarra. M.
                        Aemilius Lepidus and L. Aemilius Paulus distinguished themselves as aediles
                        this year. They inflicted fines on a large number of graziers, and out of
                        the proceeds they had gold-plated shields made, which they placed on the
                        pediment of the temple of Jupiter. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They
                        also built an arcade outside the Porta Trigemina, and in connection with it
                        a wharf on the Tiber, and a second arcade leading from the Porta Fontinalis
                        to the altar of Mars in the Campus Martius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For a considerable time nothing worth
                        recording had happened in Liguria, but at the close of the year affairs
                        assumed a very serious aspect. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        consul's camp was attacked and the attack was repulsed with great
                        difficulty, and when, not long after, the Roman army was marching through a
                        pass a Ligurian army seized the mouth of the pass. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As the exit was blocked the consul decided to go back
                        and countermarched his men. But the entrance behind them had been also
                        occupied by a portion of the enemy forces, and the disaster of Candium not
                        only occurred to the minds of the soldiers but almost presented itself
                        before their eyes. Amongst his auxiliary troops the consul had about 800
                        Numidian horse. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their commander assured
                        the consul that he would break through on whichever side he chose if only he
                        could tell him in which direction lay the most numerous villages, as he
                        would attack them and instantly fire the houses so that <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> the alarm thus created might compel the Ligurians to
                        leave their position in the pass and help their countrymen. The consul
                        highly approved of his plan and promised to reward him richly. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The Numidians mounted their horses and began to
                        ride towards the enemy's outposts without showing any aggressiveness.
                        Nothing could at first sight look more contemptible than the appearance they
                        presented; horses and men were alike thin and diminutive; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> the riders were without body armour and, except for the
                        javelins they carried, unarmed; the horses had no bridles and their pacing
                        was most ungainly, trotting as they did with head and neck stuck straight
                        out. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The contempt which they aroused they
                        did their best to increase; they fell from their horses and presented a
                        ridiculous spectacle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Consequently the men
                        at the outposts who had at first been on the alert, prepared to meet an
                        attack, now laid their arms aside and sat down to watch the show. The
                        Numidians rode forward and then galloped back, but always got a little
                        nearer <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> to the mouth of the pass, as
                        though they were carried forward by their horses which they were incapable
                        of managing. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At last, digging in their
                        spurs, they made a dash through the enemy's outposts, and emerging into open
                        country set fire to all the dwellings near the road and then to the first
                        village they came to, laying it all waste with fire and sword. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> The sight of the smoke, the cries of the
                        terrified villagers and the hasty flight of the old men and the children
                        produced great excitement in the Ligurian camp, and without waiting for
                        orders or concerted <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> action every man
                        ran off to protect his property and in a moment the camp was deserted. The
                        consul, extricated from the blockade, reached his destination. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Neither the Boii nor the Spaniards,
                        however, with whom Rome had been warring that year, were such bitter enemies
                        as the Aetolians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the Roman armies
                        had evacuated Greece they expected that Antiochus would take possession of
                        that part of Europe vacated, and that neither Philip nor Nabis would remain
                        inactive. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they saw no movement
                        anywhere they decided that to prevent their designs from being thwarted by
                        delay they must do something to produce agitation and confusion, and
                        accordingly a council was convened at Naupactus. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Here Thoas, their chief magistrate, complained of their
                        unjust treatment by the Romans and the position in which the Aetolians were
                        placed, for after a victory which was won through them, they, of all the
                        States and cities in Greece, had been shown the least consideration.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He advised that envoys should be sent
                        to each of the three kings to find out their intentions and to urge such
                        arguments on each as would goad them into a war with Rome. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Democritus was sent to Nabis, Nicander to Philip, and
                        Dicaearchus, the brother of Thoas, to Antiochus. Democritus pointed out to
                        the tyrant that by the loss of his maritime cities the very sinews of his
                        power were cut; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> it was from them that he
                        drew his soldiers, his ships and his crews. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> Little more than a prisoner within his own walls, he saw the Achaeans
                        fording it over the Peloponnese; he would never have another opportunity of
                        winning back his dominion if he let this one go by; there was no Roman army
                        in Greece, and they would never think it worth their while to send their
                        legions back again for the sake of Gytheum and the other Laconian cities on
                        the coast. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such were the arguments used to
                        influence the tyrant, so that when Antiochus landed in Greece the
                        consciousness of having broken his amity with Rome through his ill-treatment
                        of her allies might force him to join arms with the Syrian monarch. </p>
                    <p> Nicander took much the same line in his interview with Philip. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> He spoke with all the greater force because the
                        king had been brought down from a loftier position than the tyrant and had
                        lost more of his power. He reminded the king of the former prestige of
                        Macedonia and the world-wide victories of his nation. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Nicander assured him that the policy recommended was a
                        safe one both in its initiation and its execution. On the one hand he was
                        not asking Philip to take any action before Antiochus was in Greece with his
                        army, on the other there was every prospect of final success. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> With what possible force could the Romans hold
                        their own against him when leagued <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> with
                        Antiochus and the Aetolians after he had, without the help of Antiochus,
                        maintained such a protracted struggle against the Romans and against the
                        Aetolians, who were at the time a more formidable enemy than the Romans? He
                        also spoke about Hannibal as a foe to Rome from his birth, who had slain
                        more of her generals and soldiers than still survived. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Such were the arguments employed with Philip. Those
                        advanced by Dicaearchus in his interview with Antiochus were different.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The spoils of war, he said, won from
                        Philip belonged to the Romans, but the victory over him to the Aetolians;
                        they and they alone had granted the Romans an entrance into Greece and
                        provided them with the strength which secured victory. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> He went on to enumerate the amount of infantry and
                        cavalry which they were prepared to furnish to Antiochus, the localities
                        which would be available for his land army and the harbours which could
                        receive his fleet. Then, as Philip and Nabis were not present to check him,
                        he falsely <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> represented them as prepared
                        for immediate hostilities and ready to seize the very first opportunity of
                        recovering what they had lost in war. In this way the Aetolians tried to
                        stir up war against Rome throughout the world. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The kings, however, took no action, or at
                        all events their action was too late. Nabis promptly sent emissaries to all
                        the coast towns to foment a rising; some of their leading citizens he won
                        over by bribes, others who remained steadfast to the cause of Rome he put to
                        death. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> T. Quinctius had entrusted the
                        Achaeans with the defence of the coast towns and they lost no time in
                        sending envoys to the tyrant to remind him of his treaty with Rome and to
                        warn him against disturbing the peace which he had so ardently sought for.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They also sent succours to Gytheum,
                        which the tyrant was already attacking, and sent a report to Rome of what
                        was happening. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> During the winter Antiochus
                        went to Raphia in Phenicia to be present at the marriage of his daughter to
                        Ptolemy, the king of Egypt, and at the close of the winter returned through
                        Cilicia to Ephesus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After sending his son
                        Antiochus into Syria to watch the more distant frontiers of his kingdom in
                        case any disturbance should take place in his rear, he left Ephesus and
                        marched with the whole of his land army against the Pisidians in the
                        neighbourhood of Sida. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whilst he was thus
                        engaged the Roman commissioners, P. Sulpicius and P. Villius, who, as I have
                        already stated, had been sent to interview him, received instructions to
                        visit Eumenes first, and after landing at Elea they went up to Pergamum,
                        where the king's palace was situated. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Eumenes welcomed the prospect of a war with Antiochus, for he felt certain
                        that if a monarch so much more powerful than himself were left in peace he
                        would prove a troublesome neighbour, and if there was war Antiochus would be
                        no more a match for the Romans than Philip had been, and would either be
                        altogether got rid of or so completely defeated as to submit to terms of
                        peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In this case much taken from
                        Antiochus would be added to his dominions, and then he would easily be able
                        to defend himself without any assistance from Rome. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Even at the worst, Eumenes thought it better to meet
                        any misfortune with the Romans as his allies than, standing alone, have to
                        accept the supremacy of Antiochus, or if he refused, be compelled to do so
                        by force. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For these reasons he did his
                        utmost by personal influence and by argument to urge the Romans to war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Owing to illness Sulpicius stopped at
                        Pergamum, whilst Villius went on to Ephesus, as he heard that the king had
                        commenced hostilities in Pisidia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He made
                        a short stay there, and as Hannibal happened to be there at the time he made
                        a point of paying frequent visits <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> to him
                        in order to ascertain his future plans and if possible remove any
                        apprehension from his mind as to danger threatening him from Rome.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nothing else was discussed in these
                        interviews, but they had one result, which though really undesigned might
                        have been deliberately aimed at, for they lowered Hannibal's authority with
                        the king and cast suspicion upon all that he said or did. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Claudius, following Acilius who wrote in Greek, says
                        that Publius Scipio Africanus was one of the commissioners, and that he had
                        conversations with Hannibal. One of these he reports. Africanus asked
                        Hannibal whom he considered to be the greatest commander, and the reply was,
                        "Alexander of Macedon, <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> for with a small
                        force he routed innumerable armies and traversed the most distant shores of
                        the world which no man ever hoped to visit." <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Africanus then asked him whom he would put second, and Hannibal replied,
                        "Pyrrhus; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> he was the first who taught how
                        to lay out a camp, and moreover no one ever showed more cleverness in the
                        choice of positions and the disposition of troops. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He possessed, too, the art of winning popularity to
                        such an extent that the nations of Italy preferred the rule of a foreign
                        king to that of the Roman people who had so long held the foremost place in
                        that country." On Scipio's again asking him whom he regarded as the third,
                        Hannibal, without any hesitation, replied, "Myself." <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio smiled and asked, "What would you say if you had
                        vanquished me?" <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "In that case," replied
                        Hannibal, "I should say that I surpassed Alexander and Pyrrhus, and all
                        other commanders in the world." Scipio was delighted with the turn which the
                        speaker had with true Carthaginian adroitness given to his answer, and the
                        unexpected flattery it conveyed, <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                        because Hannibal had set him apart from the ordinary run of military
                        captains as an incomparable commander. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From Ephesus Villius went on to Apamea. On
                        being informed of the Roman commissioner's arrival, Antiochus proceeded
                        thither also. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The conversations between
                        them were almost on the same lines as those which Quinctius had held with
                        the king's envoys in Rome The conference was broken off in consequence of
                        intelligence received of the death of the king's son, who, as already
                        stated, had been sent to Syria. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was
                        great mourning in the court, and the young man's loss was deeply regretted.
                        He had already given proof of such qualities that it was certain, if his
                        life had been spared, he would have shown himself a great and just monarch.
                        The more universally he had made himself beloved, the stronger the
                        suspicions which were felt about his death. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> The king, it was said, looked upon the heir-apparent as a menace to his
                        old age, and so had him taken off by poison through the agency of certain
                        eunuchs, a class of men whose services kings are glad to employ in crimes of
                        this kind. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Another motive which was
                        attributed to the king strengthened this suspicion, for as he had given
                        Lysimachia to his son Seleucus he had no similar residence to which he could
                        remove Antiochus under presence of conferring an honour upon him. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The court, however, presented all the outward
                        signs of mourning for several days, and the Roman commissioner, not wishing
                        to be in the way at such an unseasonable time, withdrew to Pergamum.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The king abandoned the war which he
                        had begun and returned to Ephesus. There, with his palace closed on account
                        of the mourning, he held secret counsels with his favourite courtier, a man
                        called Minnio. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Minnio, utterly ignorant of
                        the outside world and measuring the king's power by his campaigns in Syria
                        and Asia, was fully convinced that Antiochus would prove no less superior to
                        the Romans in war than he was in the justice of his cause, as the demands of
                        the Romans were unjustifiable. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As the king
                        avoided all further discussion with the commissioners, either because he
                        found that nothing was to be gained from them or owing to the depression due
                        to his recent bereavement, Minnio said that he would act as spokesman on the
                        king's behalf, and induced Antiochus to invite the commissioners up from
                        Pergamum. Sulpicius had now recovered, so they both proceeded to Ephesus.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .Minnio apologised for the non-appearance
                        of the king and the negotiations proceeded in his absence. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Minnio opened the discussion in a carefully prepared
                        speech, in which he said: "I see that you Romans claim the fair-sounding
                        epithet of 'Liberators of the cities of Greece.' But your acts do not
                        correspond to your words; you lay down one law for Antiochus, and another
                        for yourselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For how are the
                        inhabitants of Smyrna and Lampsacus more Greek than those of Neapolis and
                        Regium and Tarentum, from whom you demand tribute and ships by virtue of
                        your treaty with them? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Why do you send
                        year by year a quaestor with full powers of life and death to Syracuse and
                        the other Greek cities of Sicily? The only reason that you could give would,
                        of course, be that you imposed these terms upon them after subjugating them
                        by force. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then accept the same reason from
                        Antiochus in the case of Smyrna and Lampsacus and the cities of Ionia and
                        Aeolis. They were conquered by his ancestors and made to pay tribute and
                        taxes, and he claims the rights which have come down to him from ancient
                        times. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I should be glad, therefore, if you
                        would answer him on these points, if, that is, you are prepared to discuss
                        them fairly, and are not simply seeking a pretext for war." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Sulpicius replied: "If these are the only
                        arguments that can be advanced in support of his case, Antiochus has shown a
                        discreet modesty in letting them be brought forward by anybody rather than
                        by himself. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For what possible resemblance
                        can there be between the circumstances of the two groups of cities which you
                        have mentioned? From the day when Regium, Tarentum, and Neapolis passed into
                        our hands we have demanded the fulfilment of their treaty obligations by an
                        unbroken tenor of right which has always been asserted and never
                        intermitted. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Those communities have never,
                        either of themselves or through anyone else, made any change in those
                        obligations; would you venture to assert that the same holds good of the
                        cities of Asia, and that after once becoming subject to the ancestors of
                        Antiochus they have remained in the uninterrupted possession of your
                        monarchy? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Can you deny that some of them
                        have been subject to Philip, others to Ptolemy, others again have for many
                        years enjoyed an independence which no one has ever challenged? <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Granting that they at some time or other under
                        the pressure of misfortune lost their freedom, does that give you the right
                        after so many ages to claim them as your vassals? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> If so, we accomplished nothing when we delivered Greece
                        from Philip; his successors can reassert their right to Corinth, Chalcis,
                        and the whole of Thessaly. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But why do I
                        defend the cause of States which they themselves should more properly defend
                        in the hearing of the king and themselves?" </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He then ordered the representatives of the
                        States to be called in. Eumenes, who quite expected that whatever strength
                        Antiochus lost would prove an accession to his own dominions, had prepared
                        the representatives beforehand and told them what to say. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Several were brought in, and as they each stated their
                        grievances and put forward their demands quite regardless as to whether
                        these were fair or not, they changed the discussion into a heated
                        altercation. Unable either to make or to obtain any concessions, the
                        commissioners resumed to Rome leaving everything as unsettled as when they
                        came. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On their departure the king held a
                        council of war. Here each speaker tried to outdo the rest in violence of
                        language, for the more bitter he showed himself against the Romans the
                        better his chance of winning the king's favour. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> One of them denounced the Roman demands as arrogant:
                        "They tried to impose on Antiochus, the greatest monarch in Asia, as though
                        he were the defeated Nabis, <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and yet even
                        Nabis they allowed to remain as sovereign over his own country and to retain
                        Lacedaemon, whilst <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> they consider it an
                        offence if Smyrna and Lampsacus are under the sway of Antiochus." <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Others argued that those cities were for so great
                        a monarch slight and insignificant grounds of war, but unjust demands always
                        began with small matters, unless indeed they were to suppose that when the
                        Persians demanded earth and water from the Lacedaemonians they were actually
                        in need of a clod of earth and a draught of water. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> A similar attempt was now being made by the Romans in
                        respect of these two cities, and as soon as others saw that these had shaken
                        off the yoke they too would go over to the people who posed as liberators.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Even if liberty were not in itself
                        preferable to servitude, everyone, whatever his present condition may be,
                        finds the prospect of change more attractive. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was amongst those present an
                        Acarnanian named Alexander. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had
                        formerly been one of Philip's friends, but had latterly attached himself to
                        the wealthier and more magnificent court of Antiochus. As he was thoroughly
                        familiar with the state of affairs in Greece and possessed some knowledge of
                        the Roman character he had come to be on such intimate terms with Antiochus
                        that he even took part in his private councils. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As though the question under discussion was not whether
                        war should be declared or not, but simply where and how it should be
                        conducted, he said that he looked forward to certain victory if the king
                        would cross over into Europe and fix the seat of war in some part of Greece.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He would first of all find the
                        Aetolians, who live in the centre of Greece, in arms, ready to take their
                        places in the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> front and face all the
                        dangers and hardships of war. Then, in what might be called the right and
                        left wing of Greece, Nabis was ready in the Peloponnesus to do his utmost to
                        recover Argos and the maritime cities from which the Romans had expelled him
                        and shut him up within his own walls. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In
                        Macedonia Philip would take up arms the moment he heard the war-trumpet
                        sound; he knew his spirit, he knew his temper, he knew that he had been
                        revolving in his mind vast schemes of revenge, chafing like wild beasts that
                        are fastened up by bars or chains. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                        remembered, too, how often during the war Philip had besought all the gods
                        to give him the help of Antiochus; if this prayer were now granted he would
                        not lose an hour in recommencing war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Only
                        there must be no delay, no holding back, for victory depended upon their
                        being the first to secure allies and to seize the most advantageous
                        positions. Hannibal, too, ought to be sent to Africa at once to create a
                        diversion and divide the Roman forces. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal had not been invited to the
                        council. He had aroused the king's suspicions by his interviews with
                        Villius, and no respect or regard was now shown to him. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> For some time he bore this affront in silence; then,
                        thinking it better to inquire the reason for this sudden estrangement and at
                        the same time to clear himself from any suspicion, he chose a fitting moment
                        and put a direct question to the king as to the reason for his disfavour.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he heard what the reason was, he
                        said, "When I was a small boy, Antiochus, my father Hamilcar took me up to
                        the altar whilst he was offering sacrifice and made me solemnly swear that I
                        would never be a friend to Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Under
                        this oath I have fought for six-and-thirty years; when peace was settled
                        this oath drove me from my native country and brought me a homeless wanderer
                        to your court. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If you cheat my hopes, this
                        oath will lead me wherever I can find support, wherever I learn that there
                        are arms, and I shall find some enemies of Rome, though I have to seek them
                        through the wide world. If, therefore, it pleases your courtiers to advance
                        in your favour by aspersing me, let them seek some other ground for
                        advancing themselves at my expense. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I hate
                        the Romans and the Romans hate me. My father Hamilcar and all the gods are
                        witness that I am speaking the truth. When, then, you are making plans for a
                        war against Rome, count Hannibal amongst the first of your friends; if
                        circumstances constrain you to remain at peace, seek someone else to share
                        your counsels." <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This speech had a great
                        effect upon the king and it brought about a reconciliation with Hannibal.
                        The king left the council, resolved on war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Rome people spoke of Antiochus as the
                        enemy, but beyond this attitude of mind they were making no preparations for
                        war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Both the consuls had Italy assigned
                        to them as their province on the understanding that they were either
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> to come to a mutual agreement or
                        leave it to the ballot as to which of them should preside at the elections.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The one to whom this duty did not fall
                        was to be prepared to take the legions wherever they were needed beyond the
                        shores of Italy. He was empowered to raise two fresh legions as well as
                        20,000 infantry and 800 cavalry from the Latins and allied States.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The two legions which L. Cornelius had
                        as consul the year before were assigned to the other consul, together with
                        15,000 allied infantry and 500 cavalry drawn from the same army. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Q. Minucius retained his command and the army
                        which he had in Liguria. and was ordered to bring it up to full strength by
                        raising 4000 Roman infantry and 150 cavalry, whilst the allies were to
                        furnish him with 5000 infantry and 250 cavalry. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The duty of taking the legions wherever the senate
                        thought fit outside Italy fell to Cn. Domitius; L. Quinctius obtained Gaul
                        as his province and also the conduct of the elections. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The result of the balloting amongst the praetors was as
                        follows: M. Fulvius Centumanus received the civic and L. Scribonius Libo the
                        alien jurisdiction; L. Valerius Tappo drew Sicily; Q. Salonius Sarra,
                        Sardinia; M. Baebius Tamphilus, Hither Spain; A. Atilius Serranus, Further
                        Spain. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two latter, however, had their
                        commands transferred first by a resolution of the senate and then by a
                        confirmatory resolution of the plebs; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A.
                        Atilius had the fleet and Macedonia assigned to him, and Baebius was
                        appointed to the command in Bruttium. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Flaminius and Fulvius were left in command in the two Spains. Baebius
                        received for his operations in Bruttium the two legions which had previously
                        been quartered in the City and also 15,000 infantry and 500 cavalry to be
                        supplied by the allies. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Atilius was
                        ordered to construct 30 quinqueremes, to take from the dockyards any old
                        ships that might be serviceable and to impress crews. The consuls were
                        required to supply him with 1000 Roman and 2000 allied infantry. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> It was stated that these two praetors with their
                        land and sea armies were to act against Nabis who was now openly attacking
                        the allies of Rome. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The arrival of the
                        commissioners who had been sent to Antiochus was, however, expected, and the
                        senate forbade Cn. Domitius to leave the City till they returned. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The praetors Fulvius and Scribonius, whose
                        department was the administration of justice, were charged with the task of
                        fitting out 100 quinqueremes in addition to the fleet which Atilius was to
                        command. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Before the consul and the
                        praetors left to take up their appointments solemn intercessions were made
                        on account of various portents. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A report
                        came from Picenum that a she-goat had produced six kids at one birth; at
                        Arretium a boy had been born with only one hand; at Amiternum there was a
                        shower of earth; at Formiae the wall and one of the gates were struck with
                        lightning. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the most appalling report
                        was that an ox belonging to Cn. Domitius had uttered the words "Roma, cave
                        tibi" ("Rome, be on thy guard!"). <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With
                        respect to the other portents public supplications were offered up, but in
                        the case of the ox the haruspices ordered it to be carefully kept and fed.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The flooded Tiber made a more serious
                        attack upon the City than in the previous year and destroyed two bridges and
                        numerous buildings, most of them in the neighbourhood of the Porta
                        Flumentana. A huge mass of rock, undermined either by the heavy rains or by
                        an earthquake not felt at the time, fell from the Capitol into the Vicus
                        Jugarius and crushed a number of people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        In the country districts cattle and sheep were carried off by the floods in
                        all directions and many farmhouses were laid in ruins. Before the consul L.
                        Quinctius reached his province Q. Minucius fought a pitched battle with the
                        Ligurians near Pisae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He killed 9000 of
                        the enemy and drove the rest in flight to their camp, which was attacked and
                        defended with furious fighting until nightfall. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> During the night the Ligurians stole away in silence,
                        and at daybreak the Romans entered the deserted camp. They found less
                        plunder than might have been expected, as the Ligurians made a practice of
                        sending what they seized in the fields to their homes. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> After this Minucius gave them no respite; advancing
                        from Pisae he laid waste their fortified villages and homesteads, and the
                        Roman soldiers loaded themselves with the plunder which the Ligurians
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> had carried off from Etruria and
                        sent to their homes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just about this time the commissioners
                        returned from their visit to the kings. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The intelligence they brought back disclosed no grounds for immediate
                        hostilities except in the case of the tyrant of Lacedaemon, who, as the
                        Achaean delegates also stated, was attacking the coastal district of
                        Lacedaemon in defiance of the treaty. Atilius was sent with the fleet to
                        Greece to protect the allies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As there was
                        no pressing danger from Antiochus, it was decided that both the consuls
                        should start for their provinces. Domitius marched against the Boii from
                        Ariminium, the nearest point, Quinctius made his advance through Liguria.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The two armies on their respective
                        routes devastated the country far and wide. A few of the Boian cavalry with
                        their officers went over to the Romans, they were followed by all the older
                        men, and at last every man of rank or wealth, up to the number of 500,
                        deserted to the consul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans were
                        successful in both the Spanish provinces this year. C. Flaminius laid siege
                        to and captured Licabrum, a wealthy and strongly fortified place, and took
                        as prisoner Conribilo, a chieftain of high rank. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The proconsul, M. Fulvius, fought two successful
                        actions and stormed many fortified places, together with two towns, Vescelia
                        and Helo; others surrendered voluntarily. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Then he marched against the Oretani, and after becoming master of two towns,
                        Noliba and Cusibis, he advanced as far as the Tagus. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Here there was a small but strongly fortified city,
                        Toletum, and whilst he was attacking it the Vettones sent a large army to
                        relieve it. Fulvius defeated them in a pitched battle, and after putting
                        them to rout invested and captured the place. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These actual wars, however, preoccupied
                        the thoughts of the senate far less than the threatening prospect of war
                        with Antiochus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Although they received
                        from time to time full information through their commissioners, there were
                        vague and unauthorised rumours afloat in which truth was largely blended
                        with falsehood. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Amongst other things it
                        was reported that as soon as Antiochus reached Aetolia he would send his
                        fleet on to Sicily. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Atilius had already
                        been sent with his fleet to Greece, but as the senate, if it <milestone
                            n="5??" unit="section"/> was to retain its hold upon the friendly
                        States, was bound to assert its authority as well as send troops, T.
                        Quinctius, Cn. Octavius, Cn. Servilius and P. Villius were despatched on a
                        special mission to Greece, and a decree was made ordering M. Baebius to
                        transfer his legions from Bruttium to Tarentum and Brundisium, and if
                        circumstances made it necessary transport them to Macedonia. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> M. Fulvius was ordered to send a fleet of twenty
                        ships to protect Sicily, its commander to possess full powers. The command
                        was vested in L. Oppius Salinator; he had been plebeian aedile the previous
                        year. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Fulvius was also to send to his
                        colleague L. Valerius and inform him <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        that fears were entertained of Antiochus sending his fleet to Sicily, and
                        the senate had therefore decided that he should strengthen his army by
                        raising an emergency force of 12,000 foot and 400 horse for the defence of
                        that part of the Sicilian coast which faced Greece. The praetor took the men
                        for the force from the adjacent islands as well as from Sicily itself, and
                        placed garrisons in all the towns on the eastern coast. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> These rumours were strengthened by the arrival of
                        Attalus, the brother of Eumenes, who brought word that Antiochus had
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> crossed the Hellespont with his
                        army, and that the Aetolians, who were thoroughly prepared, were in arms
                        immediately on his arrival. Thanks were formally accorded to Eumenes as well
                        as to Attalus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The latter was treated as
                        the guest of the State and suitably lodged; he was also presented with two
                        horses, two sets of equestrian armour, silver vases up to a hundred and gold
                        vases up to twenty pounds' weight. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As messenger after messenger brought word
                        that war was imminent, it was felt to be a matter of importance that the
                        consular elections should take place at as early a date as possible.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate therefore resolved that M.
                        Fulvius should at once write to the consul informing him that the senate
                        wished him to hand over his command to his staff and return to Rome.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On his way he was to send on his edict
                        giving notice of the consular elections. The consul carried out these
                        instructions and returned to Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There
                        was a keen contest this year, as three patricians were competing for the one
                        vacancy, namely P. Cornelius Scipio, the son of Cn. Scipio, who had been
                        defeated the previous year; L. Cornelius Scipio, and Cn. Manlius Volso.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As a proof that the honour had only
                        been deferred and not refused to a man of his eminence, the consulship was
                        bestowed on P. Scipio and the plebeian who was assigned to him as colleague
                        was Manius Acilius Glabrio. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Those who were
                        elected as praetors the next day were L. Aemilius Paullus, M. Aemilius
                        Lepidus, M. Junius Brutus, A. Cornelius Mammula, C. Livius and L. Oppius,
                        the two latter both having the cognomen Salinator. Oppius was in command of
                        the fleet of twenty sail which had gone to Sicily. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst the new magistrates were balloting for their
                        respective provinces Baebius received instructions to sail with the whole of
                        his force from Brundisium to Epirus and to remain near Apollonia; <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> M. Fulvius was commissioned to construct fifty
                        new quinqueremes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the Roman Government were thus
                        preparing to check any attempt on the part of Antiochus, <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> Nabis was already pushing on hostilities and devoting
                        his whole strength to the investment of Gytheum. The Achaeans had sent
                        succour to the besieged city, and in revenge he devastated their territory.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They did not venture upon open
                        hostilities till their delegates had returned from Rome and they had learnt
                        the decision of the senate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On their
                        return they summoned a council to meet at Sicyon and sent to ask T.
                        Quinctius to advise them as to what they ought to do. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The members of the council were unanimously in favour
                        of immediate action, but when a letter was read from T. Quinctius in which
                        he advised them to wait for the Roman praetor and the fleet there was some
                        hesitation felt. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some of the leaders
                        adhered to their opinion, others thought that after consulting T. Quinctius
                        they ought to act on his advice. The great majority, however, waited to hear
                        what line Philopoemen would take. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He was
                        at the time their chief magistrate, and surpassed all his contemporaries in
                        sound common sense and force of character. He began by commending the wisdom
                        of the regulation which the Achaeans had adopted forbidding their chief
                        magistrate to express his own view when the discussion turned on war.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then urged them to come to a speedy
                        decision as to what they wanted; their chief magistrate would carry out
                        their decision faithfully and carefully, and as far as human wisdom could
                        avail would do his utmost to prevent their regretting it whether it were in
                        favour of peace or war. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This speech did
                        more to incite them to war than if he had betrayed his desire for it by open
                        advocacy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The council passed a unanimous
                        vote in favour of hostilities, but left the date and conduct of operations
                        absolutely to the chief magistrate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Philopoemen himself was of the opinion which Quinctius had already
                        expressed, that they ought to wait for the Roman fleet which could protect
                        Gytheum by sea, but he was afraid that <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                        the position did not admit of delay and that not only Gytheum but also the
                        force sent to defend it might be lost. Accordingly, he ordered the Achaean
                        vessels to put to sea. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The tyrant had, as one of the conditions
                        of peace, surrendered his old fleet to the Romans, but he had collected a
                        small naval force, consisting of three decked ships with some barques and
                        despatch-boats, to prevent any assistance reaching the besieged city by sea.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In order to test the hardiness of
                        these new vessels and make everything fit for battle, he made them put out
                        to sea every day, and the sailors and soldiers were exercised in sham
                        fights, for he regarded the prospect of a successful siege as dependent upon
                        his intercepting all relief attempted by sea. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Though the chief magistrate of the Achaeans could vie
                        with the most famous commanders in military skill and experience he was
                        totally inexperienced in naval matters. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He
                        was a native of Arcadia, an inland country, and knew nothing of the outside
                        world with the exception of Crete where he had commanded a force of
                        auxiliary troops. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was an old
                        quadrireme which had been captured eighty years ago when it was conveying
                        Nicaea, the wife of Craterus, from Naupactus to Corinth. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Attracted by what he had heard of this ship-for it had
                        been in its day a famous unit of the royal fleet-he ordered it to be brought
                        from Aegium, though it was now very rotten and its timbers were parting
                        through age. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Whilst this vessel, with
                        Tisus of Patrae, the fleet commander, on board, was leading the armament it
                        was met by the Lacedaemonian ships which were coming from Gytheum.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the very first shock against a new
                        and firm ship the old vessel, which was leaking at every joint, completely
                        broke up and all on board were made prisoners. The rest of the fleet, after
                        seeing the commander's vessel lost, fled away as fast as their oars could
                        carry them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Philopoemen himself escaped in
                        a light scouting boat and did not end his flight till he had reached Patrae.
                        This incident did not in the least depress the spirits of a man who was a
                        thorough soldier and had had a very chequered experience; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> on the contrary, he declared that if he had made an
                        unfortunate mistake in naval matters of which he knew nothing he had all the
                        more reason to hope for success in things with which experience had made him
                        thoroughly familiar, and he promised that he would make the tyrant's
                        rejoicing over his victory a short-lived one. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Greatly elated by his victory, Nabis felt
                        no further apprehension of danger from the sea, and he now decided to close
                        all access on the land side by an effective disposition of his troops.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He withdrew a third of the army which
                        was investing Gytheum and encamped at Pleiae in a position which commanded
                        both Leucae and Acriae, as the enemy would probably advance in that
                        direction. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Only a few of the troops in
                        this camp had tents, the mass of the soldiers constructed wattled huts with
                        reeds and leafy branches to shelter them from the sun. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Before he came within sight of the enemy Philopoemen
                        decided to make a novel kind of attack and take him unawares. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Collecting some small craft in a secluded creek
                        on the Argive coast he manned them with light infantry, mostly caetrati, who
                        were armed with slings and darts and other light equipment. Sailing close
                        inshore he reached a headland near the enemy's camp, where he disembarked
                        his men and made a night march to Patrae along paths with which he was
                        familiar. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The enemy's sentinels, fearing
                        no immediate danger, were asleep and Philopoemen's men flung burning brands
                        on the huts from every side of the camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Many perished in the fire before they were aware of the enemy's presence,
                        and those who had become aware of it were unable to render any assistance.
                        Between fire and sword the destruction was complete, very <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> few escaped death from the one or the other, and those
                        who did escape fled to the camp before Gytheum. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Immediately after dealing this blow to the enemy
                        Philopoemen led his force to Tripolis in Laconia, close to the Megalopolitan
                        territory, and before the tyrant could send troops from Gytheum to protect
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the fields, he succeeded in
                        carrying off a vast quantity of booty both in men and cattle. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He then assembled the army of the league
                        at Tegea and also convened a special meeting of the Achaeans and their
                        allies at which the leading men from Epirus and Acarnania were present.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As his troops were now sufficiently
                        recovered from the humiliation of their naval defeat and the enemy were
                        correspondingly depressed he decided to march on Lacedaemon, as that seemed
                        the only means of drawing off the enemy from the siege of Gytheum. His first
                        halt on enemy territory was at Caryae, and on the very day he encamped here
                        Gytheum was taken. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Unaware of what had
                        happened he continued his advance as far as Barnosthenes, a mountain ten
                        miles distant from Lacedaemon. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> After
                        taking Gytheum Nabis returned with his army equipped for rapid marching, and
                        hurrying past Lacedaemon he seized a position known as Pyrrhus' Camp, which
                        he felt quite certain that the Achaeans were making for. From there he
                        advanced to meet them. Owing to the narrowness of the road they extended in
                        a column nearly five miles long. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The
                        cavalry and the greater part of the auxiliary troops were in the hinder part
                        of the column, as Philopoemen thought that the tyrant would probably attack
                        his rear with the mercenaries, on whom he mainly depended. Two unexpected
                        circumstances occurred which gave Philopoemen cause for anxiety; the
                        position he had hoped to secure was already occupied and he saw that the
                        enemy were intending to attack the head of the column. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> He did not see how it was possible for his hoplites to
                        advance in battle order over such broken ground without the support of the
                        light troops. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philopoemen possessed exceptional skill in
                        the conduct of a march and the selection of positions; he had made these the
                        objects of special attention in peace as well as in war. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> It was his habit, when he was travelling and had come
                        to a mountain pass difficult to traverse, to study the ground in all
                        directions. If he was alone he would think the matter over, if he were
                        accompanied he would ask those with him what they would do if an enemy
                        showed himself there, what tactics they would employ according as the attack
                        was made upon their front, or on either flank or on their rear; <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> the enemy in battle order might possibly come
                        upon them whilst they were deployed for action or possibly whilst they were
                        in column of march, unprepared for attack. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        He used to think out for himself and question others as to some position
                        which he intended to secure, what numbers and what weapons-for these
                        differed considerably-he ought to employ; where he ought to deposit the
                        baggage and the soldiers' kits; where the non-combatants ought to be placed;
                        what ought to be the strength and nature of the baggage guard; <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> and whether it would be better to go forward or
                        for the army to retrace its steps. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He used
                        also to consider very carefully the sites he ought to select for his camp,
                        the amount of ground to be enclosed, the supply of water, fodder and wood,
                        the safest route to take on the morrow and the best formation in which to
                        march. He had exercised his mind on these problems from earliest manhood to
                        such an extent that there was no device for meeting them with which he was
                        not familiar. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the present occasion he
                        first of all halted the column, and then sent up to the front the Cretan
                        auxiliaries and the so-called Tarentine horse, and the rest of the cavalry
                        were ordered to follow them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then took
                        possession of a rock which overhung a mountain torrent, so that he might
                        have a water supply. Here he collected the camp-followers and the whole of
                        the baggage and surrounded them with a guard. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> His entrenchments were such as the nature of the
                        position allowed, and the setting up of the tents on such rough and uneven
                        ground presented considerable difficulty. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The enemy were half a mile distant, both sides watered at the same stream
                        under the protection of the light infantry, and as usually happens when the
                        camps are near one another, night intervened before the forces engaged. It
                        was quite certain, however, that there would be a battle between the
                        detachments who were guarding <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> the
                        water-carriers, and in view of this Philopoemen during the night posted in a
                        valley out of the enemy's view as large a force of his caetrati as the
                        ground would conceal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At daybreak the Cretan light infantry and
                        the Tarentines commenced an action on the river bank; Telemnastus of Crete
                        commanding his countrymen, and Lycortas of Megalopolis the cavalry.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The enemy, too, had Cretan auxiliaries
                        and Tarentine horse covering their watering-parties, and as the same class
                        of troops were fighting with the same weapons on either side the issue was
                        for some time doubtful. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As the action
                        proceeded the tyrant's troops proved superior owing to their numbers, and
                        moreover Philopoemen had instructed his officers to offer only a slight
                        resistance and then pretend to flee and so draw the enemy on to the spot
                        where his ambush was set. As the enemy became disordered in the pursuit, a
                        great many were killed and wounded before they caught sight of their hidden
                        foe. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The caetrati were crouching in the
                        best formation that the narrow space admitted of, and the intervals between
                        their companies allowed their own fugitives to pass through. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Then they sprang up fresh and vigorous, in
                        perfect order, to attack an enemy who, scattered in disorderly pursuit, were
                        also exhausted by the strain of fighting and the wounds which many of them
                        had received. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The result was decisive, the
                        soldiers of the tyrant turned and fled at a much greater speed than when
                        they were the pursuers, and were driven into their camp. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Many were killed or made prisoners in the flight, and
                        the camp itself would have been in great danger had not Philopoemen sounded
                        the "retire." He feared the broken ground, so dangerous to any who advanced
                        without caution, more than he feared the enemy. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> From his knowledge of the tyrant's character
                        Philopoemen guessed what a state of alarm he would be in after this battle
                        and sent one of his men to him in the guise of a deserter. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> This man told him that he had found out that the
                        Achaeans intended to advance the following day to the Eurotas-this river
                        almost washes the walls of Lacedaemon-in order to intercept him and prevent
                        him from withdrawing into the city and also stop supplies from being
                        conveyed from the city to the camp. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They
                        also, he told him, were going to try and create a rising against him amongst
                        the citizens. Though the deserter's story was not fully accepted it afforded
                        the tyrant, now thoroughly frightened, a plausible excuse for quitting his
                        present position. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He gave Pythagoras
                        instructions to remain the next day on guard before the camp with the
                        cavalry and auxiliaries <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> whilst he
                        himself, with the main strength of his army, marched out as though for
                        action and gave the standard-bearers orders to quicken their pace and make
                        for the city. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Philopoemen saw them moving hurriedly
                        along a steep and narrow road he sent his Cretan auxiliaries and the whole
                        of his cavalry against the force which was guarding the camp. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Seeing the enemy approaching, and finding that
                        the main army had left them to themselves, they tried to retire into their
                        camp, but as the entire Achaean army was advancing in battle order they
                        dreaded <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> lest they should be captured
                        with their camp, and accordingly started after their main body which was
                        some distance ahead. The Achaean caetrati at once attacked and plundered the
                        camp, whilst the rest of the army went off in pursuit of the enemy.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The route they had taken was such that
                        even if there had been no enemy to be feared, their column could only have
                        got through with great difficulty, but now, when the rearmost ranks were
                        being assailed and cries of terror penetrated to the head of the column, it
                        was every man for himself; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> they flung away
                        their arms and fled into the forest which skirted the road on both sides. In
                        an instant the road was blocked with heaps of weapons, mostly spears, which,
                        falling with their heads towards the enemy, formed a kind of stockade across
                        the road. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Philopoemen ordered the
                        auxiliaries to press the pursuit as much as possible, since flight would be
                        a difficult matter, for cavalry at all events. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The heavy infantry he led in person by a more open road
                        to the Eurotas. Here he encamped just before sunset and waited for the light
                        troops whom he had left in pursuit of the enemy. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> They came in at the first watch with the news that the
                        tyrant had entered the city with a small body of troops; the rest of his
                        army were without arms, scattered in the forest. He told them to take food
                        and rest. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The rest of the army, having
                        come earlier into camp, had already done so and were now refreshed after a
                        short sleep. Selecting some of their number and telling them to take nothing
                        but their swords, he posted them on two of the roads which led from the
                        city, one to Pharae and the other to Barnosthenes, as he expected that the
                        fugitives would return by these roads. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        His expectation was justified, for the Lacedaemonians as long as daylight
                        remained went along the sequestered tracks in the heart of the forest, but
                        when it grew dusk and they caught sight of the lights in the enemy's camp
                        they kept out of sight on hidden paths. After they had got past it, and
                        thought all was safe, they came out into the open road. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Here they were caught by the enemy who were waiting for
                        them, and so numerous were the prisoners and the slain in all directions
                        that hardly a quarter of their whole army escaped. Now that Philopoemen had
                        shut the tyrant up in his city he spent nearly a month in devastating the
                        Lacedaemonian fields, and after thus weakening and almost shattering the
                        tyrant's power he returned home. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        Achaeans in view of his brilliant success put him on a par with the Roman
                        general, and considered him as his superior so far as the Laconian war was
                        concerned. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .While this war between the Achaeans and
                        the tyrant was going on the Roman envoys were visiting the cities of their
                        allies, for they felt some apprehension lest the Aetolians might have
                        induced some of them to go over to Antiochus. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> They did not trouble themselves much about the
                        Achaeans; as they were in declared hostility to Nabis it was thought that
                        they might be depended upon throughout. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Athens was the first place they visited, from there they proceeded to
                        Chalcis, and thence to Thessaly, where they addressed a largely attended
                        council of the Thessalians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They then went
                        on to Demetrias, where a council of the Magnetes was assembled. Here they
                        had to be careful as to what they said, for some of the leading men were in
                        opposition to Rome and gave wholehearted support to Antiochus and the
                        Aetolians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their attitude was due to the
                        fact that when it was learnt that Philip's son, who had been detained as a
                        hostage, was released and the tribute imposed upon him remitted, it was
                        stated, amongst other false rumours, that the Romans intended to restore
                        Demetrias to him also. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Rather than let
                        that happen Eurylochus, the president of the Magnetes, and some of his party
                        were anxious that the arrival of Antiochus and the Aetolians should bring
                        about a complete change of policy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In
                        meeting this hostile spirit the Roman envoys had to be on their guard lest
                        while removing this groundless suspicion they should so far destroy
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> Philip's hopes as to make an enemy
                        of a man who was for every reason of more importance to them than the
                        Magnetes were. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The envoys confined
                        themselves to pointing out that the whole of Greece was under obligations to
                        Rome for the boon of liberty, Magnesia so especially. Not only had a
                        Macedonian garrison been stationed there, but Philip had built a palace
                        there so that they were forced to have their lord and master always before
                        their eyes. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But all that Rome had done
                        for them would be useless if the Aetolians brought Antiochus into that
                        palace and they had to have a new unknown king in place of one whom they had
                        known and had experience of. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Their supreme magistrate was called
                        "Magnetarch," and Eurylochus was holding that office at the time. Feeling
                        secure in the power which his office gave him, he said that he and the
                        Magnetes could not be silent about the report which was widely current that
                        Demetrias was to be given back to Philip. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        To prevent this the Magnetes were prepared to make every effort and face
                        every danger. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Carried away by excitement
                        he threw out the ill-advised remark that even then Demetrias was only free
                        in appearance, in reality everything was at the nod and beck of Rome. These
                        words were received with murmurs and protests; some in the assembly
                        approved, but others were filled with indignation at his having dared to
                        speak in that way. As for Quinctius, he was so angry that he lifted up his
                        hands towards heaven and called upon the gods to witness the ingratitude and
                        perfidy of the Magnetes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> This exclamation
                        created universal alarm and Zeno, one of their leading men, who had gained
                        great influence amongst them, partly by the refinement which characterised
                        his private life and partly because he had always been a staunch friend to
                        Rome, implored Quinctius and other envoys not to make the whole city
                        responsible for one man's madness; it was at his own risk that anyone
                        behaved like a madman. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The Magnetes were
                        indebted to Titus Quinctius and the Roman people for more than their
                        liberty-for everything, in fact, which men hold dear and sacred; there was
                        nothing which a man could ask the gods to give him that they had not
                        received from them. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> They would sooner lay
                        frenzied hands upon themselves than violate their friendship with Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .His speech was followed by urgent
                        entreaties from the whole assembly. Eurylochus left hurriedly, and making
                        his way secretly to the city gate fled to Aetolia, for the Aetolians were
                        now throwing off the mask more and more every day from their hostile
                        intentions. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thoas, the foremost man
                        amongst them, happened to return from his mission to Antiochus just at this
                        time, bringing with him an envoy from the king in the person of Menippus.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Before the meeting of the national
                        council these two men had filled all ears with descriptions of the land and
                        sea forces which Antiochus had collected. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        They declared that a great host of infantry and cavalry were on their way,
                        elephants had been brought from India and-what they thought would most of
                        all impress the popular mind-he was bringing gold enough to buy up the
                        Romans themselves. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was obvious what
                        effect this sort of talk would have on the council, for their arrival and
                        all their proceedings were duly reported to the Roman envoy. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Although events had almost taken a decisive turn,
                        Quinctius thought it might not be altogether useless if some representatives
                        of the friendly cities attended the council who would have the courage to
                        speak frankly in reply to the king's envoy and remind the Aetolians of their
                        treaty engagements with Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        Athenians seemed best fitted for the task on account of the prestige which
                        their city enjoyed and also because of their old alliance with the
                        Aetolians. Quinctius therefore requested them to send delegates to the
                        Pan-Aetolian Council. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thoas opened the proceedings by giving a
                        report of his negotiations. He was followed by Menippus, who asserted that
                        the best thing for all the peoples of Greece and Asia would have been for
                        Antiochus to have intervened whilst Philip's power was still unimpaired,
                        everyone <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> would then have kept what
                        belonged to him, and everything would not have been completely at the mercy
                        of Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "Even now," he continued, "if
                        only you resolutely carry out the designs you have formed, he will be able
                        with the help of the gods and the assistance of the Aetolians to restore the
                        fortunes of Greece, drooping though they are, to their old place in the
                        world. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That, however, must rest on
                        liberty, and a liberty which stands in its own strength and is not dependent
                        on the will of another." <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Athenians,
                        who had received permission to speak their minds after the king's delegate,
                        made no allusion to the king, but simply reminded the Aetolians of their
                        alliance with Rome and the services which T. Quinctius had rendered to the
                        whole of Greece. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They warned them against
                        wrecking that friendship by hasty and precipitate action; bold and
                        hot-headed counsels were attractive at first sight, difficult to put into
                        practice, disastrous in their results. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        The Roman envoys and Quinctius himself were not far away, it would be better
                        to discuss the question at issue in friendly debate than to throw Europe and
                        Asia into a deadly struggle of arms. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The great mass of the assembly, eager for
                        a change of policy, were wholly on the side of Antiochus and were even
                        opposed to admitting the Romans into the council. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Mainly, however, through the influence of the elders
                        amongst their leading men, it was decided that a meeting of the council
                        should be summoned to hear them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the
                        Athenians returned and reported this decision Quinctius felt that he ought
                        to go to Aetolia, as he might do something to change their purpose, if not
                        the whole world would see that the responsibility for the war rested solely
                        on the Aetolians and that Rome was taking up arms in a just and necessary
                        cause. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Quinctius began his address to the
                        council by tracing the history of the league between the Aetolians and Rome
                        and pointing out how frequently they had infringed its provisions.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then dealt briefly with the rights
                        of the cities which were the subject of controversy and showed how much
                        better it would be, if they thought they had a fair case, to <milestone
                            n="6??" unit="section"/> send a deputation to Rome to argue their cause
                        or bring it before the senate, whichever they preferred, instead of a war
                        between Rome and Antiochus at the instigation of the Aetolians, a war which
                        would create a world-wide disturbance and utterly ruin Greece. None would
                        feel the fatal result of such a war sooner than those who set it in motion.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Roman was a true prophet, but he
                        spoke in vain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Without allowing time for
                        deliberation by adjourning the council or even waiting for the Romans to
                        retire, Thoas and the rest of his supporters got a decree passed amidst the
                        cheers of the assembly for inviting Antiochus to give liberty to Greece and
                        arbitrate between the Romans and the Aetolians. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The insolence of this decree was aggravated by the
                        personal effrontery of Damocritus their chief magistrate. When Quinctius
                        asked him for a copy of the decree, Damocritus, without the slightest regard
                        for his official position, told him that a more pressing matter demanded his
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> immediate attention, he would
                        shortly give him his reply and the decree from his camps in Italy on the
                        banks of the Tiber. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such was the madness
                        which at that time possessed the Aetolians and their magistrates. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius and the other legates returned
                        to Corinth. The Aetolians, who were continually receiving intelligence about
                        Antiochus' movements, wished to make it appear that they were doing nothing
                        themselves and simply waiting for his arrival; consequently they did not
                        hold a council of the whole league after the Romans had left. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Through their "Apokleti," however-the designation
                        they give to their inner council-they were discussing the best means of
                        effecting a revolution in Greece. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was
                        everywhere understood that the leading men and the aristocracy in the
                        various States were partisans of Rome and perfectly contented with things as
                        they were, whilst the mass of the populations and all whose circumstances
                        were not what they wished them to be were eager for change. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> On the day of their meeting the Aetolians decided upon
                        a project alike audacious and impudent, namely the occupation of Demetrias,
                        Chalcis and Lacedaemon. One of their leaders was sent to each of these
                        cities: Thoas went to Chalcis, Alexamenus to Lacedaemon, Diocles to
                        Demetrias. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Eurylochus, whose flight and
                        the reason for it have been already described, <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> came to the assistance of Diocles, as in no other way
                        did he see any prospect of returning home. He wrote to his friends and
                        relatives and the members of his party, and they brought his wife and
                        children dressed in mourning and carrying suppliant emblems into the
                        assembly, which was crowded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They appealed
                        to those present individually and implored the assembly as a whole not to
                        allow a man innocent and uncondemned to waste his life in exile. The simple
                        and unsuspecting were moved by pity, the evil-minded and seditious by the
                        prospect of profiting by the confusion which the Aetolian agitation would
                        cause. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Everyone voted for his recall. This
                        preparatory step having been taken, Diocles, who was at that time in command
                        of the cavalry, started with the whole of his force, ostensibly to escort
                        the exile home. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He covered an immense
                        distance, marching through the day and the night, and when he was six miles
                        from the city he went on in advance at daybreak with three picked troops,
                        the rest being under orders to follow. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As
                        they approached the gate he bade his men dismount and lead their horses as
                        though they were accompanying their commander on his journey instead of
                        acting as a military force. Leaving one troop at the gate to prevent the
                        cavalry who were coming up from being shut out, he took Eurylochus, holding
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> him by the hand, through the heart
                        of the city and the forum to his house amidst the congratulations of many
                        who came to meet them. In a short time the city was filled with cavalry-and
                        the commanding positions were seized. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Then parties were told off to go to the houses of the leaders of the
                        opposition and put them to death. In this way Demetrias was gained by the
                        Aetolians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Against the city of Lacedaemon no force
                        was to be employed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The tyrant was to be
                        caught by treachery. After being despoiled of his maritime towns by the
                        Romans and now actually shut up within his walls by the Achaeans, it was
                        taken for granted that whoever was the first to kill him would win the
                        gratitude of the Lacedaemonians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        Aetolians had a good excuse for sending to him, for he had been insistently
                        demanding that help should be sent to him by those at whose instigation he
                        had recommenced war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Alexamenus was
                        supplied with 1000 infantry and 30 men selected from the cavalry. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> These latter had been solemnly warned by
                        Damocritus in the Inner Council, which is described above, not to suppose
                        that they were sent to fight against the Achaeans or for any purpose which
                        they might fix upon in their own minds. Whatever plan circumstances might
                        compel Alexamenus suddenly to adopt, that plan, however unexpected,
                        hazardous or daring it might be, they must be prepared to execute with
                        unquestioning obedience, and they must so regard it as though it were the
                        only object which they had been sent from home to accomplish. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> With these men thus primed Alexamenus went to the
                        tyrant, and his visit at once filled him with hope. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He told him that Antiochus had already landed in Europe
                        and would soon be in Greece, he would cover sea and land with arms and men;
                        the Romans would find out that it was not with Philip that they had to deal;
                        the numbers of his infantry and cavalry and ships could not be counted; the
                        mere sight of the line of elephants would bring the war to a close.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He assured him that the Aetolians were
                        prepared to go to Lacedaemon with the whole of their army when circumstances
                        demanded, but they wanted Antiochus to see a considerable body of their
                        troops on his arrival. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He also advised
                        Nabis to be careful not to let the troops which he still had become
                        enervated through idleness and an indoor life; he should take them out and
                        by exercising them under arms make them keener and hardier; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> the toil and exertion would become lighter by
                        practice, and their commander could make it far from distasteful by his
                        geniality and kindness. </p>
                    <p> From that time they were frequently marched out to the plain stretching from
                        the city to the Eurotas. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The tyrant's
                        bodyguard were usually in the centre of the line; he himself with three
                        horsemen at the most, of whom Alexamenus was generally one, rode along the
                        front of the standards to inspect the wings. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> On the right were the Aetolians, including the
                        auxiliaries and the thousand who had come with Alexamenus. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Alexamenus had made a practice of accompanying the
                        tyrant during his inspection through a few of the ranks, making such
                        suggestions as seemed called for, and then riding up to the Aetolians on the
                        right and giving them the necessary instructions, after which he returned to
                        the side of the tyrant. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But on the day
                        which he had fixed for carrying out his deadly project he only accompanied
                        the tyrant for a short time, and then withdrawing to his own men addressed
                        the thirty picked troopers in these terms: <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                        /> "Young men, you have to dare and do the deed which you are under orders
                        to carry out at my bidding. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Be ready with
                        heart and hand, and let no one falter at what he sees me doing; whoever
                        hesitates and crosses my purpose with his own may be sure that there is no
                        return home for him." <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Horror seized them
                        all; they remembered the instructions with which they had come. <milestone
                            n="18" unit="section"/> The tyrant was riding up from his left wing,
                        Alexamenus ordered them to level their lances and watch him; even he himself
                        had to collect his thoughts, bewildered as he was at the contemplation of
                        such a desperate deed. When the tyrant came near he made an attack upon him
                        and speared his horse. The tyrant was flung off, and whilst he lay on the
                        ground the troopers thrust at him with their lances. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> Many of their thrusts were warded off by his cuirass,
                        but at last they reached his body, and he expired before he could be rescued
                        by his bodyguard. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Alexamenus went off with all the Aetolians
                        at the double to take possession of the palace. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst the assassination was going on before their eyes
                        they were too frightened to move; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> when
                        they saw the Aetolian contingent hurrying away they ran to the abandoned
                        body of the tyrant, but instead of bodyguards and avengers of his death,
                        they were merely a crowd of spectators. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                        fact, not a single man would have offered any resistance had Alexamenus,
                        laying aside his arms, called the whole army to attention and made an
                        address such as the situation required, keeping a considerable body of
                        Aetolians under arms and injuring no one. But what ought to happen in every
                        act begun by treachery happened here; the affair was so managed as to hasten
                        the destruction of all the actors in it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The general, shutting himself up in the palace, spent a whole day and night
                        in examining the royal <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> treasures, the
                        Aetolians took to looting as though they had captured the city of which they
                        wished to appear as the liberators. The indignation this aroused and a
                        feeling of contempt for the scanty number of Aetolians gave the
                        Lacedaemonians courage to unite together. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Some advised that the Aetolians should be driven out and the liberty
                        snatched from them just when it seemed to be restored, asserted and made
                        secure. Others thought that one of the royal blood should be chosen as the
                        ostensible head of the movement. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There was
                        a scion of the old royal house called Laconicus who had been brought up with
                        the tyrant's children; they put him on horseback, and seizing their arms
                        slew the Aetolians who were strolling about the city. Then they forced their
                        way into the palace and killed Alexamenus, who with a few of his men offered
                        an ineffectual resistance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some of the
                        Aetolians had collected together at the Chalcioecon-a bronze temple of
                        Minerva-and were all killed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A few flung
                        away their arms and fled to Tegea and Megalopolis. Here they were arrested
                        by the magistrates and sold as slaves. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On hearing of the tyrant's death
                        Philopoemen went to Lacedaemon, where he found universal panic and
                        confusion. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He invited the principal men to
                        meet him, and after addressing them as Alexamenus ought to have done,
                        incorporated the city in the Achaean league. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> This was rendered all the easier by the fact that just at that time A.
                        Atilius arrived at Gytheum with four-and-twenty quinqueremes. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Thoas was far from meeting with the same success
                        at Chalcis as was achieved at Demetrias through the agency of Eurylochus. He
                        had enlisted the services of two men-Euthymidas, one of the leading men in
                        Chalcis who had been expelled through the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"
                        /> influence of the Roman party, strengthened by the visit of T. Quinctius
                        and the fleet, and Herodorus, a trader from Chios whose wealth gave him
                        considerable weight in the city. Through their instrumentality Thoas had
                        arranged with the adherents of Euthymidas to betray the city into his hands.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Euthymidas had taken up his residence
                        at Athens, from there he went to Thebes, and then on to Salganeus. Herodorus
                        went to Thronium. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Not far from this place
                        Thoas had a force of 2000 infantry and 200 cavalry, as well as thirty light
                        transports in the Maliac Gulf. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Herodorus
                        was to take these vessels with a complement of 600 infantry to the island of
                        Atalanta with the object of sailing across to Chalcis as soon as he learnt
                        that the land force was nearing Aulis and the Euripus. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Thoas himself marched with this force as rapidly as
                        possible, mostly by night, to Chalcis. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the expulsion of Euthymidas the
                        chief command was vested in Micythio and Xenoclides. Either suspecting what
                        was going on or having received information about it, they were at first in
                        a state of panic and thought that their only safety lay in flight, but
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> when their fears subsided and they
                        saw that they would be deserting not only their city but their alliance with
                        Rome, they thought out the following plan of operations. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> It so happened that the annual festival of Diana of
                        Amarynthis was being held at the time in Eretria, and this festival was
                        attended not only by the natives but also by the people of Carystus.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A deputation was sent from Chalcis to
                        beg the Eretrians and the Carystians to take compassion on those who were
                        born in the same island as themselves, to remember their alliance with Rome,
                        and not to allow Chalcis to pass into the hands of the Aetolians. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> If they held Chalcis they would hold Euboea; the
                        Macedonians had been harsh masters, the Aetolians would be much more
                        insupportable. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The two cities were
                        influenced mainly by their respect for the Romans, whose courage in the late
                        war as well as their justice and considerateness they had had practical
                        experience of. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Each city accordingly armed
                        and despatched all their fighting men. The Chalcidians left the defence of
                        their walls to them, and crossing the Euripus with their entire force fixed
                        their camp at Salganeus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From there they
                        sent first a herald and then delegates to the Aetolians to inquire what they
                        had done or said that their allies and friends should come to attack them.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thoas, who was in command, replied
                        that they were come not to attack them but to deliver them from the Romans.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "You are fettered," he said, "with
                        more glittering but also with heavier chains than when you had a Macedonian
                        garrison in your citadel." The Chalcidians declared that they were not in
                        bondage to any man, nor did they need any man's protection. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> They then left the conference and returned to
                        their camp. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thoas and the Aetolians had
                        placed all their hopes on taking the enemy by surprise, and as they were
                        unequal to a sustained conflict and the siege of a city powerfully protected
                        both by land and sea they returned home. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        When Euthymidas heard that his countrymen were encamped at Salganeus and
                        that the Aetolians had gone away he returned to Athens. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Herodorus after anxiously awaiting the signal from
                        Atalanta sent a despatch-boat to find out the cause of the delay, and when
                        he learnt that his associates had abandoned their enterprise he went back to
                        Thronium. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On hearing what had happened Quinctius on
                        his way from Corinth met Eumenes on the Euripus off Chalcis, and it was
                        arranged that <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Eumenes should leave 500
                        troops to protect Chalcis and go on to Athens. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Quinctius went on as he had started in the direction of
                        Demetrias, and judging that the liberation of Chalcis would do much towards
                        inducing the Magnetes to resume friendly relations with Rome, he wrote to
                        Eunomus, the chief magistrate of the Thessalians, asking him to put his
                        fighting men on a war footing as a support to the party of his adherents.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the same time he sent Villius to
                        sound the feeling of the populace, but not to attempt anything more unless
                        there were a large number who were inclined to restore the old friendly
                        relations. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He went in a quinquereme, and
                        had reached the harbour mouth when he found that the whole population had
                        poured out to see him. Villius asked them whether they preferred that he
                        should come to them as friends or as enemies. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Eurylochus, their chief magistrate, told him that he
                        had come to friends, but he must keep away from the harbour and allow the
                        Magnetes to live in harmony and liberty and not seduce the populace under
                        cover of a political discussion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This
                        started a hot dispute, not a conference, as the Roman envoy bitterly
                        reproached the Magnetes for their ingratitude and predicted the disasters
                        which would quickly overtake them, whilst the townsmen shouted out in reply
                        angry aspersions on the conduct of the senate and Quinctius. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Foiled in his attempt Villius returned to
                        Quinctius, who sent off a message to the praetor to disband his forces and
                        then returned to Corinth. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The affairs of Greece, involved as they
                        were with those of Rome, have carried me, so to speak, out of my course, not
                        because they were worth narrating in themselves, but because they brought
                        about the war with Antiochus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the
                        consular elections-for that was the point at which I digressed-the new
                        consuls, L. Quinctius and Cn. Domitius, left for their provinces, Quinctius
                        for Liguria and Domitius for the country of the Boii. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The Boii remained quiet, and even their senate with
                        their children and the cavalry commanders with their men, 1500 in all, made
                        a formal surrender to the consul. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        other consul devastated the Ligurian country far and wide, captured several
                        of their fortified posts and took from them not only prisoners and booty,
                        but also many of his fellow-citizens and members of the friendly States who
                        had been in the hands of the enemy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> During
                        the year the senate and people authorised the formation of a military colony
                        at Vibo; 3700 infantry and 300 cavalry were sent there. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The supervisors of the settlement were Q. Naevius, M.
                        Minucius and M. Furius Crassipes. Fifteen jugera were allotted to each
                        infantryman and double the number to the cavalry. The land had previously
                        belonged to the Bruttii, who had taken it from the Greeks. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> During this time two alarming incidents occurred in
                        Rome, one lasted longer than the other, but was less destructive. There were
                        earth tremors which went on for thirty-eight days, and during the whole of
                        the time business was suspended amidst general anxiety and alarm.
                        Intercessions were offered up for three successive days to avert the peril.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The other was no groundless alarm, it
                        was a widespread disaster. A fire broke out in the Forum Boarium; for a day
                        and a night the buildings fronting the Tiber were blazing and all the shops
                        with their valuable stocks were burnt out. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year was now almost at an end and the
                        rumours of hostile preparations on the part of Antiochus and the anxiety
                        these caused to the senate became graver day by day. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The discussion as to the assignment of provinces to the
                        new magistrates resulted in the senate decreeing <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> that one of the consular provinces should be Italy and
                        the other wherever the senate should decide, for it was already generally
                        understood that there would be war with Antiochus. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The one to whom this latter field of operations would
                        be allotted was to be furnished with 4000 Roman and 6000 allied infantry,
                        together with 300 Roman and 400 allied cavalry. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> L. Quinctius was instructed to raise this force so that
                        there might be no delay in the new consul proceeding at once wherever the
                        senate should think it necessary. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A
                        similar decree was made in the case of the praetors-elect. The first
                        balloting was for the two departments of civic and alien jurisdiction; the
                        second for Bruttium; the third for the command of the fleet, which was to be
                        sent wherever the senate should determine; the fourth for Sicily; the fifth
                        for Sardinia, and the sixth for Further Spain. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> L. Quinctius was also commanded to raise two new Roman
                        legions and an allied contingent of 20,000 infantry and 800 cavalry. That
                        army was decreed to the praetor who should draw Bruttium as his province.
                        Two temples were dedicated this year to Jupiter. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> One had been vowed by L. Furius Purpureo, when praetor,
                        in the war against the Gauls; the other by the consul. The dedication was
                        performed by one of the decemviri, Q. Marcius Ralla. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Many severe sentences were passed this year on
                        moneylenders, the curule aediles M. Tuccius and P. Junius Brutus acting as
                        prosecutors. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> From the proceeds of the
                        fines inflicted on them gilded four-horse chariots were placed in the temple
                        on the Capitol and twelve gilded shields on the pediment of the chapel of
                        Jupiter. The same aediles constructed a colonnade outside the Porta
                        Trigemina in the Carpenters' Quarter. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans were devoting attention
                        to preparations for a fresh war, Antiochus for his part was by no means
                        idle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He was, however, detained in Asia by
                        three cities, Smyrna, Alexandria Troas and Lampsacus, none of which he had
                        been able to become master of either by force or by persuasion, and he did
                        not wish to leave them in his rear during his invasion of Europe. A further
                        cause of delay was his uncertainty about Hannibal. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The undecked ships with which he had intended to send
                        Hannibal to Africa were not ready, and then the question was raised, mainly
                        by Thoas, whether he ought to be sent at all. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Thoas asserted that the whole of Greece was in a state
                        of unrest and that Demetrias had passed into his hands. The lies about the
                        king and the wild exaggerations as to the forces which Antiochus possessed
                        with which he had excited many minds in Greece he now employed to feed the
                        king's hopes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He told him that all were
                        praying for him to come; there would be a universal rush to the shore from
                        which they had caught the first glimpse of the royal fleet. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He actually ventured to disturb the judgment which the
                        king had now without a shadow of doubt formed of Hannibal and gave it as his
                        opinion that no ships ought to be detached from the king's fleet, or if any
                        were sent Hannibal was the very last person who ought to be in command of
                        them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He was a banished man and a
                        Carthaginian to whom his fortunes or his imagination suggested a thousand
                        fresh prospects every day. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then, again,
                        the military reputation which led to Hannibal's being sought after like a
                        woman with a rich dowry was too great for any who was only officer in the
                        king's service; the king ought to be the central figure, the sole leader the
                        sole commander. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If Hannibal were to lose a
                        fleet or an army the loss would be just as great as if they were lost under
                        any other leader, but if any success were gained the glory of it would go to
                        Hannibal and not to Antiochus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Supposing
                        that they were fortunate enough to inflict a decisive defeat on the Romans
                        and win the war, how <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> could they hope
                        that Hannibal would live quietly under a monarch, under one man's rule,
                        after he had been unable to bear the restraints imposed by the laws of his
                        own country? His youthful aspirations and his hopes of winning world-wide
                        dominion had not fitted him to endure a master in his old age. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> There was no necessity for the king to give
                        Hannibal a command, he might find him employment as a member of his suite
                        and an adviser on matters concerning the war. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> A moderate demand upon such abilities as his would be
                        neither dangerous nor useless; but if the highest services he could render
                        were called for, they would prove too burdensome both for him who rendered
                        them and him who accepted them. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Such were
                        the arguments which Thoas used. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No characters are so prone to jealousy as
                        those whose birth and fortune are not on a level with their intelligence,
                        for they hate virtue and goodness in others. The plan of sending Hannibal to
                        Africa, the one useful plan which had been thought out at the beginning of
                        the war, was promptly set aside. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Encouraged by the defection of Demetrias, Antiochus determined to postpone
                        no longer his advance into Greece. Before setting sail he went up to Ilium
                        to offer sacrifices to Minerva. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then
                        rejoined his fleet and started on his expedition with 40 decked ships and 60
                        undecked ones, and these were followed by 200 transports laden with supplies
                        and military stores of every description. He first touched at the island of
                        Imbros and from there crossed the Aegean to Sciathus. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> After the ships which had lost their course during the
                        voyage had rejoined him, he sailed on to Pteleum, the first point on the
                        mainland. Here he was met by Eurylochus and the Magnetan leaders from
                        Demetrias, and the sight of so many supporters put him in excellent spirits.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The following day he entered the
                        harbour of Demetrias and disembarked his force at a spot not far from the
                        city. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His total strength consisted of
                        10,000 infantry, 500 cavalry and six elephants, a force hardly sufficient
                        for the occupation of Greece, even if there were no troops there, to say
                        nothing of maintaining a war against Rome. When the Aetolians received
                        intelligence that Antiochus was at Demetrias they at once convened a council
                        and passed a resolution inviting him to attend. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> As the king knew that this resolution would be passed
                        he had already left Demetrias and advanced to Phalara on the Maliac Gulf.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After being supplied with a copy of
                        the resolution he went on to Lamia, where he received <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> an enthusiastic welcome from the populace, who showed
                        their delight by loud cheers and other manifestations by which the common
                        crowd express their extravagant joy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he entered the council it was with
                        difficulty that the president, Phaeneas, and the other leaders obtained
                        silence in order that the king might speak. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> He began by apologising for having come with forces so much smaller than
                        everyone had hoped and expected. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This
                        ought to be taken, he said, as the greatest proof of his friendship and
                        devotion towards them, for though he was quite unprepared and the season was
                        unsuitable for a sea-passage he had unhesitatingly complied with the request
                        of their delegates, convinced as he was that when the Aetolians saw him
                        amongst them they would realise that, even had he come alone, it was in him
                        that their safety and protection lay. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At
                        the same time, he was going to fulfil to the utmost the hopes of those whose
                        expectations seemed for the moment to be disappointed. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as ever the season of the year made navigation
                        safe he should fill the whole of Greece with arms and men and horses and
                        encircle its coasts with his fleets; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> he
                        would shrink from no toil or danger till he had delivered Greece from the
                        yoke of Roman dominion and made Aetolia her foremost State. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Supplies of every description would accompany his
                        armies from Asia; for the time being it must be the care of the Aetolians to
                        furnish his troops with an abundant supply of corn and other provisions at a
                        reasonable price. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this speech, which met with
                        unanimous approval, the king left the council. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> An animated discussion then arose between the two
                        Aetolian leaders, Phaeneas and Thoas. Phaeneas argued that as their leader
                        in war Antiochus would not be so useful <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                        to them as he would be were he to act as peace-maker and as an umpire to
                        whom their differences with Rome might be referred for decision. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> His presence amongst them and his regal dignity
                        would do more to win the respect of the Romans than his arms. Many men, to
                        avoid the necessity of war, will make concessions which could not be
                        extorted from them by war and armed force. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Thoas, on the other hand, asserted that Phaeneas was not really anxious for
                        peace; he only wanted to hinder their preparations for war so that the king,
                        tired of delays, might relax his efforts and the Romans gain time for
                        completing their own preparations. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Notwithstanding all the deputations which had been despatched to Rome and
                        all the personal discussions with Quinctius, they had learnt by experience
                        that no equitable terms could be procured from Rome, nor would they have
                        sought help from Antiochus had not all their hopes been dashed to the
                        ground. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Now that he had presented himself
                        sooner than anyone expected they must not slacken their purpose, rather must
                        they beg the king, as he had come as the champion of Greece, which was the
                        main thing, to summon all his military and naval forces. A king in arms
                        would gain something, a king without arms would not have the slightest
                        weight with Romans, either as acting on behalf of the Aetolians or even
                        defending his own interests. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These
                        arguments carried the day and they decided to appoint the king as their
                        commander-in-chief with absolute powers, and thirty of their <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> leading men were selected to act as an advisory
                        council on any matter on which he might wish to consult them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the break-up of the council the members
                        dispersed to their respective cities. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        next day the king consulted the council as to where operations should
                        commence. It was thought best to begin with Chalcis, where the Aetolians had
                        recently made their futile attempt, and where they considered success would
                        depend on quick action more than on serious preparations or sustained
                        effort. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The king accordingly, with a force
                        of 1000 infantry which had come up from Demetrias, marched through Phocis,
                        and the Aetolian leaders, who had called out a few of their fighting men,
                        taking a different route, assembled at Chaeronea and followed him in ten
                        ships of war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fixing his camp at Salganeus
                        he crossed the Euripus with the Aetolians, and when he was within a short
                        distance from the harbour the magistrates and leading men of Chalcis came
                        forward in front of their gate. A small party from each side met to confer.
                        The Aetolians did their utmost to persuade the Chalcidians to receive the
                        king as an ally and friend without disturbing their friendly relations with
                        Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They said that he had sailed across
                        to Europe not to levy war <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> but to
                        liberate Greece, not with empty professions as the Romans had done, but to
                        make her really free. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nothing could be
                        more advantageous for the States of Greece than to enter into friendly
                        relations with both parties, for then they would be secure against
                        ill-treatment from either side through the protection which the other would
                        be pledged to afford. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If they refused to
                        receive the king, let them consider what they would at once have to go
                        through, with the Romans too far away to help and Antiochus, whom they were
                        powerless to resist, before their gates as an enemy. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Micythio, one of the Achaean leaders, said in reply
                        that he was wondering who the people were that Antiochus had left his
                        kingdom and come across to Europe to liberate. He knew of no city in Greece
                        which held a Roman garrison or paid tribute to Rome or had to submit against
                        its will to conditions imposed by a one-sided treaty. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The Chalcidians needed no one to vindicate their
                        liberty, for they were a free State; nor did they require protection, for it
                        was owing to this same Roman people that they were in the enjoyment of peace
                        and liberty. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They did not reject the
                        proffered friendship of the king nor even of the Aetolians, but the first
                        proof of <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> friendship would be their
                        departure from the island, for as far as they themselves were concerned it
                        was quite certain that they would not admit them within <milestone n="13??"
                            unit="section"/> their walls or even enter into any alliance with them
                        without the authority of the Roman Government. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king had remained on board, and when
                        this was reported to him he decided for the present to return to Demetrias
                        as he had not brought sufficient troops to effect anything by force.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As his first attempt had proved a
                        complete failure he consulted the Aetolians as to what the next step should
                        be. They decided to try what could be done with the Boeotians, the Achaeans
                        and the Athamanian king, Amynander. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They
                        were under the impression that the Boeotians had been estranged from Rome
                        ever since the death of Brachylles and the results which flowed from it, and
                        they <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> also believed that Philopoemen, the
                        chief magistrate of the Achaeans, was an object of dislike and jealousy on
                        the part of Quinctius owing to the reputation he had gained in the Laconian
                        war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Amynander had married Apama, the
                        daughter of a certain Alexander of Megalopolis, who represented himself as
                        being descended from Alexander the Great and had given his three children
                        the names of Philip, Alexander and Apama. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Her marriage with the king had made Apama much talked about and her elder
                        brother Philip had followed her to Athamania. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He was a weak and conceited young man, and Antiochus
                        and the Aetolians had persuaded him that if he brought Amynander and the
                        Athamanians over to the side of Antiochus he might hope to succeed to the
                        throne of Macedon, as he really belonged to the royal stock. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> These empty promises carried weight not only with
                        Philip but even with Amynander. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Aetolian agents who had been sent to
                        Achaia were received in audience at a council held at Aegium. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Antiochus' envoy spoke first. Like most men who
                        are fed by royal bounty, he talked in a grandiloquent strain and filled sea
                        and land with the empty sound of his words. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> According to him, an innumerable mass of cavalry was crossing the
                        Hellespont into Europe; some were clad in coats of mail, they were called
                        "cataphracti"; others were bowmen, and against them nothing was safe, their
                        aim was surest when they were galloping away from the enemy. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Although this cavalry force alone could overwhelm
                        the massed armies of Europe, he went on to talk about bodies of infantry
                        many times as numerous and startled his hearers with names they had hardly
                        ever heard of-Dahae, Medes, Elymaeans and Cadusii. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The naval forces were such as no harbours in Greece
                        could hold; the right division was formed by the Sidonians and Tyrians; the
                        left by the Aradii and Sidetae from Pamphylia, nations which were unequalled
                        in the whole world as skilful and intrepid seamen. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was unnecessary, he continued, to refer to the money
                        and other provision for war, his hearers themselves knew how the realms of
                        Asia had always overflowed with gold. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So
                        the Romans would not have to do with a Philip or a Hannibal, the one only
                        the foremost man in a single city, the other confined to the limits of his
                        Macedonian kingdom, but with the Great King who ruled over the whole of Asia
                        and a part of Europe. And yet, coming as he did from the remotest borders of
                        the East to liberate Greece, he asked for nothing from the Achaeans which
                        could impair their loyalty to Rome, their old friend and ally. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> He did not ask them to take up arms with him
                        against them, all he wanted was that they should stand aloof from both
                        sides. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "Let your one wish and desire," he
                        concluded, "as becomes common friends, be that each may enjoy peace; if
                        there is to be war do not become involved in it." <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Archidamus, who represented the Aetolians, spoke to the
                        same effect and urged them to maintain a passive attitude as the easiest and
                        safest course, and, whilst watching the war as mere onlookers, wait for its
                        final result upon the fortunes of others without in any way hazarding their
                        own. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then his tongue ran away with him
                        and he broke out into unrestrained abuse of the Romans in general and in
                        particular of Quinctius, reproaching them with ingratitude and asserting
                        that it was through the valour of the Aetolians that <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> they secured not only the victory over Pyrrhus, but
                        even their own safety, for it was the Aetolians who saved Quinctius and his
                        army from destruction. "What duty," he exclaimed, "incumbent on a commander
                        has that man ever discharged? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I saw him,
                        while the battle was going on, busy with auspices, offerings and vows like
                        some miserable priest, while I was exposing myself to the enemy's weapons in
                        his defence." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius replied: "Archidamus had in his
                        mind those in whose presence rather than those to whose ears he was
                        addressing his remarks, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> for you Achaeans
                        know perfectly well that all the warlike spirit of the Aetolians lies in
                        words not in deeds, and shows itself in haranguing councils more than on the
                        battlefield. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So they are indifferent to
                        the opinion which the Achaeans have of them, because they are aware that
                        they are thoroughly known to them. It is for the king's representatives, and
                        through them for the king himself, that he has uttered this bombast.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If anyone did not know before what it
                        was that led Antiochus to make common cause with the Aetolians, it came out
                        clearly in their delegate's speech. By lying to one another and boasting of
                        forces which neither of them possess they have filled each other with vain
                        hopes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These say that it was through them
                        that Philip was defeated and by their courage that the Romans were
                        protected, and as you heard just now, they talk as though you and all other
                        cities and nations were going to follow their lead. The king, on the other
                        hand, vaunts of his clouds of infantry and cavalry and covers all the seas
                        with his fleets. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It is very like something
                        that happened when we were at supper with my host in Chalcis, a worthy man
                        and one who knows how to feed his guests. It was at the height of summer; we
                        were being sumptuously entertained, and were wondering how he managed to get
                        such an abundance and variety of game at that season of the year. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The man, not a boaster like these people, smiled
                        and said, 'That variety of what looks like wild game is due to the
                        condiments and dressing, it has all been made out of a home-bred pig.' This
                        might be fitly said of the king's forces which were just now so extolled.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All that variety of equipment and the
                        crowd of names no one ever heard of-Dahae, Medes, Cadusians and
                        Elymaeans-are nothing but Syrians, whose servile, cringing temper makes them
                        much more like a breed of slaves than a nation of soldiers. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> I wish I could bring before your eyes, Achaeans, the
                        flying visits which the 'Great King' paid to the national council of the
                        Aetolians at Lamia and afterwards to Chalcis. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> You would see what looked like two badly depleted
                        legions in the king's camp; you would see the king almost on his knees
                        begging corn from the Aetolians and trying to raise a loan from which to pay
                        his men, and then standing at the gates of Chalcis, and on finding himself
                        shut out from there returning to Aetolia having gained nothing but a glimpse
                        of Aulis and the Euripus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The king's
                        confidence in the Aetolians is misplaced, so is theirs in his empty
                        professions. You must not, therefore, let yourselves be deceived; trust
                        rather in the good faith of Rome, of which you have had actual experience.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As to their saying that the best
                        course for you is to have nothing to do with the war, <milestone n="13??"
                            unit="section"/> nothing on the contrary could be further from your
                        interests, for then, winning neither gratitude nor respect, you would fall
                        as a prize to the victor." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was felt that his reply to both parties
                        was to the point, and his speech easily won the approbation of the council.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was no debate and no hesitation
                        in coming to a unanimous decision that the Achaeans would count as their
                        friends or foes those whom the Romans considered such, and would also
                        declare war on Antiochus and the Aetolians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> On the instruction of Quirinus they at once despatched a contingent of
                        500 men to Chalcis and an equal number to the Piraeus. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> At Athens matters were fast approaching a state of
                        civil war through the action of certain individuals who by holding out the
                        prospect of bribes were drawing the mob, who can always be bought by gold,
                        over to Antiochus. The supporters of Rome sent to Quirinus asking him to go
                        to Athens, and Apollodorus, the ringleader of the movement, was tried at the
                        instance of a man called Leontes, found guilty and sent into banishment.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The delegates returned to the king
                        with an unfavourable reply from the Achaeans; the Boeotians gave no definite
                        answer. They simply promised that when Antiochus appeared in Boeotia they
                        would deliberate as to what action they should take. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> When Antiochus heard that the Aetolians and Eumenes had
                        each sent reinforcements to Chalcis he saw that he must act promptly and be
                        the first to enter the place and if possible intercept the enemy on their
                        advance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He sent Menippus with about 3000
                        men and Polyxenidas with the whole of the fleet, and a few days later
                        marched thither in person with 6000 of his own men and a smaller body of
                        Aetolians, taken from such force as could be hastily concentrated at Lamia.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The 500 Achaeans and the small
                        contingent supplied by Eumenes under Xenoclides of Chalcis crossed the
                        Euripus, as the route was still open, and reached Chalcis. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The Roman troops, who were about 500 strong, came after
                        Menippus had encamped before Sanganeus at the Hermaeum, the point of
                        departure from Boeotia to the island of Euboea. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> They were accompanied by Micythio, who had been sent
                        from Chalcis to Quirinus to ask for this very contingent. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> When, however, he found that the passes were blocked,
                        he abandoned the one leading to Aulis and took the one to Delium, intending
                        to sail across from there. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Delium is a temple of Apollo overlooking
                        the sea, five miles distant from Tanagra and four miles from the nearest
                        point of Euboea by sea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here in the fane
                        and in the grove, sacred and therefore inviolable, with its rights of
                        sanctuary which it possessed in common with those temples which the Greeks
                        call "asyla," the soldiers were walking about perfectly at their ease, not
                        having yet heard that a state of war existed or that swords had been drawn
                        and blood shed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some were exploring the
                        temple and the grove, others strolling along the beach without any weapons,
                        while a large number had gone off to procure wood and fodder. Whilst thus
                        dispersed they were suddenly attacked by Menippus. Many were killed, as many
                        as fifty were made prisoners; very few made their escape. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Amongst these was Micythio, who was taken on board a
                        small transport. The losses incurred greatly disquieted Quinctius and the
                        Romans, but at the same time it was regarded as an additional justification
                        for the war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Antiochus had moved his army
                        up to Aulis and from there he despatched a second mission to Chalcis,
                        consisting of some of his own people and some Aetolians. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They employed the same arguments as before, but in much
                        more threatening tone, and in spite of the efforts of Micythio and
                        Xenoclides he had little difficulty in inducing the townsmen to open the
                        gates to him. The adherents of Rome left the city just before the king's
                        entry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Achaean troops and those of
                        Eumenes were holding Salganeus, and a small body of Romans were fortifying a
                        post on the Euripus to defend the position. Menippus commenced the attack on
                        Salganeus and Antiochus prepared to capture the fortified post. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The Achaeans and the soldiers of Eumenes were the
                        first to abandon the defence on condition of being allowed to depart in
                        safety. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Romans offered a much stouter
                        resistance, but when they found that they were blockaded by land and sea and
                        that siege artillery was being brought up they were unable to hold out any
                        longer. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As the king was now in possession
                        of the capital of Euboea, the other cities on the island did not dispute his
                        dominion. He flattered himself that he had made a most successful
                        commencement of the war, considering how large an island and how many
                        serviceable cities had fallen into his hands. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
