<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six -
                    35</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to
                                thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXXV.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Publius Scipio Africanus sent as ambassador to Antiochus; has a conversation
                        with Hannibal at Ephesus. Preparations of the Romans for war with Antiochus.
                        Nabis, the tyrant of Lacedaemon, instigated by the Aetolians, makes war on.
                        the Achaeans; is put to death by a party of the Aetolians. The Aetolians,
                        violating the treaty of friendship with the Romans, invite Antiochus, who
                        comes, with a small force, into Greece, and, in conjunction with them, takes
                        several towns, and the whole island of Eubœa. The Achaeans declare war
                        against Antiochus and the Aetolians. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> IN the beginning of the same year, Sextus
                    Digitius, praetor in the Hither Spain, fought with those states which, after the
                    departure of Marcus Cato, had, in great numbers, recommenced hostilities,
                    numerous battles, but none deserving of particular mention; and all so
                    unfavourable to him, that he scarcely delivered to his successor half the number
                    of men that he had received. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In consequence of
                    this, every state in Spain would certainly have resumed new courage, had not the
                    other praetor, Publius Cornelius Scipio, son of Cneius, been successful in
                    several engagements on the other side of the Iberus; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and, by these means, diffused such a general terror, that
                    no less than fifty towns came over to his side. These exploits Scipio performed
                    in his praetorship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Afterwards, when
                    propraetor, as the Lusitanians, after ravaging the farther province, were
                    returning home, with an immense booty, he <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    attacked them on their march, and continued the engagement from the third hour
                    of the day to the eighth, before any advantage was gained on either side. He was
                    inferior to the <pb n="1554" xml:id="p.1554"/> enemy in number of men, but he
                    had the advantage of them in other respects: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    with his troops formed in a compact body, he attacked a long train, encumbered
                    with multitudes of cattle; and with his soldiers fresh, engaged men, fatigued by
                    a long march; for the enemy had set out at the third watch, and besides
                    travelling the remainder of the night, had continued their route to the third
                    hour of the day; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> nor had they been allowed any
                    rest, as the battle immediately succeeded the toil of the march. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Wherefore, though at the beginning they retained some
                    vigour of body and spirits, and, at first, threw the Romans into disorder, yet,
                    after some time, the fight became equal. In this critical situation the
                    proprietor made a vow to celebrate games in honour of Jupiter, in case he should
                    defeat and cut off the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Romans then
                    made a more vigorous push, and the Lusitanians gave way, and, in a little time,
                    turned their backs. As the victors pursued them briskly, no less than twelve
                    thousand of them were slain, and five hundred and forty taken prisoners, most of
                    whom were horsemen. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There were taken,
                    besides, a hundred and thirty-four military standards. Of the Roman army, but
                    seventy-three men were lost. The battle was fought at a small distance from the
                    city of Ilipa. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thither Publius Cornelius led
                    back his victorious army, amply enriched with spoil; all which was exposed to
                    view under the walls of the town, and permission given to the owners to claim
                    their effects. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The remainder was put into the
                    hands of the quaestor to be sold, and the money produced by the sale was
                    distributed among the soldiers. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the time when these occurrences happened in
                    Spain, Caius Flaminius, the praetor, had not yet set out from Rome: <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> therefore these events, as well prosperous as
                    adverse, were reported by himself and his friends in the strongest
                    representations; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and he laboured to persuade
                    the senate, that, as a very formidable war had blazed out in his province, and
                    he was likely to receive from Sextus Digitius a very small remnant of an army,
                    and that, too, terrified and disheartened, they ought to decree one of the city
                    legions to him, in order that, when lie should have united to it <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> the soldiers levied by himself, pursuant to the
                    decree of the senate, he might select from the whole number six thousand five
                    hundred foot and three hundred horse. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He said,
                    that <quote> with such a legion as that, (for very little confidence could be
                        placed on the troops <pb n="1555" xml:id="p.1555"/> of Sextus Digitius,) he
                        would conduct the war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the elder part of the senate insisted,
                    that <quote> decrees of the senate were not to be passed in consequence of
                        rumours fabricated by private persons for the gratification of magistrates;
                        and that no intelligence should be deemed authentic except it were either
                        written by the praetors, from their provinces, or brought by their deputies.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If there was a tumultuous commotion in
                        Spain, they advised a vote, that tumultuary soldiers should be levied by the
                        praetor in some other country than Italy. </quote> The senate's intention
                    was that such description of men should be raised in Spain. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Valerius Antias says, that Caius Flaminius sailed to Sicily
                    for the purpose of levying troops, and that, on his voyage thence to Spain,
                    being driven by a storm to Africa, he enlisted there many stragglers who had
                    belonged to the army of Publius Africanus; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and
                    that, to the levies made in those two provinces, he added a third in Spain. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Italy the war, commenced by the Ligurians,
                    grew daily more formidable. They now invested Pisae, with an army of forty
                    thousand men; for multitudes flocked to them continually, led by the reports of
                    the war and the expectation of booty. The consul, Minucius, came to Arretium, on
                    the day which he had fixed for the assembling of the troops. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Thence he led them, in order of battle, towards Pisae; and
                    though the enemy had removed their camp to the other side of the river at a
                    distance of no more than three miles from the place, the consul marched into the
                    city, which evidently owed its preservation to his coming. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Next day he also encamped on the other side of the river,
                    about a mile from the enemy; and by slight skirmishes protected the lands of the
                    allies from their depredations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He did not
                    think it prudent to hazard a general engagement, because his troops were raw,
                    composed of many different kinds of men, and not yet so well known among
                    themselves that they could rely on one another. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The Ligurians depended so much on their numbers, that they not only came out
                    and offered battle, willing to risk every thing on the issue of it; but, from
                    their superfluity of men, they sent out many parties along the frontiers to
                    plunder; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and whenever a large quantity of
                    cattle, and other prey, was collected, there was an escort always in readiness
                    to convey it into their forts and towns. <pb n="1556" xml:id="p.1556"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the operations remained at a stand at
                    Pisae, the other consul, Lucius Cornelius Merula, led his army through the
                    extreme borders of the Ligurians, into the territory of the Boians, where the
                    mode of proceeding was quite the reverse of that which took place in the war of
                    Liguria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul took the field; the enemy
                    refused to fight; and the Romans, when no one would come out against them, went
                    out in parties to plunder, while the Boians chose to let their country be laid
                    waste with impunity rather than venture an engagement in defence of it.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When all places were completely ravaged
                    with fire and sword, the consul quitted the enemy's lands, and marched towards
                    Mutina, in a careless manner, as through a pacific population. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Boians, when they learned that the enemy had withdrawn
                    beyond their frontiers, followed him as secretly as possible, watching an
                    opportunity for an ambuscade; and, having gone by his camp in the night, took
                    possession of a defile through which the Romans were to pass. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> But as they were not able to effect this with sufficient
                    secrecy, the consul, who usually began his march late in the night, now waited
                    until day, lest, in the disorderly fight likely to ensue, darkness might
                    increase the confusion; and though he did not stir before it was light, yet he
                    sent forward a troop of horse to explore the country. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When intelligence was brought by them of the number and
                    situation of the enemy, he ordered the baggage to be heaped together in the
                    centre, and the veterans to throw up a rampart round it; and then, with the rest
                    of the army in order of battle, he advanced towards the enemy. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The Gauls did the same, when they found that their
                    stratagem was detected, and that they were to engage in a fair and regular
                    battle, where success must depend on valour alone. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle began about the second hour. The
                    left brigade of the allies, and the Extraordinaries, fought in the first line,
                    and were commanded by two lieutenant-generals of consular dignity, Marcus
                    Marcellus and Tiberius Sempronius, who had been consul the year before.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The present consul was sometimes employed
                    in the front of the line, sometimes in keeping back the legions in reserve, that
                    they might not, through eagerness for fighting, come up to the attack until the
                    signal was given. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He ordered the two Minucii,
                    Quintus and Publius, military tribunes, to lead off the cavalry of <pb n="1557"
                        xml:id="p.1557"/> the legions into open ground, at some distance from the
                    line; and "when he should give them the signal, to charge the enemy through the
                    clear space. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While he was thus employed, a
                    message came from Tiberius Sempronius Longus, that the Extraordinaries could not
                    support the onset of the Gauls; that great numbers had already fallen; and that
                    partly through weariness, partly through fear, the ardour of the survivors was
                    much abated. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He recommended it therefore to
                    the consul, if he thought proper, to send up one or other of the two legions,
                    before the army suffered disgrace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The second
                    legion was accordingly sent, and the Extraordinaries were ordered to retire. By
                    the legion coming up, with its men fresh, and the ranks complete in their
                    numbers, the fight was renewed with vigour. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The left wing was withdrawn out of the action, and the right took its place in
                    the van. The intense heat of the sun discomposed the Gauls, whose bodies were
                    very ill qualified to endure it: nevertheless, keeping their ranks close, and
                    leaning sometimes on each other, sometimes on their bucklers, they withstood the
                    attack of the Romans; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> which, when the consul
                    observed, in order to break their ranks, he ordered Caius Livius Salinator,
                    commander of the allied cavalry, to charge them at full speed, and the legionary
                    cavalry to remain in reserve. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This tempest of
                    cavalry first confused and disordered, and at length entirely broke the line of
                    the Gauls; yet it did not make them fly. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That
                    was prevented by their officers, who, when they quitted their posts, struck them
                    on the back with their spears, and compelled them to return to their ranks: but
                    the allied cavalry, riding in among them, did not suffer them to recover their
                    order. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consul exhorted his soldiers to
                        <quote> continue their efforts a little longer, for victory was within their
                        reach; to press the enemy, while they saw them disordered and dismayed; for,
                        if they were suffered to recover their ranks, they would enter on a fresh
                        battle with doubtful success. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He ordered the standard-bearers to advance
                    with the standards, and then, all exerting themselves at once, they at length
                    forced the enemy to give way. As soon as they turned their backs, and fled
                    precipitately on every side, the legionary cavalry was sent in pursuit of them.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On that day, fourteen thousand of the
                    Boians were slain; one thousand and ninety-two taken —as were seven hundred and
                    twenty-one horsemen, and three of their commanders, with <pb n="1558"
                        xml:id="p.1558"/> two hundred and twelve military standards, and sixty-three
                    chariots. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Nor did the Romans gain the victory
                    without loss of blood: of themselves, or their allies, were lost above five
                    thousand men, twenty-three centurions, four praefects of the allies, and two
                    military tribunes of the second legion, Marcus Genucius and Marcus Marcius. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Letters from both the consuls arrived at Rome
                    nearly at the same time. That of Lucius Cornelius gave an account of the battle
                    fought with the Boians at Mutina; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that of
                    Quintus Minucius, from Pisae, mentioned, that <quote> the holding of the
                        elections had fallen to his lot, but that affairs in Liguria were in so
                        uncertain a position, that he could not depart thence without bringing ruin
                        on the allies, and material injury on the commonwealth. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He therefore advised that, if the senate thought
                        proper, they should direct his colleague (as his war was decided) to return
                        to Rome for the elections. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He said, if
                        Cornelius should object to this, because that employment had not fallen to
                        his lot, he would certainly do whatever the senate should order; but he
                        begged them to consider again and again, whether it would not be more to the
                        advantage of the republic, that an interregnum should take place, than that
                        the province should be left by him in such a state. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate gave directions to Caius Scribonius
                    to send two deputies of senatorian rank to the consul, Lucius Cornelius, to
                    communicate to him the letter sent by his colleague to the senate, and to
                    acquaint him, that if he did not come to Rome to elect new magistrates, the
                    senate were resolved, rather than Quintus Minucius should be called away from a
                    war, in which no progress had been made, to suffer an interregnum to take place.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The deputies sent brought back his answer,
                    that he would come to Rome, to elect new magistrates. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The letter of' Lucius Cornelius, which contained an account
                    of the battle with the Boians, occasioned a debate in the senate; for Marcus
                    Claudius, lieutenant-general, in private letters to many of the senators, had
                    written, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> that they might thank the fortune of the Roman people, and the bravery
                        of the soldiers, that the affair had been successful. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> That the conduct of the consul had been the cause of a
                        great many men being lost, and of the enemy's army, for the annihilation of
                        which an opportunity had been offered, having made its escape. That what
                        made the loss of men the greater was, the reinforcements, <pb n="1559"
                            xml:id="p.1559"/> necessary to support them when distressed, coming up
                        too late from the reserve; and that, what enabled the enemy to slip out of
                        their hands was, the signal being given too tardily to the legionary
                        cavalry, and their not being allowed to pursue the fugitives. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was agreed, that no resolution should be
                    hastily passed on the subject; and the discussion was accordingly adjourned to a
                    fuller meeting. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Another concern also pressed upon them,
                    namely, that the public was heavily distressed by usurious practices; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> and although avarice had been restricted by many laws
                    respecting usury, yet a fraudulent course had been adopted —that of transferring
                    the securities to subjects of some of the allied states, who were not bound by
                    those laws, by which means usurers over-whelmed their debtors by unlimited
                    interest. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On considering of the best method
                    for putting a stop to this evil the senate decreed, that a certain day should be
                    fixed on for it, the next approaching festival of the infernal deities; and that
                    any of the allies who should from that day lend money to the Roman citizens,
                    should register the transaction; and that all proceedings respecting such money,
                    lent after that day, should be regulated by the laws of whichever of the two
                    states the debtor should choose. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In some time
                    after, when the great amount of debt, contracted through this kind of fraud, was
                    discovered <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> by means of the registries,
                    Marcus Sempronius, plebeian tribune, by direction of the senate, proposed to the
                    people, and the people ordered, that the laws relative to money lent between
                    Roman citizens and subjects of any of the allied states, or Latin confederacy,
                    should be the same as those between Roman citizens. Such were the transactions
                    in Italy, civil and military. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In Spain the war
                    was far from being so formidable as the exaggerations of report had represented
                    it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In Hither Spain, Caius Flaminius took the
                    town of Ilucia, in the country of the Oretanians, and then marched his army into
                    winter quarters. Several engagements took place during the winter, but none
                    deserving of particular mention, directed against incursions of robbers rather
                    than of the enemy; and yet with various success, and not without the loss of
                    some men. More important services were performed by Marcus Fulvius. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> He fought a pitched battle near the town of Toletum,
                    against the Vaccaeans, Vectonians, and Celtiberians; routed and dispersed their
                    combined forces, and took prisoner their king, Hilermus. <pb n="1560"
                        xml:id="p.1560"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While this passed in Spain, the day of
                    election was drawing near. Lucius Cornelius, therefore, the consul, left Marcus
                    Claudius, lieutenant-general, in command of the army, and came to Rome.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After representing in the senate the
                    services which he had performed, and the present state of the province, he
                    expostulated with the conscript fathers on <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    their not having ordered a thanksgiving to the immortal gods, when so great a
                    war was so happily terminated by one successful battle; and then demanded, that
                    they would at the same time decree a supplication and a triumph. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> But, before the question was put, Quintus Metellus,
                    who had been consul and dictator, said, that, <quote> letters had been brought
                        at the same time from the consul, Lucius Cornelius, to the senate, and from
                        Marcus Marcellus, to a great part of the senators; which letters
                        contradicted each other, and for that reason the consideration of the
                        business had been adjourned, in order that it might be debated when the
                        writers of those letters should be present. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> He had expected, therefore, that the consul, who knew that the
                        lieutenant-general had written something to his disadvantage, would, when he
                        himself was obliged to come, have brought him with him to Rome; especially,
                        as the command of the army would, with more propriety, have been committed
                        to Tiberius Sempronius, who already possessed authority, than to the
                        lieutenant-general. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As the case stood at
                        present, it appeared as if the latter was kept out of the way designedly,
                        lest he might assert in person the same things which he had written in his
                        letters; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and, face to face, either
                        substantiate his charges, or, if he had alleged any thing untrue, be
                        convicted of misrepresentation, until the truth should be clearly
                        discovered. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For this reason he was of
                        opinion, that the senate should not, at present, assent to either of the
                        decrees demanded by the consul. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When he, however, persisted with undiminished
                    energy in putting the question, that a thanksgiving should be ordered, and
                    himself allowed to ride into the city in triumph; the plebeian tribunes, Marcus
                    and Caius Titinius, declared, that they would enter their protest, if the senate
                    passed any decree on the subject. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the preceding year, Sextus Aelius Paetus
                    and Caius Cornelius Cethegus were created censors. Cornelius now closed the
                    lustrum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The number of citizens rated was a
                    hundred and forty-three thousand seven hundred and four. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Extraordinary quantities of rain fell in this year, and the
                    Ti- <pb n="1561" xml:id="p.1561"/> ber overflowed the lower parts of the city;
                    and some buildings near the Flumentan gate were even laid in ruins. The
                    Cœlimontan gate was struck by lightning, as was the wall on each side of it, in
                    several places. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Aricia, Lanuvium, and on
                    the Aventine, showers of stones fell. From Capua, a report was brought that a
                    very large swarm of wasps flew into the forum, and settled on the temple of
                    Mars; that they had been carefully collected, and burnt. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On account of these prodigies, the decemvirs were ordered
                    to consult the books; the nine days' festival was celebrated, a supplication
                    proclaimed, and the city purified. At the same time, Marcus Porcius Cato
                    dedicated a chapel to Maiden Victory, near the temple of Victory, two years
                    after he had vowed it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> During this year, a
                    Latin colony was established in the Thurian territory by commissioners appointed
                    for the purpose, Cneius Manlius Vulso, Lucius Apustius Fullo, and Quintus Aelius
                    Tubero, who had proposed the order for its settlement. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> There went out thither three thousand foot and three
                    hundred horsemen; a very small number in proportion to the extent of the land.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thirty acres might have been given to each
                    footman, and sixty to a horseman, but, by the advice of Apustius, a third part
                    was reserved, that they might afterwards, when they should judge proper, send
                    out thither a new colony. The footmen received twenty acres each, the horsemen
                    forty. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year was now near a close, and with regard
                    to the election of consuls, emulation was more fiercely kindled than was ever
                    known before. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The candidates, both patrician
                    and plebeian, were many and powerful: Publius Cornelius Scipio, son to Cneius,
                    and who had lately come home from Spain, having performed great exploits; Lucius
                    Quinctius Flamininus, who had commanded the fleet in Greece; and </p>
                <p> Cneius Manlius Vulso; these were the patricians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Then there were, of plebeian rank, Caius Laelius, Cneius Domitius, Caius
                    Livius Salinator, and Manius Acilius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The eyes
                    of all men were turned on Quinctius and Cornelius; for, being both patricians,
                    they sued for one place; and they were both of them recommended by high and
                    recent renown in war. Above every thing else, the brothers of the candidates,
                    the two most illustrious generals of the age, increased the violence of the
                    struggle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Scipio's fame was the more splendid,
                        <pb n="1562" xml:id="p.1562"/> and in proportion to its greater splendour,
                    the more obnoxious to envy. That of Quinctius was the most recent, as he had
                    triumphed in the course of that very same year. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Besides, the former had now for almost ten years been continually in people's
                    sight; which circumstance, by the mere effect of satiety, causes great
                    characters to be less revered. He had been a second time consul after the final
                    defeat of Hannibal, and also censor. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All
                    Quinctius's claims to the favour of the public were fresh and new; since his
                    triumph, he had neither asked nor received any thing from the people; <quote>he
                        solicited,</quote> he said, <quote> in favour of his own brother, not of a
                        half-brother; in favour of his lieutenant-general, and partner in the
                        administration of the war; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> his brother
                        having conducted the operations by sea, while he did the same on land.
                    </quote> By these arguments he carried his point. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> His brother was preferred to the brother of Africanus,
                    though supported by the whole Cornelian family, and while one of the same family
                    presided at the election, and notwithstanding the very honourable testimony
                    given by the senate, in his favour, when it adjudged him to be the best man in
                    the state: and as such, appointed him to receive the Idaean Mother into the
                    city, when she was brought from Pessinus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Quinctius and Cneius Domitius Ahenobarbus were elected consuls; so that,
                    not even with respect to the plebeian consul, could Africanus prevail; for he
                    employed his interest in favour of Caius Laelius. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Next day were elected praetors, Lucius Scribonius Libo,
                    Marcus Fulvius Centumalus, Aulus Atilius Serranus, Marcus Baebius Tamphilus,
                    Lucius Valerius Tappus, and Quintus Salonius Sarra. The aedileship of this year
                    was highly distinguished, namely, that of Marcus Aemilius Lepidus and Lucius
                    Aemilius Paulus. They prosecuted to conviction many of the farmers of the public
                    pastures, and with the money accruing from the fines, placed gilded shields in
                    the upper part of the temple of Jupiter. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They
                    built one colonnade, on the outside of the gate Tergemina, to which they added a
                    wharf on the Tiber: and another, reaching from the Frontinal gate to the altar
                    of Mars, to serve as a passage into the field of Mars. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For a long time, nothing worth recording had
                    occurred in Liguria; but, towards the end of this year, the Roman affairs there
                    were twice brought into great peril; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for the
                    consul's camp, being assaulted, was with difficulty preserved; <pb n="1563"
                        xml:id="p.1563"/> and a short time after, as the Roman army was marching
                    through a defile, the Ligurians seized on the opening through which they were to
                    pass. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul, when he found that passage
                    stopped up, faced about, resolved to return: but the entrance behind, also, was
                    occupied by a party of the enemy, and the disaster of Caudium not only occurred
                    to the memory of the Romans, but was in a manner represented to their eyes. The
                    consul had, among his auxiliary troops, about eight hundred Numidian horsemen,
                    whose commanding officer undertook to force a passage with his troops, on
                    whichever side the consul should choose. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He
                    only desired to be told on which part the greater number of villages lay, for on
                    them he meant to make an attack; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and the first
                    thing he intended doing was, to set fire to the houses, in order that the alarm,
                    which this should occasion, might induce the Ligurians to quit their posts in
                    the defile, and hasten to different quarters to carry assistance to their
                    friends. The consul highly commended him, and gave him assurance of ample
                    rewards. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Numidians mounted their horses,
                    and began to ride up to the advanced posts of the enemy, but without making any
                    attack. Nothing could appear, on the first view, more contemptible. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Both men and horses were of a small size and thin
                    make, the riders unaccoutred and unarmed, excepting that they carried javelins
                    in their hands; and the horses without bridles, and awkward in their gait,
                    running with their necks stiff and their heads stretched out. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The contempt, conceived from their appearance, they took
                    pains to increase; sometimes falling from their horses, and making themselves
                    objects of derision and ridicule. The consequence was, that the enemy, who at
                    first had been alert, and ready on their posts, in case of an attack, now, for
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the most part, laid aside their arms,
                    and sitting down amused themselves with looking at them. The Numidians often
                    rode up, then gallopped back, but still contrived to get nearer to the pass, as
                    if they were unable to manage their horses, and were carried away against their
                    will. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At last, setting spurs to them, they
                    broke out through the midst of the enemy's posts, and getting into the open
                    country, set fire to all the houses near the road. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They then set fire to the nearest village, while they
                    ravaged all around with fire and sword. At first the sight of the smoke, then
                    the shouts of the affrighted inhabitants, at last the old people and chil- <pb
                        n="1564" xml:id="p.1564"/> dren, who fled for shelter, created great
                    disorder in the camp. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In consequence of which
                    the whole of their army, without plan, and without command, ran off, each to
                    take care of his own; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> the camp was in a
                    moment deserted; and the consul, delivered from the blockade, made good his
                    march to the place whither he intended to go. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But neither the Boians nor the Spaniards, with
                    whom they had been at war during that year, were such bitter and inveterate foes
                    to the Romans as the nation of the Aetolians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    These, after the departure of the Roman armies from Greece, had, for some time,
                    entertained hopes that Antiochus would come and take possession of Europe,
                    without opposition; and that neither Philip nor Nabis would continue quiet.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But, seeing no active measures begun, in
                    any quarter, they resolved, lest their designs might be damped by delay, to
                    create some agitation and disturbance; and, with this view, they summoned a
                    general assembly at Naupactum. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here Thoas,
                    their praetor, after complaining of the injurious behaviour of the Romans, and
                    the present state of Aetolia, and asserting, that <quote> of all the nations and
                        states of Greece, they had been most unhonoured, after the victory which
                        they themselves had been the means of obtaining, </quote> moved, that
                    ambassadors should be sent to each of the kings; <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> not only to sound their dispositions, but, by such incentives as suited the
                    temper of each, to urge them to a war with Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Damocritus was sent to Nabis, Nicander to Philip, and Dicaearchus, the
                    praetor's brother, to Antiochus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To the
                    Lacedaemonian tyrant Damocritus represented, that, <quote> by the maritime
                        cities being taken from him, his government was left enervated; for from
                        them he had drawn his soldiers, as well as his ships and seamen. He was now
                        pent up almost within the walls of his capital, while he saw the Achaeans
                        domineering over the whole Peloponnesus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Never would he have another opportunity of recovering his rights, if he
                        suffered the one that now offered to pass by. There was no Roman army in
                        Greece, nor would the Romans deem Gythium, or the other towns on the coast
                        of Laconia, sufficient cause for transporting their legions a second time
                        into that country. </quote> These arguments were used for the purpose of
                    provoking the passions of Nabis; in order that when Antiochus should come into
                    Greece. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the other, conscious of having
                    infringed the treaty of amity with <pb n="1565" xml:id="p.1565"/> Rome, by
                    injuries offered to its allies, might unite himself with him. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Nicander excited Philip, by arguments somewhat similar; and
                    he had more copious matter for discourse, as the king had been degraded from a
                    more elevated state than the tyrant, and more possessions also had been taken
                    from him. In addition to this, he introduced the ancient renown of the
                    Macedonian kings, and the whole world pervaded by the victorious marches of that
                    nation. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>The plan which he proposed,</quote> he said, <quote> was free from any
                        danger, either in the commencement or in the issue. For he did not advise
                        that Philip should stir until Antiochus should have come into Greece with an
                        army; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and, considering that, without the
                        aid of Antiochus, he had maintained a war so long against the combined
                        forces of the Romans and Aetolians, with what possible force could the
                        Romans withstand him, when joined by Antiochus, and supported by the aid of
                        the Aetolians, who, on the former occasion, were more dangerous enemies than
                        the Romans? </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He added the circumstance of Hannibal being
                    general; <quote> a man born a foe to the Romans, who had slain greater numbers,
                        both of their commanders and soldiers, than were left surviving. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Such were the representations of Nicander to
                    Philip. Dicaearchus addressed other arguments to Antiochus. In the first place,
                    he told him, that <quote> the spoils of Philip belonged to the Romans, but the
                        victory over him to the Aetolians; that none other than the Aetolians had
                        afforded to the Romans admittance into Greece, and that the same people
                        supplied them with the strength which enabled them to conquer. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He next set forth the numerous forces, both
                    horse and foot, which they were willing to furnish to Antiochus, for the purpose
                    of the war; what quarters they would assign to his land armament, what harbours
                    for his naval forces. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He then asserted
                    whatever falsehoods he pleased, respecting Philip and Nabis; that <quote> both
                        were ready to recommence hostilities, and would greedily lay hold on the
                        first opportunity of recovering what they had lost in war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Thus did the Aetolians labour, in every part
                    of the world, to stir up war against the Romans. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> The kings, however, either took no steps in it or took them
                    too late. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nabis immediately despatched emissaries
                    through all the towns on the coast, to sow dissensions among the inhabitants:
                    some of the men in power he brought over to his party <pb n="1566"
                        xml:id="p.1566"/> by presents; others, who more firmly adhered to the
                    alliance with Rome, he put to death. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    charge of' protecting all the Lacedaemonians on the coast, had been committed by
                    Titus Quinctius to the Achaeans; they therefore instantly sent ambassadors to
                    the tyrant, to remind him of his treaty with the Romans, and to warn him against
                    violating a peace which he had so earnestly sued for. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They also sent succours to Gythium which he had already
                    besieged, and ambassadors to Rome to make known these transactions. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> King Antiochus having, this winter, solemnized the
                    nuptials of his daughter with Ptolemy, king of Egypt, at Raphia, in Phœnicia,
                    returned thence to Antioch, and came, towards the end of the season, through
                    Cilicia, after passing Mount Taurus, to the city of Ephesus. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Early in the spring, he sent his son Antiochus thence into
                    Syria, to guard the remote frontiers of his dominions, lest, during his absence,
                    any commotion might arise behind him and then he marched himself, with all his
                    land forces, to attack the Pisidians, inhabiting the country near Sida.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At this time, Publius Sulpicius and
                    Publius Villius, the Roman ambassadors, who were sent to Antiochus, as above
                    mentioned, having received orders to wait on Eumenes, first came to Elaea, and
                    thence went up to Pergamus, for the palace of Eumenes was there. Eumenes was
                    very desirous of a war against Antiochus, for he thought that, if peace
                    continued, a king so much superior in power would be a troublesome neighbour;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but that, in case of hostilities, he would
                    prove no more a match for the Romans than Philip had been; and that, either he
                    would be entirely removed out of the way, or, should peace be granted to him,
                    after a defeat he (Eumenes) might reasonably expect, that a great deal of what
                    should be taken from Antiochus would fall to his own share; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> so that, in future, he might be very well able to defend
                    himself against him, without any aid from the Romans; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and even if any misfortune were to happen, it would be
                    better for him, in conjunction with the Romans, to undergo any turn of fortune,
                    than, standing alone, either suffer himself to be ruled by Antiochus, or, on
                    refusal, be compelled to submission by force of arms. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Therefore, with all his influence, and every argument which
                    he could devise, he urged the Romans to a war. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Sulpicius, falling sick, staid at Pergamus.
                    Villius, on hearing that the king was carrying on war in Pisidia. went <pb
                        n="1567" xml:id="p.1567"/> on to Ephesus, and, during a few days that he
                    halted in that city, took pains <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> to procure
                    frequent interviews with Hannibal, who happened to be there at the time, in
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> order to sound his intentions, if
                    possible, and to remove his apprehensions of danger threatening him from the
                    Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> No other business, indeed, of any kind
                    was brought forward at these meetings; yet they accidentally produced an
                    important consequence, as effectually as if it had been intentionally sought;
                    the lowering Hannibal in the esteem of the king, and rendering him more
                    obnoxious to suspicion in every matter. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Claudius, following the history written in Greek by Acilius, says, that Publius
                    Africanus was employed in this embassy, and that it was he who conversed with
                    Hannibal at Ephesus. He even relates one of their conversations, in which Scipio
                    asked Hannibal, <quote>whom he thought the greatest captain?</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and that he answered, <quote> Alexander, king
                        of Macedonia; because, with a small band, he defeated armies whose numbers
                        were beyond reckoning; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and because he had
                        overrun the remotest regions, the merely visiting of which was a thing above
                        human aspiration. </quote> Scipio then asked, <quote>to whom he gave the
                        second place?</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and he replied, <quote> To Pyrrhus; for he
                        first taught the method of encamping; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and
                        besides, no one ever showed more exquisite judgment, in choosing his ground,
                        and disposing his posts; while he also possessed the art of conciliating
                        mankind to himself to such a degree, that the nations of Italy wished him,
                        though a foreign prince, to hold the sovereignty among them, rather than the
                        Roman people, who had so long possessed the dominion of that part of the
                        world. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On his proceeding to ask, <quote>whom he
                        esteemed the third?</quote> Hannibal replied, <quote>Myself, beyond
                        doubt.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On this Scipio laughed, and added,
                        <quote>What would you have said if you had conquered me?</quote>
                    <quote>Then,</quote> replied the other, <quote> I would have placed Hannibal,
                        not only before Alexander and Pyrrhus, but before all other commanders. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This answer, turned with Punic dexterity, and
                    conveying an unexpected kind of flattery, was highly grateful to Scipio, as it
                    set him apart from the crowd of commanders, as one of incomparable eminence. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From Ephesus, Villius proceeded to Apamea,
                    whither Antiochus, on hearing of the coming of the Roman delegates, came to meet
                    him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In this congress, at Apamea, the debates
                    were similar to those which passed at Rome, between Quinc- <pb n="1568"
                        xml:id="p.1568"/> tius and the king's ambassadors. The news arriving of the
                    death of Antiochus, the king's son, who, as just now mentioned, had been sent
                    into Syria, broke off the conference. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There
                    was great mourning in the court, and excessive regret for this young man; for he
                    had given such indications of his character, as afforded evident proof that, had
                    a longer life been allotted him, he would have displayed the talents of a great
                    and just prince. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The more he was beloved and
                    esteemed by all, the more was his death a subject of suspicion, namely, that his
                    father, thinking that his heir trod too closely on the heels of his own old age,
                    had him taken off by poison, by some eunuchs, who recommend themselves to kings
                    by the perpetration of such foul deeds. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> People
                    mentioned also, as another motive for that clandestine act of' villany, that, as
                    he had given Lysimachia to his son Seleucus, he had no establishment of the like
                    kind, which he could give to Antiochus, for the purpose of banishing him also to
                    a distance, under pretext of doing him honour. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Nevertheless, an appearance of deep mourning was maintained in the court for
                    several days; and the Roman ambassador, lest his presence at that inauspicious
                    time might be troublesome, retired to Pergamus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> The king, dropping the prosecution of the war which he had begun, went back
                    to Ephesus; and there, keeping himself shut up in the palace, under colour of
                    grief, held secret consultations with a person called Minio, who was his
                    principal favourite. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Minio was utterly
                    ignorant of the state of all foreign nations; and, accordingly, estimating the
                    strength of the king from his successes in Syria or Asia, lie was confident that
                    Antiochus had not only superiority from the merits of his cause, and that the
                    demands of the Romans were highly unreasonable; but also, that he would prove
                    the more powerful in war. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As the king wished
                    to avoid further debate with the envoys, either because he had found no
                    advantage to result from the former conference, or because he was too much
                    discomposed by recent grief, Minio undertook to say whatever was requisite for
                    his interest, and persuaded him to invite for that purpose the ambassadors from
                    Pergamus. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time Sulpicius had recovered his
                    health; both himself and Villius, therefore, came to Ephesus. Minio apologized
                    for the king not being present, and the business was entered upon. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Then Minio, in a studied speech, said, <quote> I <pb
                            n="1569" xml:id="p.1569"/> find, Romans, that you profess very specious
                        intentions, (the liberating of the Grecian states,) but your actions do not
                        accord with your words. You lay down one rule for Antiochus, and follow
                        another yourselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For, how are the
                        inhabitants of Smyrna and Lampsacus better entitled to the character of
                        Greeks, than the Neapolitans, Rhegians, and Tarentines, from whom you exact
                        tribute, and ships, in pursuance of a treaty? <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Why do you send yearly to Syracuse, and other Grecian
                        cities of Sicily, a praetor, vested with sovereign power, and attended by
                        his rods and axes? You can, certainly, allege no other reason than this,
                        that, having conquered them in war, you imposed these terms on them.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Admit, then, on the part of Antiochus,
                        the same reason with respect to Smyrna and Lampsacus, and the cities
                        belonging to Ionia and Aeolia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Conquered
                        by his ancestors, they were subjected to tribute and taxes, and he only
                        reclaims an ancient right. I would have you answer him on these heads, if
                        you mean a fair discussion, and do not merely seek a pretence for war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Sulpicius answered, <quote> Antiochus has
                        acted with some modesty in choosing that, since no other arguments could be
                        produced in his favour, any other person should utter these rather than
                        himself. For, what similarity is there in the cases of those states which
                        you have brought into comparison? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From the
                        Rhegians, Neapolitans, and Tarentines we require what they owe us by treaty,
                        in virtue of a right invariably exercised, in one uniform course, since they
                        first came under our power; a right always asserted, and never intermitted.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Now, can you assert, that, as these
                        states have, neither of themselves, nor through any other, ever refused
                        conforming to the treaty, so the Asiatic states, since they once came under
                        the power of Antiochus's ancestors, have been held in uninterrupted
                        possession by your reigning kings; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and
                        that some of them have not been subject to the dominion of Philip, some to
                        that of Ptolemy; and that others have not, for many years, maintained
                        themselves in a state of independence, no one calling it in question?
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For, if the circumstance of their
                        having been once subject to a foreigner, when crushed under the severity of
                        the times, conveys a right to enforce that subjection again after a lapse of
                        so many generations, what can be said of our having delivered Greece from
                        Philip, but that nothing was accomplished by us; and that his successors may
                        reclaim <pb n="1570" xml:id="p.1570"/> Corinth, Chalcis, Demetrias, and the
                        whole nation of Thessaly? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But why do I
                        plead the cause of those states, which it would <milestone n="13??"
                            unit="section"/> be fitter that both we and the king should hear pleaded
                        by themselves? </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He then desired, that the deputies of those
                    states should be called, for they had been prepared beforehand, and kept in
                    readiness by Eumenes, who reckoned, that every share of strength that should be
                    taken away from Antiochus, would become an accession to his own kingdom.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Many of them were introduced; and, while
                    each enforced his own complaints, and sometimes demands, and blended together
                    the reasonable with the unreasonable, they changed the debate into a mere
                    altercation. The ambassadors, therefore, without conceding or carrying any one
                    point, returned to Rome just as they had come, leaving every thing in an
                    undecided state. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On their departure the king
                    held a council, on the subject of a war with Rome, in which each spoke more
                    violently than his predecessor; for every one thought, that the more bitterly he
                    inveighed against the Romans, the greater share of favour he might expect to
                    obtain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> One animadverted upon the insolence of
                    their demands, in which they presume to impose terms on Antiochus, the greatest
                    king in Asia, as they would on the vanquished Nabis. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Although to Nabis they left absolute power over his own country, and its
                        capital, Lacedaemon, yet it seems to them a matter for indignation, that
                        Smyrna and Lampsacus should yield obedience to Antiochus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> —Others said, that <quote> to so great a
                        monarch, those cities were but a trivial ground of war, scarcely worth
                        mention; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but, that the beginning of unjust
                        impositions was always made in the case of matters of little consequence;
                        unless, indeed, it could be supposed, that the Persians, when they demanded
                        earth and water from the Lacedaemonians, stood in need of a scrap of the
                        land or a draught of the water. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        proceedings of the Romans, respecting the two cities, were meant as a trial
                        of the same sort. The rest of the states, when they saw that two had shaken
                        off the yoke, would go over to the party of that nation which professed the
                        patronage of liberty. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If freedom was not
                        actually preferable to servitude, yet the hope of bettering their
                        circumstances by a change, was more flattering to every one than any present
                        situation. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was, in the council, an Acarnanian named
                        <pb n="1571" xml:id="p.1571"/> Alexander, who had formerly been a friend of
                    Philip, but had lately left him, to follow the more opulent court of Antiochus.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And as being well skilled in the affairs
                    of Greece, and not unacquainted with the Romans, he was admitted by the king
                    into such a degree of intimacy, that he shared even in his secret councils.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As if the question to be considered were
                    not, whether there should be war or not, but where and in what manner it should
                    be carried on, he affirmed, that <quote> he saw an assured prospect of victory,
                        provided the king would pass into Europe and choose some part of Greece for
                        the seat of war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the first place, the
                        Aetolians, who lived in the centre of Greece, would be found in arms, ready
                        to take the lead in the most perilous operations. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Then, in the two extremities of Greece, Nabis, on the
                        side of Peloponnesus, would put every thing in motion, to recover the city
                        of Argos, and the maritime cities, from which he had been expelled by the
                        Romans, and pent up within the walls of Lacedaemon: <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> while, on the side of Macedonia, Philip would be ready
                        for the field the moment he heard the alarm sounded. He knew, </quote> he
                    said, <quote> his spirit, he knew his temper; he knew that, (as in the case with
                        wild beasts, confined by bars or chains,) for a long time past, he had been
                        revolving the fiercest resentments in his breast. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He remembered, also, how often, during the war, that
                        prince had prayed to all the gods to grant him Antiochus as an assistant;
                        and, if that prayer were now heard with favour, he would not hesitate an
                        instant to resume his arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was only
                        requisite that there should be no delay, no procrastination; for success
                        depended chiefly on securing beforehand commodious posts and proper allies:
                        besides, Hannibal ought to be sent immediately into Africa, in order to
                        distract the attention of the Romans. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal was not called to this consultation,
                    having become suspected by the king, and not having subsequently been held in
                    any honour, on account of his conferences with Villius, and he had not since
                    shown him any mark of regard. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This affront, at
                    first, he bore in silence; but afterwards thought it better to take some proper
                    opportunity to inquire the reason of the king's suddenly withdrawing his favour,
                    and to clear himself of blame. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Without any
                    preface, he asked the cause of the king's displeasure; and having heard it,
                    said, <quote> Antiochus, when I was yet an infant, my father, Hamilcar, <pb
                            n="1572" xml:id="p.1572"/> at a time when he was offering sacrifice,
                        brought me up to the altars, and made me take an oath, that I never would be
                        a friend to the Roman people. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Under the
                        obligation of this oath, I carried arms against them for thirty-six years;
                        this oath, on peace being made, drove me out of my country, and brought me
                        an exile to your court; and this oath shall guide me, should you disappoint
                        my hopes, until I traverse every quarter of the globe, where I can
                        understand that there are resources, to find out enemies to the Romans.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If, therefore, your courtiers have
                        conceived the idea of ingratiating themselves with you by insinuating
                        suspicions of me, let them seek some means of advancing their reputation
                        otherwise than at my expense. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I hate, and
                        am hated by, the Romans. That I speak the truth in this, my father,
                        Hamilcar, and the gods are witnesses. Whenever, therefore, you shall employ
                        your thoughts on a plan of waging war with Rome, consider Hannibal as one of
                        your firmest friends. If circumstances force you to adopt peaceful measures,
                        on such a subject employ some one else with whom to deliberate. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This discourse not only affected the king
                    much, but even reconciled him to Hannibal. They departed from the council with
                    the resolution that the war should be undertaken. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Rome, people in their conversations
                    anticipated, indeed, Antiochus as an enemy, but they had hitherto prepared
                    nothing for such a war but their expectations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Italy was decreed the province of both the consuls, who received directions to
                    settle between themselves, or draw lots, which of them should preside at the
                    elections of the year; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and it was ordered,
                    that he who should be disengaged from that business, should hold himself in
                    readiness, in case there should be occasion, to lead the legions any where out
                    of that country. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To the said consul,
                    permission was given to levy two new legions, and twenty thousand foot, and nine
                    hundred horse, among the allies and Latin confederates. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> To the other consul were decreed the two legions which had
                    been commanded by Lucius Cornelius, consul of the preceding year; and from the
                    same army, a body of allies and Latins, amounting to fifteen thousand foot and
                    five hundred horse. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Quintus Minucius was
                    continued in command, with the forces which he then had in Liguria; as a
                    supplement to which, four thousand Roman foot and five hundred horse were
                    ordered to be enlisted, and <pb n="1573" xml:id="p.1573"/> five thousand foot
                    and two hundred and fifty horse to be demanded from the allies. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The duty of departing from Italy, whithersoever the senate
                    should order, fell to Cneius Domitius; Gaul, and the holding the elections, to
                    Lucius Quinctius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The praetors then cast lots
                    for their provinces: to Marcus Fulvius Centumalus fell the city jurisdiction; to
                    Lucius Scribonius Libo, the foreign; Lucius Valerius Tappus obtained Sicily;
                    Quintus Salonius Sarra, Sardinia; Marcus Baebius Tamphilus, Hither Spain; and
                    Marcus Atilius Serranus, Farther Spain. But the provinces of the two last were
                    changed, first by a decree of the senate, which was afterwards confirmed by an
                    order of the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The fleet and Macedonia
                    were assigned to Atilius; Bruttium to Baebius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Flaminius and Fulvius were continued in command in both the Hither and
                    Farther Spain. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To Baebius Tamphilus, for the
                    business of Bruttium, were decreed the two legions which had served in the city
                    the year before; and he was ordered to demand from the allies, for the same
                    service, fifteen thousand foot and five hundred horse. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Atilius was ordered to build thirty ships of five banks of
                    oars: to bring out, from the docks, any old ones that were fit for service, and
                    to raise seamen. An order was also given to the consul, to supply him with two
                    thousand of the allied and Latin footmen, and a thousand Roman. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> The destination of these two praetors, and their two
                    armaments, one on land and the other on sea, was declared to be intended against
                    Nabis, who was now carrying on open hostilities against the allies of the Roman
                    people. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But it was thought proper to wait the
                    return of the ambassadors sent to Antiochus, and the senate ordered the consul
                    Cneius Domitius not to leave the city until they arrived. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The praetors, Fulvius and Scribonius, whose
                    province was the administration of justice at Rome, were charged to provide a
                    hundred quinqueremes, besides the fleet which Atilius was to command. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Before the consul and praetors set out for their
                    provinces, a supplication was performed on account of some prodigies. A report
                    was brought from Picenum, that a goat had produced six kids at a birth.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was said that a boy was born at
                    Arretium who had but one hand; that, at Amiternum, a shower of earth fell;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> a gate and wall at Formiae were struck by
                    lightning; and, what was more alarming than all, an ox, belonging to the consul,
                    Cneius Domitius, spoke <pb n="1574" xml:id="p.1574"/> these words, —
                        <quote>Rome, take care of thyself.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To expiate the other prodigies, a supplication
                    was performed; the ox was ordered by the aruspices to be carefully preserved and
                    fed. The Tiber, pouring into the city with more destructive violence than last
                    year, swept away two bridges, and many buildings, particularly about the
                    Flumentan gate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A huge rock, loosened from its
                    seat, either by the rains, or by an earthquake so slight that no other effect of
                    it was perceived, tumbled down from the Capitol into the Jugarian street, and
                    buried many people under it. In the country, many parts of which were
                    overflowed, much cattle was carried away, and a great destruction of farm houses
                    took place. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Previous to the arrival of the
                    consul, Lucius Quinctius, in his province, Quintus Minucius fought a pitched
                    battle with the Ligurians, in the territory of Pisae, slew nine thousand of the
                    enemy, and putting the rest to flight, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> drove
                    them within their works, which were assaulted and defended in an obstinate
                    contest until night came on. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> During the night,
                    the Ligurians stole away unobserved; and, at the first dawn, the Romans took
                    possession of their deserted camp, where the quantity of booty found was the
                    less, because the enemy frequently sent home the spoil taken in the country.
                    Minucius, after this, allowed them no respite. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> From the territory of Pisae he marched into that of the Ligurians, and, with
                    fire and sword, utterly destroyed their forts and towns, where the Roman
                    soldiers were abundantly enriched with <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> the
                    spoils of Etruria which the ravagers had sent home. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time, the ambassadors, who had been
                    sent to the kings, returned to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As they
                    brought no information of such a nature as called for any immediate declaration
                    of war, (except against the Lacedaemonian tyrant, whom the Achaean ambassadors
                    also represented as invading the sea-coast of Laconia, in breach of treaty,)
                    Atilius, the praetor, was sent with the fleet to Greece, for the protection of
                    the allies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was resolved, that, as there
                    was nothing to be apprehended from Antiochus at present, both the consuls should
                    go to their provinces; and, accordingly, Domitius marched into the country of
                    the Boians, by the shorter road, through Ariminum, and Quinctius through
                    Liguria. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The two armies of the consuls,
                    proceeding by these different routes, spread devastation wide over the enemy's
                    country. In <pb n="1575" xml:id="p.1575"/> consequence of which, first a few of
                    their horsemen, with their commanders, then their whole senate, and at last all
                    who possessed either property or dignity, to the number of one thousand five
                    hundred, came over and joined the consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In
                    both Spains, likewise, success attended the Roman arms during this year.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For, in one, Caius Flaminius, after a
                    siege, took Litabrum, a strong and opulent city, and made prisoner Corribilo, a
                    powerful chieftain; and, in the other, Marcus Fulvius, the proconsul, fought two
                    successful battles, with two armies of the enemy. He captured Vescelia and Holo,
                    two towns belonging to the Spaniards, with many of their forts, and others
                    spontaneously revolted to him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then, advancing
                    into the territory of Oretum, and having, there also, taken two cities, Noliba
                    and Cusibis, he proceeded to the river Tagus. Here stood Toletum, a small city,
                    but strong from its situation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While he was
                    besieging this place, a numerous army of Vectonians came to relieve the
                    Toletans, but he overthrew them in a general engagement, and having defeated the
                    Vectonians, took Toletum by means of his works. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this juncture the wars in which they were
                    actually engaged, caused not so great anxiety in the minds of the senate, as the
                    expectation of one with Antiochus, which had not yet commenced. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For although, through their ambassadors, they had, from
                    time to time, made careful inquiries into every particular, yet rumours, rashly
                    propagated without authentic foundation, intermixed many falsehoods with the
                    truth. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Among the rest, a report was spread,
                    that Antiochus intended, as soon as he should come into Aetolia, to send a fleet
                    immediately into Sicily. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate,
                    therefore, though they had already despatched the praetor, Atilius, with a
                    squadron to Greece, <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> yet, considering that
                    not only a military force, but also the influence of reputation, would be
                    necessary towards securing the attachment of the allies, they sent into Greece,
                    in quality of ambassadors, Titus Quinctius, Caius Octavius, Cneius Servilius,
                    and Publius Villius; at the same time ordering, in their decree, that Marcus
                    Baebius should lead forward his legions from Bruttium to Tarentum and
                    Brundusium, so that, if occasion required, he might transport them thence into
                    Macedonia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They also ordered, that Marcus
                    Fulvius, the praetor, should send a fleet of thirty ships to protect the coast
                    of Sicily; and that, whoever had the direc- <pb n="1576" xml:id="p.1576"/> tion
                    of that fleet, should be invested with supreme authority. To this commission was
                    appointed Lucius Oppius Salinator, who had been plebeian aedile the year before.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They likewise determined, that the same
                    praetor should write to his colleague, Lucius Valerius, that <quote> there was
                        reason to apprehend that the ships of king Antiochus would pass over from
                        Aetolia to Sicily; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> for which reason the
                        senate judged it proper, that, in addition to the army which he then had, he
                        should enlist tumultuary soldiers, to the number of twelve thousand foot and
                        four hundred horse, with which he might be able to defend that coast of his
                        province which lay next to Greece. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This enlistment the praetor carried on, not
                    only from Sicily, but from the circumjacent islands; and strengthened all the
                    towns on the coast which lay opposite to Greece with garrisons. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> To the rumours already current, the arrival of
                    Attalus, the brother of Eumenes, added confirmation, for he brought intelligence
                    that king Antiochus had crossed the Hellespont with his army, and that the
                    Aetolians were putting themselves into such a posture, that by the time of his
                    arrival they would be in arms. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thanks were
                    given to Eumenes, in his absence, and to Attalus, who was present; and there
                    were decreed to him free lodgings and every accommodation; that he should be
                    presented with two horses, two suits of horsemen's armour, vases of silver to a
                    hundred pounds' weight, and of gold to twenty pounds. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As one messenger after another brought
                    intelligence that the war was on the point of breaking out, it was judged
                    expedient that consuls should be elected as soon as possible. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Wherefore the senate passed a decree, that the praetor,
                    Marcus Fulvius, should instantly despatch a letter to the consul, informing him,
                    that it was the will of the senate that he should leave the command of the
                    province and army to his lieutenant-generals, and return to Rome; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> and that, when on the road, he should send on before
                    him an edict appointing the assemblies for the election of consuls. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The consul complied with the letter; and having sent
                    forward the edict, arrived at Rome. There was, this year also, a warm
                    competition, three patricians suing for one place: Publius Cornelius Scipio, son
                    to Cneius, who had suffered a disappointment the year before, Lucius Cornelius
                    Scipio, and Cneius Manlius Vulso. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    consulship was conferred on Publius Scipio, that it might <pb n="1577"
                        xml:id="p.1577"/> appear that the honour had only been delayed, and not
                    refused to a person of such character. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    plebeian colleague, joined with him, was Manius Acilius Glabrio. Next day were
                    created praetors, Lucius Aemilius Paulus, Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, Marcus Junius
                    Brutus, Aulus Cornelius Mammula, Caius Livius, and Lucius Oppius; the two last,
                    both of them, surnamed Salinator. This was the same Oppius who had conducted the
                    fleet of thirty ships to Sicily. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While the new
                    magistrates were settling the distribution of their provinces, orders were
                    despatched to Marcus Baebius to pass over, with all his forces, from Brundusium
                    to Epirus, and to keep the army stationed near Apollonia; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and Marcus Fulvius, city praetor, was commissioned to build
                    fifty new quinqueremes. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the precautions taken by the Roman
                    people to guard against every attempt of Antiochus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> At this time, Nabis did not procrastinate hostilities, but,
                    with his utmost force, carried on the siege of Gythium; and, being incensed
                    against the Achaeans, for having sent succours to the besieged, he ravaged their
                    lands. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Achaeans would not venture to
                    engage in war, until their ambassadors should come back from Rome, and acquaint
                    them with the sentiments of the senate: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but as
                    soon as these returned, they summoned a council at Sicyon, and also sent
                    deputies to Titus Quinctius to ask his advice. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In the council, all the members were inclined to vote for an immediate
                    declaration of war; but a letter from Titus Quinctius, in which he recommended
                    waiting for the Roman praetor and fleet, caused some hesitation. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> While some of the principal members persisted in
                    their first opinion, and others argued that they ought to follow the counsel of
                    the person to whom they of themselves had applied for advice, the generality
                    waited to hear the sentiments of Philopœmen. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    He was praetor of Achaia at the time, and surpassed all his contemporaries both
                    in wisdom and influence. He first observed, that <quote> it was a wise rule,
                        established among the Achaeans, that their praetor, when he proposed a
                        question concerning war, should not himself declare an opinion: </quote> and
                    then he desired them to <quote>fix their determination among themselves as soon
                        as possible;</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> assuring them, that <quote> their praetor
                        would faithfully and carefully carry their decrees into execution; and would
                        use his best endeavours, that, as far <pb n="1578" xml:id="p.1578"/> as
                        depended on human prudence, they should not repent either of peace or war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These words had more influence in inciting
                    them to war, than if, by openly arguing in favour of it, he had betrayed an
                    eager desire for the management of it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> War
                    was therefore unanimously resolved on: the time and mode of conducting it were
                    left to the praetor without restriction. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Philopœmen's own judgment, indeed, besides it being the opinion of Quinctius,
                    pointed it out as best to wait for the Roman fleet, which might succour Gythium
                    by sea; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but fearing that the business would
                    not endure delay, and that not only Gythium, but the party which had been sent
                    to protect the city, would fall into the hands of the enemy, he drew out the
                    ships of the Achaeans. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The tyrant also, with the view of cutting off
                    any supplies that might be brought to the besieged by sea, had fitted out a
                    small squadron, consisting of only three ships of war, with some barks and
                    cutters, as his former fleet had been given up to the Romans, according to the
                    treaty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In order to try the activity of these
                    vessels, as they were then new, and, at the same time, to have every thing in
                    fit condition for a battle, he put out to sea every day, and exercised both the
                    rowers and marines in mock-fights; for he thought that all his hopes of
                    succeeding in the siege depended on the circumstance of his cutting off all
                    supplies by sea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The praetor of the Achaeans,
                    in respect of skill for conducting operations on land, was equal to any of the
                    most celebrated commanders both in capacity and experience, yet with naval
                    affairs he was quite unacquainted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Being an
                    inhabitant of Arcadia, an inland country, he was ignorant even of all foreign
                    affairs, excepting that he had once served in Crete as commander of a body of
                    auxiliaries. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was an old ship of four
                    banks of oars, which had been taken eighty years before, as it was conveying
                    Nicaea, the wife of Craterus, from Naupactum to Corinth. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Led by the reputation of this ship, for it had formerly
                    been reckoned a very famous vessel when in the king's fleet, he ordered it,
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> though now quite rotten, and falling
                    asunder through age, to be brought out from Aegium. The fleet sailed with this
                    ship at its head, Tiso of Patrae, the commander, being on board it, when the
                    ships of the Lacedaemonians from Gythium came within view. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> At the first shock, against a new and firm vessel, that old
                    one, which before ad- <pb n="1579" xml:id="p.1579"/> mitted the water through
                    every joint, was shattered to pieces, and the whole crew were made prisoners. On
                    the loss of the commander's ship, the rest of the fleet fled as fast as each
                    could by means of its oars. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Philopœmen himself
                    made his escape in a light advice-boat, nor did he stop his flight until he
                    arrived at Patrae. This untoward event did not in the least damp the spirit of a
                    man so well versed in military affairs, and who had experienced so many
                    vicissitudes of fortune. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the contrary, as
                    he had failed of success in the naval line, in which he had no experience, he
                    even conceived, thence, the greater hopes of succeeding in another, wherein he
                    had acquired knowledge; and he affirmed, that he would quickly put an end to the
                    tyrant's rejoicing. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nabis, being both elated by this adventure,
                    and entertaining a confident hope that he had not now any danger to apprehend
                    from the sea, resolved to shut up the passages on the land also, by parties
                    stationed in proper posts. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With this view, he
                    drew off a third part of his forces from the siege of Gythium, and encamped them
                    at Pleiae, a place which commands both Leucae and Acriae, on the road by which
                    the enemy's army seemed likely to advance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    While his quarters were here, and very few of his men had tents, (the generality
                    of them having formed huts of reeds interwoven, and which they covered with
                    leaves of trees, to serve merely as <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> a
                    shelter,) Philopœmen, before he came within sight, resolved to surprise him by
                    an attack of such a kind as he did not expect. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    He drew together some small ships in a remote creek, on the coast of the
                    territory of Argos, and embarked on board them a body of light-armed soldiers,
                    mostly targeteers, furnished with slings, javelins, and other light kinds of
                    weapons. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then coasted along the shore,
                    until he came to a promontory near Nabis's post. Here he landed; and made his
                    way, by night, through paths with which he was well acquainted, to Pleiae, and
                    while the sentinels were fast asleep, as being in no immediate apprehension, he
                    set fire to the huts in every part of the camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Great numbers perished in the flames before they could discover the enemy's
                    arrival, and those who did discover it could give no assistance; so that nearly
                    the whole was destroyed by fire and sword. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    From both these means of destruction, however, a very small number made their
                    escape, and fled to the principal camp before Gythium. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The enemy <pb n="1580" xml:id="p.1580"/> having been thus
                    smitten with disaster, Philopœmen forthwith led on his forces to ravage the
                    district of Tripolis, a part of the Lacedaemonian territory, lying <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> next to the frontiers of the Megalopolitans, and
                    carrying off thence a vast number of men and cattle, withdrew before the tyrant
                    could send a force from Gythium to protect the country. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> He then collected his whole force at Tegea, to which place
                    he summoned a council of the Achaeans and their allies; at which were present,
                    also, deputies from the Epirots and Acarnanians. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Here it was resolved, that as the minds of his men were now
                    sufficiently recovered from the shame of the disgrace suffered at sea, and those
                    of the enemy dispirited, he should march directly to Lacedaemon; for he
                    considered that by this measure alone could the enemy be drawn off from the
                    siege of Gythium. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On entering the enemy's
                    country, he encamped the first day at Caryae; and, on that very day, Gythium was
                    taken. Ignorant of that event, Philopœmen advanced to the Barbosthenes, a
                    mountain ten miles from Lacedaemon. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> On the
                    other side, Nabis, after taking possession of Gythium, set out, at the head of a
                    body of light troops, marched hastily by Lacedaemon, and seized on a place
                    called the Camp of Pyrrhus, which post he did not doubt that the Achaeans
                    intended to occupy. From thence he proceeded to meet the enemy. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> From the length of their train in consequence of the
                    narrowness of the road, they spread over a space of almost five miles. The line
                    was closed by the cavalry and the greatest part of the auxiliaries, because
                    Philopœmen expected that the tyrant would attack him in the rear with his
                    mercenary troops, in whom he placed his principal confidence. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> Two unforeseen circumstances at once filled him with
                    uneasiness: one, the post at which he aimed being pre-occupied; the other, the
                    enemy having met him in front, where, as the road lay through very uneven
                    ground, he did not see how the battalions could advance without the support of
                    the light troops. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philopœmen was possessed of an admirable
                    degree of skill and experience, in conducting a march, and choosing his station;
                    having made these points his principal study, not only in times of war, but
                    likewise during peace. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whenever he was making
                    a journey to any place and came to a defile where the passage was difficult, it
                    was his practice, first, to examine the nature of the ground on every side. When
                        <pb n="1581" xml:id="p.1581"/> journeying alone, he meditated within
                    himself; if he had company, he asked them, <quote> If an enemy should appear in
                        that place, what course ought he to adopt, if they should attack him in
                        front; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> what, if on this flank, or on that;
                        what, if on the rear; for he might happen to meet them while his men were
                        formed with a regular front, or when they were in the loose order of march,
                        fit only for the road. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He would proceed to examine, either in his own
                    mind, or by asking questions, <quote> What ground he himself would choose; what
                        number of soldiers, or what kind of arms (which was a very material point)
                        he ought to employ; where he should deposit the baggage, where the soldiers'
                        necessaries, where the unarmed multitude; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        with what number and what kind of troops he should guard them, and whether
                        it would be better to prosecute his march as intended, or to return back by
                        the way he came; what spot, also, he should choose for his camp; how large a
                        space he should enclose within the lines; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        where he could be conveniently supplied with water; where a sufficiency of
                        forage and wood could be had; which would be his safest road on decamping
                        next day, and in what form the army should march? </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In such studies and inquiries he had, from his
                    early years, so frequently exercised his thoughts, that, on any thing of the
                    kind occurring, no expedient that could be devised was new to him. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> On this occasion, he first ordered the army to halt;
                    then sent forward to the van the auxiliary Cretans, and the horsemen called
                    Tarentines, each leading two spare horses; and, ordering the rest of the cavalry
                    to follow, he seized on a rock which stood over a rivulet, from which he might
                    be supplied with water. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Here he collected
                    together all the baggage with all the suttlers and followers of the army,
                    placing a guard of soldiers round them; and then he fortified his camp, as the
                    nature of the place required. The pitching of tents in such rugged and uneven
                    ground was a difficult task. The enemy were distant not more than five hundred
                    paces. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Both drew water from the same rivulet,
                    under escorts of light troops; but, before any skirmish took place, as usual
                    between men encamped so near to each other, night came on. It was evident,
                    however, that they must, unavoidably, fight next day at the rivulet, in support
                    of the watering parties. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Wherefore, during
                    the night, Philopœmen concealed, in a <pb n="1582" xml:id="p.1582"/> valley
                    remote from the view of the enemy, as great a number of targeteers as the place
                    was capable of hiding. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At break of day, the Cretan light infantry and
                    the Tarentine horse began an engagement on the bank of the rivulet. Telemnastus,
                    a Cretan, commanded his countrymen; Lycortas of Megalopolis, the cavalry.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The enemies' watering party also was
                    guarded by Cretan auxiliaries and Tarentine horsemen. The fight was, for a
                    considerable time, doubtful, as the troops on both sides were of the same kind,
                    and armed alike; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but as the contest advanced,
                    the tyrant's auxiliaries gained an advantage, both by their superiority of
                    numbers, and because Philopœmen had given directions to his officers, that,
                    after maintaining the contest for a short time, they should betake themselves to
                    flight, and draw the enemy on to the place of the ambuscade. The latter,
                    pursuing the runaways, in disorderly haste, through the valley, were most of
                    them wounded and slain, before they discovered their concealed foe. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The targeteers had posted themselves in such order,
                    as far as the breadth of the valley allowed, that they easily gave a passage to
                    their flying friends, through openings in their ranks; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> then starting up themselves, hale, fresh, and in regular
                    order, they briskly attacked the enemy, whose ranks were broken, who were
                    scattered in confusion, and were, besides, exhausted with fatigue and wounds.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The victory was no longer doubtful; the
                    tyrant's troops instantly turned their backs, and flying with much more
                    precipitation than they had pursued, were driven into their camp. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Great numbers were killed and taken in the pursuit;
                    and the consternation would have spread through the camp also, had not
                    Philopœmen ordered a retreat to be sounded; for he dreaded the ground (which was
                    rough and dangerous to advance on without caution) more than he did the enemy.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Judging, both from the issue of the battle
                    and from the disposition of the enemy's leader, in what apprehension he then
                    was, he sent to him one of the auxiliary soldiers in the character of a
                    deserter, to assure him positively, that the Achaeans had resolved <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> to advance, next day, to the river Eurotas, which
                    runs almost close to the walls, in order to intercept his way, so that the
                    tyrant could have no retreat to the city when he required it, and to prevent any
                    provisions being brought thence to the <pb n="1583" xml:id="p.1583"/> camp;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that they intended, at the same time,
                    to try whether any could be prevailed on to desert his cause. Although the
                    deserter did not gain entire credit, yet he afforded to one, who was full of
                    apprehensions, a plausible pretext for leaving his camp. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> On the day following, he ordered Pythagoras, with the
                    auxiliaries and cavalry, to mount guard before the rampart; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and then, marching out himself with the main body of the
                    army, as if intending to offer battle, he ordered them to return with all haste
                    to the city. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Philopœmen saw their army marching
                    precipitately through a narrow and steep road, he sent all his cavalry, together
                    with the Cretan auxiliaries, against the guard of the enemy, stationed in the
                    front of their camp. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These, seeing their
                    adversaries approach, and perceiving that their friends had abandoned them, at
                    first attempted to retreat within their works; but afterwards, when the whole
                    force of the Achaeans advanced in order of battle, they were seized with fear,
                    lest, together with the camp itself, they might be taken; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> they resolved, therefore, to follow the body of their army,
                    which, by this time, had proceeded to a considerable distance in advance.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Immediately, the targeteers of the
                    Achaeans assailed and plundered the camp, and the rest set out in pursuit of the
                    enemy. The road was such, that a body of men, even when undisturbed by any fear
                    of a foe, could not, without difficulty, make its way through it. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> But when an attack was made on their rear, and the
                    shouts of terror, raised by the affrighted troops behind, reached to the van,
                    they threw down their arms, and fled, each for himself, in different directions,
                    into the woods which lay on each side of the road. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> In an instant of time, the way was stopped up with heaps of
                    weapons, particularly spears, which, falling mostly with their points towards
                    the pursuers, formed a kind of palisade across the road. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Philopœmen ordered the auxiliaries to push forward,
                    whenever they could, in pursuit of the enemy, who would find it a difficult
                    matter, the horsemen particularly, to continue their flight; while he himself
                    led away the heavy troops through more open ground to the river Eurotas.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There he pitched his camp a little before
                    sun-set, and waited for the light troops which he had sent in chase of the
                    enemy. These arrived at the first watch, and brought intelligence, that Nabis,
                    with a few attendants, had made his way into the city, <pb n="1584"
                        xml:id="p.1584"/> and that the rest of his army, unarmed and dispersed, were
                    straggling through all parts of the woods; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    whereupon, he ordered them to refresh themselves, while he himself chose out a
                    party of men, who, having come earlier into camp, were, by this time, both
                    recruited by food and a little rest; and, ordering them to carry nothing with
                    them but their swords, he marched them out directly, and posted them in the
                    roads which led from two of the gates, one towards Pherae, the other towards the
                    Barbosthenes: for he supposed, that through these the flying enemy would make
                    their retreat. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor was he mistaken in that
                    opinion; for the Lacedaemonians, as long as any light remained, retreated
                    through the centre of the woods in the most retired paths. As soon as it grew
                    dusk, and they saw lights in the enemy's camp, they kept themselves in paths
                    concealed from view; but having passed it by, they then thought that all was
                    safe, and came down into the open roads, where they were intercepted by the
                    parties lying in wait; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and there such numbers
                    of them were killed and taken, that of the whole army scarcely a fourth part
                    effected their escape. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As the tyrant was now
                    pent up within the city, Philopœmen employed the greatest part of thirty
                    succeeding days in ravaging the lands of the Lacedaemonians; and then, after
                    greatly reducing, and almost annihilating the strength of the tyrant, he
                    returned home, while the Achaeans extolled him as equal in the glory of his
                    services to the Roman general, and indeed, so far as regarded the war with
                    Lacedaemon, even deemed him superior. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the Achaeans and the tyrant were
                    carrying on the war in this manner, the Roman ambassadors made a circuit through
                    the cities of the allies; being anxious lest the Aetolians might seduce some of
                    them to join the party of Antiochus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They took
                    but little pains, in their applications to the Achaeans; because, knowing their
                    animosity against Nabis, they thought that they might be safely relied on with
                    regard to other matters. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They went first to
                    Athens, thence to Chalcis, thence to Thessaly; and, after addressing the
                    Thessalians, in a full assembly, they directed their route to Demetrias, to
                    which place a council of the Magnetians was summoned. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> There a more studied address required to be delivered; for
                    a great many of the leading men were disaffected to the Romans, and entirely
                    devoted to the interests of An- <pb n="1585" xml:id="p.1585"/> tiochus and the
                    Aetolians; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> because, at the time when accounts
                    were received that Philip's son, who was a hostage, would be restored to him,
                    and the tribute imposed on him remitted, among other groundless reports it had
                    been given out, that the Romans also intended to restore Demetrias to him.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Rather than that should take place,
                    Eurylochus, a deputy of the Magnetians, and others of that faction, wished for a
                    total change of measures to be effected by the coning of Antiochus and the
                    Aetolians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In opposition to those, it was
                    necessary to reason in such a manner, that, in dispelling their mistaken fear,
                    the ambassadors should not, by cutting off his hopes at once, give any disgust
                    to Philip, to whom more importance attached, in all respects, than to the
                    Magnetians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They only observed to the
                    assembly, that, <quote> as Greece in general was under an obligation to the
                        Romans for their kindness in restoring its liberty, so was their state in
                        particular. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For there had not only been a
                        garrison of Macedonians in their capital, but a palace had been built in it,
                        that they might have a master continually before their eyes. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> But all that had been done would be of no
                        effect, if the Aetolians should bring thither Antiochus, and settle him in
                        the abode of Philip, so that a new and unknown king should be set over them,
                        in the place of an old one, with whom they had been long acquainted. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Their chief magistrate is styled Magnetarch.
                    This office was then held by Eurylochus, who assuming confidence from this
                    powerful station, openly declared that he and the Magnetians saw no reason to
                    dissemble their having heard the common report about the restoration of
                    Demetrias to Philip; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> to prevent which, the
                    Magnetians were bound to attempt and to hazard every thing; and, in the
                    eagerness of discourse, he was carried to such an inconsiderate length, as to
                    throw out, that, <quote> at that very time Demetrias was only free in
                        appearance; and that, in reality, all things were at the nod of the Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Immediately after this expression there was a
                    general murmur of dissent in the assembly; some of whom showed their
                    approbation, others expressed indignation at his presumption, in uttering it. As
                    to Quinctius, he was so inflamed with anger, that, raising his hands towards
                    heaven, he invoked the gods to witness the ungrateful and perfidious disposition
                    of the Magnetians. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> This struck terror into
                    the whole assembly; and one of the deputies, named Zeno, who <pb n="1586"
                        xml:id="p.1586"/> had acquired a great degree of influence, by his judicious
                    course of conduct in life, and by having been always an avowed supporter of the
                    interests of the Romans, with tears besought Quinctius, and the other
                    ambassadors, <quote> not to impute to the state the madness of an individual.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Every man, </quote> he said, <quote>
                        was answerable for his own absurdities. As to the Magnetians, they were
                        indebted to Titus Quinctius and the Roman people, not only for liberty, but
                        for every thing that mankind hold valuable or sacred. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> By their kindness, they were in the enjoyment of every
                        blessing, for which they could ever petition the immortal gods; and, if
                        struck with phrensy, they would sooner vent their fury on their own persons,
                        than violate the friendship with Rome. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> His entreaties were seconded by the prayers of
                    the whole assembly; on which Eurylochus retired hastily from the council, and
                    passing to the gate through private streets, fled away into Aetolia. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> As to the Aetolians, they now gave plainer
                    indications of their intention to revolt every day; and it happened, that at
                    this very time Thoas, one of their leading men, whom they had sent to Antiochus,
                    returned, and brought back with him an ambassador from the king, named Menippus.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These two, before the council met to give
                    them audience, filled every one's ears with pompous accounts of the naval and
                    land forces that were coming; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>a vast army,</quote> they said, <quote> of horse and foot was on its
                        march from India; and, besides, that they were bringing such a quantity of
                        gold and silver, as was sufficient to purchase the Romans themselves;
                    </quote> which latter circumstance they knew would influence the multitude more
                    than any thing else. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was easy to foresee
                    what effects these reports would produce in the council; for the Roman
                    ambassadors received information of the arrival of those men, and of all their
                    proceedings. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And although the matter had
                    almost come to a rupture, yet Quinctius thought it advisable, that some
                    ambassadors of the allies should be present in that council, who might remind
                    the Aetolians of their alliance with Rome, and who might have the courage to
                    speak with freedom in opposition to the king's ambassador. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The Athenians seemed to be the best qualified for this
                    purpose, by reason of the high reputation of their state, and also from their
                    long-standing alliance with the Aetolians. Quinctius, therefore, requested of
                    them to send ambassadors to the <pb n="1587" xml:id="p.1587"/> Panaetolic
                    council. At the first meeting, Thoas made a report of the business of his
                    embassy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After him, Menippus was introduced,
                    who said, that <quote> it would have been best for all the Greeks, residing both
                        in Greece and Asia, if Antiochus could have taken a part in their affairs,
                        while the power of Philip was yet unbroken; <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> for then every one would have had what of right belonged to him, and the
                        whole would not have come under the dominion and absolute disposal of the
                        Romans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But even as matters stand at
                        present, </quote> said he, <quote> provided you have constancy enough to
                        carry into effect the measures which you have adopted, Antiochus will be
                        able, with the assistance of the gods and the alliance of the Aetolians, to
                        reinstate the affairs of Greece in their former rank of dignity,
                        notwithstanding the low condition to which they have been reduced.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But this dignity consists in a state
                        of freedom which stands by its own resources, and is not dependent on the
                        will of another. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Athenians, who were permitted to deliver
                    their sentiments next after the king's ambassadors, omitting all mention of
                    Antiochus, reminded the Aetolians of their alliance with Rome, and the benefits
                    conferred by Titus Quinctius on the whole body of Greece; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> and admonished them, <quote> not inconsiderately to break
                        off that connexion by the undue precipitation of their counsels; that
                        passionate and adventurous schemes, however flattering at first view, prove
                        difficult in the execution, and disastrous in the issue; <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> that as the Roman ambassadors, and among them Titus
                        Quinctius, were within a small distance, it would be better, while all
                        hostilities were as yet uncommenced, to discuss, in conference, any matters
                        in dispute, than to rouse Europe and Asia to a dreadful war. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The multitude, ever fond of novelty, warmly
                    espoused the cause of Antiochus, and gave their opinion, that the Romans should
                    not even be admitted into the council; but, by the influence chiefly of the
                    elder members, a vote was passed, that the council should give audience to the
                    Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On being acquainted, by the Athenians,
                    with this determination, Quinctius thought it desirable to go into Aetolia;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for he thought that, <quote> either he
                        should be able to effect some change in their designs; or that it would be
                        manifest to all mankind, that the blame of the war would lie on the
                        Aetolians, and that the Romans would be warranted in taking arms by justice,
                        and, <pb n="1588" xml:id="p.1588"/> in a manner, by necessity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On arriving there, Quinctius, in his discourse
                    to the council, began with the first formation of the alliance between the
                    Romans and the Aetolians, and enumerated how many times the faith of the treaty
                    had been violated by them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then enlarged a
                    little on the rights of the states concerned in the dispute, and added, that,
                        <quote> notwithstanding, if they thought that they had any reasonable demand
                        to make, it would surely be infinitely better to send <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> ambassadors to Rome, whether they chose to argue the
                        case or to make a request to the senate, than that the Roman people should
                        enter the lists with Antiochus, while the Aetolians acted as marshals of the
                        field; not without great disturbance to the affairs of the world, and to the
                        utter ruin of Greece. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That <quote> no people would feel the fatal
                        consequences of such a war sooner than the first promoters of it. </quote>
                    This prediction of the Roman was disregarded. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Thoas, and others of the same faction, were then heard with general approbation;
                    and they prevailed so far, that, without adjourning the meeting, or waiting for
                    the absence of the Romans, a decree was passed that Antiochus should be invited
                    to vindicate the liberty of Greece, and decide the dispute between the Aetolians
                    and the Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To the insolence of this
                    decree, their praetor, Damocritus, added a personal affront: for on Quinctius
                    asking him for a copy of the decree, without any respect to the dignity of the
                    person to whom he spoke, he told him, that <quote> he had, at present, more
                        pressing business to despatch; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but he
                        would shortly give him the decree, and an answer, in Italy, from his camp on
                        the banks of the Tiber. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such was the degree of madness which
                    possessed, at that time, both the nation of the Aetolians and their magistrates. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius and the ambassadors returned to
                    Corinth. The Aetolians, that they might appear to intend taking every step
                    through Antiochus, and none directly of themselves, and, sitting inactive, to be
                    waiting for the arrival of the king, though <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    they did not, after the departure of the Romans, hold a council of the whole
                    nation, yet endeavoured, by their Apocleti, (a more confidential council,
                    composed of persons selected from the rest,) to devise schemes for setting
                    Greece in commotion. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was well known to them
                    all, that in the several states the principal people, particularly those of the
                    best characters, were disposed to maintain the Roman alliance, and well pleased
                        <pb n="1589" xml:id="p.1589"/> with the present state of affairs; but that
                    the populace, and especially such as were not content with their position,
                    wished for a general revolution. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    Aetolians, at one day's sitting, formed a scheme, the very conception of which
                    argued not only boldness, but impudence, —that of making themselves masters of
                    Demetrias, Chalcis, and Lacedaemon. One of their principal men was sent to each
                    of these places; Thoas to Chalcis, Alexamenus to Lacedaemon, Diocles to
                    Demetrias. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This last was assisted by the exile
                    Eurylochus, whose flight, and the cause of it, have been mentioned above,
                    because there was no other prospect of his restoration to his country.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Eurylochus, by letter, instructed his
                    friends and relations, and those of his own faction, to order his wife and
                    children to assume a mourning dress: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and,
                    holding the badges of supplicants, to go into a full assembly, and to beseech
                    each individual, and the whole body, not to suffer a man, who was innocent and
                    uncondemned, to grow old in exile. The simpleminded were moved by compassion;
                    the ill-disposed and seditious, by the hope of seeing all things thrown into
                    confusion, in consequence of the tumults which the Aetolians would excite; and
                    every one voted for his being recalled. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These
                    preparatory measures being effected, Diocles, at that time general of the horse,
                    with all the cavalry, set out under pretext of escorting to his home the exile,
                    who was his guest. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having, during that day and
                    the following night, marched an extraordinary length of way, and arrived within
                    six miles of the city at the first dawn, he chose out three troops, at the head
                    of which he went on before the rest of the cavalry, whom he ordered to follow.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When he came near the gate he made all
                    his men dismount, and lead their horses by the reins, without keeping their
                    ranks, but like travellers on a journey, in order that they might appear to be
                    the retinue of the general, rather than a military force. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Here he left one troop at the gate, lest the cavalry, who
                    were coming up, might be shut out; and then, holding Eurylochus by the hand,
                    conducted him to his house through the middle of the city and the forum, and
                    through crowds who met and congratulated him. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In a little time the city was filled with horsemen, and convenient posts were
                    seized; and then parties were sent to the houses of persons of the opposite
                    faction, to put them to death. In this manner Demetrias fell into the hands of
                    the Aetolians. <pb n="1590" xml:id="p.1590"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Lacedaemon, the city was not to be
                    attempted by force, but the tyrant to be entrapped by stratagem. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For though he had been stripped of the maritime towns
                    by the Romans, and afterwards shut up within the walls of his city by the
                    Achaeans, they supposed that whoever took the first opportunity of killing him
                    would engross the whole thanks of the Lacedaemonians. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The pretence which they had for sending to him, was, that
                    he had long solicited assistance from them, since, by their advice, he had
                    renewed the war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A thousand foot were put
                    under the command of Alexamenus, with thirty horsemen, chosen from among the
                    youth. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These received a charge from
                    Damocritus, the praetor, in the select council of the nation, mentioned above,
                        <quote> not to suppose that they were sent to a war with the Achaeans; or
                        even on other business, which any one might ascertain to himself from his
                        own conjectures. Whatever sudden enterprise circumstances might direct
                        Alexamenus to undertake, that (however unexpected, rash, or daring) they
                        were to hold themselves in readiness to execute with implicit obedience; and
                        should understand that to be the matter, for the sole purpose of effecting
                        which they had been sent abroad. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With these men, thus pre-instructed,
                    Alexamenus came to the tyrant, and, immediately on approaching him, filled him
                    with hopes; telling him, that <quote> Antiochus had already come over into
                        Europe; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that he would shortly be in
                        Greece, and would cover the lands and seas with men and arms; that the
                        Romans would find that they had not Philip to deal with: that the numbers of
                        the horsemen, footmen, and ships, could not be reckoned; and that the train
                        of elephants, by their mere appearance, would effectually daunt the enemy:
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that the Aetolians were prepared to
                        come to Lacedaemon with their entire force, whenever occasion required; but
                        that they wished to show the king, on his arrival, a numerous body of
                        troops: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that Nabis himself, likewise,
                        ought to take care not to suffer his soldiers to be enervated by inaction,
                        and dwelling in houses; but to lead them out, and make them perform their
                        evolutions under arms, which, while it exercised their bodies, would also
                        rouse their courage; that the labour would become lighter by practice, and
                        might even be rendered not unpleasing by the affability and kindness of
                        their commander. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thenceforward, the troops used frequently to
                    be drawn out under the walls of the city, <pb n="1591" xml:id="p.1591"/> in a
                    plain near the river Eurotas. The tyrant's life-guards were generally posted in
                    the centre. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He himself, attended by three
                    horsemen at the most, of whom Alexamenus was commonly one, rode about in front,
                    and went to view both wings to their extremities. On the right wing were the
                    Aetolians; both those who had been before in his army as auxiliaries, and the
                    thousand who came with Alexamenus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Alexamenus
                    made it his custom to ride about with Nabis through a few of the ranks, offering
                    such advice as seemed most suitable; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> then to
                    join his own troops in the right wing; and presently after, as if having given
                    the orders which the occasion might require, to return to the tyrant. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> But, on the day which he had fixed for the
                    perpetration of the deed of death, after accompanying the tyrant for a little
                    time, he withdrew to his own soldiers, and addressed the horsemen, sent from
                    home with him, in these words: <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Young men, that deed is now to be dared and done which you were ordered
                        to execute valiantly under my guidance. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        Have your courage and your hands ready, that none may fail to second me in
                        whatever he sees me attempt. If any one shall hesitate, and prefer any
                        scheme of his own to mine, let him rest assured that there is no return to
                        his home for him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Horror seized them all, and they well
                    remembered the charge which they had received at setting out. The tyrant was now
                    coming from the left wing. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Alexamenus ordered
                    his horsemen to rest their lances, and keep their eyes fixed on him; and in the
                    mean time he himself re-collected his spirits, which had been discomposed by the
                    meditation of such a desperate attempt. As soon as the tyrant came near, he
                    charged him; and driving his spear through his horse, brought the rider to the
                    ground. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The horsemen aimed their lances at
                    him as he lay, and after many ineffectual strokes against his coat of mail,
                    their points at length penetrated his body, so that, before relief could be sent
                    from the centre, he expired. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Alexamenus, with all the Aetolians, hastened
                    away, to seize on the palace. Nabis's life-guards were at first struck with
                    horror, the act being <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> perpetrated before
                    their eyes; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> then, when they observed the
                    Aetolian troops leaving the place, they gathered round the tyrant's body, where
                    it was left, forming, instead of guardians of his life or avengers of his death,
                    a mere group of spectators. Nor would any one have stirred, <pb n="1592"
                        xml:id="p.1592"/> if Alexamenus had immediately called the people to an
                    assembly, and, with his arms laid aside, there made a speech suitable to the
                    occasion, and afterwards kept a good number of Aetolians in arms, without
                    violence being offered to any one. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Instead of
                    which, by a fatality which ought to attend all designs founded in treachery,
                    every step was taken that could tend to hasten the destruction of those who had
                    committed it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The commander, shut up in the
                    palace, wasted a day and a night in searching out the tyrant's treasures; and
                    the Aetolians, as if they had stormed the city, of which they wished to be
                    thought the deliverers, betook themselves to plunder. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The insolence of their behaviour, and at the same time
                    contempt of their numbers, gave the Lacedaemonians courage to assemble in a
                    body, when some said, that they ought to drive out the Aetolians, and resume
                    their liberty, which had been ravished from them at the very time when it seemed
                    to be restored; others, that, for the sake of appearance, they ought to
                    associate with them some one of the royal family, as the director of their
                    efforts. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There was a very young boy of that
                    family, named Laconicus, who had been educated with the tyrant's children; him
                    they mounted on a horse, and taking arms, slew all the Aetolians whom they met
                    straggling through the city. They then assaulted the palace, where they killed
                    Alexamenus, who, with a small party, attempted resistance. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Others of the Aetolians, who had collected together round
                    the Chalciaecon, that is, the brazen temple of Minerva, were cut to pieces. A
                    few, throwing away their arms, fled, some to Tegea, others to Megalopolis, where
                    they were seized by the magistrates, and sold as slaves. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Philopœmen, as soon as he heard of the murder of the
                    tyrant, went to Lacedaemon, where, finding all in confusion and consternation,
                    he called together the principal inhabitants, to whom he addressed a discourse,
                    (such as ought to have been made by Alexamenus,) and united the Lacedaemonians
                    to the confederacy of the Achaeans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To this
                    they were the more easily persuaded, because, at that very juncture, Aulus
                    Atilius happened to arrive at Gythium with twenty-four quinqueremes. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, Thoas, in his attempt on Chalcis,
                    had by no means the same good fortune <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> as
                    Eurylochus had in getting possession of Demetrias; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> although, (by the intervention of Euthymidas, a man of
                    considerable consequence, who, after the <pb n="1593" xml:id="p.1593"/> arrival
                    of Titus Quinctius and the ambassadors, had been banished by those who adhered
                    to the Roman alliance; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and also of Herodorus,
                    who was a merchant of Cios, and who, by means of his wealth, possessed a
                    powerful influence at Chalcis,) he had engaged a party, composed of Euthymidas's
                    faction, to betray the city into his hands. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Euthymidas went from Athens, where he had fixed his residence, first to Thebes,
                    and thence to Salganea; Herodorus to Thronium. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    At a small distance, on the Malian bay, Thoas had two thousand foot and two
                    hundred horse, with as many as thirty light transport ships. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> With these vessels, carrying six hundred footmen, Herodorus
                    was ordered to sail to the island of Atalanta, that, as soon as he should
                    perceive the land forces approaching Aulus and the Euripus, he might pass over
                    from thence to Chalcis; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> to which place Thoas
                    himself led the rest of his forces, marching mostly by <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> night, and with all possible expedition. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mictio and Xenoclides, who were now, since the
                    banishment of Euthymidas, in possession of the supreme power, either of
                    themselves suspected the matter, or received some information of it, and were at
                    first so greatly terrified, that they saw no prospect of safety but in flight;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> but afterwards, when their fright
                    subsided, and they considered that, by such a step, they would betray and desert
                    not only their country, but the Roman alliance, they applied their minds to the
                    following plan. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It happened that, at that very
                    time, there was a solemn anniversary festival, celebrated at Eretria, in honour
                    of Diana Amarynthis, which was always attended by great numbers, not only of the
                    natives, but also of the Carystians: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> thither
                    they sent envoys to beseech the Eretrians and Carystians, <quote> as having been
                        born in the same isle, to compassionate their situation; and, at the same
                        time, to show their regard to the friendship of Rome: not to suffer Chalcis
                        to become the property of the Aetolians; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        that if they should possess Chalcis they would obtain possession of all
                        Eubœa: and to remind them, that they had found the Macedonians grievous
                        masters, but that the Aetolians would be much more intolerable. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consideration of the Romans chiefly
                    influenced those states, as they had lately experienced both their bravery in
                    war, and their justice and liberality in success. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Both states, therefore, armed, and sent the main strength
                    of their young men. To these the people of Chalcis <pb n="1594" xml:id="p.1594"
                    /> intrusted the defence of the walls, and they themselves, with their whole
                    force, crossed the Euripus, and encamped at Salganea. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> From that place they despatched, first a herald, and
                    afterwards ambassadors, to ask the Aetolians, for what word or act of theirs,
                    friends and allies came thus to invade them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Thoas, commander of the Aetolians, answered, that <quote> he came not to attack
                        them, but to deliver them from the Romans; that they were fettered at
                        present with a brighter chain indeed, but a much heavier one, than when they
                        had a Macedonian garrison in their citadel. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The men of Chalcis replied, that <quote>they
                        were neither under bondage to any one, nor in need of the protection of
                        any.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The ambassadors then withdrew from the
                    meeting, and returned to their countrymen. Thoas and the Aetolians (who had no
                    other hopes than in <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> a sudden surprise, and
                    were by no means in a capacity to undertake a regular war, and the siege of a
                    city so well secured against any attack from the land or the sea) returned home.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Euthymidas, on hearing that his
                    countrymen were encamped at Salganea, and that the Aetolians had retired, went
                    back from Thebes to Athens. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Herodorus, after
                    waiting several days at Atalanta, attentively watching for the concerted signal
                    in vain, sent an advice-boat to learn the cause of the delay; and, understanding
                    that the enterprise was abandoned by his associates, returned to Thronium from
                    whence he had come. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius, having been informed of these
                    proceedings, came with the fleet from Corinth, and met Eumenes in the Euripus of
                    Chalcis. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was agreed between them, that king
                    Eumenes should leave there five hundred of his soldiers, for the purpose of a
                    garrison, and should go himself to Athens. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Quinctius proceeded to Demetrias, as he had purposed from the first, hoping that
                    the relief of Chalcis would prove a strong inducement to the Magnetians to renew
                    the alliance with Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And, in order that
                    such of them as favoured his views might have some support at hand, he wrote to
                    Eunomus, praetor of the Thessalians, to arm the youth; sending Villius forward
                    to Demetrias, to sound the inclinations of the people: but not with a view to
                    take any step in the business, unless a considerable number of them were
                    disposed to revive the former treaty of amity. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Villius, in a ship of five banks of oars, came to the mouth of the harbour, and
                    the whole multitude of the Magnetians hastened out thither. Villius then asked,
                        <pb n="1595" xml:id="p.1595"/> whether they chose that he should consider
                    himself as having come to friends, or to enemies? <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Eurylochus, the Magnetarch, answered, that <quote> he had
                        come to friends; but desired him not to enter the harbour, but to suffer the
                        Magnetians to live in freedom and harmony; and not to attempt, under the
                        show of friendly converse, to seduce the minds of the populace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then followed an altercation, not a
                    conference, the Roman upbraiding the Magnetians with ingratitude, and
                    forewarning them of the calamities impending over them; the multitude, on the
                    other side, clamorously reproaching him, and reviling, sometimes the senate,
                    sometimes Quinctius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Villius, therefore,
                    unable to effect any part of his business, went back to Quinctius, who
                    despatched orders to the Thessalian praetor, to lead his troops home, while
                    himself returned with his ships to Corinth. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The affairs of Greece, blended with those of
                    Rome, have carried me away, as it were, out of my course: not that they were in
                    themselves deserving of a recital, but because they constituted the causes of
                    the war with Antiochus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the consular
                    election, for thence I digressed, the consuls, Lucius Quinctius and Cneius
                    Domitius, repaired to their provinces; Quinctius to Liguria, Domitius against
                    the Boians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Boians kept themselves quiet;
                    nay, the senators, with their children, and the commanding officers of the
                    cavalry, with their troops, amounting in all to one thousand five hundred,
                    surrendered to the consul. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The other consul
                    laid waste the country of the Ligurians to a wide extent, and took some forts:
                    in which expeditions he not only acquired booty of all sorts, together with many
                    prisoners, but he also recovered several of his countrymen, and of the allies,
                    who had been in the hands of the enemy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In
                    this year a colony was settled at Vibo, in pursuance of a decree of the senate
                    and an order of the people; three thousand seven hundred footmen, and three
                    hundred horsemen, went out thither, conducted by the commissioners Quintus
                    Naevius, Marcus Minucius, and Marcus Furius Crassipes. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Fifteen acres of ground were assigned to each footman,
                    double that quantity to a horseman. This land had been last in possession of the
                    Bruttians, who had taken it from the Greeks. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    About this time two dreadful causes of alarm happened at Rome, one of which
                    continued long, but was less active than the other. An earthquake lasted through
                        <pb n="1596" xml:id="p.1596"/> thirty-eight days; during all which time
                    there was a total cessation of business, amidst anxiety and fears. On account of
                    this event, a supplication was performed of three days' continuance. The other
                    was not a mere fright, but attended with the actual loss of many lives.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In consequence of a fire breaking out in
                    the cattle-market, the conflagration, among the houses near to the Tiber,
                    continued through all that day and the following night, and all the shops, with
                    wares of very great value, were reduced to ashes. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year was now almost at an end, while the
                    rumours of impending hostility, and, consequently, the anxiety of the senate,
                    daily increased. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They therefore set about
                    adjusting the provinces of the magistrates elect, in order that they might be
                    all the more intent on duty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They decreed,
                    that those of the consuls should be Italy, and whatever other place the senate
                    should vote, for every one knew that a war against Antiochus was now a settled
                    point. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That he, to whose lot the latter
                    province fell, should have under his command, —of Roman citizens, four thousand
                    foot and three hundred horse; and of the Latin confederates, six thousand foot
                    and four hundred horse. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul, Lucius
                    Quinctius, was ordered to levy these troops, that no delay might be occasioned,
                    but that the new consul might be able to proceed immediately to any place which
                    the senate should appoint. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Concerning the
                    provinces of the praetors, also, it was decreed, that the first lot should
                    comprehend the two jurisdictions, both that between natives, and that between
                    them and foreigners; the second should be Bruttium; the third, the fleet, to
                    sail wherever the senate should direct; the fourth, Sicily; the fifth, Sardinia;
                    the sixth, Farther Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> An order was also
                    given to the consul Lucius Quinctius, to levy two new legions of Roman citizens,
                    and of the allies and Latins twenty thousand foot and eight hundred horse. This
                    army they assigned to the praetor to whom should fall the province of Bruttium.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Two temples were dedicated this year to
                    Jupiter in the Capitol; one of which had been vowed by Lucius Furius Purpureo,
                    when praetor during the Gallic war; the other by the same, when consul. Quintus
                    Marcius Ralla, duumvir, dedicated both. Many severe sentences were passed this
                    year on usurers, who were prosecuted, as private persons, by the curule aediles,
                    Marcus Tuccius and Publius Junius Brutus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1597" xml:id="p.1597"/> Out of the fines imposed on those who were
                    convicted, gilded chariots, with four horses, were placed in the <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> recess of Jupiter's temple in the Capitol, over
                    the canopy of the shrine, and also twelve gilded bucklers. The same aediles
                    built a portico on the outside of the Triple Gate, in the Carpenters' Square. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the Romans were busily employed in
                    preparing for a new war, Antiochus, on his part, was not idle. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Three cities detained him some time, Smyrna, Alexandria in
                    Troas, and Lampsacus, which hitherto he had not been able either to reduce by
                    force, or to persuade into a treaty of amity; and he was unwilling, on going
                    into Europe, to leave these behind (as enemies). A deliberation also respecting
                    Hannibal occasioned him further delay. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> First,
                    the open ships, which the king was to have sent with him to Africa, were slowly
                    prepared, and afterwards a consultation was set on foot whether he ought to be
                    sent at all, chiefly by Thoas the Aetolian; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    who, after setting all Greece in commotion, came with the account of Demetrias
                    being in the hands of his countrymen; and as he had, by false representations
                    concerning the king, and multiplying, in his assertions, the numbers of his
                    forces, exalted the expectations of many in Greece; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> so now, by the same artifices, lie puffed up the hopes of
                    the king; telling him, that "every one was inviting him with their prayers, and
                    that there would be a general rush to the shore, from which the people could
                    catch a view of the royal fleet. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He even had
                    the audacity to attempt altering the king's judgment respecting Hannibal when it
                    was nearly settled. For he alleged, that <quote> the fleet ought not to be
                        weakened by sending away any part of it, but that if ships must be
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> sent no person was less fit for the
                        command than Hannibal, for he was an exile and a Carthaginian, to whom his
                        own circumstances or his disposition might daily suggest a thousand new
                        schemes. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then as to his military fame, by
                        which, as by a dowry, he was recommended to notice, it was too splendid for
                        an officer acting under a king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The king
                        ought to be the grand object of view; the king ought to appear the sole
                        leader, the sole commander. If Hannibal should lose a fleet or an army the
                        amount of the damage would be the same as if the loss were incurred by any
                        other general; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but should success be
                        obtained, all the honour would be ascribed to Hannibal, and not to
                        Antiochus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Besides, if the war should
                        prove so fortunate as to terminate finally in <pb n="1598" xml:id="p.1598"/>
                        the defeat of the Romans, could it be expected that Hannibal would live
                        under a king; subject, in short, to an individual; he who could scarcely
                        bear subjection to his own country? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That
                        he had not so conducted himself from early youth, having embraced the empire
                        of the globe in his hopes and aspirations, that in his old age he would be
                        likely to endure a master. The king wanted not Hannibal as a general: as an
                        attendant and a counsellor in the business of the war, he might properly
                        employ him. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A moderate use of such
                        abilities would be neither unprofitable nor dangerous; <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> but if advantages of the highest nature were sought
                        through him, they, probably, would be the destruction both of the giver and
                        the receiver. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There are no dispositions more prone to envy
                    than those of persons whose mental qualifications are inferior to their birth
                    and rank in life; because they are indignant both at the merit and the
                    possessions of another. The design of the expedition, to be commanded by
                    Hannibal, the only one thought of that could be of use, in the beginning of the
                    war, was immediately laid aside. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king,
                    highly flattered by the defection of Demetrias from the Romans to the Aetolians,
                    resolved to delay no longer his departure into Greece. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Before the fleet weighed anchor he went up from the shore
                    to Ilium, to offer sacrifice to Minerva. Immediately on his return he set sail
                    with forty decked ships and sixty open ones, followed by two hundred transports,
                    laden with provisions and warlike stores. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He
                    first touched at the island of Imbrus; thence he passed over to Sciathus;
                    whence, after collecting the ships which had been separated during the voyage,
                    he proceeded to Pteleum, the nearest part of the continent. Here, Eurylochus the
                    Magnetarch, and other principal Magnetians from Demetrias, met him. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Being greatly gratified by their numerous appearance,
                    he carried his fleet the next day into the harbour of their city. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> At a small distance from the town he landed his
                    forces, which consisted of ten thousand foot, five hundred horse, and six
                    elephants; a force scarcely sufficient to take possession of Greece alone, much
                    less to sustain a war with Rome. The Aetolians, as soon as they were informed of
                    Antiochus's arrival at Demetrias, convened a general council, and passed a
                    decree, inviting him into their country. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    king had already left Demetrias, (for he knew that such a decree was to be
                    passed,) and had advanced as far as Phalera <pb n="1599" xml:id="p.1599"/> on
                    the Malian bay. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Here the decree was presented
                    to him, and then he proceeded to Lamia, where he was received by the <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> populace with marks of the warmest attachment, with
                    clapping of hands and shouting, and other signs by which the extravagant joy of
                    the vulgar is testified. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he came into the council he was
                    introduced by Phaeneas, the praetor, and other persons of eminence, who, with
                    difficulty, made way for him through the crowd. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Then, silence being ordered, the king addressed himself to the assembly. He
                    began with accounting for his having come with a force so much smaller than
                    every one had hoped and expected. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>That,</quote> he said, <quote> ought to be deemed the strongest proof of
                        the warmth of his good-will towards them; because, though he was not
                        sufficiently prepared in any particular, and though the season was yet too
                        early for sailing, he had, without hesitation, complied with the call of
                        their ambassadors, and had believed that when the Aetolians should see him
                        among them they would be satisfied that in <milestone n="4??" unit="section"
                        /> him, even if he were unattended, they might be sure of every kind of
                        support. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But he would also abundantly
                        fulfil the hopes of those, whose expectations seemed at present to be
                        disappointed. For as soon as the season of the year rendered navigation
                        safe, he would cover all Greece with arms, men, and horses, and all its
                        coasts with fleets. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He would spare neither
                        expense, nor labour, nor danger, until he should remove the Roman yoke from
                        their necks, and render Greece really free, and the Aetolians the first
                        among its states. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That, together with the
                        armies, stores of all kinds were to come from Asia. For the present the
                        Aetolians ought to take care that his men might be properly supplied with
                        corn, and other accommodations, at reasonable rates. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having addressed them to this purport, and
                    with universal approbation, the king withdrew. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    After his departure a warm debate ensued between two of the Aetolian chiefs,
                    Phaeneas and Thoas. Phaeneas declared his opinion, that it would be better to
                    employ Antiochus, as a <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> mediator of peace,
                    and an umpire respecting the matters in dispute with the Roman people, than as
                    leader in a war. That <quote> his presence and his dignified station would
                        impress the Romans with awe, more powerfully than his arms. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> That in many cases men, for the sake of avoiding war,
                        voluntarily remit preten- <pb n="1600" xml:id="p.1600"/> sions, which force
                        and arms would never compel them to forego. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thoas, on the other hand, insisted, that
                        <quote> Phaeneas's motive was not a love of peace, but a wish to embarrass
                        their preparations for war, with the view that, through the tediousness of
                        the proceedings, the king's vigour might be relaxed, and the Romans gain
                        time to put themselves in readiness. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That
                        they had abundant proof from experience, after so many embassies sent to
                        Rome, and so many conferences with Quinctius in person, that nothing
                        reasonable could ever be obtained from the Romans in the way of negotiation;
                        and that they would not, until every hope of that sort was out of sight,
                        have implored the aid of Antiochus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That
                        as he had appeared among them sooner than any had expected, they ought not
                        to sink into indolence, but rather to petition the king, that since he had
                        come in person, which was the great point of all, to support the rights of
                        Greece, he would also send for his fleets and armies. For the king, at the
                        head of an army, might obtain something, but without that could have very
                        little influence with the Romans, either in the cause of the Aetolians, or
                        even in his own. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This opinion was adopted, and the council
                    voted, that the title of general should be conferred on the king. They also
                    nominated thirty distinguished men with whom he might deliberate on any business
                    which he might think proper. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> —The council was
                    then broken up, and all went home to their respective states. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next day the king held a consultation with
                    their select council, respecting the place from whence his operations should
                    commence. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They judged it best to make the
                    first trial on Chalcis, which had lately been attempted in vain by the
                    Aetolians; and they thought that the business required rather expedition than
                    any great exertion or preparation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly
                    the king, with a thousand foot, who had followed him from Demetrias, took his
                    route through Phocis; and the Aetolian chiefs, going by another road, met at
                    Cheronaea a small number of their young men whom they had called to arms, and
                    thence, in ten decked ships, proceeded after him. Antiochus pitched his camp at
                    Salganea, while himself, with the Aetolian chiefs, crossed the Euripus in the
                    ships. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he had advanced a little way from
                    the harbour, the magistrates and other chief men of Chalcis came out before
                    their gate. A small number from each side met to confer together. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The <pb n="1601" xml:id="p.1601"/> Aetolians warmly
                    recommended to the others, <quote> without violating the friendship subsisting
                        between them and the Romans, to receive the king also as a friend and ally;
                        for that he had crossed into Europe not for the purpose of making war, but
                        of vindicating the liberty of Greece; and of vindicating it in reality, not
                        in words and pretence merely, as the Romans had done. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Nothing could be more advantageous to the states of
                        Greece than to embrace the alliance of both, as they would then be always
                        secure against ill-treatment from either, under the guarantee and protection
                        of the other. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If they refuse to receive
                        the king, they ought to consider what they would have immediately to suffer;
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the aid of the Romans being far
                        distant, and Antiochus, whom with their own strength they could not possibly
                        resist, in character of an enemy at their gates. </quote> To this Mictio,
                    one of the Chalcian deputies, answered that <quote> he wondered who those people
                        were, for the vindicating of whose liberty Antiochus had left his own
                        kingdom, and come over into Europe. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For
                        his part he knew not any state in Greece which either contained a garrison,
                        or paid tribute to the Romans, or was bound by a disadvantageous treaty, and
                        obliged to submit to terms which it did not like. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The people of Chalcis, therefore, stood not in need,
                        either of any assertor of their liberty, which they already enjoyed, or of
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> any armed protector, since, through
                        the kindness of the Roman people, they were in possession of both liberty
                        and peace. They did not slight the friendship of the king, nor that of the
                        Aetolians themselves. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The first instance
                        of friendship, therefore, that they could give, would be to quit the island
                        and go home; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> for, as to themselves, they
                        were fully determined not only not to admit them within their walls, but not
                        even to agree to any alliance, but with the approbation of the Romans.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When an account of this conference was brought
                    to the king, at the ships where lie had staid, he resolved for the present to
                    return to Demetrias; for he had not come to them with a sufficient number of men
                    to attempt any thing by force. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At Demetrias he
                    held another consultation with the Aetolians, to determine what was next to be
                    done, as their first effort had proved fruitless. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> It was agreed that they should make trial of the Bœotians,
                    Achaeans, and Amynander, king of the Athamanians. The Bœotian nation they
                    believed to have <pb n="1602" xml:id="p.1602"/> been disaffected to the Romans,
                    ever since the death of Brachyllas, and the consequences which followed it.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Philopœmen, chief of the Achaeans, they
                    supposed to hate, and be hated by, Quinctius, in consequence of a rivalship for
                    fame in the war of Laconia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Amynander had
                    married Apama, daughter of a Megalopolitan, called Alexander, who, pretending to
                    be descended from Alexander the Great, had given the names of Philip and
                    Alexander to his two sons, and that of Apama to his daughter; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and when she was raised to distinction, by her marriage to
                    the king, Philip, the elder of her brothers had followed her into Athamania.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This man, who happened to be naturally
                    vain, the Aetolians and Antiochus persuaded to hope (as he was really of the
                    royal family) for the sovereignty of Macedonia, on condition of his prevailing
                    on Amynander and the Athamanians to join Antiochus; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and these empty promises produced the intended effect, not
                    only on Philip but likewise on Amynander. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Achaia, the ambassadors of Antiochus and
                    the Aetolians were admitted to an audience of the council <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> at Aegium, in the presence of Titus Quinctius. The
                    ambassador of Antiochus was heard prior to the Aetolians. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He, with all that pomp and parade which is common among
                    those who are maintained by the wealth of kings, covered, as far as the empty
                    sound of words could go, both lands and seas (with forces). He said, that
                        <quote> an innumerable body of cavalry was coming over the Hellespont into
                        Europe; some of them cased in coats of mail, whom they call Cataphracti;
                        others discharging arrows on horseback; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        and, what rendered it impossible to guard against them, shooting with the
                        surest aim even when their backs were turned, and their horses in full
                        retreat. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To this army of cavalry,
                        sufficient to crush the forces of all Europe, collected into one body,
                    </quote> he added another of infantry of many times its number; and to terrify
                    them, repeated the names of nations scarcely ever heard of before: talking of
                    Dahans, Medes, Elymaeans, and Cadusians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> As to the naval forces, no harbours in Greece were capable of containing
                        them; the right squadron was composed of Sidonians and Tyrians; the left of
                        Aradians and Sidetians, from Pamphylia, —nations which none others had ever
                        equalled, either in courage, or skill in sea affairs. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Then, as to money, and other requisites for the support
                        of war, it was needless for <pb n="1603" xml:id="p.1603"/> him to speak.
                        They themselves knew, that the kingdoms of Asia had always abounded in gold.
                        The Romans, therefore, had not now to deal with Philip, or with Hannibal;
                        the one a principal member of a commonwealth, the other confined merely to
                        the limits of the kingdom of Macedonia; but with the great monarch of all
                        Asia, and part of Europe. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nevertheless,
                        though he had come from the remotest bounds of the East to give freedom to
                        Greece, he did not demand any thing from the Achaeans, that could injure the
                        fidelity of their engagements with the Romans, their former friends and
                        allies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For he did not require them to
                        take arms on his side against them; but only, that they should not join
                        themselves to either party. That, as became common friends, they should wish
                        for peace to both parties, and not intermeddle in the war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Archidamus, ambassador of the Aetolians, made
                    nearly the same request: that, as was their easiest and safest way, they should
                    stand neuter; and, as mere spectators of the war, wait for the decision of the
                    fortunes of others, without any hazard to their own interests. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> He afterwards was betrayed, by the intemperance of
                    language, into invectives, sometimes against the Romans in general, sometimes
                    against Quinctius himself in particular; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    charging them with ingratitude, and upbraiding them, as being indebted to the
                    valour of the Aetolians, not only for the victory over Philip, but even for
                    their preservation; for, <quote> by their exertions, both Quinctius himself and
                        his army had been saved. What duty of a commander had he ever discharged?
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He used to see him, indeed, in the
                        field, taking auspices; sacrificing, and offering vows, like an
                        insignificant soothsaying priest; while he himself was, in his defence,
                        exposing his person to the weapons of the enemy. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this Quinctius replied, that <quote>
                        Archidamus had calculated his discourse for the numerous auditors, rather
                        than for the persons to whom it was particularly addressed. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> For the Achaeans very well knew, that the bold spirit
                        of the Aetolians consisted entirely in words, not in deeds; and was more
                        displayed in their councils and assemblies than in the field. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> He had therefore been indifferent concerning the
                        sentiments of the Achaeans, to whom he and his countrymen were conscious
                        that they were thoroughly known; and studied to recommend himself to the
                        king's ambassadors, and, through <pb n="1604" xml:id="p.1604"/> them, to
                        their absent master. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But, if any person
                        had been hitherto ignorant of the cause which had united Antiochus and the
                        Aetolians, it was easy to discover it from the language of their
                        ambassadors. By the false representations made by both parties, and boasts
                        of strength which neither possessed, they mutually puffed up each other; and
                        were themselves puffed up with vain expectations: <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> one party talking of Philip being vanquished by them,
                        the Romans being protected by their valour, and the rest of what you have
                        just heard; and that you, and the other states and nations, would follow
                        their party. The king, on the other side, boasting of clouds of horsemen and
                        footmen, and covering the seas with his fleets. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The king, </quote> he added, <quote> was exceedingly
                        like a supper that I remember at the house of my host at Chalcis, who is
                        both a man of worth, and an excellent conductor of a feast. Having been
                        kindly entertained by him at midsummer, when we wondered how he could, at
                        that time of the year, procure such plenty and variety of game, he, not
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> being so vain-glorious as these men,
                        told us, with a pleasant smile, that the variety was owing to the dressing,
                        and that what appeared to be the flesh of many different wild animals, was
                        entirely of tame swine. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This may be aptly
                        applied to the forces of the king, which were so ostentatiously displayed a
                        while ago; that those various kinds of armour, and multitudinous names of
                        nations, never heard of before, Dahans, and Medes, and Caducians, and
                        Elymaeans, are nothing more than Syrians, a race possessed of such
                        grovelling souls, as to be much fitter for slaves than for soldiers.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I wish, Achaeans, that I could exhibit
                        to your view the rapid excursions of this mighty monarch from Demetrias;
                        first, to Lamia, to the council of the Aetolians; then to Chalcis. You
                        should behold, in the royal camp, about the number of two small legions, and
                        these incomplete. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> You should see the
                        king, now, in a manner begging corn from the Aetolians, to be measured out
                        to his soldiers; then, striving to borrow money at interest to pay them;
                        again, standing at the gates of Chalcis, and presently, on being refused
                        admittance, returning thence into Aetolia, without having effected any
                        thing, except indeed the taking a peep at Aulis and the Euripus. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Both Antiochus had done wrong in trusting to the
                        Aetolians, and the Aetolians in trusting to the king's vain boastings. For
                        which reason, you ought the less to be deceived by them, and <pb n="1605"
                            xml:id="p.1605"/> rather to confide in the tried and approved fidelity
                        of the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For, with respect to your
                        not interfering in the war, which they recommend as your best course,
                        nothing, in fact, can be more contrary to your interest: <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> for then, without gaining thanks or esteem, you will
                        become the prize of the conqueror. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He was thought to have replied to both by no
                    means unsuitably; and there was no difficulty in bringing an audience,
                    prepossessed in his favour, to give their approbation to his discourse.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In fact, there was no debate or doubt
                    started, but all concurred in voting, that the nation of the Achaeans would
                    regard, as their friends or foes, those who were judged to be such by the Roman
                    people, and in ordering war to be declared against both Antiochus and the
                    Aetolians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They also, by the direction of
                    Quinctius, sent immediate succours of five hundred men to Chalcis, and five
                    hundred to the Piraeus; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> for affairs at Athens
                    were in a state not far from a civil war, in consequence of the endeavours, used
                    by some, to seduce the venal populace, by hopes of largesses, to take part with
                    Antiochus. But at length Quinctius was called thither by those who were of the
                    Roman party; and Apollodorus, the principal adviser of a revolt, being publicly
                    charged therewith by one Leon, was condemned and driven into exile. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Thus, from the Achaeans also, the embassy returned to
                    the king with a discouraging answer. The Bœotians made no definitive reply; they
                    only said, that <quote> when Antiochus should come into Bœotia, they would then
                        deliberate on the measures proper to be pursued. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When Antiochus heard, that both the Achaeans
                    and king Eumenes had sent reinforcements to Chalcis, he resolved to act with the
                    utmost expedition, that his troops might get the start of them, and, if
                    possible, intercept the others as they came; and he sent thither Menippus with
                    about three thousand soldiers, and Polyxenidas with the whole fleet. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> In a few days after, he marched himself, at the head
                    of six thousand of his own soldiers, and a smaller number of Aetolians, as many
                    as could be collected in haste, out of those who were at Lamia. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The five hundred Achaeans, and a small party sent by king
                    Eumenes, being guided by Xenoclides, of Chalcis, (the roads being yet open,)
                    crossed the Euripus, and arrived at Chalcis in safety. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman sol- diers, who were likewise about five hundred,
                    came, after Me- <pb n="1606" xml:id="p.1606"/> nippus had fixed his camp under
                    Salganea, at Hermaeus, the place of passage from Bœotia to the island of Eubœa.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They had with them Mictio, who had been
                    sent from Chalcis to Quinctius, deputed to solicit that very reinforcement;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and when he perceived that the passes
                    were blocked up by the enemy, he quitted the road to Aulis, and turned away to
                    Delium, with intent to pass over thence to Eubœa. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Delium is a temple of Apollo, standing over
                    the sea, five miles distant from Tanagra; and the passage thence, to the nearest
                    part of Eubœa, is less than four miles. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As
                    they were in this sacred building and grove, sanctified with all that religious
                    awe and those privileges which belong to temples, called by the Greeks asylums,
                    (war not being yet either proclaimed, or so far commenced as that they had heard
                    of swords being drawn, or blood shed any where,) the soldiers, in perfect
                    tranquillity, amused themselves, some with viewing the temple and groves;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> others with walking about unarmed, on the
                    strand; and a great part had gone different ways in quest of wood and forage;
                    when, on a sudden, Menippus attacked them in that scattered condition, slew
                    many, and took fifty of them prisoners. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Very
                    few made their escape, among whom was Mictio, who was received on board a small
                    trading vessel. Though this event caused much grief to Quinctius and the Romans,
                    on account of the loss of <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> their men, yet it
                    seemed to add much to the justification of their cause in making war on
                    Antiochus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Antiochus, when arrived with his
                    army so near as Aulis, sent again to Chalcis a deputation, composed partly of
                    his own people, and partly of Aetolians, to treat on the same grounds as before,
                    but with heavier denunciations of vengeance: and, notwithstanding all the
                    efforts of Mictio and Xenoclides to the contrary, he easily gained his object,
                    that the gates should be opened to him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Those
                    who adhered to the Roman interest, on the approach of the king, withdrew from
                    the city. The soldiers of the Achaeans, and Eumenes, held Salganea; and the few
                    Romans, who had escaped, raised, for the security of the place, a little fort on
                    the Euripus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Menippus laid siege to Salganea,
                    and the king himself to the fort. The Achaeans and Eumenes' soldiers first
                    surrendered, on the terms of being allowed to retire in safety. The Romans
                    defended the Euripus with more obstinacy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But
                    even these, when they were completely invested both by land and <pb n="1607"
                        xml:id="p.1607"/> sea, and saw the machines and engines prepared for an
                    assault, sustained the siege no longer. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    king, having thus got possession of the capital of Eubœa, the other cities of
                    the island did not even refuse to obey his authority; and he seemed to himself
                    to have signalized the commencement of the war by an important acquisition, in
                    having brought under his power so great an island, and so many cities
                    conveniently situated. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
