<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to forty-five -
                    39</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">William A. McDevitte, Sen. Class. Mod. Ex. Schol.
                    A.B.T.C.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title> History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to the end,
                                with the epitomes and fragments of the lost books </title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>William A. McDevitte</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXXIX.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Marcus Aemilius, the consul, having subdued the Ligurians, made a road from
                        Placentia as far as Ariminum, and connected it with the Flaminian way. The
                        commencement of luxury, introduced by the Asiatic army, is related. All the
                        Ligurians who dwell on the hither side of the Apennines were subdued. The
                        Bacchanalia, a Grecian sacred cere- mony, held at night, a hot-bed of every
                        vice, after having become a conspiracy including great numbers, were
                        discovered by one of the con- suls and suppressed, while many of those
                        concerned were punished. Lucius Quinctius Flamininus, the brother of Titus,
                        was expelled the senate, by the censors Lucius Valerius Flaccus and Marcus
                        Porcius Cato, who was most distinguished in the arts of war and peace, for
                        the following reason: because when, as consul, he had held the province of
                        Gaul, he slew with his own hand a certain Gaul, at the request of Philip, a
                        Carthaginian, his noble minion; or, as some have stated, because he had
                        beheaded a condemned criminal at the request of a courtesan of Placentia,
                        with whom he was desperately in love. The speech of Marcus Cato against him
                        is still extant. Scipio died at Liter- num. And, as if fortune destined for
                        the same period the death of the two most distinguished men of the day,
                        Hannibal committed suicide by taking poison, when he was on the point of
                        being given up to the Romans by Prusias, king of Bithynia, to whom he had
                        fled for refuge on the defeat of Antiochus: the Romans had sent Titus
                        Quinctius Flamininus to demand Hannibal. Philopœmen likewise, the general of
                        the Achcaeans, a most distinguished man, after having fallen into the hands
                        of the Messenians in war, was put to death by poison. Colonies are planted
                        at Potentia, Pisaurus, Modena, and Parma. This book contains in addition the
                        success over the Celtiberians, and the commence- ment and cause of the
                        Macedonian war; the origin of which proceeded from the following source:
                        Philip was dissatisfied that his kingdom was being diminished by the Romans,
                        and because he was compelled to with- draw his garrisons from Thrace and
                        other places. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> WHILE these things are done at Rome, (if they
                    were really transacted in this year,) both the consuls were em- <pb n="1792"
                        xml:id="p.1792"/> ployed in the war with the Ligurians. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This enemy seemed born for the purpose of preserving
                    military discipline among the Romans, during the intervals between important
                    wars; nor was any province better calculated to form a soldier to active valour.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For Asia, from the enticing pleasures of
                    its cities, the abundance of every production both of land and sea, the
                    unwarlike temper of the enemy, and the wealth of its princes, made Roman armies
                    rich, rather than brave. Under the command of Cneius Manlius, particularly, the
                    troops were kept in a state of idleness and licentiousness. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Therefore, in Thrace, a passage somewhat more difficult,
                    and a more vigorous enemy, checked them with severe loss. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Whereas in Liguria there was every circumstance that could
                    invigorate the courage of soldiers; the country mountainous and rugged, so that
                    even the taking possession of unoccupied posts, and much more the dislodging of
                    an enemy from those already in possession, was attended with much labour; the
                    roads hilly, narrow, and exposed to ambuscades; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> the enemy light, active, and energetic in their motions, so as to allow no
                    season or place to be quiet or secure; the necessary attack on the strong forts
                    with much toil and danger; and the country so poor as to constrain the soldier
                    to a sparing mode of living, while it afforded but a small share of' booty.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Accordingly, no sutler followed the army,
                    no long train of baggage horses extended its line of march, nothing was to be
                    seen but arms, and men having all their hopes in their arms. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was either subject or cause for hostilities with them
                    ever wanting; because on account of their poverty at home they made frequent
                    incursions on the territories of their neighbours; they did not, however, fight
                    a battle which could decide the entire war. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, Caius Flaminius, after several
                    successful battles against the Frinian Ligurians in their own country, received
                    the submission of that tribe, and ordered them to deliver up their arms;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> as they did not give them up honourably,
                    and were reproved for their behaviour, who abandoned their villages, and fled to
                    the mountain called Auginus, whither the consul immediately followed them.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A part of the enemy again betook
                    themselves to flight; and, running with precipitate haste, the greatest part
                    without arms, over pathless tracts and rocky precipices, they escaped to places
                    where an enemy could not follow them. Thus they <pb n="1793" xml:id="p.1793"/>
                    got away beyond the Apennine; the rest, who remained in the camp, were
                    surrounded and reduced by assault. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The legions
                    were then led over the Apennine; then the enemy, assisted by the height of the
                    mountain, which they had occupied at first, stood on their defence; but, in a
                    little time, submitted. Their arms were then sought for with greater care, and
                    all taken from them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The war was then
                    transferred to the Apuan tribe of Ligurians, who had made so many incursions
                    into the territory of Pisa and Bononia, that it could not be cultivated.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These being entirely subdued, the consul
                    restored peace to the neighbourhood. And, as he had effected the security of the
                    province from the war, he made a road from Bononia to Anetium, that he might not
                    keep the soldiers in a state of idleness. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    other consul, Marcus Aemilius, ravaged with fire and sword the lands of the
                    Ligurians, together with their villages that stood in the plains, while the
                    inhabitants remained posted on two mountains, Ballista and Suismontium.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then attacked those who were on the
                    mountains, harassed them for some time in skirmishes, and, at last, compelled
                    them to come to an engagement, and utterly defeated them in a regular battle: in
                    which he vowed a temple to Diana. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having now
                    reduced all on this side of the Apennine, he marched against those on the other
                    side of that mountain; among whom were the Brinian tribe, which had not been
                    attacked by Flaminius: Aemilius subdued them all, stripped them of their arms,
                    and obliged the multitude to come down from the mountains into the plains.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Ligurians being brought to a state of
                    peace, he led his army into the Gallic territory, and drew a road from Placentia
                    to Ariminum, to meet that made by Flaminius. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    During the last engagement, when he fought a pitched battle with the Ligurians,
                    he vowed a temple to Imperial Juno. Such were the transactions of this year in
                    Liguria. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Gaul, the praetor, Marcus Furius, seeking a
                    pretext for war in the midst of peace, deprived the unoffending Caenomanians of
                    their arms. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Caenomanians complained of
                    this to the senate at Rome, and were by them referred to the consul Aemilius,
                    whom the senate authorized to examine into and determine the cause; after a warm
                    contest with the praetor they gained their cause. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The praetor was ordered to restore their arms to the
                    Caenomanians, and quit the province. <pb n="1794" xml:id="p.1794"/> The senate
                    afterwards gave audience to envoys of the Latin confederation, who had come, in
                    great numbers, from all parts of Latium. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On
                    their complaint that a great multitude of their citizens had been removed to
                    Rome, and had been assessed there in the survey; a commission was given to
                    Quintus Terentius Culleo, the praetor, to make inquiry after such persons;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and on the allies proving that those
                    persons themselves, or their fathers, had been assessed in the surveys of their
                    states in the censorship of Caius Claudius and Marcus Livius, or at some time
                    subsequent to their censorship, he was ordered to compel all such to return to
                    the several states wherein they had been so rated. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> In consequence of this inquiry, twelve thousand Latins
                    returned home; as the multitude of foreigners even then burdened the city. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the consuls came home to Rome, Marcus
                    Fulvius, the proconsul, returned from Aetolia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    He, when he had as usual recited to the senate, in the temple of Apollo, the
                    services which he had performed in Aetolia and Cephallenia, then requested of
                    the fathers, that, in consideration of his having conducted the business of the
                    public with good fortune and success, they would think proper to order public
                    thanks to be offered to the immortal gods, and to decree a triumph to him.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Marcus Abutius, a tribune of the commons,
                    gave notice, that, if any thing were determined on that subject before the
                    arrival of Marcus Aemilius, he would enter his protest: <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> for <quote> the consul intended to oppose that measure;
                        and, at his setting out for his province, had given him a charge to keep the
                        discussion of it open until he should come home. That Fulvius would suffer a
                        loss of nothing but time; for, notwithstanding the presence of the consul,
                        the senate would determine according to their own wishes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Fulvius replied, that, <quote> even if the
                        quarrel subsisting between him and Marcus Aemilius was unknown to the world,
                        or with what overbearing, and, in some measure, tyrannical rancour, that man
                        prosecuted his enmity; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> yet it was
                        insufferable, that the absence of the consul should both obstruct the
                        worship of the immortal gods, and delay a triumph merited and due;
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that a commander, after performing
                        signal services, and his victorious army with its booty and prisoners,
                        should remain outside the gates, until a consul, who purposely delayed
                        abroad, should be pleased to return to <pb n="1795" xml:id="p.1795"/> Rome.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But, in the present case, when the
                        animosity between him and the consul was most notorious, what fair dealing
                        could any one expect from a man who procured clandestinely, in a thin house,
                        and lodged in the treasury, a decree of the senate, that <quote>it did not
                            appear that Ambracia was taken by force:</quote>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> a town which was attacked with mounds and
                        engines; where, after the works were burned, others were constructed anew;
                        where a fight was carried on around the walls for fifteen days, both above
                        and under ground; where, from the first dawn, when the soldiers mounted the
                        walls, a battle, for a long time doubtful, lasted until night; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> and where more than three thousand of the enemy
                        were killed? Then, again, what a malicious misrepresentation did he make to
                        the pontiffs, of the temples of the immortal gods being plundered in a
                        captured city! <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If it were allowable that
                        Rome should be decorated with the ornaments of Syracuse, and other conquered
                            <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> places, then the laws of war must
                        lose their force in the case of Ambracia alone, among conquered towns.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For his part, he besought the
                        conscript fathers, and requested the tribunes, not to suffer him to become a
                        subject of derision to a most haughty enemy. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> All around were in his favour; and some
                    entreated the tribune to desist, while others sharply reproved his conduct.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The speech of his colleague, Tiberius
                    Gracchus, moved him most, that, <quote> for a man in office to prosecute even
                        his own quarrels, was an example of no good tendency; but, that a tribune of
                        the people should take upon himself to be a solicitor in the quarrel of
                        another, was infamous, and highly unworthy of the power and sacred laws of
                        the order to which he belonged. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That men
                        ought to love or hate others, approve or disapprove of measures, according
                        to the dictates of their own judgment; but that a tribune ought not to
                        depend on the look or nod of another man, veer about at the movements of
                        another's will, and make himself a tool to his displeasure; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> nor remember a private charge, committed to him by
                        Marcus Aemilius, and forget that the tribuneship was a public charge,
                        intrusted to him by the Roman people, for the protection and liberty of
                        private citizens, not to aggrandize the arbitrary power of a consul.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His colleague did not seem to consider
                        that this circumstance would be committed to record and posterity: that, of
                        two plebeian tribunes of the same college, one sacri- <pb n="1796"
                            xml:id="p.1796"/> ficed his own resentment to the public good, the other
                        prosecuted the resentment of another man which was merely intrusted to him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the tribune, overcome by these severe
                    rebukes, had withdrawn from the meeting, a triumph was voted to Marcus Fulvius,
                    on the motion of Servius Sulpicius, the praetor. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> When he returned thanks to the conscript fathers, he then mentioned, that,
                        <quote> on the day of his taking Ambracia, he had vowed to celebrate the
                        great games in honour of Jupiter the supremely good and great; <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> that a contribution for that purpose had been
                        made to him by the several states, amounting to one hundred and ten pounds'
                        weight of gold; and he requested them to order that sum to be set apart, out
                        of the money which he was to deposit in the treasury, after being borne in
                        triumph. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The senate ordered the college of pontiffs to
                    be consulted, whether it were necessary that the whole of that sum should be
                    expended on the games: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> when the pontiffs had
                    answered, that it mattered little to religion what was the expense of the games,
                    the senate gave permission to Fulvius to expend as much as he thought proper,
                    provided he did not exceed eighty thousand sesterces. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 645 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 17 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He, at first, intended to celebrate his
                    triumph in the month of January; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but, hearing
                    that the consul Aemilius, in consequence of a letter from the tribune Abutius,
                    concerning his waving his protest, was coming in person to Rome, to hinder his
                    triumph, but had been obliged by sickness to halt on the road, lie hastened the
                    time of the celebration, lest he <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> should
                    have more contests about it than he had met in the war. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> He triumphed over the Aetolians and Cephallenia on the
                    tenth day before the calends of January. There were carried before his chariot,
                    golden crowns to the amount of one hundred and twelve pounds' weight; of silver,
                    eighty-three thousand pounds; of gold, two hundred and forty-three thousand; of
                    Attic tetradrachms, one hundred and eighteen thousand; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 15,241 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> of the coin called Philippeans, twelve
                    thousand four hundred and twenty-two; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        801 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> brazen statues, two hundred and eighty-five; marble statues, two hundred
                    and thirty; arms, weapons, and other spoils in great quantities: besides these,
                    catapultas, ballistas, and engines of every kind; <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> and in the procession were led twenty-seven commanders,
                    either Aetolian and Ce- <pb n="1797" xml:id="p.1797"/> phallenian, or belonging
                    to king Antiochus, and left with them. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Before
                    he rode into the city, in the Flaminian circus, he presented great numbers of
                    tribunes, praefects, horsemen, centurions, both Romans and allies, with military
                    gifts; to each of the soldiers he distributed out of the booty twenty-five
                    denariuses, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 16 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 1 1/4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> double to a centurion, triple to a horseman. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The time of the election of consuls now
                    approached; and as Marcus Aemilius, to whose lot that business had fallen, could
                    not attend, Caius Flaminius came home to Rome. Spurius Posthumius Albinus and
                    Quintus Marcus Philippus were elected consuls by him. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Then were chosen as praetors, — Titus Maenius, Publius
                    Cornelius Sulla, Caius Calpurnius Piso, Marcus Licinius Lucullus, Caius Aurelius
                    Scaurus, and Lucius Quintius Crispinus. At the close of the year, after the
                    magistrates were appointed, on the third day before the nones of March, Cneius
                    Manlius Vulso triumphed over the Gauls inhabiting Asia. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The reason of his deferring his triumph so long was, to
                    avoid standing a trial under the Petillian law, during the praetorship of
                    Quintus Terentius Culleo; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and the being
                    involved in the ill consequences of the sentence passed on another, that by
                    which Lucius Scipio was condemned; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> especially
                    as the judges would be more disposed to severity against him than against
                    Scipio, for this reason, because fame had reported, that he, Scipio's successor,
                    had, by tolerating every description of licentiousness, ruined military
                    discipline, so strictly preserved by his predecessor. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Nor were the facts, which were reported to have happened in
                    the province far from the eyes of spectators, the only things that disgraced his
                    character; but still more so, those circumstances which were every day beheld in
                    his soldiers; for by this army returning from Asia was the origin of foreign
                    luxury imported into the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These men first
                    brought to Rome gilded couches, rich tapestry, with hangings and other works of
                    the loom; and, what were then deemed magnificent furniture, single-footed tables
                    and buffets. At entertainments, likewise, were introduced female players on the
                    harp and timbrel, with buf- foons for the diversion of the guests. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Their meats also began to be prepared with greater
                    care and cost; while the cook, whom the ancients considered as the meanest of
                    their slaves both in estimation and use, became highly valuable, and what <pb
                        n="1798" xml:id="p.1798"/> was considered as a servile office began to be
                    considered an art. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, those
                    introductions which were then looked on as remarkable were scarcely even the
                    seeds of the future luxury. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Cneius Manlius carried in the triumph two
                    hundred golden crowns of twelve pounds' weight; two hundred and twenty thousand
                    pounds' weight of silver; two thousand two hundred and three of gold; one
                    hundred and twenty-seven thousand Attic tetradrachms; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 16,404 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> two hundred and fifty thousand cistophoruses; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 4309 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 14 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 9 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> sixteen thousand three hundred and twenty golden Philippeans; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1054 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note> together with abundance of Gallic arms and spoils <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> in chariots. Fifty-two generals of the enemy were led
                    before his car. He distributed to each of his soldiers forty-two denariuses,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6
                            <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and double that sum to a centurion; to the foot-sol- diers double pay,
                    to the horsemen triple. Great numbers of all ranks, whom he had distinguished by
                    gifts, <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> accompanied him. The verses thrown out
                    by the soldiers were of such a kind, that it was quite evident that they were
                    sung to a commander who had been indulgent to them, and courted their
                    affections. It was indeed evident that the triumph was celebrated with a greater
                    degree of favour by the troops, than by <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the
                    citizens. The friends of Manlius, however, were able to acquire for him the
                    regard of the <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> people also; through whose
                    efforts a decree of the senate was passed, ordering, that <quote> such part of
                        the soldiers' pay, contributed to the public funds by the people, as was not
                        yet repaid, should be discharged out of that which had been carried in the
                        procession to the treasury. </quote> Accordingly the city praetors, with
                    care and fidelity, paid twenty-five denariuses and a half <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 6 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 5 <hi rend="italics"
                            >d.</hi>
                    </note> instead of each <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> thousand asses. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 3 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 7 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> About this time two military tribunes arrived from the two Spains with
                    letters from Caius Atinius and Lucius Manlius, who governed <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> those provinces. From these letters it appeared, that the
                    Celtiberians and Lusitanians were in arms, and ravaging the territories of the
                    allies; the senate, however, deferred all consideration of that business until
                    the new magistrates should come into office. This year, during the celebration
                    of the Roman games which Publius Cornelius Cethegus and Aulus Postumius Albinus
                    exhibited, a pole in the circus, being loosely set in the ground, fell on the
                    statue of Pollentia, and <pb n="1799" xml:id="p.1799"/> threw <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> it down. The senate moved by such a religious circumstance,
                    voted that one day should be added to the celebration <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> of the games, that two statues should be set up instead of
                    the one, and that one of them, a new statue, should <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> be gilded. The plebeian games were likewise repeated for
                    one day, by the aediles Caius Sempronius Blaesus and Marcus Furius Luscus. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following year diverted Spurius Postumius
                    Albinus and Quintus Marcius Philippus, from the care of armies, and wars, and
                    provinces, to the punishing of an intestine conspiracy. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The proctors cast lots for their provinces, Titus Maenius
                    obtained the city jurisdiction; Marcus Licinius Lucullus, that between citizens
                    and foreigners; Caius Aurelius Scaurus, Sardinia; Publius Cornelius Sulla,
                    Sicily; Lucius Quintius Crispinus, Hither Spain; Caius Calpurnius Piso, Farther
                    Spain. The making inquisition concerning clandestine meetings was decreed to
                    both the consuls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A Greek of mean condition
                    came, first, into Etruria, not with one of the many trades which his nation, of
                    all others the most skilful in the cultivation of the mind and body, has
                    introduced among us, but a low operator in sacrifices, and a soothsayer;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> nor was he one who, by open religious
                    rites, and by publicly professing his calling and teaching, imbued the minds of
                    his followers with terror, but a priest of secret and nocturnal rites. These
                    mysterious rites were, at first, imparted to a few, but afterwards communicated
                    to great numbers, both men and women. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To their
                    religious performances were added the pleasures of wine and feasting, to allure
                    a greater number of proselytes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When wine,
                    lascivious discourse, night, and the intercourse of the sexes had extinguished
                    every sentiment of modesty, then debaucheries of every kind began to be
                    practised, as every person found at hand that sort of enjoyment to which he was
                    disposed by the passion predominant in his nature. Nor were they confined to one
                    species of vice —the promiscuous intercourse of free-born men and women; but
                    from this store-house of villany proceeded false witnesses, counterfeit seals,
                    false evidences, and pretended discoveries. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    From the same place, too, proceeded poison and secret murders, so that in some
                    cases, even the bodies could not be found for burial. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Many of their audacious deeds were brought about by
                    treachery, but most of them by force; it served to conceal the violence, that,
                    on account of the loud shouting, and the noise <pb n="1800" xml:id="p.1800"/> of
                    drums and cymbals, none of the cries uttered by the persons suffering violation
                    or murder could be heard abroad. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The infection of this mischief, like that from
                    the contagion of disease, spread from Etruria to Rome; where, the size of the
                    city affording greater room for such evils, and more means of concealment,
                    cloaked it at first; but information of it was at length brought to the consul,
                    Postumius, principally in the following manner. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Publius Aebutius, whose father had held equestrian rank in the army, was left
                    an orphan, and his guardians dying, he was educated under the eye of his mother
                    Duronia, and his stepfather Titus Sempronius Rutilus. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Duronia was entirely devoted to her husband; and
                    Sempronius, having managed the guardianship in such a manner that he could not
                    give an account of the property, wished that his ward should be either made away
                    with, or bound to compliance with his will by some strong tie. The Bacchana-
                    lian rites were the only way to effect the ruin of the youth. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> His mother told him, that, <quote> during his sickness, she
                        had made a vow for him, that if he should recover, she would initiate him
                        among the Bacchanalians; that being, through the kindness of the gods, bound
                        by this vow, she wished now to fulfil it; that it was necessary he should
                        preserve chastity for ten days, and on the tenth, after he should have
                        supped and washed himself, she would conduct him into the place of worship. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was a freedwoman called Hispala Fecenia,
                    a noted courtesan, but deserving of a better lot than the mode of life to which
                    she had been accustomed when very young, and a slave, and by which she had
                    maintained herself since her manumission. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As
                    they lived in the same neighbourhood, an intimacy subsisted between her and
                    Aebutius, which was far from being injurious either to the young man's character
                    or property; for he had been loved and wooed by her unsolicited; and as his
                    friends supplied his wants illiberally, he was supported by the generosity of
                    this woman; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> nay, to such a length did she go
                    under the influence of her affection, that, on the death of her patron, because
                    she was under the protection of no one, having petitioned the tribunes and
                    praetors for a guardian, when she was making her will, she constituted Aebutius
                    her sole heir. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As such pledges of mutual love subsisted, and
                    as neither kept any thing secret from the other, the young man, <pb n="1801"
                        xml:id="p.1801"/> jokingly, bid her not be surprised if he separated himself
                    from her for a few nights; as, <quote> on account of a religious duty, to
                        discharge a vow made for his health, he intended to be initiated among the
                        Bacchanalians. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On hearing this, the woman, greatly alarmed,
                    cried out, <quote>May the gods will more favourably!</quote> affirming that
                        <quote> it would be better, both for him and her, to lose their lives than
                        that he should do such a thing: </quote> she then imprecated curses,
                    vengeance, and destruction, on the head of those who advised him to such a step.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The young man, surprised both at her
                    expressions and at the violence of her alarm, bid her refrain from curses, for
                        <quote>it was his mother who ordered him to do so, with the approbation of
                        his stepfather.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Then,</quote> said she, <quote> your stepfather (for perhaps it is not
                        allowable to censure your mother) is in haste to destroy, by that act, your
                        chastity, your character, your hopes, and your life. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To him, now surprised by such language, and
                    inquiring what was the matter, she said, (after imploring the favour and pardon
                    of the gods and goddesses, if, compelled by her regard for him, she disclosed
                    what ought not to be revealed,) that <quote> when in service, she had gone into
                        that place of worship, as an attendant on her mistress; <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> but that, since she had obtained her liberty, she had
                        never once gone near it: that she knew it to be the receptacle of all kinds
                        of debaucheries; that it was well known that, for two years past, no one
                        older than twenty had been initiated there. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> When any person was introduced he was delivered as a victim to the
                        priests, who led him away to a place resounding with shouts, the sound of
                        music, and the beating of cymbals and drums, lest his cries, while suffering
                        violation, should be heard abroad. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> She then entreated and besought him to put an
                    end to that matter in some way or other; and not to plunge himself into a
                    situation, where he must first suffer, and afterwards commit, every thing that
                    was abominable. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor did she quit him until the
                    young man gave her his promise to keep himself clear of those rites. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he came home, and his mother made mention
                    of such things pertaining to the ceremony as were to be performed on that day,
                    and on the several following days, he told her that he would not perform any of
                    them, nor did he intend to be initiated. His stepfather was present at this
                    discourse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Immediately the woman observed,
                    that <quote> he could not deprive himself of the company of Hispala for ten
                        nights; that he <pb n="1802" xml:id="p.1802"/> was so fascinated by the
                        caresses and baneful influence of that serpent, that he retained no respect
                        for his mother or stepfather, or even the gods themselves. </quote> His
                    mother on one side and his stepfather on the other loading him with reproaches,
                    drove him out of the house, assisted by four slaves. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The youth on this repaired to his aunt Aebutia, told her
                    the reason of his being turned out by his mother, and the next day, by her
                    advice, gave information of the affair to the consul Postumius, without any
                    witnesses of the interview. The consul dismissed him, with an order to come
                    again on the third day following. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the mean
                    time, he inquired of his mother-in-law Sulpicia, a woman of respectable
                    character, <quote>whether she knew an old matron called Aebutia, who lived on
                        the Aventine hill?</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When she had answered that "she knew her well,
                    and that Aebutia was a woman of virtue, and of the ancient purity of morals; he
                    said that he required a conference with her, and that a messenger should be sent
                    for her to come. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Aebutia, on receiving the
                    message, came to Sulpicia's house, and the consul, soon after, coming in, as if
                    by accident, introduced a conversation about Aebutius, her brother's son.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The tears of the woman burst forth, and
                    she began to lament the unhappy lot of the youth: "who, after being robbed of
                    his property by persons whom it least of all became, was then residing with her,
                    being driven out of doors by his mother, because, being a good youth, (may the
                    gods be propitious to him,) he refused to be initiated in ceremonies devoted to
                    lewdness, as report goes. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, thinking that he had made
                    sufficient inquiries concerning Aebutius, and that his testimony was
                    unquestionable, having dismissed Aebutia, requested his mother-in-law to send
                    again to the Aventine, and bring from that quarter Hispala, a freedwoman, not
                    unknown in that neighbourhood; for there were some queries which he wished to
                    make of her. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hispala being alarmed because she
                    was sent for by a woman of such high rank and respectable character, and being
                    ignorant of the cause, after that she saw the lictors in the porch, the
                    multitude attending on the consul and the consul himself, was very near
                    fainting. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul led her into a retired
                    part of the house, and, in the presence of his mother-in-law, told her, that
                    "she need not be uneasy, if she could resolve to speak the truth. She might
                    receive a pro- <pb n="1803" xml:id="p.1803"/> mise of protection either from
                    Sulpicia, a matron of such dignified character, or from himself. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> That she ought to tell him, what was accustomed to be
                    done at the Bacchanalia, in the nocturnal orgies in the grove of Stimula.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the woman heard this, such terror and
                    trembling of all her limbs seized her, that for a long time she was unable to
                    speak; but recovering, at length she said, that <quote> when she was very young,
                        and a slave, she had been initiated, together with her mistress; <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> but for several years past, since she had
                        obtained her liberty, she knew nothing of what was done there. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul commended her so far, as not having
                    denied that she was initiated, but charged her to explain all the rest with the
                    same sincerity; and told her, affirming that she knew nothing further, that
                        <quote> there would not be the same tenderness or pardon extended to her, if
                        she should be convicted by another person, and one who had made a voluntary
                        confession; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that there was such a person,
                        who had heard the whole from her, and had given him a full account of it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/> The woman, now thinking without a doubt that
                    it must certainly be Aebutius who had discovered the secret, threw herself at
                    Sulpicia's feet, and at first began to beseech her, <quote> not to let the
                        private conversation of a freedwoman with her lover be turned not only into
                        a serious business, but even capital charge; </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> declaring that <quote> she had spoken of such
                        things merely to frighten him, and not because she knew any thing of the
                        kind. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On this Postumius, growing angry, said,
                        <quote> she seemed to imagine that then too she was wrangling with her
                        gallant Aebutius, and not that she was speaking in the house of a most
                        respectable matron, and to a consul. </quote> Sulpicia raised her,
                    terrified, from the ground, and while she encouraged her to speak out, at the
                    same time pacified her son-in-law's anger. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At
                    length she took courage, and, having censured severely the perfidy of Aebutius,
                    because he had made such a return for the extraordinary kindness shown to him in
                    that very instance, she declared that <quote> she stood in great dread of the
                        gods, whose secret mysteries she was to divulge; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> and in much greater dread of the men implicated, who
                        would tear her asunder with their hands if she became an informer.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Therefore, she entreated this favour
                        of Sulpicia, and likewise of the consul, that they would send her away to
                        some place out of Italy, where she might pass the remainder of her life in
                        safety. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul desired her to <pb n="1804"
                        xml:id="p.1804"/> be of good spirits, and said that it should be his care
                    that she might live securely in Rome. </p>
                <p> Hispala then gave a full account of the origin of the mysteries. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>At first,</quote> she said, <quote> those rites were performed by women.
                        No man used to be admitted. They had three stated days in the year on which
                        persons were initiated among the Bacchanalians, in the day-time. The matrons
                        used to be appointed priestesses, in rotation. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Paculla Minia, a Campanian, when priestesss, made an
                        alteration in every particular, as if by the direction of the gods. For she
                        first introduced men, who were her own sons, Minucius and Herrenius, both
                        surnamed Cerrinius; changed the time of celebration, from day to night; and,
                        instead of three days in the year, appointed five days of initiation, in
                        each month. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> From the time that the rites
                        were thus made common, and men were intermixed with women, and the
                        licentious freedom of the night was added, there was nothing wicked, nothing
                        flagitious, that had not been practised among them. There were more frequent
                        pollution of men, with each other, than with women. If any were less patient
                        in submitting to dishonour, or more averse to the commission of vice, they
                        were sacrificed as victims. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To think
                        nothing unlawful, was the grand maxim of their religion. The men, as if
                        bereft of reason, uttered predictions, with frantic contortions of their
                        bodies; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> the women, in the habit of
                        Bacchantes, with their hair dishevelled, and carrying blazing torches, ran
                        down to the Tiber; where, dipping their torches in the water, they drew them
                        up again with the flame unextinguished, being composed of native sulphur and
                        charcoal. They said that those men were carried off by the gods, whom the
                        machines laid hold of and dragged from their view into secret caves.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These were such as refused to take
                        the oath of the society, or to associate in their crimes, or to submit to
                        defilement. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Their number was exceedingly
                        great now, almost a second state in themselves, and among them were many men
                        and women of noble families. During the last two years it had been a rule,
                        that no person above the age of twenty should be initiated; for they sought
                        for people of such age as made them more liable to suffer deception and
                        personal abuse. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/> When she had completed her information, she
                    again fell at the consul's knees, and repeated the same entreaties, that he
                    might send <pb n="1805" xml:id="p.1805"/> her out of the country. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The consul requests his mother-in-law to clear some
                    part of the house, into which Hispala might remove; accordingly, an apartment
                    was assigned her in the upper part of it, of which the stairs, opening into the
                    street, were stopped up, and the entrance made from the inner court. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Thither all Fecenia's effects were immediately
                    removed, and her domestics sent for. Aebutius, also, was ordered to remove to
                    the house of one of the consul's clients. </p>
                <p> When both the informers were by these means in his power, Postumius represented
                    the affair to the senate, laying before them the whole circumstance, in due
                    order; the information given to him at first, and the discoveries gained by his
                    inquiries afterwards. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Great consternation
                    seized on the senators; not only on the public account, lest such conspiracies
                    and nightly meetings might be productive of secret treachery and mischief, but,
                    likewise, on account of their own particular families, lest some of their
                    relations might be involved in this infamous affair. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The senate voted, however, that thanks should be given to
                    the consul because he had investigated the matter with singular diligence, and
                    without exciting any alarm. They then commit to the consuls the holding an
                    inquiry, out of the common course, concerning the Bacchanals and their nocturnal
                    orgies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They order them to take care that the
                    informers, Aebutius and Fecenia, might suffer no injury on that account; and to
                    invite other informers in the matter, by offering rewards. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They ordered that the officials in those rites, whether men
                    or women, should be sought for, not only at Rome, but also throughout all the
                    market towns and places of assembly, and be delivered over to the power of the
                    consuls; and also that proclamation should be made in the city of Rome, and
                    published through all Italy, that <quote> no persons initiated in the
                        Bacchanalian rites should presume to come together or assemble on account of
                        those rites, or to perform any such kind of worship; </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and above all, that search should be made for
                    those who had assembled or conspired for personal abuse, or for any other
                    flagitious practices. The senate passed these decrees. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls directed the curule aediles to make strict
                    inquiry after all the priests of those mysteries, and to keep such as they could
                    apprehend in custody until their trial; they at the same time charged the
                    plebeian aediles to take care that no religious ceremonies <pb n="1806"
                        xml:id="p.1806"/> should be performed in private. To the capital triumvirs
                    the task was assigned to post watches in proper places of the city, and to use
                    vigilance in preventing any meetings by night. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> In order likewise to guard against fires, five assistants were joined to the
                    triumvirs, so that each might have the charge of the buildings in his own
                    separate district, on this side the Tiber. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After despatching these officers to their
                    several employments, the consuls mounted the rostrum; and, having summoned an
                    assembly of the people, one of the consuls, when he had finished the solemn form
                    of prayer which the magistrates are accustomed to pronounce before they address
                    the people, proceeded thus: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "Romans, to no
                    former assembly was this solemn supplication to the gods more suitable or even
                    more necessary: as it serves to remind you, that these are the deities whom your
                    forefathers pointed out as the objects of your worship, veneration, and prayers:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and not those which infatuated men's minds
                    with corrupt and foreign modes of religion, and drove them, as if goaded by the
                    furies, to every lust and every vice. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I am at
                    a loss to know what I should conceal, or how far I ought to speak out; for I
                    dread lest, if I leave you ignorant of any particular, I should give room for
                    carelessness, or if I disclose the whole, that I should too much awaken your
                    fears. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whatever I shall say, be assured that
                    it is less than the magnitude and atrociousness of the affair would justify:
                    exertions will be used by us that it may be sufficient to set us properly on our
                    guard. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the Bacchanalian rites have
                    subsisted for some time past in every country in Italy, and are at present
                    performed in many parts of this city also, I am sure you must have been
                    informed, not only by report, but by the nightly noises and horrid yells that
                    resound through the whole city; but still you are ignorant of the nature of that
                    business. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Part of you think it is some kind of
                    worship of the gods; others, some excusable sport and amusement, and that,
                    whatever it may be, it concerns but a few. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As
                    regards the number, if I tell you that they are many thousands, that you would
                    be immediately terrified to excess is a necessary consequence; unless I further
                    acquaint you who and what sort of persons they are. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> First, then, a great part of them are women, and this was
                    the source of the evil; the rest are males, but nearly resembling women; actors
                    and <pb n="1807" xml:id="p.1807"/> pathics in the vilest lewdness; night
                    revellers, driven frantic by wine, noise of instruments, and clamours. The
                    conspiracy, as yet, has no strength; but it has abundant means of acquiring
                    strength, for they are becoming more numerous every day. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Your ancestors would not allow that you should ever
                    assemble casually, without some good reason; that is, either when the standard
                    was erected on the Janiculum, and the army led out on occasion of elections; or
                    when the tribunes proclaimed a meeting of the commons, or some of the
                    magistrates summoned you to it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And they
                    judged it necessary, that wherever a multitude was, there should be a lawful
                    governor of that multitude present. Of what kind do you suppose are the meetings
                    of these people? In the first place, held in the night, and in the next,
                    composed promiscuously of men and women. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If
                    you knew at what ages the males are initiated, you would feel not only pity but
                    also shame for them. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Romans, can you think
                    youths initiated, under such oaths as theirs, are fit to be made soldiers? That
                    arms should be intrusted with wretches brought out of that temple of obscenity?
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Shall these, contaminated with their own
                    foul debaucheries and those of others, be champions for the chastity of your
                    wives and children? </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> But the mischief were less, if they were only effeminated by their
                        practices; of that the disgrace would chiefly affect themselves; if they
                        refrained their hands from outrage, and their thoughts from fraud.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But never was there in the state an
                        evil of so great magnitude, or one that extended to so many persons or so
                        many acts of wickedness. Whatever deeds of villany have, during late years,
                        been committed through lust; whatever, through fraud; whatever, through
                        violence; they have all, be assured, proceeded from that association alone.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They have not yet perpetrated all the
                        crimes for which they combined. The impious assembly at present confines
                        itself to outrages on private citizens; because it has not yet acquired
                        force sufficient to crush the commonwealth: but the evil increases and
                        spreads daily; it is already too great for the private ranks of life to
                        contain it, and aims its views at the body of the state. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Unless you take timely precautions, Romans, their
                        nightly assembly may become as large as this, held in open day, and legally
                        summoned by a consul. Now they one by one dread you collected together <pb
                            n="1808" xml:id="p.1808"/> in the assembly; presently, when you shall
                        have separated and retired to your several dwellings, in town and country,
                        they will again come together, and will hold a consultation on the means of
                        their own safety, and, at the same time, of your destruction. Thus united,
                        they will cause terror to every one of you. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Each of you, therefore, ought to pray that his kindred may have behaved
                        with wisdom and prudence; and if lust, if madness, has dragged any of them
                        into that abyss, to consider such a person as the relation of those with
                        whom he has conspired for every disgraceful and reckless act, and not as one
                        of your own. I am not secure, lestsome, even of yourselves, may have erred
                        through mistake; for nothing is more deceptive in appearance than false
                        religion. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the authority of the gods
                        is held out as a pretext to cover vice, fear enters our minds, lest, in
                        punishing the crimes of men, we may violate some divine right connected
                        therewith. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Numberless decisions of the
                        pontiffs, decrees of the senate, and even answers of the aruspices, free you
                        from religious scruples of this character. How often in the ages of our
                        fathers was it given in charge to the magistrates, to prohibit the
                        performance of any foreign religious rites; to banish strolling sacrificers
                        and soothsayers from the forum, the circus, and the city; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> to search for, and burn, books of divination; and to
                        abolish every mode of sacrificing that was not conformable to the Roman
                        practice! For they, completely versed in every divine and human law,
                        maintained, that nothing tended so strongly to the subversion of religion as
                        sacrifice, when we offered it not after the institutions of our forefathers,
                        but after foreign customs. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus much I
                        thought necessary to mention to you beforehand, that no vain scruple might
                        disturb your minds when you should see us demolishing the places resorted to
                        by the Bacchanalians, and dispersing their impious assemblies. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> We shall do all these things with the favour and
                        approbation of the gods; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> who, because
                        they were indignant that their divinity was dishonoured by those people's
                        lusts and crimes, have drawn forth their proceedings from hidden darkness
                        into the open light; and who have directed them to be exposed, not that they
                        may escape with impunity, but in order that they may be punished and
                        suppressed. The senate have committed to me and my colleague, an inquisition
                        extraordinary concerning <pb n="1809" xml:id="p.1809"/> that affair. What is
                        requisite to be done by ourselves, in person, we will do with energy.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The charge of posting watches through
                        the city, during the night, we have committed to the inferior magistrates;
                        and, for your parts, it is incumbent on you to execute vigorously whatever
                        duties are assigned you, and in the several places where each <milestone
                            n="13??" unit="section"/> will be placed, to perform whatever orders you
                        shall receive, and to use your best endeavours that no danger or tumult may
                        arise from the treachery of the party involved in the guilt. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They then ordered the decrees of the senate to
                    be read, and published a reward for any discoverer who should bring any of the
                    guilty before them, or <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> give information
                    against any of the absent, adding, that <quote> if any person accused should
                        fly, they would limit a certain day upon which, if he did not answer when
                        summoned, he would be condemned in his absence; and if any one should be
                        charged who was out of Italy, they would allow him a longer time, if he
                        should wish to come and make his defence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They then issued an edict, that <quote> no
                        person whatever should presume to buy or sell any thing for the purpose of
                        leaving the country; or to receive or conceal, or by any means aid the
                        fugitives. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the assembly being dismissed, great terror
                    spread throughout the city; nor was it confined merely within the walls, or to
                    the Roman territory, for every where throughout the whole of Italy alarm began
                    to be felt, when the letters from the guest-friends were received, concerning
                    the decree of the senate, and what passed in the assembly, and the edict of the
                    consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> During the night, which succeeded the
                    day in which the affair was made public, great numbers, attempting to fly, were
                    seized, and brought back by the triumvirs, who had posted guards at all the
                    gates; and informations were lodged against many, some of whom, both men and
                    women, put themselves to death. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Above seven
                    thousand men and women are said to have taken the oath of the association. But
                    it appeared that the heads of the conspiracy were the two Catinii, Marcus and
                    Caius, Roman plebeians; Lucius Opiturnius, a Faliscian; and Minius Cerrinius, a
                    Campanian: that from these proceeded all their criminal practices, and that
                    these were the chief priests and founders of the sect. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Care was taken that they should be apprehended as soon as
                        <pb n="1810" xml:id="p.1810"/> possible. They were brought before the
                    consuls, and, confessing their guilt, caused no delay to the ends of justice. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But so great were the numbers that fled from
                    the city, that because the lawsuits and property of many persons were going to
                    ruin, the praetors, Titus Maenius and Marcus Licinius, were obliged, under the
                    direction of the senate, to adjourn their courts for thirty days, until the
                    inquiries should be finished by the consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The same deserted state of the law-courts, since the persons, against whom
                    charges were brought, did not appear to answer, nor could be found in Rome,
                    necessitated the consuls to make a circuit of the country towns, and there to
                    make their inquisitions and hold the trials. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Those who, as it appeared, had been only initiated, and had made after the
                    priest, and in the most solemn form, the prescribed imprecations, in which the
                    accursed conspiracy for the perpetration of every crime and lust was contained,
                    but who had not themselves committed, or compelled others to commit, any of
                    those acts to which they were bound by the oath, —all such they left in prison.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But those who had forcibly committed
                    personal defilements or murders, or were stained with the guilt of false
                    evidence, counterfeit seals, forged wills, or other frauds, all these they
                    punished with death. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A greater number were
                    executed than thrown into prison; indeed, the multitude of men and women who
                    suffered in both ways, was very considerable. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The consuls delivered the women, who were condemned, to their relations, or to
                    those under whose guardianship they were, that they might inflict the punishment
                    in private; but if there did not appear any proper person of the kind to execute
                    the sentence, the punishment was inflicted in public. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> A charge was then given to demolish all the places where
                    the Bacchanalians had held their meetings; first, in Rome, and then throughout
                    all Italy; excepting those wherein should be found some ancient altar, or
                    consecrated statue. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With regard to the future,
                    the senate passed a decree, <quote>that no Bacchanalian rites should be
                        celebrated in Rome or in Italy:</quote> and ordering that, <quote> in case
                        any person should believe some such kind of worship incumbent on him, and
                        necessary; and that he could not, without offence to religion, and incurring
                        guilt, omit it, he should represent this to the city praetor, and the
                        praetor <pb n="1811" xml:id="p.1811"/> should lay the business before the
                        senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If permission were granted by the
                        senate, when not less than one hundred members were present, then he might
                        perform those rites, provided that no more than five persons should be
                        present at the sacrifice, and that they should have no common stock of
                        money, nor any president of the ceremonies, nor priest. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Another decree connected with this was then
                    made, on a motion of the consul, Quintus Marcius, that <quote> the business
                        respecting the persons who had served the consuls as informers should be
                        proposed to the senate in its original form, when Spurius Postumius should
                        have finished his inquiries, and returned to Rome. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They voted that Minius Cerrinius, the
                    Campanian, should be sent to Ardea, to be kept in custody there; and that a
                    caution should be given to the magistrates of that city, to guard him with more
                    than ordinary care, so as to prevent not only his escaping, but his having an
                    opportunity of committing suicide. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Spurius
                    Postumius some time after came to Rome, and on his proposing the question,
                    concerning the reward to be given to Publius Aebutius and Hispala Fecenia,
                    because the Bacchanalian ceremonies were discovered by their exertions, the
                    senate passed a vote, that <quote> the city quaestors should give to each of
                        them, out of the public treasury, one hundred thousand <hi rend="italics"
                            >asses;</hi>
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 322 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18
                                <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and that the consuls should desire the
                        plebeian tribunes to propose to the commons as soon as convenient, that the
                        campaigns of Publius Aebutius should be considered as served, that he should
                        not become a soldier against his wishes, nor should any censor assign him a
                        horse <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Those to whom the censor
                                <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> assigned a horse, were bound to
                            serve. But as liberty was granted to Aebutius to serve or not, as he
                            close, it became necessary that the censor should be thus restrained, by
                            a vote of the senate, from assigning him a horse; otherwise, if one had
                            been assigned him, whether willing or not, he must have served. </note>
                        at the public charge. </quote> They voted also, that <quote> Hispala Fecenia
                        should enjoy the privileges of alienating her property by gift or deed; of
                        marrying out of her rank, and of choosing a guardian, as if a husband had
                        conferred them by will; that she should be at liberty to wed a man of
                        honourable birth, <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and that there should be
                        no disgrace or ignominy to him who should marry her; and that the consuls
                        and praetors then in office, and their successors, should take care that no
                        injury should be <pb n="1812" xml:id="p.1812"/> offered <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> to that woman, and that she might live in safety. That
                        the senate wished, and thought proper, that all these things should be so
                        ordered. </quote> —All these particulars were proposed to the commons, and
                    executed, according to the vote of the senate; and full permission was given to
                    the consuls to determine respecting the impunity and rewards of the other
                    informers. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Marcius, having completed the
                    inquiries in his district, prepared at length to proceed into the province of
                    Liguria, for the service of which he received a supply of three thousand Roman
                    foot and one hundred and fifty horse, with five thousand Latin foot and two
                    hundred horse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The same province, and the same
                    numbers of horse and foot, had been voted to his colleague, and they received
                    the armies which, during the preceding year, the consuls, Caius Flaminius and
                    Marcus Aemilius, had commanded. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were also
                    ordered, by a decree of the senate, to raise two new legions, and they demanded
                    from the allies and Latins twenty thousand foot and one thousand three hundred
                    horse; besides, they levied three thousand Roman foot and two hundred horse.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was resolved that all this army, except
                    the legions, should be led to reinforce the army in Spain. The consuls,
                    therefore, while they themselves were engaged in the inquisitions, appointed
                    Titus Maenius to hold the levy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the
                    trials were finished, Quintus Marcius first marched against the Apuan Ligurians.
                    While he pursued these into very remote fastnesses, which <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> had always served them as lurking-places and receptacles,
                    he was surrounded in a disadvantageous position, a narrow defile which the enemy
                    had previously seized. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Here four thousand
                    soldiers fell, and three standards of the second legion, with eleven ensigns of
                    the Latin allies, were taken; abundance of arms were likewise lost, which were
                    thrown away by the men in every direction, because they impeded their flight
                    through the woody paths. The Ligurians ceased to pursue, sooner than the Romans
                    to fly. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as the consul had effected his
                    escape out of the enemy's territories, he disbanded the troops, in the country
                    of their friends, in order that the greatness of the loss sustained might not
                    appear. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But he could not obliterate all
                    memorial of his misconduct; for the pass, from which the Ligurians put him to
                    flight, has been called the Marcian pass. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1813" xml:id="p.1813"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A little before this intelligence from the war
                    in Liguria was made public, a letter from Spain was read to them, which brought
                    joy mingled with grief. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Caius Atinius, who,
                    two years before, had gone to that province in quality of praetor, fought in the
                    territory of Asta a pitched battle with the Lusitanians. About six thousand of
                    the enemy were killed, the rest routed, driven from the field, and their camp
                    taken. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then led his legions to attack the
                    town of Asta, which he took with little more trouble than he met at the camp;
                    but, having been wounded whilst he was approaching the walls too incautiously,
                    he died in a few days from the effects of the wound. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> When the letter was read, acquainting them with the
                    proprietor's death, the senate voted, that a courier should be sent to overtake
                    the praetor, Caius Calpurnius, at the port of Luna, and inform him, that the
                    senate thought proper that he should hasten his journey lest the province should
                    be without a governor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The person who was sent
                    reached Luna on the fourth day, but Calpurnius had set out some days before.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In Hither Spain, Lucius Manlius Acidinus,
                    who had come into that province at the same time when Caius Atinius came into
                    his, fought a battle with the Celtiberians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They quitted the field, the victory being undecided with the exception of this,
                    that the Celtiberians removed their camp from that quarter on the following
                    night: permission was thus afforded to the Romans to bury their dead, and
                    collect the spoils. In a few days after, the Celtiberians, having gathered a
                    large army, attacked the Romans, near the town of Calaguris. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Nothing is recorded respecting the cause that rendered them
                    weaker after their numbers were increased, but they were defeated in the battle;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> twelve thousand of their men were killed,
                    more than two thousand taken, and the Roman army got possession of their camp,
                    and had not a successor, by his arrival, checked the career of the conqueror,
                    the Celtiberians would have been completely subdued. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Both the new praetors drew off their armies into winter
                    quarters. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the time in which this intelligence was
                    announced from Spain, the games called Taurilia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Games in honour of the infernal deities, instituted in
                        the reign of Tarquin the Proud, on occasion of a malignant disorder that had
                        attacked pregnant women. Black bulls <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> were
                        sacrificed, whence the name. </note> were celebrated, during two days, on a
                    religious account. Then Marcus <pb n="1814" xml:id="p.1814"/> Fulvius exhibited
                    games, which he had vowed in the Aetolian war, and which lasted ten days. Many
                    artists, out of respect to him, came from Greece on the occasion; and now, for
                    the first time, the Romans had <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> an opportunity
                    of seeing contests of wrestlers; they were also presented with a hunt of lions
                    and panthers; the games were celebrated with almost the variety and abundance of
                    the present age. The nine days' solemnity succeeded, because showers of stones
                    had fallen, for three days, in Picenum; and fires from heaven were said to have
                    arisen in various places, and singed the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    clothes of many persons by slight flashes. By order of the pontiffs, a
                    supplication, of one day's continuance, was added because the temple of Ops, in
                    the Capitol, was struck by <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> lightning. The
                    consuls sacrificed victims of the larger kinds, and purified the city. At the
                    same time, an account was brought from Umbria, of a hermaphrodite, twelve years
                    old, being found there. The consuls wishing to get rid of the prodigy, as it was
                    a fearful omen, ordered that it should be removed instantly out of the Roman
                    territory, and put to death. During <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> this year,
                    a body of Transalpine Gauls came into Venetia, without committing depredation or
                    hostility, and pitched on a spot for building a town, not far from that where
                    Aquileia now stands. Ambassadors were sent from Rome, over the Alps, <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> on this business, and to them an answer was given
                    that <quote> they had not emigrated by the authority of their state, nor did
                        their countrymen know what they were doing in Italy. </quote> About this
                    time Lucius Scipio <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> celebrated games, which he
                    said he had vowed during the war with Antiochus; they lasted ten days, and the
                    money was contributed for the purpose by the kings and <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> states of Asia. Valerius Antias asserts, that, after his
                    condemnation, and the sale of his effects, he was sent as ambassador into Asia,
                    to adjust disputes between the kings Antiochus and Eumenes; that there the money
                    was contributed for him, and actors collected through Asia: and that after his
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> embassy, the subject of those games (of
                    which he had made no mention after the war, in which he asserted that they had
                    been vowed) was at length introduced in the senate-house. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the year was now drawing to a conclusion,
                    Quintus Marcius then abroad, was soon to go out of office. Spurius Postumius,
                    after having conducted the inquisitions with the utmost care and propriety, held
                    the elections. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Appius Clau- <pb n="1815"
                        xml:id="p.1815"/> dius Pulcher and Marcus Sempronius Tuditanus were chosen
                    consuls. Next day, Publius Cornelius Cethegus, Aulus Postumius Albinus, Caius
                    Afranius Stellio, Caius Atilius Serranus, Lucius Postumius Tempsanus, and Marcus
                    Claudius Marcellus were elected praetors. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Towards the close of the year, because the consul Spurius Postumius reported
                    that in travelling along the coasts of Italy, for the purpose of holding the
                    inquisitions, he had found two colonies deserted, Sipontum on the upper sea, and
                    Buxentum on the lower; in pursuance of a decree of the senate, Lucius Scribonus
                    Libo, Marcus Tuccius, and Cneius Bebius Tamphilus, were appointed commissioners
                    for conducting colonies thither, by Titus Maenius, city praetor. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The war with king Perseus and the Macedonians, which
                    was impending, has not derived its origin from what most persons imagine, nor
                    from Perseus himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The preliminary steps
                    were taken by Philip, and, if he had lived some time longer, he would himself
                    have carried on that war. When the conditions of peace were imposed on him, when
                    he was vanquished, one particular chagrined him more than all the rest;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> this was because the liberty of wreaking
                    his vengeance on such of the Macedonians as had revolted from him in the course
                    of the war, was taken from him by the senate; although, because Quintius had
                    left that point undetermined, when he was adjusting the articles of
                    pacification, he had not despaired of the possibility of obtaining it.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Afterwards, on the defeat of Antiochus at
                    Thermopylae, the armies being separated at the time when the consul Acilius
                    carried on the siege <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> of Heraclea, and Philip
                    besieged Lamia, because he was ordered to retire from the walls of Lamia, as
                    soon as Heraclea was taken, and the town was surrendered to the Romans, he was
                    grievously offended with this circumstance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, indeed, in some measure, soothed his resentment; for, when he was
                    hastening to Naupactum, where the Aetolians had re-assembled after their flight,
                    he gave Philip permission to make war on Amynander and Athamania; and to annex
                    to his dominions the cities which the Aetolians had taken from the Thessalians.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Without much difficulty, he expelled
                    Amynander from Athamania, and got possession of several cities. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> He also reduced under his dominion the city of
                    Demetrias, a place of great strength, and convenient in every respect; with the
                    whole of the Magnesian state. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Afterwards,
                    finding that <pb n="1816" xml:id="p.1816"/> several cities in Thrace, through an
                    abuse of the liberty which they had lately acquired, and to which they had not
                    been accustomed, were distracted by <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    dissensions among their leading men, he, by uniting himself to the parties that
                    were worsted in their disputes with their countrymen, made himself master of
                    them all. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By these means the king's wrath against the
                    Romans was appeased for the present; but he never abandoned the project of
                    collecting such a force during peace, as would enable him to maintain a war,
                    whenever the fortunate occasion should be offered. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He augmented the revenues of his kingdom, not only out of
                    the produce of the lands and the port duties, but also he worked the mines, both
                    the old ones which had been neglected, and new ones which he opened in many
                    places. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then, (in order to restore the former
                    degree of population, which had been diminished by the calamities of war,) he
                    not only caused an increase in the offspring of that generation, by compelling
                    every one <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> to marry and rear children, but he
                    transplanted a great multitude of Thracians into Macedonia, and, during a long
                    suspension of arms, he employed the utmost assiduity in augmenting, by every
                    possible means, the strength of his kingdom. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Causes afterward occurred, which served to revive his animosity against the
                    Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Complaints made by the Thessalians and
                    Perrhae- bians, of his holding possession of their towns, and, by ambassadors
                    from king Eumenes, of his having forcibly seized the cities of Thrace, and
                    transplanted great numbers of their people into Macedonia, had been received in
                    such a manner as plainly evinced that they were not thought unworthy of
                    attention. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What made the greatest impression
                    on the senate, was, their having been informed, that Philip aimed at the
                    possession of Aenus and Maronea; as to the Thessalians, they regarded them less.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Ambassadors came, likewise, from the
                    Athamanians, complaining not of the loss of a part of their territory, nor of
                    encroachment on their frontier, —but that all Athamania had been brought under
                    the dominion and jurisdiction of the king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Exiles from Maronea also appeared, who had been expelled by the king's troops,
                    for having supported the cause of liberty; who reported, that not only Maronea,
                    but Aenus too, was held in subjection by him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Ambassadors came from Philip to defend his conduct, who asserted, that, <pb
                        n="1817" xml:id="p.1817"/> nothing had been done without permission from the
                    Roman commanders. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That <quote> the states of
                        the Thessalians, Perrhaebians, and Magnesians, and the nation of the
                        Athamanians, with Amynander, had all been engaged in the same cause with the
                        Aetolians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That after the expulsion of
                        king Antiochus, the consul, being himself busy in reducing the towns of
                        $Etolia, had named Philip to subdue those states, and they remained subject
                        to him in consequence of their being conquered by his arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The senate, too, that they might not make any
                    decision concerning the king in his absence, sent Quintus Caecilius Metellus,
                    Marcus Baebius Tamphilus, and Tiberius Sempronius, ambassadors to adjust those
                    disputes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Previous to their arrival, a
                    convention of all those states who had disputes with the king, was summoned to
                    meet at Tempe in Thessaly. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When all were seated there, (the Roman
                    ambassadors in the character of arbitrators, the Thessalians, Perrhaebians, and
                    Athamanians professedly as accusers, and Philip as defendant, to hear the
                    accusations brought against him,) those <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> who
                    were the heads of the embassies, according to their several tempers, their
                    favour, or their hatred towards the king, spoke, some with acrimony, others with
                    mildness. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Philippopolis, Trica, Phaloria,
                    Eurymenae, and the other towns in their neighbourhood, became the subject of
                    dispute. The point in controversy was, whether these towns were the property of
                    the Thessalians, when they <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> were forcibly
                    taken from them, and held by the Aetolians, (for from these it was acknowledged
                    that Philip had received them,) or whether they were originally belonging to the
                    Aetolians: Acilius having granted them to the king, on the condition that
                        <quote> they had been the property of the Aetolians; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> and if they had sided with the Aetolians of their own
                        free will, and not compelled by violence and arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The question in regard to the towns of the
                    Perrhaebians and Magnesians turned on the same points; for the Aetolians, by
                    holding possession of them occasionally, had confused the rights of all.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To these particulars, which were matter of
                    discussion, the complaints of the Thessalians were added, that <quote> if these
                        towns were now restored to them, they would come into their hands in a state
                        of desolation, and depopulated; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> for
                        besides the loss of inhabitants through the casualties of war, Philip had
                        carried away <pb n="1818" xml:id="p.1818"/> five hundred of their young men
                        of the first rank into Macedonia, and abused their labour by employing them
                        in servile offices; and had taken pains to render useless whatever he should
                        be compelled to restore to the Thessalians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> That Thebes in Phthiotis was the only sea-port they had, which formerly
                        produced much profit and advantage to the inhabitants of Thessaly; but that
                        Philip, having collected there a number of ships of burthen, made them steer
                        their course past Thebes to Demetrias, and turned thither the whole commerce
                        by sea. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That he did not now scruple to
                        offer violence, even to ambassadors, who, by the law of nations, are every
                        where held inviolable, but had laid an ambush for theirs who were going to
                        Titus Quintius, that the Thessalians were in consequence seized with such
                        dread, that not one of them, even in their own states, or in the general
                        assemblies of the nation, ventured to open his lips. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> For the Romans, the defenders of their liberty, were
                        far distant; and a severe master close at their side, debarring them from
                        using the kindness of the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If
                        speech were not free, what else could be said to be so: at present, through
                        confidence in the protection of the ambassadors, they uttered their groans
                        rather than words; but, unless the Romans would take some precautions that
                        both the fears of the Greeks bordering on Macedonia and the arrogance of
                        Philip should be abated, his having been conquered, and their being set at
                        liberty, would prove utterly fruitless. Like a restive, unmanageable horse,
                        he required to be checked with a strong bridle. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These bitter expressions were used by the
                    last speakers among them; those who spoke before having endeavoured by mildness
                    to mitigate his resentment; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> requesting of him
                        <quote> that he should pardon persons pleading in defence of their liberty;
                        that he should, laying aside the harshness of a master, generally display
                        himself an ally and friend; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> that he
                        should imitate the Roman people, who wished to unite their allies to them by
                        the ties of affection, rather than of fear. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> When the Thessalians had finished, the
                    Perrhaebians pleaded that Gonnocondylos, to which Philip had given the name of
                    Olympias, belonged to Perrhaebia, and ought to be restored to them; and the same
                    demand was made with respect to Malœa, and Ericinium. The Athamanians claimed a
                    restoration of liberty, and the forts Athenaeus and Pœtneus. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1819" xml:id="p.1819"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip began his discourse also with
                    complaints, that he might maintain the appearance of an accuser rather than of a
                    defendant. He complained that <quote> the Thessalians had taken by force of
                        arms, Menelais in Dolopia, a town belonging to his dominions; likewise,
                        Petra in Pieria was taken by the same Thessalians and the Perrhaebians;
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that they had reduced under their
                        government Xyniae, which unquestionably belonged to Aetolia; and that
                        Parachelois, which was under Athamania, was, without any just claim,
                        subjected to the jurisdiction of the Thessalians. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As to the charges brought against him, concerning an
                        ambush laid for ambassadors, and of sea-ports being frequented or deserted,
                        the one was quite ridiculous, (as if he were <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> to account for what harbours merchants or sailors
                        should frequent,) and the other the constant tenor of his conduct rejected
                        with scorn. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> During a number of years,
                        ambassadors had never ceased carrying complaints against him, sometimes to
                        the Roman generals, at others to Rome to the senate. Which of them had ever
                        been injured, even in words? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They said,
                        indeed, that an ambush was once laid for some who were going to Quintius,
                        but they are silent in regard to consequences. Such were the accusations of
                        men searching for false imputations, because they had no truth on their
                        side. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He said, that <quote> the Thessalians,
                        insolently and wantonly, abused the indulgence of the Roman people, too
                        greedily drinking, as it were, strong draughts of liberty after a long
                        thirst; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and thus, in the manner of slaves
                        lately set free, made trial of their voices and tongues, and prided
                        themselves in invectives and railings against their masters. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then, hurried on by passion, he added, that
                        <quote>his sun had not set yet;</quote> which expression, not only the
                    Thessalians, but the Romans also, took as a menace to themselves; and when a
                    murmur of displeasure followed his words, and was at length hushed, he replied
                    to the ambassadors <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> of the Perrhaebians and
                    Athamanians, <quote> that the cases of the cities of which they had spoken were
                        the same. The consul Acilius and the Romans gave them to him, when they were
                        the property of enemies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If the donors
                        chose to resume what they had given, he knew he must submit, but in that
                        case they would, for the gratification of inconstant and unprofitable
                        allies, do injury to a more useful and more faithful friend. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> For no favour produced less permanent gratitude
                        than the gift of liberty, <pb n="1820" xml:id="p.1820"/> especially among
                        people who were ready to corrupt it by using it badly. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After examining the merits of the cause, the
                    ambassadors pronounced their judgment, that <quote> the Macedonian garrisons
                        should be withdrawn from the cities in question, and that the kingdom of
                        Macedonia should be limited by its ancient boundaries. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> That with regard to the injuries which both parties
                        complained of being done to them, it would be requisite to institute some
                        compact for the attainment of justice, in order to decide the controversies
                        between those states and the Macedonians. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king being grievously offended, the
                    ambassadors proceeded thence to Thessalonica, to give a hearing to the business
                    concerning the cities of Thrace. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here the
                    ambassadors of Eumenes said, that <quote> if the Romans wished that Aenus and
                        Maronea should be independent, the king felt ashamed to say more, than to
                        recommend it to them to leave those people free in fact, and not in words;
                        nor to suffer their kindness to be intercepted by another. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> But if they had not so much concern for the states
                        situated in Thrace, it was much more reasonable that Eumenes should possess,
                        as the rewards of war, the places which had been under the dominion of
                        Antiochus, than Philip; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and that, either
                        on account of his father Attalus's deserts in the war, waged by the Roman
                        people against Philip himself, or on account of his own, because he had
                        shared all the toils and dangers on land and sea, during the war with
                        Antiochus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Besides, he had the previous
                        judgment of the ten ambassadors to that purpose; who, when they granted the
                        Chersonesus and Lysimachia, surely yielded at the same time Aenus and
                        Maronea; which, even from the proximity of situation, were but a sort of
                        appendage to the larger gift. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For, as to
                        Philip, by what merits towards the Roman people, or what right of dominion,
                        had he put garrisons into those places, which were at so great a distance
                        from the borders of Macedonia? They then desired that the Romans would order
                        the Maronites to be called, from whom they would receive more positive
                        information of the condition of those cities. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Maronite ambassadors being called in,
                    declared, that <quote> not in one spot of the city, as in other garrisoned
                        towns, but in every quarter of it, there was a party of the king's troops,
                        and that Maronea was full of Macedonians; in consequence of which, the <pb
                            n="1821" xml:id="p.1821"/> favourites of the king domineered over the
                        rest; they alone had liberty of speaking, either in the senate or assemblies
                        of the people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All posts of eminence they
                        assumed to themselves, or conferred on whom they thought proper. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> That the most deserving persons, who had a regard
                        for liberty and for the laws, were either expelled their country, and in
                        exile, or remained in silence, dishonoured and subjected to men of the worst
                        description. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They added also a few words respecting their
                    right to the frontier places, affirming, that <quote> Quintus Fabius Labeo, when
                        he was in that country, had fixed as a boundary line to Philip, the old
                        royal road leading to Paroreia, in Thrace, which in no place leads towards
                        the sea; and that Philip afterwards drew a new one in another direction, in
                        order to include the cities and lands of the Maronites. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, in his reply to these charges, took
                    quite another course than when lately answering the Thessalians and
                    Perrhaebians, and said: — <quote> My dispute is not now with the Maronites, or
                        with Eumenes, but with you yourselves, Romans, from whom I have long ago
                        seen that I can obtain no justice. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        cities of Macedonia, which had revolted from me during a suspension of arms,
                        I thought should in justice be restored to me; not that they would have made
                        any great accession to my dominions, because the towns are small in
                        themselves, and besides, are situated on the extremities of the frontiers;
                        but because the example was of great consequence towards retaining the rest
                        of the Macedonians in their allegiance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        This was refused me. In the Aetolian war, I was ordered by the consul,
                        Manius Acilius, to lay siege to Lamia, and when I had there undergone a long
                        course of fatigue in fighting and constructing works, and was on the point
                        of mounting the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> walls, the consul
                        recalled me from the city when almost in my possession, and compelled me to
                        draw off my troops from it. As some consolation for this hard treatment, I
                        received permission to seize on some forts, rather than cities, of Thessaly,
                        Perrhaebia, and Athamania. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These also you
                        yourselves, Quintus Caecilius, have taken from me a few days ago. The
                        ambassadors of Eumenes, just now, took for granted, it seems, that Eumenes
                        would with more justice than I possess whatever belonged to Antiochus. I
                        judge the matter to be widely different. For Eumenes could not have remained
                        on his throne, unless the Romans had engaged in the war, and not unless they
                        had conquered. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Therefore he has received a
                        fa- <pb n="1822" xml:id="p.1822"/> vour from you, not you from him; whereas,
                        so far were any part of my dominions from being in danger, that, when
                        Antiochus voluntarily offered to purchase my alliance, with three thousand
                        talents and fifty decked ships, guaranteeing to me all the cities of Greece
                        of which I had heretofore been in possession, I rejected that offer.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I avowed myself his enemy, even before
                        Manius Acilius brought over an army into Greece. In conjunction with that
                        consul, I supported whatever share of the war he gave me in charge.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To the succeeding consul, Lucius
                        Scipio, when he proposed leading his army by land to the Hellespont, I not
                        only gave a passage through my dominions, but also made roads for him, built
                        bridges, supplied him with provisions, and escorted him, not only through
                        Macedon, but likewise through Thrace; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        where, besides other business, I had to procure peace from the barbarians.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In requital of this zeal, not to call
                        it merit, towards you, whether would it be proper in you, Romans, to enlarge
                        and increase my dominions by acts of generosity, or to ravish from me what I
                        possessed, either in my own right or through your kindness. The cities of
                        Macedon, which you acknowledge to have belonged to my kingdom, are not
                        restored. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Eumenes comes to plunder me as
                        he would Antiochus, and, if you choose to believe him, covers his most
                        shameless chicanery under the decree of the ten ambassadors, by which
                        principally he can be refuted and convicted. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> For is it not expressly and plainly set down in that
                        writing, that the Chersonese and Lysimachia are granted to Eumenes; and
                        where are Aenus, Maronea, and the cities of Thrace annexed to it in writing?
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> That which he did not dare even to
                        ask from them, shall he obtain from you, as if under their grant? It is a
                        matter of importance in what light you choose to consider me. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> If you are resolved to persecute me as an enemy
                        and foe, proceed to act as you have begun: but, if you have any
                        consideration for me as a king in friendship and alliance with you, I must
                        entreat you not to judge me deserving of such injurious treatment. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king's discourse made a considerable
                    impression on the ambassadors; they therefore left the matter in suspense, by
                    this indecisive resolution, that <quote> if the cities in question were granted
                        to Eumenes by the decree of the ten ambassadors, they would make no
                        alteration. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If Philip subdued them in war,
                        he should, by the laws of war, hold them as the prize of victory. If neither
                        were the case, then their judg- <pb n="1823" xml:id="p.1823"/> ment was,
                        that the decision should be referred to the senate; and in order that all
                        things might remain in their original state, the garrisons in those cities
                        should be withdrawn. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These causes, principally, alienated the
                    regard of Philip from the Romans, so that the war naturally seems not set on
                    foot by his son Perseus for any fresh causes, but rather for these causes,
                    bequeathed by the father to the son. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Rome
                    there was hitherto no suspicion of a war with Macedonia. Lucius Manlius, the
                    proconsul, had by this time come home from Spain. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On his demanding a triumph from the senate assembled in the
                    temple of Bellona, the greatness of his exploits justified the demand, but
                    precedent opposed it; for it was a rule, established by ancient practice, that
                    no commander, who had not brought home his troops, should triumph, unless he had
                    delivered up the province to his successor, in a state of thorough subjection
                    and tranquillity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> An honour of a middling
                    grade was conferred on Manlius, namely, that he should enter the city in
                    ovation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He carried in the procession
                    fifty-two golden crowns, one hundred and twenty-two pounds' weight of gold, with
                    sixteen thousand three hundred pounds of silver; and announced in the senate,
                    that his quaestor, Quintus Fabius, was bringing ten thousand pounds' weight of
                    silver, and eighty of gold, and that he would carry it likewise to the treasury.
                    During that year there was a formidable insurrection of the slaves in Apulia.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Lucius Postumius, praetor, governed the
                    province of Tarentum, and conducted with much severity inquiries into a
                    conspiracy of peasants, who had infested the roads and public pastures with
                    robberies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Of these, he passed sentence on no
                    less than seven thousand; many of whom made their escape, and on many punishment
                    was inflicted. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consuls, after being long
                    detained in the city by the levies, set out at length for their provinces. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year, Caius Calpurnius and Lucius
                    Quintius, the two praetors in Spain, drew their troops out of winter quarters,
                    at the commencement of spring, and making a junction of them in Baeturia, for
                    they were resolved to proceed in the operations of the campaign with united zeal
                    and harmony, advanced into Carpetania, where the enemy's camp lay. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> At a small distance from the towns of Hippo and
                    Toletum, a fight began between the foraging parties, to whom when reinforcements
                    came from both armies from the camps, the entire armies were <pb n="1824"
                        xml:id="p.1824"/> by degrees drawn out into the field. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In this irregular kind of battle, the advantage of the
                    ground and the manner of fighting were in favour of the enemy. The two Roman
                    armies were routed, and driven into their camp; but the enemy did not pursue the
                    dismayed Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Roman praetors, lest
                    their camp should be attacked next day, giving the signal in silence, led away
                    their army in the dead of the following night. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    At the first dawn, the Spaniards came up to the rampart in battle array, and
                    entered the camp which, beyond their expectation, was deserted, and made prey of
                    whatever had in the hurry and confusion been first left behind; and then,
                    returning to their own station, remained, for a few days, at rest within their
                    camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Of the Romans and allies, there were
                    killed in the battle and the pursuit, five thousand men, out of whose spoils the
                    enemy furnished themselves with arms. They then advanced to the river Tagus.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All the intermediate time the Roman
                    praetors employed in collecting aid from the allied Spanish states, and reviving
                    the spirits of their men after the dismay occasioned by their defeat. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> When their strength appeared adequate, and the
                    soldiers too called for their enemy, to blot out in vengeance their former
                    disgrace, they pitched their camp at the distance of twelve miles from the river
                    Tagus; but decamping thence at the third watch, and marching with their army in
                    a square, reached the bank of the river at break of day. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The enemy's camp was on a hill at the other side of the
                    river. They immediately led their army across the river where it was fordable in
                    two places, Calpurnius having the command of the right, Quintius of the left.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The enemy continued motionless, since
                    they were surprised at the sudden arrival of the Romans, and busy in
                    consultations, when they might have excited confusion among the troops during
                    their hurry in passing the river. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In the mean
                    time the Romans brought over all their baggage, and threw it together in a heap,
                    and seeing the enemy, at length, begin to move, and having no time for
                    fortifying a camp, they formed their line of battle. In the centre were placed
                    the fifth legion, serving under Calpurnius, and the eighth, under Quintius,
                    which composed the principal strength of their army. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> All the way to the enemy's camp they had an open plain,
                    free from all danger of ambush. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Spaniards saw the two bodies of
                    Romans, on <pb n="1825" xml:id="p.1825"/> their side of the river, they rushed
                    suddenly out of the camp, and advanced to battle at full speed, that they might
                    fall upon them before they should unite and put themselves in order. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The fight, in the beginning, was urged with great
                    fury; the Spaniards being elated by their late success, and the Roman soldiery
                    inflamed to rage, by a discomfiture to which they were unaccustomed. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The centre, consisting of two legions of the greatest
                    bravery, fought with the utmost vigour. The enemy, seeing that they could not be
                    forced from their ground by any other means, resolved to make their attack in
                    form of a wedge; and this body, becoming continually more numerous and more
                    compact, pressed hard on them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the
                    praetor, Calpur- nius, perceived that his line was distressed in this part, he
                    hastily despatched two <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> lieutenants-general,
                    Titus Quintilius Varus and Lucius Juventius Thalna, to animate the courage of
                    the two legions, who were ordered to say, that <quote> all hopes of victory, and
                        of retaining possession of Spain, depended entirely on them. If they should
                        give ground, not a man in that whole army would ever see Italy, no, nor even
                        the farther bank of the Tagus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He himself, at the head of the cavalry of the
                    two legions, making a small circuit, charged the flank of the wedge, which was
                    pressing upon his centre. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quintius, likewise,
                    with his cavalry, charged the enemy on the other flank; but the horsemen of
                    Calpurnius fought with far greater spirit, while the praetor himself exceeded
                    all others. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was the first that struck down
                    one of the enemy, and he pushed in among the troops in the centre, in such a
                    manner that it was hard to distinguish to which side he belonged. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Thus the horse were animated by the extraordinary
                    valour of the praetor, and the infantry by that of the horse. Shame, because
                    they saw the praetor in the midst of the enemy's weapons, inspired the foremost
                    centurions. They all, therefore, earnestly pressed the standard-bearers, urging
                    them to carry forward the ensigns, and the soldiers to follow with speed.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> All set up the shout anew, and made an
                    attack as violent as if it were made from the higher ground. Like a flood,
                    therefore, they broke and bore down the enemy in dismay, nor could they be
                    resisted, pouring in one after another. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    cavalry pursued the fugitives to their camp, and mixing with the crowd of the
                    runaways, penetrated within the rampart. Here the fight was renewed by the
                    troops left to guard <pb n="1826" xml:id="p.1826"/> the camp, and the Roman
                    horsemen were obliged to dismount. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> While they
                    were engaged, the fifth legion came up, and afterwards the rest of the troops
                    joined them with all the speed they could. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The Spaniards were cut to pieces in all parts of the camp; not more than four
                    thousand men made their escape. Of these about three thousand, who kept their
                    arms, took possession of a mountain in the neighbourhood, and one thousand, who
                    were in general but half armed, dispersed through the country. This army of the
                    enemy had contained thirty-five thousand men, of whom that very small number
                    survived the battle. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> One hundred and
                    thirty-three standards were taken. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Of the
                    Romans and allies, a few more than six hundred fell; and of the provincial
                    auxiliaries, about one hundred and fifty. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The
                    loss of five military tribunes, and a few Roman horsemen, served principally to
                    give the victory the appearance of being a bloody one. The army lodged in the
                    enemy's camp, as they had not had time to fortify one of their own. <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> Next day the cavalry was praised by Calpurnius in an
                    assembly, and presented with trappings; and he declared publicly, that through
                    their bravery, principally, the enemy had been defeated, and their camp stormed
                    and taken. Quinctius, the other praetor, presented his cavalry also with chains
                    and clasps. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> A great many centurions also, of
                    both the armies, received gratuities, especially those who were in the centre. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, as soon as they had finished the
                    levies, and other business which required to be done at Rome, led the army into
                    their province, Liguria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Sempronius marched
                    from Pisae against the Apuan Ligurians, and by ravaging their lands, and by
                    burning their villages and forts, he opened that difficult country, as far as
                    the river Macra and the harbour of Luna. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    enemy took possession of a mountain which had been the ancient retreat of their
                    forefathers; but the difficulty of access being overcome, they were dislodged by
                    force. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius, against the Ingaunian
                    tribe, rivalled in several successful battles the good fortune and bravery of
                    his colleague. He also stormed six of their towns, in which he made many
                    thousand prisoners, beheading forty-three of the chief promoters of the war.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The time of the elections now drew near;
                    but Claudius came home to Rome sooner than Sempronius, to whom the business of
                    presiding at the elections had been allotted, because his brother, Publius
                    Claudius, <pb n="1827" xml:id="p.1827"/> stood candidate for the consulship.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His competitors, of patrician rank, were
                    Lucius Aemilius, Quintus Fabius Labeo, and Servius Sulpicius Galba, who had been
                    candidates before, and now renewed their suit, for an honour which was the more
                    justly due to them, owing to their repulses, as it had been refused before.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Besides, as it was not lawful that more
                    than one patrician should be appointed, there was a closer contest between the
                    four candidates. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The plebeian candidates
                    likewise were men in high esteem. Lucius Porcius, Quintus Terentius Culleo, and
                    Cneius Baebius Tamphilus; these two had been disappointed, but had cherished
                    hopes of attaining the honour at some future time. Claudius was the only new
                    candidate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius Labeo and Lucius
                    Porcius Licinus were marked out by public opinion as the successful persons;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but Claudius, the consul, unattended by
                    his lictors, canvassed with his brother through all parts of the forum,
                    notwithstanding the loud remonstrances of his opponents and the greater part of
                    the senate, who insisted that <quote> he ought to remember that he was consul of
                        the Roman people, rather than the brother of Publius Claudius. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Why should he not rather sit on his tribunal,
                        content himself with presiding, and remain a silent spectator of the
                        business. </quote> Yet he could not be restrained from a display of his
                    immoderate zeal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The election was, also,
                    several times interrupted by contentions between the plebeian tribunes; some of
                    whom struggled hard in opposition to the consul, and others in support of the
                    cause which he favoured. At last, Appius conquered all opposition, so as to set
                    aside Fabius, and bring in his brother. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Thus
                    was Publius Claudius Pulcher elected consul, beyond his own, and indeed the
                    general expectation. Lucius Porcius Licinus carried his election also, because
                    the contest among the plebeian candidates was conducted with a decent degree of
                    warmth, and not with the violence of Claudius. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> Then was held the election of praetors. Caius Decimius Flavus, Publius
                    Sempronius Longus, Publius Cornelius Cethegus, Quintus Naevius Matho, Caius
                    Sempronius Blaesus, and Aulus Terentius Varro, were made praetors. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Such were the occurrences at home and abroad of this
                    year, during the consulate of Appius Claudius and Marcus Sempronius. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the following year,
                    Publius Claudius and Lucius Porcius, the consuls, when Quintus Caecilius, <pb
                        n="1828" xml:id="p.1828"/> Marcus Baebius, and Tiberius Sempronius, who had
                    been sent to adjust the matters in dispute between the kings, Philip and
                    Eumenes, and the states of the Thessalians, had given an account of <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> their embassy, introduced to the senate ambassadors
                    from those kings and states. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On this occasion,
                    the same arguments were repeated by all parties, which had been urged before the
                    ambassadors in Greece. The senate then decreed that a new embassy, the principal
                    man of which was Appius Claudius, should be sent into Macedonia and Greece, to
                    know whether the several states had been restored to the Rhodians, Thessalians,
                    and Perrhaebians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Instructions were given to
                    the same, that the garrisons should be withdrawn from Aenus and Maronea, and
                    that all the sea-coast of Thrace should be made free and independent of Philip
                    and the Macedonians. They were ordered also to go to Peloponnesus, from which
                    the former ambassadors had departed, leaving affairs in a more unsettled state
                    than they would have been if they had not come thither. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> For besides other matters, they were even sent away without
                    an answer by the Achaean council, nor was an audience of that body granted to
                    them at their request. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When Quintus Caecilius
                    made a heavy complaint on this subject, and at the same time the Lacedaemonians
                    deplored the demolition of their walls, the carrying off their poor people into
                    Achaia, the selling of them there, and the depriving them of the laws of
                    Lycurgus, by which the nation had been supported unto that time, the <milestone
                        n="7??" unit="section"/> Achaians laboured principally to excuse their
                    having refused a meeting of the council by quoting a law which enacted, that a
                    council should not be summoned, except on business of peace or war, or when
                    ambassadors should come from the senate with letters or written instructions.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That this kind of excuse should not be
                    made in future, the senate observed to them, that they ought to take care that
                    Roman ambassadors should at all times have an opportunity of applying to their
                    council, in like manner as an audience of the senate was always given to them,
                    at any time when they wished it. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After those embassies were dismissed, Philip,
                    being informed that he must yield up the states, and evacuate the towns in
                    question, was highly enraged against all, yet vented his fury on the Maronites
                    in particular. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He gave a charge to Onomastus,
                    who had the command of the sea-coast, to put <pb n="1829" xml:id="p.1829"/> to
                    death the leaders of the opposite party. This man, through the agency of a
                    person called Cassander, a partisan of the king's, who had resided a long time
                    in Maronea, having introduced Thracians by night, put the inhabitants to the
                    sword, as if the city had been taken by storm. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When the Roman ambassadors complained of his acting with such cruelty towards
                    the innocent Maronites, and with such presumption towards the Roman people, in
                    killing, as enemies, those very persons to whom the senate had adjudged the
                    restoration of liberty, he denied that <quote> any of those matters concerned
                        him, or any one belonging to him; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that
                        they had quarrelled among themselves, and fought, because some wished to
                        bring over their state to his side, others to that of Eumenes. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> That they might easily ascertain this; and they
                        had only to ask the Maronites themselves. </quote> For he was confident,
                    that while they were all under the impression of terror, since the late
                    massacre, not one of them would dare to utter a word against him. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Appius said, that <quote> a case so clear ought not
                        to be examined into as if it were doubtful. But if he wished to remove the
                        guilt from himself, let him send Onomastus and Cassander, the actors in that
                        business, to Rome, that the senate might examine them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first, these words so entirely disconcerted
                    the king, that neither his colour nor his looks remained unchanged; then, after
                    some time, having collected his thoughts, he replied, that <quote> he would send
                        Cassander, who had been in Maronea, if it was their desire: <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> but as to Onomastus, how could that matter affect him,
                        who, so far from being in Maronea, was not even near it? </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was more careful of Onomastus, as a more
                    valued friend, yet he dreaded him much more lest he might make discoveries;
                    because he had, in person, conversed with him on the subject, and he had made
                    him an agent and accomplice in many similar acts. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Cassander is supposed to have been taken off, that the
                    truth might not be divulged, by poison administered by persons sent to escort
                    him through Epirus to the seacoast. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassadors departed from the conference
                    with Philip in such a manner that they made it manifest that none of these acts
                    pleased them; and Philip, with a full resolution to have recourse again to arms.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Because his strength was as yet
                    insufficient for that purpose, he resolved, in order to pro- <pb n="1830"
                        xml:id="p.1830"/> cure delay, to send his younger son Demetrius to Rome, to
                    clear him from the above-named charges; and at the same time to deprecate the
                    wrath of the senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Philip had strong
                    expectations that the young man himself, because he had, while a hostage at
                    Rome, exhibited proofs of a princely disposition, would have a good deal of
                    influence now. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, under the pretence
                    of carrying succour to the Byzantians, but in reality with design to strike
                    terror into the chieftains of the Thracians, he marched into their country,
                    utterly defeated them in an engagement, in which he took their commander,
                    Amadocus, prisoner, and then returned to Macedonia, having first despatched
                    emissaries to induce the barbarians, living near the Danube, to make an
                    irruption into Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The arrival of the Roman
                    ambassadors, who had been ordered to go from Macedonia into Achaia, was expected
                    in Peloponnesus; and in order that the Achaeans might settle their plans of
                    conduct towards them beforehand, their praetor, Lycortas, summoned a general
                    council. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here the affair of the Lacedaemonians
                    was taken into consideration. It was observed that <quote> from enemies, they
                        were turned accusers; and there was reason to fear lest they should prove
                        more formidable, after having been conquered, than when at war: for in it
                        the Achaeans had the Romans as allies in their cause; now the same Romans
                        were more favourable to the Lacedaemonians than to the Achaeans. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Even Areus and Alcibiades, both restored from
                        exile through the kindness of the Achaeans, had undertaken an embassy to
                        Rome, in prejudice to a nation to which they were so much obliged; and had
                        used language so severe, that they seemed to have been banished from their
                        country, instead of being restored to it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A general clamour arose, requiring him to put
                    the question on each of them by name; and as every thing was directed by
                    passion, not by reason, they were condemned to die. In a few days after this the
                    Roman ambassadors arrived, and a council was summoned to meet them at Clitor, in
                    Arcadia. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before they transacted any business, alarm was
                    excited in the Achaeans, accompanied by the reflection, how unlikely the dispute
                    was to <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> receive impartial judgment, when they
                    saw in company with the ambassadors Areus and Alcibiades, whom in their last
                    council they had condemned to death; yet none of them dared to utter a word.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Appius acquainted them <pb n="1831"
                        xml:id="p.1831"/> that the senate was much displeased at those matters, of
                    which the Lacedaemonians made complaint before them; <quote> first, the massacre
                        that took place at Compasium of those who, in obedience to the summons of
                        Philopœmen, came to stand a trial; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> then
                        after such barbarity had been exercised towards men, that their cruelty
                        might be felt in every part, the having demolished the wall of that famous
                        city, having abrogated its laws of the greatest antiquity, and abolished the
                        discipline of Lycurgus, so famed throughout the world. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After Appius had spoken to this effect,
                    Lycortas, both because he was praetor and because he was of the faction of
                    Philopœmen, the adviser of all that was done at Lacedaemon, answered him thus:
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "Appius Claudius, our speech before you is
                    attended with more difficulties than we had lately before the senate at Rome;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> for then we had to answer the accusations
                    of the Lacedaemonians, but now we stand accused by yourselves, before whom our
                    cause is to be heard. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But to this disadvantage
                    of situation we submit with this hope, that you will hear us with the temper of
                    a judge, laying aside the character of an advocate, in which you just now
                    appeared. I at least, though the matters of which the Lacedaemonians complained
                    formerly in this place, before Quintus Caecilius, and afterwards at Rome, have
                    been just recapitulated by you, yet shall consider myself as answering for them,
                    not to you, but before you. You charge us with the murder of those men, who
                    being called out by the praetor, Philopœmen, to trial, were put to death.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This I think a charge of such a nature,
                    that it ought not to be advanced against us, either by you, Romans, or by any in
                    your presence. Why so? Because it was written in the treaty with you, that the
                    Lacedaemonians should not intermeddle with the cities on the coast. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> At the time when they, taking up arms, seized by
                    assault in the night those towns with which they had been forbidden to
                    interfere; if Titus Quintius, if a Roman army had been in Peloponnesus, as
                    formerly, the captured and oppressed inhabitants would surely have fled to them
                    for relief. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As you were at a great distance,
                    to whom else would they fly but to us, your allies, whom they had seen at a
                    former time bringing aid to Gythium; whom they had seen in conjunction with you,
                    besieging Lacedaemon on their account? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In
                    your stead, therefore, we undertook a just and rightful war. And <pb n="1832"
                        xml:id="p.1832"/> when other men approve of this step, and even the
                    Lacedaemonians cannot censure it; the gods themselves, also, by giving us the
                    victory, have shown their approbation of it; how then can acts done under the
                    laws of war come under civil disquisition? Of these acts, however, the greatest
                    part nowise affect us. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The summoning to trial
                    men, who had excited the populace to arms, who had stormed and plundered the
                    towns on the coast, who had murdered the principal inhabitants, was our act; but
                    the putting them to death when they were coming into the camp was yours, Areus
                    and Alcibiades, who now, since it is the will of the gods, arraign us, and not
                    ours. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The Lacedaemonian exiles (in the number
                    of whom these two men then were) were then in our camp, and believing that
                        <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> they were the objects of attack because
                    they had chosen the maritime towns for their residence, made an assault on those
                    by whose means they had been banished, and who they perceived with indignation
                    would not suffer them even to grow old in exile with safety. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> Lacedaemonians therefore, not Achaeans, slew
                    Lacedaemonians; nor is it of any consequence to dispute, whether they were slain
                    justly or unjustly. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> But then, Achaeans, the abolition of the laws and ancient discipline of
                        Lycurgus, with the demolition of the walls, are unquestionably your acts:
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> now how can both these charges be
                        brought forward by the same persons, since the walls of Lacedaemon were
                        built, not by Lycurgus, but a few years ago, for the purpose of subverting
                        the discipline of Lycurgus? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tyrants
                        erected them lately as a fortress and defence for themselves, not for the
                        state; and if Lycurgus should rise this day from the dead, he would rejoice
                        at their ruins, and would say that he now acknowledged his country, and
                        ancient Sparta. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> You ought not to have
                        waited for Philopœmen, or the Achaeans; you should have removed and razed,
                        with your own hands, every vestige of tyranny; for these were the foul scars
                        of slavery. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And as during almost eight
                        hundred years, while ye were without walls, ye were free, and for some time
                        even chiefs of Greece; so, after being bound with walls, as with fetters,
                        you were slaves for one hundred years. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As
                        to what concerns the abrogating their laws, I conceive that the tyrants took
                        away the ancient laws of Lacedaemon, and that we did not deprive them of
                        their <pb n="1833" xml:id="p.1833"/> own laws which they did not possess,
                        but gave them ours; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> nor did we neglect the
                        interests of their state, when we made it a member of our council, and
                        incorporated it with ourselves, so that the whole Peloponnesus should form
                        one body and one council. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If we were
                        living under laws different from what we imposed on them, in that case I
                        think they might complain of being treated unfairly, and consequently be
                        displeased. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I know, Appius Claudius, that
                        the kind of discourse which I have hitherto used is not proper either for
                        allies, addressing their allies, or for an independent nation; but, in
                        truth, for slaves pleading before their masters. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> For if the herald's proclamation, in which you ordered
                        the Achaeans, first of all the states of Greece, to be free, was any thing
                        more than empty sound; if the treaty be valid, if the alliance and
                        friendship be maintained on equal terms, why do not I inquire what you
                        Romans did, on the taking of Capua, as well as you demand what we, the
                        Achaeans, did towards the Lacedaemonians, when we conquered them in war?
                        Some persons were killed, suppose, by us. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        What! did not you behead the Campanian senators? We demolished their walls:
                        you not only destroyed the walls, but you took the city and the lands.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But you say, the treaty is on equal
                        terms only in appearance, but, in reality, the Achaeans possess a precarious
                        state of freedom, while the Romans enjoy supreme power. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> I am sensible of it, Appius; and if I ought not, I do
                        not remonstrate; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> but, I beseech you, let
                        the difference between the Romans and Achaeans be as great as it may, not to
                        place people, who are foes to both, on an equal footing with us, your
                        allies, or even on a better. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For, as to
                        setting them on an equality, that we ourselves have done, when we gave them
                        our own laws, when we made them members of the Achaean council. Vanquished,
                        —they are not content with what satisfies their conquerors; foes, —they
                        demand more than allies enjoy. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> What we
                        have ratified by our oaths, what we have consecrated as inviolable to
                        eternal remembrance, by records engraved in stone, they want to abolish, and
                        to load us with perjury. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Romans, for you
                        we have high respect; and, if such is your wish, dread also; but we more
                        respect and dread the the immortal gods. </quote> He was heard with general
                    approbation, and all declared that he had spoken as became the dignity of his
                    office; so that it was easily seen, that the Romans could <pb n="1834"
                        xml:id="p.1834"/> not support their ascendency by acting gently. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> Appius then said, that "he earnestly recommended it
                    to the Achaeans to conciliate friendship, while it was in their power to act
                    voluntarily; lest they might presently do so unwillingly and by compulsion.
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> "These words were heard by all with
                    grief, but inspired them with fear of refusing compliance. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> They only requested the Romans <quote> to make such
                        alterations respecting the Lacedaemonians as they should judge proper, and
                        not ininvolve the Achaeans in the guilt of annulling what they had
                        sanctioned with their oaths. </quote>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Nothing more was done, only the sentence
                    lately passed on Areus and Alcibiades was reversed. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of this year, when the
                    business of assigning the provinces to the consuls and praetors was taken under
                    consideration at Rome, Liguria was decreed <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    to the consuls, because there was no war any where else. As to the praetors,
                    Caius Decimius Flavus obtained, by lot, the city jurisdiction; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Cornelius Cethegus, that between citizens and
                    foreigners; Caius Sempronius Blaesus, Sicily; Quintus Naevius Matho, Sardinia;
                    he had also the charge of making inquisition concerning poisons; Aulus Terentius
                    Varro, Hither Spain; and Publius Sempronius Longus, Farther Spain. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> From the two latter provinces deputies arrived about
                    this time, —Lucius Juvencius Thalna and Titus Quintilius Varus; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> who, having informed the senate how formidable the war was
                    that was finished by them in Spain, requested that, in consideration of such
                    happy success, a thanksgiving should be performed to the immortal gods, and
                    permission granted to the praetors to bring home the armies. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The senate decreed a thanksgiving for two days, and ordered
                    that the question respecting the armies should lie over, and be proposed when
                    they would be deliberating concerning the armies for the consuls and praetors. A
                    few days after this, they voted to the consuls, for Liguria, two legions each,
                    which Appius Claudius and Marcus Sempronius had commanded. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> With regard to the armies in Spain, there was a warm
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> contention between the new praetors and
                    the friends of the absent ones, Calpurnius and Quintius. On each side were
                    plebeian tribunes, and, on each, a consul. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    former threatened, if the senate voted for bringing home the armies, to protest
                    against their decree; the latter, that, if such a protest were made, <pb
                        n="1835" xml:id="p.1835"/> they would not suffer any other business to
                    proceed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At last, the interest of the absent
                    praetors was overpowered, and a decree of the senate passed, that <quote> the
                        praetors should enlist four thousand Roman foot, and four hundred horse;
                        with five thousand foot, and five hundred horse, of the Latin confederates;
                        whom they should carry with them into Spain. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> That, when they should have divided these between the
                        legions, they should discharge whatever number should then be in each
                        legion, above five thousand foot and three hundred horse, dismissing those
                        first who had served out their number of campaigns, afterwards the
                            <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> others according to their bravery
                        displayed under Calpurnius and Quintius. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this dispute was ended, another
                    immediately arose, in consequence of the death of a praetor, Caius Decimius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There stood candidates for his place,
                    Cneius Sicinius and Lucius Pupius, who had been aediles the year before; Caius
                    Valerius, the flamen of Jupiter, and Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, who, though he did
                    not appear in the white gown, because he was curule aedile elect, yet pressed
                    his suit with more warmth than any of them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The contest lay between him and the priest of Jupiter. Fulvius at the beginning
                    seemed to have an equal chance with the flamen, and after- wards surpassed him;
                    on which, some of the plebeian tribunes insisted that no account should be taken
                    of him, because one person could neither hold nor administer two offices,
                    especially curule ones, at the same time; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    while others of them thought it proper that he ought to be exempted from the
                    laws, in order that the people might have the power of electing praetor the
                    person whom they wished. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul, Lucius
                    Porcius, was, from the beginning, inclined to refuse admitting him a candidate;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and afterwards, wishing to have the
                    countenance of the senate in so doing, he called the members together, and told
                    them that <quote> he desired their judgment in the case where a curule aedile
                        elect, without any colour of law, and setting a precedent insufferable in a
                        free state, stood candidate for the praetorship; for his part, unless they
                        determined otherwise, he intended to hold the election according to law. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate voted, that the consul, Lucius
                    Porcius, should recommend to Quintus Fulvius, not to obstruct the elections for
                    substituting a praetor in the room of Caius Decimius from proceeding according
                    to law. When the consul, in pursuance of <pb n="1836" xml:id="p.1836"/> this
                    decree, applied to him on the subject, he answered, that <quote> he would do
                        nothing unworthy of <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> himself, </quote> by
                    which indeterminate answer he left room for people to interpret his intention
                    agreeably to their wish, and that he meant to submit to the direction of the
                    senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But, in the assembly, he urged his
                    pretensions with more eagerness than ever: alleging as a charge, that the
                    kindness of the Roman people was being wrested from him, and an odium excited
                    against him on account of his suing for a second post of honour; as if it were
                    not manifest that, when elected praetor, he must instantly abdicate the
                    aedileship. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consul, seeing the
                    candidate's obstinacy increase, and the public favour incline to him more and
                    more, dissolved the assembly, and summoned a meeting of the senate; where, in a
                    full house, they passed a vote, that <quote> inasmuch as the directions of the
                        senate had produced no effect on Flaccus, the affair concerning him should
                        be laid before the people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A general assembly being summoned, when the
                    consul made a full representation of the matter, Fulvius, not even then swerving
                    from his determination, returned thanks to the Roman people <quote> for the
                        great zeal which they had shown in their desire to make him praetor, as
                        often as opportunity had been given them of declaring their sentiments;
                    </quote> and assured them that <quote> it was his resolution not to disappoint
                        such instances of the attachment of his countrymen. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This determined declaration increased the
                    ardour of people for his cause to such a degree, that he would undoubtedly have
                    been chosen praetor, if the consul had admitted him to stand. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The tribunes maintained a violent altercation, both with
                    their colleagues and with the consul, until, at length, the senate passed a
                    decree, that <quote> whereas the obstinacy of Quintus Flaccus, and the
                        ill-judged party zeal of many among the people, had prevented the assembly
                        for filling the place of a praetor, from being held according to law.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The senate therefore gave their
                        judgment, that the present number of praetors was sufficient, that Publius
                        Cornelius should hold both jurisdictions in the city, and celebrate the
                        games of Apollo. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No sooner was this election stopped by the
                    prudence and firmness of the senate, than another ensued, in which the contest
                    was still greater; since it was concerning a more important subject, and between
                    competitors more numerous and more powerful. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The censorship was the object of contention <pb n="1837" xml:id="p.1837"/> of
                    the following candidates, Lucius Valerius Flaccus, Publius Scipio, Lucius
                    Scipio, Cneius Manlius Vulso, and Lucius Furius Purpureo, patricians; Marcus
                    Porcius Cato, Marcus Fulvius Nobilior, Tiberius Sempronius Longus, Marcus
                    Sempronius Tuditanus, plebeians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But Marcus
                    Porcius far surpassed all of them, both plebeians and patricians of the highest
                    ranks. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So great powers of mind and energy of
                    intellect were in this man, that, no matter how lowly the position in which he
                    was born, he appeared capable of attaining to the highest rank. No one
                    qualification for the management of business, either public or private, was
                    wanting to him. He was equally skilled in affairs relating to town and country.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some have been advanced to the highest
                    honours by their knowledge of the law, others by their eloquence, some by
                    military renown; but this man's genius was so versatile, and so well adapted to
                    all things, that in whatever way engaged, it might be said, that nature formed
                    him for that alone. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In war, he was most
                    courageous, distinguishing himself highly in many remarkable battles; and, when
                    he arrived at the highest posts, was likewise a most consummate commander. Then,
                    in peace, if consulted on a point of law, he was the wisest counsellor; if a
                    cause was to be pleaded, the most eloquent advocate. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was he one of those whose oratory was striking only
                    during their own lives, without leaving after them any monument of it. On the
                    contrary, his eloquence still lives, and will long live, consecrated to memory
                    by writings of every kind. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His orations are
                    many, spoken for himself, for others, and against others; for he harassed his
                    enemies, not only by supporting prosecutions against them, but by maintaining
                    causes in opposition to them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Enmities in
                    abundance gave him plenty of employment, and he never permitted them to lie
                    dormant; nor was it easy to tell whether the nobility laboured harder to keep
                    him down, or he to oppress the nobility. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> His
                    temper, no doubt, was austere, his language bitter and unboundedly free, but his
                    mind was never conquered by his passions, his integrity was inflexible, and he
                    looked with contempt on popularity and riches. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> In spare diet, in enduring toil and danger, his body and mind were like iron;
                    so that even old age, which brings all things to dissolution, did not break his
                    vigour. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In his eighty-sixth year he stood a
                    trial, pleaded his own cause, <pb n="1838" xml:id="p.1838"/> and published his
                    speech; and in his ninetieth year, he brought Servius Galba to trial, before the
                    people. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On this occasion, when he was a candidate for
                    censorship, as in all his previous career, the nobility endeavoured to crush
                    him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> All the candidates, likewise, except
                    Lucius Flaccus, who had been his colleague in the consulship, combined to
                    disappoint him of the office, not merely with a view to their own success, in
                    preference to him, or because they felt indignant at the idea of seeing a man of
                    no family censor, but because from one who had received offence from most of
                    them, and who wished to retaliate, they anticipated a severe censorship, that
                    would endanger the reputations of many. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For,
                    even while soliciting, he uttered frequent menaces, and upbraided them with
                    using their interest against him, because they dreaded an impartial and
                    courageous execution of the duty of censor; at the same time, giving his
                    interest to Lucius Valerius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He said, that
                        <quote> he was the only colleague, in conjunction with whom he could correct
                        modern profligacy, and re-establish the ancient morals. </quote> People were
                    so inflamed by such discourses, that, in spite of the opposition made by the
                    nobility, they not only made Marcus Porcius censor, but gave him for his
                    colleague Lucius Valerius Flaccus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Immediately
                    after the election of censors, the consuls and praetors went abroad to their
                    provinces, except Quintus Naevius, who was detained from going to Sardinia, for
                    no less than four months, by inquisitions concerning poisonings, a great part of
                    which he held out of the city, in the corporate towns and villages; for that
                    method was judged the more eligible. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If we are
                    to credit Valerius Antias, he condemned about two thousand men. Lucius
                    Postumius, the praetor, to whose lot the province of Tarentum had fallen,
                    punished numerous conspiracies of the peasants, and, with great care, finished
                    the remainder of the inquiries concerning the Bacchanalians. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Many of these, who had not appeared on being summoned, or
                    had deserted their bail, were then lurking in that part of Italy; some of them
                    he sentenced to punishment, and others he sent under a guard to the senate at
                    Rome, where they were all committed to prison by Publius Cornelius. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Farther Spain, the Lusitanians being
                    weakened by the late war, matters remained quiet. In Hither Spain, <pb n="1839"
                        xml:id="p.1839"/> Aulus Terentius took the town of Corbia, in Suessetania,
                    by engines and regular works, and sold the prisoners, after which the troops had
                    rest in their winter quarters in that province also. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The former praetors, Caius Calpurnius Piso and Lucius
                    Quintius, came home to Rome; a triumph was voted to both by the senate with
                    great unanimity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Caius Calpurnius triumphed
                    first, over the Lusitanians and Celtiberians. He carried in procession
                    eighty-three golden crowns, and twelve thousand pounds' weight of silver.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In a few days after, Lucius Quintius
                    Crispinus triumphed over the same Lusitanians and Celtiberians, bearing in his
                    triumph the same quantity of gold and silver. The censors, Marcus Porcius and
                    Lucius Valerius, while anxious curiosity was blended with fear, made their
                    survey of the senate; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> they expelled seven from
                    the senate, one of them a man of consular rank, highly distinguished by nobility
                    of birth and honourable employments, —Lucius Quintius Flaminius. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> It is mentioned, as a practice instituted in the
                    memory of our forefathers, that the censors should annex marks of censure to the
                    names of such as they degraded from the senate. There are severe speeches of
                    Cato, against those whom he either expelled the senate, or degraded from the
                    equestrian rank, but by far the most so is that against Lucius Quintius.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Had he spoken, in the character of
                    prosecutor, previous to the censure, and not in that of censor after it, not
                    even his brother Titus, if he were his colleague, could have suffered Quintius
                    to remain in the senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Among other charges,
                    he objected to him, that he had, by hopes of extraordinary presents, prevailed
                    on Philip, a Carthaginian and a catamite, to accompany him into his province of
                    Gaul; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that this youth, in order to enhance the
                    merit of his complaisance to the consul, used frequently, in wanton squabbling,
                    to upbraid him for having quitted Rome just before the show of gladiators.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It happened, that while they were at a
                    feast and heated with wine, a message was brought into the place of
                    entertainment, that a Boian, of high rank, had come as a deserter with his
                    children, and wished to see the consul, that he might, in person, receive his
                    assurance of protection. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He was accordingly
                    introduced into the tent, and began to address him through an interpreter: but
                    while he was speaking, Quintius said to his catamite, <quote>Since you left the
                        show of gladiators, have you a mind to see this Gaul dying?</quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When he had assented, but <pb n="1840"
                        xml:id="p.1840"/> scarcely in earnest, the consul, drawing a sword that hung
                    over his head, first struck the Gaul as he was speaking, and then, when he was
                    running out, and imploring the protection of the Roman people, and of those
                    present, ran him through the side. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias, as he was one who never read
                    Cato's speech, and only gave credit to a tale published without authority, tells
                    the story in another manner, but similar to this in lust and cruelty. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> He writes, that, at Placentia, the consul invited to
                    an entertainment a woman of ill fame, with whom he was desperately enamoured.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There, displaying his importance to this
                    courtesan, he told her, among other matters, with what severity he had conducted
                    the inquisitions, and how many he had then in prison under sentence of death,
                    whom he intended to behead. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then she, being
                    next him on the couch, said, that having never seen an executioner perform his
                    office, she was very desirous of seeing such a thing; on which, the indulgent
                    lover ordered one of those wretches to be dragged to the spot, and there cut off
                    his head. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The deed of death, whether committed
                    as the censor or as Valerius reports it, was barbarous and inhuman; that in the
                    midst of feasting and cups, when it is customary to offer libations to the gods,
                    and to pray for happiness, a human victim should be butchered, and the table
                    stained with his blood, and this for the entertainment of an acknowledged
                    wanton. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the latter part of Cato's speech,
                    he proposes to Quintius, that if he denied this fact, and the others of which he
                    accused him, he should give security to abide a legal trial; but if he confessed
                    them, could he suppose, he asked him, that any one would be sorry for his
                    disgrace; the disgrace of him who, in the midst of a feast, being intoxicated
                    with wine and lust, had sported with the blood of a human being. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the review of the knights, Lucius Scipio
                    Asiaticus was degraded. In fixing the rates of taxation, also, the censor's
                    conduct was harsh and severe to all ranks of men. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> People were ordered to give account upon oath, of women's
                    dress, and ornaments, and carriages exceeding in value fifteen thousand asses;
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 48 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 8
                            <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and it was further ordered, that slaves, younger than twenty years,
                    which, since the last survey, had been sold for ten thousand asses <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 32 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 5 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 10 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> or more, should be estimated at ten times their value; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1841" xml:id="p.1841"/> and that, on all these articles, a tax should be
                    laid of three denariuses <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 11 1/4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> for each thousand asses. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 3
                            <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> The censors took away water which belonged to the public running or
                    carried into any private building or field; and they demolished within thirty
                    days all buildings or sheds, in possession of private persons, that projected
                    into public ground. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They then engaged
                    contractors for executing national works, with the money decreed for that
                    purpose, —for <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> paving cisterns with stone, for
                    cleansing the sewers where it was requisite, and forming new ones on the
                    Aventine, and in other quarters where hitherto there had been none. Then,
                    dividing their tasks, Flaccus built a mole at Nepthunia, on the coast, and made
                    a road through the Formian mountains. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Cato
                    purchased for the use of the people two halls, the Maenian and Titian, in the
                    Lautumiae, and four shops, and built there a court of justice, which was called
                    the Porcian. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They farmed out the several
                    branches of the revenue at the highest prices, and bargained with the
                    contractors for the performance of the public services on the lowest terms.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the senate, overcome by the prayers
                    and lamentations of the publicans, ordered those bargains to be revoked, and new
                    agreements to be made; the censors, by an edict, excluded from competition the
                    persons who had eluded the former contracts, and farmed out all the same
                    branches at prices very little reduced. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This
                    was a remarkable censorship, and the origin of many deadly feuds: it rendered
                    Marcus Porcius, to whom all the harshness was attributed, uneasy during the
                    remainder of his life. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This year, two
                    colonies were established, Potentia in Picenum, and Pisaurum in the Gallic
                    territory. Six acres were given to each settler. The same commissioners had the
                    ordering of both colonies, and the division of the lands, Quintus Fabius Labeo,
                    Marcus Fulvius Flaccus, and Quintus Fulvius Nobilior. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls of that year performed nothing memorable at
                    home or abroad. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They elected to serve as consuls for the
                    ensuing year, Marcus Claudius Marcellus and Quintus Fabius Labeo. These, on the
                    ides of March, the first day of their assuming the administration, proposed to
                    the senate to determine their provinces, and those of the praetors. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The praetors appointed were, Caius Valerius, flamen
                    of Jupiter, who had been candi- <pb n="1842" xml:id="p.1842"/> date the year
                    before, Spurius Posthumius Albinus, Publius Cornelius Sisenna, Lucius Pupius,
                    Lucius Julius, and Cneius Sicinius. Liguria was ordered to be the province of
                    the consuls, and the armies were assigned to them, which Publius Claudius and
                    Marcus Porcius had commanded. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The two Spains,
                    without being put to the lot, were reserved for the Praetors who held them the
                    year before, and also their own armies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    praetors were ordered to regulate their casting lots, in such a manner, that the
                    flamen of Jupiter should have one or other of the judicial employments at Rome.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The foreign jurisdiction fell to his lot,
                    that between citizens to Cornelius Sisenna. Sicily was assigned to Spurius
                    Posthumius, Apulia to Lucius Pupius, Gaul to Lucius Julius, Sardinia to Cneius
                    Sicinius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Lucius Julius was ordered to hasten
                    to his province, because some transalpine Gauls, as was mentioned before, having
                    made their way through the forests into Italy, by an unknown road, were building
                    a town in the country which now forms the district of Aquileia. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Orders were given to the praetor to prevent their doing so,
                    as far as might lie in his power without appealing to arms; and, if it should be
                    necessary to stop them by force, to give information to the consuls, one of whom
                    was, in that case, directed to march his legions against those Gauls. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Towards the close of the preceding year, an assembly
                    had been held for the purpose of electing an augur, in the room of Cneius
                    Cornelius deceased, when Spurius Posthumius Albinus was chosen. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of this year, Publius
                    Licinius Crassus, chief pontiff, died, in whose room was appointed Marcus
                    Sempronius Tuditanus, and Caius Servilius Geminus was raised to the place of
                    chief pontiff. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On occasion of the funeral of
                    Publius Licinius a largess of flesh was distributed to the people, and one
                    hundred and twenty pair of gladiators fought. The funeral games lasted three
                    days; and, after the games, a public feast was given. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> During the feast, and while the couches were spread over
                    the forum, a storm came on with violent gusts of wind, and compelled most of the
                    people to pitch tents in that place. The same, on the weather clearing up, in a
                    short time after, were removed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was
                    rumoured about, that they had fulfilled a prophecy which soothsayers had
                    pronounced, among the decrees of the fates, that, inevitably, tents would be
                    pitched in the forum. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As soon as <pb n="1843"
                        xml:id="p.1843"/> they were relieved from those religious fears, they were
                    struck with new ones, by showers of blood falling for two days, in the area of
                    Vulcan's temple, and a supplication was ordered by the decemvirs for the sake of
                    expiating the prodigy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before the consuls set
                    out for their provinces, they introduced the embassies from the countries beyond
                    the sea to an audience of the senate; and at no time was there in Rome such a
                    number of people from those regions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For, as
                    soon as a report spread through the nations which border on Macedon, that
                    accusations and complaints against Philip were listened to by the Romans with
                    some degree of attention, and that it had been of advantage to many to complain;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> —all these states and nations, and even
                    individuals, on their own accounts, (for he was a troublesome neighbour to every
                    one,) flocked to Rome, with hopes of obtaining either redress of their injuries,
                    or, at least, the consolation of expressing their griefs. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> An embassy came also from king Eumenes, with his brother
                    Athenaeus, to complain of the garrisons not being withdrawn by Philip out of
                    Thrace; and, likewise, of his sending succours into Bithynia, to Prusias, who
                    was at war with Eumenes. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Demetrius, who was then very young, had to
                    answer all these representations; and it was no easy matter to retain in memory,
                    either all the charges which were brought against his father, or what was proper
                    to be said in reply. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For the charges were not
                    only numerous, but most of them exceedingly frivolous; of disputes about
                    boundaries, of men forced away and cattle driven off; of justice, either
                    capriciously administered or refused; of property adjudged either by force or
                    influence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the senate perceived that
                    Demetrius could not explain any of those matters distinctly, and that they could
                    not gain satisfactory information from him, and when, at the same time, the
                    youth, through inexperience and bashfulness, was much embarrassed, they ordered
                    that he should be asked whether he had received from his father any written
                    instructions on those points; and on his answering that he had, it appeared to
                    them better and more proper to receive the answers of the king himself, on each
                    particular head; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> so they immediately called
                    for the scroll, but afterwards gave him leave to read it to them in person.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here were his apologies on each subject,
                    compressed into a narrow compass; informing them that, in some cases, he had <pb
                        n="1844" xml:id="p.1844"/> acted in conformity to the determinations of the
                    ambassadors; in others, that the fault of not conforming to them, lay not in
                    him, but actually in the persons themselves who accused him. He had
                    interspersed, also, complaints concerning the injustice of the decrees, and the
                    partiality with which the discussion was carried on in presence of Caecilius,
                    and of the insults that were offered him, in a most unworthy and unmerited
                    manner, by all. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate inferred from these
                    marks that his mind was irritated; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    nevertheless, on the young man apologizing for some things, and undertaking that
                    others should be performed in the manner most agreeable to the senate, they
                    ordered the answer to be given him, that <quote> in no instance had his father
                        acted with more propriety, or given more pleasure to the senate, than in his
                        choosing, whatever the nature <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> of those
                        transactions might be, to send his excuses for them to the Romans, by his
                        son Demetrius. That the senate could leave unnoticed, forget, and put up
                        with, many past matters, and believe also that they might place confidence
                        in Demetrius; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> for though they restored his
                        person to his father, they still had his mind as a hostage, and were
                        convinced that, as far as he could, without infringing on his duty to his
                        father, he was a friend to the Roman people. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> That, to do him honour, they would send ambassadors
                        into Macedon, in order that, if any thing which ought to have been done was
                        left undone, it might then be effected, but still without requiring an
                        atonement for former omissions. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That they
                        wished Philip also to be sensible, that it was owing to the kind offices of
                        his son Demetrius, that the treaty between him and the Roman people remained
                        inviolate. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These declarations, which were made with the
                    intention of adding to the dignity of his character, proved to the young man the
                    cause of immediate envy, and of not far distant ruin. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Lacedaemonians were next introduced, when many
                    insignificant disputes were agitated. Those which might be deemed important were
                    —whether the persons whom the Achaeans had condemned, should be reinstated or
                    not; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> whether they slew with justice or the
                    reverse those whom they put to death; the question was debated also whether the
                    Lacedaemonians should continue in the Achaeans' council, or, as had formerly
                    been the case, that single state in Peloponnesus should have separate
                    independence. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was determined <pb n="1845"
                        xml:id="p.1845"/> that the condemned should be reinstated, and the sentences
                    passed reversed; that Lacedaemon should continue in the Achaean council, and
                    that this decree should be committed to writing, and signed by the
                    Lacedaemonians and Achaeans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Quintus Marcius
                    was sent ambassador into Macedon, with orders, likewise, to take a view of the
                    affairs of the allies in Peloponnesus; for there also disturbances still
                    subsisted, in consequence of the old quarrels, and Messene had revolted from the
                    Achaean confederacy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But if I were to trace
                    out the cause and progress of this war, I should deviate from the resolution by
                    which I determined not to treat of foreign events, further than they are
                    connected with the affairs of Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One event deserves to be mentioned: that,
                    notwithstanding the Achaeans had a superiority in the war, Philopœmen, their
                    praetor, was taken prisoner on his march to secure Corone, which the enemy meant
                    to attack, being, with a small party of horse, surprised in a dangerous defile.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It is said that he might have effected his
                    own escape, by the aid of some Thracians and Cretans who were with him, but the
                    shame of deserting his horsemen, the most distinguished youths in the nation,
                    selected by himself a short time before, detained him there. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Whilst he is procuring for these an opportunity of getting
                    clear of the narrow defile, by closing the rear in person, and sustaining the
                    assaults of the enemy, his horse fell. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> By the
                    shock of his fall, and the weight of the horse, which fell upon him, he was very
                    nearly killed on the spot; for he was now seventy years old, and his strength
                    had been greatly impaired by a tedious illness, from which he was but just
                    recovered. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Lying thus on the ground, the enemy
                    pouring on, secured him. Out of respect to his character, however, and from
                    regard to his merit, they raised him up, when they recognised him, with as much
                    care as if he had been their own commander, and revived him, and carried him out
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> of that remote valley into the road, and
                    they scarcely believed their own senses, on account of the unexpected joy;
                    however, some of them sent on messages to Messene, that the war was at an end,
                    for they were bringing Philopœmen prisoner. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At
                    first it seemed so incredible, that the messenger was deemed either a liar or a
                    madman. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Afterwards, when numbers came, one
                    after another, all asserting the same, credence was at length given to the
                    matter; and, before they well knew whether he <pb n="1846" xml:id="p.1846"/> was
                    come near the city, all, freemen and slaves, with even women and children,
                    poured out to enjoy the sight; insomuch that the multitude quite closed up the
                    gate, whilst each person seemed unlikely to consider the thing as certain unless
                    he should obtain certain belief by his own eye-sight. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Those who conducted Philopœmen, with difficulty removing
                    those in their way, were able to enter the gate, but the dense crowd completely
                    blocked up the street; and, as the greatest part of these were excluded from the
                    sight, they suddenly <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> filled a theatre which
                    was contiguous to the street, and all with one voice insisted that he should be
                    brought thither for the public view. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    magistrates and leading men, fearing that compassion for so great a man, on
                    seeing him, would cause some disturbance; as many would be moved by respect for
                    his former dignity, when they compared it with his present condition, and many
                    by the recollection of his transcendent merits, placed him where he could be
                    seen at a distance. And quickly after hurried him away out of the sight of the
                    people, who were told by the praetor, Dinocrates, that there were some subjects
                    intimately connected with the decision of the war, on which the magistrates
                    wished to interrogate him. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Having carried him
                    thence to the senate-house, and called the council together, they began a
                    consultation on the measures to be pursued. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The evening came on while they were still at a
                    loss, not only about other matters, but even about the place where he might be
                    kept with proper security during the following night. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They were quite confounded at the greatness of his former
                    fortune and merit; and they neither dared to undertake the guarding of him at
                    their houses, nor thought it safe to trust the custody of him to any individual.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At last some persons reminded them of a
                    public treasury under ground, enclosed with hewn stone; into this place he was
                    put down, in chains, and a huge stone, with which it is generally covered, was
                    placed over it, with the help of a machine. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    After having thus determined to trust to the place, rather than to any man, for
                    his safe keeping, they waited with impatience for the dawn. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On the following day, the whole populace, mindful of his
                    former services to the state, declared their opinion, that they ought to spare
                    him, and to seek through his means some remedies for their present misfortunes.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the authors of the <pb n="1847"
                        xml:id="p.1847"/> revolt, in whose hands was the management of affairs, con-
                    sulting in secret, unanimously resolved to put him to death; but whether they
                    should do it speedily, or defer it, was for some time a matter of doubt.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The party that were more eager for his
                    immediate execution, at length prevailed, and a person was sent to him with
                    poison. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They relate, that on receiving the
                    cup, he only asked if Lycortas, the other commander of the Achaeans, and the
                    horsemen had escaped; and being told that they were safe, he said, <quote>It is
                        well,</quote> and then intrepidly drinking the contents of the cup, expired
                    shortly after. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The actors of this piece of
                    cruelty, however, did not long rejoice at his death; for Messene being conquered
                    in war, delivered up the guilty individuals to the Achaeans, when they
                    positively demanded them. The bones of Philopœmen were restored, and his funeral
                    was attended by the whole Achaean council, every human honour being heaped on
                    him to such a degree, that they did not withhold divine ones. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> So much is conceded to this man by historians, both Greek
                    and Latin, that several of them have recorded, as a circumstance remarkably
                    distinguishing this year, that three illustrious commanders died in it,
                    Philopœmen, Hannibal, and Publius Scipio. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To
                    such an extent have they placed him on an equal footing with the most consummate
                    generals of the two most powerful nations. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Titus Quintius Flamininus came ambassador to
                    king Prusias, who had incurred the jealousy of the Romans, by entertaining
                    Hannibal after the flight of Antiochus, and by making war on Eumenes. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> At the court of Prusias, either because, among other
                    discourse, he reproached him with his giving protection to a person, who, of all
                    men living, was the most inveterate enemy to the Roman nation, who had incited,
                    first his own country, and afterwards, when its power was reduced, king
                    Antiochus, to make war on Rome; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> or because
                    Prusias himself, with the design of gratifying Flamininus and the Roman people,
                    conceived the design of killing Hannibal, or delivering him into their hands;
                    immediately after the first conference with Flamininus, a party of soldiers was
                    sent to guard Hannibal's house. The Carthaginian had always foreseen some such
                    end of his life; for he knew the implacable hatred which the Romans bore him,
                    and placed little confidence in the faith of kings. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Besides, he had ex- <pb n="1848" xml:id="p.1848"/>
                    perienced the fickle temper of Prusias, and had, for some time, dreaded the
                    arrival of Flamininus, as an event fatal to him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Encircled by enemies on every side, in order to have always some path open
                    for flight, he had made seven passages from his house, of which some were
                    concealed, lest they might be invested by a guard. But the imperious government
                    of kings suffers nothing to remain secret which they choose to discover.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They surrounded the circuit of the entire
                    house with guards in such a manner, that no one could escape from it. Hannibal,
                    on being told that some of the king's soldiers were in the porch, endeavoured to
                    escape through a <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> back door, which was the
                    most private, and from which the passage was most secret; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> but, perceiving that to be guarded by a body of soldiers,
                    and every avenue round to be blocked up by the guards that were posted, he
                    called for poison, which he had long kept in readiness to meet such an event,
                    and said, <quote> Let us release the Romans from their long anxiety, since they
                        think it too long to wait for the death of an old man. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Flamininus will gain no very great or memorable victory
                        over one unarmed and betrayed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> What an
                        alteration has taken place in the behaviour of the Roman people, this day
                        affords abundant proof. Their fathers gave warning to Pyrrhus, their armed
                        foe, then heading an army against them in Italy, to beware of poison.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The present generation have sent an
                        ambassador, of consular rank, to persuade Prusias villanously to murder his
                        guest. </quote> Then imprecating curses on the head of Prusias, and on his
                    kingdom, and calling on the gods who presided over hospitality, and were
                    witnesses <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> of his breach of faith, he drank
                    off the contents of the cup. This was the end of the life of Hannibal. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Both Polybius and Rutilius say, that Scipio
                    died in this year; but I do not agree either with them, or Valerius. Not with
                    them, because I find that in the censorship of Marcus Porcius and Lucius
                    Valerius, the censor himself, Lucius Valerius, was chosen prince of the senate,
                    although Africanus had occupied that place for the three preceding lustrums;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and, if he were alive, unless he had been
                    displaced from the senate, which disgrace no one has recorded, another prince
                    would not have been chosen in his room. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    authority of Antias is refuted by the plebeian tribunate of Marcus Naevius,
                    against whom there is extant a speech signed by Publius Africanus. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1849" xml:id="p.1849"/> Now, this Marcus Naevius, in the register of the
                    magistrates, appears to have been plebeian tribune in the consulate of Publius
                    Claudius and Lucius Porcius; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but he entered on
                    the tribuneship in the consulate of Appius Claudius and Marcus Sempronius, on
                    the fourth day before the ides of December, from which time to the ides of
                    March, when Publius Claudius and Lucius Porcius became consuls, there are three
                    months. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thus it appears that he was living in
                    the tribunate of Marcus Naevius, and might have been prosecuted by him; but that
                    he died before the censorship of Lucius Valerius and Marcus Porcius. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The deaths of the three most illustrious men of their
                    respective nations have a similarity, not only in respect to the concurrence of
                    the times, but in this circumstance also, that no one of them met a death
                    suitable to the splendour of his life. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the
                    first place, neither of them died or was buried in his native soil. Hannibal and
                    Philopœmen were taken off by poison; Hannibal breathed his last in exile,
                    betrayed by his host; Philopœmen in captivity, in a prison, and in chains.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio, though neither banished nor
                    condemned, yet under prosecution, and summoned as an absent criminal to a trial,
                    at which he did not appear, passed sentence of voluntary exile, not only on
                    himself while alive, but likewise on his body after death. </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these transactions in Peloponnesus,
                    from which my narration digressed, the return of Demetrius with the ambassadors
                    into Macedonia, affected people's minds in various manners. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The generality of the Macedonians, whom the apprehension of
                    an impending war with the Romans had struck with terror, looked with the highest
                    esteem on Demetrius, as the promoter of peace; and, at the same time, with
                    confident hope, destined for him the throne, after the demise of his father.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They argued, that <quote> although he was
                        younger than Perseus, yet he was born of a wife, and the other of a
                        concubine; that the latter, born of a mother who prostituted her person, had
                        no likeness to any particular father, whereas the former had a striking
                        resemblance of Philip. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Besides it was
                        probable that the Romans would place him on the throne of his father, as
                        Perseus had no pretensions to their favour. </quote> Such was the
                    conversation of people in general. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Fear
                    tortured Perseus, lest his age alone might not sufficiently secure his interest,
                    his brother having the advantage of him in every <pb n="1850" xml:id="p.1850"/>
                    other particular; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> while Philip himself,
                    believing that it would scarcely rest with his decision which of them he should
                    leave heir to his dominions, began to think that his younger son encroached on
                    him more than he could wish. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He was sometimes
                    displeased at the numerous attendance of the Macedonians round Demetrius, and
                    chagrined at perceiving that there was a second court during his own life-time.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The young prince no doubt came home much
                    elevated in his own estimation, elated with the honours paid him by the senate,
                    and their having conceded to him, what they had refused to his father;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> insomuch that every mention of the Romans,
                    whatever degree of respect it procured him from the rest of the Macedonians,
                    created an equal degree of envy, not only in the breast of his brother, but also
                    in that of his father; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> especially after the
                    Roman ambassadors arrived, and the king was obliged to evacuate Thrace, to
                    withdraw his garrisons, and to perform the other articles, either according to
                    the decisions of the former ambassadors or the late regulations made by the
                    senate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But all this he did with great
                    reluctance, and even with anguish of mind, the more on this account, because he
                    saw his son more frequently in company with them than with himself;
                    nevertheless, to avoid giving any pretence for an immediate commencement of
                    hostilities, he acted submissively towards the Romans. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Thinking it necessary to turn away their thoughts from a
                    suspicion of any such designs, he led an army into the heart of Thrace, against
                    the Odrysians, Dantheletians, and Bessians. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    He took the city of Philoppopolis, after it was deserted by the inhabitants, who
                    fled with their families to the tops of the nearest mountains; and, by wasting
                    the country, reduced the barbarians living in the plains to submission.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then leaving a garrison in Philoppopolis,
                    which was soon after expelled by the Odrysians, he began to build a town in
                    Deuriopus. This is a district of Paeonia, near the river Erigonus, which,
                    flowing from Illyricum through Paeonia, falls into the river Axius. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Not far from the old city of Stobae he built his new
                    one, which he ordered to be called Perseis, that this honour might be conferred
                    on his eldest son. </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things passed in Macedonia, the
                    consuls went to their provinces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Marcellus
                    sent forward an express to Lucius Porcius, the proconsul, to lead up the legions
                    to the new town of the Gauls; they surrendered themselves to the <pb n="1851"
                        xml:id="p.1851"/> consul on his arrival. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    There were of these twelve thousand fighting men, most of whom had arms, which
                    they had forced from the inhabitants: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> all
                    which, to their great mortification, were taken from them, as was every thing
                    else which they had either acquired by plundering in the country, or had brought
                    along with them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They sent ambassadors to Rome
                    to complain of those proceedings, who being introduced to an audience of the
                    senate, by the praetor Caius Valerius, represented, that <quote> in consequence
                        of a redundancy of people in Gaul, they had been compelled by the want of
                        land, and indeed of every thing, to cross the Alps in quest of a settlement:
                        that they had settled in those lands which they found waste and uncultivated
                        without doing injury to any. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They had
                        likewise begun to build a town, which was a proof that they did not come to
                        ravage either city or lands. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That some
                        time ago, Marcus Claudius sent them a message, that unless they surrendered
                        to him he would march against them, and that preferring a certain, though
                        not very honourable peace, to the uncertainties of war, they had thrown
                        themselves on the protection of Rome before they submitted to its power.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That in a short time after, being
                        ordered to quit the country, they had intended to remove without murmuring
                        to whatever part of the world they were able; and that, notwithstanding,
                        their arms, and finally all the property which they had brought with them,
                        or driven before them, were taken from them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> They therefore besought the senate and people of Rome not to treat
                        harmless people, who had surrendered themselves, with greater severity than
                        they would enemies. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To this discourse the senate ordered the
                    following answer to be given: That <quote> neither had they acted properly in
                        coming into Italy, and attempting to build a town in the territory of
                        others, without permission from any Roman magistrate commanding in that
                        province; nor did the senate approve of people who had surrendered being
                        stripped of their property. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They would
                        therefore send to the consuls ambassadors, who would order all their effects
                        to be restored, provided they returned to the place whence they came; and
                        who would also proceed to the other side of the Alps, and give warning to
                        the Gallic states to keep their people at home. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> That the Alps, an almost impassable barrier, lay
                        between the two countries, and whoever should pass in future, should meet no
                            <pb n="1852" xml:id="p.1852"/> better fate than those who first proved
                        them to be passable. </quote> The ambassadors sent were Lucius Furius
                    Purpureo, Quintus Minucius, Publius Manlius Acidinus. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The Gauls, on the restoration of such property as they were
                    in possession of, without wronging any man, withdrew out of Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The transalpine states answered the Roman
                    ambassadors in terms of kindness. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Their elders
                    even found fault with the excessive lenity of the Roman people, in <quote>
                        suffering men to depart with impunity, who, without an order of their
                        nation, left their home, attempted to seize on lands belonging to the Roman
                        empire, and to build a town in a territory which belonged to others.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They ought, </quote> they said,
                        <quote> to have paid a heavy penalty for their inconsiderate conduct; and as
                        to the restoration of their effects, they expressed a fear, lest, in
                        consequence of this too great forbearance, others might be encouraged to
                        attempts of a like nature. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They not only entertained the ambassadors, but
                    conferred considerable presents on them. The consul, Marcus Claudius, when he
                    had sent the Gauls out of his province, began to prepare for a war with the
                    Istrians, and wrote to the senate for permission to lead the legions into their
                    country. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That measure pleased the senate. They
                    formed an intention of establishing a colony at Aquileia; nor were they able to
                    decide whether it should consist of Latins or Roman citizens; at last however
                    they passed a vote in favour of a Latin settlement. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The commissioners appointed for the purpose were, Publius
                    Scipio Nasica, Caius Flaminius, and Lucius Manlius Acidinus. In the same year,
                    colonies of Roman citizens were led out to Mutina and Parma. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Two thousand men were settled in each colony, on lands
                    which lately belonged to the Boians, and formerly to the Tuscans; they received
                    at Parma eight acres, at Mutina five each. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    These colonists were conducted by Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, Titus Aebutius Carus,
                    and Lucius Quintius Crispinus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The colony of
                    Saturnia, also consisting of Roman citizens, was settled on the lands of
                    Caletra, by Quintus Fabius Labeo, Caius Afranius Stellio, and Tiberius
                    Sempronius Gracchus. Ten acres were assigned to each man. </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year Aulus Terentius Varro, the
                    proprietor, fought some successful battles with the Celtiberians, not far from
                    the river Iberus, in the territory of Auseta, reducing several towns, which they
                    had fortified in that quarter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The <pb
                        n="1853" xml:id="p.1853"/> Farther Spain was quiet during the whole year,
                    because Publius Sempronius, the propraetor, was seized with a lingering
                    disorder, and the Lusitanians, when no one attacked them, very opportunely kept
                    quiet. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In Liguria nothing extraordinary was
                    performed by Quintus Fabius, the consul. Marcus Marcellus being recalled out of
                    Istria to attend the elections, disbanded his army, and came home to Rome.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He elected Cneius Baebius Tamphilus and
                    Lucius Aemilius Paulus consuls. This latter had been curule aedile, along with
                    Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, from the time of whose consulate this was the fifth
                    year; and this very Lepidus had been made consul after two repulses. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Then Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, Marcus Valerius
                    Laevinus, Publius Manlius a second time, Marcus Ogulnius Gallus, Lucius
                    Caecilius Denter, and Caius Terentius Istra, were elected praetors. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Towards the close of the year, a supplication was
                    performed on occasion of prodigies, for people were persuaded that it had rained
                    blood for two days in the court of the temple of Concord; and an account was
                    received, that near the coast of Sicily a new island, which had never been there
                    before, rose out of the sea. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Valerius, of
                    Antium, asserts that Hannibal died in this year, and that besides Titus Quintius
                    Flamininus, whose name was celebrated in this business, Lucius Scipio Asiaticus,
                    and Publius Scipio Nasica, were sent ambassadors to Prusias on that occasion.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
