<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 39</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="book">
                <head>The Bacchanalia in Rome and Italy</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these incidents were occurring in
                        Rome-if indeed they did occur in this year-both consuls were engaged in war
                        with the Ligurians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That enemy seemed born
                        to keep up the military discipline of the Romans in the intervals between
                        the more important wars; no other field of operations did more to whet the
                        soldiers' courage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In Asia the pleasures
                        of city life, the ample supply of luxuries furnished by land and sea, the
                        effeminacy of the enemy, and the princely wealth had enriched the armies
                        instead of making them more efficient. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Especially under the command of Manlius they became careless and
                        undisciplined, and so the somewhat rougher march through Thrace and a more
                        warlike enemy gave them a much-needed lesson through severe defeat.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In Liguria there was everything to try
                        a soldier's mettle; a rough and difficult country, mountainous heights which
                        it cost the men as much labour to secure for themselves as it did to
                        dislodge the enemy from them; steep narrow roads where there was always the
                        danger of an ambush; an enemy lightly armed, rapid in his movements, sudden
                        in his onset, who never allowed any place or hour to remain quiet and
                        undisturbed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Any attack on a fortified
                        position involved much toil and danger; there was but little to be got out
                        of the country, and the soldiers were reduced to scanty food, as they could
                        secure very little plunder. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Consequently,
                        there were no camp-followers, no extended line of baggage animals; there was
                        nothing beyond the arms and the men who depended solely upon them.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Occasions of fighting were never
                        lacking, for the natives driven by their poverty were in the habit of
                        raiding their neighbours' fields; they never, however, engaged in a pitched
                        battle. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul C. Flaminius, after several
                        successful actions with the Ligurian Freniates, accepted their surrender and
                        disarmed them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As they evaded this demand,
                        he took severe measures with them, on which they abandoned their villages
                        and took refuge on Mt. Auginus, the consul following in close pursuit.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In scattered parties, mostly without
                        arms, they fled precipitately over trackless and rocky ground, where their
                        enemy could not follow them, and in this way escaped across the Apennines.
                        Those who had held to their camp were surrounded and driven out. The legions
                        were then led across the Apennines. The Gauls were protected for a short
                        time by the mountain height which they had occupied, but they soon made
                        their surrender. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This time there was a
                        closer search made for arms and they were all secured. From them the war was
                        transferred to the Apuani, whose continual incursions into the territories
                        of Pisa and Bononia made any cultivation of the soil impossible. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The consul thoroughly vanquished these also and
                        so brought peace to their neighbours. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now
                        that the province was brought from a state of war into one of peace and
                        quiet, he determined that his soldiers should not be kept in idleness, so he
                        employed them in constructing a road from Bononia to Arretium. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The other consul, M. Aemilius, destroyed and
                        burnt the farms and villages of the Ligurians who dwelt in the lowland
                        country the inhabitants having previously fled and taken possession of the
                        heights of Ballista and Suismontium. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                        then attacked them on the mountains, harassing them with skirmishes, and at
                        last forcing them into a regular engagement, in which he completely defeated
                        them. During the battle he vowed a temple to Diana. As all the tribes south
                        of the Apennines were now subjugated, Aemilius advanced against those on the
                        other side of the range, including those of the Freniates with whom C.
                        Flaminius had not been in touch. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                        reduced them all to submission, deprived them of their arms and brought down
                        the whole population from the mountains into the plains. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> After establishing peace in Liguria he led his army
                        into Gaul and made a road from Placentia to Ariminum to join the Via
                        Flaminia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In the last pitched battle he
                        fought in Liguria he vowed a temple to Queen Juno. These were the events of
                        the year in Liguria. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Gaul all was peaceful, but the praetor
                        M. Furius, anxious to make it appear as though he were engaged in war,
                        deprived the unoffending Cenomani of their arms. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> They sent to Rome to complain and were referred by the
                        senate to Aemilius, who was empowered to investigate the case. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> There was a long and heated debate with the
                        praetor, but they maintained their ground throughout, and Furius was ordered
                        to restore their arms and leave his province. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The senate then gave audience to the deputations who
                        had come from all the cities and colonies of the Latin allies. Their
                        grievance was that a large number of their citizens had migrated to Rome and
                        were placed on the census there. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Q.
                        Terentius Culleo, one of the praetors, was charged with the task of finding
                        them out, and whoever was proved to have been registered at home during the
                        censorship of C. Claudius and M. Livius or their successors, he was to order
                        his return to the city in which he had been registered; 12,000 Latins
                        returned in consequence to their homes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Even then the City was overcrowded by the multitude of immigrants. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the consuls returned to Rome M.
                        Fulvius came back from Aetolia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had an
                        audience of the senate in the temple of Apollo and gave a detailed report of
                        his operations in Aetolia and Cephallenia. He then asked the senate to pass
                        a resolution that it was right and proper, in consideration of the success
                        and good fortune with which he had served the State, that honours should be
                        paid to the immortal gods and that a triumph should be decreed to him.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> M. Albutius, one of the tribunes of
                        the plebs, declared his intention of vetoing any decree which should be
                        passed before the arrival of M. Aemilius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The consul had wished to speak against it, and on his departure for his
                        province had charged him, the tribune, to reserve all discussion of the
                        question till his return. Fulvius, he argued, would lose nothing by the
                        delay; even when the consul was present, the senate would decree what it
                        wished. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To this Fulvius replied: "Even if
                        Aemilius' hostility to him and the arbitrary and dictatorial temper he
                        showed towards his opponents were not a matter of common knowledge, still it
                        would be intolerable that an absent consul should stand in the way of honour
                        being paid to the immortal gods and should <milestone n="6??" unit="section"
                        /> delay a triumph which was well earned and justly due, or that a general
                        who had achieved brilliant success should be standing before the gate of the
                        City with his <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> victorious army and the
                        spoils of war and the prisoners until the consul, who was for this very
                        purpose delaying his movements, should please to return to Rome. But as a
                        matter of fact his differences with the consul were notorious. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> What fair dealing could any one look for from the
                        man who in a thinly attended and secret meeting of the senate got a
                        resolution carried and deposited in the treasury in the temple of Saturn
                        stating that there was no evidence that Ambracia had been carried by
                        assault. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Why, that city was besieged by
                        agger and vineae, and when the siege-works were burnt, new ones were
                        constructed; for fifteen days fighting went on there round the walls above
                        ground and below, and even when the soldiers had surmounted the walls, there
                        was a long and doubtful struggle from early dawn till nightfall; more than
                        3000 of the enemy were slain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> What was
                        that malicious story which he told the pontiffs about the spoliation of the
                        temples of the gods in the captured city? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Unless, indeed, we are to suppose that whilst the adornments of Syracuse and
                        other captured cities may decorate the City, this right of war does not hold
                        in the solitary case of Ambracia." <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He
                        implored the senators and begged the tribune not to make him an object of
                        derision to his insolent enemy. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                        senators were with him to a man; some tried to persuade the tribune to forgo
                        his veto, others assailed him with bitter reproaches. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But it was the speech of his colleague,
                        Tiberius Gracchus, that produced the greatest effect. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He said that for a man to use his official position as
                        the instrument of his own personal animosities was in any case setting a bad
                        precedent, but for a tribune of the plebs to become the agent of another
                        man's vindictiveness was a disgraceful proceeding quite unworthy of the
                        power and inviolability of the college of tribunes. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Each man ought to judge for himself whom to love and
                        whom to hate, what actions to approve of and what to disapprove of; he must
                        not wait upon another man's look or nod, nor must he be driven hither and
                        thither by the motives which sway another man's mind. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> A tribune who becomes the tool of an angry consul and
                        is careful to remember what M. Aemilius entrusted to him privately, forgets
                        that the tribuneship was entrusted to him publicly by the people of Rome,
                        and entrusted to him for the protection and liberty of private citizens, not
                        for the defence of an autocratic consul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Albutius does not see that it will go down to posterity that of two members
                        of the same college of tribunes one subordinated his private quarrels to the
                        interests of the State, the other took <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        up a quarrel which was not even a private one, but was entrusted to him by
                        some one else. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Smarting under this
                        castigation the tribune left the senate-house, and on the proposal of Ser.
                        Sulpicius a triumph was decreed to M. Fulvius. He thanked the senators and
                        went on to tell them that on the day he took Ambracia he had vowed to
                        exhibit the Great Games in honour of Jupiter Optimus Maximus, and that a
                        hundred pounds of gold had been contributed by the cities for this purpose.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Out of the money which he was going to
                        place in the treasury after it had been borne in the triumph, he requested
                        the senate to order that this hundred pounds <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> of gold should be set apart. The senate ordered the
                        question to <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> be referred to the college
                        of pontiffs whether it was necessary that all that gold should be spent on
                        the Games. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They replied that no question
                        of religion arose as to what amount should be spent on the Games, and the
                        senate consequently allowed Fulvius to spend what he liked on the Games as
                        long as it did not exceed 80,000 sesterces. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Fulvius had fixed the date of his triumph
                        in January but, on learning that M. Aemilius had received a letter from
                        Albutius stating that he had withdrawn his opposition and had himself at
                        once started for Rome to stop the triumph, but was detained on his journey
                        by sickness, he fixed an <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> earlier date,
                        for he was afraid there might be more serious conflicts over the triumph
                        than during the war. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> It was on December
                        23 that he celebrated his triumph over the Aetolians and the Cephallenians.
                        Before his chariot were carried golden crowns weighing in all 112 pounds,
                        1083 pounds of silver, 243 pounds of gold, 118,000 Attic tetrachmas and
                        12,422 "philippei"; 780 brazen statues and 230 marble statues. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> There was a large quantity of armour, weapons
                        and all other spoil taken from the enemy, as well as catapults, ballistae,
                        and every kind of artillery. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The generals
                        led in the procession-Aetolian, Caphallenian and those of Antiochus left
                        behind in Aetolia-numbered seven and twenty. Before he actually entered the
                        City, Fulvius bestowed rewards on many of the military tribunes, prefects,
                        cavalrymen and centurions, both those in the Roman army and in the allied
                        contingents. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Out of the booty he gave to
                        each private soldier 25 denarii, double the amount to each centurion, and
                        three times as much to each cavalryman. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The time for the consular elections was
                        now at hand, and as M. Aemilius, to whom the task of conducting them had
                        been assigned, was unable to undertake it, C. Flaminius went to Rome for the
                        purpose. The consuls elected were Spurius Postumius Albinus and Q. Marcius
                        Philippus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The new praetors were T.
                        Maenius, P. Cornelius Sulla, C. Calpurnius Piso, M. Licinius Lucullus, C.
                        Aurelius Scaurus and L. Quinctius Crispinus. At the close of the year, after
                        the new magistrates had been appointed, Cneius Manlius Vulso celebrated his
                        triumph over the Asiatic Gauls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The reason
                        why he deferred his triumph to so late a date was his anxiety to avoid a
                        prosecution under <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the Petillian Law
                        whilst Q. Terentius Culleo was praetor, and the possibility of being caught
                        by the flames of the verdict which condemned Scipio. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He thought the judges would be even more hostile to him
                        than they had been to Scipio owing to reports which had reached Rome of his
                        allowing the soldiers every kind of licence and completely destroying the
                        discipline which his predecessor Scipio had maintained. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Nor were the stories of what had gone on in his
                        province far away from men's eyes the only things that discredited him.
                        Still worse things were witnessed amongst his soldiers every day' for it was
                        through the army serving in Asia that the beginnings of foreign luxury were
                        introduced into the City. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These men
                        brought into Rome for the first time, bronze couches, costly coverlets,
                        tapestry, and other fabrics, and-what was at that time considered gorgeous
                        furniture-pedestal tables and silver salvers. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Banquets were made more attractive by the presence of
                        girls who played on the harp and sang and danced, and by other forms of
                        amusement, and the banquets themselves began to be prepared with greater
                        care and expense. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The cook whom the
                        ancients regarded and treated as the lowest menial was rising in value, and
                        what had been a servile office came to be looked upon as a fine art. Still
                        what met the eye in those days was hardly the germ of the luxury that was
                        coming. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In his triumph Cn. Manlius had borne
                        before him 200 golden crowns, each weighing 12 pounds, 220,000 pounds weight
                        of silver, 2103 pounds of gold, 127,000 Attic tetrachmas, 250 cistophori,
                        16,320 golden coins of Philip's mintage, and a large quantity of arms and
                        spoils taken from the Gauls, which were carried in wagons. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Fifty-two of the enemy leaders were marched before his
                        chariot. He distributed amongst the soldiers 42 denarii for each legionary,
                        twice as much for the centurions, and three times as much for the cavalry,
                        and double pay for all. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Many of those who
                        followed his chariot had received military rewards, and it was clear from
                        the songs which the soldiers sang that they addressed him as an indulgent
                        general who sought their goodwill, and that it was his popularity with the
                        soldiers rather than with the people that lent lustre to his triumph.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the friends of Manlius succeeded
                        in winning the favour of the people also; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        by their efforts a resolution was passed in the senate ordering that so much
                        of the soldiers' stipends contributed by the people as had not yet been paid
                        should be paid out of the money borne in the triumphal procession. The
                        quaestors, making a true and just valuation, paid back 25 1/2 for every 1000
                        ases. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Just at this time two military
                        tribunes arrived with despatches from C. Atinius and L. Manlius, who were
                        commanding in Hither and Further Spain. It appeared that the Celtiberi and
                        Lusitanians were in arms and were ravaging the lands of the friendly tribes.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate left the new magistrates to
                        deal with the situation. Whilst the Roman Games were being celebrated this
                        year by P. Cornelius Cethegus and A. Postumius Albinus, a pole insecurely
                        fixed on the race-course fell on the statue of Pollentia and threw it down.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This was regarded as an omen, and the
                        senate decided that the Games should be celebrated for one day longer,
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> and that two statues should be
                        erected in place of the one that had fallen, one of them to be gilded.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Plebeian Games were exhibited for
                        one day by the aediles C. Sempronius Blaesus and M. Furius Luscus. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the following year the consuls Sp.
                        Postumius Albinus and Q. Marcius Philippus had their attention diverted from
                        the army and the wars, and the administration of provinces, by the necessity
                        of putting down a domestic conspiracy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        provinces were allotted to the praetors as follows: the civic jurisdiction
                        to T. Maenius, the alien to M. Licinius Lucullus, Sardinia to C. Aurelius
                        Scaurus, Sicily to P. Cornelius Sulla, Hither Spain to L. Q. Crispinus, and
                        Further Spain to C. Calpurnius Piso. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both
                        the consuls were charged with the investigation into the secret
                        conspiracies. A low-born Greek went into Etruria first of all, but did not
                        bring with him any of the numerous arts which that most accomplished of all
                        nations has introduced amongst us for the cultivation of mind and body.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He was a hedge-priest and wizard, not
                        one of those who imbue men's minds with error by professing to teach their
                        superstitions openly for money, but a hierophant of secret nocturnal
                        mysteries. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At first these were divulged to
                        only a few; then they began to spread amongst both men and women, and the
                        attractions of wine and feasting increased the number of his followers.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they were heated with wine and
                        the nightly commingling of men and women, those of tender age with their
                        seniors, had extinguished all sense of modesty, debaucheries of every kind
                        commenced; each had pleasures at hand to satisfy the lust he was most prone
                        to. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor was the mischief confined to the
                        promiscuous intercourse of men and women; false witness, the forging of
                        seals and testaments, and false informations, all proceeded from the same
                        source, as also poisonings and murders of families where the bodies could
                        not even be found for burial. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Many crimes
                        were committed by treachery; most by violence, which was kept secret,
                        because the cries of those who were being violated or murdered could not be
                        heard owing to the noise of drums and cymbals. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This pestilential evil penetrated from
                        Etruria to Rome like a contagious disease. At first, the size and extent of
                        the City allowing more scope and impunity for such mischiefs, served to
                        conceal them, but information at length reached the consul, mainly through
                        the following channel. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> P. Aebutius, whose
                        father had served in the cavalry and was dead, had been left under
                        guardians. On their death he had been brought up under the care of his
                        mother Duronia and his stepfather T. Sempronius Rutilus. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The mother was completely in her husband's hands; and
                        as the stepfather had so exercised his guardianship that he was not in a
                        position to give a proper account for it, he was anxious that his ward
                        should either be put out of the way or placed at his mercy through his
                        getting some hold upon him. One way of corrupting the youth's morals was
                        through the Bacchanalia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The mother told
                        the youth that she had made a vow on his behalf during an illness, namely,
                        that as soon as he recovered she would initiate him into the Bacchic
                        mysteries, and in that way would through the kindness of the gods discharge
                        the vow by which she was bound. He must preserve his chastity for ten days,
                        then after supper on the tenth day she would take him to a place set apart
                        for the rite of initiation. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was a freedwoman named Hispala
                        Fecenia who, though she was a courtesan, was worthy of better things than
                        the gains to which she had been accustomed from her girlhood, and by which
                        she supported herself even after she had been manumitted. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As their houses were near one another, an intimacy had
                        sprung up between her and Aebutius, which was in no way injurious to either
                        his reputation or his purse. She sought his company and his love
                        unsolicited, and as his parents kept him close in every way, he was
                        maintained by the girl's generosity. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Her
                        passion for him had gone so far that after her guardian had died, and she
                        was no longer a ward, she begged the tribunes and the praetor to appoint a
                        guardian for her. Then she could make a will and she constituted Aebutius
                        her sole heir. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With these proofs of her love they had no
                        secrets from each other, and the youth told her in a jocular tone not to be
                        surprised if he absented himself from her for some nights; he had a
                        religious duty to perform, the discharge of a vow made while he was ill, and
                        he intended therefore to be initiated into the Bacchic mysteries. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> On hearing this she was terribly upset and
                        exclaimed, "Heaven forbid. Better for us both to die than that you should do
                        this," and then invoked deadly curses on the heads of those who had advised
                        him to take this course. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The youth,
                        astonished at her outburst and excitement, bade her spare her curses; it was
                        his mother who had given him this command with the consent of his
                        stepfather. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "Your stepfather, then," she
                        replied, "for, perhaps, it is not right to charge your mother with it, is by
                        this act hurrying on the ruin of your modesty, your reputation, your hopes
                        and your life." Still more astonished, he asked her what she meant.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With a prayer to the gods and
                        goddesses to forgive her if, constrained by her affection, she disclosed
                        what she ought to be silent about, she explained that when she was in
                        service she had accompanied her mistress into that place of initiation, but
                        had never gone near it when once she was free. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> She knew it to be a sink of every form of corruption,
                        and it was a matter of common knowledge that no one had been initiated for
                        the last two years above the age of twenty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> As each person was brought in, he was handed over to the priests like a
                        victim and taken into a place which resounded with yells and songs, and the
                        jangling of cymbals and drums, so that no cry from those who were suffering
                        violation could be heard. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> She then begged
                        and implored him to get out of the affair in whatever way he could, and not
                        to rush blindly into a place where he would first have to endure, and then
                        to commit, every conceivable outrage. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Until he had given his word to keep clear of these rites she would not let
                        him go. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After he reached home his mother brought
                        up the subject of the initiation and told him what he had to do in
                        connection with it on that day, and what on the following days. He informed
                        her that he would do nothing of the kind; he had no intention of being
                        initiated. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His stepfather was present. The
                        mother at once exclaimed, "He cannot pass ten nights away from Hispala's
                        embraces; he is so intoxicated with the fascinations of that venomous
                        serpent, that he has no respect for either his parent or his stepfather or
                        the gods." Amid the objurgations of his mother on the one side and his
                        stepfather on the other, he was finally, with the assistance of four slaves,
                        driven out of the house. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The youth betook
                        himself to his aunt Aebutia, and explained why he had been expelled from his
                        home, and at her suggestion laid the matter privately before the consul the
                        following day. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Postumius told him to come
                        again in three days' time, and in the meantime inquired of Sulpicia, his
                        mother-in-law, a grave and judicious woman, whether she knew an old woman
                        called Aebutia living in the Aventine quarter. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> She replied that she knew her to be a woman of
                        respectable and strictly moral character; on which the consul said that it
                        was important that he should have an interview with her, and Sulpicia must
                        send for her to see her. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Aebutia came to
                        Sulpicia, and the consul coming in as though by accident turned the
                        conversation on to her brother's son. The woman burst into tears and began
                        to lament the youth's misfortunes, robbed as he had been of his fortune by
                        those who ought to have been the very last to do so. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He was, she said, at her house at the time, "he had
                        been driven away by his mother because the honest and respectable youth
                        refused-may the gods forgive me-to be initiated into what were commonly
                        believed to be impure and obscene mysteries." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the consul considered that he had
                        ascertained all that was necessary about Aebutius, and that the evidence was
                        trustworthy, he dismissed Aebutia and asked his mother-in-law to send for
                        Hispala, a freedwoman, who was well known round the Aventine, as there were
                        some questions he wished to put to her. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Hispala was alarmed at the message, and at being summoned into the presence
                        of a woman of such high rank and character, without knowing the reason, and
                        when she saw the lictors and the consul's attendants in the vestibule, she
                        nearly fainted. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> She was conducted into an
                        inner apartment where the consul and his mother-in-law were present, and the
                        consul told her that there was nothing to be afraid of if she could make up
                        her mind to speak the truth; she might trust the pledged word of such a
                        woman as Sulpicia and his own promise of safety, but she must give him a
                        description of what <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> usually went on at
                        the nocturnal Bacchic rites in the grove of Simila. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> On hearing this, the woman was seized with such a
                        fright and a trembling in all her limbs that she could not open her lips.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At last she recovered her nerves, and
                        said that when quite a girl she had been initiated, together with her
                        mistress, but since she had been manumitted, now some years ago, she knew
                        nothing of what went on there. The consul commended her for having confessed
                        that she had been initiated and begged her to be equally truthful in the
                        rest of her story. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> She avowed that she
                        knew nothing further, on which the consul warned her that she <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> would not receive the same consideration and
                        forbearance if she were confuted by some one else, as she would if she made
                        a free confession, for the person who had heard these things from her had
                        disclosed everything to him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The woman being convinced, and quite
                        rightly, that Aebutius was the informer, flung herself at Sulpicia's feet
                        and implored her not to let a conversation between a freedwoman and her
                        lover be treated so seriously as to amount to treason. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> What she had told him was for the purpose of
                        frightening, not because she really knew anything. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Postumius was very angry, and told her that she must be
                        imagining that she was joking with her lover, and not speaking in the house
                        of a grave and august lady and in the presence of the consul. Sulpicia
                        raised the terrified woman from the floor, spoke soothingly to her and tried
                        to quiet her. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At length she became calm,
                        and after bitterly reproaching Aebutius for the return he had made after all
                        she had done for him, and declared that while she stood in great fear of the
                        gods, whose occult mysteries <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> she was
                        revealing, she stood in much greater fear of men who would tear her to
                        pieces if she turned informer. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So she
                        begged Sulpicia and the consul to remove her to some place outside the
                        borders of Italy where she could pass the rest of her days in safety. The
                        consul bade her be under no apprehension; he would see to it that she found
                        a safe home in Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then Hispala gave an
                        account of the origin of these rites. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At first they were confined to women; no
                        male was admitted, and they had three stated days in the year on which
                        persons were initiated during the daytime, and matrons were chosen to act as
                        priestesses. Paculla Annia, a Campanian, when she was priestess, made a
                        complete change, as though by divine monition, for she was the first to
                        admit men, and she initiated her own sons, Minius Cerinnius and Herennius
                        Cerinnius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At the same time she made the
                        rite a nocturnal one, and instead of three days in the year celebrated it
                        five times a month. When once the mysteries had assumed this promiscuous
                        character, and men were mingled with women with all the licence of nocturnal
                        orgies, there was no crime, no deed of shame, wanting. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> More uncleanness was wrought by men with men than with
                        women. Whoever would not submit to defilement, or shrank from violating
                        others, was sacrificed as a victim. To regard nothing as impious or criminal
                        was the very sum of their religion. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                        men, as though seized with madness and with frenzied distortions of their
                        bodies, shrieked out prophecies; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> the
                        matrons, dressed as Bacchae, their hair dishevelled, rushed down to the
                        Tiber with burning torches, plunged them into the water, and drew them out
                        again, the flame undiminished, as they were made of sulphur mixed with lime.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Men were fastened to a machine and
                        hurried off to hidden caves, and they were said to have been rapt away by
                        the gods; these were the men who refused to join their conspiracy or take a
                        part in their crimes or submit to pollution. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> They formed an immense multitude, almost equal to the
                        population of Rome; amongst them were members of noble families both men and
                        women. It had been made a rule for the last two years that no one more than
                        twenty years old should be initiated; they captured those to be deceived and
                        polluted. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When she had finished giving her evidence,
                        she fell on her knees and again begged the consul to send her abroad.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He asked his mother-in-law to set
                        apart some portion of her house where she could take up her abode. An upper
                        room was assigned to her which was approached by a flight of steps from the
                        street; these were blocked up and an entrance made from inside the house.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All Fecenia's effects were at once
                        transferred, and her household slaves brought in, and Aebutius was ordered
                        to take up his quarters with a client of the consul's. As both his
                        informants were now in his hands, Postumius reported the affair to the
                        senate. Everything was explained as it occurred, the information which he
                        had first received, and then that which he had obtained in answer to his
                        questions. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate were greatly alarmed
                        for the public safety; these secret conspiracies and nocturnal gatherings
                        were a danger to the State; and they were alarmed for themselves, lest their
                        own relations and friends might be involved. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> They passed a vote of thanks to the consul for having conducted his
                        investigations so carefully and without creating any public disturbance.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then, arming the consuls with
                        extraordinary powers, they placed in their hands the inquiry into the
                        proceedings at the Bacchanalia and the nocturnal rites. They were to take
                        care that Aebutius and Fecenia suffered no injury for the information they
                        had given, and they were to offer rewards to induce other informers to come
                        forward. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Those who presided over these
                        mysteries were to be sought out not only in Rome, but everywhere where
                        people were in the habit of assembling, so that they might be delivered up
                        to the consuls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Edicts were published in
                        Rome and throughout Italy forbidding any who had been initiated from meeting
                        together to celebrate their mysteries or performing any rites of a similar
                        character, and above all, strict inquiry was to be made in the case of those
                        who attended gatherings in which crime and debauchery had occurred. These
                        were the measures which the senate decreed. The consuls sent orders to the
                        curule aediles to search out all the priests of those rites and, when they
                        were arrested, to keep them in such custody as they thought best until their
                        trial. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The plebeian aediles were to see
                        that no rites were performed in open day; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        the police commissioners were instructed to post watches throughout the City
                        and take care that no nocturnal gatherings took place; and as a precaution
                        against fires, five men were appointed to assist the commissioners and take
                        charge of the buildings assigned to them on this side the Tiber. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the various officials had been told
                        off to their duties, the consuls convened the Assembly and mounted the
                        Rostra. After the usual prayers with which proceedings are opened before the
                        magistrates address the people, the consul began thus: "In no meeting of the
                        Assembly has this solemn appeal to the gods been so appropriate and, I would
                        add, so necessary. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For it reminds you that
                        it is these gods whom your ancestors ordained that we should worship,
                        reverence, and pray to; not those who have driven the minds of people
                        enslaved by foul and foreign superstitions, as though by goading furies,
                        into every form of crime and every kind of lust. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> I am at a loss to know how far I ought to keep silence,
                        and how far I ought to go, in what I have to say. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> I fear, if you remain in ignorance of anything, that I
                        may leave an opening for neglect, whilst, if I disclose everything, I may
                        create too much alarm. Whatever I say, you may be certain that it does not
                        come up to the enormity and horror of the thing. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> We shall make it our business to say enough to put you
                        on your guard. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the Bacchanalia have
                        for some time been going on throughout Italy and are now practiced in many
                        parts of the City you have, I am sure, learnt not only by report, but also
                        by the nightly noises and yells which resound all over the City; but I do
                        not think you know what it all means. Some of you fancy that it is a
                        particular form of worship; others think that it is some permissible kind of
                        sport and dalliance; its real nature is understood by few. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> As to their numbers, you would inevitably be very much
                        alarmed if I were to say that there are many thousands of them, unless I
                        went on to explain who and what sort of people they are. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "In the first place, then, women form the
                        great majority, and this was the source of all the mischief. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Then there are the males, the very counterparts
                        of the women, committing and submitting to the foulest uncleanness, frantic
                        and frenzied, driven out of their senses by sleepless nights, by wine, by
                        nocturnal shouting and uproar. The conspiracy does not so far possess any
                        strength, but its numbers are rapidly increasing day by day, and its
                        strength is growing. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Your ancestors would
                        not have even your Assembly meet in an irregular and haphazard way, but only
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> when the standard was hoisted on
                        the citadel and the centuries in their array marched out, or when the
                        tribunes had given notice of a meeting of the plebs, or the Assembly had
                        been duly convened by one of the magistrates. Whenever the people met
                        together there was bound to be a lawful authority to preside over it. Have
                        you any idea what these nocturnal gatherings, these promiscuous associations
                        of men and women are? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If you knew at what
                        age those of the male sex are initiated, you would feel not only compassion
                        for them, but shame as well. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Do you
                        consider, Quirites, that young men who have taken this unhallowed oath are
                        to be made into soldiers? That after the training they have received in that
                        shrine of obscenity they are to be entrusted with arms? <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Shall these men, reeking with their impurity and that
                        of those round them, wield their swords in defence of the chastity of your
                        wives and children? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "The mischief would not be serious, if
                        they had only lost their manhood through their debauchery-the disgrace would
                        fall mainly upon themselves-and had kept from open outrage and secret
                        treason. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Never has there been such a
                        gigantic evil in the commonwealth, or one which has affected greater numbers
                        or caused more numerous crimes. Whatever instances of lust, treachery, or
                        crime have occurred during these last years, have originated, you may be
                        perfectly certain, in that shrine of unhallowed rites. They have not yet
                        disclosed all the criminal objects of their conspiracy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> So far, their impious association confines itself to
                        individual crimes; it has not yet strength enough to destroy the
                        commonwealth. But the evil is creeping stealthily on, and growing day by
                        day; it is already too great to limit its action to individual citizens; it
                        looks to be supreme in the State. Unless, Quirites, you take precautions,
                        this Assembly legally convened by a consul in the daylight will be
                        confronted by another assembly gathered together in the darkness of the
                        night. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now they, disunited, fear you, a
                        united Assembly, but when you are dispersed to your homes and your farms
                        they will hold their assembly and plot their own safety and your ruin. It
                        will then be your turn, scattered as you will be, to fear them in their
                        united strength. </p>
                    <p> "You ought, therefore, every one of you, to pray that your friends may have
                        preserved their good sense. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If unbridled
                        and maddening lust has swept any one away into that whirlpool, you must
                        judge him as belonging not to you but to those whom he has joined as
                        fellow-conspirators in every kind of wickedness. I do not feel sure that
                        even some of you may not have been misled. For there is nothing which wears
                        a more deceptive appearance than a depraved superstition. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Where crimes are sheltered under the name of religion,
                        there is fear lest in punishing the hypocrisy of men we are doing violence
                        to something holy which is mixed up with it. From these scruples you are
                        delivered by numberless decisions of the pontiffs, resolutions of the senate
                        and responses of the augurs. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> How often in
                        the times of your fathers and grandfathers has the task been assigned to the
                        magistrates of forbidding all foreign rites and ceremonies, prohibiting
                        hedge-priests and diviners from entering either the Forum, the Circus, or
                        the City, seeking out and burning all books of pretended prophecies, and
                        abolishing every sacrificial ritual except what was accordant with Roman
                        usage! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those men were masters of all human
                        and divine love, and they believed that nothing tended so much to destroy
                        religion as the performance of sacrificial rites, not after the manner of
                        our fathers, but in fashions imported from abroad. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> I thought I ought to tell you this beforehand, so that
                        none of you may be distressed by fears on the score of religion when you see
                        us demolishing the seats of the Bacchanalia and dispersing their impious
                        gatherings. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> All that we shall do will be
                        done with the sanction of the gods and in obedience to their will.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To show their displeasure at the
                        insult offered to their majesty by these lusts and crimes they have dragged
                        them out of their dark hiding-places into the light of day, and they have
                        willed that they shall be exposed not to enjoy impunity, but to be punished
                        and put an end to. "The senate has entrusted my colleague and myself with
                        extraordinary powers for conducting an inquiry into this matter. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> We shall make an energetic use of them, and we
                        have charged the subordinate magistrates with the care of the night-watches
                        throughout the City. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It is only right
                        that you should show equal energy in doing your duty in whatever position
                        you may be placed and whatever orders you receive, and also in making it
                        your business to see that no danger or disturbance arise through the secret
                        plots of the criminals." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They then ordered the resolutions of the
                        senate to be read, and offered a reward for any one who should bring a
                        guilty person before the consuls, or give in his name if he were not
                        forthcoming. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the case of any one who
                        had been denounced and then taken to flight, they would fix a day for him to
                        answer the charge, and if he failed to appear, he would be condemned in his
                        absence; for any one who was abroad at the time they would extend the date
                        should he wish to make his defence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They
                        then published an edict forbidding any one to sell or buy anything for the
                        purpose of flight, or to receive, harbour, or in any way assist those who
                        fled. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the Assembly had broken up,
                        the whole of the City was thoroughly alarmed. Nor was the alarm confined
                        within the walls of the City or the frontiers of Rome; there was uneasiness
                        and consternation throughout the whole of Italy when letters began to arrive
                        announcing the resolutions of the senate, the proceedings in the Assembly
                        and the edict of the consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> During the
                        night following the disclosure of the affair in the Assembly, guards were
                        posted at all the gates, and many who tried to escape were arrested by the
                        police commissioners and brought back. Many names were handed in, and some
                        of these, both men and women, committed suicide. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was asserted that more than 7000 of both sexes were
                        implicated in the conspiracy. The ringleaders were, it appears, the two
                        Atinii, Marcus and Caius, both members of the Roman plebs; L. Opiternius of
                        Falerium, and Minius Cerrinius, a Campanian. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> They were the authors of all the crime and outrage, the high priests and
                        founders of the cult. Care was taken that they should be arrested as soon as
                        possible, and when brought before the consuls they at once made a complete
                        confession. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> So great, however, was the number of those
                        who fled from the City that law-suits and rights of property were in
                        numerous cases lost by default, and the praetors were compelled through the
                        intervention of the senate to adjourn their courts for a month, to allow the
                        consuls to complete their investigations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Owing to the fact that those whose names were on the list did not answer to
                        the summons, and were not to be found in Rome, the consuls had to visit the
                        country towns and conduct their inquiries and try the cases there.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Those who had simply been initiated,
                        who, that is, had repeated after the priest the prescribed form of
                        imprecation which pledged them to every form of wickedness and impurity, but
                        had not been either active or passive participants in any of the proceedings
                        to which their oath bound them, were detained in prison. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Those who had polluted themselves by outrage and
                        murder, those who had stained themselves by giving false evidence, forging
                        seals and wills and by other fraudulent practices, were sentenced to death.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The number of those executed exceeded
                        the number of those sentenced to imprisonment; there was an enormous number
                        of men as well as women in both classes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The women who had been found guilty were handed over to their relatives or
                        guardians to be dealt with privately; if there was no one capable of
                        inflicting punishment, they were executed publicly. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The next task awaiting the consuls was the destruction
                        of all the Bacchanalian shrines, beginning with Rome, and then throughout
                        the length and breadth of Italy; those only excepted where there was an
                        ancient altar or a sacred image. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        senate decreed that for the future there should be no Bacchanalian rites in
                        Rome or in Italy. If any one considered that this form of worship was a
                        necessary obligation and that he could not dispense with it without
                        incurring the guilt of irreligion, he was to make a declaration before the
                        City praetor and the praetor was to consult the senate. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> If the senate gave permission, not less than one
                        hundred senators being present, he might observe those rites on condition
                        that not more than five persons took part in the service, that they had no
                        common fund, and that there was no priest or conductor of the ceremonies.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Another matter connected with this was
                        brought forward by the consul Q. Marcius and made the subject of a decree,
                        namely, the cases of those whom the consuls had employed as informers. The
                        question was left for the senate to deal with as soon as Sp. Postumius had
                        closed his inquiry and returned to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The senate decided that Minius Cerrinius, the Campanian, should be sent in
                        chains to Ardea, and that the magistrates there should be warned to keep him
                        in custody under close observation to prevent not only his escape but any
                        chance of his committing suicide. After some time Sp. Postumius returned to
                        Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He brought up the question of the
                        rewards to be given to P. Aebutius and Hispala Fecenia, as it was owing to
                        them that the Bacchanalia had been detected. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> The senate decided that the City praetor should give each of them 100,000
                        ases out of the treasury, and that the consul should arrange with the
                        tribunes to propose to the plebs on the first opportunity that P. Aebutius
                        should be exempted from military conscription, and not compelled, unless he
                        wished, to serve in either the infantry or the cavalry. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> To Fecenia was granted the right of disposing of her
                        property in any way she chose, of marrying out of her gens, and selecting
                        her own guardian, just as though a husband had left her this power in his
                        will. She was also at liberty to marry a free-born citizen, and whoever
                        married her should not suffer in reputation or position. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Moreover, the consuls and praetors then in office, and
                        those who should succeed them, were to make it their care that no harm
                        should happen to the woman but that she should live a safe life. These
                        proposals the senate considered equitable and thought it right that they
                        should be adopted. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were submitted to
                        the plebs and the resolution of the senate was confirmed, and the consuls
                        were to secure the impunity of the other informers and decide upon their
                        rewards. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time Q. Marcius had completed his
                        inquiry throughout the district assigned to him, and was preparing to start
                        for his province in Liguria. He was reinforced by 3000 Roman infantry and
                        150 cavalry, together with a contingent from the Latin allies of 5000
                        infantry and 200 cavalry. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This province
                        had been decreed to his colleague in conjunction with him, and he, too,
                        received reinforcements of equal strength. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        They took over the armies which the previous consuls had commanded, and on
                        the authority of the senate enrolled two fresh legions in addition. They
                        required the Latin allies to furnish 20,000 infantry and 800 cavalry, and
                        called up 3000 Roman infantry and 200 cavalry as well. The whole of this
                        force, with the exception of the legions, was destined to reinforce the
                        armies in Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While the consuls were
                        preoccupied with their judicial investigations they appointed T. Maenius to
                        superintend the levying of the troops. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Q.
                        Marcius was the first to complete his inquiry, and he at once advanced
                        against the Apuani. Whilst he was following them into the depths <milestone
                            n="6??" unit="section"/> of secluded passes, where they were in the
                        habit of sheltering and concealing themselves, the enemy seized a narrow
                        defile and hemmed him in. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Four thousand
                        men were lost, three standards belonging to the second legion and eleven
                        ensigns from the Latin allies fell into the enemy's hands, together with a
                        large quantity of arms which the fugitives, finding that they hampered their
                        flight through the forest tracks, had everywhere thrown away. The enemy
                        stopped their pursuit before the Romans stopped their flight. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as the consul got clear of the enemy's
                        country, he dispersed his army in friendly territory to prevent the extent
                        of his losses from being known. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was
                        not, however, able to efface the memory of his ill-success. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The pass out of which the Ligurians had chased
                        him was afterwards known as the "Marcian Pass." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No sooner had the news from Liguria become
                        generally known, than despatches were received from Spain which aroused
                        mingled feelings of joy and grief. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> C.
                        Atinius, who two years before had gone to that province as propraetor,
                        fought a pitched battle with the Lusitanians in the neighbourhood of Hasta.
                        As many as 6000 of the enemy were killed; the rest were routed and driven
                        out of their camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then he led the legions
                        to an attack on the fortified town of Hasta which he captured with as little
                        difficulty as he had met with in the capture of the camp. But while he was
                        approaching the walls somewhat incautiously, he was struck by a missile and
                        in a few days died of his wound. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the
                        despatch announcing his death was read, the senate were of opinion that a
                        courier ought to be sent to overtake the praetor C. Calpurnius at the port
                        of Luna and inform him that the senate advised him to hasten his departure,
                        so that the province might not be left without an administrator. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The courier reached Luna in four days; Calpurnius
                        had started a few days previously. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In
                        Hither Spain there was also fighting; L. Manlius Acidinus had a battle with
                        the Celtiberi just at the time when C. Atinius reached the province.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The battle was undecided, except so
                        far as the Celtiberi shifted their camp in the following night and the
                        Romans were allowed by the enemy to bury their dead and collect the spoils.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A few days later the Celtiberi, having
                        collected a larger force, took the aggressive and attacked the Romans near
                        the town of Calagurris. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There is no
                        explanation as to why, though their numbers were increased, they proved to
                        be the weaker side. They were worsted in the battle; 12,000 were killed,
                        2000 made prisoners, and the Romans gained possession of their camp.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If his successor had not stopped
                        Calpurnius' victorious advance, the Celtiberi would have been subjugated.
                        The new praetors took both their armies into winter quarters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the time when this intelligence was
                        received from Spain, the "Taurii" Games were celebrated as a special
                        religious observance. These were followed by the Games which M. Fulvius had
                        vowed in the Aetolian war and were exhibited for ten days. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Many actors from Greece came to do him honour, and
                        athletic contests were witnessed for the first time in Rome. The hunting of
                        lions and panthers formed a novel feature, and the whole spectacle presented
                        almost as much splendour and variety as those of the present day. A shower
                        of stones, lasting three days, fell at Picenum, and fire from the sky was
                        said to have appeared in various places and singed many persons' garments.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In consequence of these portents,
                        special religious services were held for nine days. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> An additional day's service was ordered by the pontiffs
                        owing to the temple of Ops on the Capitol being struck by lightning. The
                        consuls sacrificed full-grown victims and purified the City. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Almost at the same time a report came from Umbria
                        of the discovery of a child there, nine years old, who was a hermaphrodite.
                        Horrified at such a portent the auruspices gave orders for it to be removed
                        from Roman soil as speedily as possible and put to death. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> During the year some transalpine Gauls
                        moved into Venetia without doing any damage or attempting hostilities. They
                        took possession of some land not far from where Aquileia now stands on which
                        to build a town. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Roman envoys were sent
                        across the Alps to inquire about this proceeding, and they were informed
                        that the migration had taken place without the authority of their tribe, nor
                        did they know what they were doing in Italy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> L. Scipio now exhibited for ten days the Games which he said that he had
                        vowed in the war with Antiochus; the cost was met by money contributed by
                        the kings and cities of Asia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> According to
                        Valerius Antias, he was sent, after his condemnation and the sale of his
                        property, as special commissioner to settle the differences between
                        Antiochus and Eumenes, and whilst he was on this mission contributions in
                        money were made for him, and actors gathered together from all parts of
                        Asia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He had made no mention of these
                        Games after the war in which he said that he had vowed them; it was only
                        after his mission that they came before the senate. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the year was now closing, Q. Marcius
                        was preparing to lay down his office while still abroad; S. Postumius, who
                        had completed the investigations which he had conducted with the most
                        scrupulous impartiality, held the election. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> The new consuls were Ap. Claudius Pulcher and M. Sempronius Tuditanus.
                        The next day the following were elected praetors: P. Cornelius Cethegus, A.
                        Postumius Albinus, C. Afranius Stellio, C. Atilius Serranus, L. Postumius
                        Tempsanus and M. Claudius Marcellus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> S.
                        Postumius had reported that whilst engaged on his enquiries he had traversed
                        both coasts of Italy, and had found two deserted colonies, Sipontum on the
                        Adriatic and Buxentum on the Mediterranean. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> Three commissioners were appointed by the City praetor to enrol colonists
                        for these places, namely, L. Scribonius Libo, M. Tuccius and Cn. Baebius
                        Tamphilus. The war which was threatening with Perseus and the Macedonians
                        did not owe its origin to what most people imagined, nor was it due to the
                        action of Perseus himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Its beginnings
                        were prepared by Philip, and had he lived longer, he would himself have
                        undertaken it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the terms of peace
                        were imposed upon him after his defeat, the thing which exasperated him most
                        was the interference of the senate with his claim to punish those of his
                        subjects who had revolted from him during the war. In drawing up the
                        conditions of peace Quinctius had left this point for further consideration,
                        and he was not without hopes of making his claim good. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> A second grievance which he felt bitterly was that when
                        Antiochus was <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> worsted at Thermopylae and
                        the two armies separated, the consul advancing against Heraclea and Philip
                        against Lamia, he was ordered to <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> retire
                        from the walls of Lamia, after the capture of Heraclea, and the town was
                        surrendered to the Romans. The Aetolians were rallying from their flight at
                        Naupactus, and the consul, hastening there, mollified Philip's anger by
                        permitting <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> him to make war on Athamania
                        and Amynander and annex the cities, which the Aetolians had taken from the
                        Thracians, to his own dominions. He expelled Amynander from Athamania
                        without much trouble and took some of his cities. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He also reduced Demetrias, a strong city and useful in
                        every respect, and brought the tribe of the Magnetes beneath his sway.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In Thrace, too, there were some
                        cities in a state of turmoil owing to the quarrels of their leaders
                            <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> and the misuse of a liberty to
                        which they were unaccustomed, and these he secured by supporting the weaker
                        side in these domestic conflicts. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These successes for the time being allayed
                        the king's anger against the Romans. Never, however, was his attention
                        diverted from amassing a force during the years of peace which he could,
                        whenever a favourable opportunity presented itself make use of in war.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He raised the taxes which were levied
                        on agricultural produce and increased the amount of the import and export
                        duties; he also re-opened old and disused gold and silver mines and started
                        new ones. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In order to make good the loss
                        of population caused by his wars, he made provision for fresh growths from
                        the stock by compelling all his subjects to marry and bring up children.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He further transported a large body of
                        Thracians into Macedonia, and in these ways, during all the time he was
                        undisturbed by alarms of war, he devoted all his thoughts and care to
                        increasing the power and resources of his realm. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Then fresh incidents occurred to rekindle his
                        indignation against the Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        Thessalians and Perrhaebians protested against his retaining possession of
                        their cities; envoys from Eumenes complained of the forcible occupation of
                        towns in Thrace and the removal of the population into Macedonia. The
                        reception given to these remonstrances made it clear that they would not be
                        ignored. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What created the deepest
                        impression on the senate was the information they had received that he was
                        contemplating the seizure of Aenus and Maronea; they were less interested in
                        the Thessalians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Delegates also appeared
                        from Athamania, the burden of whose complaint was not the loss of a part of
                        their country but the subjection of the whole of Athamania to the power and
                        rule of the king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some Maronite refugees
                        were present who had been expelled because they had tried to defend their
                        liberty against the king's garrison. They declared that not only Maronea but
                        Aenus also was in Philip's power. Envoys came from Philip to defend him
                        against these charges. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They affirmed that
                        nothing had been done without the sanction of the Roman generals; <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> that the cities of the Thessalians and
                        Perrhaebians and Magnetes, as well as the people of Athamania with their
                        king Amynander, were in the same case as the Aetolians. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> For when after the expulsion of Antiochus the consul
                        was engaged in the reduction of the cities of Aetolia, he sent Philip to
                        take the cities in question; they were his by the rights of war. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The senate would not come to any decision in the
                        king's absence, and accordingly they sent Q. Caecilius, M Baebius Tamphilus
                        and Ti. Sempronius, as special commissioners, to settle the dispute.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Previous to their arrival, notice was
                        sent to all the cities concerned that a council would be convened at Tempe
                        in Thessaly. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When all had taken their seats-the Roman
                        commissioners appearing as arbitrators, the Thessalians, Perrhaebians and
                        Athamanians as open accusers, and Philip, who had to listen to the charges
                        against him, as <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> defendant-the leaders of
                        the different delegations revealed their characters in the attitude they
                        assumed towards Philip, whether of sympathy or of more or less violent
                        antagonism. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The dispute turned upon the
                        status of the cities of Philippopolis, Tricca, Phaloria, Eurymenae, and the
                        other towns in their neighbourhood. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Did
                        they belong of right to the Thessalians, though they had been forcibly
                        seized and taken possession of by the Aetolians-for it was admitted that it
                        was from the Aetolians that Philip had wrested them-or had they always been
                        Aetolian towns? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was argued that Acilius
                        had granted them to the king on the understanding that they belonged to the
                        Aetolians, and had joined their League voluntarily, not under the compulsion
                        of arms. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A similar question arose with
                        regard to the towns in Perrhaebia and Magnesia, for the Aetolians, by
                        seizing all these towns as they had opportunity, had made their rightful
                        position uncertain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To these matters in
                        dispute were added the complaints of the Thessalians, who pointed out that
                        if those towns were restored to them as they were, he would restore them
                        plundered and deserted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Besides those lost
                        through the accidents of war, he had carried off 500 of their young men to
                        Macedonia, where they were wasting their energies in servile tasks, and
                        whatever he was compelled to restore to the Thessalians, he took care to
                        render of no further use. In former times the one mercantile port which the
                        Thessalians had access to was Phthian Thebes, from which they derived profit
                        and revenue. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The king fitted out a number
                        of merchant ships there which made their voyages past Thebes to Demetrias,
                        and so diverted all sea-borne traffic from that port. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Now things had come to such a pass that he did not
                        shrink from doing violence to their envoys, who were protected by the law of
                        nations; he had waylaid and captured them on their way to T. Quinctius.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The whole of Thessaly was in
                        consequence so intimidated that no one dared to open his mouth, either in
                        their cities or in their national council. The Romans, the authors of their
                        liberties, were far away; an oppressive tyrant was close at their side,
                        making it impossible for them to enjoy the benefits which the people of Rome
                        had conferred upon them. What liberty was there, where there was no liberty
                        of speech? Even now, whilst relying on the protection of the commissioners,
                        they were uttering groans rather than coherent words. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Unless the Romans devised some means of checking
                        Philip's audacity and relieving the fears of the Greek neighbours of
                        Macedonia, his defeat and their liberation would be in vain. If he does not
                        obey, he must, like a stubborn horse, be coerced with a severer bit.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These bitter invectives were from
                        those who spoke last; the former speakers had softened his resentment by
                        asking him to pardon their speaking in defence of their liberties.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> They expressed a hope that he would
                        lay aside the <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> harshness of a master and
                        reconcile himself to becoming their friend and ally, and so follow the
                        example of the Romans who prefer to extend their alliances through affection
                        and not through fear. After the Thessalians, the Perrhaebians stated their
                        case. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> They claimed Gonnocondylum, which
                        Philip had re-named Olympias, as belonging to Perrhaebia, and pleaded for
                        its restoration. The same request was made with regard to Malloea and
                        Ericinium. The Athamanians sought to recover their independence and the
                        fortified posts of Athenaeum and Poetneum. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip's role was to appear as accuser
                        rather than defendant. He began by charging the Thessalians with seizing
                        Menelais in Dolopia by force of arms, a place which belonged to his
                        dominions, and in conjunction with the Perrhaebians capturing also Petra in
                        Pieria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Even Xynias, beyond all doubt an
                        Aetolian town, had been forced to join their confederacy, and without a
                        shadow of right they had made themselves masters of Parachelois, which was
                        under Athamania. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As to the charges brought
                        against him of waylaying envoys, of causing the fulness or emptiness of
                        seaports, the latter was absurd; he was not responsible for the preference
                        which traders or skippers showed for certain ports; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> and as to the former, it was quite alien from his
                        character. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Through all these years,
                        charges had been continually made against him either to the Roman generals
                        or to the Roman senate. Who had ever been injured even by a word? 'They said
                        that a plot was once formed against those who were going to Quinctius, but
                        they did not go on to say what happened to them. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> These are the accusations of men who are hunting for
                        false charges, since they have nothing true to go upon. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The Thessalians in their insolence were shamelessly
                        abusing the indulgence of the people of Rome; like men who after a long
                        thirst drank wine too eagerly, they were intoxicated with liberty.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Like slaves suddenly and unexpectedly
                        manumitted, they show their freedom by putting no constraint on their speech
                        and language and showering abuse on their late masters. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Then in a towering rage he exclaimed: "The evening of
                        all days has not yet come!'' The Thessalians and even the Romans took this
                        as a threat against themselves. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the
                        murmurs of disapprobation at these words had died away, he replied to the
                        Perrhaebian and Athamanian envoys, and maintained that the cities which they
                        represented were in the same position as the others; Acilius and the Romans
                        had given them to him at a time when they belonged to the enemy. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> If the donors wished to take away what they had
                        given, he knew <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> he must give them up,
                        but in that case they would be ingratiating themselves with fickle and
                        useless allies by doing an injustice to a more deserving and faithful
                        friend. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Nothing evoked a more short-lived
                        gratitude than the gift of liberty, especially among those who were ready to
                        abuse and corrupt it. After hearing all sides the commissioners announced
                        their decision. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The king's garrisons must
                        be withdrawn from the cities in dispute, and his kingdom limited to the
                        ancient frontiers of Macedonia. As for the complaints which each side made
                        against the other, a court of arbitration must be formed to settle the
                        differences between these peoples and the Macedonians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Leaving the king intensely annoyed, the
                        commissioners proceeded to Thessalonica to consider the question of the
                        cities of Thrace. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here they met the envoys
                        of Eumenes, who asserted that if the Romans wished Aenus and Maronea to be
                        free, their sense of honour forbade them to say more, unless it was to warn
                        them to leave those people in the enjoyment of a real and not merely nominal
                        liberty, and not to allow their boon to be intercepted by some one else.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But if they thought the question of
                        the Thracian cities comparatively unimportant, it would be much more
                        reasonable that those which had been under Antiochus should be held as
                        prizes of war by Eumenes rather than by Philip. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> This would be a return to Eumenes for the services of
                        his father Attalus during the war which the Romans waged against this same
                        Philip, and also for what he had himself done in sharing all their toils and
                        dangers on land and sea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Moreover, Eumenes
                        had the decision of the ten commissioners in his favour, for in giving him
                        the Chersonese and Lysimachia they certainly gave him Aenus and Maronea as
                        well, for these two places owing to their proximity formed appendages as it
                        were of the larger gift. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "What service
                        rendered to the Roman people, or what sovereign right could justify Philip
                        in forcing his garrison on these cities, lying as they do so far from the
                        frontiers of Macedonia? Let the Maronites be called in, then the
                        commissioners will learn everything about the status of those cities."
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Maronites were then called in.
                        They told the commissioners that the king's troops were not confined to one
                        part of the city, as in other places, but were dispersed everywhere; the
                        city was full of Macedonians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The king's
                        adherents were complete masters; they alone were allowed to speak in the
                        senate and the public assembly; they secured all the posts of honour for
                        themselves and their friends. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Every
                        respectable citizen who had any regard for liberty and law was either
                        expelled from his native place or, unhonoured, and at the mercy of the mob,
                        was compelled to remain silent. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Briefly
                        explaining what were their legal boundaries, they stated that when Q. Fabius
                        Labeo was in that district he fixed the old "king's road," which goes up to
                        Parorea in Thrace and nowhere descends to the sea, as Philip's boundary
                        line; Philip subsequently constructed a new road by which he took in the
                        cities and lands of the Maronites. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip took a very different course in his
                        reply from that which he adopted towards the Thessalians and Perrhaebians.
                        "My contention," he began, "is not with the Maronites or with Eumenes, but
                        with you, Romans. I have for some time perceived that I shall get no fair
                        treatment from you. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I thought it just and
                        right that the cities of the Macedonians which revolted from me during the
                        suspension of hostilities should be restored to me; not that these would
                        have been a great addition to my kingdom, for they are small places situated
                        on the extreme frontiers, but because such an example would have gone far to
                        restrain the rest of the Macedonians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This
                        has been refused me. During the Aetolian war I was instructed by Manius
                        Acilius to attack Lamia, and when after long and weary siege operations and
                        fighting I was at last surmounting the walls, and the city was all but
                        taken, the consul recalled me, and compelled me to draw off my troops.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As some consolation for this
                        injustice, I was allowed to seize some places in Thessaly, Perrhaebia and
                        Athamania-forts rather than cities. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those
                        very places you, Q. Caecilius, took from me a few days ago. </p>
                    <p> "The envoys of Eumenes actually assumed just now, as a matter beyond doubt,
                        that it would be more equitable for Eumenes to hold the places which
                        belonged to Antiochus, than that I should do so. I take a very different
                        view. Unless the Romans had-I will not say conquered, but even-undertaken
                        that war, Eumenes could not have remained on his throne. So it is he who is
                        indebted to you, not you to him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So far
                        was any part of my kingdom from being in danger, that when Antiochus sought
                        to purchase my support by the promise of 3000 talents, 50 decked ships, and
                        all the cities of Greece which he had previously held, I rejected his offer
                        and declared myself his enemy even before Manius Acilius landed his army in
                        Greece. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In concert with him I took
                        whatever part in the war he assigned to me, and when his successor, Lucius
                        Scipio, decided to take his <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> army to the
                        Hellespont overland, I not only allowed him a free passage through my
                        dominions, but I constructed roads, built bridges and furnished supplies,
                        and this not through Macedonia only, but through Thrace as well, where
                        amongst other things peace had to be secured from the barbarians. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> In return for this proof of my goodwill towards
                        you-I will not call it meritorious service-what is the right thing to do,
                        Romans: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> to augment and amplify my kingdom
                        by your generosity, or to rob me as you are now doing of what I hold,
                        whether by my own right or by your liberality? The Macedonian cities which,
                        you admit, formed part of my dominions are not restored. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Eumenes has come here to despoil me as though I were
                        Antiochus, and actually has the impudence to put forward the decision of the
                        ten commissioners as a cloak for his dishonest intrigues; the very decision
                        by which he can be most effectually confuted. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> It is quite clearly stated there that the Chersonese
                        and Lysimachia are given to Eumenes. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Where, pray, are Aenus and Maronea and the cities of Thrace mentioned? Is he
                        going to get from you what he did not dare to ask from them, as though they
                        had granted it? It is a matter of some importance to me in what light you
                        regard me. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If you have made up your minds
                        to persecute me as an enemy, go on as you have begun; but if you have any
                        feeling of regard for me as a royal friend and ally, do not judge me
                        deserving of so great an injustice." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king's address made a considerable
                        impression on the commissioners. Their reply was a compromise; nothing was
                        decided. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If those cities were given to
                        Eumenes by the decision of the ten commissioners, they said, they would make
                        no change; if Philip had taken them in war, he should hold them as the prize
                        of war; if neither of these proved to be the case, the question must be left
                        to the senate. In order that matters might remain as they were, the
                        garrisons must be withdrawn from those cities. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> These were the main reasons why Philip turned against
                        the Romans. The war was not started by his son Perseus on any fresh ground;
                        it might be regarded as a legacy from his father. At Rome there was no
                        suspicion of a war with Macedonia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        proconsul L. Manlius had returned from Spain. The senate met in the temple
                        of Bellona, and he asked to be allowed to celebrate his triumph. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The magnitude of his operations justified his
                        request, but precedent was against it; the immemorial practice had been that
                        no commander should enjoy a triumph unless he had brought back his army, or
                        unless he left to his successor a province thoroughly subjugated and
                        pacified. However, the intermediate honour was allowed to Manlius; he was to
                        enter the City in ovation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In his
                        procession were borne 52 golden crowns, 132 <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> pounds of gold, and 16,300 pounds of silver, and he
                        announced in the senate that his quaestor, Q. Fabius, was bringing 10,000
                        pounds of silver and 80 pounds of gold, and this also he would place in the
                        treasury. There was a wide-spread movement amongst the slaves in Apulia this
                        year. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The herdsmen had entered into a
                        conspiracy and were making the highroads and public pastures insecure
                        through acts of brigandage. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The praetor L.
                        Postumius, who was administering the district from Tarentum, made a strict
                        and close investigation, and sentenced as many as 7000 men. Many took to
                        flight and many were executed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        consuls who had been for a long time detained in the City by the enrolment
                        of troops departed at last for their provinces. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as their troops left their winter
                        quarters, the two praetors, C. Calpurnius and L. Quinctius, joined their
                        forces in Baeturia, and as the enemy were encamped in Carpetania they
                        advanced thither, prepared to carry out their operations in mutual concert.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A fight began at a spot not far from
                        the cities of Dipo and Toletum between foraging parties, who were reinforced
                        from both camps, and gradually the whole of the two armies were drawn out to
                        battle. In this tumultuary conflict the enemy were helped by their knowledge
                        of the country and the nature of the fighting. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The two Roman armies were routed and driven back to
                        their camp. The enemy did not press their demoralised adversaries. The Roman
                        commanders, fearing lest the camp might be stormed on the morrow, withdrew
                        their armies in silence during the night. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The Spaniards formed in battle-array at dawn and marched up to the rampart;
                        surprised at finding the camp empty, they entered it and appropriated what
                        had been left behind in the confusion of the night. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After this they returned to their own camp and remained
                        inactive for some days. The losses of the Romans and the allies in the
                        battle amounted to 5000, and the enemy armed themselves with the spoils
                        taken from their bodies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then they moved
                        on to the Tagus. </p>
                    <p> The Roman generals in the meantime had spent their whole time in drawing
                        Spanish troops from the friendly cities and restoring the courage of their
                        men which had been so shaken in the battle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> When they considered that they were strong enough and the soldiers were
                        asking that they might meet the enemy and wipe out <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> their disgrace, they moved forward and fixed their camp
                        at a distance of twelve miles from the Tagus. Then, taking up the standards
                        and forming into a closed square, they reached the Tagus at daybreak.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The enemy camp was on a hill on the
                        other side of the river. There were two places where the river was fordable,
                        and the armies were promptly led across-Calpurnius on the right and
                        Quinctius on the left. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The enemy remained
                        quiet-taken aback at the sudden advance of the Romans and making up their
                        minds what to do-when they might have attacked the Romans and thrown them
                        into confusion during the passage of the river. The Romans meanwhile had
                        transported their baggage across and placed it all together. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> There was not space enough for an entrenched
                        camp, so seeing the enemy in motion, they deployed into line of battle. Two
                        legions, the fifth from Calpurnius' army and the eighth under Quinctius,
                        formed the centre-the main strength of the army. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The ground was level and open up to the hostile camp;
                        there was no fear of surprise or ambush. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Spaniards saw the two Roman
                        divisions on their side of the river, they decided to engage them before
                        they could form a united front, and swarming out of their camp they rushed
                        down to battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The fighting began very
                        fiercely, as the Spaniards were full of spirit after their recent victory,
                        and the Romans were smarting under their unwonted humiliation. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman centre, formed by two of the bravest
                        legions, fought most gallantly, and the enemy finding themselves unable to
                        dislodge them in any other way, formed themselves into a wedge and thus
                        massed, the ranks behind always more numerous than those in front, they
                        forced the centre back. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he saw that
                        the line was in trouble, Calpurnius sent two of his staff, T. Quinctilius
                        Varus and L. Juventius Thalna, one to each legion, to stimulate their
                        courage, and warn them that all hopes of victory or of keeping their hold on
                        Spain rested with them; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> if they gave way,
                        not a man would ever see the other side of the Tagus, let alone any return
                        to Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He, himself, with the cavalry,
                        made a short detour and charged the flank of the enemy's wedge as it was
                        pressing back the centre, and Quinctilius delivered a similar charge on the
                        other side. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the cavalry under
                        Calpurnius fought with much the greater determination, and he, himself, most
                        of all. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was the first to strike down an
                        enemy, and he rode so far into the hostile ranks that it was difficult to
                        recognise to which side he belonged. The praetor's conspicuous courage fired
                        the cavalry, and the cavalry fired the infantry. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The leading centurions who saw the praetors in the
                        midst of the enemy's weapons felt that their honour was at stake; they each
                        urged on their standard-bearers, shouting to them to carry their standards
                        forward, and then called upon the soldiers to follow them up. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The battle-shout rose again from the whole army,
                        and they dashed forward as if they were charging from higher ground. Just
                        like a mountain torrent they bore down and swept away their unnerved foe,
                        and as rank after rank pressed on, they carried all before them. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The cavalry pursued the fugitives up to their
                        camp, and mingling with the crowded enemy forced their way into it. Here a
                        fresh battle began with those left to guard the camp, and the Roman troops
                        were obliged to dismount and fight on foot. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> The fifth legion now joined the combatants, and the rest came up as fast
                        as they could. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Spaniards were cut
                        down everywhere throughout the camp; not more than 4000 men escaped. Of
                        these about 3000, who had retained their arms, occupied a mountain in the
                        neighbourhood, and the rest, only half-armed, straggled about the country.
                        The enemy had numbered more than 35,000, out of whom this small number alone
                        survived the battle. One hundred and thirty-two standards were captured.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Of the Romans and allies little more
                        than 600 fell, and of the native auxiliaries about 150. <milestone n="15??"
                            unit="section"/> It was mainly the loss of five military tribunes and a
                        few of the Roman cavalry that gave the victory the appearance of a bloody
                        one. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> As they had not ground sufficient
                        for their own camp, they remained in the enemy's camp. The next day
                        Calpurnius addressed words of thanks and praise to the cavalry, and
                        presented them with ornamental trappings for their horses. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> He told them that it was mainly due to them that the
                        enemy had been routed, and his camp captured. Quinctius presented his
                        cavalry with chains and brooches. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The
                        centurions also in both armies received rewards, especially those who had
                        been posted in the centre. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the enrolment of troops and the other
                        business which kept the consuls in Rome was finished, they led the army into
                        Liguria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Sempronius advanced from Pisae
                        against the Apuani, and after devastating their fields and burning their
                        villages, opened up the pass leading to the river Macra and the port of
                        Luna. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The enemy took up their position on
                        a mountain range, where their ancestors had long been settled, and though
                        the approach was extremely difficult they were driven off. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In his good fortune and courage Appius Claudius was not
                        behind his colleague. He won several victories over the Ingauni, took six of
                        their towns and many thousands of the inhabitants. Forty-three of the chief
                        instigators of the war were beheaded. The time for the elections was now
                        approaching. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It fell to Sempronius to
                        conduct them, but Claudius reached Rome before him, as his brother Publius
                        was standing for the consulship. The other patrician candidates were L.
                        Aemilius, Q. Fabius and Ser. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Sulpicius
                        Galba. They had been unsuccessful in previous contests, and they considered
                        that they had all the stronger claim to the honour because it had been
                        denied them before. Only one consul could be a patrician, and this lent
                        additional keenness to the contest. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        plebeian candidates were all popular men: L. Porcius, Q. Terentius Culleo
                        and Cnaeus Baebius Tamphilus, and they, too, had had their hopes of
                        attaining the distinction deferred by previous defeats. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Out of all the candidates, Claudius was the only new
                        one. It was generally looked upon as a certainty that Q. Fabius Labeo and L.
                        Porcius Licinius would be the successful candidates. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> But Claudius, unattended by his lictors, was bustling
                        about with his brother in every corner of the Forum, notwithstanding the
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> loud remonstrances of his opponents
                        and of most of the senators, who told him to bear in mind that he was the
                        consul of the people of Rome rather than that he was Publius' brother.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "Why," they asked, "did he not take
                        his seat on the tribunal and show himself as a witness or silent spectator
                        of the proceedings?" In spite of all, he could not be restrained from his
                        zealous exertions. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The elections were
                        from time to time disturbed by heated quarrels between the tribunes of the
                        plebs; some were fighting against the consul, and some in his support. At
                        last Appius succeeded in defeating Fabius and carrying his brother in.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Contrary to his own expectation and
                        everybody else's, P. Claudius Pulcher was elected consul. L. Porcius
                        Licinius gained his position because he had conducted his canvass amongst
                        the plebeians in a temper of moderation, not with the violence of a
                        Claudius. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Those who were elected praetors
                        on the following day were C. Decimius Flavus, P. Sempronius Longus, P.
                        Cornelius Cethegus, Q. Naevius Matho, C. Sempronius Blaesus and A. Terentius
                        Varro. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> These were the main incidents at
                        home and abroad during the consulship of Appius Claudius and M. Sempronius.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commissioners who had been sent to
                        adjust the differences between Philip and Eumenes and the cities in Thrace
                        had given in their report, and at the commencement of the year, the consuls
                        introduced the envoys from the two monarchs and the cities to the senate.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The same arguments as had been used
                        before the commissioners in Greece were repeated on both sides. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The senate decreed that a fresh commission should
                        go to Greece and Macedonia to find out whether the cities had been given
                        back to the Thessalians and Perrhaebians. Instructions were also given that
                        the garrisons should be withdrawn from Aenus and Maronea, and that the whole
                        of the Thracian sea-board should be cleared of Philip and his Macedonians.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The commissioners were further ordered
                        to visit the Peloponnese which the former commission had left in a more
                        unsatisfactory situation than if they had <milestone n="5??" unit="section"
                        /> not gone there, for they had come away without receiving any assurances,
                        and the council of the Achaean League had refused their request for an
                        interview. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Q. Caecilius complained in very
                        strong terms of their conduct, and the Lacedaemonians at the same time
                        deplored the razing of their walls, the removal of the population as slaves
                        into Achaia, and the abolition of the laws of Lycurgus, on which up to that
                        day the stability of their State had rested. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The Achaeans met the charge of refusing to convene their council by
                        quoting the law which forbade the summoning of a council except where the
                        question was one of peace or war, or when delegates came from the senate
                        with despatches or written instructions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        That they might not have that excuse for the future, the senate pointed out
                        to them that it was their duty to see that Roman envoys had at all times an
                        opportunity of approaching their council, just as an audience of the senate
                        was granted to them whenever they wished for one. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The delegations left for their homes, and
                        Philip was informed by his delegates that he must withdraw his garrisons
                        from the cities. Furious as he was with everybody, he wreaked his vengeance
                        on the Maronites. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He sent instructions to
                        Onomastus, the governor of the coastal district, to put to death the leaders
                        of the party opposed to him. There was a certain Casander, one of the king's
                        courtiers, who had been living a considerable time in Maronea. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Through his agency a body of Thracians were
                        admitted by night and a general massacre followed as though the place had
                        been taken by assault. The Roman commissioners censured him for behaving so
                        cruelly to the unoffending Maronites and so defiantly towards the people of
                        Rome; those to whom the senate had guaranteed their liberty had been
                        butchered as though they were enemies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Philip said that neither he nor any of his people were concerned in the
                        matter; a domestic quarrel had broken out amongst them, some wanting to
                        bring the city over to him, others to Eumenes; the commissioners could
                        easily get at the facts by questioning the Maronites themselves. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He made this suggestion fully convinced that the
                        Maronites had been too much terrified by the recent bloodshed to open their
                        mouths against him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Appius replied that he
                        should make no enquiry, as though there was any doubt in his mind, the facts
                        were quite clear. If Philip wished to remove all suspicion, he must send
                        those who were reported to have been his agents-Onomastus and Casander-to
                        Rome, that the senate might examine them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        The king was so startled at this that the colour fled from his face. At
                        last, recovering his presence of mind, he promised that he would send
                        Casander, if they really wished it, as he had been at Maronea; <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> but how, he asked, could Onomastus be connected
                        with the affair, seeing that he was not in Maronea nor anywhere near it?
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was anxious to keep Onomastus out
                        of danger because he valued him as a friend, and he was afraid of any
                        evidence he might give, for he had had frequent conversations with him and
                        made him his agent and confidant in many similar designs. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> As for Casander, it is believed that to prevent him
                        from giving any information, he was poisoned by emissaries, who were sent
                        direct through Epirus down to the sea </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commissioners came away from the
                        conference making no secret of their failure to get anything satisfactory,
                        and Philip on his side entertained no doubt that he would have to renew
                        hostilities. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His resources were not yet
                        sufficient, and in order to gain time, he decided <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> to send his younger son Demetrius to Rome with the
                        object of exculpating him from the charges brought against him, and at the
                        same time deprecating the anger of the senate. He quite hoped that in spite
                        of his youth, the prince, who had given proof of his princely character
                        whilst a hostage in Rome, would have considerable influence there.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, under cover of carrying
                        succour to the Byzantines but really to intimidate the Thracian chiefs, he
                        advanced against the latter and completely defeated them in a single battle,
                        taking Amodocus, their leader, prisoner. He had previously sent messages to
                        the barbarians dwelling round the Hister urging them to make an incursion
                        into Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman commissioners were
                        under orders to proceed from Macedonia to Achaia, and their arrival was
                        being awaited in the Peloponnese. The captain-general Lycortas summoned a
                        special meeting of the national council to decide upon the policy to be
                        adopted. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The subject of discussion was the
                        Lacedaemonians. From being enemies they had become accusers, and there was
                        fear lest they should be more dangerous now that they were defeated than
                        when engaged in war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In that war the
                        Achaeans had found the Romans useful allies; now these very Romans were more
                        partial to the Lacedaemonians than to the Achaeans. Areus and Alcibiades,
                        both of them exiles and repatriated through the good offices of the
                        Achaeans, had actually undertaken a mission to Rome against the interests of
                        the nation to whom they owed so much, and had spoken in such a hostile tone
                        that it might be thought that they were expelled from, not restored to,
                        their country. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Demands arose from all
                        sides that the council should deal with them individually. As the whole
                        proceedings were governed by passion, not by reason, they were condemned to
                        death. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days later the Roman commissioners
                        arrived. The council was convened to meet them at Clitoris in Arcadia.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Before the business began, the
                        Achaeans saw Areus and Alcibiades, who had been condemned to death at the
                        last meeting, sitting with the commissioners. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They were thoroughly alarmed and did not consider that
                        the coming discussion would be very favourable to them; no one, however,
                        dared to open his mouth. Appius pointed out how the various things that the
                        Lacedaemonians complained of were viewed with displeasure by the senate-the
                        assassination at Campasium of the delegates <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> who on the invitation of Philopoemen had gone to make
                        their defence, and then after this cruelty towards men, their filling up the
                        measure of savagery by razing the walls of a great and famous city and
                        annulling the immemorial laws and world-famed discipline of Lycurgus.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After this speech, Lycortas in his
                        capacity of captain-general, and also as a supporter of Philopoemen, the
                        prime mover in all that had happened in Lacedaemon, rose to reply.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "It is more difficult," he began, "for
                        us to speak before you, Appius Claudius, than it was the other day before
                        the Roman senate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then we had to answer
                        the accusations of the Lacedaemonians; now it is you who are our accusers,
                        you before whom the issue is to be tried. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Whilst labouring under this disadvantage, we still hope that you will lay
                        aside the heated temper in which you spoke just now, and listen to us in a
                        judicial frame of mind. At all events, as regards the complaints which the
                        Lacedaemonians laid before Q. Caecilius and afterwards at Rome, and which
                        you yourself have now repeated, it is to them, and not to you, that I shall
                        suppose myself to be replying. </p>
                    <p> "You bring up against us the assassination of the delegates who had gone on
                        the invitation of Philopoemen to make their defence. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> I hold this charge ought never to have been made by
                        you, Romans, or even by others in your presence. Why so? Because it was laid
                        down in your treaty with the Lacedaemonians that they should not interfere
                        with the cities on the coast. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Had T.
                        Quinctius been in the Peloponnese; had there been a Roman there at the time
                        when the Lacedaemonians made an armed attack upon the cities which they were
                        pledged to leave alone, the inhabitants would, of course, have taken refuge
                        with the Romans. As you were far away, with whom else could they have found
                        shelter but with us, your allies? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They
                        had previously seen us carrying succour to Gytheum and attacking Lacedaemon
                        on similar grounds in conjunction with you. On your behalf, then, we
                        undertook the war as a just one, prompted by our sense of duty. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Since others commend our conduct, and not even
                        the Lacedaemonians can find fault with it, since the gods themselves, who
                        have given us the victory, showed their approval of it, how can what we did
                        by right of war admit of question? And yet the thing they lay most stress
                        upon in no way concerns us. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> We are
                        responsible for having called to trial the men who had excited the
                        population to take up arms, who had stormed and plundered the maritime towns
                        and massacred their leading men; but the putting them to death as they were
                        coming into the camp was your doing, Areus and Alcibiades; and now, good
                        heavens! <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> you are actually accusing us of
                        it! The Lacedaemonian refugees, these two men amongst them, were with us at
                        the time, and because they had selected the maritime towns for <milestone
                            n="15??" unit="section"/> their residence, they believed that their
                        lives were in danger, and in retaliation made an attack upon those who had
                        been the instruments of their banishment and would not suffer them to pass
                        their lives in security, even though it were in exile. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> It was not, therefore, the Achaeans but the
                        Lacedaemonians who slew Lacedaemonians, whether justly or unjustly, we are
                        not concerned to discuss. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "'Well but,' you say, 'these things are
                        your doing, Achaeans-the abolition of the laws and discipline of Lycurgus
                        which have come down from a remote antiquity, and the destruction of the
                        walls.' <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now, how can both these charges be
                        made by the same people, seeing that the walls were built, not by Lycurgus
                        but only a few years ago, and built, too, for the purpose of undermining the
                        discipline of Lycurgus? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is quite
                        recently that the tyrants raised them as a stronghold and defence for
                        themselves, not for the city; and if Lycurgus could today rise from the
                        dead, he would be glad to see them in ruins, and would say that he now
                        recognised his old Sparta. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For like
                        disfiguring brands they marked you as slaves, and you ought to have torn
                        down and demolished with your own hands, Lacedaemonians, every vestige of
                        the tyrant's rule, and not have waited for Philopoemen and the Achaeans to
                        do it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst for 800 years you were
                        without walls, you were free and for some time the foremost power in Greece,
                        but when shut in by walls, bound as it were by fetters, you have for the
                        last century been slaves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As for the
                        deprivation of their laws and constitution, I consider that the tyrants
                        deprived the Lacedaemonians of their ancient laws; we did not deprive them
                        of their laws and constitution, for they had none; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> but we gave them our own laws, nor did we in any way do
                        the city a wrong when we made it a member of our council and incorporated it
                        in our League, so that there might be one political body and one common
                        council for the whole of the Peloponnese. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        If we ourselves had been living at the time under different laws from those
                        which we imposed on them, they could, in my opinion, have complained and
                        felt justly indignant at not enjoying equal rights with us. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "I am quite aware, Appius Claudius, that
                        the language I have so far used is not the language that allies should hold
                        towards allies, nor does it befit a nation of freemen; it is really
                        appropriate to the bickerings of slaves before their masters. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> If there is any meaning in the words of the
                        herald in which you ordered that the Achaeans should be the first of all the
                        Greeks to be free; if our treaty is still in force; if the terms of amity
                        and alliance are kept equally for both sides, why should I not ask what you
                        Romans did when you took Capua, as you demand from us an account for what we
                        Achaeans did to the Lacedaemonians, after we had conquered them in war?
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> 'Some of them were killed.' Suppose
                        they were killed by us, what then? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Did
                        not you, senators, behead the Campanians? We destroyed the walls; you
                        deprived the Campanians not only of their walls but of their city and their
                        fields. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The treaty, you say, is on the
                        face of it just to both sides. As a matter of fact, the Achaeans enjoy a
                        precarious freedom; the supreme power rests with the Romans. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> I am sensible of this, and I do not, unless
                        compelled, protest against it; but I do implore you, however great the
                        difference between the Romans and the Achaeans, not to let our common
                        enemies stand in as favourable position with you as we, who are your allies,
                        still less in a more favourable one. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For
                        we put them on an equality with ourselves when we gave them our laws. What
                        satisfies the victors is too little for the vanquished; enemies demand more
                        than allies receive. The agreement which has been sworn to and inscribed in
                        stone for a perpetual memorial as being sacred and inviolable, that
                        agreement they are preparing to do away with, and make us forsworn.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> We have a profound respect for you,
                        Romans, and if you wish it, we hold you in fear, but we have a more profound
                        respect for and a greater fear of the immortal gods." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> His speech was received with general
                        approbation; all recognised that he had spoken as befitted the high position
                        he held, so that it was quite clear that the Romans could not maintain their
                        authority, if they did not take a strong line. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> Appius said that he would strongly advise the Achaeans
                        to court the favour of the Romans whilst they could do so of their own
                        free-will, lest they should soon be compelled to do so against their will.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> These words called forth a general
                        murmur, but they were afraid of what might happen if they refused to comply
                        with the Roman demands. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> They only
                        requested the Romans to make such changes with regard to the Lacedaemonians
                        as seemed desirable, and not involve the Achaeans in the guilt of perjury by
                        making them undo what they had sworn to. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                        The only decision arrived at was the cancelling of the sentence against
                        Areus and Alcibiades. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the assignment of provinces at the
                        commencement of the year to the consuls and praetors, Liguria, the only
                        country where war was going on, was assigned to the consuls. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The allocation of provinces to the praetors was
                        as follows: the civic jurisdiction fell to C. Decimius Flavus; <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> the alien, P. Cornelius Cethegus; C. Sempronius
                        Blaesus took Sicily; Q. Naevius Matho, Sardinia, and also the investigation
                        into the alleged cases of poisoning; A. Terentius Varro, Hither Spain, and
                        P. Sempronius Longus, Further Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From
                        these two last-mentioned provinces, two representatives of the praetors-L.
                        Juventius Thalna and T. Quinctius Varus-went to Rome and after explaining to
                        the senate the magnitude of the war in Spain which had now been terminated,
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> they made a request that for such a
                        great success, honours should be paid to the immortal gods and the praetors
                        allowed to bring home their army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A two
                        days' thanksgiving was appointed; as to the return of the legions, the
                        senate ordered the matter to be adjourned till the question of the armies
                        for the consuls and praetors was considered. A few days later a decree was
                        made transferring to each of the consuls two of the legions which Appius
                        Claudius and M. Sempronius had had. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        question of the armies in Spain gave rise to a serious <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> dispute between the new praetors and the friends of the
                        praetors in Spain. Each side was supported by tribunes of the plebs and by
                        one of the consuls. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The one party
                        threatened to veto any senatorial decree which ordered the return of the
                        armies; the other side declared that if such a veto took place, they would
                        stop all further business. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The interests
                        of the praetors abroad proved the stronger, and a resolution was passed by
                        the senate that the new praetors should enrol 4000 Roman infantry and 300
                        cavalry, and from the Latin allies 5000 infantry and 500 cavalry, as the
                        force which they were to take with them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        When they had incorporated them with the four legions in Spain, so that each
                        legion should not contain more than 5000 infantry and 300 cavalry, they were
                        to discharge the remainder; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> first, those
                        who had served their time, and then those who had shown exceptional bravery
                        in battle under Calpurnius and Quinctius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No sooner was this dispute settled than a
                        fresh one started on the death of the praetor C. Decimius. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The candidates for the vacant post were Cnaeus Sicinius
                        and L. Pupius, who had been aediles during the previous year; C. Valerius,
                        one of the Flamens of Jupiter, and Q. Fulvius Flaccus, who was curule aedile
                        designate, and therefore did not appear in a candidate's dress, though he
                        was most active of all in his canvassing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The contest lay between him and the Flamen. At first they were level, but
                        when he appeared to be winning, some of the tribunes of the plebs said that
                        votes must not be accepted for him, because no one could accept or hold two
                        magistracies, especially curule magistracies, at the same time. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Other tribunes thought it only right that he
                        should be exempted from the legal disability in order that the people might
                        be at liberty to elect whom they would as praetor. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> L. Porcius, the consul, was at first disposed not to
                        allow votes for him; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> then in order to have
                        the authority of the senate for doing this, he summoned the senators and
                        said that he referred the question to them because the canvassing for a
                        praetorship on the part of a curule aedile elect was not in accordance with
                        justice, nor would the precedent be one which a free commonwealth could
                        allow. As far as he was concerned, unless they thought some other course
                        desirable, he intended to conduct the election according to law. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The senate decided that the consul should come to
                        an understanding with Q. Fulvius not to prevent the election of a praetor in
                        place of C. Decimius from being conducted according to law. Acting on this
                        resolution the consul approached Flaccus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        He replied that he would do nothing unworthy of himself. Those who
                        interpreted this evasive reply in accordance with their wishes were led to
                        hope that he would yield to the authority of the senate. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> On the day of the election he displayed more determined
                        activity than ever, and accused the consul and the senate of trying to
                        deprive him of the goodwill and sympathy of the people of Rome, and creating
                        odium against him for aspiring to double honours, as if it were not
                        perfectly obvious that as soon as he was elected praetor he would resign the
                        aedileship. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the consul saw that he
                        was becoming more obstinate, and the popular feeling was more and more in
                        his favour, he suspended the election and convened a meeting of the senate.
                        There was a full attendance, and they resolved that since the authority of
                        the senate had no weight with Flaccus, the case must be brought before the
                        people. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Assembly met and the consul
                        laid the matter before them. Not even then was Flaccus moved from his
                        determination. He expressed his gratitude to the Roman People for their
                        zealous support and their desire to make him praetor as often as they had
                        the opportunity of expressing their desire. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> He had no intention of forgoing the zealous support which his
                        fellow-citizens accorded him. The fixed determination thus expressed kindled
                        the popular enthusiasm to such an extent that he would undoubtedly have
                        become praetor, had the consul been willing to accept votes for him.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There was a heated dispute amongst
                        the tribunes themselves and between them and the consul, until at a meeting
                        of the senate convened by the consul it was decreed that whereas the
                        obstinacy of Q. Fulvius and the mischief of party strife prevented the
                        election from being conducted according to law, the senate considered that
                        the number of praetors was sufficient. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> P.
                        Cornelius was to exercise both jurisdictions m the City and also to
                        celebrate the Games of Apollo. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This election had been stopped through the
                        good sense and courage of the senate, but another followed where more
                        important interests were at stake and more numerous and more influential
                        competitors appeared. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was the
                        election to the censorship. Those who were standing were L. Valerius
                        Flaccus, the two Scipios, Publius and Lucius, Cnaeus Manlius Vulso, L.
                        Furius Purpurio as patricians, and the following plebeians: M. Porcius Cato,
                        M. Fulvius Nobilior, the two Sempronii, Tiberius and Sempronius Longus, and
                        M. Sempronius Tuditanus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The contest was a
                        very animated one, but patricians and plebeians alike, even those belonging
                        to the noblest families, were far outstripped by M. Porcius. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> This man possessed such ability and force of
                        character that in whatever station he had been born he must have been a
                        fortunate and successful man. In no department of business, whether public
                        or private, was the requisite knowledge lacking to him, he was equally
                        versed in the affairs of town and country life. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Some men have reached the highest posts through their
                        knowledge of law, others through eloquence, others again through their
                        military reputation. This man's versatile genius made him at home in all
                        alike, so much so indeed that whatever he took up you would say that he was
                        born for that one thing alone. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In war he
                        was a most doughty fighter and distinguished himself in many famous battles,
                        and when he reached the highest posts he proved himself a consummate
                        general. In peace, if you consulted him you found him a most able lawyer,
                        and if he had to plead in a case, a most eloquent one. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Nor was he one of those whose power of speech lasts
                        only during their lifetime, and of whose eloquence no memorial survives; his
                        eloquence is still alive and vigorous, enshrined in writings on all sorts of
                        subjects. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There are a great number of
                        speeches made in his own defence and in defence of others, and also against
                        others, for he harassed his opponents equally whether he was prosecuting or
                        defending. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Personal quarrels-far too many
                        of them-kept him busy, and he himself took care to keep them alive, so that
                        it would be difficult to say who displayed the greater energy, the nobility
                        in trying to suppress him, or he in worrying the nobility. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He was undoubtedly a man of a rough temper and a bitter
                        and unbridled tongue, absolute master of his passions, of inflexible
                        integrity, and indifferent alike to wealth and popularity. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He lived a life of frugality capable of enduring toil
                        and danger, with a mind and body tempered almost like steel, which not even
                        old age that weakens everything could break. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> In his eighty-sixth year he defended himself in a
                        lawsuit and published his speech, in his ninetieth year he brought Ser.
                        Galba to trial before the people. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was the man who was a candidate for
                        the censorship, and the nobility tried now, as they had done all through his
                        life, to crush him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With the exception of
                        L. Flaccus, who had been his colleague in the consulship, all the candidates
                        combined to keep him out, not so much because they wanted the post for
                        themselves, or because they were indignant at the prospect of a "novus homo"
                        as censor, as because they expected that his censorship would be strict and
                        severe and damaging to many reputations; most of them had done him a bad
                        turn and he would be eager to retaliate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Even in his candidature he assumed a menacing tone and accused his opponents
                        of trying to prevent his election, because they were afraid of a censor who
                        would act with impartiality and courage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        At the same time he supported the candidature of L. Valerius, for he
                        considered him the only man with whom as colleague he could repress the
                        vices of the time and restore the old standard of morality. His speeches
                        awoke general enthusiasm and the people, in the teeth of the nobility, not
                        only made him censor but gave him L. Valerius as his colleague. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Close upon the election of censors followed the
                        departure of the consuls and praetors for their provinces. Q. Naevius,
                        however, did not leave for Sicily till four months had elapsed, as he was
                        detained by the task of investigating charges of poisoning. These were gone
                        into mostly in the boroughs and market towns, a more convenient arrangement
                        than transferring them to Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If we are
                        to believe Valerius Antias, he sentenced more than 2000 persons. L.
                        Postumius, to whom Tarentum had been assigned as his province, crushed the
                        wide-spread conspiracy of the herdsmen, and made a close and careful
                        examination into the remaining cases connected with the Bacchanalia.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Many who had been summoned to Rome had
                        not put in an appearance or had deserted their securities and were in hiding
                        in that part of Italy. Some he arrested and sent to Rome for the senate to
                        deal with, others he convicted and sentenced. They were all thrown into
                        prison by P. Cornelius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Further Spain matters were quiet as the
                        strength of the Lusitanians was broken in the last war. In Hither Spain A.
                        Terentius besieged and took the town of Corbio belonging to the Suessetani
                        and sold the prisoners. After this Hither Spain was also quiet through the
                        winter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The late praetors returned to
                        Rome, and the senate unanimously decreed a triumph to each of them.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> C. Calpurnius celebrated his triumph
                        over the Lusitanians and the Celtiberi; 83 golden crowns and 12,000 pounds
                        of silver were carried in the procession. A few days later L. Quinctius
                        Crispinus triumphed over the same nations and a similar amount of gold and
                        silver was carried in his procession. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        censors M. Porcius and L. Valerius, amidst many forebodings, revised the
                        roll of the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They removed seven
                        names, including that of a man of consular rank, L. Quinctius Flamininus,
                        distinguished for his high birth and the offices he had held. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> There is said to have been an old regulation that
                        the censors should commit to writing their reasons for excluding any from
                        the senate. There are extant some incriminating speeches which Cato
                        delivered against those whom he removed from the roll of the senate or the
                        register of the equites, but by far the most damaging is the one he made
                        against L. Quinctius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If Cato had
                        delivered this speech as accuser before the name was erased and not as
                        censor after he had erased it, not even his brother T. Quinctius, had he
                        been censor at the time, could have kept him on the roll. </p>
                    <p> Amongst other charges he brought up against him was the following. He had
                        persuaded by huge bribes a Carthaginian boy named Philip, an attractive and
                        notorious catamite, to accompany him into Gaul. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This boy in petulant wantonness used very often to
                        reproach the consul for having carried him away from Rome <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> just before the exhibition of gladiators, in order that
                        he might put a high price upon his compliance with the consul's passions.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It happened that while they were
                        banqueting and heated with wine a message was brought in that a Boian noble
                        had come as a refugee with his children and wanted to see the consul in
                        order to obtain from him personally a promise of protection. He was brought
                        into the tent and began to address the consul through an interpreter.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In the middle of his speech the
                        consul turned to his paramour and said: "As you have given up the show of
                        gladiators, would you like to see this Gaul die?" Hardly meaning what he
                        said, the boy assented. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The consul seized
                        a naked sword hanging above him and struck the Gaul, who was still speaking,
                        on the head. He turned to flee, imploring the protection of the Roman People
                        and of those who were present, when the consul ran his sword through him.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias, as though he had never
                        read Cato's speech and had only given credence to an unauthenticated; story,
                        relates a different incident, but resembling the above in its lust and
                        cruelty. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> According to him, a woman of
                        Placentia, a bad character, with whom the consul was madly in love, was
                        invited by him to a banquet. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here,
                        boasting of his exploits, he told the harlot, amongst other things, what a
                        stern inquisitor he had been, how many who had been condemned to death he
                        was keeping in chains till he executed them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> She was reclining on the same couch with him, and remarked that she had
                        never seen an execution and would dearly love to see one. Thereupon, to
                        indulge her, he ordered one of those unhappy wretches to be brought in and
                        then struck off his head. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whether the
                        incident took the form described in the censor's speech, or whether it was
                        as Valerius narrates it, in any case a cruel and brutal crime was
                        perpetrated. During a festive meal, when it is customary to pour libations
                        to the gods and wish all happiness to the guests, a human victim was
                        sacrificed and the table sprinkled with blood to delight the eyes of a
                        wanton harlot lying on a consul's breast! <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Cato closed his speech by saying that if Quinctius denied the charges he
                        gave him the option of providing security and letting the case go to trial,
                        but if he admitted them, did he suppose that any one would grieve over his
                        disgrace after he had amused himself, when maddened by wine and lust, by
                        shedding a man's blood at a banquet? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the revision of the register of the
                        equites L. Scipio Asiagenes was struck out. In fixing the assessments the
                        censorship was severe and harsh on all classes. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Orders were issued that an account should be taken on
                        oath of all female dress, ornaments and carriages which were valued at more
                        than 15,000 ases, and that they should be assessed at ten times their value.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Similarly, slaves less than twenty
                        years old who had been sold since the last lustrum for 10,000 ases or more
                        were to be assessed at ten times that amount, and on all these assessments a
                        tax was imposed of one-third per cent. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        censors cut off from the public aqueducts all supplies of water for private
                        houses or land, and wherever private owners had built up against public
                        buildings or on public ground, they demolished these structures within
                        thirty days. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They next made contracts for
                        lining the reservoirs with stone and, where it was necessary, cleaning out
                        the sewers, money having been set apart for the purpose, and also for the
                        construction of sewers in the Aventine quarter and in other places where as
                        yet there were none. Flaccus constructed a raised causeway at the Fountain
                        of Neptune to serve as a public road and also a road along the Formian Hill.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Cato purchased for the State two
                        auction halls in the Lautumiae, the Maenium and the Titium, as well as four
                        shops, and on the site he built a basilica, known afterwards as the Porcian.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They farmed the taxes to the highest
                        bidders, and let out the contracts to the lowest tenders. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The senate, yielding to the prayers and lamentations of
                        the tax-farmers, annulled these arrangements and ordered fresh terms to be
                        made. The censors gave public notice that those who had treated the former
                        contracts with contempt should not be allowed to make fresh bids. They
                        signed fresh contracts for everything on slightly easier terms. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> This censorship was noteworthy for the feuds and
                        quarrels it gave rise to, and for which Cato through his severity was held
                        responsible; feuds which made his life a stormy one to the end. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Two colonies were founded this year, one at
                        Potentia in the Picene district, the other at Pisaurum in the land of the
                        Gauls. Six jugera were allotted to each colonist; the commissioners who
                        supervised the settlement were Q. Fabius Labeo, M. Fulvius Flaccus and Q.
                        Fulvius Nobilior. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consuls for this
                        year did nothing worth recording. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls elected for the next year were
                        M. Claudius Marcellus and Q. Fabius Labienus. On the day they entered upon
                        office-March 15-they brought before the senate the question of their
                        provinces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Liguria was assigned to both
                        consuls with the armies which their predecessors had had. When the new
                        praetors balloted for their provinces, the two Spains were reserved for the
                        praetors of the year before who retained their armies. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> C. Valerius, the Flamen, who had been an unsuccessful
                        candidate the year before, was in any case to have one of the two
                        jurisdictions in Rome; he drew the alien jurisdiction. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The other provinces went as follows: the civic
                        jurisdiction to Sisenna Cornelius, Sicily to Sp. Postumius, Apulia to L.
                        Pupius, Gaul to L. Julius, Sardinia to Cnaeus Sicinius. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> L. Julius was required to hasten his departure.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The transalpine Gauls, who, as stated
                        above, had descended into Italy by a hitherto unknown mountain road, were
                        building a town in the territory which now belongs to Aquileia. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The praetor received instructions to prevent
                        their doing this, without war if he could; if they had to be restrained by
                        force of arms he was to inform the consuls, and one of them was to lead the
                        legions against the Gauls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the end of
                        the preceding year there was an election of an augur to fill the place of
                        Cnaeus Cornelius Lentulus who had died. Sp. Postumius Albinus was elected.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the commencement of this year P.
                        Licinius Crassus, the Pontifex Maximus, died. M. Sempronius Tuditanus was
                        co-opted as pontiff to fill the vacancy in the college, and C. Servilius
                        Geminus was elected Pontifex Maximus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On
                        the day of the funeral of P. Licinius a public distribution of meat was
                        made, and a hundred and twenty gladiators fought in the funeral games which
                        lasted for three days and after the games a public feast. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The couches had been spread all over the Forum when a
                        violent storm of wind and rain burst and compelled most people to put up
                        shelter tents there. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the sky clearing,
                        everywhere soon after they were removed, and it was commonly said that the
                        people had fulfilled a prediction which the prophets of fate had made that
                        it was necessary for tents to be set up in the Forum. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> No sooner were they relieved from their religious fears
                        than another portent followed. There was a rain of blood for two days and
                        the Keepers of the Sacred Books ordered special intercessions to be made to
                        expiate the portent. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before the consuls
                        left for their provinces they introduced various overseas deputations to the
                        senate. Never before had there been so many men from that part of the world
                        assembled in Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as it became
                        generally known amongst the tribes inhabiting Macedonia that the complaints
                        about Philip were not falling on deaf ears and that many people had found it
                        quite <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> worth their while to bring forward
                        complaints, they flocked to Rome, cities, tribes, even individual
                        complainants, each with their own grievance-for the hand of their neighbour,
                        Philip, was heavy on them all-in the hope of obtaining redress for their
                        wrongs or comfort under their sufferings. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Eumenes, too, sent his brother Athenaeus with a deputation to complain that
                        the garrisons had not been withdrawn from Thrace, and that Philip had
                        assisted Prusias in his war with Eumenes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Demetrius, who was at the time quite a
                        young man, had to answer all the charges. It was by no means an easy matter
                        for him to retain in his memory either the details of the allegations or the
                        proper reply to be made to them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were
                        not only very numerous, but most of them were very trivial, such as disputes
                        about boundaries, the carrying off of cattle and men, the capricious
                        administration of justice, judges corrupted by bribes or intimidated by
                        threats of violence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the senate found
                        that Demetrius could not explain things clearly and that they could get no
                        definite information from him and saw that the youth was embarrassed and at
                        a loss what to say, they ordered the question to be put to him whether he
                        had received from his father any memorandum dealing with these matters. On
                        his stating that he had received one, they thought by far the wisest course
                        would be to have the king's own replies to each point raised. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> They at once called for the book and allowed him
                        to quote from it. It contained concise explanations under each head.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some of the things he had done were,
                        he said, in compliance with the dictates of the commissioners; with regard
                        to other of his acts, it was not his fault but that of his accusers that he
                        had failed to comply. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Interspersed
                        throughout the memorandum were protests against the partiality shown in the
                        rulings of the commissioners and the unfair way in which the discussion had
                        been carried on before Caecilius, and also the undeserved and unworthy
                        insults heaped upon him from all sides. The senate took these as marks of
                        irritation on his part; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> however, as the
                        young prince apologised for some things, and gave an undertaking that for
                        the future all would be done as the senate wished, it was decided that the
                        following reply should be given: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "Nothing
                        which his father had done was more correct or more in accordance with the
                        senate's wishes than his willingness, whatever his conduct had been, to send
                        his son Demetrius to give satisfaction to Rome. Much of the past the senate
                        could close their eyes to and forget and put up with, and <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> they believed that they could trust Demetrius, for
                        though they returned him to his father in bodily presence, they had his mind
                        and feelings with them still as a <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                        hostage, and they knew that so far as was consistent with his affection for
                        his father he was a friend to the People of Rome. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Out of regard for him they would send a commission to
                        Macedonia, so that whatever had not been done which ought to have been done
                        it might even yet be carried out without any penalty for past omissions."
                        They also wished Philip to understand that he was indebted to his son
                        Demetrius for the complete restoration of his good relations with Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This, which was done to enhance the
                        dignity of the young prince, immediately aroused jealousy against him and
                        finally proved to be his ruin. The Lacedaemonians were introduced next.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Many questions, quite insignificant,
                        were raised; there were some, however, of great importance, for instance,
                        whether those whom the Achaeans had condemned should be restored, whether
                        those whom they had put to death <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> were
                        justly or unjustly slain, and also whether the Lacedaemonians should remain
                        in the Achaean League, or whether, as had previously been the case, that
                        city alone out of the whole of the Peloponnese should keep its own separate
                        laws. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was decided that the exiles
                        should be restored and the sentences passed on them annulled, and that
                        Lacedaemon should remain in the Achaean League. This decree was to be
                        committed to writing and signed by the Lacedaemonians and Achaeans.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Q. Marcius was sent as special
                        commissioner to Macedonia, he was also instructed to examine the state of
                        affairs in the Peloponnese. The unrest left by the old dissensions still
                        prevailed there and Messene had seceded from the Achaean League. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> If I were to go into the origin and progress of
                        this war I should be forgetting my resolution not to touch on foreign
                        affairs except so far as they are connected with those of Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was one incident worth recording.
                        Though the Achaeans proved superior in the war, their captain-general
                        Philopoemen was taken prisoner. He was on his way to occupy Corone, against
                        which place the enemy were advancing, and whilst he was traversing a valley
                        over difficult and broken ground with a small cavalry escort, he was
                        surprised by the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It is said that
                        with the help of the Thracians and Cretans he could have effected his
                        escape, but honour forbade him to desert his cavalry, men of good family
                        whom he had himself selected. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whilst he
                        was closing up his rear to meet the enemy's onset, and so give his cavalry a
                        chance of escaping through the narrow pass, his horse fell, and what with
                        his own fall and the weight of the horse rolling over him, he was very
                        nearly killed on the spot. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He was now
                        seventy years old and his strength was greatly impaired by a long illness
                        from which he was just recovering. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        enemy, closing round him as he lay, made him their prisoner. As soon as he
                        was recognised, the enemy, out of personal regard for him and recalling his
                        great services, treated him just as if he had been their own general, lifted
                        him up carefully, gave him restoratives, and carried him out of <milestone
                            n="6??" unit="section"/> the entangled ravine into the high road, hardly
                        believing the good fortune which had befallen them. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Some of them at once dispatched messengers to Messene
                        to announce that the war was over, and Philopoemen was being brought in as a
                        prisoner. The affair seemed at first so incredible that the messenger was
                        regarded as not only false but out of his senses. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As one after another arrived, all bringing the same
                        story, it was at last believed, and before they really knew that he was
                        anywhere near the city, the whole population, citizens and slaves, even boys
                        and women, poured out to see him. The crowd had blocked the gate, it looked
                        as though each must have the evidence of his own eyes before he could
                        believe that such a great event had really happened. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Those who were bringing Philopoemen in had the greatest
                        difficulty in forcing an entrance into the city through the crowd. An
                        equally dense crowd blocked the rest of the route and, as the great majority
                        were prevented <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> from seeing, they rushed
                        to the theatre which was near the road and all with one voice demanded that
                        he should be brought where the people could see him. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The magistrates and principal citizens were afraid that
                        the compassion evoked by the sight of so great a man might lead to a
                        disturbance, for whilst some would contrast his former greatness with his
                        present position, others would be moved by the memory of all he had done for
                        them. They placed him where he could be seen at a distance, and then
                        hurriedly removed him from men's eyes. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Dinocrates, the governor, gave out that there were certain questions
                        connected with the conduct of the war which the magistrates wished to put to
                        him. He was then led away to the senate house and on the assembling of the
                        senate they commenced their deliberations. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Evening was now coming on, and they were
                        not only unable to get through their other business but they could not even
                        agree as to where he could be safely kept during the night. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> They were dazed by the greatness of the man and the
                        splendour of his career, and they did not dare to take him to their own
                        homes or trust his custody to any single individual. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Somebody reminded them of the public treasury which was
                        an underground chamber, walled with hewn stone. Here he was let down in
                        chains and the huge stone with which it was covered was lowered with
                        pulleys. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Having thus made up their minds
                        that his safe-keeping ought to be entrusted to a place rather than to any
                        man, they waited for the day. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the
                        morrow the whole population, bearing in mind his former services to their
                        city, considered that he ought to be spared and that through his means they
                        must look for the remedy for their present troubles. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The authors of the secession, who were in control of
                        the government, held a secret meeting and unanimously decided that he must
                        be put to death, but they were not agreed whether they should act at once or
                        not. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The party who were eager for his
                        death carried the day, and a man was sent to him with the poison. It is said
                        that he took the bowl and merely asked whether Lycortas was safe and whether
                        the cavalry had escaped. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When he was
                        assured that they were safe he said, "It is well," and without the slightest
                        sign of fear drained the bowl and shortly afterwards expired. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The authors of this cruelty did not congratulate
                        themselves on his death for long. Messene was captured in the war, and on
                        the demand of the Achaeans the criminals were surrendered. The remains of
                        Philopoemen were restored to them and the whole of the Achaean council were
                        present at his funeral. After heaping upon him every human honour they did
                        not shrink from according to him divine honours. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Greek and Latin historians pay this man so high a
                        tribute that some of them have placed on record as a notable feature of this
                        year that three illustrious generals died during its course-Philopoemen,
                        Hannibal and Lucius Scipio. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To such an
                        equality with the greatest generals of the most powerful nations in the
                        world have they raised him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Prusias had for some time fallen under
                        suspicion in Rome, partly owing to his having sheltered Hannibal after the
                        flight of Antiochus and partly because he had started a war with Eumenes.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> T. Quinctius Flamininus was
                        accordingly sent on a special mission to him. He charged Prusias, amongst
                        other things, with admitting to his court the man who of all men living was
                        the most deadly foe to the People of Rome, who had instigated first his own
                        countrymen and then, when their power was broken, King Antiochus to levy war
                        on Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Either owing to the menacing
                        language of Flamininus or because he wished to ingratiate himself with
                        Flamininus and the Romans, he formed the design of either putting Hannibal
                        to death or delivering him up to them. In any case, immediately after his
                        first interview with Flamininus he sent soldiers to guard the house in which
                        Hannibal was living. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal had always
                        looked forward to such a fate as this; he fully realised the implacable
                        hatred which the Romans felt towards him, and he put no trust whatever in
                        the good faith of monarchs. He had already had experience of Prusias'
                        fickleness of temper and he had dreaded the arrival of Flamininus as certain
                        to prove fatal to himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In face of the
                        dangers confronting him on all sides he tried to keep open some one avenue
                        of escape. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With this view he had
                        constructed seven exits from his house, some of them concealed, so that they
                        might not be blocked by the guard. But the tyranny of kings leaves nothing
                        hidden which they want to explore. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        guards surrounded the house so closely that no one could slip out of it.
                        When Hannibal was informed that the king's soldiers were in the vestibule,
                        he tried to escape through a postern gate which afforded the most secret
                        means of exit. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He found that this too was
                        closely watched and that guards were posted all round the place. Finally he
                        called for the poison which he had long kept in readiness for such an
                        emergency. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "Let us," he said, "relieve the
                        Romans from the anxiety they have so long experienced, since they think it
                        tries their patience too much to wait for an old man's death. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The victory which Flamininus will win over a
                        defenceless fugitive will be neither great nor memorable; this day will show
                        how vastly the moral of the Roman People has changed. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Their fathers warned Pyrrhus, when he had an army in
                        Italy, to beware of poison, and now they have sent a man of consular rank to
                        persuade Prusias to murder his guest." <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Then, invoking curses on Prusias and his realm and appealing to the gods who
                        guard the rights of hospitality to punish his broken faith, he drained the
                        cup. Such was the close of Hannibal's life. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="52" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> According to Polybius and Rutilius this
                        was the year in which Scipio died. I do not agree with either of these
                        writers, nor with Valerius; I find that during the censorship of M. Porcius
                        and L. Valerius, Valerius was himself chosen as leader of the senate, though
                        Africanus had held that position through the two <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> previous censorships, and unless we are to assume that
                        he was removed from the senatorial roll-and there is no record of any such
                        stigma being affixed to his name-no other leader of the senate would have
                        been chosen. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias is proved to
                        be wrong by the following considerations. There was a tribune of the plebs,
                        M. Naevius, against whom Scipio delivered a speech which is still extant.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From the lists of the magistrates it
                        appears that this Naevius was tribune of the plebs during the consulship of
                        P. Claudius and L. Porcius, but actually entered upon office on December 10,
                        when Appius Claudius and M. Sempronius were the consuls. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Three months elapsed from that date to March I5, when
                        P. Claudius and L. Porcius assumed office. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Thus it appears that Scipio was alive when Naevius was tribune and might
                        have been impeached by him, but dead before L. Valerius and M. Porcius were
                        censors. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We may trace a correspondence in
                        the death of these three men, who were each the most illustrious of his
                        nation, for not only did they die about the same time, but not one of the
                        three ended his life in a way worthy of his splendid career. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> None of them died on his native soil or was
                        buried there. Hannibal and Philopoemen were carried off by poison; Hannibal
                        was an exile, and betrayed by his host, Philopoemen was a captive and died
                        in prison and in chains. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Though Scipio had
                        not been banished or condemned to death, still, as he did not appear on the
                        day fixed for his trial, though duly cited, he passed upon himself a
                        sentence of banishment, not only for life but even after he was dead. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="53" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the incidents in the Peloponnese
                        from which I have made a digression, Demetrius and his legation returned to
                        Macedonia. There was much divergence of view as to the results of their
                        embassy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The bulk of the Macedonian
                        people, appalled at the imminent prospect of a war with Rome, were
                        enthusiastic supporters of Demetrius. They looked upon him as the author of
                        peace and regarded his succession to the throne after his father's death as
                        a certainty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Although younger than
                        Perseus, he was a legitimate son, the other was the son of a concubine.
                        People said that Perseus, the offspring of a prostitute, had no note or mark
                        of any particular father, whereas Demetrius showed a remarkable likeness to
                        his father; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> moreover, Perseus was no
                        favourite with the Romans and they would place Demetrius on his father's
                        throne. Such was the common talk. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Perseus
                        felt himself superior to his brother in everything else, but he was haunted
                        by the thought that his age alone would count but little in his favour.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Philip himself, too, whilst feeling
                        doubtful whether it would be in his power to decide whom he should leave as
                        heir to the throne, considered that his younger son was assuming more
                        authority than he wished him to possess. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        He was annoyed at the way in which the Macedonians resorted to Demetrius and
                        he looked upon the existence of a second royal court as an indignity to
                        himself. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The young prince had certainly
                        come home with a much higher sense of his own importance, presuming as he
                        did upon the compliments paid him by the senate and the concessions they had
                        made to him after refusing them to his father. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Every allusion he made to the Romans raised his
                        prestige amongst the Macedonians and evoked a corresponding amount of
                        jealousy and ill-will in his father and brother. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> This was particularly the case when the fresh
                        commissioners arrived from Rome and Philip was compelled to evacuate Thrace
                        and withdraw his garrisons and carry out the other measures demanded by the
                        previous commissioners and the fresh orders of the senate. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> All these things were a source of grief and bitterness
                        to him, all the more so because he saw him associating with the Romans much
                        more frequently than with himself. Still he acted in obedience to the orders
                        of Rome that there might be no pretext for commencing hostilities.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thinking to divert any suspicions the
                        Romans might entertain as to his designs, he led his army into the interior
                        of Thrace, against the Odrysae, the Dentheleti and the Bessi. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> He took the city of Philippopolis which had been
                        deserted by the inhabitants, who with their families had taken refuge in the
                        nearest mountains. After ravaging the fields of the barbarians who lived in
                        the lowlands, he accepted their surrender. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                        /> Leaving a garrison in Philippopolis which was shortly afterwards expelled
                        by the Odrysae, he began to build a town in Deuriopus, a district in
                        Paeonia, near the river Erigonus which, rising in Illyria, flows through
                        Paeonia into the Axius, not far from the ancient city of Stobae. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> He ordered the new city to be called Perseis in
                        honour of his eldest son. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="54" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these events in Macedonia the
                        consuls left for their provinces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Marcellus sent a message to L. Porcius, the proconsul, asking him to take
                        his legions to the town which the Gauls had lately built. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> On the consul's arrival the Gauls surrendered. There
                        were 12,000 under arms, most of them had arms which they had taken by force
                        from the peasants. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These were taken from
                        them as well as what they had carried off from the fields or brought with
                        them. They resented this strongly and sent envoys to Rome to complain. C.
                        Valerius the praetor introduced them to the senate. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They explained how, owing to over-population, want of
                        land and general destitution, they had been compelled to seek a home across
                        the Alps. Where they saw the country uninhabited and uncultivated there they
                        had settled, without doing injury to any one. They had even begun to build a
                        town, a clear proof that they were not going to attack either town or
                        village. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> M. Claudius had recently sent a
                        message to them that if they did not surrender he would make war upon them.
                        As they preferred a secure if not a very honourable peace to the
                        uncertainties of war, they had placed themselves under the protection,
                        before they had to submit to the power, of Rome. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> A few days afterwards they were ordered to evacuate
                        their city and territory, and they intended to depart quietly and settle in
                        what part of the world they could. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Next,
                        their arms were taken from them, and at last all that they possessed, their
                        goods and their cattle. They implored the senate and the People of Rome not
                        to treat those who had surrendered without striking a blow with greater
                        severity than they treated active enemies. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To these pleas the senate ordered the
                        following reply to be given: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They had
                        acted wrongfully in coming into Italy and attempting to build a town on
                        ground that was not their own without the permission of any Roman magistrate
                        who was over that province. On the other hand, it was not the pleasure of
                        the senate that after they had surrendered they should be despoiled of their
                        goods and possessions. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The senate would
                        send back with them commissioners to the consul, who on their returning
                        whence they had come would order all that belonged to them to be restored.
                        The commissioners would also cross the Alps and warn the Gaulish communities
                        to keep their population at home. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        Alps lay between as an almost impassable frontier line; those who were the
                        first to make them easy of transit would certainly not be the better for it.
                        The commissioners who were sent were L. Furius Purpurio, Q. Minucius and L.
                        Manlius Acidinus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After everything which
                        they had any right to was restored to them, the Gauls departed from Italy.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="55" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The transalpine tribes gave a satisfactory
                        reply to the commissioners. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The older men
                        amongst them blamed the excessive leniency of the Romans for having sent
                        away, unpunished, men who without any authority from their tribe had set out
                        to occupy territory belonging to the Roman government, and had attempted to
                        build a town on land that did not belong to them. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They ought to have paid heavily for their audacity. The
                        indulgence shown them in the restoration of their property might, they
                        feared, invite others to similar ventures. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The hospitality which they showed towards the commissioners was so generous
                        that they loaded them with presents. After the Gauls had been cleared out of
                        his province, M. Claudius began to lay his plans for a Histrian war. He
                        wrote to the senate for permission to lead his legions into Histria and the
                        senate sanctioned his doing so. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They were
                        at the time discussing the question of sending colonists to Aquileia, and
                        the question was whether they should make it a Latin colony or send Roman
                        citizens. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was finally decided that the
                        colony should consist of Latin settlers. The commissioners for
                        superintending the settlement were P. Scipio Nasica, C. Flaminius and L.
                        Manlius Acidinus. Mutina and Parma were also colonised this year by Roman
                        citizens. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Two thousand men were settled in
                        each colony on land which had recently belonged to the Boii, formerly to the
                        Tuscans. Those at Parma received eight jugera each, those at Mutina, five.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The allocation of the land was carried
                        out by M. Aemilius Lepidus, T. Aebutius Carus and L. Quinctius Crispinus.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Saturnia, also, a colony of Roman
                        citizens, was founded under the supervision of Q. Fabius Labeo, C. Afranius
                        Stellio and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus. Ten jugera were assigned to each
                        colonist. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="56" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the year the proconsul A. Terentius
                        fought some successful actions with the Celtiberi not far from the Ebro in
                        the Ausetanian country, and stormed several places which they had fortified
                        there. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Further Spain was quiet during the
                        year owing to the long illness of P. Sempronius, and the Lusitanians,
                        receiving no provocation, remained, fortunately, quiet. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Nor did Q. Fabius do anything worth mentioning in
                        Liguria. M. Marcellus was recalled from Histria and his army disbanded. He
                        returned to Rome to conduct the elections. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The new consuls were Cnaeus Baebius Tamphilus and L. Aemilius Paulus. The
                        latter had been curule aedile with M. Aemilius Lepidus who five years before
                        had won his consulship after two previous defeats. The new praetors were Q.
                        Fulvius Flaccus, M. Valerius Laevinus, P. Manlius for the second time, M.
                        Ogulnius Gallus, L. Caecilius Denter, and C. Terentius Istra. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> At the end of the year there were intercessions
                        owing to portents. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was firmly believed
                        that a rain of blood had fallen for two days in the temple precinct of
                        Concord, and it was reported that not far from Sicily a new island had been
                        thrown up by the sea. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias is
                        our authority for stating that Hannibal died this year, and that in addition
                        to T. Quinctius Flamininus, whose name is well known in connection with that
                        incident, L. Scipio Asiaticus and P. Scipio Nasica were sent to Prusias on
                        that occasion. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
