<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 5-7 - 6</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books V, VI and VII With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1924: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.195"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="book">
                <head>Book VI.</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THE history of the Romans from the founding
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 389</note> of
                    the City of Rome to the capture of the same —at first under kings and afterwards
                    under consuls and dictators, decemvirs and consular tribunes —their <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> foreign wars and their domestic dissensions, I have
                    set forth in five books, dealing with matters which are obscure not only by
                    reason of their great antiquity —like far-off objects which can hardly be
                    descried —but also because in those days there was but slightly and scanty use
                    of writing, the sole trustworthy guardian of the memory of past events, and
                    because even such records as existed in the commentaries of the pontiffs and in
                    other public and private documents, nearly all perished in the conflagration of
                    the City. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From this point onwards a clearer
                    and more definite account shall be given of the City's civil and military
                    history, when, beginning for a second time, it sprang up, as it were from the
                    old roots, with a more luxuriant and fruitful growth. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now it stood at first by leaning on the same
                    support by which it had raised itself up, that is on Marcus Furius, its foremost
                    citizen; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> neither would men suffer him to
                    resign the dictatorship till the completion of the year. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy means the year (ending June 30th) for which the
                        consular tribunes were elected whom Camillus, as dictator, superseded. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That elections for the ensuing year should be
                    held by the tribunes, in whose magistracy the City had been captured, was
                    considered inadvisable, and the state reverted to an <pb n="p.197"/>
                    interregnum. While the citizens were engrossed in <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 389</note> unremitting toil and labour
                    to restore the City, Quintus Fabius had no sooner quitted his magistracy than he
                    was indicted by Gnaeus Marcius, a tribune of the plebs, on the ground of his
                    having fought in violation of the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> law of
                    nations against the Gauls, to whom he had been sent as an envoy —a trial which
                    he escaped by a death so opportune that the majority believed it voluntary.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The interregnum began: Publius Cornelius
                    Scipio was interrex; and after him Marcus Furius Camillus, who effected the
                    election, as tribunes of the soldiers with consular authority, of Lucius
                    Valerius Publicola (for the second time) Lucius Verginius, Publius Cornelius,
                    Aulus Manlius, Lucius Aemilius, and Lucius Postumius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having, immediately <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">On July 6th at the earliest.</note> after the
                    interregnum, entered upon their term, they consulted the senate before
                    everything else on questions of religious observance. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Among the first decrees they passed was one for searching
                    out the treaties and laws — to wit, the twelve tables and certain laws of the
                    kings, —so far as they could be discovered. Some of these were made accessible
                    even to the common people, but such as dealt with sacred rites were kept private
                    by the pontiffs, chiefly that they might hold the minds of the populace in
                    subjection through religious fear. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then they
                    proceeded to deliberate about days of evil omen. The 18th of July was notorious
                    for a double misfortune, since it was on that day that the Fabii were massacred
                    at the Cremera and that subsequently the rout at the Allia occurred, which
                    resulted in the destruction of the City. From the latter disaster they named it
                    the Day of the Allia, and forbade any public or <pb n="p.199"/> private business
                    to be done that day. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some think, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 389</note> because
                    Sulpicius had, on the day after the Ides of July, made an unacceptable
                    sacrifice, and, without having gained the divine approval, had two days later
                    exposed the Roman army to the enemy, that therefore religious rites were omitted
                    also on the days after the several Ides; and that afterwards it became
                    traditional that the morrow after Kalends and Nones should likewise be avoided,
                    from the same scruple. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the Romans were not left long to the
                    peaceful consideration of plans for raising their state after its grievous fall.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the one hand the Volsci, their ancient
                    foes, had armed for the purpose of extinguishing the Roman name: on the other,
                    merchants brought word from Etruria that the leading men of all her nations had
                    met at the shrine of Voltumna and conspired to make war. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> A fresh alarm, too, was occasioned by the revolt of the
                    Latins and the Hernici, who since the battle fought at Lake Regillus had
                    continued for close upon a hundred years, with unquestioned loyalty, in the
                    friendship of the Roman People. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And so, when
                    such dangers threatened them on every side, and it was clear to all that the
                    name of Rome was not only held in hatred by her enemies, but even in contempt by
                    her allies, it was <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> resolved that the
                    republic should be defended under the same auspices under which it had been
                    redeemed and that Marcus Furius Camillus should be named dictator. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Being appointed dictator he designated Gaius
                    Servilius Ahala master of the horse, and after proclaiming a cessation of legal
                    business, held a levy of the juniors, yet without excluding such of the older
                    men as still <pb n="p.201"/> possessed any vigour, to whom also he administered
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 389</note> the
                    oath and mustered them into centuries. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having enrolled the army and equipped it, he
                    divided it into three parts. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> One division he
                    stationed in the Veientine district to confront Etruria; a second he ordered to
                    encamp before the City. These divisions were put under the command of military
                    tribunes, Aulus Manlius for the home troops, Lucius Aemilius for those which
                    were being dispatched against the Etruscans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The third division he led himself against the Volsci, and not far from Lanuvium
                    — <hi rend="italics">ad Mecium</hi> the place is called —advanced to attack
                    their camp. The enemy had gone to war from a feeling of contempt for the Romans,
                    believing that their fighting strength had been nearly wiped out by the Gauls,
                    but merely on hearing that Camillus was their general, they were so terrified
                    that they protected themselves with a rampart and <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> the rampart with a barricade of logs, that the Romans might
                    nowhere be able to penetrate to their defences. On perceiving this, Camillus
                    ordered his men to throw fire on the barrier. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    It so happened that there was a high wind blowing towards the enemy, which not
                    only caused the blaze to open a path, but what with the flames making towards
                    the camp, and the heat and smoke and the crackling of the green wood, so alarmed
                    the enemy, that the Roman soldiers experienced less difficulty in scaling the
                    fortifications of the Volscian camp than they had met with in crossing the burnt
                    barricade. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Having routed and slain his
                    enemies and taken their camp by assault, the dictator gave the booty to his
                    soldiers, an act which, coming unexpectedly from a commander who <pb n="p.203"/>
                    was by no means open-handed, was all the more <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 389</note> acceptable to the men.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then after pursuing the fugitives and
                    laying waste all the Volscian countryside, he forced the Volsci to surrender at
                    last, after seventy years of war. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Writing of Tarquinius Superbus, Livy says (I. liii. 2) that he began a war
                        with the Volsci which was to last more than two hundred years after his
                        time. It is not known where he could have found the seventy years tradition. </note>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The victor, leaving the Volsci, crossed over
                    to the Aequi, who were themselves making preparations for war; their army he
                    surprised at Bolae, and carried not only their camp but their city, too, at the
                    first assault. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While affairs were thus prosperous in that
                    region where Camillus commanded for Rome, in another direction a great danger
                    threatened. Well-nigh the whole of Etruria was in arms and was laying siege to
                    Sutrium, an ally of the Roman People. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Envoys
                    of the Sutrines had appeared before the senate to beg for assistance in their
                    distress, and had obtained a decree that the dictator should march to the aid of
                    their people at the earliest opportunity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But
                    the plight of the besieged would not admit of their waiting till this hope was
                    realized; and the population of the little town, exhausted with the labour,
                    guard-mounting, and wounds, which fell always to the lot of the same men, had
                    come to terms, and having surrendered their city to the enemy, were leaving
                    their homes in a sad procession, unarmed and with but a single garment each,
                    when, as it chanced, Camillus appeared on the scene with a Roman army.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The disconsolate rabble cast themselves at
                    his feet, while their leading men addressed him with words drawn from them by
                    the direst necessity and accompanied by the wailing of the women and children,
                    who were being dragged along as the companions of their exile. He bade the
                    Sutrines spare their lamentations; the Etruscans <pb n="p.205"/> were those to
                    whom he was bringing grief and tears. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 389</note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then gave orders that the packs should be
                    set down; that the Sutrines should stop there, with a small guard which he left
                    them; and that his soldiers should take their weapons and follow him. So, with
                    his army in light marching order, he set out for Sutrium, where he was not
                    surprised to find everything at loose ends, as a consequence —common enough —of
                    their success; there was no outpost before the walls; the gates were open; and
                    the victors had dispersed and were fetching the booty out of the houses of their
                    enemies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the second time, therefore, on
                    the same day, Sutrium was captured. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    victorious Etruscans were everywhere slaughtered by the new enemy, and had no
                    time given them to assemble and unite their forces or to arm. As they tried,
                    every man for himself, to reach the gates, if by chance they might somehow
                    escape out into the fields, they found them shut, for so the general had ordered
                    in the beginning. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After that some caught up
                    their swords; others, whom the sudden attack had found already armed, tried to
                    call their fellows together for a battle, and this would have been hotly fought,
                    because of the enemy's despair, had not heralds been dispatched through the town
                    who made proclamation that arms should be laid down and the unarmed receive
                    quarter, and that none should suffer any violence except those that carried
                    weapons. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then even such as had in their
                    extremity resolved to fight to the death, now that hope of life was held out to
                    them, began everywhere to throw down their swords, and to go unarmed —for
                    fortune had made this the safer way —to meet their enemies. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The <pb n="p.207"/> great throng was divided among
                    companies of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        389</note> guards; and before night the town was restored to the Sutrines,
                    unharmed and without scathe of war, because it had not been carried by assault,
                    but had been surrendered upon terms. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Camillus returned to the City and triumphed
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 388</note> for
                    his victories in three simultaneous wars. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By
                    far the greatest number of the captives led before his chariot were Etruscans;
                    they were sold under the spear, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A sign
                        that booty was to be sold at auction.</note> and fetched so large a sum that
                    after the matrons had been repaid for their gold, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See v. 1. 6-7.</note> the surplus sufficed to make three
                    golden bowls, which were inscribed, as is well known, with <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> the name of Camillus, and kept, until the burning of the
                    Capitol, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> July 6th, <date when="-0083"
                            >83 B.C.</date> The restoration of the temple was completed <date
                            when="-0069">69 B.C.</date>
                    </note> in the chapel of Jupiter, at Juno's feet. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This year were received into the state such of
                    the Veientes, Capenates, and Faliscans as had come over to the Romans in the
                    course of these wars, and lands were allotted to these new citizens. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> There were also recalled from Veii to the City, by
                    senatorial decree, those who being too indolent to build in Rome had taken
                    possession of empty houses in Veii and had gone there to live. They had indeed
                    murmured at first, and had flouted the order; but the designation of a day and
                    the threat of a capital penalty for failure to return to Rome reduced them from
                    a defiant group to obedient individuals, as each became alarmed for himself.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Rome was now growing in numbers, and in
                    every part at once new buildings were springing up; the state contributed
                    towards the costs, and the aediles forwarded the work as though it had been
                    public business, while the citizens themselves, incited by their desire to be
                        <pb n="p.209"/> using it, hurried their building to a conclusion; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 388</note> and within
                    the year there was a new City standing. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the close of the year an election of
                    military tribunes with consular powers was held. Those chosen were Titus
                    Quinctius Cincinnatus, Quintus Servilius Fidenas (for the fifth time), Lucius
                    Julius Iulus, Lucius Aquilius Corvus, Lucius Lucretius Tricipitinus, and Servius
                    Sulpicius Rufus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These men led one army
                    against the Aequi, not to war —for they confessed themselves vanquished —but
                    from hatred, in order to waste, their territories and leave them with no
                    strength to make new trouble; with another they invaded the district of
                    Tarquinii, where they captured by assault the Etruscan towns Cortuosa and
                    Contenebra. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At Cortuosa there was no struggle:
                    in a surprise attack they carried the place at the first shout and onset, and
                    then sacked and burned it. Contenebra held out for a few days, but the
                    continuous fighting, without respite either day or night, overcame them.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Roman army had been divided into six
                    corps, of which each in its turn went into battle for six hours; while the
                    townsmen were so few that the same men were exposed to an attack that was
                    constantly renewed, until at last they gave way and afforded the Romans an
                    opening to enter the City. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The tribunes
                    decided that the booty should go to the state, but were less prompt in issuing
                    orders than in planning; and, while they procrastinated, it was already in the
                    hands of the soldiers and could not be taken away without offending them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That same year, that the City might not grow
                    in private buildings only, the Capitol was provided with a substructure of hewn
                    stone, a work which even <pb n="p.211"/> amidst the present splendours of the
                    City is deserving <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        388</note> of remark. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And now, while the citizens were taken up
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 387</note> with
                    building, the tribunes of the plebs were trying to attract crowds to their
                    meetings by proposals for agrarian laws. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                    held out hopes of the Pomptine district, of which the Romans had then for the
                    first time —since the defeat inflicted on the Volsci by Camillus —acquired
                    undisputed control. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes brought the
                    charge that this district was worse plagued by the nobility than it had been by
                    the Volsci; for the latter, as long as they were strong enough and had arms, had
                    done no more than make incursions into it; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but
                    the nobles were taking violent possession of the public domain, and unless it
                    should be parcelled out before they seized it all, there would be no room there
                    for the commons. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They made no great impression
                    on the plebs, who were seldom in the Forum, because they were so intent on
                    building, and, exhausted with the expense thereby incurred, had no thought of
                    land, which they lacked the means of stocking. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The citizens were much given to religious
                    fears, and at that time, owing to the recent calamity, even the leaders were a
                    prey to superstition; so, in order that new auspices might be had, the state
                    went into an interregnum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The office of
                    interrex was successively held by Marcus Manlius Capitolinus, Servius Sulpicius
                    Camerinus, and Lucius Valerius Potitus. Finally, the last-named held an election
                    of military tribunes and announced that the choice had fallen on Lucius
                    Papirius, Gaius Cornelius, Gaius Sergius, Lucius Aemilius (for the second time),
                    Lucius <pb n="p.213"/> Menenius and Lucius Valerius Publicola (for the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 387</note> third time).
                    These men took office at the conclusion of the interregnum. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In that year the temple of Mars vowed in the
                    Gallic war was dedicated by Titus Quinctius, duumvir for sacrifices. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">duumviri</hi>
                        had charge of the Sibylline Books, which they were directed to consult in
                        times of stress to ascertain what expiation Heaven demanded for the sins of
                        the people Their number was raised to ten in <date when="-0367">367
                            B.C.</date> and later (in <date when="-0051">51 B.C.</date> ) to
                        fifteen. </note> Four additional tribes were formed out of the new citizens,
                    the Stellatina, Tromentina, Sabatina, and Arniensis; these filled up the number
                    of tribes to twenty-five. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The question of the Pomptine territory was
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 386</note>
                    brought up by Lucius Sicinius, a tribune of the plebs, in popular meetings which
                    were now more numerously attended, and by men more easily induced to covet land,
                    than had been the case before. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate
                    talked also of war with the Latins and the Hernici, but dread of a greater war
                    —Etruria being up in arms —caused them to defer it. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The government passed to Camillus, as tribune
                    of the soldiers with consular authority. He was given five colleagues: Servius
                    Cornelius Maluginensis, Quintus Servilius Fidenas (for a sixth term), Lucius
                    Quinctius Cincinnatus, Lucius Horatius Pulvillus, and Publius Valerius.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Early in the year the general concern was
                    diverted from the Etruscan war, when a band of fugitives from the Pomptine
                    district suddenly appeared in Rome with tidings that the Antiates were in arms.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Latin communities, so they reported,
                    had sent their soldiers to help in the war, but asserted that their government
                    was not involved, since they had merely, as they said, not forbidden their young
                    men to serve, as volunteers, where they liked. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.215"/>
                <p> The Romans had ceased by this time to make light <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 386</note> of any wars. And so the
                    senate gave thanks to the gods that Camillus was in office, for in sooth they
                    would have been obliged to make him dictator, if he had been a private citizen;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and his colleagues declared that the
                    general control, when any warlike danger threatened, belonged to one man alone,
                    and that they were resolved to subordinate their own authority to Camillus; nor
                    did they believe that there was any derogation of their own dignity in such
                    concessions as they might make to his. The senate commended the tribunes, and
                    Camillus himself, deeply moved, expressed his thanks. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A heavy responsibility he said, was placed upon him by the
                    Roman People, who had now elected him for the fourth time; no small one by the
                    senate, in so judging of him; but the greatest of all proceeded from the
                    deference accorded him by such distinguished colleagues. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, if it were possible to add to his exertions
                    and his vigilance, he should vie with himself in an effort to make the very high
                    opinion which his fellow citizens so unanimously entertained of him an abiding
                    one. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As for the war with the men of Antium,
                    there was more bluster in that quarter than real danger; nevertheless, as he
                    would have them fear nothing, so he would counsel them to despise nothing.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The City of Rome was ringed about by the
                    envy and ill-will of her neighbours; consequently there needed several generals
                    and armies to administer the interests of the state. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>It is my wish,</quote> said he, <quote> that you, Publius Valerius,
                        should share my authority and deliberations, and join me in leading the
                        legions against the enemy at Antium; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> that
                        you, Quintus Servilius, should organize <pb n="p.217"/> and equip a second
                        army, and maintain your camp <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="marg">B.C. 386</note> near Rome, on the alert, in case any move
                        should be made in the meantime from Etruria, as happened recently, or from
                        this new source of anxiety, the Latins and Hernici; certain I am that you
                        will discharge the commission in a manner worthy of your father, your
                        grandfather, and yourself, and of your six tribuneships. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Let a third army be enrolled by Lucius Quinctius, out
                        of those who are invalided or over age, to defend the City and the walls.
                        Let Lucius Horatius provide arms, missiles, corn, and what else the
                        exigencies of the war demand. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> You,
                        Servius Cornelius, we, your colleagues, appoint to be president of this
                        state council, guardian of religious rites, of the elections, the laws, and
                        all the affairs of the City. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> All promised loyally to do their best in
                    their respective departments of their office; and Valerius, who had been
                    selected to share in the command, added that he should regard Marcus Furius as a
                    dictator and himself as his master of the horse; <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> in proportion therefore to men's confidence in their unique
                    commander should be their hopes of the outcome of the war. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> Whereat the senators in their enthusiasm shouted that they
                    hoped right well of the war, and of the peace, and of the common weal in
                    general; adding that the state would never need a dictator if it might have such
                    men in office, united in such loving concord, equally ready to command and obey,
                    and rather contributing to the common stock of glory than drawing upon it for
                    their own behoof. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After proclaiming a suspension of legal
                    business and holding a levy, Furius and Valerius set <pb n="p.219"/> out for
                    Satricum, where the Antiates had collected <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 386</note> not only the fighting men of
                    the Volsci, recruited from a new generation, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.,</hi> since the disastrous defeat they had suffered
                        in 389 (chap. ii. § 12). </note> but also a large force of Latins and
                    Hernici, nations which, having been long at peace, were extremely strong. The
                    consequence of this addition of new enemies to their old ones was to trouble the
                    spirit of the Roman soldiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But when the
                    centurions reported to Camillus, as he was already drawing up his line, that the
                    men were demoralized; that they had been loath to arm and had hesitated and
                    delayed in leaving the camp, nay, that some had even been heard to say that they
                    would be one against a hundred in the battle, and that so great a host could
                    hardly be withstood even though unarmed, much less when provided with weapons
                    —being <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> told of this, I say, Camillus vaulted
                    upon his horse, and riding along the ranks in front of the standards, faced his
                    troops and thus addressed them: </p>
                <p> "Soldiers, what means this gloom and this unwonted reluctance? Are you strangers
                    to the enemy, or to me, or to yourselves? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    enemy —what else are they but inexhaustible material for you to fashion into
                    glorious deeds of valour? As for yourselves, when acting as my soldiers, though
                    I say nothing of your capturing Falerii and Veii and routing the Gallic legions
                    in your captured City, you celebrated, only the other day, a three-fold triumph
                    for a triple victory over these very Volsci and Aequi and over Etruria.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Or is it that I, having given you the
                    signal not as dictator but as tribune of the soldiers, am not recognized as your
                    commander? And yet neither do I desire supreme authority over you, nor ought you
                    to regard in me anything but myself; for <pb n="p.221"/> the dictatorship could
                    never give me resolution, nor <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C.386</note> could even exile deprive me of it. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> We are all, therefore, exactly as we were, and since
                    we bring the same qualities in all respects to this campaign that we brought to
                    earlier ones, let us look forward to the same result. As soon as you have joined
                    battle, every man will do what he has learned and has become accustomed to: you
                    will conquer, they will run away. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He then sounded the charge, and leaping from
                    his horse, caught hold of the nearest standard bearer and hurried him towards
                    the enemy, calling out: <quote>Forward soldiers!</quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But when they saw Camillus, who for bodily
                    feats was now grown old and infirm, advancing in person against the foe, they
                    all gave a cheer and rushed forward together, and every man took up the cry of
                        <quote>Follow the General!</quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is even said that Camillus bade the
                    standard-bearer hurl his ensign into the press of enemies, and urging the front
                    ranks to recover it, then for the first time discomfited the Antiates.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The panic did not stop with the first
                    line, but spread even to the troops in support. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> It was not only the dash of the Roman soldiers, inspired by their leader's
                    presence, which overcame them; for nothing so daunted the spirits of the Volsci
                    as the sight of Camillus himself, when they happened to encounter him —so
                    surely, wherever he went, did he carry victory with him. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> This was especially apparent on the left. That wing had
                    already nearly given way, when Camillus suddenly threw himself upon a horse,
                    and, armed with an infantry-shield, rode up and by his presence retrieved the
                    battle, calling out that the rest of the army was conquering. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The fortune of the day had now turned, <pb n="p.223"/> but
                    the enemy's numbers were an obstacle even to <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 386</note> their flight, and a great
                    multitude remained for the weary soldiers to dispatch with long-drawn massacre,
                    when suddenly great gusts of wind brought on a downpour of rain, which broke off
                    what was rather a certain victory than a battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Thereupon the recall was sounded, and the night that followed finished the
                    campaign for the Romans, while they slept. For the Latins and Hernici abandoned
                    the Volsci and marched off to their homes, their evil counsels rewarded with as
                    evil an outcome; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and the Volsci, perceiving
                    themselves to be deserted by those on whom they had relied in their rebellion,
                    forsook their camp and shut themselves up within the walls of Satricum.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Camillus at first set about confining
                    them with a palisade and mound, intending to lay siege to them; but finding the
                    enemy made no sorties to interrupt the work, he concluded they had not
                    sufficient resolution to make him wait so long for victory. He therefore
                    encouraged his troops not to wear themselves out with protracted toil, as though
                    they were besieging Veii, when victory was within their grasp; and with great
                    alacrity on the part of the soldiers, he approached the walls from every side
                    and captured the town with scaling ladders. The Volsci threw away their weapons
                    and surrendered. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the general's thoughts were turning to a
                    matter of greater moment, namely Antium, which, as being the Volscian capital,
                    he held responsible for the last war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But
                    because, without extensive equipment of artillery and engines, it was impossible
                    to take so strong a town, he left his colleague in command of the army and
                    proceeded to Rome, that he might <pb n="p.225"/> urge the senate to undertake
                    the destruction of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        386</note> Antium. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While he was speaking
                    —I suppose it was Heaven's will that the Antian state should continue somewhat
                    longer <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">With this remark compare I. iv.
                        1.</note> —envoys from Nepete and Sutrium appeared, who asked for help
                    against the Etruscans, saying that the opportunity of lending aid would soon be
                    past. To this quarter Fortune diverted the energies of Camillus, away from
                    Antium. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For since these places were on the
                    frontier of Etruria, and were the barriers, so to speak, and gateways of that
                    region, the Etruscans were concerned to seize them, as often as they had any new
                    design in hand, and the Romans to recover or defend them. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The senate therefore resolved to request of Camillus that
                    he should relinquish Antium and undertake the Etruscan war, and voted him the
                    city levies which had been under the command of Quinctius. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Although Camillus would have preferred the army,
                    disciplined and used to his authority, which lay in the Volscian country, he
                    made no objection, only stipulating that Valerius should be associated with him
                    in the command. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quinctius and Horatius were
                    dispatched to succeed Valerius against the Volsci. </p>
                <p> Leaving the City and marching to Sutrium, Furius and Valerius found that a part
                    of the town was already captured by the Etruscans, and that in the other part
                    the townspeople had barricaded the streets and were defending themselves with
                    great difficulty from the onslaughts of their enemies. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The arrival of succour from Rome, and particularly the
                    great reputation which Camillus enjoyed with both friends and foes, checked for
                    the moment the disastrous course of events and afforded time to render
                    assistance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly, Camillus divided the
                    army, <pb n="p.227"/> and directed his colleague to make a circuit with his
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 386</note>
                    forces and to attack the walls on the side which was held by the enemy. His hope
                    was not so much that the city would be taken by escalade, as that the enemy
                    might be diverted to that quarter —easing thereby the strain upon the townsmen,
                    who were already worn out with fighting —and that he might himself have an
                    opportunity of entering the place without encountering resistance. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> But on this plan being put into effect
                    simultaneously at both points, the Etruscans, finding themselves threatened on
                    either side and seeing that the walls were being violently assailed and that the
                    enemy was inside the city, threw themselves out by the only gate which chanced
                    to be unguarded, in one panic-stricken throng. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> Great was the carnage they suffered as they fled, both in the city and in the
                    fields. Furius's men slew more within the walls; the soldiers of Valerius were
                    more lightly equipped for pursuit, and kept up the massacre until night made it
                    impossible to see. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Having retaken Sutrium and restored it to our
                    allies, the army marched to Nepete, which had surrendered to the Etruscans, who
                    were now in complete possession. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It appeared likely that this town would be
                    more troublesome to recover, not only because it was wholly in the hands of the
                    enemy, but also because a faction of the Nepesini had betrayed their state and
                    arranged the capitulation. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was nevertheless
                    decided to send word to their leaders, that they should sever themselves from
                    the Etruscans and extend to the Romans the same trusty aid which they had
                    requested at their hands. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the reply came
                        <pb n="p.229"/> back that they were powerless, that the Etruscans <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 386</note> held the
                    walls and guarded the gates, the Romans first laid waste their fields, in an
                    effort to frighten the townsfolk; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> then, when
                    the sanctity of their surrender proved to be more binding on them than that of
                    their alliance, they gathered osiers from the fields and made fascines, and the
                    army being led against the walls filled up the moat, erected scaling ladders,
                    and carried the town at the first shout and charge. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Nepesini were then commanded to lay down their weapons
                    and the order was given to spare such as were unarmed. The Etruscans were put to
                    death, whether armed or not. Of the Nepesini, too, those who were responsible
                    for the surrender were executed; the innocent populace were given back their
                    possessions, and the town was left with a garrison. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> After thus regaining from the enemy two cities of the
                    allies, the victorious army under its tribunes marched gloriously back to Rome. </p>
                <p> The same year demands for reparation were made upon the Latins and the Hernici,
                    and they were asked why, during recent years, they had furnished no soldiers, as
                    they had agreed to do. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Both nations replied in
                    plenary assemblies that no blame or evil purpose attached to the state because a
                    few of their young men had served with the Volsci. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> These men had, for that matter, paid the penalty for their
                    distorted judgment, and not one of them had come back; as to their having
                    furnished no soldiers, this had been due to their constant fear of the Volsci —a
                    pest that clung so fast to them that with all that long succession of wars they
                    had been unable to shake it off. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On learning
                    of this answer, the <pb n="p.231"/> senators were of opinion that they lacked
                    not so <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 386</note>
                    much the ground for war as a favourable opportunity. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the following year, when the consular <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 385</note> tribunes
                    were Aulus Manlius, Publius Cornelius, Titus and Lucius Quinctius Capitolinus,
                    Lucius Papirius Cursor (for the second time) and Gaius Sergius (for the second
                    time), a serious foreign war broke out, and an even more serious domestic
                    schism. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The war was set on foot by the Volsci,
                    in conjunction with a revolt on the part of the Latins and Hernici; the schism
                    originated where such a thing was least to be apprehended, with a man of
                    patrician family and high renown, Marcus Manlius Capitolinus. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This man, scorning, in his overweening pride, the other
                    nobles, but envying the one who excelled them all in honours and good qualities,
                    namely Marcus Furius, could ill endure that Camillus should at last have
                    attained to such solitary eminence, both amongst the magistrates and in the
                    armies, as to have those who had been chosen under the same auspices not for
                    colleagues but for servants; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> whereas —if one
                    considered the situation fairly —it would have been impossible for Marcus Furius
                    to redeem his native City from the leaguer of her enemies, unless Manlius
                    himself had before that saved the Capitol and Citadel. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Camillus had assailed the Gauls while they were receiving
                    the gold and while their resolution was relaxed by thoughts of peace; but he
                    himself had driven them back, as they came on, sword in hand, in the act of
                    taking the Citadel. Of the glory of Camillus a goodly portion belonged to all
                    the soldiers who had conquered with him: in his own victory it was acknowledged
                    that no mortal soever had a share. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Puffed up
                    with these <pb n="p.233"/> opinions, and being besides, through a defect of
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 385</note>
                    nature, impetuous and passionate, when he perceived that his abilities did not
                    bring him that leadership amongst the nobles <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    which he thought they merited, he was the first of all the patricians to turn
                    demagogue and to cast in his lot with the plebeian magistrates. He abused the
                    nobles, he courted the favour of the plebs; and swept along by the breath of
                    popularity and not by good counsel chose rather to be reputed great than
                    virtuous. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Moreover, not content with agrarian
                    proposals, which had ever served the tribunes to stir up sedition, he began an
                    attack on credit; for he held that debt was a sharper goad, since it not only
                    threatened poverty and shame, but terrified the freeman with the thought of
                    shackles and imprisonment. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And in fact there
                    had been a vast piling up of debts, by reason of a thing that is ruinous even to
                    the rich, to wit, building. And so the Volscian war, grave in itself and made
                    still graver by the defection of the Latins and Hernici, was alleged as a reason
                    for seeking a greater authority; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but the
                    revolutionary schemes of Manlius were the more compelling cause of the senate's
                    naming a dictator. They appointed Aulus Cornelius Cossus, who appointed as his
                    master of the horse Titus Quinctius Capitolinus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator perceived that a greater struggle
                    was impending at home than abroad. But either the war demanded haste, or he
                    believed that by a victory and triumph he could add power to the dictatorship
                    itself. So he mustered his forces and proceeded to the Pomptine territory, which
                    he had heard was invaded by a Volscian army. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I doubt not that those who are surfeited with
                        <pb n="p.235"/> reading in all these books about endless wars waged <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 385</note> with the
                    Volsci will ask, as with great astonishment I did myself, on examining the
                    historians who were nearer in point of time to those events, where the so oft
                    defeated Volsci and Aequi got their supply of soldiers. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But since the ancients have passed over this question in
                    silence, what can I adduce other than an opinion such as everyone can by
                    conjecture arrive at for himself? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is
                    probable either that in the intervals between wars successive generations sprang
                    up —as happens nowadays in the levies of the Romans —which they used for their
                    frequent renewals of war; or that it was not always the same tribes from which
                    they enrolled their armies —though it was always the same nation which made war;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> or else that there was an innumerable
                    multitude of freemen in those regions which in our day scarce afford a scanty
                    seed-plot for soldiers, and are only saved from becoming a waste desert by gangs
                    of Roman slaves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In any case, all the
                    authorities would agree that the army of the Volsci was an enormous one,
                    although their state had recently suffered a heavy blow from the generalship and
                    auspices of Camillus. There were, besides, additional forces of Latins and
                    Hernici, as well as a certain number from Circeii, and even Roman colonists from
                    Velitrae. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the morning after he had made his camp, the
                    dictator took the auspices, and coming forth from his tent offered up a victim
                    and besought the favour of Heaven. He then with great cheerfulness presented
                    himself before the soldiers, who were already arming by the first rays of light,
                    as they had been warned to do when the signal for battle <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">A red flag flown from the general's tent.</note> should
                    be displayed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Ours is the victory, soldiers,</quote> he <pb n="p.237"/> exclaimed,
                        <quote> if the gods and the soothsayers who <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 385</note> interpret them can at
                        all see what is coming. And so, as befits men who with sure confidence are
                        about to fight with those who are no match for them, let us lay our javelins
                        at our feet and arm our right hands with swords only. I would have none run
                        out from the line, but all stand firmly planted and receive the onset of our
                        enemies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they have discharged their
                        missiles without effect, and come thronging upon you where you stand, then
                        let your blades flash out, and let every man of you bethink him that the
                        gods are the Roman's helpers, that the gods have with fair omens sent him
                        into battle. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Do you, Titus Quinctius,
                        hold back your cavalry and watch for the first beginning of the mellay; when
                        you see that the lines are already close-locked, foot to foot, then loose
                        the terrors of your horse against them, while they are taken up with another
                        fear; charge them as they fight, and break their ranks. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> so horse and foot fought exactly as they had
                    been ordered; the general failed not his legions, nor fortune the general. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The hostile multitude, relying on numbers only
                    and measuring both armies with their eyes, recklessly began the fight and as
                    recklessly gave it up; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> their boldness went no
                    further than the battle-cry, the discharge of missiles, and the first fury of
                    the onset; the play of swords, when foot met foot, and the glance of the foeman
                    that darted out the fire of his spirit, they could not abide. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Their front was first driven in and communicated its
                    disorder to the supports; the horsemen, too, inspired a terror of their own;
                    next the ranks were broken at many points, and all was in commotion, and the
                    line <pb n="p.239"/> resembled a surging wave. Then, as soon as each <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 385</note> began to
                    see that with the fall of those in front his own turn to be killed would soon be
                    coming, they turned and fled. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans
                    pressed on after them, and as long as they retained their arms and withdrew in
                    masses, it was the infantry's task to pursue them; but when the enemy were seen
                    to be throwing away their weapons on every hand and their army to be dispersed
                    in flight over the fields; then the cavalry squadrons were let loose, with
                    orders not to stop to kill single fugitives and afford meanwhile an opportunity
                    to the main body of escaping; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> it was
                    sufficient if by darting missiles at them to alarm them, and by riding across
                    their path, they should hold the column in check, till the infantry could
                    overtake the enemy and utterly destroy them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Flight and pursuit continued until nightfall. The Volscian camp was also
                    captured the same day and sacked, and all the booty except the persons of
                    freemen was turned over to the soldiers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    chief part of the prisoners consisted of Latins and Hernici, not all of whom
                    were plebeians, such as might be supposed to have served as mercenaries, but
                    certain youths of high rank were discovered, a clear proof that their states had
                    publicly countenanced the Volscian enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Some, again, were recognized as being from Circeii and from the colony at
                    Velitrae. They were all sent to Rome, and being questioned by the chief
                    senators, gave the same answers they had given the dictator, and in no uncertain
                    terms laid bare the defection of their respective peoples. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator maintained his army in camp, not
                    doubting in the least that the senate would <pb n="p.241"/> declare war on those
                    nations; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Actually the senate could
                        only recommend a declaration of war, the ultimate decision resting with the
                            <hi rend="italics">comitia centuriata.</hi>
                    </note> when a greater <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B.C. 385</note> disturbance broke out at home and obliged them to summon
                    him to the City, where the sedition was increasing from day to day, and
                    occasioned more than the usual alarm by reason of the man who was behind it.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For now not only the speeches of Marcus
                    Manlius, but his actions as well, while ostensibly democratic, were really
                    revolutionary, considering the purpose which inspired them. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> A centurion renowned for military prowess had been
                    condemned for debt. As he was being led away, Manlius caught sight of him, and
                    hastening to his side through the midst of the Forum with his band of retainers,
                    he laid hold of him, and exclaiming at the arrogance of the patricians, the
                    heartlessness of the money-lenders, the sufferings of the plebs, and the merits
                    and misfortunes of this man, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Then in very truth,</quote> he cried, <quote> was it all in vain that
                        with this right hand I saved the Capitol and the Citadel, if I am to see my
                        fellow citizen and fellow soldier carried off a captive —as though the Gauls
                        had conquered us —to servitude and chains! </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then paid the money to the creditor in full
                    sight of the people, and with the ceremony of the scales and bronze <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Symbolical of the <hi rend="italics"
                            >sale</hi> by which the debtor was conceived to be transferred from the
                        ownership of his creditor to that of Liberty. </note> redeemed the debtor
                    and set him free, to invoke the blessing of gods and men on Marcus Manlius, his
                    liberator, the father of the Roman plebs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    man was at once received into the midst of a tumultuous throng, and added to the
                    tumult by displaying the scars he had received in the Veientine, the Gallic, and
                    other successive wars. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While he had himself
                    been fighting, he said, and rebuilding his ruined home, he had been overwhelmed
                    with usury, though he had paid already many times the amount of the capital <pb
                        n="p.243"/> debt, for the interest always swallowed up the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 385</note> principal;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that he beheld the light of day, the
                    Forum, the faces of his fellow citizens, he owed to the generosity of Marcus
                    Manlius, at whose hands he had experienced all the loving-kindness of parents;
                    to him he solemnly devoted his remaining strength and life and blood; what ties
                    soever bound him to native land and the gods of his state and family, bound him
                    to one man alone. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Excited by these words, the
                    commons were already at the beck of a single man, when Manlius did another thing
                    even better calculated to promote a general embroilment. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> For he gave a farm in the Veientine district, which formed
                    the main part of his fortune, to an auctioneer to sell, — <quote>that I may not
                        suffer one of your number, Quirites,</quote> said he, <quote> to be
                        condemned, made over, and carried off to slavery, so long as anything of my
                        estate remains. </quote> At this their ardour was so kindled that it was
                    clear that in every measure, right or wrong, they would follow the champion of
                    their liberty. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Besides this he delivered in his house
                    harangues that were full of accusation against the patricians; amongst other
                    things, he declared, with reckless indifference to truth or falsehood, that the
                    patricians were concealing treasures of Gallic gold, and were no longer content
                    with possessing the state lands, unless they could also divert to their own use
                    the money of the state —money which, if it were employed for the common weal,
                    would suffice to clear the plebs of debt. On this hope being held out to them,
                    the commons felt that they were indeed ill-used. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> When, they said, it had been necessary to raise gold for
                    the redemption of their City from the <pb n="p.245"/> Gauls, it had been
                    collected by taxation; but this <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 385</note> same gold, after being captured from the enemy,
                    had become the spoil of a few. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They therefore
                    persistently demanded to be told where all that stolen money was hid; and when
                    he put them off with the promise that he would tell them at the proper time,
                    they dropped their other concerns and became one and all so absorbed in this,
                    that it was evident he would reap no little gratitude if his report proved true,
                    and no small offence if it turned out to be false. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the critical state of affairs when
                    the dictator was sent for from the army and came to Rome. Next day he held a
                    meeting of the senate, and having satisfied himself of the people's support, he
                    commanded the senators not to leave him, and coming forth with a great company
                    of them into the Comitium, he there set up his curule chair and dispatched an
                    officer for Marcus Manlius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Being thus
                    summoned by order of the dictator, Manlius signalled to his friends that the
                    struggle was <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> at hand, and advanced with a
                    great train of followers to the tribunal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On
                    this side were ranged the senators, on that the plebs, looking, every man of
                    them, to his respective leader, as though they had formed up for battle. Then,
                    having obtained silence, the dictator began: <quote>I would,</quote> said he,
                        <quote> that I arid the senators of Rome might agree with the plebs in all
                        things else as readily as I am confident we shall do regarding you, Manlius,
                        and the demand I am about to make of you. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        I perceive that you have caused the citizens to hope that the money which
                        has been lent may be repaid, without injury to credit, out of Gallic
                        treasure which prominent <pb n="p.247"/> patricians are concealing.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This proposal I am so <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 385</note> far from
                        hindering, that on the contrary I exhort you, Marcus Manlius, to free the
                        Roman plebs from usury, and dislodge from their secret hoards those men who
                        are brooding jealously over the public treasure; which if you do not,
                        whether that you may share the spoil yourself, or because your story is a
                        lie, I shall order you into custody, nor suffer you any longer to excite the
                        multitude with delusive hopes. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To this Manlius replied that he had not failed
                    to perceive that the appointment of a dictator was aimed, not at the Volsci, who
                    were enemies whenever it suited the convenience of the patricians, nor at the
                    Latins and Hernici, whom they were driving by false accusations to take up arms,
                    but at himself and the Roman plebs. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And now
                    they had dropped their pretended war and were attacking him; now the dictator
                    was coming out as the champion of the money-lenders against the plebs; and they
                    were seeking now to derive from the people's friendliness to him some charge
                    that might lead to his destruction. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Does it offend you,</quote> he asked, <quote> Aulus Cornelius, and you,
                        Conscript Fathers, that a crowd attends me? Why do you not take it from me
                        by doing, each of you, acts of kindness, by saving debtors, by rescuing your
                        fellow citizens from prison, by preventing the enslavement of those who have
                        been condemned and assigned, by employing your superfluity of wealth to
                        sustain the necessities of others? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But
                        why should I ask of you that you spend of your own money? Receive what is
                        outstanding of the original debts, after deducting from the principal what
                        has been paid in interest, and <pb n="p.249"/> my retinue will soon attract
                        no more notice than <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                            >B.C. 385</note> any man's. But why, you will ask, am I the only man to
                        be concerned for my fellow citizens? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I
                        can no more answer you than if you were to ask why I was the only man to
                        save the Capitol and Citadel. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As then —to
                        the best of my ability —I helped the people at large, so now will I help
                        single persons. And touching the Gallic treasure —the thing itself is
                        simple, but your questioning makes it difficult. For why do you ask about a
                        thing you know? Why do you bid us shake out what is in your purses, and not
                        rather lay it down yourselves —unless there is some cheat involved?
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The more you bid us expose your
                        sleight-of-hand, the more I fear you may have robbed us even of our eyes,
                        while we were watching you. And so it is not I that must be forced to tell
                        of your plunder, but you that must be compelled to give it up. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the dictator bade him cease to quibble,
                    and insisted that he should either make his indictment good or confess to the
                    crime of having accused the senate falsely and exposed it to the unmerited odium
                    of a charge of theft; and when Manlius refused to speak at the pleasure of his
                    enemies, he commanded him to be imprisoned. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On
                    being arrested by the attendant, Manlius cried out, <quote> Jupiter Optimus
                        Maximus, and Queen Juno and Minerva, and all ye other gods and goddesses
                        that dwell in the Capitol and in the Citadel, is it thus ye suffer your
                        soldier and protector to be tormented by his adversaries? <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Shall this right arm wherewith I routed the Gauls from
                        your shrines be now chained and fettered? </quote> There was none that could
                    endure to behold or hear this shame; but there were <pb n="p.251"/> certain
                    rules of conduct which the citizens, deeply <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 385</note> submissive to regular
                    authority, had made inviolable; nor did either the tribunes of the plebs or the
                    plebs themselves dare to lift their eyes or open their mouths against the power
                    of the dictator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But after Manlius was cast
                    into gaol, it is certain that a great part of the people put on mourning, and
                    that many men permitted their hair and beards to grow, and that a mournful
                    throng hung about the entrance to the prison. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The dictator triumphed over the Volsci, but
                    gained more ill-will thereby than glory; for men murmured that he had earned it,
                    not in the field, but at home, not over an enemy, but over a citizen; one thing
                    only had been lacking to his arrogance, in that Marcus Manlius had not been led
                    before his car. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By this time the feeling was
                    grown well-nigh seditious; and to appease it the senate —though none demanded it
                    —became all at once a voluntary giver, and commanded two thousand Roman citizens
                    to be led out to plant a colony at Satricum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Two <hi rend="italics">iugera</hi> and a half <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> About one and two-thirds acres. The allotment of
                        Veientine land had been seven <hi rend="italics">iugera.</hi>
                    </note> of land were allotted them; but since they chose to regard it as too
                    little, and only given to a few, and as being the price of Manlius's
                    condemnation, the remedy but aggravated the sedition. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> And now the Manlian party were more conspicuous than
                    before, both for their sordid dress and for the sorrowful countenances of
                    defendants; men's fears had been removed by the abdication of the dictator,
                    following his triumph, and their tongues and spirits had been set free. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accordingly one began to hear the opinion
                    openly expressed that the people were to blame, because they always by their
                    favours raised their <pb n="p.253"/> champions to a dizzy eminence, and then at
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 385</note>
                    critical juncture left them in the lurch: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> it
                    had been so with Spurius Cassius and with Spurius Maelius, of whom the former
                    was destroyed while summoning the people to the land, and the latter while
                    endeavouring at his own expense to stave off starvation from his fellow
                    citizens; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> it was so with Marcus Manlius, who,
                    finding a part of the citizens overwhelmed and sunk in debt, was dragging them
                    out into light and liberty, when they betrayed him to his adversaries; the plebs
                    fattened their own defenders for the shambles. Was this the penalty a consular
                    must undergo, if he answered not when the dictator nodded to him? <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Let them assume that he had lied before, and for that
                    reason was then unable to reply: what slave had ever been cast into prison for a
                    lie? Did they not recall that night which had almost been the last eternal night
                    of the Roman name? Could they not see the line of Gauls scaling the Tarpeian
                    Rock? Could they not see Marcus Manlius himself, as they had seen him, covered
                    with sweat and blood, when he had rescued as it were Jupiter himself from the
                    hands of our enemies? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Had their half-pound
                    measures of meal requited the saviour of their country? <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See v. xlvii. 8.</note> Would they suffer one whom they
                    had well-nigh made a god, and in surname, at any rate, the equal of Jupiter
                    Capitolinus, to be confined in prison, and to draw his breath in darkness, at
                    the mercy of the executioner? When one man had been quite able to help them all,
                    was there no help in so many men for one? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By
                    this time the crowd would not even leave the place at night and were threatening
                    that they would force the gaol, when suddenly, just as <pb n="p.255"/> they were
                    about to rescue Manlius, the senate voted <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 385</note> to release him —an act
                    which, instead of ending the sedition, supplied it with a leader. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At about this time came Latins and Hernici,
                    with colonists from Circeii and from Velitrae, to clear themselves of the charge
                    of joining in the Volscian war and to ask for the release of the captives, that
                    they might punish them in accordance with their own laws. They were harshly
                    answered —especially the colonists, because, though Roman citizens, they had
                    formed the impious design of attacking their native country. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> And so they were not only denied the captives, but received
                    a rebuke which the allies were spared; being commanded in the name of the senate
                    to make haste and depart the City, out of the presence and sight of the Roman
                    People, lest they should find no protection in the rights of envoys, which were
                    meant for foreigners, not for citizens. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The sedition of Manlius was breaking out <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 384</note> afresh,
                    towards the end of the year, when an election was held which resulted in the
                    choice of the following consular tribunes: Servius Cornelius Maluginensis (for
                    the second time), Publius Valerius Potitus (for the second), Marcus Furius
                    Camillus (for the fifth), Servius Sulpicius Rufus (for the second), Gaius
                    Papirius Crassus, and (for the second time) Titus Quinctius Cincinnatus.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The peace which was enjoyed in the early
                    part of this year was equally advantageous to the patricians and to the plebs;
                    to the plebs because, not being called to service by the levy, they had hopes
                    that they might be able under their powerful leader to storm the stronghold of
                    usury; to the patricians, because they desired not to be diverted by any foreign
                    peril from healing the <pb n="p.257"/> sores of the state. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly both sides had taken <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 384</note> the field with much more
                    spirit, and the hour of conflict was now at hand. Manlius indeed was inviting
                    the plebeians to his house, and night and day discussing with their leaders
                    plans for accomplishing the revolution, for he was much bolder and more
                    resentful than before. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His wrath had been
                    kindled by his recent humiliations, for his pride was a stranger to insult; and
                    his courage had waxed, as he considered that the dictator had not dared to serve
                    him as Quinctius Cincinnatus had served Spurius Maelius, and that his
                    imprisonment had aroused such hatred as not only the dictator had resigned his
                    office to escape, but even the senate had been unable to endure. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> At once elated and exasperated by these thoughts, he
                    began to work upon the already excited emotions of the plebs. </p>
                <p>
                    <quote>How long, pray,</quote> he asked them, <quote> will you remain ignorant
                        of your own strength, which nature has willed that even brutes shall know?
                        At least count up your numbers and the number of your adversaries. For as
                        many as you were that gathered as clients about a single patron, so many
                        shall you now be against a single enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        If you were going to meet them man for man, I should still believe that you
                        would fight more fiercely for your liberty than they for domination.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Make but a show of war, and you shall
                        have peace. Let them see you ready to resist, and they will give you your
                        rights of their own accord. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> We must all
                        unite in some bold stroke, or else, divided, submit to every evil. How long
                        will you keep looking round for me? It is true I shall not fail a single one
                        of you; but you must see to it that fortune fail not me. I myself, your
                        champion, <pb n="p.259"/> was suddenly brought to naught, when it pleased
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 384</note>
                        your enemies; and you all beheld that man dragged off to prison who had
                        protected each of yourselves from imprisonment. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> What can I expect, if my enemies grow bolder? Must I
                        look forward to dying like Cassius and Maelius? You do well to express
                        abhorrence. The gods <hi rend="italics">will</hi> forbid such a thing; but
                        they will never come down from heaven on my account; they must give you the
                        inspiration to forbid it, as they gave me, in war and in peace, the
                        inspiration to defend you from the barbarity of your foes and the arrogance
                        of your fellow citizens. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Is there so
                        little spirit in this great people that you are always satisfied with the
                        help your tribunes lend you against your adversaries, and never quarrel with
                        the senators, save as to the length you will suffer them to go in ruling
                        you? And this is no native trait in you, but you are slaves by use.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Why, pray, are you so high and mighty
                        with foreigners as to deem yourselves meet to be their lords? <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> It is because you have been used to vie with
                        them for sovereignty; but against these men, though you make attempts at
                        gaining your liberty, you are not used to defend it. Nevertheless, with such
                        leaders as you have had, and such courage as you yourselves could muster,
                        you have thus far obtained, by violence or good fortune, whatever you have
                        sought. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The time has come to attempt even
                        greater things. Do but make trial of your own good fortune and of me, whom,
                        as I think, you have already happily proved; you will find it less trouble
                        to impose a ruler on the patricians, than you encountered in imposing
                        tribunes on them to resist their rule. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Dictatorships and consulships must be levelled with <pb n="p.261"/> the
                        ground, that the Roman plebs may be enabled <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 384</note> to lift its head.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Stand by me, then; prevent all
                        court-proceedings regarding moneys; I avow myself the patron of the commons
                        —a title with which my zeal and loyalty have invested me: if you choose to
                        give your leader a more striking title of authority or honour, you will find
                        him the more able to make good your wishes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It was thus, they say, that the agitation for
                    kingly power was begun; but there is no very clear tradition with whom or to
                    what length his plans were matured. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the other side the senate were discussing
                    the secret gathering of the plebs in a private house —a house, too, that, as it
                    happened, was situated in the Citadel —and the grave danger that threatened
                    liberty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The majority exclaimed that a
                    Servilius Ahala was needed, one who would not exasperate a public enemy by
                    ordering his imprisonment, but would sacrifice a single citizen to end a
                    domestic war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, they had recourse to a
                    proposal which sounded milder, though its force was identical, namely, that the
                    magistrates should see to it that the republic took no harm by the ruinous
                    devices of Marcus Manlius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thereupon the
                    consular tribunes and the tribunes of the plebs —for they too, perceiving that
                    their own authority would come to an end with the general liberty, had made
                    their submission to the Fathers —all these men, I say, thereupon took counsel
                    together, what was needful to be done. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                    could none of them see any way but violence and bloodshed, which would clearly
                    involve a mighty struggle, when Marcus Menenius and Quintus Publilius, tribunes
                    of the plebs, addressed them as follows: <quote> Why do we make a conflict
                        between patricians and <pb n="p.263"/> plebeians out of what ought to be the
                        quarrel of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                            384</note> state with a single pestilent citizen? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Why in attacking him do we attack the plebs as well,
                        when it is safer to attack him by the help of this same plebs, that his very
                        strength may bring about his ruin? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We
                        propose to summon him to trial. Nothing is less popular than kingly power.
                        As soon as the populace, perceiving that our quarrel is not with them, are
                        changed from supporters into judges, and see that the prosecutors are
                        plebeians, the defendant a patrician, and the accusation that of seeking to
                        set up a kingdom, they will not favour any man at the expense of their own
                        liberty. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This argument won universal approbation, and
                    Manlius was indicted. The first effect of this was to rouse <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> great feeling in the commons, especially when they saw the
                    defendant meanly clad and not attended by a single senator, or even by his
                    kinsmen or connexions, or indeed by his own brothers, Aulus and Titus Manlius.
                    That a man's nearest friends should not join him in assuming mourning in an hour
                    so fraught with danger to him, was something that had never until that day
                    occurred. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They remembered that on the
                    imprisonment of Appius Claudius, his enemy Gaius Claudius and all the Claudian
                    family had gone into mourning; and they concluded that there must be a general
                    conspiracy to put down the people's friend because he had been the first to
                    forsake the patricians for the plebs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The day of the trial came, but I do not find
                    it stated in any authority what facts were alleged by his accusers that bore
                    directly on the charge of plotting to establish a kingdom, except gatherings of
                    the populace and seditious expressions and his <pb n="p.265"/> largesses and
                    false charge; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and yet I doubt not they <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 384</note> were of
                    moment, since the reluctance of the plebs to condemn him was not owing to his
                    cause but to the place. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Campus
                        Martius, from which they could see the Capitol ( <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>
                        § 10). </note> One thing appears worthy of remark, that men may know what
                    great and glorious achievements a vile lust for regal power rendered not merely
                    thankless but actually hateful. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It is said
                    that he brought forward nearly four hundred men to whom he had lent money
                    without interest, thus saving their goods from being sold and their persons from
                    enslavement; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that besides this the military
                    distinctions which he not only enumerated but produced for all to see, comprised
                    the spoils of thirty enemies whom he had slain, and some forty decorations from
                    his generals, amongst which were conspicuous two mural and eight civic crowns;
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A mural crown was conferred on
                        the soldier who was the first to scale the enemy's wall, a civic crown on
                        one who had saved a fellow citizen (Aulus Gellius v. vi. 11). </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that he told, besides, of citizens saved from
                    the enemy, and among these named Gaius Servilius, the master of the horse, who
                    was not present. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And after rehearsing his
                    services in war, in a speech as magnificent as the height of his achievements
                    and equalling his deeds with its words, he is said to have bared his breast,
                    marked with the scars of battle, and gazing steadily at the Capitol to have
                    called on Jupiter and the other gods to help him, that they might inspire the
                    Roman People in his hour of danger with the same spirit they had given him when
                    he- defended the Capitoline Hill; and to have implored the Romans one and all to
                    fix their eyes on the Capitol and Citadel, and turn to the immortal gods while
                    they judged him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the Campus Martius, when the people were
                    being called by centuries, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi
                            rend="italics">comitia centuriata</hi> being a military organisation
                        might not assemble within the pomerium. The meeting referred to in the
                        preceding paragraph was a <hi rend="italics">contio,</hi>
                    </note> and the defendant, <pb n="p.267"/> stretching forth his hands to the
                    Capitol, had turned <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        384</note> from men to make his prayers to the gods, the tribunes clearly
                    saw that unless they could also emancipate men's eyes from the associations of
                    so glorious a deed, no accusation, however true, could ever find lodgment in
                    their grateful hearts. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And so they adjourned
                    the day of trial and appointed a council of the people to meet in the Peteline
                    Wood outside the Flumentane Gate, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                            <hi rend="italics">Porta Flumentana</hi> was at a point in the wall
                        between the Aventine and the Capitoline. </note> whence no prospect of the
                    Capitol was afforded. There they made good their charge; men steeled their
                    hearts and pronounced a dolorous judgment, abhorrent to the very ones who
                    rendered it. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some authorities assert that he
                    was condemned by duumvirs appointed to deal with a charge of treason. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">For another instance of this procedure,
                        see I. xxvi. 5.</note> The tribunes flung him from the Tarpeian Rock, and
                    the same spot served to commemorate extraordinary fame and the extremity of
                    punishment, as experienced by the self-same man. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> To his death were added marks of ignominy:
                    one of a public nature, because the people were asked to vote that, since his
                    house had stood where the temple and mint of Moneta now are, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The temple of Juno Moneta, vowed by
                        Lucius Furius Camillus ( <date when="-0345">345 B.C.</date> ) was dedicated
                        June 1st, 344. Money was coined in this temple. </note> no patrician might
                    dwell in the Citadel or the Capitol; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> the
                    other proceeding from his family, in that the Manlian clan made a decree
                    forbidding anyone thenceforth to bear the name of Marcus Manlius. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As a matter of fact, no patrician
                        Marcus Manlius of a later date is known to us. </note> Such was the end of a
                    man who, had he not been born in a free state, would have left a memorable name.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In a short time the people, remembering
                    —now that he was no longer a source of danger —only his good qualities,
                    regretted him. Moreover a pestilence soon ensued, and caused a heavy mortality
                    for which there were no obvious causes, and this many people ascribed to the
                    execution of Manlius: <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> the Capitol, they said,
                    had <pb n="p.269"/> been polluted by the blood of its saviour, and the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 384</note> gods had
                    not been pleased that the man who had rescued their temples from the hands of
                    the enemy, should be punished almost under their very eyes. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The pestilence was succeeded by a scarcity
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 383</note> of
                    corn, and in the following year, when the rumour of these two misfortunes had
                    got abroad, by various wars. The consular tribunes were Lucius Valerius (for the
                    fourth time), Aulus Manlius (for the third), Servius Sulpicius (for the third),
                    Lucius Lucretius, Lucius Aemilius (for the third time) and Marcus Trebonius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Besides the Volsci, who had been provided,
                    as it were by a kind of fatality, to furnish perpetual occupation for the Roman
                    arms, and the colonies of Circeii and Velitrae, which had long been scheming a
                    rebellion, and the Latins, whose loyalty was suspected, a new enemy suddenly
                    rose up at Lanuvium, a city which until then had been very faithful. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Believing that they were now actuated by contempt, on
                    finding the revolt of the Veliterni, who were Roman citizens, to go so long
                    unpunished, the senate decreed that a proposal should be laid before the people,
                    at the earliest possible moment, for declaring war on them; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and, to make the plebs readier for this campaign, they
                    appointed five commissioners to divide up the Pomptine land, and three to
                    conduct a colony to Nepete. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They then asked
                    the people for a declaration of war, and notwithstanding the opposition of the
                    plebeian tribunes, all the tribes voted for war. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy has perhaps made a slip in ascribing this action
                        to the <hi rend="italics">tribes,</hi> as it was regularly the assembly of
                            <hi rend="italics">centuries</hi> which declared war. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Preparations for the campaign were made that
                    year, but owing to the pestilence the army did not take the field. This delay
                    would have given the colonists time to sue the senate for pardon — and in fact a
                    majority of them were in favour of <pb n="p.271"/> sending an embassy to Rome to
                    make submission — <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        383</note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but danger to the commonwealth was bound up,
                    as often happens, with that of individuals, and the ring-leaders of the revolt
                    were so afraid of the Romans —lest they alone might be charged with the crime
                    and offered up as a sacrifice to Roman indignation —that they turned the
                    colonies away from peaceful counsels. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover, not content with merely opposing the embassy in their senate, they
                    egged on a great part of the commons to go out and pillage the Roman lands; and
                    this new outrage destroyed all hope of peace. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The Praenestines, too, were that year, for the first time, reported as disloyal;
                    evidence against them was given by the Tusculans, the Gabini, and the Labicani,
                    whose borders they had invaded; but the senate returned so mild an answer that
                    it was evident that they refused to believe in the charges because they wished
                    them not to be true. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next year Spurius and Lucius Papirius,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 382-381</note>
                    the new consular tribunes, led the levies to Velitrae, while their four
                    colleagues, Servius Cornelius Maluginensis (in his third term), Quintus
                    Servilius, Gaius Sulpicius, and Lucius Aemilius (in his fourth term), remained
                    behind to protect the City and to guard against any fresh commotion which might
                    be reported from Etruria —a quarter from which everything was suspected.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Near Velitrae the Romans defeated an army
                    in which auxiliaries from Praeneste almost outnumbered the colonists themselves;
                    but the city was so close at hand that, as it occasioned their early retreat, so
                    it afforded them their only refuge. The tribunes abstained from attacking the
                    place; they were not certain of succeeding, nor did they think it right to aim
                    at the extermination of the colony. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In <pb
                        n="p.273"/> the letter which they sent to the senate in Rome, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 382-381</note>
                    announcing the victory, they were more severe upon the enemies from Praeneste
                    than upon those of Velitrae. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And so, by resolution of the senate and
                    popular enactment, war was proclaimed against the people of Praeneste; who,
                    uniting in the following year with the Volsci, attacked the Roman colony of
                    Satricum, and having carried it, despite the obstinate resistance of the
                    colonists, abused their victory by cruel treatment of the captives. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> This incensed the Romans, and they elected Marcus
                    Furius Camillus tribune of the soldiers, for the sixth time. To be his
                    colleagues they gave him Aulus and Lucius Postumius Regillensis and Lucius
                    Furius, together with Lucius Lucretius and Marcus Fabius Ambustus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Volscian war was entrusted, out of the
                    regular course, to Marcus Furius. Of the other tribunes, Lucius Furius was
                    assigned him by lot for his assistant, not so much (it should seem) for the good
                    of the commonwealth, as that he might be the source of all honour to his
                    colleague; who gained it in his public capacity because he made good what the
                    other's rashness had lost, and as a man because he used the error of Lucius to
                    earn his gratitude rather than glory for himself. Camillus was now extremely
                    old. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the election he was prepared to excuse
                    himself by taking the customary oath on the score of health, had not the
                    unanimous wishes of the people prevented him. But a lusty spirit flourished in
                    his sturdy breast, and his senses were as keen as ever; and though he no longer
                    much concerned himself with politics, wars excited him. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He enrolled four legions, each of four thousand men,
                    appointed <pb n="p.275"/> the army to assemble on the following day <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 382-381</note> at the
                    Esquiline Gate, and marched on Satricum. There the conquerors of the colony were
                    waiting for him, undismayed, for they confided in their numbers, in which they
                    possessed a considerable superiority. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On
                    perceiving the approach of the Romans they formed up at once. It was their
                    purpose to engage immediately in a decisive battle; for so the numerical
                    weakness of their enemies would derive no help from the skill of their unique
                    commander, which constituted —so they assumed —their sole reliance. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was the same ardour in the Roman army,
                    and in one of its generals. The hazard of an immediate battle was only postponed
                    by the wisdom and the authority of one man, who sought an opportunity to
                    supplement his resources with strategy, by prolonging the campaign. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> This made the enemy the more urgent, and, no longer
                    content with deploying their line before the camp, they advanced into the middle
                    of the field, and, marching up almost to the rampart of the Romans, displayed
                    the proud confidence which their strength gave them. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman soldiers were mortified at this, and even more
                    mortified was one of their two tribunes, Lucius Furius. His youth and native
                    disposition made him head strong, and the utterly baseless enthusiasm of the
                    rank and file filled him with assurance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    soldiers were already in a state of excitement, but he further instigated them
                    by disparaging his colleague in the only possible way, on the score of age.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Wars, he insisted, were the province of
                    youth; the growth and decay of the spirit kept pace with those of the body; the
                    most energetic of soldiers was become a procrastinator, and he who had been wont
                    to storm a camp <pb n="p.277"/> or a city on the first approach, was sitting
                    still and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        382-381</note> wasting time behind intrenchments. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> What accession to his own strength did he look for, or what
                    diminution of the enemy's? What opportunity, what favourable moment, what ground
                    for an ambush was he making ready? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The old
                    man's strategy was cold and torpid. But why, though Camillus had had enough both
                    of life and of glory, should they permit the state, which ought to be immortal,
                    to sink into decrepitude in company with the mortal body of one man? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When he had won over the entire army by these
                    speeches, and the men were everywhere demanding battle, he said to his
                    colleague: <quote> Marcus Furius, we can no longer resist the enthusiasm of the
                        soldiers; and the enemy, whose courage we have augmented by our delay, is
                        insulting us with an arrogance no longer to be endured. Give way, for you
                        are alone against us all, and suffer yourself to be overcome in counsel,
                        that you may overcome the sooner in war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To this Camillus replied that in the wars
                    which up to that day had been conducted under his sole auspices neither the
                    Roman People nor himself had repented of his strategy or fortune; he was aware
                    that he had now a colleague of equal commission and authority, and of more
                    vigorous years; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and so, although —as regarded
                    the army —he was accustomed not to be governed but to govern, yet he had no
                    power to thwart the authority of his associate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> Let him proceed, with Heaven's blessing, to do what he thought best for the
                    commonwealth: for his own grey hairs he begged this favour, that he might not be
                    assigned to the front; of such duties as belonged in war to an old man he would
                    not be <pb n="p.279"/> negligent. One thing he entreated of the immortal <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 382-381</note> gods:
                    that no mischance might occur, to make his own appear to have been the wiser
                    plan. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But neither did men heed these salutary
                    words, nor the immortal gods his loyal prayers. The man responsible for the
                    engagement marshalled the battle-line. Camillus provided adequate supports, and
                    stationed a strong out-guard before the camp; he then took up his post on an
                    eminence, and watched intently for the issue of another's strategy. <milestone
                        n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the very instant of the first clash of arms
                    the enemy gave ground, not out of fear, but guile. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Behind them the ground sloped gently up from the
                    battle-line to their camp; and having plenty of men they had left a few strong
                    cohorts armed and drawn up within the camp, which were to sally forth when the
                    fighting had got under way, and the Romans had approached the rampart.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans pursued the retreating enemy
                    without order, and were drawn into an unfavourable position, where this attack
                    could be made upon them with advantage. Thus the victors were threatened in
                    their turn, and, what with the new foe and the declivity, the Roman line gave
                    way. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were closely pressed by the fresh
                    Volsci who had made the sortie, and those, too, who had pretended flight renewed
                    the battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And now the Roman soldiers were no
                    longer retiring in order, but regardless of their late impetuosity and their
                    ancient fame, had turned their backs and were everywhere in full flight towards
                    the camp; when Camillus was lifted into the saddle by his attendants, and
                    rapidly throwing his reserves into the fight, <quote>Soldiers,</quote> he cried,
                        <quote> is this the battle you demanded? What man, what god is there, whom
                            <pb n="p.281"/> you could accuse? Yours was the rashness then, <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 382-381</note> now
                        the infamy is yours. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You have followed
                        another leader: follow now Camillus, and, as your habit is when I am
                        leading, conquer. Why do you look on the rampart and the camp? Not one of
                        you shall find entrance there, save as a victor. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A sense of shame at first checked their
                    headlong flight; then, as they saw the standards face about and the line form up
                    against the enemy, while their general, distinguished for his many triumphs and
                    rendered venerable by his age, exposed himself at the front amidst the ensigns,
                    where the fighting and the danger were the greatest, they began each and every
                    one to cry out against themselves and their fellows, and their mutual
                    encouragements ran through the entire army in a ringing cheer. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was the other tribune behindhand, but being sent by his
                    colleague —who was re-forming the line of foot —to rally the horse, he did not
                    chide them —for his share in their fault would have made this of little use —but
                    turning wholly from commands to entreaties, he besought them one and all to save
                    him from the guilt of that day's mishap, for which he was responsible.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Notwithstanding,</quote> he said, <quote> the refusal and the opposition
                        of my colleague, I gave my adhesion to the general recklessness in
                        preference to the prudence of one man. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Camillus sees glory for himself, whichever way your fortune turns; but I, if
                        the battle is not restored, shall experience the utter misery of sharing
                        with everybody the disaster, while enduring the infamy alone. </quote> It
                    seemed best, as the battle-line was wavering, to dismiss the horses and attack
                    the enemy on foot. Conspicuous for their arms and their courage, they advanced
                    where <pb n="p.283"/> they saw the foot-soldiers hardest pressed. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Neither <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 382-381</note> generals nor soldiers relaxed their utmost
                    efforts, and the help afforded by their brave exertions was felt in the result.
                    The Volsci fled in a genuine panic over the ground where they had lately
                    pretended fear. Great numbers of them were slain both in the battle itself and
                    in the flight which followed; the others were cut down in the camp, which was
                    captured in the same charge; but more were made prisoners than were slain. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Niebuhr thinks that this battle was a
                        pure invention, for there is no indication that it had any effect: Satricum
                        was not taken, nor was a triumph decreed. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In taking account of the prisoners, they
                    recognized some as being Tusculans. These were separated from the rest and
                    brought before the tribunes, to whom they confessed, on being questioned, that
                    they had served at the bidding of the state. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The danger of so near a war disturbed Camillus, who declared that he would
                    straight-way carry the prisoners to Rome, that the Fathers might not be kept in
                    ignorance how the Tusculans had broken the alliance. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In the meantime he proposed that his colleague should, if
                    agreeable, take charge of the camp and the army. A single day had taught Lucius
                    Furius not to prefer his own to wiser counsels, yet neither he nor anyone in the
                    army supposed that Camillus would condone his fault, which had plunged the
                    commonwealth into such desperate peril; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and
                    everybody, not in the army only, but also in Rome, agreed in saying, that in the
                    ups and downs of the Volscian war, the responsibility for the defeat and flight
                    lay with Lucius Furius, and all the credit for the victory with Camillus.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But when the prisoners had been introduced
                    into the senate, and the Fathers, having decided that they must make war on
                    Tusculum, had <pb n="p.285"/> designated Camillus to conduct it, he requested
                    that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 382-381</note>
                    he might have a single lieutenant to assist him, and being permitted to select
                    any one of his colleagues whom he might desire, contrary to everybody's
                    expectation he selected Lucius Furius —an instance of magnanimity which, while
                    it lightened the disgrace of his colleague, also brought great honour to
                    himself. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But no war was, in fact, waged with the
                    Tusculans: by their steadfast adherence to peace they saved themselves from
                    violation by the Romans, as they could not have done by resorting to arms.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the Romans entered their territory,
                    they did not withdraw from the places near the line of march, nor break off
                    their labour in the fields; the gates of their city stood wide open; the
                    citizens, wearing the toga, came out in great numbers to meet the generals;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and provisions for the army were
                    obligingly brought into the camp from the city and the farms. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Camillus set up his camp before the gates, and desirous of
                    knowing whether the same aspect of peace prevailed within the walls that was
                    displayed in the country, entered the city and beheld the house-doors open, the
                    shops with their shutters off and all their wares exposed, the craftsmen all
                    busy at their respective trades, the schools buzzing with the voices of the
                    scholars, crowds in the streets, and women and children going about amongst the
                    rest, this way and that, as their several occasions called them —with <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> never anywhere an indication of surprise, much less
                    of fear. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He looked everywhere for any visible
                    evidence that a war had been on foot; but there was no sign that anything had
                    been either removed or brought out for the moment; everything looked so
                    undisturbed and <pb n="p.287"/> peaceful that it seemed scarce credible that so
                    much <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 382-381</note>
                    as a rumour of war should have come there. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Overcome therefore by the enemy's
                    submissiveness, he commanded their senate to be called. <quote>Men of
                        Tusculum,</quote> he said, <quote> until now you alone have discovered the
                        right weapons and the right resources with which to defend your possessions
                        from the resentment of the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Go to
                        Rome, to the senate; the Fathers will determine whether you have deserved
                        more punishment hitherto or pardon now. I will not forestall them by
                        accepting your gratitude for a favour that must be granted by the state;
                        from me you shall have an opportunity to solicit mercy; the answer to your
                        suit must be such as the senate sees fit to make. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the Tusculans arrived in Rome, and the
                    senators of a people who before had been faithful allies appeared in the
                    vestibule of the Curia, covered with dejection, the Fathers were straightway
                    moved, and in a spirit that had already more in it of hospitality than hostility
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For a similar play on words see I.
                        lviii. 8.</note> bade them be at once admitted. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Tusculan dictator thus addressed them: <quote> Though
                        you declared war on us and invaded our country, Conscript Fathers, we went
                        forth to meet your generals and your legions armed and accoutred exactly as
                        you now behold us standing in the entrance of your senate-house. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Such has ever been our garb and the garb of our
                        people —ay, and ever shall be —save at such times as we have been armed by
                        you and for your defence. We give thanks to your commanders and your armies,
                        since they have believed their eyes more than their ears, and where they
                        encountered no hostility, themselves have showed none. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The peace we have used towards you, we ask <pb
                            n="p.289"/> of you in return; direct your war, we beseech you, <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 382-381</note> to
                        that quarter where war, if anywhere, exists; if we must try, by suffering,
                        what your arms can achieve against ourselves, we will try unarmed.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such is our resolution; Heaven send it
                        be not less fortunate than loyal. As to the charges which stirred you to
                        declare a war, though it skills not to disprove with words what facts have
                        already confuted, still, even were they true, we think we might safely plead
                        guilty to them, since our repentance is so evident. Let men wrong you, so
                        long as you continue worthy to receive such amends. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> the honour done you by our confiding in your
                        mercy should outweigh the injury. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To this purport was the speech of the
                    Tusculans. They were granted peace for the present, and not long after were even
                    admitted to be citizens. The legions were withdrawn from Tusculum. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Renowned for his strategy and courage <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 380</note> in the
                    Volscian war and his success in the expedition against Tusculum, and for his
                    singular gentleness and generosity on both occasions towards his colleague,
                    Camillus laid down his office, after announcing the election of military
                    tribunes for the ensuing year. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The successful
                    candidates were Lucius and Publius Valerius (Lucius for the fifth and Publius
                    for the third time), Gaius Sergius (for the third time), Lucius Menenius (for
                    the second time), Publius Papirius, and Servius Cornelius Maluginensis.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was need also this year of censors,
                    chiefly on account of the uncertain reports which were going about in regard to
                    debt. The tribunes of the plebs even exaggerated the extent of this grievance,
                    whereas it was understated by those who were interested in having it appear that
                    loans were more in danger from the bad faith than the bad fortune of the
                    debtors. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The censors <pb n="p.291"/> chosen
                    were Gaius Sulpicius Camerinus and Spurius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 380</note> Postumius Regillensis, and
                    they had already set about their task, when it was interrupted by the death of
                    Postumius; for there were religious scruples against replacing the colleague of
                    a censor. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> v. xxxi. 6. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So then, Sulpicius resigned, and other censors
                    were elected, but, owing to a defect in the election, did not serve. The senate
                    could not bring itself to proceed to a third election, being persuaded that the
                    gods would permit no censorship that year. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But
                    this irresolution the tribunes characterized as an intolerable mockery of the
                    plebs. The senate, they said, was seeking to avoid the evidence of witnesses and
                    public records regarding the property of every man, because they were unwilling
                    it should be seen how great was the volume of debt, which would show that half
                    of the state had been ruined by the other half, while the debt-ridden plebs were
                    in the meantime being exposed to one enemy after another; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> wars were now sought indiscriminately, far and wide; from
                    Antium the legions had been marched to Satricum, from Satricum to Velitrae, from
                    there to Tusculum; now it was the Latins, the Hernici and the Praenestini who
                    were threatened with attack, more out of hatred of Rome's citizens than of her
                    enemies. The object was to wear the plebeians out with service and give them no
                    time to take breath in the City, or leisure to bethink them of liberty or to
                    stand in the assembly, where they might sometimes hear the voice of a tribune
                    urging the reduction of interest and the removal of their other grievances.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But if the plebs had the spirit to recall
                    their fathers' liberty, they would allow no Roman citizen to be bound to a
                    creditor, nor any levy to be held, until the amount of <pb n="p.293"/>
                    indebtedness had been examined and a plan for <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 380</note> lessening it put into
                    operation, that every man might know what was his own and what another's, and
                    whether his person was still free, or whether even that was owing to the gaol. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The reward held out to sedition soon brought
                    sedition to a head. For many were being bound over, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> , to their creditors, to work out their debts.
                    </note> and the senate had voted to enlist new levies on the rumour of
                    hostilities at Praeneste. Both these proceedings began at the same time to be
                    interfered with by the exercise of the tribunician protection and the common
                    action of the plebs; for the tribunes would not allow those who had been bound
                    over to be led away, nor would the young men give in their names. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The patricians were for the moment less concerned
                    with enforcing the law of debt than with the levy —not unnaturally, since the
                    enemy were reported as having already set out from Praeneste and encamped in the
                    territory of Gabii —but <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> on the tribunes of
                    the plebs this intelligence had acted more as an incentive to the struggle they
                    had undertaken than as a deterrent, and the only thing that was able to allay
                    the quarrel in the City was the approach of the enemy to its very walls. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For when the Praenestini were informed that no
                    army had been enrolled in Rome, that there was no one definitely in command,
                    that patricians and plebeians had turned against each other, their leaders
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> concluded that their opportunity had
                    come, and quickly putting their troops in motion, they devastated the fields
                    along their line of march and advanced against the Colline Gate. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Great was the consternation in the City. The call to
                    arms was given, and men hurried to the walls and gates. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They <pb n="p.295"/> had turned at last from domestic
                    strife to war, and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        380</note> proceeded to make Titus Quinctius Cincinnatus dictator, who named
                    Aulus Sempronius Atratinus master of the horse. No sooner was this known —so
                    great was the terror the dictatorship inspired —than the enemy at once withdrew
                    from before the walls, and the Romans of military age assembled without offering
                    objection, in accordance with the edict. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While the army was being enrolled at Rome, the
                    enemy had gone into camp not far from the Allia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> From this centre they pillaged in all directions, and boasted to one another
                    that they had occupied a position that was fraught with fate for the City of
                    Rome; there would be another rout there like the one in the Gallic war; for if
                    the Romans feared a day infected with evil omen and marked it with the name of
                    that place, how much more than the Day of the Allia would they dread the Allia
                    itself, that memorial of their great defeat? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They were sure to behold there apparitions of ruthless Gauls, and to have the
                    sound of their voices in their ears. Indulging these idle speculations on idle
                    themes, they had rested their hopes on the fortune of the place. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The Romans on the other hand were well assured that
                    wherever their Latin enemy was, he was one whom they had conquered at Lake
                    Regillus and had held in peaceable subjection for a hundred years; a place
                    notorious for the memory of disaster would rather inspire them to wipe out the
                    recollection of the disgrace than cause them to fear that any ground was
                    inauspicious for their victory; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> nay, if the
                    Gauls themselves should confront them on that spot, they would fight as they had
                    fought at Rome in recovering <pb n="p.297"/> their City and on the following day
                    at Gabii, when <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        380</note> they left no enemy who had entered the walls of Rome, to bear
                    home tidings either of weal or woe. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the feelings on either side when the
                    Romans arrived at the Allia. As they came within sight of the enemy, drawn up
                    and eager for the fray, the dictator addressed Sempronius. <quote>Do you
                        see,</quote> he said, <quote> how they have made their stand at the Allia,
                        putting their trust in the fortune of the place? We shall find the immortal
                        gods have given them no surer grounds for confidence nor any more
                        substantial help. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But do you confide in
                        arms and valour, and charge their centre at the gallop; I, with the legions,
                        will attack them when they are in disorder and confusion. Be with us, gods
                        of the treaty, and exact the penalties due to you for the injury you have
                        suffered and to us for the deception put upon us in your holy name! </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The men of Praeneste could cope with neither
                    horse nor foot. Their ranks were broken at the first shout and charge; then, as
                    their line yielded at every point, they turned and fled, and in their confusion
                    were carried even beyond their own camp; neither did they check their headlong
                    flight until they had come within sight of Praeneste. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> There the scattered remnants of the rout took up a position
                    which lent itself to hasty fortification, lest, if they sought refuge within the
                    walls, they might immediately find the torch put to their crops, and, after
                    losing everything, be subjected to a siege. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    But no sooner had the victorious Romans appeared, fresh from plundering the camp
                    on the Allia, than they abandoned these defences also, and, regarding even walls
                    as little enough protection, immured themselves in the town of Praeneste.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There were eight <pb n="p.299"/> other
                    towns which were under the sway of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 380</note> Praenestini. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Against these the Romans directed their campaign, and having taken them, with no
                    great exertion, one after the other, marched to Velitrae and stormed that place
                    also. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Coming then to Praeneste, the
                    fountain-head of the war, they got possession of it not by force but through
                    capitulation. Titus Quinctius had gained one pitched battle, captured two camps,
                    taken nine towns by assault, and received the surrender of Praeneste. He
                    returned to Rome bringing with him from Praeneste the image of Jupiter
                    Imperator. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This he bore in triumph to the
                    Capitol, where he dedicated it, between the shrine of Jupiter and that of
                    Minerva. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Below it he placed a tablet, in
                    commemoration of his deeds, with an inscription to the following effect: <quote>
                        Jupiter and all the gods granted Titus Quinctius the dictator that he should
                        take nine towns. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Festus (p. 363) the
                        offering was a golden crown weighing 2 1/3 lbs. </note> On the twentieth day
                    after his appointment he resigned the dictatorship. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the ensuing election of military tribunes
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 379</note> with
                    consular powers, patricians and plebeians came off alike. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Of the patricians Publius and Gaius Manlius were
                    successful, along with Lucius Julius; the plebs returned Gaius Sextilius, Marcus
                    Albinius, and Lucius Antistius. The Manlii were superior in birth to their
                    plebeian colleagues, and in popularity to Julius. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To them, therefore, by special enactment, without reference
                    to the lot or to mutual agreement, was given the command against the Volsci —an
                    honour which they rued in the upshot, as did also the senators who had conferred
                    it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Without reconnoitring they sent some
                    troops to forage, and believing them to be cut of, for they had received a false
                        <pb n="p.301"/> report that such was the case, they hastened to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 379</note> their
                    assistance, without so much as securing the author of the story —a Latin enemy
                    who had deceived them in the guise of a Roman soldier, —and plunged into an
                    ambuscade. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While they were making a stand
                    there on unfavourable ground, by the sheer courage of the men, who were selling
                    their lives dearly, the Roman camp which lay in the plain was attacked by the
                    enemy on the opposite side. In both places victory was thrown away by the
                    rashness and ignorance of the generals. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Whatever was left of the good fortune of the Roman People was saved by the pluck
                    of the soldiers, which continued steadfast even when it lacked guidance.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the announcement of these events at
                    Rome, it was at first resolved to appoint a dictator; but later, when word came
                    that things were quiet in the Volscian country, and it appeared that the enemy
                    knew not how to use his victory and opportunity, even the armies and commanders
                    which were there were withdrawn, and thereafter there was no trouble as far as
                    the Volsci were concerned; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the only
                    disturbance —towards the close of the year —was a mutiny of the Praenestini, who
                    had stirred the peoples of Latium to revolt. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That same year new colonists were enrolled for
                    Setia, whose inhabitants themselves were complaining of their lack of men. For
                    the ill success of the war there was consolation in the tranquillity at home,
                    which was due to the influence of the plebeian military tribunes and the honour
                    in which their order held them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following year started off in a blaze
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 378</note> of
                    party strife. The military tribunes with consular powers were Spurius Furius,
                    Quintus Servilius (for <pb n="p.303"/> the second time), Lucius Menenius (for
                    the third), <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        378</note> Publius Cloelius, Marcus Horatius, and Lucius Geganius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now the subject and reason of the strife
                    was debt. But when Spurius Servilius Priscus and Quintus Cloelius Siculus had
                    been made censors in order that they might investigate the situation, they were
                    prevented from doing so by a war; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for first
                    frightened messengers, and then the country-folk fleeing from the fields,
                    brought word that the Volscian legions had crossed the border, and were
                    everywhere devastating Roman territory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Yet
                    with all this alarm, the danger from abroad was so far from restraining
                    dissensions at home, that on the contrary the tribunes but acted with the
                    greater violence, in exerting their powers to block the levy; until the senate
                    submitted to their terms, and agreed that till the war was finished no one
                    should pay a war-tax or give judgment in a case of debt. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The plebs, on obtaining this relief, ceased to obstruct the
                    levy. When the new legions had been enrolled, it was resolved to divide them and
                    form two armies to invade the country of the Volsci. Spurius Furius and Marcus
                    Horatius marched to the right, towards Antium and the coast; Quintus Servilius
                    and Lucius Geganius to the left, in the direction of Ecetra and the mountains.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In neither region did they find the enemy.
                    They accordingly laid waste the country, not in the desultory fashion of the
                    Volsci, who like bandits, trusting in the discord of their foes but fearing
                    their courage, had made a hasty foray in fear and trembling, —but with a regular
                    army, justly provoked, and the more destructive in that they took more time.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In fact, the Volsci had confined their
                    pillaging to the borders, because of their fear lest an <pb n="p.305"/> army
                    might come out from Rome while they were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 378</note> at it; the Romans, on the
                    contrary, were partly actuated, in remaining on hostile ground, by the desire of
                    luring the enemy into a battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So they burned
                    all the farm-houses everywhere, and even certain villages, and leaving not a
                    single fruit-tree nor the standing corn with its hope of harvest, they carried
                    off as booty all the men and beasts outside the towns, and led both armies back
                    to Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The debtors had been given a little time <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 377</note> for
                    breathing, but no sooner did hostilities cease than the courts began once more
                    to be alive with prosecutions, and not only was there no prospect of obtaining
                    relief from the old debts, but further debts were incurred through the levying
                    of a tax to build a wall of hewn stone, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The reference is probably to a section of the city
                        wall, damaged in the Gallic war. </note> which the censors had contracted
                    for. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To this burden the plebs were forced to
                    submit, in the absence of any levy which their tribunes could obstruct.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The nobles even possessed sufficient
                    influence to oblige the plebs to elect all patricians to the millitary
                    tribunate; these were Lucius Aemilius, Publius Valerius (for the fourth time),
                    Gaius Veturius Servius Sulpicius, Lucius and Gaius Quinctius Cincinnatus.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The same influence enabled them to carry
                    through their plans against the Latins and the Volsci, who had united their
                    forces and were encamped near Satricum. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No one
                    objected when the men of military age were all compelled to take the oath, and
                    three armies were enrolled: one was intended to defend the City; another was for
                    use in sudden expeditions, if a revolt should break out anywhere; a third —much
                    the strongest —marched to Satricum, under Publius Valerius and Lucius Aemilius.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There they found the <pb n="p.307"/> enemy
                    drawn up in a strong position, and at once <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 377</note> attacked them; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and though victory was not yet assured, yet the
                    battle was in a hopeful state, when great gusts of wind brought on a heavy
                    downpour of rain and interrupted it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Next day
                    the combat was renewed, and for some little time the enemy —particularly the
                    Latin legions, schooled in Roman discipline by their long alliance —resisted
                    with equal courage and success. But the cavalry were sent against them and threw
                    their ranks into confusion, and before they could recover, the infantry were
                    upon them; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> in proportion as the Roman line
                    advanced, was the enemy forced out of his position; and when once the tide of
                    battle turned, there was no stopping the onrush of the Romans. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The routed enemy made for Satricum, two miles away, instead
                    of their camp, and suffered great slaughter, especially at the hands of the
                    cavalry. Their camp was taken and sacked. The night after the battle they fled
                    rather than marched towards Antium; and though the Roman army followed hard
                    after, fear proved swifter than wrath. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So the
                    enemy got within the walls before the Romans could harass or delay their rear. A
                    few days were then consumed in ravaging the land, since the Romans had not
                    enough equipment to attack the walls, nor the enemy to risk a battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A quarrel now broke out between the Antiates
                    and the Latins. The men of Antium, overwhelmed by their misfortunes and worn out
                    by a war which had lasted from their birth to their old age <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These words are really applicable to
                        the Volsci in general, but not to the Antiates in particular. In § 4 the
                        word <hi rend="italics">Volscos</hi> is used as though equivalent to <hi
                            rend="italics">Antiates.</hi>
                    </note> were minded to capitulate: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the Latins
                    had but just revolted after a long peace; their spirits were still fresh; and
                    they meant to continue boldly with <pb n="p.309"/> the war. The dispute came to
                    an end as soon as <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        377</note> each party saw that the other could not prevent it in any way
                    from carrying out its policy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Latins
                    departed, and freed themselves from all share in what they considered a
                    degrading peace; the Antiates, being rid of inconvenient witnesses to their
                    salutary measures, surrendered their city and lands to the Romans. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The frenzied wrath of the Latins sought relief —since
                    they could neither do the Romans any injury in war nor retain the Volsci under
                    arms —in burning Satricum, the town which had been their first place of refuge
                    after their defeat. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They applied the torch
                    without discrimination both to sacred and to secular buildings, and not one
                    escaped destruction, except the temple of Mater Matuta; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> An ancient Italian deity worshipped by matrons and
                        having to do with birth, and perhaps with the dawn. She had a temple in Rome
                        and in Praeneste, and appears to have been the principal god of Satricum.
                    </note> from this they were kept away, according to the story, neither by their
                    own scruples, nor by their reverence for the gods, but by an awe-inspiring voice
                    that issued from the temple and threatened dire retribution if they did not
                    remove those impious fires to a distance from the sacred walls. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Crazed and infuriated, a sudden impulse carried them to
                    Tusculum. They were angry that the Tusculans had deserted the common council of
                    the Latins and had yielded themselves to be not only allies but citizens of
                    Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The gates were open, for their attack
                    was unexpected, and the first shout had not died away when the town was taken,
                    all except the citadel. To this the townsfolk fled for safety, with their wives
                    and children, and sent off messengers to Rome to let the senate know of their
                    predicament. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With a promptness worthy of the
                    honour of the Roman People, an army marched to Tusculum, commanded by the
                    military tribunes Lucius Quinctius <pb n="p.311"/> and Servius Sulpicius.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They found the gates of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 377</note> Tusculum
                    closed and the Latins at once besiegers and besieged; on the one hand they were
                    defending the walls of the town, on the other assailing the fortress, and they
                    experienced themselves the same terror they inspired. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The arrival of the Romans produced a change in the spirits
                    of both sides: the Tusculans were roused from the depths of despair to the
                    greatest cheerfulness; the Latins, who had felt almost certain that since the
                    town was theirs they would soon possess the citadel, were reduced almost to
                    despair of their own lives. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Tusculans in
                    the citadel gave a cheer and were answered by one much louder from the Roman
                    army. On both sides the Latins were hard pressed: they could neither resist the
                    charges of the townsmen, as they rushed down from above, nor drive back the
                    Romans, who were coming up under the walls and forcing the bars of the gates.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The walls were first scaled and captured;
                    then the fastenings of the gates were burst. The Latins were caught between two
                    enemies, who assailed them hotly in front and rear; they had no strength to
                    fight and no room to escape, and were slain where they stood, to the very last
                    man. Having recovered Tusculum from its enemies, the army returned to Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But in proportion as the successful wars of
                    that year had everywhere secured tranquillity abroad, in the City the violence
                    of the patricians and the sufferings of the plebs were increasing from one day
                    to another, since the very fact that payment was compulsory made it more
                    difficult to pay. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And so, now that a man could
                    make no compensation with his property, his reputation and his person <pb
                        n="p.313"/> were made over and assigned to his creditor by way <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 377</note> of
                    satisfaction, and punishment had come to take the place of payment. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> So abject indeed was the surrender not only of the
                    lowest of the plebs but even of their leaders, that, far from contending with
                    patricians for the military tribuneship —a <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    privilege for which they had striven with such energy —there was not a man of
                    them of sufficient force and enterprise to seek or to administer the plebeian
                    magistracies. The patricians seemed therefore to have regained possession in
                    perpetuity of an office which the plebeians had merely assumed for some few
                    years. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That this state of affairs might not inspire
                    excessive joy in the patricians, a trivial cause —as often happens —set on foot
                    a mighty change. Marcus Fabius Ambustus <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Father of the three envoys to the Gauls whose story is
                        told at v. xxxv.-xxxvi. </note> was very influential, not only amongst his
                    fellows, but with the plebs as well, for the members of that class felt that he
                    was far from looking down upon it. This man had married his two daughters, the
                    elder to Servius Sulpicius, the younger to Gaius Licinius Stolo, a man of mark,
                    albeit a plebeian; and the very fact that he had not rejected such an alliance
                    had won regard for Fabius with the common people. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> It fell out that the sisters Fabia were together in the
                    house of Servius Sulpicius, then a consular tribune, and were whiling away the
                    time in talk, as women will, when a lictor of Sulpicius, who was returning from
                    the Forum, rapped on the door, in the usual manner, with his rod. At this the
                    younger Fabia, being unused to the custom, went white, which made the elder
                    laugh with surprise at her sister's ignorance. But that laugh rankled in the
                    other's mind, for a woman's feelings <pb n="p.315"/> are influenced by trifles.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I suppose, too, that the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 37</note> crowd of
                    people who attended the tribune and took a ceremonious leave of him made her
                    look upon her sister's marriage as a fortunate one and regret her own, in that
                    ill-judging spirit which makes us all so very loath to be outdone by our nearest
                    friends. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> She was still suffering from the
                    smart of wounded pride, when her father, happening to see her, asked if anything
                    was wrong. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> She would fain have concealed the
                    reason of her grief, which was too little consistent with sisterly affection and
                    did no great honour to her husband; but he brought her by tender inquiries to
                    confess that she was unhappy in being mated to one beneath her, having married
                    into a house where neither dignities nor influence could enter. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Ambustus then comforted his daughter and bade her be
                    of good cheer: she would see ere long in her own home the same state she beheld
                    at her sister's. <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> From that moment he began
                    to make plans with his son-in-law, taking into their counsels also Lucius
                    Sextius, a strenuous youth, whose aspirations were thwarted only by his lack of
                    patrician blood. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An opportunity for innovation was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 375-371</note>
                    presented by the enormous load of debt, which the plebs could have no hope of
                    lightening but by placing their representatives in the highest offices. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy has omitted the military tribunes
                        for A.U.C. 378 = B.C. 376. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They therefore argued that they must gird
                    themselves to think of this: with toil and effort the plebeians had already
                    advanced so far that it was in their power, if they continued to exert
                    themselves, to reach the highest ground, and to equal the patricians in honours
                    as well as in worth. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For the present it was
                    resolved that Gaius Licinius and <pb n="p.317"/> Lucius Sextius should be
                    elected tribunes of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B.C. 375-379</note> plebs, a magistracy in which they might open for
                    themselves a way to the other distinctions. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Once elected, they proposed only such measures as abated the influence of the
                    patricians, while forwarding the interests of the plebs. One of these had to do
                    with debt, providing that what had been paid as interest should be deducted from
                    the original sum, and the remainder discharged in three annual instalments of
                    equal size. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A second set a limit on lands,
                    prohibiting anyone from holding more than five hundred <hi rend="italics"
                        >iugera.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This law appears to have had
                        reference only to the public lands. The reduction of excessive holdings was
                        intended to make the land accommodate a large number of poorer tenants. In
                        the year <date when="-0357">357 B.C.</date> Licinius was punished for
                        transgressing his own law (vii. xvi. 9). </note> A third did away with the
                    election of military tribunes, and prescribed that of the consuls one, at any
                    rate, should be chosen from the plebs. These were all matters of great moment,
                    and it would not be possible to carry them without a tremendous struggle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now when all the things that men immoderately
                    covet, lands, money, and promotion, were jeopardized at once, the patricians
                    became thoroughly alarmed; and failing, after frightened conference in public
                    and private gatherings, to devise any other remedy than that veto which they had
                    already tried before in many struggles, provided themselves with friends amongst
                    the colleagues of the tribunes, to oppose their measures. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> These men, seeing Licinius and Sextius summon the tribes to
                    vote, came up in the midst of a body-guard of patricians, and refused to permit
                    the bills to be recited or anything else to be done that was usual in passing a
                    resolution of the plebs. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And now the assembly
                    had been summoned repeatedly without avail, and the rogations were as though
                    they had been voted down, when Sextius cried out, <quote> So be it! Since it is
                        your pleasure that <pb n="p.319"/> the intercession should be so powerful,
                        we will use <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                            375-371</note> that very weapon for the protection of the plebs.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Come now, senators, and proclaim an
                        assembly for the choice of military tribunes; I warrant you shall have no
                        joy of that word <hi rend="italics">veto,</hi> which you now hear with such
                        satisfaction from the chorus of our colleagues. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> His threats were no idle ones: except for the
                    aediles and tribunes of the plebs, there was not an election held. Licinius and
                    Sextius were chosen again, and suffered no curule magistrates to be elected; and
                    this dearth of magistrates continued in the City for five years, while the plebs
                    continued to re-elect the two men tribunes, and they to prevent the election of
                    military tribunes. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was fortunately a respite from <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 370-369</note> other
                    wars, but the colonists of Velitrae, growing insolent in time of peace, because
                    they knew that the Romans had no army, not only made several incursions into
                    Roman territory, but went so far as to lay siege to Tusculum. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This circumstance affected not only the senators but even
                    the plebeians; that the Tusculans, who had long been their friends and were now
                    their fellow citizens, should be imploring aid filled them with shame.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the plebs relaxing their
                    opposition, elections were held by an interrex, which resulted in the choice of
                    the following military tribunes: Lucius Furius, Aulus Manlius, Servius
                    Sulpicius, Servius Cornelius, and Publius and Gaius Valerius. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They found the plebs much less submissive to the levy than
                    they had been to the election; but by strenuous efforts they enrolled an army,
                    and, marching out, not only drove the enemy away from <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> Tusculum, but even shut him up within his own walls, and
                    Velitrae was besieged with far <pb n="p.321"/> more vigour than Tusculum had
                    been. Yet those <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        370-369</note> who had begun the siege were not able to conclude it before
                    the election of new military tribunes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    candidates chosen were Quintus Servilius, Gaius Veturius, Aulus and Marcus
                    Cornelius, Quintus Quinctius, and Marcus Fabius. Even these tribunes
                    accomplished nothing memorable at Velitrae. </p>
                <p> At home the situation was more dangerous. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For
                    besides Sextius and Licinius, who had proposed the laws and were now for the
                    eighth time re-elected tribunes of the plebs, the military tribune Fabius,
                    Stolo's father-in-law, was openly advocating the adoption of the measures he had
                    himself suggested. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And whereas there had been
                    at first eight members of the college of plebeian tribunes who opposed the
                    bills, there were now but five; and these, puzzled and confounded, as is apt to
                    be the case with men who forsake their party, were no more than mouthpieces,
                    repeating in justification of their vetoes only what they had been privately
                    schooled to say, to wit, that a majority of the plebeians were absent at
                    Velitrae with the army; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and that the
                    assemblies ought to be put off until the return of the soldiers, so that the
                    entire body of the plebs might vote on matters that concerned them. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Sextius and Licinius, with some of their colleagues
                    and one of the military tribunes, Fabius, being experts now —after so many years
                    of practice —in the art of playing on the passions of the commons, would bring
                    the leading senators forward and ply them with questions about each of the
                    measures they were laying before the people: Had they the hardihood to demand
                    that, when land was being assigned to the plebs in parcels of two <hi
                        rend="italics">iugera,</hi> they themselves should be authorized to hold
                    more <pb n="p.323"/> than five hundred <hi rend="italics">iugera?</hi>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Did they desire that single <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 370-369</note>
                    patricians should possess the allotments of almost three hundred citizens; and
                    that the plebeian should have a farm scarce large enough to contain a shelter
                    for his necessities or a place of burial? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Or
                    was it their wish that the plebs, undone with usury, should give up their bodies
                    to imprisonment and torture, instead of paying the principal sums they owed? Did
                    they mean every day to drag off gangs of condemned debtors from the Forum? to
                    fill with prisoners the houses of the nobles? to make of every patrician's
                    dwelling a private gaol? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The shame and pity of these conditions awoke
                    more indignation in their hearers, who feared for their own safety, than the
                    speakers had themselves felt in denouncing them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> And yet the patricians —as they proceeded to assert —would never check their
                    greed for land, nor cease murdering the plebs with usury, until the commons
                    should elect one of the two consuls from their own number, to guard their
                    liberties. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Contempt, they argued, was now
                    become the portion of the plebeian tribunes, for they used the veto to break
                    down their own power. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There could be no
                    question of equal rights, where the other side commanded and they themselves
                    could do nothing but protest. Until they shared in the authority, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Imperium,</hi> which the tribunes of the plebs did not
                        possess. </note> the plebs would never have an equal footing in the state.
                    And let no one think that it would be sufficient if plebeians were accepted as
                    candidates at the consular elections: unless it were required that at least one
                    consul must be chosen from the commons, none ever would be. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Had they already forgotten, that although the election of
                    tribunes of the soldiers rather than <pb n="p.325"/> consuls had been resolved
                    upon, expressly in order <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B.C. 370-369</note> that the highest honour might be open even to
                    plebeians, yet for four and forty years no commoner had been chosen to that
                    office? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> How could they suppose, that with two
                    places only now available, the patricians would of their own volition bestow the
                    office on the plebs, when they had habitually claimed eight places in electing
                    military tribunes? Would those men allow the consulship to be approached, who
                    had blocked so long the road to the tribuneship? <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> The law must make good for them what they could not gain by favour at the
                    elections; one of the two consulships must be set apart for the undisputed use
                    of the plebs, for if left in dispute it would always fall a prize to the more
                    powerful. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Neither could it any longer be
                    maintained —as the nobles had been wont to assert — that among the plebeians
                    were none who were suitable for curule magistracies. Had the public
                    administration been a jot more indifferent or slipshod since the tribuneship of
                    Publius Licinius Calvus, who was the first man elected from the plebs, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In <date when="-0400">400 B.C.</date>
                        (v. xii. 9). </note> than it had been during those years in which none but
                    patricians had been military tribunes? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nay, on
                    the contrary, several patricians had been impeached after holding the
                    tribuneship, but not one plebeian. Quaestors, too, like military tribunes, had
                    begun a few years before to be elected from the commons, nor had the Roman
                    People regretted it in a single case. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    consulship remained for the commons to achieve; this was the citadel of liberty,
                    this its pillar. If they attained to this, then would the Roman People hold that
                    the kings had been really driven from the City, and their freedom <pb n="p.327"
                    /> firmly based; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for the commons would
                    thenceforward <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        319-369</note> be partakers in all that made the patricians now surpass
                    them, —authority and honour, martial renown, birth and nobility, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The nobles were those who had held —or
                        whose ancestors had held —curule chairs. Originally nobility had been
                        confined to the patriciate, with which, indeed —since most patrician
                        families could point to some office-holding ancestor, —it had been
                        practically identical. The new nobility comprised plebeians as well as
                        patricians, and owing to the tendency of the electorate to continue the same
                        families in office, it became almost as exclusive a body as the old
                        patriciate. </note> —great things for themselves to enjoy, but even greater
                    to bequeath to their children. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Perceiving that speeches of this sort were
                    well received, they introduced a new measure, providing that in place of two men
                    vested with superintendence of the sacred rites, a board of ten should be
                    elected, with a proviso that half the number should be of the plebs, and half
                    patricians; the voting on all these bills they deferred until the return of the
                    army which was besieging Velitrae. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A year rolled round before the legions <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 368</note> could be
                    brought back from Velitrae; consequently the question of the laws remained in
                    abeyance and was put off until the coming in of the new military tribunes; for
                    as to the tribunes of the plebs, the commons chose the same men over again —the
                    two, at any rate, who had brought in the bills. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The military tribunes chosen were Titus Quinctius, Servius Cornelius, Servius
                    Sulpicius, Spurius Servilius, Lucius Papirius, and Lucius Veturius. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> At the very outset of the year came a final struggle
                    over the laws; and when the tribes were summoned to vote, and the proposers of
                    the measures would not yield to the vetoes of their colleagues, the frightened
                    patricians were put to their two last shifts —the greatest office, and the
                    greatest of the citizens. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They voted to name a
                    dictator, and appointed Marcus Furius Camillus, who chose Lucius Aemilius for
                    his master of the horse. To meet these formidable preparations of their
                    adversaries, the proposers <pb n="p.329"/> of the laws on their side armed the
                    commons with <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        368</note> tremendous enthusiasm for the cause, and proclaiming a council of
                    the plebs, called up the tribes to vote. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Attended by a body of patricians, and
                    breathing wrath and menaces, the dictator took his seat, and the affair began
                    with the usual skirmish between the tribunes of the plebs, some of whom urged
                    the passing of the law while others interposed their vetoes. But powerful as the
                    veto was on the legal side, it was being overcome by the popularity of the bills
                    themselves and their proposers, and the tribes which had been summoned first
                    were voting <quote>Ay,</quote> when Camillus addressed the people. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Quirites,</quote> he said, <quote> since you are now swayed not by the
                        authority of the tribunes but by their lawlessness, and are bringing to
                        naught the right of protest —obtained through the secession of the plebs
                        —with the same violence with which you won it; for your own sake no less
                        than for the sake of tile whole republic, I shall, as dictator, sustain the
                        veto, and safeguard with my absolute authority your defence which you are
                        overthrowing. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If then Gaius Licinius and
                        Lucius Sextius yield to the protest of their colleagues, I will in no way
                        intrude a patrician magistracy upon a council of the plebs; but if, in
                        defiance of the protest, they try to impose their terms, as though upon a
                        conquered state, I will not permit the tribunician power to work its own
                        undoing. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This warning the tribunes treated with
                    contempt, and were proceeding with unabated energy to carry out their plans,
                    when Camillus, in high dudgeon, sent his lictors to turn the commons out; and
                    threatened, that if they continued in their course, he would <pb n="p.331"/>
                    administer the oath to all of military age, and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 368</note> forthwith lead the army out
                    of the City. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The plebs were greatly dismayed; but the
                    courage of their leaders was rather kindled than damped by his vehemence. Yet
                    before the matter had been decided either way, Camillus resigned his office,
                    whether because there had been a flaw in his election —as certain writers have
                    held —or because the tribunes proposed to the plebs and the plebs decreed, that
                    if Marcus Furius should take any action in the capacity of dictator, he should
                    be fined five hundred thousand asses. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But
                    that the auspices, and not a law without a precedent, were responsible for his
                    withdrawal, the very nature of the man inclines me to believe; also the fact
                    that Publius Manlius was at once made dictator in his place —for what good would
                    his appointment do, in a struggle in which Marcus Furius had been beaten?
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Besides, Marcus Furius himself was
                    dictator again in the following year, and he would surely have been ashamed to
                    resume an authority which had broken down in his own hands the year before.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Moreover at the time when the proposal to
                    fine him is said to have been made, either he had the power to resist this order
                    —which <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> deprived him, as he could see, of all
                    authority, —or else he lacked the power to obstruct even those measures in
                    defence of which this order had been proposed. Finally, whatever conflicts have
                    occurred between tribunes and consuls, down to the times we can ourselves
                    remember, the dictatorship has always towered above them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the interval between the abdication of the
                    earlier dictator and the entrance upon his office of the new one, Manlius, the
                    tribunes —as <pb n="p.333"/> though there were an interregnum <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the consular tribunes counted for nothing, and
                        the tribunes of the plebs could proceed without let or hindrance. </note>
                    —held a council <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        368</note> of the plebs, and it became evident which of the measures
                    proposed were more acceptable to the plebeians, and which to their introducers.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For the tribes were on the point of
                    passing the bills relating to interest and land, and of rejecting the one about
                    the plebeian consul, and both policies would have been finally <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> disposed of, if the tribunes had not said that they
                    were putting all these questions to the plebs collectively. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then Publius Manlius, becoming dictator, gave the affair a
                    turn in favour of the plebs by naming Gaius Licinius, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Not the tribune of the plebs, but possibly his father.
                        Livy perhaps included him among the consular tribunes for <date when="-0378"
                            >378 B.C.</date> ( <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> chap. xxxi. § 1; where
                        the text is uncertain) or should have included him among those for the year
                            <date when="-0376">376 B.C.</date> , but has omitted the entire list
                        (chap. xxxiv). <hi rend="italics">Diod.</hi> xv. 57, gives Gaius Licinius as
                        one of four consular tribunes for the year <date when="-0378">378
                            B.C.</date>
                    </note> who had been military tribune and was a commoner, his master of the
                    horse. I find that the patricians took offence at this, but that the dictator
                    was wont to excuse himself to them by alleging his close relationship to
                    Licinius, and asserting that a master of the horse possessed no greater
                    authority than a consular tribune. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Licinius and Sextius, when an assembly had
                    been proclaimed for the election of plebeian tribunes, so bore themselves that
                    while professing an unwillingness to be re-elected, they furnished the plebs
                    with the strongest incentives to give them what they pretended not to covet.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They said it was now nine years that they
                    had stood embattled, as it were, against the optimates, with the greatest danger
                    to themselves and no advantage to the public. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The measures they had proposed and the whole power of the tribunate had, like
                    themselves, grown old and useless. First the intercession of their colleagues
                    had been employed to attack their laws; then the young men had been banished to
                    the seat of war at Velitrae; finally they had themselves been menaced <pb
                        n="p.335"/> with the thunderbolt of the dictatorship. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> At present <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 368</note> they were thwarted neither by their colleagues,
                    nor by war, nor even by the dictator, for he had actually given them a presage
                    of plebeian consuls by appointing a plebeian master of the horse: <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> no, it was the plebs themselves who stood in the way
                    of their own advancement. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A City and a Forum
                    rid of creditors, and lands delivered from unlawful occupation, were things they
                    might enjoy at once, if they would. When, pray, did they expect to weigh these
                    blessings and be duly grateful, if at the very moment of entertaining measures
                    for their own advantage they cut off all hope of office from the men who
                    introduced them? It was not like the reasonableness of the Roman People to ask
                    to be relieved themselves of usury and settled on lands which the nobles had
                    unjustly held, while leaving the men to whom they owed these advantages to grow
                    old as tribunicians —not only without honours, but even without the hope of
                    them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So let them first make up their minds
                    what it was they wished; and then declare their wishes at the election of the
                    tribunes. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If they desired to enact together
                    the measures which the tribunes had brought forward, there was some reason for
                    re-electing them; for they would carry through what they had advocated; but if
                    every man cared only for the adoption of such clauses as concerned him
                    personally, there was no use in an invidious prolongation of their term; they
                    would do without the tribuneship, and the people would do without the proposed
                    reforms. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On hearing the tribunes make this stubborn
                    speech, though the other senators were dazed and dumbfounded by such outrageous
                    arguments, they <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.337"/> say that Appius Claudius Crassus, the decemvir's <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 368</note> grandson,
                    moved more by hate and resentment than by hope, came forward to oppose them, and
                    spoke to the following purpose: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> "It would be
                    no strange or surprising thing to me, Quirites, if on this occasion I, too,
                    should be taunted with the one reproach that rebellious tribunes have ever
                    directed at our family, to wit, that the Claudian gens from its very origin has
                    regarded no feature of our public life as more important than the majesty of the
                    senate and has always opposed the interests of the plebs. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The former of these charges I neither deny nor seek to
                    refute —namely, that we have striven with all our might, from the day we were
                    first called to be citizens and senators, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See ii. xvi. 4-5.</note> that, so far as in us lay, the
                    dignity of those families with which you proposed to rank us might truthfully be
                    said to have rather gained than lost; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> as to
                    the other charge, I would venture to maintain, Quirites, speaking for myself and
                    for my forefathers, that unless one should assume that what is done for the good
                    of the whole nation is opposed to the welfare of the plebs, —as though they
                    inhabited another city, —we have never wittingly done anything, whether as
                    private citizens or magistrates, disadvantageous to the plebs; and that no word
                    or act of ours can be truthfully alleged as being against your interests, though
                    some there may have been which ran counter to your wishes. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But were I not a Claudius, nor sprung from a patrician
                    line, but were merely any one of the Quirites, assuming only that I knew my
                    parents had both been born to freedom and that I lived in a free state, could I
                    pass this by in silence? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Are Lucius Sextius
                    yonder and Gaius Licinius, our perpetual tribunes — <pb n="p.339"/> save the
                    mark! —grown so presumptuous in the nine <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 368</note> years of their reign, as to
                    threaten that they will leave you free to exercise your right of suffrage
                    neither in elections nor in enacting laws? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "' On a certain condition,' says one of them,
                    ' you shall elect us tribunes for the tenth time '; as though he were to say,'
                    What others sue for we are so surfeited withal that we will not accept it
                    without a great reward.' <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But what in short is
                    that reward by the grant of which we may always have you for tribunes of the
                    plebs? ' That you adopt,' says he, 'all our rogations in a lump, whether you
                    like them or detest them, —be they good or bad.' <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> I beseech you, Tarquin tribunes of the plebs, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.,</hi> tribunes as tyrannical as the Tarquin kings.
                    </note> imagine me a simple citizen calling out from the midst of the assembly,
                    ' By your good leave, suffer us to choose from these proposals those we regard
                    as wholesome for us, and to reject the rest.' <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    'No,' he answers, 'you shall not have leave to enact the measures that concern
                    you all, touching interest and lands, unless you will put up with the monstrous
                    sight in Rome of Lucius Sextius and Gaius Licinius here as consuls —an idea you
                    loathe and abominate; —accept everything, or I offer nothing.' <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> As though a man were starving, and one should serve poison
                    to him with his food, and command him either to abstain from what would give him
                    life, or mix the deadly with the life-giving. Well then! If this state were
                    free, would not the people have cried out to you in full assembly, 'Begone, with
                    your tribuneships and your rogations!' Come! If you will not propose what is
                    profitable to the people to accept, shall there be none to do it? <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Suppose that some patrician, or —what those fellows
                    would make out to be still more hateful —some <pb n="p.341"/> Claudius, should
                    say, ' Either take all or I will propose <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 368</note> nothing,' which of you,
                    Quirites, would endure it? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Will you never
                    choose rather to look at facts than at advocates, but always lend ready ears to
                    the utterances of that noble magistrate, and refuse to hear what is said by any
                    of us? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> " <hi rend="italics">His language,</hi> you
                    will admit, is far from appropriate in a free state; well, what of his <hi
                        rend="italics">rogation,</hi> which they resent your refusal to accept?
                    Quirites, it is all of a piece with his words. ' I propose,' he says, 'that it
                    shall not be permitted you to choose such consuls as you will.' <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> For can aught else be his meaning, when he commands
                    that in any case one consul be chosen from the plebs, and deprives you of the
                    power to name two patricians? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> If wars should
                    arise in these days, like the Etruscan war, when Porsinna held Janiculum, or
                    like the Gallic war a little while ago, when all this City —except the Capitol
                    and the Citadel —was in the hands of your enemies; and if Lucius Sextius were
                    standing for the consulship, along with Marcus Furius here, and any other
                    patrician whomsoever; could you endure that Lucius Sextius should be certain of
                    election, while Camillus had to risk defeat? <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Is it thus they would equalize the opportunities of office? Would they authorize
                    the election of two plebeian consuls, and forbid the choice of two patricians?
                    Must we perforce take one plebeian, while for both places we may pass the
                    patricians by? What sort of fellowship, of partnership, is this? Are you not
                    satisfied to get a part of that in which you had no part before, unless in
                    reaching for the part you can seize the whole? <milestone n="19" unit="section"
                    /> 'I fear' he replies, 'lest if it be permitted to choose two patricians, you
                    may <pb n="p.343"/> choose no one from the plebs.' His meaning is: <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 368</note> 'Since of
                    your own accord you will never choose unworthy men, I will make it obligatory on
                    you to elect those whom you do not wish.' <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    What follows? Why, a man would not owe the people so much as thanks, if he were
                    the sole plebeian candidate along with two patricians: he would say that he had
                    been elected not by your suffrages, but by the statute. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "They would force us, not invite us, to grant
                    them office; and thus they mean to win the very highest honours without
                    incurring even such obligations as would be imposed by the least important. They
                    would make their canvass not on worth but on opportunity. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> There is many a man who resents being investigated and
                    appraised, who thinks it right that he alone should be certain of success, while
                    his competitors are struggling for office; who would withdraw himself from your
                    judgment; who would have you vote for him from compulsion, not from choice —not
                    as freemen, but as slaves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I say nothing of
                    Licinius and Sextius, whose years of continuous power you reckon like those of
                    the kings on the Capitol: <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Statues of
                        the kings were set up on the Capitol, and on their bases were recorded the
                        years they had reigned. But this had not yet been done in <date when="-0368"
                            >368 B.C.</date>
                    </note> who is there in the state to-day so lowly that the opportunities
                    afforded by that law would not make access to the consulship easier for him than
                    for us and for our children? To elect us will sometimes be beyond your power,
                    even though you wish it; but those persons you would be compelled to elect, even
                    against your inclinations. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Of the indignity of the thing I have said enough. But dignity after all
                        is concerned with men: what of religious observances and auspices —for the
                        immortal gods are involved in insult and disrespect to these? That this City
                        was founded under auspices; <pb n="p.345"/> that all measures, warlike and
                        peaceful, at home and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                            >B.C. 368</note> in the field, are carried out with auspices, who does
                        not know? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Who then control the auspices,
                        by the tradition of our fathers? The patricians, to be sure; for no plebeian
                        magistrate is elected under auspices; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the
                        auspices belong so exclusively to us, that not only are the patrician
                        magistrates whom the people elect no otherwise elected than with auspices,
                        but we ourselves even —without the people's suffrage —take auspices and
                        nominate an interrex; and have, as private citizens, the right of taking
                        them, which you plebeians have not even in your magistracies. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> He therefore deprives the state outright of
                        auspices, who by electing plebeian consuls deprives the patricians of them
                        —for they alone can take them. They may jeer now, if they like, at religious
                        scruples. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> 'After all,' they will say,
                        'what difference does it make if the sacred chickens <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> The speaker alludes to two kinds of omens: (1) the
                            general took with him to the field a coop of chickens, and if these, on
                            being offered corn, came out and devoured it with avidity, the presage
                            was favourable; this kind of divination was called <hi rend="italics">ex
                                tripudiis,</hi> from the way the corns danced upon the ground as
                            they fell from the beaks of the greedy fowls; (2) the flight of certain
                            birds was observed and any noise —such as the cry of a bird —was held to
                            vitiate the auspice. </note> will not feed; if they are slow to come out
                        from the coop; if a bird utters an ill-omened cry? ' These are trivial
                        things; but because they did not scorn these trivial things, your fathers
                        were able to build this great republic; and now we, as though we had no
                        further use for Heaven's favour, are polluting all <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> the ceremonies. Let pontiffs then, augurs, and kings of
                        the sacrifices, be chosen from the vulgar herd; let us set the mitre of the
                        Flamen Dialis on anybody's head, so he but be a man; let us make over the
                        sacred shields, the inner shrine, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            In the Atrium of Vesta, where among other relies was preserved the
                            Palladium. </note> the gods and the service of the gods, to those whom
                        we may not without sin intrust <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> with them;
                        let laws be proposed and magistrates elected <pb n="p.347"/> without the
                        approval of the auspices; neither to <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 386</note> centuriate nor curiate
                        comitia let the fathers give their sanction; let Sextius and Licinius bear
                        sway in Rome, like Romulus and Tatius —because they give away the moneys and
                        the lands <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> of others. Is it so sweet to
                        plunder others of their fortunes? Does it not occur to them that one of
                        their laws will make vast deserts in the country-side, by driving the
                        landlords out from their demesnes, while the other will wipe out credit, and
                        with it all <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> human intercourse? Upon every
                        account I urge you to reject these bills; and may Heaven prosper what you
                        do! </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The speech of Appius availed no further <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 367</note> than to put
                    off the passing of the measures. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Returned for
                    the tenth time to office, the tribunes Sextius and Licinius obtained the
                    enactment of a law requiring that half the board of ten who had charge of sacred
                    rites should be plebeians. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See chap.
                        xxxvii. § 12.</note> Having elected five patricians and five plebeians, the
                    people felt that they had set a precedent for the consulship. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Satisfied with their victory, the plebs gave way to the
                    patricians, and relinquishing for the moment discussion about the consuls,
                    permitted the election of military tribunes. Those chosen were Aulus and Marcus
                    Cornelius (for their second terms), Marcus Geganius, Publius Manlius, Lucius
                    Veturius, and (for the sixth time) Publius Valerius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Rome's foreign relations were now peaceful
                    everywhere except for the siege of Velitrae —the result of which, though
                    delayed, was scarce in doubt —when a sudden rumour of a Gallic war drove the
                    state to appoint Marcus Furius to his fifth dictatorship. He nominated Titus
                    Quinctius Poenus to be <pb n="p.349"/> master of the horse. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Claudius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Quintus
                        Claudius Quadrigarius, the annalist, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Vol. I.,
                        introd., p. xxx, and note 2. </note> relates that the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 367</note> battle with the Gauls took
                    place that year near the river Anio; and that this was the occasion of the
                    famous duel on the bridge in which Titus Manlius slew a Gaul who had challenged
                    him to combat, and despoiled him of his chain, while the two armies looked on.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But I am more inclined to believe, with
                    the majority of our authorities, that this exploit took place no less than ten
                    years later, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy himself narrates
                        the episode as having occurred <hi rend="italics">six</hi> years later cf.
                        Book VII. chapters ix-x. ( <date when="-0361">361 B.C.</date> ). </note> and
                    that in the year of which I am now writing, the dictator, Marcus Furius, fought
                    a battle against the Gauls on Alban soil. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Notwithstanding the great terror occasioned by the invasion of the Gauls and the
                    recollection of their old defeat, the Romans gained a victory that was neither
                    difficult nor uncertain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Many thousands of
                    barbarians fell in battle, and many after the camp was taken. The others roamed
                    about, making mostly towards Apulia, and owed their escape from the Romans to
                    their distant flight and the dispersion which resulted from their panic and
                    their straggling. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The dictator was awarded a
                    triumph with the consent of both senate and plebs. </p>
                <p> Hardly had Camillus brought the war to an end, when he was confronted with a
                    fiercer opposition in the City. After desperate struggles the senate and the
                    dictator were beaten, and the measures advocated by the tribunes were adopted.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> An election of consuls was held, against
                    the wishes of the nobles, and resulted in the choice of Lucius Sextius, the
                    first of the plebeians to attain that honour. Even this did not end their
                    disputes. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The patricians declared that they
                    would not ratify the election, and the affair had almost led to a <pb n="p.351"
                    /> secession of the plebs and threatened other terrible <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 367</note> embroilments, when the
                    dictator finally proposed a compromise which allayed the discord; the nobles
                    gave way to the plebs in regard to the plebeian consul, and the plebs conceded
                    to the nobles that they might elect from the patricians one praetor to
                    administer justice in the City. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This
                        step was made necessary by the growth of the City and the increasing burden
                        laid upon the consuls; but, as Livy intimates, it also served as partial
                        compensation to the patricians for the privileges they were now forced to
                        share with the plebs-until, in <date when="-0337">337 B.C.</date> ( <hi
                            rend="italics">cf.</hi> VIII. xv. 9), the praetorship, too, was thrown
                        open to the plebs. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thus after their long quarrel the orders were
                    reconciled at last. The senate decided that this was a fitting occasion to
                    honour the immortal gods —who deserved it then, if ever at any time —by
                    celebrating the Great Games, and voted that one day should be added to the
                    customary three; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> this burden the aediles of
                    the plebs refused to shoulder, whereupon the young patricians called out that
                    they would willingly do it for the sake of honouring the gods. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The entire people united in thanks to them, and the senate
                    decreed that the dictator should hold a popular election of two aediles <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Later known as <hi rend="italics"
                            >aediles curules.</hi> The provision that only patricians might be
                        chosen was modified in the following year ( <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> VII.
                        i.). </note> to be chosen from the patricians, and that the Fathers should
                    ratify all the elections of that year. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
