<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight books - 6</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight Books</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1857</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/4/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="391" xml:id="p.391"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="book">
                <head>BOOK VI.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Successful operations against the Volscians, and Aequans, and Praenestines.
                        Four tribes were added. Marcus Manlius, who had defended the Capitol from
                        the Gauls, being condemned for aspiring to regal power, is thrown from the
                        Tarpeian rock; in commemoration of which circumstance a decree of the senate
                        was passed, that none of the Manlian family should henceforward bear the
                        cognomen of Marcus. Caius Licinius and Lucius Sextius, tribunes of the
                        people, proposed a law that consuls might be chosen from among the commons;
                        and after a violent contest, succeeded in passing that law, notwithstanding
                        the opposition of the patricians, the same tribunes of the commons being for
                        five years the only magistrates in the state; and Lucius Sextius was the
                        first consul elected from the commons. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THE transactions of the Romans, from the
                    building of the city of Rome to the capture of the same city, first under kings,
                    then under consuls, and dictators, and decemvirs, and consular tribunes, their
                    wars abroad, their dissensions at home, I have exhibited in five books:
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> matters obscure, as well by reason of
                    their very great antiquity, like objects which from their great distance are
                    scarcely perceptible, as also because in those times the use of letters, the
                    only faithful guardian of the memory of events, was inconsiderable and rare:
                    and, moreover, whatever was contained in the commentaries of the pontiffs, and
                    other public and private records, were lost for the most part in the burning of
                    the city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Henceforwards, from the second
                    origin of the city, which sprung up again more healthfully and vigorously, as if
                    from its root, its achievements at home and abroad, shall be narrated with more
                    clearness and authenticity. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But it now stood
                    erect, leaning chiefly on the same support, Marcus Furius, by which it had bean
                    first raised; nor did they suffer him to lay down the dictatorship until the end
                    of the year. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was not agreeable to them,
                    that <pb n="392" xml:id="p.392"/> the tribunes during whose time of office the
                    city had been taken, should preside at the elections for the following year: the
                    administration came to an interregnum. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whilst
                    the state was kept occupied in the employment and constant labour of repairing
                    the city, in the mean time a day of trial was named by Caius Marcius, tribune of
                    the people, for Quintus Fabius, as soon as he went out of office, because whilst
                    an ambassador he had, contrary to the law of nations, appeared <milestone
                        n="7??" unit="section"/> in arms against the Gauls, to whom he had been sent
                    as a negotiator: from which trial death removed him so opportunely that most
                    people thought it voluntary. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The interregnum
                    commenced. Publius Cornelius Scipio was interrex, and after him Marcus Furius
                    Camillus. He nominates as military tribunes with consular power, Lucius Valerius
                    Publicola a second time, Lucius Virginius, Publius Cornelius, Aulus Manlius,
                    Lucius Aemilius, Lucius Postumius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These
                    having entered on their office immediately after the interregnum, consulted the
                    senate on no other business previous to that which related to religion. In the
                    first place they ordered that the treaties and laws which could be found, should
                    be collected; (these consisted of the twelve tables, and some laws made under
                    the kings.) <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Some of them were publicly
                    promulgated; but such as appertained to religious matters were kept secret
                    chiefly by the pontiffs, that they might hold the minds of the people fettered
                    by them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then they began to turn their
                    attention to the subject of desecrated days; and the day before the fifteenth
                    day of the calends of August, remarkable for a double disaster, (as being the
                    day on which the Fabii were slain at Cremera, and afterwards the disgraceful
                    battle attended with the ruin of the city had been fought at Allia,) they called
                    the Allian day from the latter disaster, and they rendered it remarkable for
                    transacting no business whether public or private. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Some persons think, that because Sulpicius, the military
                    tribune, had not duly offered sacrifice on the day after the ides of July, and
                    because, without having obtained the favour of the gods, the Roman army had been
                    exposed to the enemy on the third day after, an order was also made to abstain
                    from all religious undertakings on the day following the ides: thence the same
                    religious observance was derived with respect to the days following the calends
                    and the nones. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But it was not long allowed them to consult in
                    quiet re- <pb n="393" xml:id="p.393"/> garding the means of raising the city,
                    after so grievous a fall. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the one side
                    their old enemies, the Volscians, had taken up arms, to extinguish the Roman
                    name: on the other, some traders brought [intelligence] that a conspiracy of the
                    leading men of Etruria from all the states had been formed at the temple of
                    Voltumna. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A new cause of terror also had been
                    added by the defection of the Latins and Hernicians, who, since the battle
                    fought at the lake Regillus, had remained in friendship with the Roman people
                    with fidelity not to be questioned. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, when such great alarms surrounded them on every side, and it became
                    apparent to all that the Roman name laboured not only under hatred with their
                    enemies, but under contempt also with their allies; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> it was resolved that the state should be defended under the
                    same auspices, as those under which it had been recovered, and that Marcus
                    Furius should be nominated dictator. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He, then
                    dictator, nominated Caius Servilius Ahala master of the horse; and a suspension
                    of all public business being proclaimed, he held a levy of the juniors, in such
                    a manner as to divide them into centuries after they had sworn allegiance to
                    him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The army, when raised and equipped with
                    arms, he divided into three parts. One part he opposed to Etruria in the
                    Veientian territory; another he ordered to pitch their camp before the city.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A military tribune, Aulus Manlius,
                    commanded the latter; those who were sent against the Etrurians, Lucius Aemilius
                    commanded. The third part he led in person against the Volscians; and not far
                    from Lanuvium, (the place is called ad Maecium,) he set about storming their
                    camp. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Into these, who set out to the war from
                    motives of contempt, because they thought that all the Roman youth were cut off
                    by the Gauls, the fact of having heard that Camillus was appointed to the
                    command struck such terror, that they fenced themselves with a rampart, and the
                    rampart itself with trees piled up together, lest the enemy might by any means
                    reach to the works. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When Camillus observed
                    this, he ordered fire to be thrown into the fence opposed to him; and it so
                    happened that a very strong wind was turned towards the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore not only opened a passage by the fire, but the
                    flames being directed against the camp, by the vapour also and the smoke, and by
                    the crackling of the green timber as it burned, he so confounded the enemy that
                    the Romans had less diffi- <pb n="394" xml:id="p.394"/> culty in passing the
                    rampart into the camp of the Volscians, than they had experienced in climbing
                    over the fence which had been consumed by the fire. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The enemy being routed and cut down, after the dictator had
                    taken the camp by assault, he gave up the booty to the soldiers, which was so
                    much the more agreeable, as it was less expected, the commander being by no
                    means profusely generous. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then having pursued
                    them in their flight, after he had depopulated the entire Volscian land, he at
                    length in the seventieth year forced the Volscians to a surrender. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> After his victory he passed from the Volscians to
                    the Aequans, who were also preparing for hostilities: he surprised their army at
                    Bolae, and having attacked not only their camp, but their city also, he took
                    them at the first onset. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When such fortune manifested itself on that
                    side where Camillus, the life and soul of the Roman interest, was, a great alarm
                    had fallen on another quarter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For almost all
                    Etruria, taking up arms, were besieging Sutrium, allies of the Roman people,
                    whose ambassadors having applied to the senate, imploring aid in their distress,
                    obtained a decree, that the dictator should at the earliest opportunity bear aid
                    to the Sutrians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when the circumstances of
                    the besieged would not suffer them to brook the delay of this hope, and the
                    small number of the townsmen were spent with labour, watching, and wounds, all
                    which fell heavily on the same individuals, and when, the city being delivered
                    up to the enemy by a capitulation, they were leaving their habitations in a
                    miserable train, being discharged without their arms with only a single garment;
                    at that juncture Camillus happened to come up at the head of the Roman army.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And when the mournful crowd prostrated
                    themselves at his feet, and the address of the leading men, wrung from them by
                    extreme necessity, was followed by the weeping of women and boys, who were
                    dragged along by the companions of their exile, he bade the Sutrians to give
                    over their lamentations: that he brought with him grief and tears to the
                    Etrurians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then orders the baggage to be
                    deposited, and the Sutrians to remain there with a small guard left with them,
                    and the soldiers to follow him in arms. Having thus proceeded to Sutrium with
                    his army disencumbered, he found, as he expected, every thing in disorder, as
                    usually happens in success; no advanced guard before the walls, the gates lying
                    open, and the conquerors dispersed, carrying out <pb n="395" xml:id="p.395"/>
                    the booty from the houses of the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Sutrium is therefore taken a second time on the same day; the Etrurians, lately
                    victorious, are cut down in every quarter by their new enemy, nor is time
                    afforded them to collect and form one body, or even to take up arms. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When each pushed eagerly towards the gates, to try if
                    by any chance they could throw themselves into the fields, they found the gates
                    shut for the dictator had given those orders in the first instance. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Upon this some took up arms, others, who happened to
                    be armed before the tumult came on them, called their friends together in order
                    to make battle; which would have been kindled by the despair of the enemy, had
                    not criers, sent in every direction through the city, issued orders that their
                    arms should be laid down, that the unarmed should be spared, and that no one
                    should be injured except those who were armed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Then even those whose minds had been, in their last hope, obstinately bent on
                    fighting, when hopes of life were offered, threw down their arms in every
                    direction, and surrendered themselves unarmed to the enemy, which fortune ad
                    rendered the safer method. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Their number being
                    considerable, they were distributed among several guards; the own was before
                    night restored to the Sutrians uninjured and free from all the calamities of
                    war, because it had not been taken by force but delivered up on terms. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Camillus returned to the city in triumph,
                    being victorious in three wars at the same time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> By far the greatest number of the prisoners whom he led before his chariot
                    were from among the Etrurians. And these being sold by auction, such a sum of
                    money was raised, that after paying the matrons the price of their gold, out of
                    that which was over and above, three golden bowls were made; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> which, inscribed with the name of Camillus, it is certain,
                    lay, before the burning of the Capitol, in the recess of Jupiter's temple at the
                    feet of Juno. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On that year such of the
                    Veientians, Capenatians, and Faliscians as had come over to the Romans during
                    the wars with those nations, were admitted into the state, and land was assigned
                    to these new citizens. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those also were
                    recalled by a decree of the senate from Veii, who, from a dislike to building at
                    Rome, had betaken themselves to Veii, and had seized on the vacant houses there.
                    And at first there was a murmuring on their part disregarding the order; then a
                    day having <pb n="396" xml:id="p.396"/> been appointed, and capital punishment
                    [denounced against any one] who did not return to Rome, from being refractory as
                    they were collectively, rendered them when taken singly obedient, each through
                    fear for himself. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And Rome both now increased
                    in numbers, and rose throughout its entire extent by its buildings, the state
                    assisting in the expenses, and the aediles urging on the work as if public, and
                    private persons (for the want felt of accommodation stimulated them) hastening
                    to complete the work; and within a year a new city was erected. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> At the termination of the year an election was held of
                    military tribunes with consular power. Those elected were, Titus Quinctius
                    Cincinnatus, Quintus Servilius Fidenas a fifth time, Lucius Julius Iulus, Lucius
                    Aquillius Corvus, Lucius Lucretius Tricipitinus, Servius Sulpicius Rufus.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They led one army against the Aequans, not
                    to war, (for they owned themselves conquered,) but from motives of animosity, to
                    lay waste their territories, lest they should leave them any strength for new
                    designs; the other into the territory of Tarquinii. Here Cortuosa and
                    Contenebra, towns belonging to the Etrurians, were taken by storm and
                    demolished. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At Cortuosa there was no contest;
                    having attacked it by surprise, they took it at the first shout and onset; the
                    town was plundered and burned. Contenebra sustained a siege for a few days; and
                    it was continual labour, abated neither by night nor by day, that reduced them.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the Roman army, having been divided
                    into six parts, each [division] relieved the other in the battle one hour in six
                    in rotation, and the paucity of numbers exposed the same individual townsmen,
                    wearied as they were, to a contest ever new, they at length yielded, and an
                    opportunity was afforded to the Romans of entering the city. It was the wish of
                    the tribunes that the spoil should be made public property; but the order [that
                    such should be so] was too late for their determination. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Whilst they hesitate, the spoil already became the property
                    of the soldiers; nor could it be taken from them, except by means calculated to
                    excite dissatisfaction. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On the same year,
                    that the city should not increase by private buildings only, the lower parts of
                    the Capitol also were built of hewn stone; a work deserving of admiration even
                    amid the present magnificence of the city. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now, whilst the state was busily occupied in
                    building, the tribunes of the commons endeavoured to draw crowds to their <pb
                        n="397" xml:id="p.397"/> harangues by [proposing] the agrarian laws.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Promptine territory was then, for the
                    first time since the power of the Volscians had been reduced by Camillus, held
                    out to them as their indisputable right. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They
                    alleged it as a charge, that <quote> that district was much more harassed on the
                        part of the nobility than it had been on that of the Volscians, for that
                        incursions were made by the one party on it, only as long as they had
                        strength and arms; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that persons belonging
                        to the nobility encroached on the possession of land that was public, nor
                        would there be any room in it for the commons, unless a division were now
                        made, before they seized on all. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They made not much impression on the commons,
                    who through their anxiety for building attended the forum only in small numbers,
                    and were drained by their expenses on the same object, and were therefore
                    careless about land for the improvement of which means were wanting. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The state being full of religious impressions, and
                    then even the leading men having become superstitious by reason of their recent
                    misfortunes, in order that the auspices might be taken anew, the government had
                    once more recourse to an interregnum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    successive interreges were, Marcus Manlius Capitolinus, Servius Sulpicius
                    Camerinus, and Lucius Valerius Potitus. The last at length held an election of
                    military tribunes with consular power. He nominates Lucius Papirius, Caius
                    Cornelius, Caius Sergius, Lucius Aemilius a second time, Lucius Menenius, and
                    Lucius Valerius Publicola a third time. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These
                    entered on their office after the interregnum. This year the temple of Mars,
                    vowed in the Gallic war, was dedicated by Titus Quinctius, duumvir for
                    performing religious rites. Four tribes were added from the new citizens, the
                    Stellatine, the Tormentine, the Sabatine, and the Arnian, and they made up. the
                    number of twenty-five tribes. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Regarding the Pomptine land the matter was
                    pressed by Lucius Sicinius, plebeian tribune, on the people, who now attended in
                    greater numbers, and more readily aroused to the desire of land than they had
                    been. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And mention having been introduced in
                    the senate regarding war against the Latins and Hernicians, the matter was
                    deferred in consequence of their attending to a more important war, because
                    Etruria was up in arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Matters reverted to
                    their electing Camillus military tribune with consular power. Five colleagues
                    were <pb n="398" xml:id="p.398"/> added, Servius Cornelius Maluginensis, Quintus
                    Servilius Fidenas a sixth time, Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus, Lucius Horatius
                    Pulvillus, and Publius Valerius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the
                    commencement of the year the attention of the people was drawn away from the
                    Etrurian war, because a body of fugitives from the Pomptine district, suddenly
                    entering the city, brought word that the Antians were up in arms; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> and that the states of the Latins privately sent
                    their youth to that war, denying that there was any public concert in it, they
                    alleging that volunteers were only not prevented from serving in whatever
                    quarter they pleased. They had now ceased to despise any wars. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the senate returned thanks to the gods, because
                    Camillus was in office; for (they knew) that it would have been necessary to
                    nominate him dictator, if he were in a private station. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And his colleagues agreed that when any terror with respect
                    to war threatened, the supreme direction of every thing should be vested in one
                    man, and that they had determined to consign their authority into the hands of
                    Camillus; and that they did not consider, that any concession they should make
                    to the dignity of that man, derogated in any way from their own. The tribunes
                    having been highly commended by the senate, Camillus himself also, covered with
                    confusion, returned thanks. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then said that
                    " a heavy burden was laid on him by the Roman people, by their having now
                    nominated him dictator for the fourth time; a great one by the senate, by reason
                    of such flattering judgments of that house concerning him; the greatest of all,
                    however, by the condescension of such distinguished colleagues. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Where if any addition could be made to his diligence and
                    vigilance, that, vying with himself, he would strive to render the opinion of
                    the state, [expressed] with such unanimity regarding him, as permanent as it was
                    most honourable. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In reference to the war and
                    to the people of Antium, that there was more of threats there than of danger;
                    that he, however, would advise that, as they should fear nothing, so should they
                    despise nothing. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That the city of Rome was
                    beset by the ill-will and hatred of its neighbours: therefore that the
                    commonwealth should be maintained by a plurality, both of generals and of
                    armies. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>It is my wish,</quote> said he, <quote> that you, Publius Valerius, as my
                        associate in command and counsel, should lead the troops with me against the
                        enemy at Antium; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> that <pb n="399"
                            xml:id="p.399"/> you, Quintus Servilius, after raising and equipping
                        another army, shall encamp in the city, ready to act, whether Etruria, as
                        lately, or these new causes of anxiety, the Latins and Hernicians, should
                        bestir themselves. I deem it as certain that you, will conduct matters, as
                        is worthy of your father and grandfather, and of yourself and six
                        tribuneships. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Let a third army be raised
                        by Lucius Quinctius, out of hose excused from service and the seniors,
                        [those past the military age,] who may protect the city and the walls. Let
                        Lucius Horatius provide arms, weapons, corn, and whatever the other
                        exigencies of the war shall demand. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> You,
                        Servius Cornelius, we your colleagues appoint the president of this council
                        of the state, the guardian of religion, of the assemblies, of the laws, and
                        of all matters pertaining to the city. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> All cheerfully promising their utmost
                    endeavours in the discharge of their apportioned offices, Valerius, chosen as
                    his associate in command, added, <quote> that Marcus Furius should be considered
                        by him as dictator, and that he would act as master of the horse to him.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Wherefore, that they should entertain
                        hopes regarding the war, proportioned to the opinion they formed of their
                        sole commander. </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The senate, elated with joy, cry out, that
                    "they entertained good hopes both regarding war, and peace, and the republic in
                    general; and that the republic would never have need of a dictator, if it were
                    to have such men in office, united together in such harmony of sentiments,
                    prepared alike to obey and to command, and who were laying up praise as common
                    stock, rather than taking it from the common fund to themselves individually. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A suspension of civil business being
                    proclaimed, and a levy being held, Furius and Valerius set out to Satricum; to
                    which place the Antians had drawn together not only the youth of the Volscians,
                    selected out of the new generation, but immense numbers of the Latins and
                    Hernicians, out of states which by a long [enjoyment of] peace were in the most
                    unimpaired condition. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The new enemy then added
                    to the old shook the spirits of the Roman soldiers. When the centurions reported
                    this to Camillus, whilst forming his line of battle, that <quote> the minds of
                        the soldiers were disturbed, hat arms were taken up by them with
                        backwardness, and that they left the camp with hesitation and reluctance;
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> nay, that some expressions were heard,
                        that they should each have to fight with <pb n="400" xml:id="p.400"/> one
                        hundred enemies, and that such numbers, even if unarmed, much less when
                        furnished with arms, could with difficulty be withstood, </quote> he leaped
                    on his horse, and in front of the troops, turning to the line, and riding
                    between the ranks, <quote> What dejection of mind is this, soldiers, what
                        backwardness? Is it with the enemy, or me, or yourselves you are
                        unacquainted? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What else are the enemy, but
                        the constant subject of your bravery and your glory? on the other hand, with
                        me as your general, to say nothing of the taking of Falerii and Veii, you
                        have lately celebrated a triple triumph for a threefold victory over these
                        self-same Volscians and Aequans, and Etruria. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Do you not recognise me as your general, because I gave
                        you the signal, not as dictator, but as tribune? I neither feel the want of
                        the highest authority over you, and you should look to nothing in me but
                        myself; for the dictatorship neither added to my courage, any more than
                        exile took it from me. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> We are all
                        therefore the same individuals; and as we bring to this war the same
                        requisites as we brought to former wars, let us look for the same result of
                        the war. As soon as you commence the fight, each will do that which he has
                        learned and been accustomed to do. You will conquer, they will run. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then having given the signal, he leaps from
                    his horse, and seizing the standard-bearer who was next him by the hand, he
                    hurries him on with him against the enemy, calling aloud, <quote>Soldiers,
                        advance the standard.</quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And when they saw Camillus himself, now
                    disabled through age for bodily exertion, advancing against the enemy, they all
                    rush forwards together, having raised a shout, each eagerly crying out,
                        <quote>Follow the general.</quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They say further that the standard was thrown
                    into the enemy's line by order of Camillus, and that the van was then exerted to
                    recover it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That there first the Antians were
                    forced to give way, and that the panic spread not only to the first line, but to
                    the reserve troops also. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor was it merely the
                    ardour of the soldiers animated by the presence of their general that made this
                    impression, but because nothing was more terrible to the minds of the Volscians,
                    than the sight of Camillus which happened to present itself. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Thus, in whatever direction he went, he carried certain
                    victory with him. This was particularly evident, when, hastily mounting his
                    horse, he rode with a footman's shield to the left wing, which <pb n="401"
                        xml:id="p.401"/> was almost giving way, by the fact of showing him elf he
                    restored the battle, pointing out the rest of the line gaining the victory.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Now the result was decided, but the flight
                    of the enemy was impeded by their great numbers, and the wearied soldiers would
                    have had tedious work in putting so great a number to the sword, when rain
                    suddenly falling with a violent storm, put an end to the pursuit of the victory
                    which was now decided, rather than to the battle. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Then the signal for retreat being given, the fall of night
                    put an end to the war, without further trouble to the Romans. For the Latins and
                    Hernicians, having abandoned the Volscians, marched to their homes, having
                    attained results corresponding to their wicked measures. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The Volscians, when they saw themselves deserted by those
                    through reliance on whom they had resumed hostilities, abandoned their camp, and
                    shut themselves up within the walls of Satricum. Camillus at first prepared to
                    surround them by lines of circumvallation, and to prosecute the siege by a mound
                    and other works. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But seeing that this was
                    obstructed by no sally from the town, and considering that the enemy possessed
                    too little spirit for him to wait in tedious expectation of victory under the
                    circumstances, after exhorting his soldiers not to waste themselves by tedious
                    labours, as [they had done] when besieging Veii, that the victory was in their
                    hands, he attacked the walls on every side, amid the great alacrity of the
                    soldiers, and took the town by scalade. The Volscians, having thrown down their
                    arms, surrendered themselves. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the general's thoughts were fixed on a
                    higher object, on Antium: [he knew] that that was the great aim of the
                    Volscians, and main source of the late war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But because so strong a city could not be taken without great preparations,
                    engines and machines, leaving his colleague with the army, he set out for Rome,
                    in order to advise the senate to have Antium destroyed. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In the middle of his discourse, (I suppose that it was the
                    wish of the gods that the state of Antium should last a longer time,)
                    ambassadors came from Nepete and Sutrium, soliciting aid against the Etrurians,
                    urging that the time for giving them aid would soon pass by. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Thither did fortune avert the force of Camillus from
                    Antium; for as those places were situate opposite Etruria, and were barriers or
                    gates as it were on that side, both they had a wish to get possession of them,
                    whenever they meditated any new enter- <pb n="402" xml:id="p.402"/> prise, and
                    the Romans to recover and secure them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore the senate resolved to treat with Camillus, that he would relinquish
                    Antium and undertake the Etrurian war. The city troops, which Quinctius had
                    commanded, are decreed to him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Though he would
                    have preferred the army which was in the Volscian territory, as being tried and
                    accustomed to him, he made no objection: he only demanded Valerius as his
                    associate in command. Quinctius and Horatius were sent against the Volscians, as
                    successors to Valerius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Furius and Valerius,
                    having set out from the city to Sutrium, found one part of the town already
                    taken by the Etrurians, and on the other part, the approaches to which were
                    barricaded, the townsmen with difficulty repelling the assault of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Both the approach of aid from Rome, as
                    also the name of Camillus, universally respected both with the enemy and the
                    allies, sustained their tottering state for the present, and afforded time for
                    bringing them relief. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly Camillus,
                    having divided his army, orders his colleague to lead round his troops to that
                    side which the enemy already possessed, and to assault the walls; not so much
                    from any hope that the city could be taken by scalade, as that, by turning away
                    the enemy's attention to that quarter, both the townsmen who were wearied with
                    fighting might have some relaxation of their toil, and that he himself might
                    have an opportunity of entering the city without a contest. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> This having been done on both sides, and the double terror
                    now surrounding the Etrurians, when they saw that the walls were assailed with
                    the utmost fury, and that the enemy were within the walls, they threw themselves
                    out in consternation, in one body, by a gate which alone happened not to be
                    guarded. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Great slaughter was made on them as
                    they fled, both in the city and through the fields. The greater number were
                    slain within the walls by Furius' soldiers: those of Valerius were more alert
                    for the pursuit; nor did they put an end to the slaughter until night, which
                    prevented them from seeing. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Sutrium being
                    recovered and restored to the allies, the army was led to Nepete, which having
                    been received by capitulation, was now entirely in the possession of the
                    Etrurians. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It appeared probable, that there would be more
                    of labour in recovering the city, not only for this reason, be- <pb n="403"
                        xml:id="p.403"/> cause it was all in possession of the enemy, but also
                    because the surrender had been made in consequence of a party of the Nepesinians
                    having betrayed the state. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was determined,
                    however, that a message should be sent to their leading men, to separate
                    themselves from the Etrurians, and that they themselves should evince that
                    strict fidelity, which they had implored from the Romans. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Whence as soon as an answer was brought that there was
                    nothing in their power, that the Etrurians occupied the walls and the guards of
                    the gates, first, terror was struck into the townsmen by laying waste their
                    land; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> then, when the faith of the capitulation
                    was more religiously observed than that of the alliance, the army was led up to
                    the walls with fascines of bushes collected from the fields, and the ditches
                    being filled, the scaling ladders were raised, and the town was taken at the
                    first shout and attack. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Proclamation was then
                    made to the Nepesinians, that they should lay down their arms, and orders were
                    given that the unarmed should be spared. The Etrurians, armed and unarmed, were
                    put to the sword without distinction: of the Nepesinians also the authors of the
                    surrender were beheaded. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To the unoffending
                    multitude their property was restored, and the town was left with a garrison.
                    Thus having recovered two allied cities from the enemy, the tribunes marched
                    back their victorious army to Rome. During the same year restitution was
                    demanded from the Latins and Hernicians, and the cause was asked why they had
                    not during some years supplied soldiers according to stipulation. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> An answer was given in a full assembly of both
                    nations, <quote> that neither the blame was public, nor was there any design in
                        the circumstance of some of their youth having served among the Volscians.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That these individuals, however,
                        suffered the penalty of their improper conduct, and that none of them had
                        returned. But that the cause of their not supplying the soldiers had been
                        their continual terror from the Volscians, which pest adhering to their
                        side, had not been capable of being destroyed by so many successive wars. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Which answer being reported to the senate,
                    they decided that there was wanting rather a seasonable time for declaring war
                    than sufficient grounds for it. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the following year, Aulus Manlius, Publius
                    Cornelius, Titus and Lucius Quintii Capitolini, Lucius Papirius <pb n="404"
                        xml:id="p.404"/> Cursor a second time, Caius Sergius a second time, being
                    military tribunes with consular power, a grievous war broke out abroad, a still
                    more grievous disturbance at home; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the war
                    originated on the part of the Volscians, to which was added a revolt of the
                    Latins and Hernicians; the sedition from one from whom it could be least of all
                    apprehended, a man of patrician birth and distinguished character, Marcus
                    Manlius Capitolinus; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> who being too aspiring in
                    mind, whilst he despised the other leading men, envied one, who was peculiarly
                    distinguished both by honours and by merit, Marcus Furius: he became indignant
                    that he should be the only man among the magistrates; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> the only man at the head of the armies; that he now
                    attained such eminence that he treated not as colleagues but as mere tools the
                    persons elected under the same auspices; though, in the mean time, if any one
                    would form a just estimate, his country could not have been recovered by Marcus
                    Furius from the siege of the enemy, had not the Capitol and citadel been first
                    preserved by him; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and the other attacked the
                    Gauls, whilst their attention was distracted between receiving the gold and the
                    hope of peace, when he himself drove them off when armed and taking the citadel;
                    of the other's glory, a man's share appertained to all the soldiers who
                    conquered along with him; that in his victory no man living was a sharer.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His mind puffed by these notions, and
                    moreover, from a viciousness of disposition being vehement and headstrong, when
                    he perceived that his influence among the patricians did not stand forth as
                    prominent as he thought it should, he, the first of all the patricians, became a
                    plebeian partisan, and formed plans in conjunction with the plebeian
                    magistrates; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and by criminating the fathers,
                    and alluring the commons to his side, he now came to be carried along by the
                    tide of popular applause, not by prudence, and preferred to be of a great,
                    rather than of a good character: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and not
                    content with agrarian laws, which had ever served the tribunes of the commons as
                    material for disturbances, he now began to undermine public credit; for [he well
                    knew] <quote> that the incentives of debt were sharper, as not only threatening
                        poverty and ignominy, but intimidated personal liberty with stocks and
                        chains. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And the amount of the debt was immense,
                    contracted by building, a circumstance most destructive even to the rich. The
                    Volscian war therefore, heavy in <pb n="405" xml:id="p.405"/> itself, charged
                    with additional weight by the defection of the Latins and Hernicians, was held
                    out as a colourable pretext, for having a higher authority resorted to.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But it was rather the reforming plans
                    that drove the senate to create a dictator. Aulus Cornelius Cossus having been
                    elected dictator, nominated Titus Quinctius Capitolinus his master of the horse. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator, though he perceived that a
                    greater struggle was reserved for him at home than abroad; still, either because
                    there was need of despatch for the war, or supposing that by a victory and a
                    triumph he should add to the powers of the dictatorship itself, held a levee and
                    proceeds into the Pomptine territory, where he had heard that the Volscians had
                    appointed their army to assemble. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I doubt not
                    but that, in addition to satiety, to persons reading of so many wars waged with
                    the Volscians, this same circumstance will suggest itself, which often served as
                    an occasion of surprise to me when perusing the writers who lived nearer to the
                    times of these occurrences, from what source the Volscians and Aequans, so often
                    vanquished, could have procured supplies of soldiers. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> And as this has been unnoticed and passed over in silence
                    by ancient writers; on which matter what can I state, except mere opinion, which
                    every one may from his own conjecture form for himself? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It seems probable, either that they employed, as is now
                    practised in the Roman levies, successive generations of their young men one
                    after the other, during the intervals between the wars; or that the armies were
                    not always recruited out of the same states, though the same nation may have
                    made war; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> or that there was an innumerable
                    multitude of free-men in those places, which, at the present day, Roman slaves
                    save from being a desert, a scanty seminary of soldiers being scarcely left.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Certain it is, (as is agreed upon among
                    all authors,) although their power was very much impaired under the guidance and
                    auspices of Camillus, the forces of the Volscians were strong: besides, the
                    Latins and Hernicians had been added, and some of the Circeians, and some Roman
                    colonists also from Velitrae. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The dictator,
                    having pitched his camp on that day, and on coming forth on the day following
                    after taking the auspices, and having, by sacrificing a victim, implored the
                    favour of the gods, with joyful countenance presented himself to the soldiers,
                    who were now taking arms at day-break, according to orders, on the signal for
                    battle being displayed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="406" xml:id="p.406"/>
                    <quote>Soldiers,</quote> says he, <quote> the victory is ours, if the gods and
                        their prophets see aught into futurity. Accordingly, as it becomes men full
                        of well-grounded hope, and who are about to engage with their inferiors, let
                        us place our spears at our feet, and arm our right hands only with our
                        swords. I would not even wish that any should push forward beyond the line;
                        but that, standing firm, you receive the enemy's charge in a steady posture.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they shall have discharged their
                        ineffective missives, and, breaking their ranks, they shall rush on you as
                        you stand firm, then let your swords glitter, and let each man recollect,
                        that there are gods who aid the Roman; those gods, who have sent us into
                        battle with favourable omens. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Do you,
                        Titus Quinctius, keep back the cavalry, attentively observing the very
                        commencement of the contest; as soon as you observe the armies closed foot
                        to foot, then, whilst they are taken up with another panic, strike terror
                        into them with your cavalry, and by making a charge on them, disperse the
                        ranks of those engaged in the fight. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The cavalry, the infantry conduct the fight,
                    just as he had ordered them. Nor did either the general disappoint the legions,
                    nor fortune the general. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The army of the enemy, relying on nothing but
                    on their number, and measuring both armies merely by the eye, entered on the
                    battle inconsiderately, and inconsiderately gave it over: <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> fierce only in their shout and with their missive weapons,
                    and at the first onset of the fight, they were unable to withstand the swords,
                    and the close engagement foot to foot, and the looks of the enemy, darting fire
                    through their ardour for the fight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Their
                    front line was driven in, and confusion spread to the reserve troops, and the
                    cavalry occasioned alarm on their part: the ranks were then broken in many
                    places, every thing was set in motion, and the line seemed as it were
                    fluctuating. Then when, the foremost having fallen, each saw that death was
                    about to reach himself, they turn their backs. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman followed close on them; and as long as they went off armed and in
                    bodies, the labour in the pursuit fell to the infantry; when it was observed
                    that their arms were thrown away in every direction, and that the enemy's line
                    was scattered in flight through the country; then squadrons of horse were sent
                    out, intimation being given that they should not, by losing time with the
                    massacre of individuals, <pb n="407" xml:id="p.407"/> afford an opportunity in
                    the mean time to the multitude to escape: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> it
                    would be sufficient that their speed should be retarded by missive weapons and
                    by terror, and that the progress of their forces should be detained by
                    skirmishing, until the infantry should be able to overtake and despatch the
                    enemy by regular slaughter. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There was no end
                    of the flight and slaughter before night; on the same day the camp of the
                    Volscians was taken also and pillaged, and all the plunder, save the persons of
                    free condition, was given up to the soldiers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The greatest part of the prisoners consisted of Latins and Hernicians, and these
                    not men of plebeian rank, so that it could be supposed that they had served for
                    hire, but some young men of rank were found among them: an evident proof that
                    the Volscian enemies had been aided by public authority. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Some of the Circeians also were recognised, and colonists
                    from Velitrae; and being all sent to Rome, on being interrogated by the leading
                    senators, plainly revealed the same circumstances as they had done to the
                    dictator, the defection each of his respective state. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator kept his army in the standing
                    camp, not at all doubting that the senate would order war with these states;
                    when a more momentous difficulty having occurred at home, rendered it necessary
                    that he should be sent for to Rome, the sedition gaining strength every day,
                    which the fomenter was now rendering more than ordinarily formidable. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For now it was easy to see from what motives
                    proceeded not only the discourses of Manlius, but his actions also, apparently
                    suggested by popular zeal, but at the same time tending to create disturbance.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he saw a centurion, illustrious for
                    his military exploits, leading off to prison by reason of a judgment for debt,
                    he ran up with his attendants in the middle of the forum and laid hands on him;
                    and exclaiming aloud against the insolence of the patricians, the cruelty of the
                    usurers, and the grievances of the commons, and the deserts and misfortunes of
                    the man. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Then indeed,</quote> said he, <quote> in vain have I preserved the
                        Capitol and citadel by this right hand, if I am to see my fellow-citizen and
                        fellow-soldier, as if captured by the victorious Gauls, dragged into slavery
                        and chains. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then paid the debt to the creditor openly
                    before the people, and having purchased his freedom with the scales and brass,
                    he sets the man at liberty, whilst the latter implored both gods and men, that
                    they would grant a recompence to Marcus <pb n="408" xml:id="p.408"/> Manlius,
                    his liberator, the parent of the Roman commons; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> and being immediately received into the tumultuous crowd, he himself also
                    increased the tumult, displaying the scars received in the Veientian, Gallic,
                    and other succeeding wars: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> that he, whilst serving in the field, and rebuilding his dwelling which
                        had been demolished, though he had paid off the principal many times over,
                        the interest always keeping down the principal, had been overwhelmed with
                        interest: that through the kind interference of Marcus Manlius, he now
                        beheld the light, the forum, and the faces of his fellow-citizens:
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that he received from him all the kind
                        services usually conferred by parents; that to him therefore he devoted
                        whatever remained of his person, of his life, and of his blood; whatever
                        ties subsisted between him and his country, public and private guardian
                        deities, were all centred in that one man. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the commons, worked upon by these
                    expressions, were now wholly in the interest of the one individual, another
                    circumstance was added, emanating from a scheme still more effectually
                    calculated to create general confusion. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A
                    farm in the Veientian territory, the principal part of his estate, he subjected
                    to public sale: <quote>that I may not,</quote> says he, <quote> suffer any of
                        you, Romans, as long as any of my property shall remain, to be dragged off
                        to prison, after judgment has been given against him, and he has been
                        consigned to a creditor. </quote> That circumstance, indeed, so inflamed
                    their minds, that they seemed determined on following the assertor of their
                    freedom through every thing, right and wrong. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Besides this, speeches [were made] at his house, as if he were delivering an
                    harangue, full of imputations against the patricians; among which he threw out,
                    waving all distinction whether he said what was true or false, that treasures of
                    the Gallic gold were concealed by the patricians; that <quote> they were now no
                        longer content with possessing the public lands, unless they appropriated
                        the public money also; if that were made public, that the commons might be
                        freed from their debt. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When this hope was presented to them, then
                    indeed it seemed a scandalous proceeding, that when gold was to be contributed
                    to ransom the state from the Gauls, the collection was made by a public tribute;
                    that the same gold, when taken from the Gauls, had become the plunder of a few.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Accordingly they followed up the inquiry,
                    where the furtive possession of so <pb n="409" xml:id="p.409"/> enormous a
                    treasure could be kept; and when he deferred, and told them that he would inform
                    them at the proper time, all other objects being given up, the attention of all
                    was directed to this point; and it became evident that neither their gratitude,
                    if the information were true, nor their displeasure if it proved false, would
                    know any bounds. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Matters being in this state, the dictator,
                    being summoned home from the army, came into the city. A meeting of the senate
                    being held on the following day, when, having sufficiently sounded the
                    inclinations of the people, he forbade the senate to leave him, attended by that
                    body, he placed his throne in the comitium, and sent his sergeant to Marcus
                    Manlius; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> who on being summoned by the
                    dictator's order, after he had given intimation to his party that a contest was
                    at hand, came to the tribunal, attended by a numerous party. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> On the one side stood the senate, on the other the people
                    as if in battle-array, attentively observing, each party, their respective
                    leader. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then silence being made, the dictator
                    said, <quote> I wish that I and the Roman patricians may agree with the commons
                        on all other matters, as I am confident we shall agree on the business which
                        regards you, and on that about which I am about to interrogate you.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I perceive that hopes have been raised
                        by you in the minds of the citizens, that, with safety to the public credit,
                        their debts may be paid off out of the Gallic treasures, which it is alleged
                        the leading patricians are secreting. To which proceeding so far am I from
                        being any obstruction, that on the contrary, Marcus Manlius, I exhort you to
                        free the Roman commons from the weight of interest; and to tumble from their
                        secreted spoil, those who lie now brooding on those public treasures.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If you refuse to do this, whether
                        because you yourself desire to be a sharer in the spoil, or because the
                        information is unfounded, I shall order you to be carried off to prison, nor
                        will I any longer suffer the multitude to be disquieted by you with delusive
                        hopes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To this Manlius replied, <quote> That it had
                        not escaped him, that it was not against the Volscians, who were enemies as
                        often as it suited the interests of the patricians, nor against the Latins
                        and Hernicians, whom they were driving into hostilities by false charges,
                        but against him and the Roman commons, that he was appointed dictator.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Now the war being dropped, which was
                        only feigned, that an attack was being <pb n="410" xml:id="p.410"/> made
                        against himself; that the dictator now professed to defend the usurers
                        against the commons; that now a charge and destruction was sought for him
                        out of the favour of the multitude. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Does
                        the crowd that surrounds my person offend you, </quote> said he, <quote>
                        Aulus Cornelius, and you, conscript fathers? Why then do you not draw it
                        away from me, each of you by your own acts of kindness? by becoming surety,
                        by delivering your fellow-citizens from the stocks, by preventing those cast
                        in law-suits, and assigned over to their creditors, from being dragged away
                        to prison, by sustaining the necessities of others out of your own
                        superfluities? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But why do I exhort you to
                        expend out of your own property? Fix some capital; deduct from the principal
                        what has been paid in interest; soon will my crowd not be a whit more
                        remarkable than that of any other person. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        But [I may be asked] why do I alone thus interest myself in behalf of my
                        fellow-citizens? I have no other answer to give, than if you were to ask me,
                        why in the same way did I alone preserve the Capitol and the citadel. Both
                        then I afforded the aid which I could to all collectively, and now I will
                        afford it to each individually. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Now with
                        respect to the Gallic treasures, the mode of interrogation renders difficult
                        a matter which in itself is easy. For why do you ask that which you know?
                        why do you order that which is in your own laps to be shaken out of them
                        rather than resign it, unless some fraud lurks beneath? <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The more you require your own impositions to be
                        examined into, the more do I dread lest you should blind the eyes of those
                        narrowly watching you. Wherefore, it is not I that am to be compelled to
                        discover your hoard, but you must be forced to produce it to the public.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the dictator ordered him to lay aside
                    evasion, and urged him to prove the truth of his information, or to own the
                    guilt of having advanced a false accusation against the senate, and of having
                    exposed them to the odium of a lying charge of concealment; when he refused to
                    speak, to meet the wishes of his enemies, he ordered him to be carried off to
                    prison. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When arrested by the sergeant, he
                    said, <quote> O Jupiter, supremely great and good, imperial Juno, and Minerva,
                        and ye other gods and goddesses, who inhabit the Capitol and citadel, do ye
                        suffer your soldier and defender to be thus harassed by his enemies?
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Shall this right hand, by which I beat
                        off the Gauls from your temples, be now in bonds and <pb n="411"
                            xml:id="p.411"/> chains? </quote> Neither the eyes nor ears of any one
                    could well endure the indignity [thus offered him], but the state, most patient
                    of legitimate authority, had rendered certain offices absolute to themselves;
                    nor did either the tribunes of the commons, nor the commons themselves, dare to
                    raise their eyes or utter a sentence in opposition to the dictatorial power.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On Manlius being thrown into prison, it
                    appears that a great part of the commons put on mourning, that a great many
                    persons had let their hair and beard grow, and that a dejected crowd presented
                    itself at the entrance of the prison. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    dictator triumphed over the Volscians; and that triumph was the occasion rather
                    of ill-will than of glory. For they murmured that <quote> it had been acquired
                        at home, not abroad, and that it was celebrated over a citizen, not over an
                        enemy; that only one thing was wanting to his arrogance, that Manlius was
                        not led before his car. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And now the affair fell little short of
                    sedition, for the purpose of appeasing which, the senate, without the
                    solicitation of any one, suddenly becoming bountiful of their own free-will,
                    decreed that a colony of two thousand Roman citizens should be conducted to
                    Satricum; two acres and half of land were assigned to each. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And when they considered this, both as scanty in itself,
                    conferred on a few, and as a bribe for betraying Marcus Manlius, the sedition
                    was irritated by the remedy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And now the crowd
                    of Manlius' partisans was become more remarkable, both by their squalid attire
                    and by the appearance of persons under prosecutions, and terror being removed by
                    the resignation of the dictatorship, after the triumph had set both the tongues
                    and thoughts of men at liberty. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Expressions were therefore heard freely
                    uttered of persons upbraiding the multitude, that <quote> by their favour they
                        always raised their defenders to a precipice, then at the very critical
                        moment of danger they forsook them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That
                        in this way Spurius Cassius, when inviting the commons to a share in the
                        lands, in this way Spurius Maelius, when warding off famine from the mouths
                        of his fellow-citizens at his own expense, had been undone; thus Marcus
                        Manlius was betrayed to his enemies, whilst drawing forth to liberty and
                        light one half of the state, when sunk and overwhelmed with usury.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That the commons fattened their
                        favourites that they might be slaughtered. Was this punishment to be
                        suffered, if a man <pb n="412" xml:id="p.412"/> of consular rank did not
                        answer at the nod of a dictator? Suppose that he had lied before, and that
                        on that account he had had no answer to make; what slave was ever imprisoned
                        in punishment of a lie? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Did not the memory
                        of that night present itself, which was well nigh the last and an eternal
                        one to the Roman name? nor any idea of the band of Gauls climbing up the
                        Tarpeian rock? nor that of Marcus Manlius himself, such as they had seen him
                        in arms, covered with sweat and blood, after having in a manner rescued
                        Jupiter himself from the hands of the enemy? <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Was a recompence made to the preserver of their country with their half
                        pounds of corn? and would they suffer a person, whom they almost deified,
                        whom they had set on a footing with Jupiter, at least with respect to the
                        surname of Capitolinus, to drag out an existence subject to the will of an
                        executioner, chained in a prison and in darkness? Was there thus sufficient
                        aid in one person for all; and no relief for one in so many? </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The crowd did not disperse from that place
                    even during the night, and they threatened that they would break open the
                    prison; when that being conceded which they were about to take by force, Manlius
                    was discharged from prison by a decree of the senate; by which proceeding the
                    sedition was not terminated, but a leader was supplied to the sedition.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> About the same time the Latins and
                    Hernicians, as also the colonists of Circeii and Velitrae, when striving to
                    clear themselves of the charge [of being concerned] in the Volscian war, and
                    demanding back the prisoners, that they may punish them according to their own
                    laws, received a harsh answer; the colonists the severer, because being Roman
                    citizens they had formed the abominable design of attacking their own country.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were therefore not only refused with
                    respect to the prisoners, but notice was given them in the name of the senate,
                    who however forbore from such a proceeding in the case of the allies, instantly
                    to depart from the city, from the presence and sight of the Roman people; lest
                    the law of embassy, provided for the foreigner, not for the citizen, should
                    afford them no protection. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The sedition excited by Manlius reassuming its
                    former violence, on the expiration of the year the election was held, and
                    military tribunes with consular power were elected from among the patricians;
                    they were Servius Cornelius Malugi- <pb n="413" xml:id="p.413"/> nensis a third
                    time, Publius Valerius Potitus a second time, Marcus Furius Camillus, Servius
                    Sulpicius Rufus a second time, Caius Papirius Crassus, Titus Quinctius
                    Cincinnatus a second time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the commencement
                    of which year peace with foreign countries afforded every opportunity both to
                    the patricians and plebeians: to the plebeians, because not being called away by
                    any levy, they conceived hopes of destroying usury, whilst they had so
                    influential a leader; to the patricians, because their minds were not called
                    away by any external terror from relieving the evils existing at home.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, as both sides arose much more
                    strenuous then ever, Manlius also was present for the approaching contest.
                    Having summoned the commons to his house, he holds consultations both by night
                    and day with the leading men amongst them with respect to effecting a revolution
                    of affairs, being filled with a much higher degree both of spirit and of
                    resentment than he had been before. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The recent
                    ignominy had lighted up resentment in a mind unused to affront; it gave him
                    additional courage, that the dictator had not ventured to the same extent
                    against him, as Quinctius Cincinnatus had done in the case of Spurius Maelius,
                    and because the dictator had not only endeavoured to avoid the unpopularity of
                    his imprisonment by abdicating the dictatorship, but not even the senate could
                    bear up against it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Elated by these
                    considerations, and at the same time exasperated, he set about inflaming the
                    minds of the commons, already sufficiently heated of themselves: <quote>How
                        long,</quote> says he, <quote> will you be ignorant of your own strength,
                        which nature has not wished even the brutes to be ignorant of? At least
                        count how many you are, and how many enemies you have. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Even if each of you were to attack an individual
                        antagonist, still I should suppose that you would strive more vigorously in
                        defence of liberty, than they in defence of tyranny. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> For as many of you as have been clients around each
                        single patron, in the same number will ye be against a single enemy. Only
                        make a show of war; ye shall have peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Let them see you prepared for open force; they themselves will relax their
                        pretensions. Collectively you must attempt something, or individually submit
                        to every thing. How long will you look to me? I for my part will not be
                        wanting to any of you: do you see that my fortune fail not. I, your avenger,
                        when my enemies thought well of <pb n="414" xml:id="p.414"/> it, was
                        suddenly reduced to nothing; and you all in a body beheld that person thrown
                        into chains, who had warded off chains from each one of you. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> What am I to hope, if my enemies attempt more
                        against me? Am I to expect the fate of Cassius and Maelius? You acted kindly
                        in appearing shocked at it: the gods will avert it: but never will they come
                        down from heaven on my account: they must inspire you with a determination
                        to avert it; as they inspired me, in arms and in peace, to defend you from
                        barbarous foes and tyrannical fellow-citizens. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Is the spirit of so great a people so mean, that aid
                        against your adversaries always satisfies you? And are you not to know any
                        contest against the patricians, except how you may suffer them to domineer
                        over you? Nor is this implanted in you by nature; but you are theirs by
                        possession. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For why is it you bear such
                        spirit with respect to foreigners, as to think it meet that you should rule
                        over them? because you have been accustomed to vie with them for empire,
                        against these to essay liberty rather than to maintain it. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Nevertheless, whatsoever sort of leaders you have,
                        whatever has been your own conduct, ye have up to this carried every thing
                        which ye have demanded, either by force, or your own good fortune.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It is now time to aim at still higher
                        objects. Only make trial both of your own good fortune, and of me, who have
                        been, as I hope, already tried to your advantage. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Ye will with less difficulty set up some one to rule
                        the patricians, than ye have set up persons to resist their rule.
                        Dictatorships and consulships must be levelled to the ground, that the Roman
                        commons may be able to raise their heads. Wherefore stand by me, prevent
                        judicial proceedings from going on regarding money. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> I profess myself the patron of the commons a title
                        with which my solicitude and zeal invests me. If you will dignify your
                        leader by any more distinguishing title of honour or command, ye will render
                        him still more powerful to obtain what ye desire. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> From this his first attempt is said to have
                    arisen with respect to the obtaining of regal power; but no sufficiently clear
                    account is handed down, either with whom [he acted], or how far his designs
                    extended. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But, on the other side, the senate began to
                    deliberate regarding the secession of the commons into a private house, and
                    that, as it so happened, situate in the citadel, and regarding <pb n="415"
                        xml:id="p.415"/> the great danger that was threatening liberty. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Great numbers cry out, that a Servilius Ahala was
                    wanted, who would not irritate a public enemy by ordering him to be led to
                    prison, but would finish an intestine war with the loss of one citizen.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They came to a resolution milder in terms,
                    but possessing the same force, that the magistrates should see that <quote>the
                        commonwealth received no detriment from the designs of Marcus
                        Manlius.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then the consular tribunes, and the tribunes
                    of the commons, (for these also had submitted to the authority of the senate,
                    because they saw that the termination of their own power and of the liberty of
                    all would be the same,) all these then consult together as to what was necessary
                    to be done. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When nothing suggested itself to
                    the mind of any, except violence and bloodshed, and it was evident that that
                    would be attended with great risk; then Marcus Maenius, and Quintus Publilius,
                    tribunes of the commons, say, <quote> Why do we make that a contest between the
                        patricians and commons, which ought to be between the state and one
                        pestilent citizen? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Why do we attack,
                        together with the commons, a man whom it is safer to attack through the
                        commons themselves, that he may fall overpowered by his own strength? We
                        have it in contemplation to appoint a day of trial for him. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Nothing is less popular than regal power; as soon as
                        the multitude shall perceive that the contest is not with them, and that
                        from advocates they are to be made judges, and shall behold the prosecutors
                        from among the commons, the accused a patrician, and that the charge between
                        both parties is that of aiming at regal power, they will favour no object
                        more than their own liberty. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the approbation of all, they appoint a
                    day of trial for Manlius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When this took
                    place, the commons were at first excited, especially when they saw the accused
                    in a mourning habit, and with him not only none of the patricians, but not even
                    any of his kinsmen or relatives, nay, not even his brothers Aulus and Titus
                    Manlius; a circumstance which had never occurred before, that at so critical a
                    juncture a man's nearest friends did not put on mourning. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When Appius Claudius was thrown into prison [they
                    remarked], that Caius Claudius, who was at enmity with him and the entire
                    Claudian family, appeared in mourning; that this favourite of the people was
                    about to be destroyed by a con- <pb n="416" xml:id="p.416"/> spiracy, because he
                    was the first who had come over from the patricians to the commons. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> When the day arrived, I find in no author, what acts
                    were alleged by the prosecutors against the accused bearing properly on the
                    charge of aspiring to kingly power, except his assembling the multitude, and his
                    seditious expressions and his largesses, and pretended discovery; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> nor have I any doubt that they were by no means
                    unimportant, as the people's delay in condemning him was occasioned not by the
                    merits of the cause, but by the place of trial. This seems deserving of notice,
                    that men may know what great and glorious achievements his depraved ambition of
                    regal power rendered not only bereft of all merit, but absolutely hateful.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He is said to have brought forward near
                    four hundred persons to whom he had lent money without interest, whose goods he
                    had prevented from being sold, whom he had prevented from being carried off to
                    prison after being adjudged to their creditors. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Besides this, that he not only enumerated also his military rewards, but also
                    produced them to view; spoils of enemies slain up to thirty; presents from
                    generals to the number of forty; in which the most remarkable were two mural
                    crowns and eight civic. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In addition to this,
                    that he brought forward citizens saved from the enemy, amongst whom was
                    mentioned Caius Servilius, when master of the horse, now absent. Then after he
                    had recounted his exploits in war, in pompous language suitable to the dignity
                    of the subject, equalling his actions by his eloquence, he bared his breast
                    marked with scars received in battle: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and now
                    and then, directing his eyes to the Capitol, he called down Jupiter and the
                    other gods to aid him in his present lot; and he prayed, that the same
                    sentiments with which they had inspired him when protecting the fortress of the
                    Capitol, for the preservation of the Roman people, they would now inspire the
                    Roman people with in his critical situation: and he entreated them singly and
                    collectively, that they would form their judgment of him with their eyes fixed
                    on the Capitol and citadel and their faces turned to the immortal gods.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As the people were summoned by centuries
                    in the field of Mars, and as the accused, extending his hands towards the
                    Capitol, directed his prayers from men to the gods; it became evident to the
                    tribunes, that unless they removed the eyes of men also from the memory of so
                    great an exploit, the best founded <pb n="417" xml:id="p.417"/> charge would
                    find no place in minds prejudiced by services. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> Thus the day of trial being adjourned, a meeting of the people was summoned
                    in the Pteline grove outside the Nomentan gate, from whence there was no view
                    of the Capitol; there the charge was made good, and their minds being now
                    unmoved [by adventitious circumstances], a fatal sentence, and one which excited
                    horror even in his judges, was passed on him. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    There are some who state that he was condemned by duumvirs appointed to inquire
                    concerning cases of treason. The tribunes cast him down from the Tarpeian rock:
                    and the same place in the case of one man became a monument of distinguished
                    glory and of extreme punishment. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Marks of
                    infamy were offered to him when dead: one, a public one; that, when his house
                    had been that where the temple of Moneta and the mint-office now stand, it was
                    proposed to the people, that no patrician should dwell in the citadel and
                    Capitol: the other appertaining to his family; <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> it being commanded by a decree that no one of the Manlian family should ever
                    after bear the name of Marcus Manlius. Such was the fate of a man, who, had he
                    not been born in a free state, would have been celebrated with posterity.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In a short time, when there was no longer
                    any danger from him, the people, recollecting only his virtues, were seized with
                    regret for him. A pestilence too which soon followed, no causes of so great a
                    calamity presenting themselves, seemed to a great many to have arisen from the
                    punishment inflicted on Manlius: <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>The Capitol</quote> [they said] <quote> had been polluted with the blood
                        of its preserver; nor was it agreeable to the gods that the punishment of
                        him by whom their temples had been rescued from the hands of the enemy, had
                        been brought in a manner before their eyes. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The pestilence was succeeded by a scarcity of
                    the fruits of the earth, and the report of both calamities by spreading [was
                    followed] by a variety of wars in the following year, Lucius Valerius a fourth
                    time, Aulus Manlius a third time, Servius Sulpicius a third time, Lucius
                    Lucretius, Lucius Aemilius a third time, Marcus Trebonius, being military
                    tribunes with consular power. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Besides the
                    Volscians, assigned by some fatality to give eternal employment to the Roman
                    soldiery, and the colonies of Circeii and Velitrae, long meditating a revolt,
                    and Latium which had been suspected, new <pb n="418" xml:id="p.418"/> enemies
                    suddenly sprung up in the people of Lanuvium, which had been a most faithful
                    city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The fathers, considering that this arose
                    from contempt, because the revolt of their own citizens, the people of Velitrae,
                    had been so long unpunished, decreed that a proposition should be submitted to
                    the people at the earliest opportunity on the subject of declaring war against
                    them: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and in order that the commons might be
                    the more disposed for that service, they appointed five commissioners for
                    distributing the Pomptine land, and three for conducting a colony to Nepete.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then it was proposed to the people that
                    they should order a declaration of war; and the plebeian tribunes in vain
                    endeavouring to dissuade them, all the tribes declared for war. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> That year preparations were made for war; the army was not
                    led out into the field on account of the pestilence. And that delay afforded
                    full time to the colonists to deprecate the anger of the senate; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and a great number of the people were disposed that a
                    suppliant embassy should be sent to Rome, had not the public been involved, as
                    is usual, with the private danger, and the abettors of the revolt from the
                    Romans, through fear, lest they, being alone answerable for the guilt, might be
                    given up as victims to the resentment of the Romans, dissuaded the colonies from
                    counsels of peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And not only was the
                    embassy obstructed by them in the senate, but a great part of the commons were
                    excited to make predatory excursions into the Roman territory. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> This new injury broke off all hope of peace. This year a
                    report first originated regarding a revolt of the Praenestines; and the people
                    of Tusculum, Gabii and Lavici, into whose territories the incursions had been
                    made, accusing them of the fact, the senate returned so placid an answer, that
                    it became evident that less credit was given to the charges, because they wished
                    them not to be true. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the following year the Papirii, Spurius and
                    Lucius, new military tribunes, led the legions to Velitrae; their four
                    colleagues in the tribuneship, Servius Cornelius Maluginensis a fourth time,
                    Quintus Servilius, Servius Sulpicius, Lucius Aemilius a fourth time, being left
                    behind to protect the city, and in case any new commotion should be announced
                    from Etruria; for every thing was apprehended from that quarter. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> At Velitrae they fought a successful battle against
                    the auxiliaries of the Praenestines, who were almost greater than the <pb
                        n="419" xml:id="p.419"/> number of colonists themselves; so that the
                    proximity of the city was both the cause of an earlier flight to the enemy, and
                    was their only refuge after the flight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    tribunes refrained from besieging the town, both because [the result] was
                    uncertain, and they considered that the war should not be pushed to the total
                    destruction of the colony. Letters were sent to Rome to the senate with news of
                    the victory, expressive of more animosity against the Praenestine enemy than
                    against those of Velitrae. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In consequence, by
                    a decree of the senate and an order of the people, war was declared against the
                    Praenestines: who, in conjunction with the Volscians, took, on the following
                    year, Satricum, a colony of the Roman people, by storm, after an obstinate
                    defence by the colonists, and made, with respect to the prisoners, a disgraceful
                    use of their victory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Incensed at this, the
                    Romans elected Marcus Furius Camillus a seventh time military tribune. The
                    colleagues conjoined with him were the two Postumii Regillenses, Aulus and
                    Lucius, and Lucius Furius, with Lucius Lucretius and Marcus Fabius Ambustus.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Volscian war was decreed to Marcus
                    Furius out of the ordinary course, Lucius Furius is assigned by lot from among
                    the tribunes his assistant; [which proved] not so advantageous to the public as
                    a source of all manner of praise to his colleague: both on public grounds,
                    because he restored the [Roman] interest which had been prostrated by his rash
                    conduct; and on private grounds, because from his error he sought to obtain his
                    gratitude rather than his own glory. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Camillus
                    was now in the decline of life, and when prepared at the election to take the
                    usual oath for the purpose of excusing himself on the plea of his health, he was
                    opposed by the consent of the people: but his active mind was still vigorous
                    within his ardent breast, and he enjoyed all his faculties entire, and now that
                    he concerned himself but little in civil affairs, war still aroused him.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Having enlisted four legions of four
                    thousand men each, and having ordered the troops to assemble the next day at the
                    Esquiline gate, he set out to Satricum. There the conquerors of the colony,
                    nowise dismayed, confiding in their number of men, in which they had
                    considerably the advantage, awaited him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                    they perceived that the Romans were approaching, they marched out immediately to
                    the field, determined to make no delay to put all to the risk of an engagement,
                    that by proceeding thus they <pb n="420" xml:id="p.420"/> should derive no
                    advantage from the judgment of their distinguished commander, on which alone
                    they confided. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same ardour existed also in the Roman
                    army; nor did any thing, but the wisdom and authority of one man, delay the
                    fortune of the present engagement, who sought, by protracting the war, an
                    opportunity of aiding their strength by skill. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The enemy urged them the more on that account, and now not only did they draw
                    out their troops in order of battle before their camp, but advanced into the
                    middle of the plain, and by throwing up trenches near the battalions of the
                    enemy, made a show of their insolent confidence in their strength. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman soldier was indignant at this; the other
                    military tribune, Lucius Furius, still more so, who, encouraged both by his
                    youth and his natural disposition, was still further elated by the hopes
                    entertained by the multitude, who assumed great spirits on grounds the most
                    uncertain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The soldiers, already excited of
                    themselves, he still further instigated by disparaging the authority of his
                    colleague by reference to his age, the only point on which he could do so:
                    saying constantly, <quote> that wars were the province of young men, and that
                        with the body the mind also flourishes and withers; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> that from having been a most vigorous warrior he was
                        become a drone; and that he who, on coming up, had been wont to carry off
                        camps and cities at the first onset, now consumed the time inactive within
                        the trenches. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What accession to his own
                        strength, or diminution of that of the enemy, did he hope for? <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> What opportunity, what season, what place for
                        practising stratagem? that the old man's plans were frigid and languid.
                        Camillus had both sufficient share of life as well as of glory. What use was
                        it to suffer the strength of a state which ought to be immortal, to sink
                        into old age along with one mortal body. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By such observations, he had attracted to
                    himself the attention of the entire camp; and when in every quarter battle was
                    called for, <quote>We cannot,</quote> he says, <quote> Marcus Furius, withstand
                        the violence of the soldiers; and the enemy, whose spirits we have increased
                        by delaying, insults us by insolence by no means to be borne. Do you, who
                        are but one man, yield to all, and suffer yourself to be overcome in
                        counsel, that you may the sooner overcome in battle. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To this Camillus replies, that <quote>
                        whatever wars had been waged up to that day under his single auspices, in
                            <pb n="421" xml:id="p.421"/> these that neither himself nor the Roman
                        people had been dissatisfied either with his judgment or with his fortune;
                        now he knew that he had a colleague, his equal in command and in authority,
                        in vigour of age superior; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> with respect
                        to the army, that he had been accustomed to rule, not to be ruled; with his
                        colleague's authority he could not interfere. That he might do, with the
                        favour of the gods, whatever he might deem to be to the interest of the
                        state. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That he would even solicit for his
                        years the indulgence, that he might not be placed in the front line; that
                        whatever duties in war an old man could discharge, in these he would not be
                        deficient; that he prayed to the immortal gods, that no mischance might
                        prove his plan to be the more advisable. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Neither his salutary advice was listened to
                    by men, nor such pious prayers by the gods. The adviser of the battle draws up
                    the front line; Camillus forms the reserve, and posts a strong guard before the
                    camp; he himself took his station on an elevated place as a spectator, anxiously
                    watching the result of the other's plan. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as the arms clashed at the first
                    encounter, the enemy, from stratagem, not from fear, retreated. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> There was a gentle acclivity in their rear, between the
                    army and their camp; and because they had sufficient numbers, they had left in
                    the camp several strong cohorts, armed and ready for action, which were to rush
                    forth, when the battle was now commenced, and when the enemy had approached the
                    rampart. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman being drawn into
                    disadvantageous ground by following the retreating enemy in disorder, became
                    exposed to this sally. Terror therefore being turned on the victor, by reason of
                    this new force, and the declivity of the valley, caused the Roman line to give
                    way. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Volscians, who made the attack from
                    the camp, being fresh, press on them; those also who had given way by a
                    pretended flight, renew the fight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman
                    soldiers no longer recovered themselves; but unmindful of their recent
                    presumption and former glory, were turning their backs in every direction, and
                    with disorderly speed were making for their camp, when Camillus, being mounted
                    on his horse by those around him, and hastily opposing the reserved troops to
                    them, <quote>Is this,</quote> says he, <quote> soldiers, the battle which ye
                        called for? What man, what god is there, whom ye can blame? That was your
                        rashness, this your <pb n="422" xml:id="p.422"/> cowardice. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Having followed another leader, now follow Camillus;
                        and as ye are accustomed to do under my leadership, conquer. Why do ye look
                        to the rampart and camp? Not a man of you shall that camp receive, except as
                        victor. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Shame at first stopped their disorderly
                    flight; then when they saw the standards wheel about, and a line formed to meet
                    the enemy, and the general, besides being distinguished by so many triumphs,
                    venerable also by his age, presented himself in front of the battalions, where
                    the greatest toil and danger was, every one began to upbraid both himself and
                    others, and mutual exhortation with a brisk shout pervaded the entire line.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor was the other tribune deficient on the
                    occasion. Being despatched to the cavalry by his colleague, who was restoring
                    the line of the infantry, not by rebuking them, (for which task his share in
                    their fault had rendered him an authority of little weight,) but from command
                    turning entirely to entreaties, he besought them individually and collectively,
                        <quote> to redeem him from blame, who was answerable for the events of that
                        day. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Notwithstanding the repugnance and
                        dissuasion of my colleague, I gave myself a partner in the rashness of all
                        rather than in the prudence of one. Camillus sees his own glory in your
                        fortune, whatever it be; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> for my part,
                        unless the battle is restored, I shall feel the result with you all, the
                        infamy alone (which is most distressing). </quote> It was deemed best that
                    the horse should be transferred into the line whilst still unsteady, and that
                    they should attack the enemy by fighting on foot. Distinguished by their arms
                    and courage, they proceed in whatever direction they perceive the line of the
                    infantry most pressed; nor among either the officers or soldiers is there any
                    abatement observed from the utmost effort of courage. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The result therefore felt the aid of the bravery exerted;
                    and the Volscians being put to real flight in that direction in which they had
                    lately retreated under pretended fear, great numbers were slain both in the
                    battle itself, and afterwards in flight; the others in the camp, which was taken
                    in the same onset: more, however, were captured than slain. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Where when, on taking an account of the
                    prisoners, several Tusculans were recognised, being separated from the rest,
                    they are brought to the tribunes; and they confessed to those who interrogated
                    them, that they had taken up arms by the authority of the state. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> By the fear of which war <pb n="423" xml:id="p.423"/>
                    so near home Camillus being alarmed, says that he would immediately carry the
                    prisoners to Rome, that the senate might not be ignorant, that the Tusculans had
                    revolted from the alliance; meanwhile his colleague, if he thought proper,
                    should command the camp and army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> One day had
                    been a lesson to him not to prefer his own counsels to better. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> However neither himself, nor any person in the army,
                    supposed that Camillus would pass over his misconduct without some angry
                    feelings, by which the commonwealth had been brought into so perilous a
                    situation; and both in the army and at Rome, the uniform account of all was,
                    that, as matters had been conducted with varying success among the Volscians,
                    the blame of the unsuccessful battle and of the flight lay with Lucius Furius,
                    all the glory of the successful one was to be attributed to Camillus. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The prisoners being brought into the senate, when the
                    senate decreed that the Tusculans should be punished with war, and they
                    intrusted the management of that war to Camillus, he requests one assistant for
                    himself in that business, and being allowed to select which ever of his
                    colleagues he pleased, contrary to the expectation of every one, he solicited
                    Lucius Furius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By which moderation of feeling
                    he both alleviated the disgrace of his colleague, and acquired great glory to
                    himself. There was no war, however, with the Tusculans. By firm adherence to
                    peace they warded off the Roman violence, which they could not have done by
                    arms. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the Romans entered their
                    territories, no removals were made from the places adjoining to the road, the
                    cultivation of the lands was not interrupted: the gates of the city lying open,
                    they came forth in crowds clad in their gowns to meet the generals; provision
                    for the army was brought with alacrity from the city and the lands. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Camillus having pitched his camp before the gates,
                    wishing to know whether the same appearance of peace, which was <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> displayed in the country, prevailed also within the
                    walls, entered the city, where he beheld the gates lying open, and every thing
                    exposed to sale in the open shops, and the workmen engaged each on their
                    respective employments, and the schools of learning buzzing with the voices of
                    the scholars, and the streets filled amid the different kinds of people, with
                    boys and women going different ways, whithersoever the occasions of their
                    respective callings carried them; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> nothing in
                    any quarter that bore any appear- <pb n="424" xml:id="p.424"/> ance of panic or
                    even of surprise; he looked around at every object, attentively inquiring where
                    the war had been. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No trace was there of any
                    thing having been removed, or brought forward for the occasion; so completely
                    was every thing in a state of steady tranquil peace, so that it scarcely seemed
                    that even the rumour of war could have reached them. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Overcome therefore by the submissive demeanour
                    of the enemy, he ordered their senate to be called. <quote>Tusculans,</quote> he
                    says, <quote> ye are the only persons who have yet found the true arms and the
                        true strength, by which to protect your possessions from the resentment of
                        the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Proceed to Rome to the senate.
                        The fathers will consider, whether you have merited more punishment for your
                        former conduct, or forgiveness for your present. I shall not anticipate your
                        gratitude for a favour to be conferred by the state. From me ye shall have
                        the power of seeking pardon. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate
                        will grant to your entreaties such a result, as they shall consider meet.
                    </quote> When the Tusculans came to Rome, and the senate [of a people], who were
                    till a little before faithful allies, were seen with sorrowful countenances in
                    the porch of the senate-house, the fathers, immediately moved [at the sight,]
                    even then ordered them to be called in rather in a friendly than a hostile
                    manner. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Tusculan dictator spoke as
                    follows: <quote> Conscript fathers, we against whom ye proclaimed and made war,
                        just as you see us now standing in the porch of your house, so armed and so
                        attired did we go forth to meet your generals and your legions. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> This was our habit, this the habit of our
                        commons; and ever shall be, unless whenever we shall receive arms from you
                        and defence of you. We return thanks to your generals and your troops for
                        having trusted their eyes more than their ears; and for having committed
                        nothing hostile, where none subsisted. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        peace, which we observed, the same we solicit at your hands: we pray you,
                        avert war to that quarter where, if any where, it subsists. What your arms
                        may be able to effect on us, if after our submission we are to experience
                        it, we will experience unarmed. This is our determination. May the immortal
                        gods grant that it be as successful as it is dutiful! <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> With respect to the charges, by which you were induced
                        to declare war against us, though it is needless to refute by words what has
                        been contradicted by facts; yet, admitting they were true, we think it safe
                        for us to confess <pb n="425" xml:id="p.425"/> them, after having shown such
                        evident marks of repentance. Admit then that we have offended against you,
                        since ye deserve that such satisfaction be made to you. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These were nearly the words used by the
                    Tusculans. They obtained peace at the present, and not long after the freedom of
                    the state also. The legions were withdrawn from Tusculum. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Camillus, distinguished by his prudence and
                    bravery in the Volscian war, by his success in the Tusculan expedition, in both
                    by his extraordinary moderation and forbearance towards his colleague, went out
                    of office; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the military tribunes for the
                    following year being Lucius and Publius Valerius, Lucius a fifth, Publius a
                    third time, and Caius Sergius a third time, Lucius Menenius a second time,
                    Spurius Papirius, and Servius Cornelius Maluginensis. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The year required censors also, chiefly on account of the
                    uncertain representations regarding the debt; the tribunes of the commons
                    exaggerating the amount of it on account of the odium of the thing, whilst it
                    was underrated by those whose interest it was that the difficulty of procuring
                    payment should appear to depend rather on [the want of] integrity, than of
                    ability in the debtors. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The censors appointed
                    were Caius Sulpicius Camerinus, Spurius Postumius Regillensis; and the matter
                    having been commenced was interrupted by the death of Postumius, because it was
                    not conformable to religion that a substitute should be colleague to a censor.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly after Sulpicius had resigned
                    his office, other censors having been appointed under some defect, they did not
                    discharge the office; that a third set should be appointed was not allowed, as
                    though the gods did not admit a censorship for that year. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The tribunes denied that such mockery of the commons was to
                    be tolerated; <quote> that the senate were averse to the public tablets, the
                        witnesses of each man's property, because they were unwilling that the
                        amount of the debt should be seen, which would clearly show that one part of
                        the state was depressed by the other; whilst in the mean time the commons,
                        oppressed with debt, were exposed to one enemy after another. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Wars were now sought out in every direction
                        without distinction. Troops were marched from Antium to Satricum, from
                        Satricum to Velitrae, and thence to Tusculum. The Latins, Hernicians, and
                        the Praenestines were now threatened with hostilities, more through a hatred
                        of their fellow-citizens than of the enemy, in order to wear out the commons
                        under arms, <pb n="426" xml:id="p.426"/> and not suffer them to breathe in
                        the city, or to reflect on their liberty at their leisure, or to stand in an
                        assembly where they may hear a tribune's voice discussing concerning the
                        reduction of interest and the termination of other grievances. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> But if the commons had a spirit mindful of the
                        liberty of their fathers, that they would neither suffer any Roman citizen
                        to be assigned to a creditor on account of debt, nor a levy to be held;
                        until, the debts being examined, and some method adopted for lessening them,
                        each man should know what was his own, and what another's; whether his
                        person was still free to him, or that also was due to the stocks. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The price held out for sedition soon raised
                    it: for both several were made over to creditors, and on account of the rumour
                    of the Praenestine war, the senate decreed that new legions should be levied;
                    both which measures began to be obstructed by tribunitian interposition and the
                    combined efforts of the commons. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For neither
                    the tribunes suffered those consigned to their creditors to be thrown into
                    prison, nor did the young men give in their names. While the senate felt less
                    pressing anxiety about enforcing the laws regarding the lending of money than
                    about the levy; for now it was announced that the enemy, having marched from
                    Praeneste, had encamped in the Gabinian territory; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> meanwhile this very report rather aroused the tribunes of
                    the commons to the struggle commenced than deterred them; nor did any thing else
                    suffice to allay the discontent in the city, but the approach of hostilities to
                    the very walls. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For when the Praenestines had been informed
                    that no army was levied at Rome, no general fixed on, that the senate and people
                    were turned the one against the other; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> their
                    leaders thinking that an opportunity presented itself, making a hasty march, and
                    laying waste the country as they went along, they advanced their standards as
                    far as the Colline gate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Tile panic in the
                    city was great. The alarm was given to take up arms; persons ran together to the
                    walls and gates, and at length turning from sedition to war, they created Titus
                    Quinctius Cincinnatus dictator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He appointed
                    Aulus Sempronius Atratinus his master of the horse. When this was heard, (such
                    was the terror of that office,) the enemy retired from the walls, and the young
                    Romans assembled to the edict without refusal. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Whilst the army is being levied at Rome, in the <pb n="427" xml:id="p.427"/>
                    mean time the enemy's camp is pitched not far from the river Allia: thence
                    laying waste the land far and wide, they boasted one to the other that they had
                    chosen a place fatal to the Roman city; that there would be a similar
                    consternation and flight from thence as occurred in the Gallic war. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> For <quote> if the Romans dread a day deemed
                        inauspicious, and marked with the name of that place, how much more than the
                        Allian day would they dread the Allia itself, the monument of so great a
                        disaster. No doubt the fierce looks of the Gauls and the sound of their
                        voices would recur to their eyes and ears. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Turning over in mind those groundless notions
                    of circumstances as groundless, they rested their hopes on the fortune of the
                    place. On the other hand, the Romans [considered] that, <quote> in whatever
                        place a Latin enemy stood, they knew full well that they were the same whom,
                        after having utterly defeated at the lake Regillus, they kept in peaceable
                        subjection for one hundred years; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that the
                        place being distinguished by the memory of their defeat, would rather
                        stimulate them to blot out the remembrance of their disgrace, than raise a
                        fear that any land should be unfavourable to their success. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Were even the Gauls themselves presented to them in
                        that place, that they would fight just as they fought at Rome in recovering
                        their country, as the day after at Gabii; then, when they took care, that no
                        enemy, who had entered the walls of Rome, should carry home an account of
                        their success or defeat. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With these feelings on either side they came
                    to the Allia. The Roman dictator, when the enemy were in view drawn up and ready
                    for action, says, <quote> Aulus Sempronius, do you see that these men have taken
                        their stand at the Allia, relying on the fortune of the place? nor have the
                        immortal gods granted them any thing of surer confidence, or any more
                        effectual support. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But do you, relying on
                        arms and on courage, make a brisk charge on the middle of their line; I will
                        bear down on them when thrown into disorder and consternation with the
                        legions. Ye gods, witnesses of the treaty, assist us, and exact the penalty,
                        due for yourselves having been violated, and for us who have been deceived
                        through the appeal made to your divinity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Praenestines sustained not the attack of
                    cavalry, or infantry; their ranks were broken at the first charge and shout.
                    Then when their line maintained its ground in no quarter, they turn their backs;
                    and being <pb n="428" xml:id="p.428"/> thrown into consternation and carried
                    beyond their own camp by their panic, they stop not from their precipitate
                    speed, until Praeneste came in view. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There,
                    having been dispersed in consequence of their flight, they select a post for the
                    purpose of fortifying it in a hasty manner; lest, if they betook themselves
                    within the walls, the country should be burned forthwith, and when all places
                    should be desolated, siege should be laid to the city. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> But when the victorious Romans approached, the camp at the
                    Allia having been plundered, that fortress also was abandoned, and considering
                    the walls scarcely secure, they shut themselves up within the town of Praeneste.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There were eight towns besides under the
                    sway of the Praenestines. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hostilities were
                    carried round to these also; and these being taken one after the other without
                    much difficulty, the army was led to Velitrae. This also was taken by storm.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They then came to Praeneste, the main
                    source of the war. That town was obtained, not by force, but by capitulation.
                    Titus Quinctius, being once victorious in a pitched battle, having taken also
                    two camps belonging to the enemy, and nine towns by storm, and Praeneste being
                    obtained by surrender, returned to Rome: and in his triumph brought into the
                    Capitol the statue of Jupiter Imperator, which he had conveyed from Praeneste.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was dedicated between the recesses of
                    Jupiter and Minerva, and a tablet fixed under it, as a monument of his exploits,
                    was engraved with nearly these words: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Jupiter and all the gods granted, that Titus Quinctius, dictator, should
                        take nine towns. </quote> On the twentieth day after the appointment he
                    abdicated the dictatorship. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An election was then held of military tribunes
                    with consular power; in which the number of patricians and plebeians was equal.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From the patricians were elected Publius
                    and Caius Manlius, with Lucius Julius; the commons gave Caius Sextilius, Marcus
                    Albinius, and Lucius Antistius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the Manlii,
                    because they had the advantage of the plebeians in family station, and of Julius
                    in interest, the province of the Volscians was assigned out of the ordinary
                    course, without lots, or mutual arrangement; of which circumstance both
                    themselves and the patricians who conferred it afterwards repented. Without any
                    previous reconnoitre they sent out some cohorts to forage. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It having been falsely reported to <pb n="429"
                        xml:id="p.429"/> them that these were ensnared, whilst they march in great
                    haste, in order to support them, without even retaining the author [of the
                    report] who had deceived them, he being a Latin enemy instead of a Roman
                    soldier, they themselves fell into an ambuscade. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> There, whilst they suffer and commit great havoc, making resistance on
                    disadvantageous ground solely by the valour of the soldiers, the enemy in the
                    mean time in another quarter attacked the Roman camp which was situate on a
                    plain. By their temerity and want of skill, matters were brought into jeopardy
                    in both places by the generals. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whatever
                    portion [of the army] was saved, the good fortune of the Roman people, and the
                    steady valour of the soldiers, even without a director, protected. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When an account of these events was brought to Rome,
                    it was at first agreeable to them that a dictator should be appointed; then when
                    intelligence was received from the Volscian country that matters were quiet, and
                    it appeared manifest that they knew not how to take advantage of victory and of
                    opportunity, the army and generals were recalled from thence also; and there was
                    quiet from that quarter, as far as regarded the Volscians. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The only disturbance there was towards the end of the year
                    was, that the Praenestines, having stirred up some of the states of the Latins,
                    renewed hostilities. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> During the same year new
                    colonists were enrolled for Setia, the colony itself complaining of the paucity
                    of men. Domestic tranquillity, which the influence of the plebeian military
                    tribunes and the respect shown to them among their own party procured, was a
                    consolation for the want of success in war. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commencement of the following year blazed
                    forth with violent sedition, the military tribunes with consular power being
                    Spurius Furius, Quintus Servilius a second time, Caius Licinius, Publius
                    Cllius, Marcus Horatius, Lucius Geganius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    debt was both the ground-work and cause of the disturbance: for the purpose of
                    ascertaining which Spurius Servilius Priscus and Quintus Cllius Siculus, being
                    appointed censors, were prevented by war from proceeding in the business.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For alarming news at first, then the
                    flight [of the country people] from the lands, brought intelligence that the
                    legions of the Volscians had entered the borders, and were laying waste the
                    Roman land in every direction. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In which alarm,
                    so far was the fear of the foreign enemy <pb n="430" xml:id="p.430"/> from
                    putting a check to the domestic feuds, that on the contrary the tribunitian
                    power became even more vehement in obstructing the levy; until these conditions
                    were imposed on the patricians, that no one was to pay tribute as long as the
                    war lasted, nor issue any judicial process respecting money due. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> This relaxation being obtained for the commons, there
                    was no delay with respect to the levy. New legions being enlisted, it was
                    resolved that two armies should be led into the Volscian territory, the legions
                    being divided. Spurius Furius and Marcus Horatius proceed to the right, towards
                    the sea-coast and Antium; Quintus Servilius and Lucius Geganius to the left, to
                    Ecetra towards the mountains. On neither side did the enemy meet them.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Devastation was therefore committed, not
                    similar to that straggling kind which the Volscian had practised by snatches
                    under the influence of trepidation after the manner of a banditti, relying on
                    the dissensions among the enemy and dreading their valour; but committed with
                    the full meed of their resentment by a regular army, more severe also by reason
                    of their continuance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For the incursions had
                    been made by the Volscians on the skirts of the borders, as they were afraid
                    lest an army might in the mean time come forth from Rome: the Romans, on the
                    contrary, had a motive for tarrying in the enemy's country, in order to entice
                    them to an engagement. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All the houses
                    therefore on the lands, and some villages also, being burnt down, not a
                    fruit-tree nor the seed being left for the hope of a harvest, all the booty both
                    of men and cattle, which was outside the walls, being driven off, the troops
                    were led back from both quarters to Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A short interval having been granted to the
                    debtors to recover breath, when matters became perfectly quiet with respect to
                    the enemy, legal proceedings began to be instituted anew; and so remote was all
                    hope of relieving the former debt, that a new one was now contracted by a tax
                    for building a wall of hewn stone bargained for by the censors: <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> to which burden the commons were obliged to submit, because
                    the tribunes of the commons had no levy which they could obstruct. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Forced by the influence of the nobles, they elected
                    all the military tribunes from among the patricians, Lucius Aemilius, Publius
                    Valerius a fourth time, Caius Veturius, Servius Sulpicius, Lucius and Caius
                    Quinctius Cincinnatus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="431" xml:id="p.431"/> By the same influence they succeeded in raising
                    three armies against the Latins and Volscians, who with combined forces were
                    encamped at Satricum, all the juniors being bound by the military oath without
                    any opposition; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> one army for the protection of
                    the city; the other to be sent for the sudden emergencies of war, if any
                    disturbance should arise elsewhere. The third, and by far the most powerful,
                    Publius Valerius and Lucius Aemilius led to Satricum. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Where when they found the enemy's line of battle drawn up
                    on level ground, they immediately engaged; and before the victory was
                    sufficiently declared, the battle, which held out fair hopes of success, was put
                    a stop to by rain accompanied by a violent storm of wind. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> On the following day the battle was renewed; and for a
                    considerable time the Latin troops particularly, who had learned the Roman
                    discipline during the long confederacy, stood their ground with equal bravery
                    and success. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A charge of cavalry broke their
                    ranks; when thus confused, the infantry advanced upon them; and as much as the
                    Roman line advanced, so much were the enemy dislodged from their ground; and
                    when once the battle gave way, the Roman prowess became irresistible. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> When the enemy being routed made for Satricum, which
                    was two miles distant, not for their camp, they were cut down chiefly by the
                    cavalry; their camp was taken and plundered. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The night succeeding the battle, they betake themselves to Antium in a march
                    resembling a flight; and though the Roman army followed them almost in their
                    steps, fear however possessed more swiftness than anger. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Wherefore the enemy entered the walls before the Roman
                    could annoy or impede their rear. After that several days were spent in laying
                    waste the country, as the Romans were neither supplied with military engines to
                    attack walls, nor the others to hazard the chance of a battle. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this time a dissension arose between the
                    Antians and the Latins; when the Antians, overcome by misfortunes and reduced by
                    a war, in which they had both been born and had grown old, began to think of a
                    surrender; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> whilst their recent revolt after a
                    long peace, their spirits being still fresh, rendered the Latins more determined
                    to persevere in the war. There was an end to the contest, when it became evident
                    to both parties that neither would stand in the way of the other <pb n="432"
                        xml:id="p.432"/> so as to prevent them from following out their own views.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Latins by departing redeemed
                    themselves from a share in what they deemed a dishonourable peace. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The Antians, on the removal of those who by their
                    presence impeded their salutary counsels, surrender their city and lands to the
                    Romans. The resentment and rage of the Latins, because they were neither able to
                    damage the Romans in war, nor to retain the Volscians in arms, vented itself in
                    setting fire to the city of Satricum, which had been their first place of
                    retreat after their defeat; nor did any other building in that city remain,
                    since they cast firebrands indiscriminately into those sacred and profane,
                    except the temple of Mother Matuta. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From that
                    neither the sanctity of the building itself, nor respect for the gods, is said
                    to have restrained them, but an awful voice, emitted from the temple with
                    threats of dismal vengeance, unless they removed their abominable fires to a
                    distance from the temples. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Fired with this
                    rage, their impetuosity carried them on to Tusculum, under the influence of'
                    resentment, because, having abandoned the general association of the Latins,
                    they joined themselves not only in alliance with the Romans, but also as members
                    of their state. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As they unexpectedly rushed in
                    at the gates, which were lying open, the town, except the citadel, was taken at
                    the first shout. The townsmen with their wives and children took refuge in the
                    citadel, and sent messengers to Rome, to inform the senate of their situation.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> An army was led to Tusculum with no less
                    expedition than was worthy of the honour of the Roman people. Lucius Quinctius
                    and Servius Sulpicius, military tribunes, commanded it. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> They beheld the gates of Tusculum shut, and the Latins,
                    with the feelings of besiegers and besieged, on the one side defending the walls
                    of Tusculum, on the other hand attacking the citadel; they struck terror and
                    felt it at the same time. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The arrival of the
                    Romans produced a change in the minds of both parties: it turned the Tusculans
                    from great alarm into the utmost alacrity, and the Latins from almost assured
                    confidence of soon taking the citadel, as they were masters of the town, to very
                    slender hope of even their own safety. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A
                    shout is raised by the Tusculans from the citadel; it is answered by a much
                    louder one from the Roman army. The Latins are hard pressed on both sides: they
                    neither withstand the force of the Tusculans pouring down on them from the
                    higher ground; nor are they <pb n="433" xml:id="p.433"/> able to repel the
                    Romans advancing up to the walls, and forcing the bars of the gates. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> The walls were first taken by scalade; the gates
                    were then broken open; and when the two enemies pressed them both in front and
                    in the rear, nor did there remain any strength for fight, nor any room for
                    running away, between both they were all cut to pieces to a man. Tusculum being
                    recovered from the enemy, the army was led back to Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In proportion as all matters were more
                    tranquil abroad in consequence of their successes in war this year, so much did
                    the violence of the patricians and the distresses of the commons in the city
                    increase every day; as the ability to pay was prevented by the very fact that it
                    was necessary to pay. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly, when
                    nothing could now be paid out of their property, being cast in suits and
                    assigned over to custody, they satisfied their creditors by their character and
                    persons, and punishment was substituted for payment. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Wherefore not only the lowest, but even the leading men in
                    the commons had sunk so low in spirit, that no enterprising and adventurous man
                    had courage, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> not only to stand for the
                    military tribuneship among the patricians, (for which privilege they had
                    strained all their energies,) but not even to take on them and sue for plebeian
                    magistracies: and the patricians seemed to have for ever recovered the
                    possession of an honour that had been only usurped by the commons for a few
                    years. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A trifling cause, as generally happens,
                    which had the effect of producing a mighty result, intervened to prevent the
                    other party from exulting too much in that. Two daughters of Marcus Fabius
                    Ambustus, an influential man, both among persons of his own station, and also
                    with the commons, because he was by no means considered a despiser of persons of
                    that order, had been married, the elder to Servius Sulpicius, the younger to
                    Caius Licinius Stolo, a distinguished person, but still a plebeian; and the fact
                    of such an alliance not having been scorned, had gained influence for Fabius
                    with the people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It so happened, that when the
                    two sisters, the Fabiae, were passing away the time in conversation in the house
                    of Servius Sulpicius. military tribune, a lictor of Sulpicius, when he returned
                    home from the forum, rapped at the door, as is usual, with the rod. When the
                    younger Fabia, a stranger to this custom, was frightened at it, she was laughed
                    at by her sister, who was surprised at her sister not knowing the matter.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That laugh, however, gave a sting to the
                    female <pb n="434" xml:id="p.434"/> mind, sensitive as it is to mere trifles.
                    From the number of persons attending on her, and asking her commands, her
                    sister's match, I suppose, appeared to her to be a fortunate one, and she
                    repined at her own, according to that erroneous feeling, by which every one is
                    most annoyed at being outstripped by those nearest to him. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When her father happened to see her disappointed after the
                    recent mortification, by kindly inquiring he prevailed on her, who was
                    dissembling the cause of her annoyance, (as being neither affectionate with
                    respect to her <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> sister, nor respectful
                    towards her husband,) to confess, that the cause of her chagrin was, that she
                    had been united to an inferior, and married into a house which neither honour
                    nor influence could enter. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Ambustus then,
                    consoling his daughter, bid her keep up good spirits; that she should soon see
                    the same honours at her own house, which she now sees at her sister's. Upon
                        <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> this he began to draw up his plans with
                    his son-in-law, having attached to himself Lucius Sextius, an enterprising young
                    man, and one to whose hope nothing was wanting but patrician descent. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There appeared a favourable opportunity for
                    making innovations on account of the immense load of debt, no alleviation of
                    which evil the commons could hope for unless their own party were placed in the
                    highest authority. To [bring about] that object [they saw] that they should
                    exert themselves. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That the plebeians, by
                    endeavouring and persevering, had already gained a step towards it, whence, if
                    they struggled forward, they might reach the summit, and be on a level with the
                    patricians, in honour as well as in merit. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For
                    the present it was resolved that plebeian tribunes should be created, in which
                    office they might open for themselves a way to other honours. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And Caius Licinius and Lucius Sextius, being elected
                    tribunes, proposed laws all against the power of the patricians, and for the
                    interests of the commons: one regarding the debt, that, whatever had been paid
                    in interest being deduced from the principal, the remainder should be paid off
                    in three years by equal instalments; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the other
                    concerning the limitation of land, that no one should possess more than five
                    hundred acres of land; a third, that there should be no election of military
                    tribunes, and that one at least of the consuls should be elected from the
                    commons; all matters of great importance, and such as could not be attained
                    without <pb n="435" xml:id="p.435"/> the greatest struggles. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> A contest therefore for all those objects, of which there
                    is ever an inordinate desire among men, viz. land, money, and honours, being now
                    proposed, the patricians became terrified and dismayed, and finding no other
                    remedy in their public and private consultations except the protest, which had
                    been tried in many previous contests, they gained over their colleagues to
                    oppose the bills of the tribunes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When they
                    saw the tribes summoned by Licinius and Sextius to announce their votes,
                    surrounded by bands of patricians, they neither suffered the bills to be read,
                    nor any other usual form for taking the votes of the commons to be gone through.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And now assemblies being frequently
                    convened to no purpose, when the propositions were now considered as rejected;
                        <quote>It is very well,</quote> says Sextius; "since it is determined that a
                    protest should possess so much power, by that same weapon will we protect the
                    people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Come, patricians, proclaim an assembly
                    for the election of military tribunes; I will take care that that word, I FORBID
                    IT, which you listen to our colleagues chaunting with so much pleasure, shall
                    not be very delightful to you. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor did the
                    threats fall ineffectual: no elections were held, except those of aediles and
                    plebeian tribunes. Licinius and Sextius, being re-elected plebeian tribunes,
                    suffered not any curule magistrates to be appointed, and this total absence of
                    magistrates continued in the city for the space of five years, the people
                    re-electing the two tribunes, and these preventing the election of military
                    tribunes. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was an opportune cessation of other
                    wars: the colonists of Velitrae, becoming wanton through ease, because there was
                    no Roman army, made repeated incursions on the Roman territory, and set about
                    laying siege to Tusculum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This circumstance,
                    the Tusculans, old allies, new fellow-citizens, imploring aid, moved not only
                    the patricians, but the commons also, chiefly with a sense of honour. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the commons relaxing their
                    opposition, the elections were held by the interrex; and Lucius Furius, Aulus
                    Manlius, Servius Sulpicius, Servius Cornelius, Publius and Caius Valerius, found
                    the commons by no means so complying in the levy as in the elections; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> and an army having been raised amid great contention,
                    they set out, and not only dislodged the enemy from Tusculum, but shut them up
                    even within their own walls. Velitrae began to be besieged by a much <pb n="436"
                        xml:id="p.436"/> greater force than that with which Tusculum had been
                    besieged; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> nor still could it be taken by those
                    by whom the siege had been commenced. The new military tribunes were elected
                    first: Quintius Servilius, Caius Veturius, Aulus and Marcus Cornelius, Quintus
                    Quinctius, Marcus Fabius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nothing worthy of
                    mention was performed even by these at Velitrae. Matters were involved in
                    greater peril at home: for besides Sextius and Licinius, the proposers of the
                    laws, reelected tribunes of the commons now for the eighth time, Fabius also,
                    military tribune, father-in-law of Stolo, avowed himself the unhesitating
                    supporter of those laws of which he had been the adviser. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And whereas, there had been at first eight of the college
                    of the plebeian tribunes protesters against the laws, there were now only five:
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and (as is usual with men who leave their
                    own party) dismayed and astounded, they in words borrowed from others, urged as
                    a reason for their protest, that which had been taught them at home; <quote>
                        that a great number of the commons were absent with the army at Velitrae;
                        that the assembly ought to be deferred till the coming of the soldiers, that
                        the entire body of the commons might give their vote concerning their own
                        interests. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Sextius and Licinius with some of their
                    colleagues, and Fabius one of the military tribunes, well-versed now by an
                    experience of many years in managing the minds <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> of the commons, having brought forward the leading men of
                    the patricians, teased them by interrogating them on each of the subjects which
                    were about to be brought before the people: <quote> would they dare to demand,
                        that when two acres of land a head were distributed among the plebeians,
                        they themselves should be allowed to have more than five hundred acres?
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that a single man should possess the
                        share of nearly three hundred citizens; whilst his portion of land scarcely
                        extended for the plebeian to a stinted habitation and a place of burial?
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Was it their wish that the commons,
                        surrounded with usury, should surrender their persons to the stocks and to
                        punishment, rather than pay off their debt by [discharging] the principal;
                        and that persons should be daily led off from the forum in flocks, after
                        being assigned to their creditors, and that the houses of the nobility
                        should be filled with prisoners? and that wherever a patrician dwelt, there
                        should be a private prison? </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they had uttered these statements,
                    exasperating <pb n="437" xml:id="p.437"/> and pitiable in the recital, before
                    persons alarmed for themselves, exciting greater indignation in the hearers than
                    was <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> felt by themselves, they affirmed
                        <quote> that there never would be any other limit to their occupying the
                        lands, or to their butchering the commons by usury, unless the commons were
                        to elect one consul from among the plebeians, as a guardian of their
                        liberty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That the tribunes of the commons
                        were now despised, as being an office which breaks down its own power by the
                        privilege of protest. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That there could be
                        no equality of right, where the dominion was in the hands of the one party,
                        assistance only in that of the other. Unless the authority were shared, the
                        commons would never enjoy an equal share in, the commonwealth; nor was there
                        any reason why any one should think it enough that plebeians were taken into
                        account at the consular elections; unless it were made indispensable that
                        one consul at least should be from the commons, no one would be elected.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Or had they already forgotten, that
                        when it had been determined that military tribunes should be elected rather
                        than consuls, for this reason, that the highest honours should be opened to
                        plebeians also, no one out of the commons was elected military tribune for
                        forty-four years? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> How could they suppose,
                        that they would voluntarily confer, when there are but two places, a share
                        of the honour on the commons, who at the election of military tribunes used
                        to monopolize the eight places? and that they would suffer a way to be
                        opened to the consulship, who kept the tribuneship so long a time fenced up?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That they must obtain by a law, what
                        could not be obtained by influence at elections; and that one consulate must
                        be set apart out of the way of contest, to which the commons may have
                        access; since when left open to dispute it is sure ever to become the prize
                        of the more powerful. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor can that now be
                        alleged, which they used formerly to boast of, that there were not among the
                        plebeians qualified persons for curule magistracies. For, was the government
                        conducted with less activity and less vigour, since the tribunate of Publius
                        Licinius Calvus, who was the first plebeian elected to that office, than it
                        was conducted during those years when no one but patricians was a military
                        tribune? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nay, on the contrary, several
                        patricians had been condemned after their tribuneship, no plebeian.
                        Quaestors also, as military tribunes, began to be elected from the commons a
                            <pb n="438" xml:id="p.438"/> few years before; nor had the Roman people
                        been dissatisfied with any one of them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The consulate still remained for the attainment of the plebeians; that it
                        was the bulwark, the prop of their liberty. If they should attain that, then
                        that the Roman people would consider that kings were really expelled from
                        the city, and their liberty firmly established. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> For from that day that every thing in which the
                        patricians surpassed them, would flow in on the commons, power and honour,
                        military glory, birth, nobility, valuable at present for their own
                        enjoyment, sure to be left still more valuable to their children. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When they saw such discourses favourably
                    listened to, they publish a new proposition; that instead of two commissioners
                    for performing religious rites, ten should be appointed; so that one half should
                    be elected out of the commons, the other half from the patricians; and they
                    deferred the meeting [for the discussion] of all those propositions, till the
                    coming of that army which was besieging Velitrae. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year was completed before the legions were
                    brought back from Velitrae. Thus the question regarding the laws was suspended
                    and deferred for the new military tribunes; for the commons re-elected the same
                    two plebeian tribunes, because they were the proposers of the laws. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius, Servius Cornelius, Servius
                    Sulpicius, Spurius Servilius, Lucius Papirius, Lucius Valerius, were elected
                    military tribunes. Immediately at the commencement of the year the question
                    about the laws was pushed to the extreme of contention; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and when the tribes were called, nor did the protest of
                    their colleagues prevent the proposers of the laws, the patricians being alarmed
                    have recourse to their two last aids, to the highest authority and the highest
                    citizen. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is resolved that a dictator be
                    appointed: Marcus Furius Camillus is appointed, who nominates Lucius Aemilius
                    his master of the horse. To meet so powerful a measure of their opponents, the
                    proposers of the laws also set forth the people's cause with great determination
                    of mind, and having convened an assembly of the people, they summon the tribes
                    to vote. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the dictator took his seat,
                    accompanied by a band of patricians, full of anger and of threats, and the
                    business was going on at first with the usual contention of the plebeian
                    tribunes, some proposing the law and others protesting against it, and though
                    the protest was more powerful by right, still it was <pb n="439" xml:id="p.439"
                    /> Overpowered by the popularity of the laws themselves and of their proposers,
                    and when the first tribes pronounced, <quote> Be it as you <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> propose, </quote> then Camillus says, <quote> Since,
                        Romans, tribunitian extravagance, not authority, sways you now, and ye are
                        rendering the right of protest, acquired formerly by a secession of the
                        commons, totally unavailing by the same violent conduct by which you
                        acquired it, I, as dictator, will support the right of protest, not more for
                        the interest of the whole commonwealth than for your sake; and by my
                        authority I will defend your rights of protection, which have been
                        overturned. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Wherefore if Caius Licinius
                        and Lucius Sextius give way to the protest of their colleagues, I shall not
                        introduce a patrician magistrate into an assembly of the commons. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> If, in opposition to the right of protest, they
                        will strive to saddle laws on the state as though captive, I will not suffer
                        the tribunitian power to be destroyed by itself. </quote> When the plebeian
                    tribunes still persisted in the matter with unabated energy and contemptuously,
                    Camillus, being highly provoked, sent his lictors to disperse the commons; and
                    added threats, that if they persisted he would bind down the younger men by the
                    military oath, and would forthwith lead an army out of the city. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> He struck great terror into the people; by the
                    opposition he rather inflamed than lessened the spirits of their leaders. But
                    the matter inclining neither way, he abdicated his dictatorship, either because
                    he had been appointed with some informality, as some have stated; or because the
                    tribunes of the people proposed to the commons, and the commons passed it, that
                    if Marcus Furius did any thing as dictator, he should be fined five hundred
                    thousand <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But both the disposition of the man himself,
                    and the fact that Publius Manlius was immediately substituted as dictator for
                    him, incline me to believe, that he was deterred rather by some defect in the
                    auspices than by this unprecedented order. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    What could be the use of appointing him (Manlius) to manage a contest in which
                    Camillus had been defeated? and because the following year had the same Marcus
                    Furius dictator, who certainly would not without shame have resumed an authority
                    which but the year before had been worsted in his hands; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> at the same time, because at the time when the motion about
                    fining him is said to have been published, he could either resist this order, by
                        <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> which he saw himself degraded, or <pb
                        n="440" xml:id="p.440"/> he could not have obstructed those others on
                    account of which this was introduced, and throughout the whole series of
                    disputes regarding the tribunitian and consular authority, even down to our own
                    memory, the pre-eminence of the dictatorship was always decided. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Between the abdication of the former
                    dictatorship and the new one entered on by Manlius, an assembly of the commons
                    being held by the tribunes, as if it were an interregnum, it became evident
                    which of the laws proposed were more grateful to the commons, which to the
                    proposers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For they passed the bills regarding
                    the interest and the land, rejected the one regarding the plebeian consulate.
                    And both decisions would have been carried into effect, had not the tribunes
                    declared that they consulted the people on all the laws collectively. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Publius Manlius, dictator, then inclined the
                    advantage to the side of the people, by naming Caius Licinius from the commons,
                    who had been military tribune, as master of the horse. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The patricians, I understand, were much displeased at this
                    nomination, but the dictator used to excuse himself to the senate, alleging the
                    near relationship between him and Licinius; at the same time denying that the
                    authority of master of the horse was higher than that of consular tribune.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the elections for the appointment of
                    plebeian tribunes were declared, Licinius and Sextius so conducted themselves,
                    that by denying that they any longer desired a continuation of the honour, they
                    most powerfully stimulated the commons to effectuate that which they were
                    anxious for notwithstanding their dissimulation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> "That they were now standing the ninth year as it were in battle-array
                    against the patricians, with the greatest danger to their private interests,
                    without any benefit to the public. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the
                    measures published, and the entire strength of the tribunitian authority, had
                    grown old with them; the attack was made on their propositions, first by the
                    protest of their colleagues, then by banishing their youth to the war at
                    Velitrae; at length the dictatorial thunder was levelled against them.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That now neither colleagues, nor war, nor
                    dictator stood in their way; as being a man, who by nominating a plebeian as
                    master of the horse, has even given an omen for a plebeian consul. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> That the commons retarded themselves and their
                    interests. They could, if they liked, have the city and forum free from
                    creditors, their <pb n="441" xml:id="p.441"/> lands immediately free from unjust
                    possessors. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Which kindnesses, when would they
                    ever estimate them with sufficiently grateful feelings, if, whilst receiving the
                    measures respecting their own interests, they cut away from the authors of them
                    all hopes of distinction? That it was not becoming the modesty of the Roman
                    people to require that they themselves be eased from usury, and be put in
                    possession of the land unjustly occupied by the great, whilst they leave those
                    persons through whom they attained these advantages, become old tribunitians,
                    not only without honour, but even without the hope of honour. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Wherefore they should first determine in their minds what
                    choice they would make, then declare that choice at the tribunitian elections.
                    If they wished that the measures published by them should be passed
                    collectively, there was some reason for re-electing the same tribunes; for they
                    would carry into effect what they published. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    But if they wished that only to be entertained which may be necessary for each
                    in private, there was no occasion for the invidious continuation of honour; that
                    they would neither have the tribuneship, nor the people those matters which were
                    proposed. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In reply to such peremptory language of the
                    tribunes, when amazement at the insolence of their conduct and silence struck
                    all the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> rest of the patricians motionless,
                    Appius Claudius Crassus, the grandson of the decemvir, is said to have stepped
                    forward to refute their arguments, [urged on] more by hatred and anger than by
                    hope [of succeeding], and to have spoken nearly to this effect: <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> "Romans, to me it would be neither new nor surprising, if I
                    too on the present occasion were to hear that one charge, which has ever been
                    advanced against our family by turbulent tribunes, that even from the beginning
                    nothing in the state has been of more importance to the Claudian family than the
                    dignity of the patricians; that they have ever resisted the interests of the
                    commons. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of which charges I neither deny nor
                    object to the one, that we, since we have been admitted into the state and the
                    patricians, have strenuously done our utmost, that the dignity of those
                    families, among which ye were pleased that we should be, might be truly said
                    rather to have been increased than diminished. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    With respect to the other, in my own defence and that of my ancestors, I would
                    venture to maintain, Romans, (unless any one may consider those things, which
                    may be done for the <pb n="442" xml:id="p.442"/> general good of the state, were
                    injurious to the commons as if inhabitants of another city,) that we, neither in
                    our private nor in our official capacity, ever knowingly did any thing which was
                    intended to be detrimental to the commons; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and
                    that no act nor word of ours can be mentioned with truth contrary to your
                    interest (though some may have been contrary to your inclinations). Even though
                    I were not of the Claudian family, nor descended from patrician blood, but an
                    ordinary individual of the Roman citizens, who merely felt that I was descended
                    from free-born parents, and that I lived in a free state, could I be silent on
                    this matter: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that Lucius Sextius and Caius
                    Licinius, perpetual tribunes, forsooth, have assumed such a stock of arrogance
                    during the nine years in which they have reigned, as to refuse to allow you the
                    free exercise of your suffrage either at the elections or in enacting laws.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On a certain condition, one of them says,
                    ye shall re-elect us tribunes for the tenth time. What else is it, but saying,
                    what others sue for, we disdain so thoroughly, that without some consideration
                    we will not accept it? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But in the name of
                    goodness, what is that consideration, for which we may always have you tribunes
                    of the commons? that ye admit collectively all our measures, whether they please
                    or displease, are profitable or unprofitable. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    I beg you, Tarquinii, tribunes of the commons, suppose that I, an individual
                    citizen, should call out in reply from the middle of the assembly, With your
                    good leave be it permitted us to select out of these measures those which we
                    deem to be beneficial to us; to reject the others. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> It will not be permitted, he says. Must you enact
                    concerning the interest of money and the lands, that which tends to the interest
                    of you all; and must not this prodigy take place in the city of Rome, that of
                    seeing Lucius Sextius and this Caius Licinius consuls, a thing which you loathe
                    and abominate? Either admit all; or I propose none. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Just as if any one were to place poison and food together
                    before any one who was oppressed with famine, and order him either to abstain
                    from that which would sustain life, or to mix with it that which would cause
                    death. Wherefore, if this state were free, would they not all in full assembly
                    have replied to you, Begone hence with your tribuneships and your propositions?
                    What? if you will not propose that which it is the interest of the people to
                    accept, will there be no one who <pb n="443" xml:id="p.443"/> will propose it?
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If any patrician, if (what they desire to
                    be still more invidious) any Claudius should say, Either accept all, or I
                    propose nothing; which of you, Romans, would bear it? <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Will ye never look at facts rather than persons? but always
                    listen with partial ears to every thing which that officer will say, and with
                    prejudiced ears to what may be said by any of us? <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> But, by Jove, their language is by no means becoming
                    members of a republic. What! what sort is the measure, which they are indignant
                    at its having been rejected by you? very like their language, Romans. I ask, he
                    says, that it may not be lawful for you to elect, as consuls, such persons as ye
                    may wish. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Does he require any thing else, who
                    orders that one consul at least be elected from the commons; nor does he grant
                    you the power of electing two patricians? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> If
                    there were wars at the present day, such as the Etrurian for instance, when
                    Porsenna took the Janiculum, such as the Gallic war lately, when, except the
                    Capitol and citadel, all these places were in possession of the enemy; and
                    should Lucius Sextius stand candidate for the consulate with Marcus Furius or
                    any other of the patricians: could ye endure that Sextius should be consul
                    without any risk; that Camillus should run the risk of a repulse? <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> Is this allowing a community of honours, that it
                    should be lawful that two plebeians, and not lawful that two patricians, be made
                    consuls, and that it should be necessary that one be elected from among the
                    commons, and lawful to pass by both of the patricians? what fellowship, what
                    confederacy is that? Is it not sufficient, if you come in for a share of that in
                    which you had no share hitherto, unless whilst suing for a part you seize on the
                    whole? <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> I fear, he says, lest, if it be lawful
                    that two patricians are to be elected, ye will elect no plebeian. What else is
                    this but saying, Because ye will not of your own choice elect unworthy persons,
                    I will impose on you the necessity of electing persons whom you do not wish?
                        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> What follows, but that if one plebeian
                    stand candidate with two patricians, he owes no obligation to the people, and
                    may say that he was appointed by the law, not by suffrages? </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> How they may extort, not how they may sue for honours, is what they
                        seek: and they are anxious to attain the highest honour, so that they may
                        not owe the obligations incurred even for the lowest; and they prefer to sue
                        for honours <pb n="444" xml:id="p.444"/> rather through favourable
                        conjunctures than by merit. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Is there any
                        one who can feel it an affront to have himself inspected and estimated; who
                        thinks it reasonable that to himself alone, amidst struggling competitors,
                        honours should be certain? who would withdraw himself from your judgment?
                        who would make your suffrages necessary instead of voluntary; servile
                        instead of free? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I omit mention of
                        Licinius and Sextius, whose years of perpetuated power ye number, as that of
                        the kings in the Capitol; who is there this day in the state so mean, to
                        whom the road to the consulate is not rendered easier through the advantages
                        of that law, than to us and to our children? inasmuch as you will sometimes
                        not be able to elect us even though you may wish it; those persons you must
                        elect, even though you were unwilling. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of
                        the insult offered to merit enough has been said (for merit appertains to
                        human beings); what shall I say respecting religion and the auspices, which
                        is contempt and injustice relating exclusively to the immortal gods? Who is
                        there who does not know that this city was built by auspices, that all
                        things are conducted by auspices during war and peace, at home and abroad?
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In whom therefore are the auspices
                        vested according to the usage of our forefathers? In the patricians, no
                        doubt; for no plebeian magistrate is ever elected by auspices. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> So peculiar to us are the auspices, that not only
                        do the people elect in no other manner, save by auspices, the patrician
                        magistrates whom they do elect, but even we ourselves, without the suffrages
                        of the people, appoint the interrex by auspices, and in our private station
                        we hold those auspices, which they do not hold even in office. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> What else then does he do, than abolish auspices
                        out of the state, who, by creating plebeian consuls, takes them away from
                        the patricians who alone can hold them? They may now mock at religion. For
                        what else is it, if the chickens do not feed? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> if they come out too slowly from the coop? if a bird
                        chaunt an unfavourable note? These are trifling: but by not despising these
                        trifling matters, our ancestors have raised this state to the highest
                        eminence. Now, as if we had no need of the favour of the gods, we violate
                        all religious ceremonies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Wherefore let
                        pontiffs, augurs, kings of the sacrifices be appointed at random. Let us
                        place the tiara of Jupiter's flamen on any person, provided he be a man. Let
                        us hand over the ancilia, the shrines, the gods, and the charge of the
                        worship of the gods, to those <pb n="445" xml:id="p.445"/> to whom it is
                        impious to commit them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Let not la s be
                        enacted, nor magistrates elected under auspices. Let not the senate give
                        their approbation, either to the assemblies of the centuries or of the
                        Curiae. Let Sextius and Licinius, like Romulus and Tatius, reign in the city
                        of Rome, because they give away as donations other persons' money and lands.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So great is the charm of plundering
                        the possessions of other persons: nor does it occur to you that by the one
                        law vast wilds are produced throughout the lands by expelling the
                        proprietors from their territories; by the other credit is destroyed, along
                        with which all human society ceases to exist. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> For every reason, I consider that those propositions
                        ought to be rejected by you. Whatever ye may do, I pray the gods to render
                        it successful. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The speech of Appius merely had this effect,
                    that the time for passing the propositions was deferred. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The same tribunes, Sextius and Licinius, being re-elected
                    for the tenth time, succeeded in passing a law, that of the decemvirs for
                    religious matters, one half should be elected from the commons. Five patricians
                    were elected, and five out of the plebeians; and by that step the way appeared
                    opened to the consulship. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The commons, content
                    with this victory, yielded to the patricians, that, all mention of consuls being
                    omitted for the present, military tribunes should be elected. Those elected
                    were, Aulus and Marcus Cornelius a second time, Marcus Geganius, Publius
                    Manlius, Lucius Veturius, and Publius Valerius a six h time. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> When, except the siege of Velitrae, a matter rather of a
                    slow than dubious result, there was no disquiet from foreign concerns among the
                    Romans; the sudden rumour of a Gallic war being brought, influenced the state to
                    appoint Marcus Furius dictator for the fifth time. He named Titus Quinctius
                    Pennus master of the horse. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Claudius asserts
                    that a battle was fought that year with the Gauls, on the banks of the Anio; and
                    that then the famous battle was fought on the bridge, in which Titus Manlius,
                    engaging with a Gaul by whom he had been challenged, slew him in the sight of
                    the two armies and despoiled him of his chain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But I am induced by the authority of several writers to believe that those
                    things happened not less than ten years later; but that in this year a pitched
                    battle was fought with the Gauls by the dictator, Marcus Furius, in the
                    territory of Alba. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The victory was either <pb
                        n="446" xml:id="p.446"/> doubtful nor difficult to the Romans, though from
                    the recollection of the former defeat the Gauls had diffused great terror. Many
                    thousands of the barbarians were slain in the field, and great numbers in the
                    storming of the camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The rest dispersing,
                    making chiefly for Apulia, saved themselves from the enemy, both by continuing
                    their flight to a great distance, as also because panic and terror had scattered
                    them very widely. A triumph was decreed to the dictator with the concurrence of
                    the senate and commons. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scarcely had he as yet
                    finished the war, when a more violent disturbance awaited him at home; and by
                    great struggles the dictator and the senate were overpowered, so that the
                    measures of the tribunes were admitted; and the elections of the consuls were
                    held in spite of the resistance of the nobility, at which Lucius Sextius was
                    made consul, the first of plebeian rank. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And
                    not even was that an end of the contests. Because the patricians refused to give
                    their approbation, the affair came very near a secession of the people, and
                    other terrible threats of civil contests: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    when, however, the dissensions were accommodated on certain terms through the
                    interference of the dictator; and concessions to the commons were made by the
                    nobility regarding the plebeian consul; by the commons to the nobility, with
                    respect to one praetor to be elected out of the patricians, to administer
                    justice in the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The different orders
                    being at length restored to concord after their long-continued animosity, when
                    the senate were of opinion that for the sake of the immortal gods they would
                    readily do a thing deserving, and that justly, if ever on any occasion before,
                    that the most magnificent games should be performed, and that one day should be
                    added to the three; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> the plebeian aediles
                    refusing the office, the young patricians cried out with one accord, that they,
                    for the purpose of paying honour to the immortal gods, would readily undertake
                    the task, so that they were appointed aediles. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> And when thanks were returned to them by all, a decree of the senate passed,
                    that the dictator should ask of the people two persons as aediles from among the
                    patricians; that the senate should give their approbation to all the elections
                    of that year. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
