<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.21/tei-epidoc.rng"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.21/tei-epidoc.rng"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eclogues</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <author n="Verg.">P. Vergilius Maro</author>
            <editor role="editor" n="Greenough">J. B. Greenough</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
         	<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
         	<respStmt>
         		<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
         		<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
         		<name>William Merrill</name>
         		<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
         		<name>David Smith</name>
         	</respStmt>
            <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>about 60Kb</extent>
      	<publicationStmt>
      		<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
      		<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
      		<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      	</publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Vergil</author>
                  <title>Eclogues</title>
                  <editor role="editor">J. B. Greenough</editor>
                  <imprint>
	                    <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
	                    <publisher>Ginn &amp; Co.</publisher>
                     <date>1895</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
      	<refsDecl n="CTS">
      		<cRefPattern n="line" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']//tei:l[@n='$2'])">
      			<p>This pointer pattern extracts poem and line</p>
      		</cRefPattern>
      		<cRefPattern n="poem" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
      			<p>This pointer pattern extracts poem</p>
      		</cRefPattern>
      	</refsDecl>
         <refsDecl n="TEI">
            <refState unit="poem"/>
            <refState unit="line"/>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>

      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2014-11-06" who="Thibault Clerice">Moving to Epidoc with new URN</change>
      	<change when="2010-07-01" who="student">fixed place tags - zr</change>
      	<change when="2009-12-09" who="rsingh04">moved more xml files around based on copyright status</change>
      	<change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
      	<change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
      	<change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
      	<change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
      	<change when="2003-02-05" who="amahoney">don't EVER put angle brackets in comments: it fouls up the whole file</change>
      	<change when="2003-02-04" who="gcrane">systematic error -- we have lots of places where closing L tags were missing a bracket</change>
      	<change when="2000-12-04" who="amahoney">fix misspelling of title</change>
      	<change when="2000-03-06" who="amahoney">remove headers so poem numbers get into short toc</change>
      	<change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
      	<change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Changed line tags to handle verse translation.</change>
      	<change when="1999-08-04" who="textgod">Changed header.</change>
      	<change when="1997-09-24" who="textgod">Changed names and redid headers.</change>
      	<change when="1997-03-01" who="KW">converted mdashes, quotes; added speaker, LG, div2 tags, designated capital letters at line beginnings to keep with an *.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0690.phi001.perseus-eng2">
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="1">
            <head>MELIBOEUS TITYRUS</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MELIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="1">You, Tityrus, 'neath a broad beech-canopy</l>
               <l n="2">reclining, on the slender oat rehearse</l>
               <l n="3">your silvan ditties: I from my sweet fields,</l>
               <l n="4">and home's familiar bounds, even now depart.</l>
               <l n="5">Exiled from home am I; while, Tityrus, you</l>
               <l n="6">sit careless in the shade, and, at your call,</l>
               <l n="7">“Fair Amaryllis” bid the woods resound.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>TITYRUS</speaker>
               <l n="8">O Meliboeus, 'twas a god vouchsafed</l>
               <l n="9">this ease to us, for him a god will I</l>
               <l n="10">deem ever, and from my folds a tender lamb</l>
               <l n="11">oft with its life-blood shall his altar stain.</l>
               <l n="12">His gift it is that, as your eyes may see,</l>
               <l n="13">my kine may roam at large, and I myself</l>
               <l n="14">play on my shepherd's pipe what songs I will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MELIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="15">I grudge you not the boon, but marvel more,</l>
               <l n="16">such wide confusion fills the country-side.</l>
               <l n="17">See, sick at heart I drive my she-goats on,</l>
               <l n="18">and this one, O my Tityrus, scarce can lead:</l>
               <l n="19">for 'mid the hazel-thicket here but now</l>
               <l n="20">she dropped her new-yeaned twins on the bare flint,</l>
               <l n="21">hope of the flock—an ill, I mind me well,</l>
               <l n="22">which many a time, but for my blinded sense,</l>
               <l n="23">the thunder-stricken oak foretold, oft too</l>
               <l n="24">from hollow trunk the raven's ominous cry.</l>
               <l n="25">But who this god of yours? Come, Tityrus, tell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>TITYRUS</speaker>
               <l n="26">The city, Meliboeus, they call <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>,</l>
               <l n="27">I, simpleton, deemed like this town of ours,</l>
               <l n="28">whereto we shepherds oft are wont to drive</l>
               <l n="29">the younglings of the flock: so too I knew</l>
               <l n="30">whelps to resemble dogs, and kids their dams,</l>
               <l n="31">comparing small with great; but this as far</l>
               <l n="32">above all other cities rears her head</l>
               <l n="33">as cypress above pliant osier towers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MELIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="34">And what so potent cause took you to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>TITYRUS</speaker>
               <l n="35">Freedom, which, though belated, cast at length</l>
               <l n="36">her eyes upon the sluggard, when my beard</l>
               <l n="37">'gan whiter fall beneath the barber's blade—</l>
               <l n="38">cast eyes, I say, and, though long tarrying, came,</l>
               <l n="39">now when, from Galatea's yoke released,</l>
               <l n="40">I serve but Amaryllis: for I will own,</l>
               <l n="41">while Galatea reigned over me, I had</l>
               <l n="42">no hope of freedom, and no thought to save.</l>
               <l n="43">Though many a victim from my folds went forth,</l>
               <l n="44">or rich cheese pressed for the unthankful town,</l>
               <l n="45">never with laden hands returned I home.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MELIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="46">I used to wonder, Amaryllis, why</l>
               <l n="47">you cried to heaven so sadly, and for whom</l>
               <l n="48">you left the apples hanging on the trees;</l>
               <l n="49">'twas Tityrus was away. Why, Tityrus,</l>
               <l n="50">the very pines, the very water-springs,</l>
               <l n="51">the very vineyards, cried aloud for you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>TITYRUS</speaker>
               <l n="52">What could I do? how else from bonds be freed,</l>
               <l n="53">or otherwhere find gods so nigh to aid?</l>
               <l n="54">There, Meliboeus, I saw that youth to whom</l>
               <l n="55">yearly for twice six days my altars smoke.</l>
               <l n="56">There instant answer gave he to my suit,</l>
               <l n="57">“Feed, as before, your kine, boys, rear your bulls.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MELIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="58">So in old age, you happy man, your fields</l>
               <l n="59">will still be yours, and ample for your need!</l>
               <l n="60">Though, with bare stones o'erspread, the pastures all</l>
               <l n="61">be choked with rushy mire, your ewes with young</l>
               <l n="62">by no strange fodder will be tried, nor hurt</l>
               <l n="63">through taint contagious of a neighbouring flock.</l>
               <l n="64">Happy old man, who 'mid familiar streams</l>
               <l n="65">and hallowed springs, will court the cooling shade!</l>
               <l n="66">Here, as of old, your neighbour's bordering hedge,</l>
               <l n="67">that feasts with willow-flower the Hybla bees,</l>
               <l n="68">shall oft with gentle murmur lull to sleep,</l>
               <l n="69">while the leaf-dresser beneath some tall rock</l>
               <l n="70">uplifts his song, nor cease their cooings hoarse</l>
               <l n="71">the wood-pigeons that are your heart's delight,</l>
               <l n="72">nor doves their moaning in the elm-tree top.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>TITYRUS</speaker>
               <l n="73">Sooner shall light stags, therefore, feed in air,</l>
               <l n="74">the seas their fish leave naked on the strand,</l>
               <l n="75">germans and Parthians shift their natural bounds,</l>
               <l n="76">and these the <placeName key="tgn,1084764">Arar</placeName>, those the <placeName key="tgn,1130850">Tigris</placeName> drink,</l>
               <l n="77">than from my heart his face and memory fade.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MELIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="78">But we far hence, to burning <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName> some,</l>
               <l n="79">some to the Scythian steppes, or thy swift flood,</l>
               <l n="80">cretan Oaxes, now must wend our way,</l>
               <l n="81">or <placeName key="tgn,7008653">Britain</placeName>, from the whole world sundered far.</l>
               <l n="82">Ah! shall I ever in aftertime behold</l>
               <l n="83">my native bounds—see many a harvest hence</l>
               <l n="84">with ravished eyes the lowly turf-roofed cot</l>
               <l n="85">where I was king? These fallows, trimmed so fair,</l>
               <l n="86">some brutal soldier will possess these fields</l>
               <l n="87">an alien master. Ah! to what a pass</l>
               <l n="88">has civil discord brought our hapless folk!</l>
               <l n="89">For such as these, then, were our furrows sown!</l>
               <l n="90">Now, Meliboeus, graft your pears, now set</l>
               <l n="91">your vines in order! Go, once happy flock,</l>
               <l n="92">my she-goats, go. Never again shall I,</l>
               <l n="93">stretched in green cave, behold you from afar</l>
               <l n="94">hang from the bushy rock; my songs are sung;</l>
               <l n="95">never again will you, with me to tend,</l>
               <l n="96">on clover-flower, or bitter willows, browse.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>TITYRUS</speaker>
               <l n="97">Yet here, this night, you might repose with me,</l>
               <l n="98">on green leaves pillowed: apples ripe have I,</l>
               <l n="99">soft chestnuts, and of curdled milk enow.</l>
               <l n="100">And, see, the farm-roof chimneys smoke afar,</l>
               <l n="101">and from the hills the shadows lengthening fall!</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="2">
            <head>ALEXIS</head>
            <l n="1">the shepherd Corydon with love was fired</l>
            <l n="2">for fair Alexis, his own master's joy:</l>
            <l n="3">no room for hope had he, yet, none the less,</l>
            <l n="4">the thick-leaved shadowy-soaring beech-tree grove</l>
            <l n="5">still would he haunt, and there alone, as thus,</l>
            <l n="6">to woods and hills pour forth his artless strains.</l>
            <l n="7">“Cruel Alexis, heed you naught my songs?</l>
            <l n="8">Have you no pity? you'll drive me to my death.</l>
            <l n="9">Now even the cattle court the cooling shade</l>
            <l n="10">and the green lizard hides him in the thorn:</l>
            <l n="11">now for tired mowers, with the fierce heat spent,</l>
            <l n="12">pounds Thestilis her mess of savoury herbs,</l>
            <l n="13">wild thyme and garlic. I, with none beside,</l>
            <l n="14">save hoarse cicalas shrilling through the brake,</l>
            <l n="15">still track your footprints 'neath the broiling sun.</l>
            <l n="16">Better have borne the petulant proud disdain</l>
            <l n="17">of Amaryllis, or Menalcas wooed,</l>
            <l n="18">albeit he was so dark, and you so fair!</l>
            <l n="19">Trust not too much to colour, beauteous boy;</l>
            <l n="20">white privets fall, dark hyacinths are culled.</l>
            <l n="21">You scorn me, Alexis, who or what I am</l>
            <l n="22">care not to ask—how rich in flocks, or how</l>
            <l n="23">in snow-white milk abounding: yet for me</l>
            <l n="24">roam on Sicilian hills a thousand lambs;</l>
            <l n="25">summer or winter, still my milk-pails brim.</l>
            <l n="26">I sing as erst Amphion of Circe sang,</l>
            <l n="27">what time he went to call his cattle home</l>
            <l n="28">on Attic Aracynthus. Nor am I</l>
            <l n="29">so ill to look on: lately on the beach</l>
            <l n="30">I saw myself, when winds had stilled the sea,</l>
            <l n="31">and, if that mirror lie not, would not fear</l>
            <l n="32">daphnis to challenge, though yourself were judge.</l>
            <l n="33">Ah! were you but content with me to dwell.</l>
            <l n="34">Some lowly cot in the rough fields our home,</l>
            <l n="35">shoot down the stags, or with green osier-wand</l>
            <l n="36">round up the straggling flock! There you with me</l>
            <l n="37">in silvan strains will learn to rival Pan.</l>
            <l n="38">Pan first with wax taught reed with reed to join;</l>
            <l n="39">for sheep alike and shepherd Pan hath care.</l>
            <l n="40">Nor with the reed's edge fear you to make rough</l>
            <l n="41">your dainty lip; such arts as these to learn</l>
            <l n="42">what did Amyntas do?—what did he not?</l>
            <l n="43">A pipe have I, of hemlock-stalks compact</l>
            <l n="44">in lessening lengths, Damoetas' dying-gift:</l>
            <l n="45">‘Mine once,’ quoth he, ‘now yours, as heir to own.’</l>
            <l n="46">Foolish Amyntas heard and envied me.</l>
            <l n="47">Ay, and two fawns, I risked my neck to find</l>
            <l n="48">in a steep glen, with coats white-dappled still,</l>
            <l n="49">from a sheep's udders suckled twice a day—</l>
            <l n="50">these still I keep for you; which Thestilis</l>
            <l n="51">implores me oft to let her lead away;</l>
            <l n="52">and she shall have them, since my gifts you spurn.</l>
            <l n="53">Come hither, beauteous boy; for you the Nymphs</l>
            <l n="54">bring baskets, see, with lilies brimmed; for you,</l>
            <l n="55">plucking pale violets and poppy-heads,</l>
            <l n="56">now the fair Naiad, of narcissus flower</l>
            <l n="57">and fragrant fennel, doth one posy twine—</l>
            <l n="58">with cassia then, and other scented herbs,</l>
            <l n="59">blends them, and sets the tender hyacinth off</l>
            <l n="60">with yellow marigold. I too will pick</l>
            <l n="61">quinces all silvered-o'er with hoary down,</l>
            <l n="62">chestnuts, which Amaryllis wont to love,</l>
            <l n="63">and waxen plums withal: this fruit no less</l>
            <l n="64">shall have its meed of honour; and I will pluck</l>
            <l n="65">you too, ye laurels, and you, ye myrtles, near,</l>
            <l n="66">for so your sweets ye mingle. Corydon,</l>
            <l n="67">you are a boor, nor heeds a whit your gifts</l>
            <l n="68">alexis; no, nor would Iollas yield,</l>
            <l n="69">should gifts decide the day. Alack! alack!</l>
            <l n="70">What misery have I brought upon my head!—</l>
            <l n="71">loosed on the flowers Siroces to my bane,</l>
            <l n="72">and the wild boar upon my crystal springs!</l>
            <l n="73">Whom do you fly, infatuate? gods ere now,</l>
            <l n="74">and Dardan Paris, have made the woods their home.</l>
            <l n="75">Let Pallas keep the towers her hand hath built,</l>
            <l n="76">us before all things let the woods delight.</l>
            <l n="77">The grim-eyed lioness pursues the wolf,</l>
            <l n="78">the wolf the she-goat, the she-goat herself</l>
            <l n="79">in wanton sport the flowering cytisus,</l>
            <l n="80">and Corydon Alexis, each led on</l>
            <l n="81">by their own longing. See, the ox comes home</l>
            <l n="82">with plough up-tilted, and the shadows grow</l>
            <l n="83">to twice their length with the departing sun,</l>
            <l n="84">yet me love burns, for who can limit love?</l>
            <l n="85">Ah! Corydon, Corydon, what hath crazed your wit?</l>
            <l n="86">Your vine half-pruned hangs on the leafy elm;</l>
            <l n="87">why haste you not to weave what need requires</l>
            <l n="88">of pliant rush or osier? Scorned by this,</l>
            <l n="89">elsewhere some new Alexis you will find.”</l>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="3">
            <head>MENALCAS   DAMOETAS   PALAEMON</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="1">Who owns the flock, Damoetas? Meliboeus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="2">Nay, they are Aegon's sheep, of late by him</l>
               <l n="3">committed to my care.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="4">O every way</l>
               <l n="5">unhappy sheep, unhappy flock! while he</l>
               <l n="6">still courts Neaera, fearing lest her choice</l>
               <l n="7">should fall on me, this hireling shepherd here</l>
               <l n="8">wrings hourly twice their udders, from the flock</l>
               <l n="9">filching the life-juice, from the lambs their milk.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="10">Hold! not so ready with your jeers at men!</l>
               <l n="11">We know who once, and in what shrine with you—</l>
               <l n="12">the he-goats looked aside—the light nymphs laughed—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="13">Ay, then, I warrant, when they saw me slash</l>
               <l n="14">micon's young vines and trees with spiteful hook.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="15">Or here by these old beeches, when you broke</l>
               <l n="16">the bow and arrows of Damon; for you chafed</l>
               <l n="17">when first you saw them given to the boy,</l>
               <l n="18">cross-grained Menalcas, ay, and had you not</l>
               <l n="19">done him some mischief, would have chafed to death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="20">With thieves so daring, what can masters do?</l>
               <l n="21">Did I not see you, rogue, in ambush lie</l>
               <l n="22">for Damon's goat, while loud Lycisca barked?</l>
               <l n="23">And when I cried, “Where is he off to now?</l>
               <l n="24">Gather your flock together, Tityrus,”</l>
               <l n="25">you hid behind the sedges.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="26">Well, was he</l>
               <l n="27">whom I had conquered still to keep the goat.</l>
               <l n="28">Which in the piping-match my pipe had won!</l>
               <l n="29">You may not know it, but the goat was mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="30">You out-pipe him? when had you ever pipe</l>
               <l n="31">wax-welded? in the cross-ways used you not</l>
               <l n="32">on grating straw some miserable tune</l>
               <l n="33">to mangle?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="34">Well, then, shall we try our skill</l>
               <l n="35">each against each in turn? Lest you be loth,</l>
               <l n="36">I pledge this heifer; every day she comes</l>
               <l n="37">twice to the milking-pail, and feeds withal</l>
               <l n="38">two young ones at her udder: say you now</l>
               <l n="39">what you will stake upon the match with me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="40">Naught from the flock I'll venture, for at home</l>
               <l n="41">I have a father and a step-dame harsh,</l>
               <l n="42">and twice a day both reckon up the flock,</l>
               <l n="43">and one withal the kids. But I will stake,</l>
               <l n="44">seeing you are so mad, what you yourself</l>
               <l n="45">will own more priceless far—two beechen cups</l>
               <l n="46">by the divine art of Alcimedon</l>
               <l n="47">wrought and embossed, whereon a limber vine,</l>
               <l n="48">wreathed round them by the graver's facile tool,</l>
               <l n="49">twines over clustering ivy-berries pale.</l>
               <l n="50">Two figures, one Conon, in the midst he set,</l>
               <l n="51">and one—how call you him, who with his wand</l>
               <l n="52">marked out for all men the whole round of heaven,</l>
               <l n="53">that they who reap, or stoop behind the plough,</l>
               <l n="54">might know their several seasons? Nor as yet</l>
               <l n="55">have I set lip to them, but lay them by.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="56">For me too wrought the same Alcimedon</l>
               <l n="57">a pair of cups, and round the handles wreathed</l>
               <l n="58">pliant acanthus, Orpheus in the midst,</l>
               <l n="59">the forests following in his wake; nor yet</l>
               <l n="60">have I set lip to them, but lay them by.</l>
               <l n="61">Matched with a heifer, who would prate of cups?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="62">You shall not balk me now; where'er you bid,</l>
               <l n="63">I shall be with you; only let us have</l>
               <l n="64">for auditor—or see, to serve our turn,</l>
               <l n="65">yonder Palaemon comes! In singing-bouts</l>
               <l n="66">i'll see you play the challenger no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="67">Out then with what you have; I shall not shrink,</l>
               <l n="68">nor budge for any man: only do you,</l>
               <l n="69">neighbour Palaemon, with your whole heart's skill—</l>
               <l n="70">for it is no slight matter—play your part.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PALAEMON</speaker>
               <l n="71">Say on then, since on the greensward we sit,</l>
               <l n="72">and now is burgeoning both field and tree;</l>
               <l n="73">now is the forest green, and now the year</l>
               <l n="74">at fairest. Do you first, Damoetas, sing,</l>
               <l n="75">then you, Menalcas, in alternate strain:</l>
               <l n="76">alternate strains are to the Muses dear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="77">“From Jove the Muse began; Jove filleth all,</l>
               <l n="78">makes the earth fruitful, for my songs hath care.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="79">“Me Phoebus loves; for Phoebus his own gifts,</l>
               <l n="80">bays and sweet-blushing hyacinths, I keep.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="81">“Gay Galatea throws an apple at me,</l>
               <l n="82">then hies to the willows, hoping to be seen.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="83">“My dear Amyntas comes unasked to me;</l>
               <l n="84">not Delia to my dogs is better known.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="85">“Gifts for my love I've found; mine eyes have marked</l>
               <l n="86">where the wood-pigeons build their airy nests.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="87">“Ten golden apples have I sent my boy,</l>
               <l n="88">all that I could, to-morrow as many more.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="89">“What words to me, and uttered O how oft,</l>
               <l n="90">hath Galatea spoke! waft some of them,</l>
               <l n="91">ye winds, I pray you, for the gods to hear.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="92">“It profiteth me naught, Amyntas mine,</l>
               <l n="93">that in your very heart you spurn me not,</l>
               <l n="94">if, while you hunt the boar, I guard the nets.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="95">“Prithee, Iollas, for my birthday guest</l>
               <l n="96">send me your Phyllis; when for the young crops</l>
               <l n="97">I slay my heifer, you yourself shall come.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="98">“I am all hers; she wept to see me go,</l>
               <l n="99">and, lingering on the word, ‘farewell’ she said,</l>
               <l n="100">‘My beautiful Iollas, fare you well.’”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="101">“Fell as the wolf is to the folded flock,</l>
               <l n="102">rain to ripe corn, Sirocco to the trees,</l>
               <l n="103">the wrath of Amaryllis is to me.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="104">“As moisture to the corn, to ewes with young</l>
               <l n="105">lithe willow, as arbute to the yeanling kids,</l>
               <l n="106">so sweet Amyntas, and none else, to me.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="107">“My Muse, although she be but country-bred,</l>
               <l n="108">is loved by Pollio: O Pierian Maids,</l>
               <l n="109">pray you, a heifer for your reader feed!”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="110">“Pollio himself too doth new verses make:</l>
               <l n="111">feed ye a bull now ripe to butt with horn,</l>
               <l n="112">and scatter with his hooves the flying sand.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="113">“Who loves thee, Pollio, may he thither come</l>
               <l n="114">where thee he joys beholding; ay, for him</l>
               <l n="115">let honey flow, the thorn-bush spices bear.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="116">“Who hates not Bavius, let him also love</l>
               <l n="117">thy songs, O Maevius, ay, and therewithal</l>
               <l n="118">yoke foxes to his car, and he-goats milk.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="119">“You, picking flowers and strawberries that grow</l>
               <l n="120">so near the ground, fly hence, boys, get you gone!</l>
               <l n="121">There's a cold adder lurking in the grass.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="122">“Forbear, my sheep, to tread too near the brink;</l>
               <l n="123">yon bank is ill to trust to; even now</l>
               <l n="124">the ram himself, see, dries his dripping fleece!”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="125">“Back with the she-goats, Tityrus, grazing there</l>
               <l n="126">so near the river! I, when time shall serve,</l>
               <l n="127">will take them all, and wash them in the pool.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="128">“Boys, get your sheep together; if the heat,</l>
               <l n="129">as late it did, forestall us with the milk,</l>
               <l n="130">vainly the dried-up udders shall we wring.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="131">“How lean my bull amid the fattening vetch!</l>
               <l n="132">Alack! alack! for herdsman and for herd!</l>
               <l n="133">It is the self-same love that wastes us both.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="134">“These truly—nor is even love the cause—</l>
               <l n="135">scarce have the flesh to keep their bones together</l>
               <l n="136">some evil eye my lambkins hath bewitched.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMOETAS</speaker>
               <l n="137">“Say in what clime—and you shall be withal</l>
               <l n="138">my great Apollo—the whole breadth of heaven</l>
               <l n="139">opens no wider than three ells to view.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="140">“Say in what country grow such flowers as bear</l>
               <l n="141">the names of kings upon their petals writ,</l>
               <l n="142">and you shall have fair Phyllis for your own.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PALAEMON</speaker>
               <l n="143">Not mine betwixt such rivals to decide:</l>
               <l n="144">you well deserve the heifer, so does he,</l>
               <l n="145">with all who either fear the sweets of love,</l>
               <l n="146">or taste its bitterness. Now, boys, shut off</l>
               <l n="147">the sluices, for the fields have drunk their fill.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="4">
            <head>POLLIO</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l n="1">muses of <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, essay we now</l>
               <l n="2">a somewhat loftier task! Not all men love</l>
               <l n="3">coppice or lowly tamarisk: sing we woods,</l>
               <l n="4">woods worthy of a Consul let them be.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="5">Now the last age by Cumae's Sibyl sung</l>
                  <l n="6">has come and gone, and the majestic roll</l>
                  <l n="7">of circling centuries begins anew:</l>
                  <l n="8">justice returns, returns old Saturn's reign,</l>
                  <l n="9">with a new breed of men sent down from heaven.</l>
                  <l n="10">Only do thou, at the boy's birth in whom</l>
                  <l n="11">the iron shall cease, the golden race arise,</l>
                  <l n="12">befriend him, chaste Lucina; 'tis thine own</l>
                  <l n="13">apollo reigns. And in thy consulate,</l>
                  <l n="14">this glorious age, O Pollio, shall begin,</l>
                  <l n="15">and the months enter on their mighty march.</l>
                  <l n="16">Under thy guidance, whatso tracks remain</l>
                  <l n="17">of our old wickedness, once done away,</l>
                  <l n="18">shall free the earth from never-ceasing fear.</l>
                  <l n="19">He shall receive the life of gods, and see</l>
                  <l n="20">heroes with gods commingling, and himself</l>
                  <l n="21">be seen of them, and with his father's worth</l>
                  <l n="22">reign o'er a world at peace. For thee, O boy,</l>
                  <l n="23">first shall the earth, untilled, pour freely forth</l>
                  <l n="24">her childish gifts, the gadding ivy-spray</l>
                  <l n="25">with foxglove and Egyptian bean-flower mixed,</l>
                  <l n="26">and laughing-eyed acanthus. Of themselves,</l>
                  <l n="27">untended, will the she-goats then bring home</l>
                  <l n="28">their udders swollen with milk, while flocks afield</l>
                  <l n="29">shall of the monstrous lion have no fear.</l>
                  <l n="30">Thy very cradle shall pour forth for thee</l>
                  <l n="31">caressing flowers. The serpent too shall die,</l>
                  <l n="32">die shall the treacherous poison-plant, and far</l>
                  <l n="33">and wide Assyrian spices spring. But soon</l>
                  <l n="34">as thou hast skill to read of heroes' fame,</l>
                  <l n="35">and of thy father's deeds, and inly learn</l>
                  <l n="36">what virtue is, the plain by slow degrees</l>
                  <l n="37">with waving corn-crops shall to golden grow,</l>
                  <l n="38">from the wild briar shall hang the blushing grape,</l>
                  <l n="39">and stubborn oaks sweat honey-dew. Nathless</l>
                  <l n="40">yet shall there lurk within of ancient wrong</l>
                  <l n="41">some traces, bidding tempt the deep with ships,</l>
                  <l n="42">gird towns with walls, with furrows cleave the earth.</l>
                  <l n="43">Therewith a second Tiphys shall there be,</l>
                  <l n="44">her hero-freight a second Argo bear;</l>
                  <l n="45">new wars too shall arise, and once again</l>
                  <l n="46">some great Achilles to some <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> be sent.</l>
                  <l n="47">Then, when the mellowing years have made thee man,</l>
                  <l n="48">no more shall mariner sail, nor pine-tree bark</l>
                  <l n="49">ply traffic on the sea, but every land</l>
                  <l n="50">shall all things bear alike: the glebe no more</l>
                  <l n="51">shall feel the harrow's grip, nor vine the hook;</l>
                  <l n="52">the sturdy ploughman shall loose yoke from steer,</l>
                  <l n="53">nor wool with varying colours learn to lie;</l>
                  <l n="54">but in the meadows shall the ram himself,</l>
                  <l n="55">now with soft flush of purple, now with tint</l>
                  <l n="56">of yellow saffron, teach his fleece to shine.</l>
                  <l n="57">While clothed in natural scarlet graze the lambs.</l>
                  <l n="58">“Such still, such ages weave ye, as ye run,”</l>
                  <l n="59">sang to their spindles the consenting Fates</l>
                  <l n="60">by Destiny's unalterable decree.</l>
                  <l n="61">Assume thy greatness, for the time draws nigh,</l>
                  <l n="62">dear child of gods, great progeny of Jove!</l>
                  <l n="63">See how it totters—the world's orbed might,</l>
                  <l n="64">earth, and wide ocean, and the vault profound,</l>
                  <l n="65">all, see, enraptured of the coming time!</l>
                  <l n="66">Ah! might such length of days to me be given,</l>
                  <l n="67">and breath suffice me to rehearse thy deeds,</l>
                  <l n="68">nor Thracian Orpheus should out-sing me then,</l>
                  <l n="69">nor Linus, though his mother this, and that</l>
                  <l n="70">his sire should aid—Orpheus Calliope,</l>
                  <l n="71">and Linus fair Apollo. Nay, though Pan,</l>
                  <l n="72">with Arcady for judge, my claim contest,</l>
                  <l n="73">with Arcady for judge great Pan himself</l>
                  <l n="74">should own him foiled, and from the field retire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l n="75">Begin to greet thy mother with a smile,</l>
                  <l n="76">o baby-boy! ten months of weariness</l>
                  <l n="77">for thee she bore: O baby-boy, begin!</l>
                  <l n="78">For him, on whom his parents have not smiled,</l>
                  <l n="79">gods deem not worthy of their board or bed.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="5">
            <head>MENALCAS   MOPSUS</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="1">Why, Mopsus, being both together met,</l>
               <l n="2">you skilled to breathe upon the slender reeds,</l>
               <l n="3">I to sing ditties, do we not sit down</l>
               <l n="4">here where the elm-trees and the hazels blend?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOPSUS</speaker>
               <l n="5">You are the elder, 'tis for me to bide</l>
               <l n="6">your choice, Menalcas, whether now we seek</l>
               <l n="7">yon shade that quivers to the changeful breeze,</l>
               <l n="8">or the cave's shelter. Look you how the cave</l>
               <l n="9">is with the wild vine's clusters over-laced!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="10">None but Amyntas on these hills of ours</l>
               <l n="11">can vie with you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOPSUS</speaker>
               <l n="12">What if he also strive</l>
               <l n="13">to out-sing Phoebus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="14">Do you first begin,</l>
               <l n="15">good Mopsus, whether minded to sing aught</l>
               <l n="16">of Phyllis and her loves, or Alcon's praise,</l>
               <l n="17">or to fling taunts at Codrus. Come, begin,</l>
               <l n="18">while Tityrus watches o'er the grazing kids.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOPSUS</speaker>
               <l n="19">Nay, then, I will essay what late I carved</l>
               <l n="20">on a green beech-tree's rind, playing by turns,</l>
               <l n="21">and marking down the notes; then afterward</l>
               <l n="22">bid you Amyntas match them if he can.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="23">As limber willow to pale olive yields,</l>
               <l n="24">as lowly Celtic nard to rose-buds bright,</l>
               <l n="25">so, to my mind, Amyntas yields to you.</l>
               <l n="26">But hold awhile, for to the cave we come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOPSUS</speaker>
               <l n="27">“For Daphnis cruelly slain wept all the Nymphs—</l>
               <l n="28">ye hazels, bear them witness, and ye streams—</l>
               <l n="29">when she, his mother, clasping in her arms</l>
               <l n="30">the hapless body of the son she bare,</l>
               <l n="31">to gods and stars unpitying, poured her plaint.</l>
               <l n="32">Then, Daphnis, to the cooling streams were none</l>
               <l n="33">that drove the pastured oxen, then no beast</l>
               <l n="34">drank of the river, or would the grass-blade touch.</l>
               <l n="35">Nay, the wild rocks and woods then voiced the roar</l>
               <l n="36">of Afric lions mourning for thy death.</l>
               <l n="37">Daphnis, 'twas thou bad'st yoke to Bacchus' car</l>
               <l n="38">armenian tigresses, lead on the pomp</l>
               <l n="39">of revellers, and with tender foliage wreathe</l>
               <l n="40">the bending spear-wands. As to trees the vine</l>
               <l n="41">is crown of glory, as to vines the grape,</l>
               <l n="42">bulls to the herd, to fruitful fields the corn,</l>
               <l n="43">so the one glory of thine own art thou.</l>
               <l n="44">When the Fates took thee hence, then Pales' self,</l>
               <l n="45">and even Apollo, left the country lone.</l>
               <l n="46">Where the plump barley-grain so oft we sowed,</l>
               <l n="47">there but wild oats and barren darnel spring;</l>
               <l n="48">for tender violet and narcissus bright</l>
               <l n="49">thistle and prickly thorn uprear their heads.</l>
               <l n="50">Now, O ye shepherds, strew the ground with leaves,</l>
               <l n="51">and o'er the fountains draw a shady veil—</l>
               <l n="52">so Daphnis to his memory bids be done—</l>
               <l n="53">and rear a tomb, and write thereon this verse:</l>
               <l n="54">‘I, Daphnis in the woods, from hence in fame</l>
               <l n="55">am to the stars exalted, guardian once</l>
               <l n="56">of a fair flock, myself more fair than they.’”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="57">So is thy song to me, poet divine,</l>
               <l n="58">as slumber on the grass to weary limbs,</l>
               <l n="59">or to slake thirst from some sweet-bubbling rill</l>
               <l n="60">in summer's heat. Nor on the reeds alone,</l>
               <l n="61">but with thy voice art thou, thrice happy boy,</l>
               <l n="62">ranked with thy master, second but to him.</l>
               <l n="63">Yet will I, too, in turn, as best I may,</l>
               <l n="64">sing thee a song, and to the stars uplift</l>
               <l n="65">thy Daphnis—Daphnis to the stars extol,</l>
               <l n="66">for me too Daphnis loved.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOPSUS</speaker>
               <l n="67">Than such a boon</l>
               <l n="68">what dearer could I deem? the boy himself</l>
               <l n="69">was worthy to be sung, and many a time</l>
               <l n="70">hath Stimichon to me your singing praised.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="71">“In dazzling sheen with unaccustomed eyes</l>
               <l n="72">daphnis stands rapt before <placeName key="perseus,Olympos,Lycia">Olympus</placeName>' gate,</l>
               <l n="73">and sees beneath his feet the clouds and stars.</l>
               <l n="74">Wherefore the woods and fields, Pan, shepherd-folk,</l>
               <l n="75">and Dryad-maidens, thrill with eager joy;</l>
               <l n="76">nor wolf with treacherous wile assails the flock,</l>
               <l n="77">nor nets the stag: kind Daphnis loveth peace.</l>
               <l n="78">The unshorn mountains to the stars up-toss</l>
               <l n="79">voices of gladness; ay, the very rocks,</l>
               <l n="80">the very thickets, shout and sing, ‘A god,</l>
               <l n="81">a god is he, Menalcas’  Be thou kind,</l>
               <l n="82">propitious to thine own. Lo! altars four,</l>
               <l n="83">twain to thee, Daphnis, and to Phoebus twain</l>
               <l n="84">for sacrifice, we build; and I for thee</l>
               <l n="85">two beakers yearly of fresh milk afoam,</l>
               <l n="86">and of rich olive-oil two bowls, will set;</l>
               <l n="87">and of the wine-god's bounty above all,</l>
               <l n="88">if cold, before the hearth, or in the shade</l>
               <l n="89">at harvest-time, to glad the festal hour,</l>
               <l n="90">from flasks of Ariusian grape will pour</l>
               <l n="91">sweet nectar. Therewithal at my behest</l>
               <l n="92">shall Lyctian Aegon and Damoetas sing,</l>
               <l n="93">and Alphesiboeus emulate in dance</l>
               <l n="94">the dancing Satyrs. This, thy service due,</l>
               <l n="95">shalt thou lack never, both when we pay the Nymphs</l>
               <l n="96">our yearly vows, and when with lustral rites</l>
               <l n="97">the fields we hallow. Long as the wild boar</l>
               <l n="98">shall love the mountain-heights, and fish the streams,</l>
               <l n="99">while bees on thyme and crickets feed on dew,</l>
               <l n="100">thy name, thy praise, thine honour, shall endure.</l>
               <l n="101">Even as to Bacchus and to Ceres, so</l>
               <l n="102">to thee the swain his yearly vows shall make;</l>
               <l n="103">and thou thereof, like them, shalt quittance claim.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOPSUS</speaker>
               <l n="104">How, how repay thee for a song so rare?</l>
               <l n="105">For not the whispering south-wind on its way</l>
               <l n="106">so much delights me, nor wave-smitten beach,</l>
               <l n="107">nor streams that race adown their bouldered beds.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MENALCAS</speaker>
               <l n="108">First this frail hemlock-stalk to you I give,</l>
               <l n="109">which taught me “Corydon with love was fired</l>
               <l n="110">for fair Alexis,” ay, and this beside,</l>
               <l n="111">“Who owns the flock?—Meliboeus?”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOPSUS</speaker>
               <l n="112">But take you</l>
               <l n="113">this shepherd's crook, which, howso hard he begged,</l>
               <l n="114">antigenes, then worthy to be loved,</l>
               <l n="115">prevailed not to obtain—with brass, you see,</l>
               <l n="116">and equal knots, Menalcas, fashioned fair!</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="6">
            <head>TO VARUS</head>
            <l n="1">first my Thalia stooped in sportive mood</l>
            <l n="2">to Syracusan strains, nor blushed within</l>
            <l n="3">the woods to house her. When I sought to tell</l>
            <l n="4">of battles and of kings, the Cynthian god</l>
            <l n="5">plucked at mine ear and warned me: “Tityrus,</l>
            <l n="6">beseems a shepherd-wight to feed fat sheep,</l>
            <l n="7">but sing a slender song.” Now, Varus, I—</l>
            <l n="8">for lack there will not who would laud thy deeds,</l>
            <l n="9">and treat of dolorous wars—will rather tune</l>
            <l n="10">to the slim oaten reed my silvan lay.</l>
            <l n="11">I sing but as vouchsafed me; yet even this</l>
            <l n="12">if, if but one with ravished eyes should read,</l>
            <l n="13">of thee, O Varus, shall our tamarisks</l>
            <l n="14">and all the woodland ring; nor can there be</l>
            <l n="15">a page more dear to Phoebus, than the page</l>
            <l n="16">where, foremost writ, the name of Varus stands.</l>
            <lg>
               <l n="17">Speed ye, Pierian Maids! Within a cave</l>
               <l n="18">young Chromis and Mnasyllos chanced to see</l>
               <l n="19">silenus sleeping, flushed, as was his wont,</l>
               <l n="20">with wine of yesterday. Not far aloof,</l>
               <l n="21">slipped from his head, the garlands lay, and there</l>
               <l n="22">by its worn handle hung a ponderous cup.</l>
               <l n="23">Approaching—for the old man many a time</l>
               <l n="24">had balked them both of a long hoped-for song—</l>
               <l n="25">garlands to fetters turned, they bind him fast.</l>
               <l n="26">Then Aegle, fairest of the Naiad-band,</l>
               <l n="27">aegle came up to the half-frightened boys,</l>
               <l n="28">came, and, as now with open eyes he lay,</l>
               <l n="29">with juice of blood-red mulberries smeared him o'er,</l>
               <l n="30">both brow and temples. Laughing at their guile,</l>
               <l n="31">and crying, “Why tie the fetters? loose me, boys;</l>
               <l n="32">enough for you to think you had the power;</l>
               <l n="33">now list the songs you wish for—songs for you,</l>
               <l n="34">another meed for her”—forthwith began.</l>
               <l n="35">Then might you see the wild things of the wood,</l>
               <l n="36">with Fauns in sportive frolic beat the time,</l>
               <l n="37">and stubborn oaks their branchy summits bow.</l>
               <l n="38">Not Phoebus doth the rude Parnassian crag</l>
               <l n="39">so ravish, nor Orpheus so entrance the heights</l>
               <l n="40">of Rhodope or Ismarus: for he sang</l>
               <l n="41">how through the mighty void the seeds were driven</l>
               <l n="42">of earth, air, ocean, and of liquid fire,</l>
               <l n="43">how all that is from these beginnings grew,</l>
               <l n="44">and the young world itself took solid shape,</l>
               <l n="45">then 'gan its crust to harden, and in the deep</l>
               <l n="46">shut Nereus off, and mould the forms of things</l>
               <l n="47">little by little; and how the earth amazed</l>
               <l n="48">beheld the new sun shining, and the showers</l>
               <l n="49">fall, as the clouds soared higher, what time the woods</l>
               <l n="50">'gan first to rise, and living things to roam</l>
               <l n="51">scattered among the hills that knew them not.</l>
               <l n="52">Then sang he of the stones by Pyrrha cast,</l>
               <l n="53">of Saturn's reign, and of Prometheus' theft,</l>
               <l n="54">and the Caucasian birds, and told withal</l>
               <l n="55">nigh to what fountain by his comrades left</l>
               <l n="56">the mariners cried on Hylas till the shore</l>
               <l n="57">then re-echoed “Hylas, Hylas!” soothed</l>
               <l n="58">pasiphae with the love of her white bull—</l>
               <l n="59">happy if cattle-kind had never been!—</l>
               <l n="60">o ill-starred maid, what frenzy caught thy soul</l>
               <l n="61">the daughters too of Proetus filled the fields</l>
               <l n="62">with their feigned lowings, yet no one of them</l>
               <l n="63">of such unhallowed union e'er was fain</l>
               <l n="64">as with a beast to mate, though many a time</l>
               <l n="65">on her smooth forehead she had sought for horns,</l>
               <l n="66">and for her neck had feared the galling plough.</l>
               <l n="67">O ill-starred maid! thou roamest now the hills,</l>
               <l n="68">while on soft hyacinths he, his snowy side</l>
               <l n="69">reposing, under some dark ilex now</l>
               <l n="70">chews the pale herbage, or some heifer tracks</l>
               <l n="71">amid the crowding herd. Now close, ye Nymphs,</l>
               <l n="72">ye Nymphs of Dicte, close the forest-glades,</l>
               <l n="73">if haply there may chance upon mine eyes</l>
               <l n="74">the white bull's wandering foot-prints: him belike</l>
               <l n="75">following the herd, or by green pasture lured,</l>
               <l n="76">some kine may guide to the Gortynian stalls.</l>
               <l n="77">Then sings he of the maid so wonder-struck</l>
               <l n="78">with the apples of the Hesperids, and then</l>
               <l n="79">with moss-bound, bitter bark rings round the forms</l>
               <l n="80">of Phaethon's fair sisters, from the ground</l>
               <l n="81">up-towering into poplars. Next he sings</l>
               <l n="82">of Gallus wandering by Permessus' stream,</l>
               <l n="83">and by a sister of the Muses led</l>
               <l n="84">to the Aonian mountains, and how all</l>
               <l n="85">the choir of Phoebus rose to greet him; how</l>
               <l n="86">the shepherd Linus, singer of songs divine,</l>
               <l n="87">brow-bound with flowers and bitter parsley, spake:</l>
               <l n="88">“These reeds the Muses give thee, take them thou,</l>
               <l n="89">erst to the aged bard of Ascra given,</l>
               <l n="90">wherewith in singing he was wont to draw</l>
               <l n="91">time-rooted ash-trees from the mountain heights.</l>
               <l n="92">With these the birth of the Grynean grove</l>
               <l n="93">be voiced by thee, that of no grove beside</l>
               <l n="94">apollo more may boast him.” Wherefore speak</l>
               <l n="95">of Scylla, child of Nisus, who, 'tis said,</l>
               <l n="96">her fair white loins with barking monsters girt</l>
               <l n="97">vexed the Dulichian ships, and, in the deep</l>
               <l n="98">swift-eddying whirlpool, with her sea-dogs tore</l>
               <l n="99">the trembling mariners? or how he told</l>
               <l n="100">of the changed limbs of Tereus—what a feast,</l>
               <l n="101">what gifts, to him by Philomel were given;</l>
               <l n="102">how swift she sought the desert, with what wings</l>
               <l n="103">hovered in anguish o'er her ancient home?</l>
               <l n="104">All that, of old, Eurotas, happy stream,</l>
               <l n="105">heard, as Apollo mused upon the lyre,</l>
               <l n="106">and bade his laurels learn, Silenus sang;</l>
               <l n="107">till from <placeName key="perseus,Olympos,Lycia">Olympus</placeName>, loth at his approach,</l>
               <l n="108">vesper, advancing, bade the shepherds tell</l>
               <l n="109">their tale of sheep, and pen them in the fold.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="7">
            <head>MELIBOEUS   CORYDON   THYRSIS</head>
            <l n="1">daphnis beneath a rustling ilex-tree</l>
            <l n="2">had sat him down; Thyrsis and Corydon</l>
            <l n="3">had gathered in the flock, Thyrsis the sheep,</l>
            <l n="4">and Corydon the she-goats swollen with milk—</l>
            <l n="5">both in the flower of age, Arcadians both,</l>
            <l n="6">ready to sing, and in like strain reply.</l>
            <l n="7">Hither had strayed, while from the frost I fend</l>
            <l n="8">my tender myrtles, the he-goat himself,</l>
            <l n="9">lord of the flock; when Daphnis I espy!</l>
            <l n="10">Soon as he saw me, “Hither haste,” he cried,</l>
            <l n="11">“O Meliboeus! goat and kids are safe;</l>
            <l n="12">and, if you have an idle hour to spare,</l>
            <l n="13">rest here beneath the shade. Hither the steers</l>
            <l n="14">will through the meadows, of their own free will,</l>
            <l n="15">untended come to drink. Here Mincius hath</l>
            <l n="16">with tender rushes rimmed his verdant banks,</l>
            <l n="17">and from yon sacred oak with busy hum</l>
            <l n="18">the bees are swarming.” What was I to do?</l>
            <l n="19">No Phyllis or Alcippe left at home</l>
            <l n="20">had I, to shelter my new-weaned lambs,</l>
            <l n="21">and no slight matter was a singing-bout</l>
            <l n="22">'twixt Corydon and Thyrsis. Howsoe'er,</l>
            <l n="23">I let my business wait upon their sport.</l>
            <l n="24">So they began to sing, voice answering voice</l>
            <l n="25">in strains alternate—for alternate strains</l>
            <l n="26">the Muses then were minded to recall—</l>
            <l n="27">first Corydon, then Thyrsis in reply.</l>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CORYDON</speaker>
               <l n="28">“Libethrian Nymphs, who are my heart's delight,</l>
               <l n="29">grant me, as doth my Codrus, so to sing—</l>
               <l n="30">next to Apollo he—or if to this</l>
               <l n="31">we may not all attain, my tuneful pipe</l>
               <l n="32">here on this sacred pine shall silent hang.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>THYRSIS</speaker>
               <l n="33">“<placeName key="tgn,7002735">Arcadian</placeName> shepherds, wreathe with ivy-spray</l>
               <l n="34">your budding poet, so that Codrus burst</l>
               <l n="35">with envy: if he praise beyond my due,</l>
               <l n="36">then bind my brow with foxglove, lest his tongue</l>
               <l n="37">with evil omen blight the coming bard.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CORYDON</speaker>
               <l n="38">“This bristling boar's head, Delian Maid, to thee,</l>
               <l n="39">with branching antlers of a sprightly stag,</l>
               <l n="40">young Micon offers: if his luck but hold,</l>
               <l n="41">full-length in polished marble, ankle-bound</l>
               <l n="42">with purple buskin, shall thy statue stand.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>THYRSIS</speaker>
               <l n="43">“A bowl of milk, Priapus, and these cakes,</l>
               <l n="44">yearly, it is enough for thee to claim;</l>
               <l n="45">thou art the guardian of a poor man's plot.</l>
               <l n="46">Wrought for a while in marble, if the flock</l>
               <l n="47">at lambing time be filled,stand there in gold.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CORYDON</speaker>
               <l n="48">“Daughter of Nereus, Galatea mine,</l>
               <l n="49">sweeter than Hybla-thyme, more white than swans,</l>
               <l n="50">fairer than ivy pale, soon as the steers</l>
               <l n="51">shall from their pasture to the stalls repair,</l>
               <l n="52">if aught for Corydon thou carest, come.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>THYRSIS</speaker>
               <l n="53">“Now may I seem more bitter to your taste</l>
               <l n="54">than herb Sardinian, rougher than the broom,</l>
               <l n="55">more worthless than strewn sea-weed, if to-day</l>
               <l n="56">hath not a year out-lasted! Fie for shame!</l>
               <l n="57">Go home, my cattle, from your grazing go!”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CORYDON</speaker>
               <l n="58">“Ye mossy springs, and grass more soft than sleep,</l>
               <l n="59">and arbute green with thin shade sheltering you,</l>
               <l n="60">ward off the solstice from my flock, for now</l>
               <l n="61">comes on the burning summer, now the buds</l>
               <l n="62">upon the limber vine-shoot 'gin to swell.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>THYRSIS</speaker>
               <l n="63">“Here is a hearth, and resinous logs, here fire</l>
               <l n="64">unstinted, and doors black with ceaseless smoke.</l>
               <l n="65">Here heed we Boreas' icy breath as much</l>
               <l n="66">as the wolf heeds the number of the flock,</l>
               <l n="67">or furious rivers their restraining banks.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CORYDON</speaker>
               <l n="68">“The junipers and prickly chestnuts stand,</l>
               <l n="69">and 'neath each tree lie strewn their several fruits,</l>
               <l n="70">now the whole world is smiling, but if fair</l>
               <l n="71">alexis from these hill-slopes should away,</l>
               <l n="72">even the rivers you would ; see run dry.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>THYRSIS</speaker>
               <l n="73">“The field is parched, the grass-blades thirst to death</l>
               <l n="74">in the faint air; Liber hath grudged the hills</l>
               <l n="75">his vine's o'er-shadowing: should my Phyllis come,</l>
               <l n="76">green will be all the grove, and Jupiter</l>
               <l n="77">descend in floods of fertilizing rain.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CORYDON</speaker>
               <l n="78">“The poplar doth Alcides hold most dear,</l>
               <l n="79">the vine Iacchus, Phoebus his own bays,</l>
               <l n="80">and Venus fair the myrtle: therewithal</l>
               <l n="81">phyllis doth hazels love, and while she loves,</l>
               <l n="82">myrtle nor bay the hazel shall out-vie.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>THYRSIS</speaker>
               <l n="83">“Ash in the forest is most beautiful,</l>
               <l n="84">pine in the garden, poplar by the stream,</l>
               <l n="85">fir on the mountain-height; but if more oft</l>
               <l n="86">thou'ldst come to me, fair Lycidas, to thee</l>
               <l n="87">both forest-ash, and garden-pine should bow.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MELIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="88">These I remember, and how Thyrsis strove</l>
               <l n="89">for victory in vain. From that time forth</l>
               <l n="90">is Corydon still Corydon with us.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="8">
            <head>TO POLLIO.   DAMON   ALPHESIBOEUS</head>
            <l n="1">of Damon and Alphesiboeus now,</l>
            <l n="2">those shepherd-singers at whose rival strains</l>
            <l n="3">the heifer wondering forgot to graze,</l>
            <l n="4">the lynx stood awe-struck, and the flowing streams,</l>
            <l n="5">unwonted loiterers, stayed their course to hear—</l>
            <l n="6">how Damon and Alphesiboeus sang</l>
            <l n="7">their pastoral ditties, will I tell the tale.</l>
            <lg>
               <l n="8">Thou, whether broad Timavus' rocky banks</l>
               <l n="9">thou now art passing, or dost skirt the shore</l>
               <l n="10">of the Illyrian main,—will ever dawn</l>
               <l n="11">that day when I thy deeds may celebrate,</l>
               <l n="12">ever that day when through the whole wide world</l>
               <l n="13">I may renown thy verse—that verse alone</l>
               <l n="14">of Sophoclean buskin worthy found?</l>
               <l n="15">With thee began, to thee shall end, the strain.</l>
               <l n="16">Take thou these songs that owe their birth to thee,</l>
               <l n="17">and deign around thy temples to let creep</l>
               <l n="18">this ivy-chaplet 'twixt the conquering bays.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="19">Scarce had night's chilly shade forsook the sky</l>
               <l n="20">what time to nibbling sheep the dewy grass</l>
               <l n="21">tastes sweetest, when, on his smooth shepherd-staff</l>
               <l n="22">of olive leaning, Damon thus began.</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DAMON</speaker>
               <l n="23">“Rise, Lucifer, and, heralding the light,</l>
               <l n="24">bring in the genial day, while I make moan</l>
               <l n="25">fooled by vain passion for a faithless bride,</l>
               <l n="26">for Nysa, and with this my dying breath</l>
               <l n="27">call on the gods, though little it bestead—</l>
               <l n="28">the gods who heard her vows and heeded not.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="29">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="30">Ever hath Maenalus his murmuring groves</l>
               <l n="31">and whispering pines, and ever hears the songs</l>
               <l n="32">of love-lorn shepherds, and of Pan, who first</l>
               <l n="33">brooked not the tuneful reed should idle lie.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="34">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="35">Nysa to Mopsus given! what may not then</l>
               <l n="36">we lovers look for? soon shall we see mate</l>
               <l n="37">griffins with mares, and in the coming age</l>
               <l n="38">shy deer and hounds together come to drink.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="39">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="40">Now, Mopsus, cut new torches, for they bring</l>
               <l n="41">your bride along; now, bridegroom, scatter nuts:</l>
               <l n="42">forsaking Oeta mounts the evening star!</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="43">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="44">O worthy of thy mate, while all men else</l>
               <l n="45">thou scornest, and with loathing dost behold</l>
               <l n="46">my shepherd's pipe, my goats, my shaggy brow,</l>
               <l n="47">and untrimmed beard, nor deem'st that any god</l>
               <l n="48">for mortal doings hath regard or care.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="49">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="50">Once with your mother, in our orchard-garth,</l>
               <l n="51">a little maid I saw you—I your guide—</l>
               <l n="52">plucking the dewy apples. My twelfth year</l>
               <l n="53">I scarce had entered, and could barely reach</l>
               <l n="54">the brittle boughs. I looked, and I was lost;</l>
               <l n="55">a sudden frenzy swept my wits away.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="56">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="57">Now know I what Love is: 'mid savage rocks</l>
               <l n="58">tmaros or <placeName key="tgn,7002754">Rhodope</placeName> brought forth the boy,</l>
               <l n="59">or Garamantes in earth's utmost bounds—</l>
               <l n="60">no kin of ours, nor of our blood begot.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="61">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="62">Fierce Love it was once steeled a mother's heart</l>
               <l n="63">with her own offspring's blood her hands to imbrue:</l>
               <l n="64">mother, thou too wert cruel; say wert thou</l>
               <l n="65">more cruel, mother, or more ruthless he?</l>
               <l n="66">Ruthless the boy, thou, mother, cruel too.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="67">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="68">Now let the wolf turn tail and fly the sheep,</l>
               <l n="69">tough oaks bear golden apples, alder-trees</l>
               <l n="70">bloom with narcissus-flower, the tamarisk</l>
               <l n="71">sweat with rich amber, and the screech-owl vie</l>
               <l n="72">in singing with the swan: let Tityrus</l>
               <l n="73">be Orpheus, Orpheus in the forest-glade,</l>
               <l n="74">arion 'mid his dolphins on the deep.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="75">‘Begin, my flute, with me Maenalian lays.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="76">Yea, be the whole earth to mid-ocean turned!</l>
               <l n="77">Farewell, ye woodlands I from the tall peak</l>
               <l n="78">of yon aerial rock will headlong plunge</l>
               <l n="79">into the billows: this my latest gift,</l>
               <l n="80">from dying lips bequeathed thee, see thou keep.</l>
               <l n="81">Cease now, my flute, now cease Maenalian lays.’”</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="82">thus Damon: but do ye, Pierian Maids—</l>
                  <l n="83">we cannot all do all things—tell me how</l>
                  <l n="84">alphesiboeus to his strain replied.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALPHESIBOEUS</speaker>
               <l n="85">“Bring water, and with soft wool-fillet bind</l>
               <l n="86">these altars round about, and burn thereon</l>
               <l n="87">rich vervain and male frankincense, that I</l>
               <l n="88">may strive with magic spells to turn astray</l>
               <l n="89">my lover's saner senses, whereunto</l>
               <l n="90">there lacketh nothing save the power of song.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="91">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="92">Songs can the very moon draw down from heaven</l>
               <l n="93">circe with singing changed from human form</l>
               <l n="94">the comrades of Ulysses, and by song</l>
               <l n="95">is the cold meadow-snake, asunder burst.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="96">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="97">These triple threads of threefold colour first</l>
               <l n="98">I twine about thee, and three times withal</l>
               <l n="99">around these altars do thine image bear:</l>
               <l n="100">uneven numbers are the god's delight.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="101">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="102">Now, Amaryllis, ply in triple knots</l>
               <l n="103">the threefold colours; ply them fast, and say</l>
               <l n="104">this is the chain of Venus that I ply.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="105">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="106">As by the kindling of the self-same fire</l>
               <l n="107">harder this clay, this wax the softer grows,</l>
               <l n="108">so by my love may Daphnis; sprinkle meal,</l>
               <l n="109">and with bitumen burn the brittle bays.</l>
               <l n="110">Me Daphnis with his cruelty doth burn,</l>
               <l n="111">I to melt cruel Daphnis burn this bay.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="112">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="113">As when some heifer, seeking for her steer</l>
               <l n="114">through woodland and deep grove, sinks wearied out</l>
               <l n="115">on the green sedge beside a stream, love-lorn,</l>
               <l n="116">nor marks the gathering night that calls her home—</l>
               <l n="117">as pines that heifer, with such love as hers</l>
               <l n="118">may Daphnis pine, and I not care to heal.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="119">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="120">These relics once, dear pledges of himself,</l>
               <l n="121">the traitor left me, which, O earth, to thee</l>
               <l n="122">here on this very threshold I commit—</l>
               <l n="123">pledges that bind him to redeem the debt.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="124">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="125">These herbs of bane to me did Moeris give,</l>
               <l n="126">in <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName> culled, where baneful herbs abound.</l>
               <l n="127">With these full oft have I seen Moeris change</l>
               <l n="128">to a wolf's form, and hide him in the woods,</l>
               <l n="129">oft summon spirits from the tomb's recess,</l>
               <l n="130">and to new fields transport the standing corn.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="131">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="132">Take ashes, Amaryllis, fetch them forth,</l>
               <l n="133">and o'er your head into the running brook</l>
               <l n="134">fling them, nor look behind: with these will</l>
               <l n="135">upon the heart of Daphnis make essay.</l>
               <l n="136">Nothing for gods, nothing for songs cares he.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="137">‘Draw from the town, my songs, draw Daphnis home.’</l>
               </lg>
               <l n="138">Look, look I the very embers of themselves</l>
               <l n="139">have caught the altar with a flickering flame,</l>
               <l n="140">while I delay to fetch them: may the sign</l>
               <l n="141">prove lucky! something it must mean, for sure,</l>
               <l n="142">and Hylax on the threshold 'gins to bark!</l>
               <l n="143">May we believe it, or are lovers still</l>
               <l n="144">by their own fancies fooled?</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="145">Give o'er, my songs,</l>
                  <l n="146">daphnis is coming from the town, give o'er.”</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="9">
            <head>LYCIDAS   MOERIS</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCIDAS</speaker>
               <l n="1">Say whither, Moeris?—Make you for the town,</l>
               <l n="2">or on what errand bent?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOERIS</speaker>
               <l n="3">O Lycidas,</l>
               <l n="4">we have lived to see, what never yet we feared,</l>
               <l n="5">an interloper own our little farm,</l>
               <l n="6">and say, “Be off, you former husbandmen!</l>
               <l n="7">These fields are mine.” Now, cowed and out of heart,</l>
               <l n="8">since Fortune turns the whole world upside down,</l>
               <l n="9">we are taking him—ill luck go with the same!—</l>
               <l n="10">these kids you see.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCIDAS</speaker>
               <l n="11">But surely I had heard</l>
               <l n="12">that where the hills first draw from off the plain,</l>
               <l n="13">and the high ridge with gentle slope descends,</l>
               <l n="14">down to the brook-side and the broken crests</l>
               <l n="15">of yonder veteran beeches, all the land</l>
               <l n="16">was by the songs of your Menalcas saved.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOERIS</speaker>
               <l n="17">Heard it you had, and so the rumour ran,</l>
               <l n="18">but 'mid the clash of arms, my Lycidas,</l>
               <l n="19">our songs avail no more than, as 'tis said,</l>
               <l n="20">doves of <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> when an eagle comes.</l>
               <l n="21">Nay, had I not, from hollow ilex-bole</l>
               <l n="22">warned by a raven on the left, cut short</l>
               <l n="23">the rising feud, nor I, your Moeris here,</l>
               <l n="24">no, nor Menalcas, were alive to-day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCIDAS</speaker>
               <l n="25">Alack! could any of so foul a crime</l>
               <l n="26">be guilty? Ah! how nearly, thyself,</l>
               <l n="27">reft was the solace that we had in thee,</l>
               <l n="28">Menalcas! Who then of the Nymphs had sung,</l>
               <l n="29">or who with flowering herbs bestrewn the ground,</l>
               <l n="30">and o'er the fountains drawn a leafy veil?—</l>
               <l n="31">who sung the stave I filched from you that day</l>
               <l n="32">to Amaryllis wending, our hearts' joy?—</l>
               <l n="33">“While I am gone, 'tis but a little way,</l>
               <l n="34">feed, Tityrus, my goats, and, having fed,</l>
               <l n="35">drive to the drinking-pool, and, as you drive,</l>
               <l n="36">beware the he-goat; with his horn he butts.“</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOERIS</speaker>
               <l n="37">Ay, or to Varus that half-finished lay,</l>
               <l n="38">“Varus, thy name, so still our <placeName key="perseus,Mantua">Mantua</placeName> live—</l>
               <l n="39">
                  <placeName key="perseus,Mantua">Mantua</placeName> to poor <placeName key="perseus,Cremona">Cremona</placeName> all too near—</l>
               <l n="40">shall singing swans bear upward to the stars.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCIDAS</speaker>
               <l n="41">So may your swarms Cyrnean yew-trees shun,</l>
               <l n="42">your kine with cytisus their udders swell,</l>
               <l n="43">begin, if aught you have. The Muses made</l>
               <l n="44">me too a singer; I too have sung; the swains</l>
               <l n="45">call me a poet, but I believe them not:</l>
               <l n="46">for naught of mine, or worthy Varius yet</l>
               <l n="47">or Cinna deem I, but account myself</l>
               <l n="48">a cackling goose among melodious swans.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOERIS</speaker>
               <l n="49">'Twas in my thought to do so, Lycidas;</l>
               <l n="50">even now was I revolving silently</l>
               <l n="51">if this I could recall—no paltry song:</l>
               <l n="52">“Come, Galatea, what pleasure is 't to play</l>
               <l n="53">amid the waves? Here glows the Spring, here earth</l>
               <l n="54">beside the streams pours forth a thousand flowers;</l>
               <l n="55">here the white poplar bends above the cave,</l>
               <l n="56">and the lithe vine weaves shadowy covert: come,</l>
               <l n="57">leave the mad waves to beat upon the shore.”</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCIDAS</speaker>
               <l n="58">What of the strain I heard you singing once</l>
               <l n="59">on a clear night alone? the notes I still</l>
               <l n="60">remember, could I but recall the words.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOERIS</speaker>
               <l n="61">“Why, Daphnis, upward gazing, do you mark</l>
               <l n="62">the ancient risings of the Signs? for look</l>
               <l n="63">where Dionean Caesar's star comes forth</l>
               <l n="64">in heaven, to gladden all the fields with corn,</l>
               <l n="65">and to the grape upon the sunny slopes</l>
               <l n="66">her colour bring! Now, the pears;</l>
               <l n="67">so shall your children's children pluck their fruit.”</l>
               <lg>
                  <l n="68">Time carries all things, even our wits, away.</l>
                  <l n="69">Oft, as a boy, I sang the sun to rest,</l>
                  <l n="70">but all those songs are from my memory fled,</l>
                  <l n="71">and even his voice is failing Moeris now;</l>
                  <l n="72">the wolves eyed Moeris first: but at your wish</l>
                  <l n="73">Menalcas will repeat them oft enow.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCIDAS</speaker>
               <l n="74">Your pleas but linger out my heart's desire:</l>
               <l n="75">now all the deep is into silence hushed,</l>
               <l n="76">and all the murmuring breezes sunk to sleep.</l>
               <l n="77">We are half-way thither, for Bianor's tomb</l>
               <l n="78">begins to show: here, Moeris, where the hinds</l>
               <l n="79">are lopping the thick leafage, let us sing.</l>
               <l n="80">Set down the kids, yet shall we reach the town;</l>
               <l n="81">or, if we fear the night may gather rain</l>
               <l n="82">ere we arrive, then singing let us go,</l>
               <l n="83">our way to lighten; and, that we may thus</l>
               <l n="84">go singing, I will case you of this load.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>MOERIS</speaker>
               <l n="85">Cease, boy, and get we to the work in hand:</l>
               <l n="86">we shall sing better when himself is come.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="10">
            <head>GALLUS</head>
            <l n="1">This now, the very latest of my toils,</l>
            <l n="2">vouchsafe me, Arethusa! needs must I</l>
            <l n="3">sing a brief song to Gallus—brief, but yet</l>
            <l n="4">such as Lycoris' self may fitly read.</l>
            <l n="5">Who would not sing for Gallus? So, when thou</l>
            <l n="6">beneath Sicanian billows glidest on,</l>
            <l n="7">may Doris blend no bitter wave with thine,</l>
            <l n="8">begin! The love of Gallus be our theme,</l>
            <l n="9">and the shrewd pangs he suffered, while, hard by,</l>
            <l n="10">the flat-nosed she-goats browse the tender brush.</l>
            <l n="11">We sing not to deaf ears; no word of ours</l>
            <l n="12">but the woods echo it. What groves or lawns</l>
            <l n="13">held you, ye Dryad-maidens, when for love—</l>
            <l n="14">love all unworthy of a loss so dear—</l>
            <l n="15">Gallus lay dying? for neither did the slopes</l>
            <l n="16">of Pindus or <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName> stay you then,</l>
            <l n="17">no, nor Aonian Aganippe. Him</l>
            <l n="18">even the laurels and the tamarisks wept;</l>
            <l n="19">for him, outstretched beneath a lonely rock,</l>
            <l n="20">wept pine-clad Maenalus, and the flinty crags</l>
            <l n="21">of cold Lycaeus. The sheep too stood around—</l>
            <l n="22">of us they feel no shame, poet divine;</l>
            <l n="23">nor of the flock be thou ashamed: even fair</l>
            <l n="24">Adonis by the rivers fed his sheep—</l>
            <l n="25">came shepherd too, and swine-herd footing slow,</l>
            <l n="26">and, from the winter-acorns dripping-wet</l>
            <l n="27">Menalcas. All with one accord exclaim:</l>
            <l n="28">“From whence this love of thine?” Apollo came;</l>
            <l n="29">“Gallus, art mad?” he cried, “thy bosom's care</l>
            <l n="30">another love is following.” Therewithal</l>
            <l n="31">Silvanus came, with rural honours crowned;</l>
            <l n="32">the flowering fennels and tall lilies shook</l>
            <l n="33">before him. Yea, and our own eyes beheld</l>
            <l n="34">pan, god of Arcady, with blood-red juice</l>
            <l n="35">of the elder-berry, and with vermilion, dyed.</l>
            <l n="36">“Wilt ever make an end?” quoth he, “behold</l>
            <l n="37">love recks not aught of it: his heart no more</l>
            <l n="38">with tears is sated than with streams the grass,</l>
            <l n="39">bees with the cytisus, or goats with leaves.”</l>
            <l n="40">“Yet will ye sing, Arcadians, of my woes</l>
            <l n="41">upon your mountains,” sadly he replied—</l>
            <l n="42">“Arcadians, that alone have skill to sing.</l>
            <l n="43">O then how softly would my ashes rest,</l>
            <l n="44">if of my love, one day, your flutes should tell!</l>
            <l n="45">And would that I, of your own fellowship,</l>
            <l n="46">or dresser of the ripening grape had been,</l>
            <l n="47">or guardian of the flock! for surely then,</l>
            <l n="48">let Phyllis, or Amyntas, or who else,</l>
            <l n="49">bewitch me—what if swart Amyntas be?</l>
            <l n="50">Dark is the violet, dark the hyacinth—</l>
            <l n="51">among the willows, 'neath the limber vine,</l>
            <l n="52">reclining would my love have lain with me,</l>
            <l n="53">Phyllis plucked garlands, or Amyntas sung.</l>
            <l n="54">Here are cool springs, soft mead and grove, Lycoris;</l>
            <l n="55">here might our lives with time have worn away.</l>
            <l n="56">But me mad love of the stern war-god holds</l>
            <l n="57">armed amid weapons and opposing foes.</l>
            <l n="58">Whilst thou—Ah! might I but believe it not!—</l>
            <l n="59">alone without me, and from home afar,</l>
            <l n="60">look'st upon Alpine snows and frozen <placeName key="tgn,7012611">Rhine</placeName>.</l>
            <l n="61">Ah! may the frost not hurt thee, may the sharp</l>
            <l n="62">and jagged ice not wound thy tender feet!</l>
            <l n="63">I will depart, re-tune the songs I framed</l>
            <l n="64">in verse Chalcidian to the oaten reed</l>
            <l n="65">of the Sicilian swain. Resolved am I</l>
            <l n="66">in the woods, rather, with wild beasts to couch,</l>
            <l n="67">and bear my doom, and character my love</l>
            <l n="68">upon the tender tree-trunks: they will grow,</l>
            <l n="69">and you, my love, grow with them. And meanwhile</l>
            <l n="70">I with the Nymphs will haunt Mount Maenalus,</l>
            <l n="71">or hunt the keen wild boar. No frost so cold</l>
            <l n="72">but I will hem with hounds thy forest-glades,</l>
            <l n="73">parthenius. Even now, methinks, I range</l>
            <l n="74">o'er rocks, through echoing groves, and joy to launch</l>
            <l n="75">Cydonian arrows from a Parthian bow.—</l>
            <l n="76">as if my madness could find healing thus,</l>
            <l n="77">or that god soften at a mortal's grief!</l>
            <l n="78">Now neither Hamadryads, no, nor songs</l>
            <l n="79">delight me more: ye woods, away with you!</l>
            <l n="80">No pangs of ours can change him; not though we</l>
            <l n="81">in the mid-frost should drink of <placeName key="tgn,7002660">Hebrus</placeName>' stream,</l>
            <l n="82">and in wet winters face Sithonian snows,</l>
            <l n="83">or, when the bark of the tall elm-tree bole</l>
            <l n="84">of drought is dying, should, under Cancer's Sign,</l>
            <l n="85">in Aethiopian deserts drive our flocks.</l>
            <l n="86">Love conquers all things; yield we too to love!”</l>
            <lg>
               <l n="87">These songs, Pierian Maids, shall it suffice</l>
               <l n="88">your poet to have sung, the while he sat,</l>
               <l n="89">and of slim mallow wove a basket fine:</l>
               <l n="90">to Gallus ye will magnify their worth,</l>
               <l n="91">Gallus, for whom my love grows hour by hour,</l>
               <l n="92">as the green alder shoots in early Spring.</l>
               <l n="93">Come, let us rise: the shade is wont to be</l>
               <l n="94">baneful to singers; baneful is the shade</l>
               <l n="95">cast by the juniper, crops sicken too</l>
               <l n="96">in shade. Now homeward, having fed your fill—</l>
               <l n="97">eve's star is rising—go, my she-goats, go.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>