<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Against Lucius Calpurnius Piso </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <head>THE ORATION OF M. T. CICERO AGAINST LUCIUS CALPURNIUS PISO.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>After the decision which the senate came to in consequence of Cicero's speech on
                    the subject of the consular provinces, Piso returned home from <placeName
                        key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, being the first senator of consular
                    rank who had ever had that province, and had returned from it without a triumph.
                    On the contrary, he had lost most of his troops in engagements with the
                    barbarians on the frontiers. When he arrived in <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                        >Rome</placeName>, he stripped his forces of their laurels, and entered the
                    city as obscurely and quietly as he could. But on his first appearance in the
                    senate, relying on the influence of Caesar, who was his son-in-law, he attacked
                    Cicero violently, complaining that he had treated him ill in his absence,
                    especially in promoting the measure which deprived him of his province. And
                    among other topics he reproached him with having been banished; on which the
                    whole senate interrupted him with evident indignation. He reproached him also
                    with his bad verses, and with his vanity in praising himself in them. Cicero was
                    exasperated by this attack to break out with the following invective against him
                    by way of reply, of which a good deal of the beginning is lost, and one or two
                    other portions are in a very corrupt or doubtful state.</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="fr1" unit="section"/>
            <p>O ye immortal gods, what a day is this which has dawned <gap reason="****"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="****"/>What specimen, even the slightest, have you ever given of
                ability? Of ability, do I say? Rather should I say, what proof have you ever given
                of being an honourable or a free man? You, who by your complexion seem to throw a
                doubt on your country, by your speech on your family, by your morals on your name
                    <gap reason="****"/><milestone n="fr9" unit="section"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="****"/>This has nothing to do with leading us to think slightly of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Placentia">Placentia</placeName>, of which place he
                boasts that he is a native: for my nature does not incline me to his; nor does the
                dignity of a municipal town, especially of one which has <pb n="343"/> deserved
                exceedingly well at my hands, allow me to entertain such feelings.<gap reason="****"
                    /><milestone n="fr11" unit="section"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="****"/>There was a certain Insubrian who was both a merchant and a
                crier; he, when he had come to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> with
                his daughter, ventured to call a young man of high birth, named Caesoninus, the son
                of a most thorough rogue: he gave his daughter in marriage to <gap reason="****"/>
                him. And she became the mother of you, a beast rather than a man. [Concerning Piso's
                maternal grandfather] <gap reason="****"/> When he had settled on the banks of the
                Po at <placeName key="perseus,Placentia">Placentia</placeName>, a few years
                afterwards he obtained the freedom of that city; for it was a city at that time. For
                before that he was considered a <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>; then
                a man of Gallic extraction; and at last he began to be considered a sort of
                    half-Placentian.<gap reason="****"/><milestone n="fr12" unit="section"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="****"/>That Insubrian grandfather of his adopted the elder<gap
                    reason="****"/><milestone n="fr13" unit="section"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="****"/>Your father wanted a more luxurious son-in-law than Caius Piso
                did at that time of his distress <gap reason="****"/> I did not give my daughter in
                marriage to that man whom, when I had the power of choosing from all the world, I
                should have selected in preference to any one.<gap reason="****"/><milestone
                    n="fr15" unit="section"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="****"/>When the whole of your relations arrive in a wagon <gap
                    reason="****"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="***"/> You put out your head, butting at him <gap reason="****"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="**"/> I was sitting next to Pompeius<gap reason="****"/>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/></p>
            <p><gap reason="******"/> Do you not see now, do you not feel, O you beast, what
                complaints men make of your impudence? No one complains that a Syrian, that a man
                whom nobody knows, that some one of that body of lately emancipated slaves, was made
                consul. For that complexion, like that of slaves, and those hairy cheeks and
                discoloured teeth, did not deceive us: your eyes, your eyebrows, your brow, in short
                your whole countenance, which is, as it were, a sort of silent language of the mind,
                led men into error, this it was which led those to whom this man was unknown into
                mistake and error, and blunders. There were but few of us who were acquainted with
                those foul vices of yours; few of us who knew the deficiency of your abilities, your
                stolid manner, and your embarrassed way of speaking. Your voice had never been heard
                in the forum; no one had had any experience of your wisdom in counsel: you had not
                only never performed any, I will not say illustrious exploit, but any action at all
                    <pb n="344"/> that was known of either in war or at home. You crept into honours
                through men's blunders, by the recommendation of some old smoke-dried images, though
                there is nothing in you at all resembling them except your colour. <milestone n="2"
                    unit="section"/> Will he also boast to me that he obtained even magistracy
                without one repulse? I am able to make that boast concerning myself with true
                exultation; for the Roman people did confer all its honours on me in that way-on me,
                a new man. But when you were made quaestor, even men who had never seen you gave
                that honour to your name. You were made aedile. A Piso was elected by the Roman
                people; but not the Piso that you are. The praetorship also was conferred in reality
                on your ancestors. They, though dead, were well known; but no one had as yet known
                anything of you, though you were alive. </p>
            <p>When the Roman people made me quaestor among the first of the candidates, and first
                aedile, and first praetor, as they did by a unanimous vote, they were paying that
                compliment to me on my own account and not to my family,—to my habits of life, not
                to my ancestors,—to my proved virtue, and not to any nobleness of birth of which
                they had heard. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For why should I speak of my
                consulship? whether as to the manner in which it was obtained, or in which it was
                conducted? Wretched man that I am! am I comparing myself to this disgrace and plague
                of the republic? But I will say nothing with the view of drawing any comparison; but
                I will bring together those circumstances which are very widely separated. You were
                declared consul (I will say nothing more severe than what all men admit to be true)
                at a time when the affairs of the republic were in a state of great embarrassment,
                when the consuls Caesar and Bibulus were at variance, when you had no objection to
                those men by whom you were declared consul thinking you undeserving of the light of
                day if you did not prove more worthless than Gabinius. All <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, all ranks of men, the entire city declared
                me the first consul with acclamation even before they gave in their voting tablets.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But I say nothing of the circumstances under which each of us was elected. I will
                allow that chance may have been the mistress of the <placeName key="tgn,7006964"
                    >Campus Martius</placeName>. It is more to the purpose to say how we conducted
                ourselves in our respective consulships, than how we obtained them. <milestone n="4"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>I, on the first of January, delivered the senate and all <pb n="345"/> virtuous
                citizens from the fear of an agrarian law and of extravagant largesses. I preserved
                the Campanian district, if it was not expedient that it should be divided; if it was
                expedient, I reserved it for more respectable authors of the division. I, in the
                case of Caius Rabirius, a man on his trial for high treason, supported and defended
                against envy the authority of the senate which had been interposed forty years
                before the time of my consulship. I, at the cost of incurring great enmity myself,
                but without any enmity falling on the senate, deprived some young men—virtuous and
                brave men indeed but still men in such a peculiar condition that if they had
                obtained magistracies they would have convulsed the constitution of the republic of
                the opportunity of canvassing the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By my patience and complaisant conduct I
                propitiated Antonius my colleague eager for a province, and cherishing many designs
                injurious to the republic. I in the public assembly renounced the province of
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, fully equipped and well appointed
                with an army and with funds by the authority of the senate, which I had taken in
                exchange from Antonius, because I thought it advantageous to the republic at that
                time that I should do so in spite of the outcry raised by the Roman people against
                my doing so. I ordered Lucius Catiline planning not obscurely, but openly, the
                slaughter of the senate and the destruction of the city, to depart from the city in
                order that you might be protected by our walls from his designs from which our laws
                were insufficient to defend us. I wrested from the nefarious hands of the
                conspirators the weapons which in the last month of my consulship were aimed at the
                throats of the citizens. I seized, and brought to light and extinguished the
                firebrands which were already kindled for the conflagration of the city. <milestone
                    n="3" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="6" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Quintus Catulus the chief of this body the great leader of the public council, in the
                fullest possible house, called me the father of my country. This most illustrious
                man, who is at this moment sitting close to you, Lucius Gellius, in the hearing of
                all these people, said that a civic crown was owed to me by the republic.<note
                    anchored="true">A civic crown was given to those who had saved the life of a
                    citizen.</note> Though I was only clad in the garb of peace, the senate, by an
                unprecedented sort of supplication, opened the temples of the gods in my <pb n="346"
                /> honour; not because I had successfully governed the republic, that being a
                compliment which had been paid to many, but because I had saved it, that being an
                honour which has never been conferred on any one. When in the assembly of the
                people, on giving up my office, I was prevented saying what I had intended by the
                tribune of the people, and when he would only allow me to take the oath, I swore
                without any hesitation that the republic and this city had been saved by my single
                exertions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On that day, the entire Roman people
                gave me in that assembly, not a congratulation to be remembered for the rest of the
                day, but they gave me immortality and eternal glory, when they themselves swearing
                also, with one voice and consent approved of my oath couched in such proud and
                triumphant words. And on that occasion, my return home from the forum was of such a
                nature that there did not appear to be a single citizen who was not in my train. And
                my consulship was conducted throughout in such a manner, that I did nothing without
                the advice of the senate,—nothing without the approbation of the Roman people; that
                in the <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign> I constantly defended the senate,—in
                the senate-house I was the unwearied advocate of the people; that in that manner, I
                united the multitude with the chief men, and the equestrian order with the senate. I
                have now briefly described my consulship. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="8" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Dare now, O you Fury to describe yours; the beginning of which was the Compitalitian
                games, then first celebrated since the time that Lucius Metellus and Quintus Marcius
                were consuls, contrary to the inclination of this order: games which Quintus
                Metellus (I am doing injury to a gallant man who is dead when I compare him, to whom
                this city has produced few equals, to this ill-omened beast)—but he, being consul
                elect when a certain tribune of the people, relying on his own power, had ordered
                the master of the games to celebrate them in contempt of a resolution passed by the
                senate, though still a private individual, forbade it to be done, and he carried
                that point by the weight of his character, which he had not as yet any power to
                enforce. You, when the day of the Compitalitia<note anchored="true">The <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">compitalicii ludi</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >compitalia</foreign>, as they are called a few lines after, were a festival
                    celebrated once a year in honour of the <foreign xml:lang="la">lares
                        compitales</foreign>, to whom sacrifices were offered at places where two
                    ways met. It is said to have been instituted by Tarquinius Priscus, in honour of
                    the birth of Servius Tullius, and Tarquinius Superbus is said to have sacrificed
                    boys at them to Mania the mother of the Lares; but after his expulsion this
                    custom was abolished, and the offerings were garlic and poppies. The exact day
                    on which the games were celebrated varied, but it was always in the winter. In
                    one of Cicero's letters to Atticus, (<bibl n="Cic. Att. 7.7.1">vii. 7,</bibl>)
                    he speaks of them as falling one year on the second of January. According to
                    some editions the proper reading here is the thirtieth of December. Smith, Dict.
                    Ant. p.279, v. <foreign xml:lang="la">Compitolia</foreign>.</note> had fallen on
                the first <pb n="347"/> of January, permitted Sextus Clodius, who had never before
                filled any office which entitled him to wear the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >pratetexta</foreign>, to celebrate the games, and to strut about in a <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">praetexta</foreign> like a profligate man, as he was, a man
                thoroughly worthy of your countenance and regard. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                Therefore, when you had laid this foundation of your consulship, three days after,
                while you were looking on in silence, the Aelian and Fufian law, that bulwark and
                wall of tranquillity and peace, was overturned by Publius Clodius, that fatal
                prodigy and monster of the republic. Not only the guilds which the senate had
                abolished were restored but countless new ones were established of all the dregs of
                the city and even of slaves. The same man, immersed in unheard of and impious
                debaucheries, abolished that old preceptress of modesty and charity, the severity of
                the censor, while you in the mean time, you sepulchre of the republic, you who say
                that you were at that time consul at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>,
                never by one single word intimated any opinion of your own amid such a terrible
                shipwreck of the state. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="10"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I have not yet said what you did yourself, but only what you allowed to be done. Nor
                does it make much difference, especially in a consul whether he himself harnesses
                the republic with pernicious laws mid infamous harangues, or allows others to harass
                it. Can there be any excuse for a consul, I will not say being disaffected to the
                state, but sitting with his hands before him dawdling and sleeping amid the greatest
                commotions of the republic? For nearly a hundred years had we possessed the Aelian
                and Fufian law; for four hundred years had we enjoyed the censor's power of deciding
                on, and animadverting on, the conduct of citizens; laws which I will not say no
                wicked man has ever dared to uproot, but which no one has ever been able to uproot,
                a power which no one, not if he were ever so profligate has ever attempted to
                diminish so as to <pb n="348"/> prevent a formal judgment from being passed every
                fifth year on our morals. </p>
            <p><milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These things now, O worst of men, are entombed in
                the bosom of your consulship. Proceed on to the days which followed their funeral
                obsequies. In front of the tribunal of Aurelius, while you were not only shutting
                your eyes to the measure, which of itself would have been wicked enough, but while
                you were looking on with a more delighted countenance than usual, a levy of slaves
                was had by that man who never considered anything too infamous for him either to say
                or to do. Arms (O you betrayer of all temples) were placed in the temples of Castor
                by that robber, while you were looking on, to whom that temple, while you were
                consul, was a citadel for profligate citizens,—a receptacle for the veteran soldiers
                of Catiline,—a castle for forensic robbery, and the sepulchre of all law and of all
                religion. Not only my house, but the whole <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine
                    Hill</placeName>, was crowded by the senate, by Roman knights, by the entire
                city, by the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, while you not
                only never once came near that Cicero (for I omit all mention of domestic
                circumstances, which perhaps you would deny, and speak only of those facts which
                were done openly and are notorious)—you never, I say, came near that Cicero to whom
                all the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> in which you were elected consul
                had given the first tablet of the prerogative tribe, but who in the senate was the
                third person whose opinion you asked; but more, you were present, yes, and you
                presided in the most cruel manner, over all the counsels which were entertained for
                the purpose of crushing me. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="12"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But what was it that you dared to say to me myself, in the presence of my son-in-law,
                your own relation? “That Gabinius was a beggar, without either house or property;
                that he could not exist if he did not obtain a province; that you had hopes from a
                tribune of the people, if you united your plans to his; that you had no hope at all
                from the senate; that you were complying with his covetousness as I had done in the
                case of my colleague; that there was no reason why I should implore the protection
                of the consuls; that every one ought to take care of his own interests.” And these
                things I scarcely venture to say. I am afraid that there may be some one who does
                not clearly see his enormous wickedness, concealed as it is under his impenetrable
                countenance; still I <pb n="349"/> will say it: he himself, at all events, will
                recognise the truth, and will feel some pain in recollecting his crimes. <milestone
                    n="13" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Do you recollect you infamous fellow, when about the fifth hour of the day I came to
                you with Caius Piso, that you came out of some hovel or other with your head wrapped
                up, and in slippers? and when you, with that fetid breath of yours, had filled us
                with the odour of that vile cookshop, that you made the excuse of your health,
                because you said that you were compelled to have recourse to some vinous remedies?
                and when we had admitted the pretence, (for what could we do?) we stood a little
                while amid the fumes and smell of your gluttony, till you drove us away by filthy
                language and still more filthy behaviour? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>About two days afterwards you were brought forward in the assembly of the people by
                that man with whom you had shared your consulship in that manner; and when you were
                asked what were your sentiments respecting my consulship, you, a very grave
                authority, some Calatinus, I suppose, or Africanus, or Maximus, surely not a
                Caesoninus half-Placentian Calventius, make answer, lifting one eyebrow up to your
                forehead, and depressing the other down to your chin, “that you did not approve of
                its entirety.” <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>On this, that noble man, so exceedingly worthy of being admitted into your counsels,
                praised you. Do you, then, you scoundrel, do you as consul condemn the senate for
                cruelty before an assembly of the people? For you are not condemning one who only
                obeyed the senate;—for that salutary and diligent report of the conspiracy was the
                work of the consul; the sentence and the punishment were the act of the senate. And
                when you find fault with them, you show what sort of consul you would have been at
                that time, if by chance it had so happened. You, I make no doubt would have
                considered that Catiline deserved to be aided with pay and provisions. For, what was
                the difference between Catiline and that man to whom you sold the authority of the
                senate, the safety of the state, and the whole republic, for the reward of a
                province? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For the consuls assisted Clodius while
                doing those very things which Catiline was only attempting when I as consul defeated
                his machinations. He, indeed, wished to massacre the senate; you two abolished it.
                He wished to destroy the laws by fire and sword; you two abrogated them. <pb n="350"
                /> He wished the country to perish; you two aided him. What, during your consulship,
                was ever accomplished except by force of arms? That band of conspirators wished to
                fire the city; you two sought to burn the house of that man, to whom it was owing
                that the city was not burnt. And even these men, if they had a consul like you,
                would never have thought of burning the city: For they did not wish to deprive
                themselves of their homes; but as long as those consuls flourished, they thought
                that there would be no home for their wickedness. They desired the slaughter of the
                citizens; you desired to bring them to slavery; and in this were even more cruel
                than they; for, until your consulship, the spirit of liberty was so deeply implanted
                in this people, that they would have thought it preferable to die rather than to
                become slaves. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But that pair of you, acting on
                the designs of Catiline and Lentulus, expelled me from my house, and confined Cnaeus
                Pompeius to his; for they did not think that as long as I stood firm, and remained
                in the city exerting all my vigilance for its defence, and as long as Cnaeus
                Pompeius, the conqueror of all the world, opposed them, they should ever be able
                utterly to destroy the republic. You sought even to inflict punishment on me, by
                which you might make atonement to the shades of the dead conspirators. You poured
                forth upon me all the hatred which had been long nursed in the wicked feelings of
                impious men. And if I had not yielded for a while to their frenzy, I should have
                been murdered in the tomb of Catiline, under your leadership. But what greater proof
                do you want that there is no real difference between you and Catiline, than is the
                fact, that you awakened again that same band from the half-dead relics of Catiline's
                army? that you collected all abandoned men from all quarters? that you let loose
                against me the dregs of the prisons? that you armed conspirators? that you sought to
                expose my person and the lives of all good men to their frenzy and to their swords?
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="17" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But I come back now to that splendid harangue of yours. You are the man who
                disapprove of cruelty, are you? you who, when the senate had decided on displaying
                its grief and indignation by a change of their garments, and when you saw that the
                whole republic was grieving in the mourning of its most honourable order, you, O
                merciful man, what do you <pb n="351"/> do? Why, what no tyrant in any country of
                barbarians ever dreamt of. For, I say nothing of the fact of a consul issuing an
                edict, that the senate should not obey a resolution of the senate; an action than
                which none more shameful can either be done or imagined. I return to the merciful
                disposition of that man, who thinks that the senate were over cruel in preserving
                the country. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> He with his mate—whom however he was
                desirous to surpass in all vices—dared to issue an edict that the senate should
                return to its usual dress contrary to the resolution which that body itself had
                passed. What tyrant in any part of <placeName key="tgn,6005315">Scythia</placeName>
                ever behaved in such a way as not to permit those men to mourn whom he was loading
                with misery? You leave them their grief, you take away the emblems of grief, you
                take away their tears not by comforting them but by threatening them. But even if
                the conscript fathers had changed their attire not in consequence of any public
                resolution, but out of private affection or pity still it would have been an
                intolerable stretch of power that your interdict should prohibit them from doing so;
                but when the senate in a full house had passed a resolution to that effect, and all
                the other orders in the state had already changed their attire, then you, a consul,
                dragged out of a dark dirty cookshop, with that shaved dancing girl of yours,
                forbade the senate of the Roman people to mourn for the setting and death of the
                republic. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But a little time before, he even asked me what need I had of his assistance? why I
                had not resisted my enemies with my own resources? Just as if not only I who had
                often been of assistance to many others, but as if any one were ever in so wholly
                desperate a condition as to consider himself not only safer if he had that man for a
                protector but more ready for the struggle if he had him only for an advocate or
                seconder. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Was I, forsooth, anxious to lean on the
                counsel or protection of that piece of senseless cattle, of that bit of rotten
                flesh? was I likely to seek for any support or ornament for myself from that
                contemptible carcass? I suppose I was looking for a consul, I say, but one (that I
                was not likely to find in that hog) who might uphold the cause of the republic with
                his dignity and wisdom, not one who like a stock or like a trunk of a tree, if he
                only stood upright, might maintain the title of consul. For as the whole of my cause
                was the cause of a consul and of the senate, I had need of the assistance of the <pb
                    n="302"/> consul and senate; one of which sources of aid was even turned by you
                when you were consuls to my injury; the other was entirely suspended, if not
                abolished in the republic. </p>
            <p>But if you ask what were my intentions; I would not have yielded, and the republic
                should still have retained me in its embrace, if I had only had to contend with
                contemptible gladiators,<note anchored="true">The Latin is <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >bustuarius</foreign>; literally, one who fights at the funeral pile in
                    honour of the dead.</note> and with you, and with your colleague. For the cause
                of that most admirable man Quintus Metellus was a wholly different one; a citizen
                whom, in my opinion, I consider equal in glory to the immortal gods; <milestone
                    n="20" unit="section"/> who thought it best for him to leave the city in order
                to avoid a contest with Caius Marius—a most gallant man, a consul, yes, a man who
                had been consul six times—and with his invincible legions. For what contest like
                this lay before me? Should I have had to fight with Caius Marius or with any one
                like him, or rather with one consul who was a sort of barbarian Epicurus, and with
                the other, a mere hut-boy of Catiline's? I was not, in truth, afraid of your
                supercilious looks, or of the cymbals and castanets of your colleague; nor was I so
                nervous, after having guided the vessel of the state amid the most terrible storms
                and billows of the republic, and placed it safe in harbour, as to fear the little
                cloud which gathered on your brow, or the polluted breath of your colleague. </p>
            <p>They were other gales which I beheld threatening; they were other storms which my
                mind foresaw; <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> and I did not so much yield to
                those other storms which were impending, but rather exposed myself alone to them to
                secure the safety of all the rest of the citizens. </p>
            <p>Accordingly at that time, on my departure, all those wicked swords fell from the
                hands of those most cruel men; when you, O senseless and insane man,—while all good
                men shut themselves up and hid themselves out of grief, and lamented for the
                temples, and bewailed the very houses of the city,—you, I say, embraced that fatal
                monster, the progeny of nefarious licentiousness, and civil bloodshed, and the
                foulness or every sort of wickedness, and the impunity of every crime; and in the
                same temple, at that very same time and in the very same place, you forbade the
                senate to express its opinion not only on my destruction, but on that of their
                country. <pb n="353"/>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="22" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Why need I speak of the banquets of those days, why of your joy and
                self-congratulation, why of your most intemperate drinking-bouts with your crew of
                infamous companions? Who in those days ever saw you sober, who ever saw you doing
                any thing which was worthy of a freeman; who, in short, ever saw you in public at
                all? while the house of your colleague was resounding with song and cymbals, and
                while he himself was dancing naked at banquets; in which even then, when he was
                going round in the circle of the dance, he seemed to have no fear of any revolution
                of fortune. But this man, who is not quite so refined in gluttony nor so musical,
                lay stupefied amid the reeking orgies of his Greek crew. The banquets celebrated by
                that fellow at the time of all this misery of the republic, resembled what is
                reported of the feast of the Centaurs and Lapithae; and it is quite impossible to
                tell in what sort of debauchery he indulged to the most disgraceful excess. </p>
            <p>Will you dare to make mention of your consulship? will you dare to say that you ever
                were consul at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>? <milestone n="23"
                    unit="section"/> What? do you think that the consulship consists in being
                attended by lictors and in wearing the <foreign xml:lang="la">toga
                    praetexta</foreign>? ornaments which, while you were consul you wished to belong
                also to Sextus Clodius. And do you, O you dog of Clodius's, think that the
                consulship consists wholly in the possession of these insignia? A consul ought to be
                a consul in courage, in wisdom, in good faith, in dignity, in vigilance, in
                prudence, in performing all the labours and duties of the consulship, and above all
                things—as, indeed, the name of the magistracy itself points out—in consulting the
                interests of the republic. Am I to think that man a consul who thought that the
                senate had no existence in the republic? and am I to account him a consul, who takes
                no heed of that great council without which, even in the time of the kingly power,
                the kings could not have any existence at <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName>? But I pass over all those points. When a levy of slaves was
                being held in the forum; when arms were in open daylight being carried to the temple
                of Castor; and when that temple, having its doors thrown down and its steps torn up,
                was occupied by the remnant of the conspirators, and by the man who had once been a
                pretended accuser of Catiline, but who now was seeking to be his avenger; when Roman
                knights were being banished; when <pb n="353"/> virtuous men were being driven with
                stones out of the forum; when the senate were prevented not only from assisting the
                republic, but even from mourning over it; when that citizen, whom this venerable
                body, with the assent of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> and all the
                nations of the earth, had styled the saviour of his country, was being driven away
                without a trial, in a manner contrary to all law, contrary to all precedent, by
                slaves and an armed mob;—I will not say, with your assistance (though I might say
                that with truth), but certainly without your lifting up your voice against it;—will
                any one believe that there were any consuls at all at to me at that time? <milestone
                    n="24" unit="section"/> Who, then, are robbers, if you were consuls? Who can be
                called pirates, or enemies, or traitors, or tyrants? <milestone n="11"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Great, O senators, is the name, great is the honour, great is the dignity, great is
                the majesty of a consul. Your narrow mind, O Piso, your paltry soul, your spiritless
                heart, is unable to comprehend that greatness. The weakness of your intellect cannot
                grasp it; your inexperience of prosperity cannot support so dignified, so solemn a
                character. Seplasia,<note anchored="true">The Seplasia was a street at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, full of perfumers and hairdressers,
                    and much frequented.</note> in truth, as I heard said, the moment that it beheld
                you, refused to acknowledge you as the consul of <placeName key="tgn,7003005"
                    >Campania</placeName>. It had heard of the Decii, of the Magii, it knew
                something also about Jubellius Taurea; and if those men did not display all the
                moderation which is usually found in our consuls, at all events there was a pomp
                about them, there was a magnificence, there was a gait and behaviour worthy of
                Seplasia and of <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>. <milestone n="25"
                    unit="section"/> Indeed, if those perfumers had beheld your colleague Gabinius
                as their duumviri; <note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="la">Duumvir</foreign>
                    was the title of the chief magistrate in the colonies and municipal towns in
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>.</note> they would sooner
                have acknowledged him. He at least had carefully-dressed hair, and perfumed fringes
                of curls, and anointed and carefully-rouged cheeks, worthy of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>,—of <placeName key="perseus,Capua"
                    >Capua</placeName>, I mean, such as it used to be. For the <placeName
                    key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> that now is is full of most excellent
                characters, of most gallant men, of most virtuous citizens, and of men most friendly
                and devoted to me; not one of whom ever saw you at <placeName key="perseus,Capua"
                    >Capua</placeName> clad in your <foreign xml:lang="la">praetexta</foreign>
                without groaning out of regret for me, by whose counsels they recollected that the
                whole republic and that city in particular had been preserved. <pb n="355"/> They
                had paid me the honour of a gilded statue; they had adopted me as their especial
                patron; they considered that it was owing to me that they were still enjoying their
                lives, their fortunes, and their children; they had defended me when I was present
                against your piratical attacks, by their decrees, and by their deputations; and when
                I was absent they recalled me, when that great man Cnaeus Pompeius submitted the
                motion to them, and tore the weapons of your wickedness out of the body or the
                republic. </p>
            <p><milestone n="26" unit="section"/> Were you consul when my house on the <placeName
                    key="tgn,3000935">Palatine Hill</placeName> was set on fire, not by any accident
                but by men applying fire brands to it at your inspiration? Was there ever before any
                conflagration of any great extent or importance in the city without the consul
                coming to bring assistance? But you at that very time were sitting in the house of
                your mother in law, close to my house; you had opened her house to receive the
                plunder of mine; you were sitting there not for the purpose of extinguishing, but as
                the originator of the fire and you—I may almost say—were yourself as consul
                supplying burning firebrands to the Furies of Clodius's party. <milestone n="12"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And all the rest of the year did any one consider you as consul? Did any one obey
                you? Did any one ever rise up to show respect to you when you came into the senate
                house? Did any one ever think it worth his while to answer you when you asked his
                opinion? In short, is that year at all to be counted in the republic when the senate
                was mute, the courts of justice silent,—when all good men were mourning, when the
                violence of your troops of banditti was raging over the whole city, and when not one
                citizen only had departed from the city, but when the city itself had yielded to the
                wickedness and frenzy of you and Gabinius? <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But even then, O you impious Caesoninus, you did not emerge from the miserable
                vileness of your nature, when after a time the reawakened virtue of a most
                illustrious man quickly demanded the restoration of one who was his own true friend,
                and a citizen who had deserved well of the state, and of the ancient customs and
                principles of the republic. Nor would that great man permit the pestilence of your
                wickedness to remain any longer in that republic, which he himself had embellished
                and whose power he had extended. But when that Gabinius, such as he is, a man who is
                surpassed <pb n="350"/> in infamy by you alone, recollected himself,—with
                difficulty, indeed, but still he did recollect himself,—he contended against his
                dear friend Clodius, at first only feignedly, then very unwillingly, but at last
                with genuine ardour and vehemence, in support of Cnaeus Pompeius. And in that
                spectacle the impartiality of the Roman people was very admirable. It looked on like
                a master of gladiators, and whichever of them perished, it thought would he an equal
                advantage to itself; but if both fell, that indeed would be a most heavenly
                blessing. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/> But still your colleague did do
                something. He upheld the austerity of a most admirable man. He was himself a wicked
                man; he was a mere ruffian and gladiator himself; but still he was fighting against
                one who was as wicked and as much a gladiator and ruffian as himself. You, forsooth,
                religious and conscientious man that you were, were reluctant to violate the treaty
                which you had ratified in my blood concerning the bargain made about the provinces.
                For that fellow, the adulterer with his own sister, had made this bargain for
                himself, that if he gave you a province, if he gave you an army, if he gave you
                money torn from the very life-blood of the republic, you were to give yourself up to
                him as his partner and assistant in all his crimes. Therefore, in that tumult the
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">fasces</foreign> were broken; you yourself were wounded;
                every day there were weapons, stonings, and banishments. At last a man was arrested
                close to the senate, armed with a sword, who it was notorious had been placed there
                for the purpose of assassinating Pompeius. <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="29" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Did any one all that time hear, not only of any act of yours, or of any report of
                yours to the senate of all these transactions, but of even any word at all uttered
                by you on the subject or of any complaint of yours? Do you think that you were
                consul at that time, you, during whose period of authority the man who, by means of
                the authority of the senate, had saved the republic, and who in <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> had united all parties of all nations by the
                celebration of three triumphs, made up his mind that he could not appear in public
                with safety? Were you and your colleague consuls at that time when, if you ever
                ventured to say one word on any subject or to submit any motion whatever to the
                senate, the whole body raised an outcry against you, and declared that you should do
                nothing whatever till you had first made a motion <pb n="357"/> concerning me and my
                affairs? and when you both, though in fact you were fettered by your treaty with
                that man, still said that you were anxious to do so, but that were hindered by the
                law? <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>A law which even to private individuals seemed to be no law at all, having been
                framed by slaves, posted up by violence, carried by piratical fury when the senate
                was driven away when all virtuous men had been frightened from the forum when the
                republic had been taken by storm in violation of all laws whatever, and which was
                drawn up in violation of every precedent; were men who said that they were afraid of
                that law, consuls? could, I will not say the minds of men, but could any records or
                annals even style them such? For even if you did not consider that a law, which was
                contrary to all law, being the proscription by the mere power of a tribune of a
                citizen who had never been condemned, and the deprivation of his rights and the
                confiscation of his property, but nevertheless were held fast by the agreement which
                you had made; who would consider you to have been then, not only consuls, but even
                free men at all, when your minds were hampered by a bribe, your tongues padlocked by
                wages? But if, on the other hand, you, being the only people in the state who did
                so, did consider that a law; can any one think that you were consuls then, or that
                you are men of consular rank now, you who are ignorant of the laws, and principles,
                and usages, and rights of that state in which you wish to be accounted some of the
                chief citizens? <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>When you were going in your robes as generals into those—provinces which you had
                (shall I say bought or stolen?) did any one consider you consuls? Therefore, I
                imagine, even if men did abstain from escorting you on your departure from the city
                with a numerous attendance to pay you a compliment and do honour to you, at all
                events they followed you with their good wishes as consuls, but with curses as
                enemies or traitors. <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Did you, O you most horrible and foul monster! dare also to speak of that departure
                of mine,—that evidence or your wickedness and cruelty,—as if it were a subject for
                your abuse and insult? And when you did so, then, O conscript fathers, I received an
                immortal reward of your attachment to, and favourable opinion of me,—when you
                crushed <pb n="358"/> the frenzy and insolence of that abject and frightened man,
                not only with a murmur, but with a loud and indignant outcry. <milestone n="32"
                    unit="section"/> Will you speak of the mourning of the senate,—the regret of the
                equestrian order,—the universal sadness of <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>,—the silence of the senate-house, which lasted the whole
                year,—the uninterrupted vacation of the courts of justice and the forum,—and all the
                other circumstances of that time, as grounds for abuse of me? They were the wounds
                which my departure inflicted on the republic. And if my departure had been ever so
                full of calamity, still it would have been deserving of pity rather than of insult;
                and it would have been considered as connected with my glory rather than with any
                reproach; and it would have been accounted my misfortune only, but your crime and
                wickedness. </p>
            <p>But when,—(perhaps this thing which I am about to say may appear a strange thing to
                you to hear, but still I will certainly say what I feel to be true,)—when I, O
                conscript fathers, have had such kindnesses and such honours conferred on me by you,
                I not only do not consider that a calamity, but, if I could have any feeling
                whatever unconnected with the interests of the republic, (which is hardly possible,)
                I should consider it, as far as my private interests were concerned, a fortune
                greatly to be wished for and desired by me. <milestone n="33" unit="section"/> And,
                if I may compare that day which was most joyful to you with that one which was most
                sorrowful to me, which do you think most desirable to a virtuous and wise man,—to
                depart from his country in such a manner that all his fellow-citizens pray for his
                safety, for his preservation, and for his return, which happened to me; or, (which
                happened to you when you left the city,) to depart in such a way that every one
                should curse him, should pray for harm to him, and should wish that that road might
                be his only one? I call the gods to witness, that if I were so hated by all
                mortals,—especially if I were so justly and deservedly hated,—I should think any
                banishment whatever preferable to any province that could be given to me. <milestone
                    n="15" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But to proceed. If that most disturbed period, when I was forced to depart from the
                city, is superior to the time of your greatest triumph, why need I compare our other
                circumstances, which in your case were all full of disgrace, and in mine of dignity?
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/> On the first day of January,—that <pb n="359"
                /> first day of hope which dawned on the republic after my setting and eclipse,—the
                senate, in a very full house, amid a crowd gathered together from all <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, on the motion of a most illustrious man,
                Publius Lentulus, with one voice and one consent pronounced my recall. The same
                senate recommended me to all foreign nations, and to all our own magistrates and
                lieutenants, by its authority and by letters under the hand of the consuls, not (as
                you, you Insubrian, have dared to say) an exile from my country, but (as the senate
                itself styled me at the very time) a citizen who had been the saviour of the
                republic. The senate thought it right to implore, by the voice and letters of the
                consul, the assistance of all the citizens in all <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>, who were desirous of securing the safety of the republic to
                assist also in promoting the safety of me, a single individual. For the sake of the
                preservation of my life and rights, the whole of Italy assembled at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> at one time, as if in obedience to a signal
                which had been given. <milestone n="35" unit="section"/> Concerning my safety most
                magnificent and admirable speeches were made by Publius Lentulus a most excellent
                man and a most admirable consul by Cnaeus Pompeius, that most illustrious and
                invincible citizen, and by the other leading men of the city, and concerning me the
                senate passed a resolution, at the instigation and on the especial motion of Cnaeus
                Pompeius, that if any one hindered my return in any manner, he should be considered
                as an enemy of the state, and the authoritative opinion of the senate concerning me
                was declared in such language that no triumph was ever decreed to any one in a more
                complimentary or more honourable manner than that in which my safety and restoration
                to my country was provided for. </p>
            <p>When all the magistrates had concurred in the law respecting me, with the exception
                of one praetor from whom it was not reasonable to ask it as he was the brother of my
                great enemy, and with the exception also of two tribunes of the people, who had been
                bought like slaves,<note anchored="true">The Latin is <foreign xml:lang="la">de
                        lapide emptos</foreign>, the <foreign xml:lang="la">lapis</foreign> being a
                    raised stone on which the <foreign xml:lang="la">praeco</foreign> or auctioneer
                    stood when slaves were sold with reference to which Plautus says: <quote
                        xml:lang="la">
                        <l>O stulte, stulte! nescis nunc venire te, </l>
                        <l>In eo ipso slas lapide ubi praeco praedicat.</l>
                    </quote></note> then Publius Lentulus the consul passed a law concerning me in
                the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia centuriata</foreign>, <pb n="360"/>acting with
                the consent of his colleague, Quintus Metellus, whom the same republic, which had
                alienated us from one another in his tribuneship, reconciled to me again in his
                consulship, in consequence of the virtue of one most excellent and most sensible
                man. <milestone n="36" unit="section"/> And why need I tell you how that law was
                received? I hear from you yourselves that no pretext was admitted in the case of any
                one whatever as sufficiently reasonable to excuse him from being present; that at no
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> that ever were held was there either a
                more numerous or a more respectable number of men assembled; and this I can
                certainly see for myself,—what the public records prove,—that you were the movers of
                the vote, that you were the distributors and keepers of the voting tablets,—and that
                you did of your own accord for the sake of ensuring my safety, though no one
                requested you to do so, what, when the honours of your own relations are at stake,
                you avoid doing under the plea either of your age, or of your rank. <milestone
                    n="16" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="37" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Compare, now, my fine Epicurus, brought forward out of his sty, not out of his
                school,—compare, if you dare, your absence with mine. You obtained a consular
                province with no other limitations than those which the law of your covetousness,
                not the law of your son-in-law, had agreed upon. For by that most just and admirable
                law of Caesar free nations were really and truly free; but by that law which no one
                except you and your colleague considered a law at all, all <placeName
                    key="tgn,7002733">Achaia</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,7001399"
                    >Thessaly</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                >Athens</placeName>,—in short the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                    >Greece</placeName>, was made over to you. You had an army, not of that strength
                which the senate or people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> had
                assigned to you, but such as your own lust had prompted you to enlist. You had
                entirely drained the treasury. <milestone n="38" unit="section"/> Well, what
                exploits did you perform in this command, with this army, and in this consular
                province? I ask, O conscript fathers, what exploits he performed. A man who, the
                moment he arrived—(I am not yet speaking of his acts of rapine, I am not yet
                speaking of the sums of money which he extorted, or seized, or levied, nor of his
                slaughter of our allies, nor of his murders of his own friends, nor of his perfidy,
                nor of his inhumanity, nor of his wicked actions: presently, if you choose to hear
                me, I will argue with him as with a thief, as with a robber of temples, as with an
                assassin; but for the present I am only <pb n="361"/> going to compare my own
                fortune when stripped of everything, with that of that great commander when at the
                height of prosperity.) Who ever had any province with a fine army without sending
                some letters recounting his achievements, to the senate? But who ever had so
                important a province as that, with so splendid an army? who ever had <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> of all provinces—a land which has on its
                borders so many tribes of barbarians that the commanders in <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> have always had only just those
                boundaries of their province which were also the boundaries of their swords and
                javelins,—without sending such letters? Letters! why, not only several men who have
                had only praetorian authority have triumphed, but there is not one single instance
                of any man who had exercised consular authority in that province returning in health
                and vigour, without celebrating a triumph for his achievements performed in that
                command. It is quite a new thing; this which I am going to mention is newer still.
                This vulture of that province—(hear it, O ye gods) has been styled <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>! <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="39" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And did you not even then, my great Paullus,<note anchored="true">He refers here to
                    the great victory of Paullus Aemilius, which was gained in this country over
                    Perseus at <placeName key="perseus,Pydna">Pydna</placeName>.</note> dare to send
                expresses to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> crowned with laurel?
                Yes, says he, I sent them. Did you? Who ever read them? who ever demanded to have
                them read? For it makes no difference, as far as my argument is concerned, whether
                you, being overwhelmed by the consciousness of your wicked actions, never dared to
                write any letters to that body which you had treated with contempt, which you had
                ill-treated, which you had sought to destroy, or whether your friends concealed your
                letters, and by their silence expressed their condemnation of your rashness and
                audacity. And I do not know whether I should not prefer that you should appear so
                utterly destitute of all shame as to have sent the letters, and that your friends
                should appear to have had more modesty and more sense than yourself, rather than
                that you should seem to have had some little modesty, and that your conduct should
                not have been condemned by the judgment of your friends. <milestone n="40"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But even if you had not shut the senate-house against yourself for ever by your
                nefarious insults to this order, still, what exploit was ever performed or achieved
                by you in that <pb n="362"/> province, concerning which it would have been becoming
                for you to have written to the senate in the war of congratulation? Was it the way
                in which <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> was harassed? or the
                shameful loss of the towns? or the manner in which the allies were plundered? or the
                devastation of the lands? or the fortifying of <placeName key="tgn,7011182"
                    >Thessalonica</placeName>? or the occupation of our military road? or the
                destruction of our army by sword and famine, and cold and pestilence? But you who
                did not write any account of anything to the senate, as in the city you were
                discovered to be more worthless than Gabinius, so in your province you turned out
                somewhat more inactive than even he. <milestone n="41" unit="section"/> For that
                gulf of all things—that glutton, born for his own belly, not for glory or
                renown,—when he had deprived the Roman knights in his province; when be had deprived
                the farmers of the revenue, men united to us by mutual goodwill and in dignity;—when
                he had deprived, I say, all of them of their fortunes, many of them of their
                franchises and of their lives; when with that mighty army he had done nothing except
                plunder the cities, lay waste the lands, and drain the private houses of his
                province, dared (for what will he not dare?) to send letters at last to the senate
                to demand a supplication! <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>O ye immortal gods! Do you, do you,—you two whirlpools and rocks which endanger the
                republic—do you seek to disparage my fortune? to extol your own? when concerning me
                in my absence such resolutions of the senate were passed, such speeches were
                delivered, such agitation pervaded all the municipal towns and colonies, such votes
                were passed by all the farmers of the revenue, by all the different guilds, by all
                ranks and classes of the citizens, as I should not only never have dared to hope
                for, but as I could not possibly hare dreamt of; and while you, on the other hand,
                have met with the everlasting brand of the deepest infamy. <milestone n="42"
                    unit="section"/> Should I, if I were to see you and Gabinius both nailed to a
                cross, feel greater rejoicing at the laceration of your bodies, than I do at the
                tearing to pieces of your reputations? Surely not: for there is no punishment
                imaginable, which, owing to some accident or other, even virtuous and brave men may
                not have inflicted on them. And this is what even your Greek followers of pleasure
                say; men whom I wish you would listen to in the spirit in which they deserve to be
                listened to; you would <pb n="363"/> never have immersed yourself in such a vortex
                of wickedness. But you listen to them in brothels, in scenes of adultery, in
                reveling and drunkenness. </p>
            <p>But they themselves those very men who define evil by pain, and good by pleasure say
                that the wise man even if he were shut up in Phalaris's bull and roasted by fire
                being placed under him would still say that it was pleasant and would not allow
                himself to be moved the least from his assertion. They insist upon it that the power
                of virtue is so great that it is absolutely impossible for a virtuous man ever to be
                otherwise than happy. <milestone n="43" unit="section"/> What then is punishment?
                what is chastisement? A thing which in my opinion, can happen to no one unless he is
                guilty; it is dishonesty undertaken; it is a mind hampered and overwhelmed by
                conscience; it is the hatred of all virtuous men; it is the deserved brand of the
                senate; it is the loss of dignity. <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Nor does that illustrious man Marcus Regulus whom the Carthaginians, having cut off
                his eyelids and bound him in a machine, killed by keeping him awake, appear to have
                had punishment inflicted on him. Nor does Caius Marius whom <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, which he had saved, saw sunk in the marshes
                of <placeName key="perseus,Minturnae">Minturnae</placeName>, and whom <placeName
                    key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, which he had subdued, beheld banished and
                shipwrecked. For those were the wounds of fortune, not of guilt, but punishment is
                the penalty of crime. Nor should I, if I were now to pray for evils to fall upon you
                as I often have done (and indeed the immortal gods have heard those prayers of
                mine,) pray for disease, or death, or tortures to befall you. That is an execution
                worthy of Thyestes, the work of a poet who wishes to affect the minds of the common
                people, not of philosophers, that you, <quote>
                    <l>Wrecked on some vast inhospitable shore </l>
                    <l>Clinging to rugged rocks, with bleeding limbs </l>
                    <l>Might trembling hang, and all the rocks defile </l>
                    <l>With gore and black pollution.</l>
                </quote>
                <milestone n="44" unit="section"/> I do not mean to say that I should be much vexed
                if such a thing were to happen but still it would be an accident such as all men are
                liable to. Marcus Marcellus, who was three times consul, a man of the most excessive
                virtue and piety and military glory was lost at sea; through his virtue he still
                lives in glory and renown. A death such as that is <pb n="364"/> to be attributed to
                fortune, not to be considered a punishment. What then is punishment? What is
                chastisement? What is stoning? What is the cross? It is punishment that there should
                be two generals in the provinces of the Roman people, that they should have armies,
                that they should be styled “<foreign xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>,” that one of
                them should be so completely cowed by the consciousness of his crimes and of his
                atrocities, as not to dare to send any letter of any sort to the senate from that
                province which was of all others the richest in triumphs. From that province that
                man, so distinguished for every sort of worth and dignity, Lucius Torquatus, was
                returning, when on account of his mighty deeds he was, on my motion, styled
                    “<foreign xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>” by the senate. In that province it
                was that those well-deserved triumphs of Cnaeus Dolabella, and Caius Curio, and
                Marcus Lucullus were earned within the last few years; and from that while you were
                the commander, no messenger whatever was ever sent to the senate. </p>
            <p>From the other consul certainly letters have been brought and read, and motions
                respecting him have been submitted to the senate. <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                O ye immortal gods, could I have desired that my chief enemy should be branded with
                such ignominy as no one ever was before? that that senate, which has now got into
                such a regular habit and practice of kindness as to confer on those who have managed
                the affairs of the republic successfully, honours hitherto unexampled, both in the
                number of days which they last and in the language in which they are decreed, should
                refuse belief to the letters of this man alone, when reporting his success, and
                should refuse him what he demanded in them? <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I feed on these facts, I am delighted, I am in ecstasies at them. I am delighted that
                this order thinks of you both as it does of its bitterest enemies; that the Roman
                knights, the other orders and the whole state detests you both; that there is no
                good man, no, and no citizen who remembers that he is a citizen, who does not shun
                you both with his eyes, reject you with his ears, scorn you in his mind, and shudder
                at the bare recollection of your consulship. <milestone n="46" unit="section"/> This
                is what I have always wished respecting you, this is what I have desired, this is
                what I have prayed for. Even more has happened than I could have desired. For, in
                truth, I never formed a wish that you should lose your armies. That has happened <pb
                    n="365"/> quite beyond my wish, though I cannot say that it has grieved me; but
                it never could have occurred to me to wish you the insanity and frenzy into which
                you have both fallen. Still it might well have been wished. But I had forgotten that
                that was the most invariable of all the punishments which were appointed by the
                immortal gods for wicked and impious men. </p>
            <p>For think not, O conscript fathers, that, as you see on the stage, wicked men are, by
                the instigation of the gods, terrified by the blazing torches of the Furies. It is
                his own dishonesty, his own crime, his own wickedness, his own audacity that
                deprives each individual of sense and discernment. These are the Furies, these the
                flames, these the firebrands which distress the impious. <milestone n="47"
                    unit="section"/> Must I not think you senseless and frantic, and out of your
                mind,—must I not think you madder than that Orestes in the tragedy, or than Athamas,
                when you dared first of all to act so, (for this is the head and front of your
                offending,) and again, a short time afterwards, when Torquatus, a most influential
                and conscientious man, pressed you openly to confess that you left <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, that province into which you had
                carried so vast an army, without one single soldier? I say nothing of your having
                lost the greater part of your army; that might be owing to your ill fortune. But
                what reason can you allege for having disbanded any part of your army? What power
                had you to do so? What law, what resolution of the senate authorized such a step?
                Where was your right to do so? What precedent was there for it? What is this but
                madness, but ignorance of men, ignorance of the laws, and of the senate, and of the
                constitution? </p>
            <p>To wound one's body is a trifle; to wound one's life, one's character, one's safety,
                like this, is a more serious business. <milestone n="48" unit="section"/> If you had
                discharged your household, a matter which would have concerned no one but yourself,
                your friends would have thought that you required to be put under restraint; could
                you have disbanded the protection of the republic, the garrison of the province,
                without the orders of the Roman senate or people, if you had been in your sound
                senses? <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Now for your colleague; he, having dissipated an enormous booty which he had acquired
                by draining the fortunes of the farmers of the revenue, and the lands and cities of
                the allies, after his insatiable lusts had swallowed some <pb n="363"/> portion of
                that booty, his new and unexampled luxury had devoured part, when part had gone in
                purchases in those districts where he plundered everything, and part had been spent
                in effecting exchanges of property for the purpose of heaping hill upon hill in this
                Tusculan estate of his; after he had become needy, and after that intolerable mass
                that he was heaping up had been interrupted and had come to a standstill,—be, I say,
                then sold himself, and his <foreign xml:lang="la">fasces</foreign>, and the army of
                the Roman people, and the oracular consent and prohibition of the immortal gods, and
                the answer of the priests, and the authority of the senate, and the commands of the
                people, and the name and dignity of the Roman empire, to the king of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. <milestone n="49" unit="section"/> Though
                he had the boundaries of his province as extensive as he had desired, as he had
                wished, as he had procured them to be, by purchasing them at the price of my
                existence as a citizen, still he could not contain himself within them; he led his
                army out of <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>. How could he lead it out
                of his province? He let himself out as a hired comrade to the king of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>. </p>
            <p>What can be more shameful than this? He came into <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                    >Egypt</placeName>. He engaged the men of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria"
                    >Alexandria</placeName> in battle. When was it that either this senatorial body
                or the Roman people undertook this war? He took <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria"
                    >Alexandria</placeName>. What else are we to expect from his frenzy, but that he
                should send letters to the senate concerning such mighty exploits? <milestone n="50"
                    unit="section"/> If he had been in his senses, if he had not been already paying
                to his country and to the immortal gods that penalty which is the most terrible of
                all, by his frenzy and insanity, would he have cared, (I say nothing of his leaving
                his province, of his taking his army out of it, of his declaring and carrying on war
                of his own accord, of his entering a foreign kingdom without any command from the
                people or from the senate to do so; conduct which many of the ancient laws, and
                especially the Cornelian law concerning treason, and the Julian law concerning
                extortion, forbid in the plainest manner; but I say nothing of all this,)—would he,
                I say, if he had not been most outrageously mad, have dared to take to himself the
                province which Publius Lentulus, a man most sincerely attached to this order, had
                abdicated from scruples of religion, though he had obtained it both by the authority
                of the senate and by lot when even if there were no religious obstacles in his case,
                still the <pb n="367"/> usage of our ancestors, and all precedents, and the severest
                penalties of the laws forbade it? <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="51" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But since we have begun to institute a comparison between our fortunes we will say no
                more of the return of Gabinius, whom, though he has cut the ground from under his
                own feet, I still wish to see to admire the impudence of the man. Let us, if you
                please, compare your return with mine. Mine was such that the whole way from
                    <placeName key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName> to <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> I was beholding one unbroken line of the
                inhabitants of all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. For there was no
                district nor municipal town, nor prefecture, nor colony, from which a deputation was
                not sent by the public authority to congratulate me. Why should I speak of my
                arrival in the different towns? why of the crowds of men who thronged out to meet
                me? why of the way in which the fathers of families with their wives and children
                gathered together to greet me? why of those days which were celebrated by every one
                on my arrival and return, as if they had been solemn festival days of the immortal
                gods? <milestone n="52" unit="section"/> That one day was to me like an immortality,
                on which I returned to my country, and saw the senate which had come forth to meet
                me, and the whole Roman people; while <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>
                itself, torn, if I may so say, from its foundations, seemed to come forward to
                embrace her saviour. <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, which received
                me in such a manner that not only all men and all women of all classes, and ages,
                and orders of society, of every fortune and every rank, but that even the walls and
                houses of the city and temples appeared to be exulting. And on the succeeding days,
                the pontiffs, the consuls, the conscript fathers, placed me in that very house from
                which you had driven me, which you had pillaged, and which you had burnt and voted
                that my house was to be built up for me again at the public expense, an honour which
                they had never paid to any one before. </p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="section"/> Now you know the circumstances of my return. Now
                compare yours with it, since, having lost your army, you have brought nothing safe
                back with you except that pristine countenance and impudence of yours. And who is
                there who knows where you first came to with those laurelled lictors of yours? What
                meanders, what turnings and windings did you thread, while seeking for the most
                solitary possible places? What municipal town saw you? What friend invited <pb
                    n="368"/> you? What entertainer beheld you? Did you not make night take the
                place of day? solitude of society? a cookshop of the town? so that you did not
                appear to be returning from <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> as a
                noble commander, but to be being brought back as a disgraced corpse? and even
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> itself was polluted by your
                arrival. <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>Alas for the disgrace of the family, I
                will not say the Calpurnian family, but the Calventian; nor will I say the disgrace
                of this city, but of the municipality of <placeName key="perseus,Placentia"
                    >Placentia</placeName>; nor of your father's family, but of your
                    breeches-wearing<note anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >braccae</foreign>, drawers or breeches, were the national costume of
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, especially of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7012209">Gallia Narbonensis</placeName>, which is called by Pliny
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">Gallia Braccata</foreign>.</note> kinsmen. How, I
                say, did you come? Who, I will not say of these men, or of the rest of the citizens,
                but who, even of your own lieutenants, came to meet you? <milestone n="54"
                    unit="section"/> For Lucius Flaccus, a man most undeserving of the disgrace of
                being your lieutenant, and more worthy of those counsels by which he was united with
                me in my consulship for the salvation of the republic, was with me when some one
                came and said that you had been seen wandering not far from the gate with your
                house. I know, too, that one of the very bravest of men, a man skillful both in war
                and in civil business, an intimate friend of mine, Quintus Marcius, one of those
                lieutenants whose “<foreign xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>” you had been called
                in battle, when you were in reality a long way off, was at the time of your arrival
                sitting quietly in his own house. <milestone n="55" unit="section"/> But why do I
                count up all the people who did not go forth to meet you? when I say that scarcely
                any one did, not even of that most officious body of candidates for office, though
                they had been repeatedly warned and requested to do so, both on that very day, and
                many days before. </p>
            <p>Short gowns were ready for the lictors at the gate, which they took, and laid aside
                their military cloaks, and so formed a new crowd to escort their chief. And in this
                manner he, the Macedonian “<foreign xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>,” returning
                home from his mighty and from his important province, after three years government,
                entered the city in such a guise that no obscure peddler ever returned home in a
                more solitary condition. And yet this is the very point on which (so ready is he to
                defend himself) he finds fault with me. When I said that he had <pb n="369"/>
                entered the city by the Caelimontane gate, that ever ready man wanted to lay me a
                wager that he had entered by the <placeName key="tgn,4012794">Esquiline</placeName>
                gate; as if I was bound to know, or as if any one of you had heard, or as if it had
                anything on earth to do with the matter, by what gate you had entered, as long as it
                was not by the triumphal one; for that is the gate which had previously always been
                open for the Macedonian proconsuls. You are the first person ever discovered who,
                having been invested with consular authority there, did not triumph on your return
                from <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>. <milestone n="24"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="56" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But you have heard, O conscript fathers, the voice of the philosopher. He has said
                that he never had any desire for a triumph. O you wickedness! you pest! you
                disgrace! when you were extinguishing the senate, and putting up for sale the
                authority of this order—when you were knocking down your own consulship to a tribune
                of the people, and overturning the republic, and betraying my privileges as a
                citizen, and my safety, for the mere bribe of a province,—if you then had no desire
                for a triumph, what is it that you will allege in your defence that you did desire
                so ardently? For I have often seen men, who appeared to me and to others to be over
                desirous of a province, veil and excuse their desire under the pretence of eagerness
                for a triumph. This is what Decimus Silanus the consul lately said before this
                order,—this is what my colleague, too, stated. Nor is it possible for any one to
                desire an army, and openly to demand one, without putting forward as his pretext for
                such a demand his desire of a triumph. <milestone n="57" unit="section"/> But if the
                senate and people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> had compelled
                you (when you did not desire it, or though you even endeavoured to avoid it) to
                undertake a war and to command an army still it would have been the act of a narrow
                and mean spirit to despise the honour and dignity of a well earned triumph. For as
                it is a proof of a trifling character to catch at such praise as is derived from
                empty reports, and to hunt after all the shadows of even false glory; so it is
                surely a sign of a very worthless disposition, of one that hates all light and all
                respectability, to reject true glory, which is the most honourable reward of genuine
                virtue. But when the senate was so far from requesting and compelling you to take
                this charge upon you, that it was only unwillingly and under compulsion that it
                allowed you to do <pb n="370"/> so; when, not only did the Roman people betray no
                eagerness that you should do so, but not one single freeman voted for it; when that
                province was your wages for having, I will not say overturned, but utterly destroyed
                the constitution, and when this covenant ran through all your wicked actions, that
                if you handed over the whole republic to nefarious robbers, as a reward for that
                conduct <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> should be handed over to
                you with whatever boundaries you chose; when you were draining the treasury, when
                you were depriving <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> of all its youth,
                when you were passing over the vast sea in the winter season,—if you did at that
                time despise a triumph, what was it, O you most insane of pirates, that urged you
                on, unless it was some blind desire for booty and rapine? <milestone n="58"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>It is now in the power of Cnaeus Pompeius to act on your plan. For he has made a
                mistake. He had never had a taste for that philosophy of yours. The foolish man has
                already triumphed three times. Crassus, I am ashamed of you. What was the reason
                that, after a most formidable war had been brought to a termination by you, you
                showed such eagerness to get that laurel crown decreed to you by the senate? Publius
                Servilius, Quintus Metellus, Caius Curio, Lucius Africanus, why did not you all
                become pupils of this learned, of this most wise man, before falling into such
                blunders as you did? Even my friend Caius Pomptinus has it not now in his power to
                retrace his steps, for he is prevented by the religious ceremonies which have been
                    begun.<note anchored="true">Pomptinus had been praetor in Cicero's consulship;
                    the next year he had subdued the Allobroges, but he did not celebrate his
                    triumph till the year A.U.C. 700, in the consulship of Lucius Domitius
                    Ahenobarbus and Appius Claudius Pulcher.</note> O you foolish Camilli, and
                Curii, and Fabricii, and Calatini, and Scipios, and Marcelli, and Maximi! O you
                insane Paullus, you blockhead Marius! Oh how stupid, too, were the fathers of both
                these consuls; for they, too, celebrated triumphs. <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="59" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But since we cannot change what is already past, why does this mannikin, this
                Epicurus of mud and clay, delay to instill these admirable precepts of wisdom into
                that most illustrious and consummate general, his son-in-law? That man, believe me,
                is influenced by glory. He burns, he is on fire with the desire of a well-deserved
                and great triumph. <pb n="371"/> He has not learnt the same lessons that you have.
                Send him a book. Or rather, at once, if you yourself can contrive to meet him in
                person, think over what language you can find to check and extinguish that violent
                passion of his, and as a man of moderation and consistency you will have great
                influence over one who is quite giddy with his desire for glory; as a learned man,
                you will easily convince an ignorant man like him, as his father-in-law no doubt you
                will prevail with your son-in-law. For you will say to him like a man formed to
                persuade as you are neat, accomplished, a polished specimen of the schools. “How is
                it possible, O Caesar, for these supplications, which have now been decreed so often
                and for so many days, to delight you so excessively? Men are greatly mistaken about
                these things,—things which the gods disregard as that godlike Epicurus of ours has
                said, nor are they in the habit of being propitious to, or angry with, any one on
                account of such trifles.” </p>
            <p>I am afraid you will hardly get him to agree with you when you argue in this manner.
                For he will see that they both are, and have been, angry with you. <milestone n="60"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Turn to another school, and then speak thus of a triumph: “What is the meaning of
                that chariot? What is the use of those generals bound in front of the chariot? and
                of the images of towns? and of the gold? and of the silver? and of the lieutenants
                on horseback? and of the tribunes? What avail all the shouts of the soldiery? and
                all that procession? To hunt for applause, to be carried through the city, to wish
                to he gazed upon, are all mere trifles, believe me, things to please children. There
                is nothing in all those things which you can grasp as solid, nothing which you can
                refer to as causing pleasure to the body. <milestone n="61" unit="section"/> You see
                me who have returned from the same province on returning from which Titus
                Flamininus, and Lucius Paullus, and Quintus Metellus, and Titus Didius, and
                multitudes of others, inflamed with empty desires, have celebrated triumphs; you see
                me, I say, returning in such a spirit, that I trampled my Macedonian laurels under
                foot at the <placeName key="tgn,4012794">Esquiline</placeName> gate,—that I arrived
                with fifteen ill-dressed men thirsting at the Coelimontane gate, where my freedman
                had a couple of days before hired me a house suited to so great a general; and if
                that house had not been to be let, I should have pitched myself a <pb n="372"/> tent
                in the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName>. Meanwhile, O Caesar,
                in consequence of my neglect of all that triumphal pomp, my money remains safe at
                home, and will remain there. Immediately on my return, I gave in my accounts to the
                treasury, as your law required; but in no other particular have I complied with your
                law. And if you examine those accounts, you will see that no one has ever gained
                greater advantage from his learning than I have. For they are drawn up so learnedly
                and so cleverly, that the clerk who made the return to the treasury, when he had
                written them all out, scratching his head with his left hand, murmured out, ‘Indeed,
                the accounts are wonderfully clear, the money <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                    >oi)/xetai</foreign>.’”<note anchored="true">A Greek word signifying “is gone,
                    perished.”</note> If you make him this speech, I have no doubt that you will be
                able to recall him to his senses even when actually stepping into his chariot.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="62" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>O thou darkness, thou filth, thou disgrace! O thou forgetful of your father's family,
                scarcely mindful of your mother's,—there is actually something so broken-down, so
                mean, so base, so sordid, even too low to be considered worthy of the Milanese
                crier, your grandfather. </p>
            <p>Lucius Crassus, the wisest man of our state, searched almost the whole <placeName
                    key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName> with javelins to find out some pretext for a
                triumph where there was no enemy. A man of the highest genius, Caius Cotta, burnt
                with the same desire, though he could find no regular enemy. Neither of them had a
                triumph, because his colleague deprived one of that honour, and death prevented the
                other from enjoying it. A little while ago, you derided Marcus Piso's desire for a
                triumph, from which you said that you yourself were far removed; for he, even if it
                was not a very important war which he had conducted, as you say that it was not,
                still did not think that an honour to be slighted. But you are more learned than
                Piso, more wise than Cotta. Richer in prudence, and genius, and wisdom than Crassus,
                you despise those things which those idiots, as you term them, have considered
                glorious: <milestone n="63" unit="section"/> and if you blame them for having been
                covetous of glory, though they had conducted wars which were insignificant, or no
                wars at all; surely, you who have subdued such mighty nations, and performed such
                great achievements, were not bound to despise the fruit of your labours, the reward
                of <pb n="373"/> your dangers, the tokens of your valour. And the truth is that you
                did not despise them, even though you may be wiser than Themista;<note
                    anchored="true">Themista is the name of a woman who devoted herself to the study
                    of philosophy, to whom Epicurus wrote many of his letters.</note> but you shrank
                from exposing even your iron countenance to be chastised by the reproaches of the
                senate. </p>
            <p>You see now, since I have been so much an enemy to myself as to compare myself to
                you, that my departure, and my absence, and my return, were all so far superior to
                yours, that all these circumstances have shed immortal glory on me, and have
                inflicted everlasting infamy on you. <milestone n="64" unit="section"/> To come even
                to our present daily regular manner of life in this city will you venture to prefer
                your respectability, your influence, your reputation at home, your energy in the
                forum, your counsel, your assistance your authority and your opinion as a senator,
                to that which belongs to us or I would rather say to even the lowest and most
                desperate of men? <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Come, the senate hates you, which, indeed, you admit that it does deservedly since
                you have been the oppressor and destroyer, not only of its dignity and authority but
                altogether of its existence and its name. The Roman knights cannot bear the sight of
                you, since one of their order a most excellent and accomplished man Lucius Aelius
                was banished by you when consul. The Roman people wishes your destruction, to whom,
                for the purpose of bringing infamy upon them you have attributed those things which
                you did concerning me by the instrumentality of your band of robbers and slaves. All
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> execrates you whose resolutions
                and entreaties you have scorned in the most arrogant and haughty manner. <milestone
                    n="65" unit="section"/> Make experiment of this excessive and universal hatred
                if you dare. The most carefully prepared and magnificent games within the memory of
                man are just at hand, games such as not only never have been exhibited, but such
                that we cannot form a conception how it will he possible for any like them ever to
                be exhibited for the future. Trust yourself to the people, venture on attending
                these games. Are you afraid of hisses? Where are all the precepts of your schools?
                Are you afraid that there will be no acclamations raised in your honour? Surely it
                does not become a philosopher to regard even such a thing as that. You are <pb
                    n="374"/> afraid that violent hands may be laid on you. For pain is an evil, as
                you assert. The opinion which men entertain of you, disgrace, infamy,
                baseness,—these are all empty words, mere trifles. But about this I have no
                question. He will never dare to come near the games. He will attend the public
                banquet not out of regard for his dignity, (unless, perchance, for the purpose of
                supping with the conscript fathers,<note anchored="true">There is great doubt about
                    the text here.</note> that is to say, with those men who love him,) but merely
                for the sake of gratifying his appetite. <milestone n="66" unit="section"/> The
                games he will leave to us idiots, as he calls us. For he is in the habit, in all his
                arguments, of preferring the pleasures of his stomach to all delight of his eyes and
                ears. </p>
            <p>For though you have perhaps considered him previously only dishonest, cruel, and a
                bit of a thief, and though he now appears to you also voracious, and sordid, and
                obstinate, and haughty, and deceitful, and perfidious, and imprudent, and audacious,
                know, too, that there is also nothing which is more licentious, nothing more
                lustful, nothing more base, nothing more wicked than this man. But do not think that
                it is mere luxury to which he is devoted. <milestone n="67" unit="section"/> For
                there is a species of luxury, though it is all vicious and unbecoming, which is
                still not wholly unworthy of a well-born and a free man. But in this man there is
                nothing refined, nothing elegant nothing exquisite; I will do justice even to an
                enemy,—there is nothing which is even very extravagant, except his lusts. There is
                no expense for works of carving. There are immense goblets, and those (in order that
                he may not appear to despise his countrymen) made at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Placentia">Placentia</placeName>. His table is piled up, not with
                shell-fish and other fish, but with heaps of half-spoilt meat. He is waited on by a
                lot of dirty slaves, many of them old men. His cook is the same; his butler and
                porter the same. He has no baker at home, no cellar. His bread and his wine came
                from some huckster and some low wine-vault. His attendants are Greeks, five on a
                couch, often more. He is used to sit by himself, and to drink as long as there was
                anything in the cask.<note anchored="true">There is great uncertainty about the true
                    reading here.</note> When he hears the cock crow, then, thinking that his
                grandfather has come to life again, he orders the table to be cleared. <milestone
                    n="28" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="68" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Some one will say, “How did you find out all <pb n="375"/> this?” I will not indeed,
                describe any one in such a manner as to insult him, especially if he be an ingenious
                and learned man, a class with whom I could not be angry, even if I wished it. There
                is a certain Greek who lives with him, a man, to tell the truth, (I speak as I have
                found him,) of good manners, at least as long as he is in other company than Piso's,
                or while he is by himself. He, when he had met that man, as a young man, though even
                then he had an expression of countenance as if he were angry with the gods, did not
                disdain his friendship, as the other sought for it with great eagerness; he gave
                himself up to intimacy with him, so as indeed to live wholly with him, and I may
                almost say, never to depart from him. I am speaking not before illiterate men, but,
                as I imagine, in a company of the most learned and highly accomplished men possible.
                You have no doubt heard it said, that the Epicurean philosophers measure everything
                which a man ought to desire by pleasure;—whether that is truly said or not is
                nothing to us, or if it be anything to us, it certainly has no bearing on the
                present subject; but still it is a tempting sort of argument for a young man, and
                one always dangerous to a person of no great intelligence. </p>
            <p><milestone n="69" unit="section"/> Therefore, that profligate fellow, the moment that
                he heard that pleasure was so exceedingly praised by a philosopher, inquired nothing
                further; he so excited all his own senses which could be affected by pleasure, he
                neighed so on hearing this statement, that it was plain he thought that he had
                discovered not a teacher of virtue, but a pander to his lust. The Greek first began
                to distinguish between those precepts, and to separate them from one another, and to
                show in what sense they are uttered; but that cripple held the ball, as they say; he
                was determined to retain what he had got; he would have witnesses, and would have
                all the papers sealed up; he said, that Epicurus was an eloquent man. And so he is;
                he says, as I conceive, that he cannot understand the existence of any good when all
                the pleasures of the body are taken away. Why need I say much on such a topic?
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/> The Greek is an easy man, and very
                complaisant; he had no idea of being too contradictory to an “<foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >Imperator</foreign>” of the Roman people. <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"
                /></p>
            <p>But the man of whom I am speaking is excessively accomplished, not in philosophy
                alone, but also in general <pb n="376"/> literature, which they say that the rest of
                the Epicureans commonly neglect. He composes a poem, so witty, so neat, so elegant,
                that nothing can be cleverer. In respect of which any one may find fault with him
                who pleases, provided he does so good-humouredly, treating him not as a profligate,
                or a rascal, or a desperado, but merely as a Greekling, as a flatterer, as a poet.
                He comes to, or rather, I should say, he falls in with him, deceived by the same
                rigid brow of his (being, too, a Greek and a stranger) as this wise and great city
                was beguiled by. He could not withdraw when he had once become entangled in his
                intimacy, and he was afraid also of getting the character of being fickle. Being
                entreated, and invited, and compelled, he wrote so many things which he addressed to
                him, so many things too about him, that he has described in the most delicate poetry
                possible all the lusts of the man, all his debaucheries, all his different suppers
                and revels, and even all his adulteries. <milestone n="71" unit="section"/> And, in
                that poetry, any one who pleases can see that fellow's way of life reflected as in a
                mirror. And I would recite you much of it, which many men have read or heard, if I
                were not afraid that even the kind of speech which I am indulging in at this moment
                is at variance with the general usages of this place; and at the same time, I do not
                wish to do any injury to the character of the man who wrote it. </p>
            <p>For if he had had better fortune in getting a pupil, perhaps he might have turned out
                a more strict and dignified man himself; but chance has led him into a habit of
                writing in this manner, very unworthy of a philosopher; if at least philosophy does,
                as is reported, comprehend the whole system of virtue, and duty, and living
                properly; and a man who professes it appears to me to have taken on himself a very
                serious and difficult character. <milestone n="72" unit="section"/> But the same
                chance has polluted the man, who was quite ignorant of what he was professing when
                he called himself a philosopher, with the mud and filth of that fellow's most
                obscene and intemperate flock. </p>
            <p>And when he had praised the achievements of my consulship, (and I feel that the
                panegyric of that basest of men was almost a discredit to me myself,) “it was not,”
                says he, “any odium that you incurred by your conduct then, which injured you, but
                your verses.” It was too great a punishment that was established, I trust, by you
                when you were consul, for a <pb n="377"/> poet, whether he were a bad one, or too
                free an one. For you wrote—<quote>
                    <l>Arms to the gown must yield.</l>
                </quote> What then?—“This was what excited all that storm against you.” But I
                imagine that never was written in that panegyric, which, while you were consul was
                engraved on the sepulchre of the republic—“May it please you, that because Marcus
                Cicero has written a verse,...” but because he punished the guilty. <milestone
                    n="30" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="73" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But since we are to consider you not as Aristarchus, but as a sort of grammatical
                Phalaris, a man who does not put a mark to a bad verse but who pursues the poet with
                arms, I wish to know what fault you find with this verse “Arms to the gown must
                yield.” “You say,” says he “that the greatest generals must yield to the gown.”Why
                now, you ass, am I to teach you letters? I do not want words for such a purpose but
                a stick. I did not say <emph>this</emph> gown, in which I am clothed, nor, when I
                said “arms,” did I mean the sword and shield of any one particular general. But as
                the gown is the emblem of peace and tranquillity, and arms on the contrary are a
                token of disturbance and war, speaking after the manner of poets, I wished this to
                be understood that war and tumult were to yield to peace and tranquillity.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/> Ask your own intimate friend, that Greek
                poet; he will recognise and approve of such a figure of speech, and he will not
                wonder that you have no taste. “But” says he, “I cannot digest that other sentence
                either: <quote>
                    <l>The soldier's bays shall yield to true renown.</l>
                </quote>” Indeed, I am much obliged to you; for I, too, should stick at that, if you
                had not released me. For when you, frightened and trembling, threw down at the
                    <placeName key="tgn,4012794">Esquiline</placeName> gate the bays which with your
                own most thievish hands you had stripped off from your blood-stained <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">fasces</foreign>, you showed that those bays were granted not only
                to the highest but even to the very paltriest degree of glory. </p>
            <p>And yet, by this argument you try, O you wretch, to make out that Pompeius was made
                an enemy to me by that verse; so that, if my verse has injured me, the injury may
                appear to have been sought for me by that man whom that verse offended. <milestone
                    n="75" unit="section"/> I say nothing of the fact, that that verse had no
                reference <pb n="378"/> to him that it was not at all my object to insult with one
                single verse the man whom I had repeatedly extolled in many speeches and writings.
                But grant that he was offended. In the first place, will he not put in the scale
                against this one verse, the many volumes full of his praises which have proceeded
                from me? And if he has been moved by such a consideration, could he have
                countenanced so cruel an injury (I will not say to his own dearest friend, to one
                who did not deserve such treatment at his hands by the anxiety which he has shown
                for his glory, nor at the hands of the republic; to a man of consular rank, to a
                senator, to a citizen, or to a freeman, but) to any human being, on account of a
                verse? <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Are you aware what you are saying, to whom and of whom you are saying it? You are
                implicating most honourable men in your and Gabinius's wickedness, and that without
                any disguise. For a little while before you say that I was contending against men
                whom I despised; but that I was leaving those men alone who had more influence,
                though they were the men with whom I ought to be angry. But as for those men, (for
                who is there who is not aware whom you mean?) although the case of them all is not
                the same, still I have no cause of complaint against any of them. <milestone n="76"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Cnaeus Pompeius, though many men have fried to oppose his zeal for and attachment to
                my interests, has always had a regard for me; has always considered me entirely
                worthy of his intimacy; has always wished me to be not merely safe, but loaded with
                as much honour and distinction as possible. It is the dishonesty of you and your
                friends—it is your wickedness, your accusations against me, as if I were cherishing
                treacherous designs and he were in danger,—accusations most wickedly invented, and
                at the same time the accusations of those men who, abusing the liberty which their
                friendship with him gave them, contrived a home for their most infamous statements
                in his ears, at your instigation, and it is your desires of provinces which caused
                me to be excluded from his house, and all the men who were anxious for the
                preservation of his glory, and of the republic, to be cut off from all conversation
                with and all access to him. <milestone n="77" unit="section"/> And by all these
                measures it was brought about that he was prevented from abiding by what was
                notoriously his own opinion, while certain men had (I will not say wholly alienated
                his affections from me, but had) checked his eagerness to be of assistance to me.
                    <pb n="379"/>
            </p>
            <p>Did not Lucius Lentulus, who was at that time praetor, did not Quintus Sanga, did not
                Lucius Torquatus the father, did not Marcus Lucullus come to you? All of whom, and
                many others, had come to him, at his house on the Alban Hill, to pray and entreat
                him not to desert my fortune, which was bound up with the safety of the republic.
                And he sent those men to you and to your colleague, that you might espouse the
                public cause, and submit a motion to the senate. He said, that he was unwilling to
                enter into a contest with a tribune of the people in arms, unless he had a public
                resolution on his side; but that if the consuls were defending the republic in
                obedience to a resolution of the senate, then he would take up arms. <milestone
                    n="78" unit="section"/> Do you at all recollect you wretch, what answer you
                gave? an answer at which all those men, but especially Torquatus above all, were in
                a fury at the insolence of your reply, when you said that you were not as brave as
                Torquatus had been in his consulship, or as I had been; that there was no need of
                arms, nor of a contest; that it was in my power a second time to save the republic
                by yielding to the storm; that there would be endless bloodshed if I resisted; and
                at the last he said, that neither he nor his son-in-law nor his colleague would
                desert the tribune of the people. And now, you enemy and traitor, do you say that I
                ought to be a more determined enemy to any one else than to you? <milestone n="32"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="79" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I know well that Caius Caesar has not always had the same opinion about the republic
                that I have; but nevertheless, as I have often said of him before, in the hearing of
                these men, he communicated to me all his intentions during the whole of his
                consulship, and he wished me to be his partner in all the honours which he shared
                with his nearest friends; he offered them to me, he invited, he entreated me to
                accept them. I was not brought over to his party, perhaps out of too great a regard
                for my character for consistency; I did not wish to be exceedingly beloved by him to
                whose kindnesses I would never have given up my own opinion. While you were consul,
                the matter was supposed to be disputed and to have come to a close contest, whether
                the acts which he had carried the previous year should continue in force, or be
                rescinded. Why need I say more on this subject? If he thought that there was so much
                virtue, and vigour, and influence in me, that all the acts which he had performed
                would be undone if <pb n="380"/> I opposed them, why should I not excuse him if he
                preferred his own safety to mine? <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But I will say nothing of what is past. When Cnaeus Pompeius embraced my cause with
                all his energies, using all his exertions, and encountering even danger to his life
                for my sake; when he was going round to the municipal towns to plead my cause, and
                was imploring the good faith of all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>;
                when he was continually sitting by Publius Lentulus, the consul, the author of my
                safety; when he was always delivering his opinion to the senate, and when in all his
                harangues he was not only professing himself the defender of my safety, but was
                descending even to supplications in my behalf; he then took to himself as a
                companion of and an assistant in his zeal for me, Caius Caesar, whom he knew to have
                the very greatest influence, and to be no enemy of mine. You see now that I am not
                an antagonist of yours, not an enemy to you; and that, as for those men whom you
                hint at, I am bound not only not to be offended with them, but to be a friend to
                them. One of them, and I will take care always to remember it, has been as great a
                friend to me as to himself; the other, what I will forget some day or other,
                certainly was more of a friend to himself than to me. <milestone n="81"
                    unit="section"/> But this is a common state of things, that brave men, even
                after they have fought together in close combat sword in hand, still lay aside the
                hostility engendered by the contest at the same time that they cease from the battle
                itself, and lay down their arms. Nor, indeed, was he ever able to hate me, not even
                when we were most at variance. Virtue, which you do not even know by sight, has this
                quality, that its appearance and beauty delight brave men even when existing in an
                enemy. <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>In truth, I will say sincerely, O conscript fathers, what I feel, and what I have
                often said before in your hearing. If Caius Caesar had never been friendly towards
                me; if he had always been hostile to me; if he had despised my friendship, and had
                always shown himself implacable and irreconcilable towards me; still I could not
                feel otherwise than friendly towards a man who had performed and was daily
                performing such mighty actions. Now that he is in command, I no longer oppose and
                array the rampart of the <placeName key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName> against the
                ascent and crossing of the Gauls, nor the channel of the <placeName
                    key="tgn,7012611">Rhine</placeName>, foaming with its vast whirlpools, to those
                most savage <pb n="381"/> nations of the Germans. <milestone n="82" unit="section"/>
                Caesar has brought things to such a pass, that even if the mountains were to sink
                down, and the rivers to be dried up, we should still have <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> fortified, not indeed, by the bulwarks of
                nature, but by his victory and great exploits. But as he courts me, and loves me,
                and thinks me worthy of every sort of praise, will you call me off from my enmity
                against you to a quarrel with him? Will you thus reopen the past wounds of the
                republic by your enormities? Which, indeed, you, who were well acquainted with the
                union subsisting between Caesar and me, sought to elude, when you asked me,—with
                trembling lips, indeed, but still you did ask me,—why I did not proceed against you?
                Although, as far as I am concerned—<quote>
                    <l>Never shall you from care or pain be freed </l>
                    <l>By my denial,—</l>
                </quote><note anchored="true">This is from the Atreus of Accius.</note> still I must
                consider how much anxiety and how great a burden I, being exceedingly friendly to
                him, am imposing on him, while embarrassed with such important affairs of the
                republic, and with so formidable a war. </p>
            <p>Nor do I despair, though the youth of the city is indolent, and does not concern
                itself with the desire of praise and glory as it should, that there will be some men
                who will not be unwilling to stop this prostrate carcass of its consular spoils,
                especially in the case of so contemptible, and powerless, and helpless a criminal in
                the case of you who have behaved in such a manner that you have been afraid of
                appearing utterly unworthy of kindness, unless you showed yourself, in all respects,
                like the man by whom you were despatched into that province. <milestone n="34"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="83" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Do you imagine that we have inquired in only a cursory manner into the disgraces
                incurred during your command, and into the losses suffered by the province? We have
                investigated them, not tracking your footsteps merely by scent but marking every
                wriggle of your body, and every seat where you have left your print. Everything has
                been noted by us, both the very first crimes which you committed on your arrival,
                when, having received money from the people of <placeName key="tgn,7010750"
                    >Dyrrachium</placeName> for the murder of Plato; who was connected with you by
                ties of hospitality, you <pb n="382"/> destroyed the house of the man to whose
                murder you had sold yourself: when, after you had accepted from him some musical
                slave and other presents, he was still alarmed and hesitated a good deal, you
                assured him with promises, and desired him to come to <placeName key="tgn,7011182"
                    >Thessalonica</placeName> on the security of your good faith. <milestone n="84"
                    unit="section"/> And at last you did not even put him to death according to the
                custom of our ancestors, when that miserable man was willing to place his neck
                beneath the axe of his hereditary friend, but you ordered the physician whom you had
                brought with you to open his veins. After that, you added to the murder of Plator,
                that of Pleuratus, his companion, whom you put to death by scourging, being a man of
                extreme old age. After that, you are put to death by the hand of the executioner,
                Rabocentus, a prince of the Bessic tribe, having sold yourself to do this to king
                Cottus, for three hundred talents. And you did not murder him alone, but all the
                other ambassadors also who had come with him, all whose lives you sold to king
                Cottus. You waged a wicked and cruel war against the Denseletae, a nation which has
                at all times been obedient to this empire, and which even at the time of that
                general defection of all the barbarians, preserved <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                    >Macedonia</placeName> for us, when Caius Sentius was praetor. And though you
                might have had that people for your most faithful allies, you preferred to treat
                them as our most bitter enemies. Thereby you made those who might have been the
                perpetual defenders of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, desirous
                to harass and destroy it. They have thrown our revenues into confusion, they have
                taken our cities, laid waste our lands, led away cur allies into slavery, carried
                off whole families, driven off our cattle, and compelled the people of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7011182">Thessalonica</placeName>, as they despaired of saving their
                town, to fortify their citadel. <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="85"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>It was by you that the temple of Jupiter Urius, the most ancient and the most
                venerated of all the temples of the barbarians, was plundered. They are your crimes
                which the immortal gods have been avenging on our soldiers; for when they were all
                attacked by one kind of disease, and when no one who had once fallen sick was found
                to recover, no one had any doubt that it must have been the insults offered to men
                connected with us by ties of hospitality, and the murder of ambassadors, and the
                attacking of peaceful and allied tribes with wanton and wicked war, and the
                plundering of temples, <pb n="383"/> which were the causes of this great
                destruction. You can recognise in such brief particulars as these the universal
                nature of your wickedness and cruelty. <milestone n="86" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Why need I now detail the whole course of your avarice which is connected with
                innumerable crimes? I will just mention a few which are most notorious in a lump.
                Did you not after they had been paid to you from the treasury leave behind you at
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, to be put out to usury the
                eighteen millions of sesterces which you had obtained under pretence of its being
                money for your fit out as governor of a province, but which was in reality the price
                for which you had sold my life?<note anchored="true">The reader may as well be
                    reminded that the Latin word <foreign xml:lang="la">caput</foreign>, here and
                    elsewhere translated <gloss>life</gloss>, means in reality, when employed, as
                    here, in a legal sense, the civil privileges of a Roman citizen as well as his
                    life, and they were destroyed by banishment as completely as by death.</note>
                Did you not when the people of <placeName key="perseus,Apollonia"
                    >Apollonia</placeName> had given you two hundred talents at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, in order, by your means, to avoid payment
                of their just debts,—did you not, I say, actually give up Fufidius, a Roman knight,
                a most accomplished man, to his debtors? Did you not when you had given up your
                winter quarters to your lieutenant and prefect, utterly destroy those miserable
                cities? which were not only drained of all their wealth, but were compelled to
                undergo all the unholy cruelties and excesses of your lusts. What was your method of
                valuing corn? or the compliment which you claimed? if, indeed, that which is
                extorted by violence and by fear can be called a compliment. And this conduct of
                yours was felt nearly equally by all, but most bitterly by the Boeotians, and
                Byzantines, and by the people of the <placeName key="tgn,7012057"
                    >Chersonesus</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011182"
                    >Thessalonica</placeName>. You were the only master, you were the only valuer,
                you were the only seller of all the corn in the whole province for the space of
                three years. <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="87" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>Why need I bring forward your investigations into capital charges, your agreements
                with criminals, your most iniquitous condemnation of some, your most profligate
                acquittal of others? You know well that every circumstance concerning these matters
                is known to me, and I will leave you to recollect how many crimes of that class and
                of what great enormity they were. What? have you any recollection of that workshop
                of arms where, having collected together all the <pb n="384"/> cattle of the whole
                province, under some pretext connect with the hides, you repeated the whole of the
                profits which had been made by your family, and by your own father? For you, when
                you were a pretty big boy, at the time of the Italian war, had seen your house
                crammed full of the gains made when your father superintended the manufactory of
                arms. What? do you not recollect that the province was made a source of revenue to
                your slaves to whom you farm it, by putting a fixed import duty on every single
                thing which was sold? What? do you forget that centurionships were sold openly?
                    <milestone n="88" unit="section"/> What? do you deny that rank was dispensed by
                your slaves? What? do you deny that during all the years pay was furnished to your
                troops by the cities of the province, the months for which each city was to find the
                money being openly settled? What? have you forgotten that journey of yours into
                    <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName> and your attempts there? have
                you forgotten your prostration and abjectness of mind when news was brought to you
                that <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> was made praetorian
                province, and when you fell down fainting a half dead, not only because your
                successor was appointed, but also that Gabinius's was not? <gap reason="****"/><note
                    anchored="true">There is great corruption of the text here.</note> Did you not
                send away a quaestor of aedilitian rank? Was not every one of the most virtuous of
                your lieutenants insulted by you? Did you not refuse to receive the military
                tribunes? Was not Marcus Baebius, a brave man, murdered by your commands? <milestone
                    n="89" unit="section"/> Why need I tell how often you, distrusting and
                despairing of your fortunes, lay down in mourning, and lamentation, and misery? Why
                need I tell how you sent to that priest, so beloved the people, six hundred men of
                the friends, or allies, or tributaries of the Roman people, to be exposed to wild
                beasts? </p>
            <p>Need I relate how, when you were scarcely able to supply your disappointment and
                grief at your departure from the province, you first of all went to <placeName
                    key="tgn,1008943">Samothrace</placeName>, after that <placeName
                    key="tgn,7011078">Thasos</placeName> with your train of young dancing boys, and
                with Autobulus, and Athamas, and Timocles, those beautiful brothers?—that when you
                departed thence you lay for many days weeping in the villa of Euchadia, who was the
                wife Execestus? and from thence, disguised in shabby garments you came to <placeName
                    key="tgn,7011182">Thessalonica</placeName> by night, without any one knowing
                it?—that then, when you could not bear the crowds of in <pb n="385"/> who came about
                you bewailing the state to which you had reduced them, nor the torrent of their
                complaints, you fled away to <placeName key="tgn,7002252">Beroea</placeName>, a town
                out of your road? Need I relate how, when a rumour that Quintus Ancharius was not
                going to be appointed your successor had elated your mind with false hopes, while
                you were in that town, you again, O wretched man, gave the rein to all your former
                intemperance? <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="90" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>I say nothing of the gold for a crown, which tormented you a long time, while at one
                time you were inclined towards it and at another time unwilling to take it. For the
                law of your son-in-law forbade it to be decreed or to be accepted, unless a triumph
                was also decreed. But nevertheless you, in respect of that gold, could not find in
                your heart to disgorge the money which you had received and devoured, as in the case
                of the hundred talents of the Achaeans; you only changed the names and descriptions
                of the pretexts under which you extracted the money. I say nothing of the
                commissions which you scattered at random over the provinces; I say nothing of the
                number of vessels, or of the sum total of the plunder you acquired; I say nothing of
                the system under which you levied and extorted all the corn; I say nothing of your
                having stripped both nations and individuals of their liberties, even though they
                had had those liberties given them by name as rewards, not one of all which things
                is not carefully provided against and expressly forbidden to be done by the Sullan
                law. <milestone n="91" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>You, on your departure (O you punishment, O you Fury of the allies) destroyed the
                unhappy <placeName key="tgn,7002678">Aetolia</placeName>, which being separated by a
                great distance from the barbarian nations, is placed in the lap of peace and is in
                almost the centre of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. You confess as
                indeed you mentioned yourself only just now that Arsinoë and Stratus and Naupactus
                noble and wealthy cities were taken by the enemy. And by what enemies? Why, by those
                whom you, while encamped at Ambracia, on your first arrival, compelled to depart
                from the towns of the Agrinae and of the Dolopes, and to leave their altars and
                their homes. But now, on this departure of yours, O you illustrious “<foreign
                    xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>” though the sudden destruction of Aetolia was
                no trifling addition to your previous disasters,—you disbanded your army; nor was
                there any punishment which could be considered due to such guilt as yours <pb
                    n="385"/> which you were not willing to undergo, rather than allow any one to
                become acquainted with the existing numbers of the relics of your army. <milestone
                    n="38" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="92" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And, that you, O conscript fathers, may see how great is the resemblance between the
                two Epicurean generals in their military exploits and management of their command;
                Albucius, after he had triumphed in Sardinia, was condemned at Rome. And as this man
                expected a similar end to his campaigns, he laid aside his trophies in Macedonia;
                and those things which all nations have agreed in considering the insignia and
                monuments of military glory and victory, this extraordinary “<foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >Imperator</foreign>” of ours made the fatal evidences of towns which had been
                lost of legions which had been cut to pieces, of a province stripped of its garrison
                and of all the rest of its troops, to the everlasting disgrace of his family and
                name; and then, in order that there should to something which might be recorded and
                engraved on the pedestal of his trophies, when, on his departure from his province,
                he arrived at Dyrrachium, he was besieged by those very soldiers whom he told
                Torquatus just now, in answer to his questions, had been disbanded by him out of
                kindness. </p>
            <p>And when he had assured them with an oath that he would pay them the next day all
                that was due to them, he hid himself at home; and then on a very stormy night, in
                slippers and in the garb of a slave, he embarked on board a ship, and avoided
                Brundusium, and sailed towards the furthest part of the coast of the Adriatic Sea;
                    <milestone n="93" unit="section"/> while, in the meantime, the soldiers at
                Dyrrachium began to besiege the house in which they thought that he was, and as they
                thought that he was hiding himself there, they began to set fire to it. And the
                people of Dyrrachium, being alarmed at that proceeding, told them that their
                    “<foreign xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>” had fled away by night in his
                slippers. Then the troops displace, and throw down, and deface, and destroy a statue
                of his, an excellent likeness of him, which he had caused to be erected in the most
                frequented place, that the recollection of so delightful a man might not perish; and
                in this way they expended on his likeness and on his effigy the hatred which they
                had hoped to wreak on himself. </p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="94" unit="section"/> And as all this is the truth, (for I have no
                doubt that, when you see that I am acquainted with these which are the more <pb
                    n="387"/> prominent facts of your career, you will suppose that the more
                ordinary cases, that the main body of your crimes, has not been entirely unheard of
                by me,) you have no occasion to tempt me either by exhortation or by invitation. It
                is quite enough for me to be reminded. And no one and nothing will remind me except
                the critical occasions of the republic which appear to me indeed to be more
                immediately pressing than you have ever thought. <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"
                /></p>
            <p>Do you not in the least see or perceive what sort of judges we are going to have for
                the future when the law regulating the courts of justice is passed? Then it will not
                be the case that every one who likes will be appointed and that every one who has
                any objection will be excused. No men will be thrust into the order of judges no one
                will be irregularly removed from it. Ambition will not be allowed to work its way to
                popularity, nor wickedness to gratify its enmity, by that means. Those will be the
                judges whom the law itself, not those whom the depraved caprices of men appoint. And
                as this is the case believe me you will not have need to demand a prosecutor against
                your will. The case itself, or the necessities of the republic will either call
                forth me myself—which I should be sorry for—or some one else, or will repress us.
                    <milestone n="95" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>In truth, as I said a little time ago, I do not think that the same things are
                punishments to men which most people consider such, namely condemnation, banishment,
                or death. Lastly, it seems to me that that which may happen to an innocent, or to a
                brave or to a wise or to a virtuous man and citizen, cannot be a punishment in the
                proper sense of the word. That condemnation which is now demanded to be inflicted on
                you, befell Publius Rutilius, a man whom this city accounted a pattern of innocence.
                Lucius Opimius was driven from his country—he who, as praetor and consul, had
                delivered the republic from the greatest dangers. The punishment of guilt and of the
                consciousness of it, did not belong to the man to whom the injury was done, but to
                those who did it. But on the other hand, Catiline was twice acquitted; even that man
                who was the cause of your obtaining your province was acquitted after he had
                profaned the sacred rites of the Good Goddess. But who was there in all this city
                who thought that he was released from the guilt of impiety, and <pb n="388"/> not
                that those who acquitted him were, by their sentence, made accomplices in his
                wickedness? <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="96" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Am I to wait while seventy-five voting tablets are distributed in your case; when all
                men of all classes and ages and ranks of society have long since formed their
                opinions concerning you? For who is there who thinks you deserving of a visit; or of
                any compliment or even of an ordinary salutation? All men wish to efface all
                recollection of your consulship, to extirpate your conduct, your habits, your very
                appearance and name from the republic. The lieutenants who were with you are
                alienated from you, the military tribunes are hostile to you; the centurions and any
                other soldiers who may be left out of that once numerous army, and who were not
                disbanded by you but scattered abroad, hate you, wish for calamities to befall you,
                execrate you. Achaia which has been drained by you, Thessaly which has been harassed
                by you, Athens which has been plundered by you, Dyrrachium and Apollonia which have
                been completely emptied by you, Ambracia which has been pillaged by you, the
                Parthinians and Bulliensians who have been mocked by you, Epirus which has been laid
                waste by you, the Locrians, the Phocians, the Boeotians whom you have ravaged with
                fire and sword, Acarnania, Amphilochia, Perrhaebia, and the nation of the Athamanes
                who have been sold by you, Macedonia which has been sacrificed by you to the
                barbarians, Aetolia which has been lost, the Dolopians and the neighbouring
                mountaineers who have been driven from their towns and from their lands, the Roman
                citizens who have dealings as merchants in those countries,—all feel that you came
                among them as their chief despoiler, and harasser, and robber, and enemy. </p>
            <p><milestone n="97" unit="section"/> To all these numerous and weighty opinions formed
                respecting you in this manner, there has been added the private sentence of
                condemnation which you have passed upon yourself. Your secret arrival, your stealthy
                journey through Italy, your entry into the city deserted by your friends;—the fact
                of your sending no letters to the senate, of your addressing no congratulation to
                them on successes achieved by you during the whole of three summer campaigns, of
                your making no mention of any triumph;—you do not only omit to say what you did, but
                you do not even dare to say where you were. </p>
            <p>When you had brought back the dry withered leaves of <pb n="389"/> your laurels from
                that fountain and seed-ground of triumphs, when you threw them down and left them at
                the gate, then you yourself gave your verdict against yourself, and pronounced
                yourself “guilty.” And if you had done nothing deserving of honour, what had become
                of your army? where was the need for all that expense? what did you want with a
                military command? why did you seek for that province so fruitful in supplications
                and triumphs? But if you had ventured to cherish hopes of anything,—if you had
                nourished the thoughts which the name of “<foreign xml:lang="la"
                >Imperator</foreign>,” the <foreign xml:lang="la">fasces</foreign> bound with
                laurel, and those trophies so full of disgrace and ridicule to you, show that you
                had entertained,—who can be more miserable, who more thoroughly condemned than you,
                who neither when absent ventured to write to the senate that the affairs of the
                republic had been prosperously conducted by you, nor dare to say as much when you
                are present? <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="98" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>Do you think that you can possibly appear to be anything but a condemned man to me,
                who have always been of opinion that a man's fortune was to be estimated by his
                actions themselves, and not by their results, and that our character and our
                fortunes depended not on the voting tablets of a few judges, but on the opinions and
                judgments of all the citizens? when I see that the allies, and the people of the
                federate states, and all free nations, and all the tributary peoples, and the
                merchants, and the farmers of the public revenue, and the whole population of the
                city, and the lieutenants, and the military tribunes, and all the soldiers who are
                left of your army—as many as have escaped the sword, and famine, and disease, think
                you worthy of every extremity of punishment? when no excuse can be possibly alleged
                either before the senate, or before any order of men whatever, or before the Roman
                knights, or in the city, or in any part of Italy, sufficient to induce any one to
                pardon your enormous crimes? when I see that even you yourself hate yourself, and
                are afraid of everybody, and can find no one to whom you can venture to entrust your
                cause, and by your own verdict condemn yourself? <milestone n="99" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>I have never thirsted for your blood; I have never sought in your case for that
                extreme severity of the law and of judgment which at times may fall alike on the
                virtuous and on the guilty. But I have wished to see you abject, despised, <pb
                    n="390"/> scorned by all the rest of the citizens; looking with despair on your
                prospects, and abandoned even by yourself; looking timidly around at every noise
                which sounded near you; trembling at everything; distrusting the continuance of even
                your present safety, such as it is; not daring to utter a word; deprived of all
                liberty, destitute of all authority, stripped of all the dignity of a consul and of
                a man of consular rank; shivering, trembling, and fawning on all men. And I have
                seen you. Wherefore, if that future befalls you which you are in hourly apprehension
                of, I shall be in no respect concerned at it; if it is even a long while coming,
                still I shall enjoy the indignities to which you are exposed; and I shall be quite
                as well pleased to see you in daily fear of a prosecution as actually before the
                court; nor shall I rejoice less at seeing you in constant and unceasing distress,
                than I should if I saw you for a short time in the mourning robe of a criminal on
                his trial.</p>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
