<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 23-25 - 25</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Moore" role="editor"> Frank Gardener Moore, Professor Emeritus in
                    Columbia University </editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XXIII-XXV With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1940: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.341"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="book">
                <head>Book XXV</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> WHILE these things were being done in Africa
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> and
                    Spain, Hannibal spent the summer in the Sallentine region, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Hannibal is now in the southern part of Calabria, three
                        days' march from Tarentum; cf. viii. 12. He had previously been near Arpi,
                        in Apulia; XXIV. xlv. 11 ff. </note> in the hope of getting possession of
                    the city of Tarentum through treachery. Meantime, however, Sallentine cities of
                    no importance went over to his side. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the
                    same time among the Bruttians, out of twelve states which in the previous year
                    had revolted to the Carthaginians, Consentia and Taurianum returned to their
                    allegiance to the Roman people; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and more would
                    have returned if a prefect of the allies, Titus Pomponius Veientanus, who by
                    successfully ravaging Bruttian territory a number of times gained the appearance
                    of a regularly appointed general, had not gathered a hastily mustered army and
                    engaged Hanno. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A great many men were slain or
                    captured there, an ill-organized mass, however, of rustics and slaves. It was
                    the smallest part of the loss that, along with the rest, the prefect was
                    captured, who was responsible at that time for a reckless battle, and had
                    previously been a tax-farmer possessed of all the dishonest devices, faithless
                    and ruinous both to the state and to the companies. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Sempronius, the consul, fought many small engagements in
                    Lucania, not one worthy of record, and took by storm a number of unimportant
                    Lucanian towns. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.343"/>
                <p> The longer the war dragged on and success and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> failure altered the
                    situation, and quite as much so the attitude of men, superstitious fears, in
                    large part foreign at that, invaded the state to such a degree that either men
                    or else gods suddenly seemed changed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And now
                    not only in secret and within the walls of houses were Roman rites abandoned,
                    but in public places also and in the Forum and on the Capitol there was a crowd
                    of women who were following the custom of the fathers neither in their
                    sacrifices nor in prayers to the gods. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > Forsaken, as they felt, by their own gods, the populace were turning to
                        foreign divinities and strange cults. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Petty priests and also prophets had taken hold
                    on men's minds. And the number of these was increased by the mass of rustics
                    forced by want and fear into the city from their farms neglected and endangered
                    because of the long war, and by easy profit from the delusion of others-a trade
                    which they plied as though it were sanctioned. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    At first good men's indignation was voiced in private; then the matter reached
                    the senate and now even official complaints. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The aediles and the three police magistrates were roundly censured by the senate
                    because they did not stop it; and after they had attempted to drive that crowd
                    out of the Forum and to scatter the properties required for the rites, they
                    narrowly escaped violence. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Now that the
                    disorder appeared to be too strong to be quelled by the lower magistrates, the
                    senate assigned to Marcus Aemilius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        An error of Livy for Marcus Atilius; XXIV. xliv. 2, where Aemilius, <hi
                            rend="italics">praetor peregrinus,</hi> assigns his duties to Atilius,
                            <hi rend="italics">praetor urbanus,</hi> and takes a command in Apulia.
                        The error is repeated in iii. 12 and xii. 3. </note> the city praetor, the
                    task of freeing the people from such superstitions. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> He read the decree of the senate in an assembly, and also
                    issued an edict that whoever had books of prophecies or prayers or a ritual of
                    sacrifice set down in writing should bring all such <pb n="p.345"/> books and
                    writings <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Exact compliance with
                        written directions being essential, as in the Roman religion, to seize the
                        texts was in effect to suppress the cults. </note> to him before the first
                    of April, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        213</note> and that no one should sacrifice in a public or consecrated place
                    according to a strange or foreign rite. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A number of priests of the state died that
                    year: Lucius Cornelius Lentulus, pontifex maximus, and Gaius Papirius Masso, son
                    of Gaius, a pontifex, and Publius Furius Philus, an augur, and Gaius Papirius
                    Masso, son of Lucius, a decemvir in charge of rites. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. xii. 10 f.</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In place of Lentulus they made Marcus
                    Cornelius Cethegus a pontiff and Gnaeus Servilius Caepio in that of Papirius;
                    Lucius Quinctius Flamininus was named augur, Lucius Cornelius Lentulus, decemvir
                    in charge of rites. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For the consular elections the time was now
                    approaching, but because the consuls were occupied with the war and it was not
                    thought advisable to call them away, Tiberius Sempronius, the consul, named
                    Gaius Claudius Cento dictator to hold the elections. He in turn named Quintus
                    Fulvius Flaccus master of the horse. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the
                    first day available for elections the dictator announced the choice as consuls
                    of Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, master of the horse, and Appius Claudius Pulcher,
                    who as praetor had had Sicily as his province. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Then the following were elected praetors: Gnaeus Fulvius Flaccus, Gaius Claudius
                    Nero, Marcus Junius Silanus, Publius Cornelius Sulla. Having finished the
                    elections, the dictator laid down his office. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Curule aedile that year, together with Marcus Cornelius Cethegus, was Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Scipio was probably
                        only 22, but the famous law fixing statutory ages for the different offices
                        (Lex Villia annalis) was not passed until <date when="-0180">180 B.C.</date>
                        ; XL. xliv. 1. </note> who was later called Africanus. When he was a
                    candidate for the aedileship, and the tribunes of the plebs tried to oppose him,
                    saying that he ought not to be considered because he did <pb n="p.347"/> not
                    have the legal age for candidacy, he said, <quote> If all <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> the citizens want to
                        make me aedile I have years enough. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thereupon with such enthusiasm they separated
                    to form by tribes in order to cast their votes, that the tribunes suddenly gave
                    up their attempt. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The generosity of the
                    aediles consisted in celebrating the Roman Games <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">ludi Romani</hi> or <hi
                            rend="italics">maximi</hi> occurred in mid-September and lasted four
                        days. For repetition cf. XXIII. xxx. 16. </note> splendidly, for the
                    resources of that time, and in repeating them for one day; also in giving ...
                    measures <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">A congius</hi> held about three quarts. </note> of oil
                    for each precinct. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lucius Villius Tappulus and
                    Marcus Fundanius Fundulus as plebeian aediles brought before the people charges
                    of immorality against a number of matrons. Some of these being convicted, they
                    drove them into exile. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Plebeian Games
                    were repeated for two days, and on account of the festival a banquet for Jupiter
                    was held. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Flaccus and Appius Claudius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    entered upon their consulship, the former for the third time. And the praetors
                    received by lot the following assignments: Publius Cornelius Sulla, the duties
                    of praetor urbanus and praetor peregrinus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> As in wartime cases to be heard by the <hi
                            rend="italics">praetor peregrines</hi> would be much reduced in number,
                        he could be spared for service at the front; XXIV. xliv. 2. </note>
                    previously two separate offices; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Gnaeus
                    Fulvius Flaccus, Apulia, Gaius Claudius Nero, Suessula, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A military base in Campania, southeast of Capua,
                        half-way to Nola. Its Castra Claudiana lay near the entrance to the Caudine
                        Pass. Cf. XXIII. xxxi. 3; XXIV. xvii. 2; xliv. 3. </note> Marcus Junius
                    Silanus, Etruria. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the consuls were assigned
                    by decree the war with Hannibal and two legions each. The one was to take over
                    his troops from Quintus Fabius, consul in the previous year, the other from
                    Fulvius Centumalus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of the praetors, Fulvius
                    Flaccus was to have the legions which had been at Luceria under the praetor
                    Aemilius, Nero Claudius the one <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Terentius Varro had had only one legion; XXIV. xliv. 5.</note> which had
                    been in the Picene district under Gaius Terentius. They were themselves to
                    enlist more recruits for the same. To Marcus Junius the <pb n="p.349"/> city
                    legions of the previous year were given for <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> Etruria. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> For Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus and Publius Sempronius
                    Tuditanus their commands and provinces, Lucania and Gaul, with their armies,
                    were continued. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And the same was done for
                    Publius Lentulus, within the limits of the old province in Sicily, and for
                    Marcellus, whose province was Syracuse and up to the former boundaries of
                    Hiero's kingdom. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV. xliv. 4;
                        vii. 9.</note> The fleet was assigned to Titus Otacilius, Greece to Marcus
                    Valerius, Sardinia to Quintus Mucius Scaevola, the Spanish provinces to Publius
                    and Gnaeus Cornelius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In addition to the old
                    armies two city legions were enrolled by the consuls, and the total that year
                    amounted to twenty-three legions. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consular levy was hampered by the conduct
                    of Marcus Postumius of Pyrgi, which almost occasioned a serious insurrection.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Postumius was a tax-farmer, who in many
                    years had had no equal in dishonesty and avarice in the state, except Titus
                    Pomponius Veientanus, whom the Carthaginians under Hanno's command had captured
                    in the preceding year, while he was rashly ravaging the country in Lucania.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. i. 3 f.</note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These men, since the state assumed the risk
                    from violent storms in the case of shipments to the armies, had falsely reported
                    imaginary shipwrecks, and even those which they had correctly reported had been
                    brought about by their own trickery, not by accident. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They would put small cargoes of little value on old,
                    battered vessels, sink them at sea, after taking off the crews in small boats
                    that were in readiness, and then falsely declare that the shipments were far
                    more valuable. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This dishonesty had been
                    reported in the previous year to Marcus Aemilius, the praetor, and by him
                    brought before the senate, but it was not branded by <pb n="p.351"/> any decree
                    of the senate, because the senators were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> unwilling to offend the
                    tax-farmers as a class at such a crisis. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    people proved a more unsparing avenger of dishonesty; namely, two tribunes of
                    the plebs, Spurius and Lucius Carvilius, were at length aroused, and seeing that
                    the affair was unpopular and notorious, imposed a fine of two hundred thousand
                    asses upon Marcus Postumius. When the day for his protest against this fine
                    arrived, the assembly of the commons <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        It was left for the people to confirm or remit such a fine; cf. XXXVII. li.
                        4 f.; lviii. 1; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Phil.</hi> XI. 18; <hi
                            rend="italics">de Leg.</hi> III. 6. </note> was so large that the open
                    space on the Capitol could scarcely contain the crowd. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> After the arguments were concluded, there seemed to be but
                    one hope, namely, if Gaius <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> Servilius Casca,
                    a tribune of the plebs who was a blood-relative of Postumius, should interpose
                    his veto before the tribes should be called to vote. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> The tribunes provided witnesses, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The witnesses were to watch the balloting.</note>
                    cleared the people away, and the urn was brought, that they might determine by
                    lot in which tribe the Latins <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> such Latins as were present at Rome. In which
                        of the tribes they should vote was determined by the tribunes, who cast
                        lots. </note> should vote. Meantime the tax-farmers pressed Casca to adjourn
                    that day's hearing before the assembly. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The
                    people protested; and it so happened that the first seat at the end of the
                    platform was occupied by Casca, whose mind was swayed at once by fear and shame.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Finding in him no sufficient protection,
                    the publicans, in order to prevent action, rushed in a wedge through the space
                    cleared by removal of the crowd, while at the sametime they reviled the people
                    and the tribunes. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> And it had almost come to a
                    battle when Fulvius, the consul, said to the tribunes, <quote> Do you not see
                        that you are reduced to the ranks, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            > Any action interfering with a tribune's duties or privileges was held
                            equivalent to degrading him from office; cf. XLIII. 16. 9f. </note> and
                        that this means an insurrection if you do not promptly dismiss the popular
                        assembly? </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The assembly being <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> dismissed, the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> senate
                    was summoned <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> and the consuls brought
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> up the matter <pb n="p.353"/> of
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the disturbance <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> in the popular <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> assembly
                    owing to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    the <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> violence and audacity of the <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> publicans. Marcus <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> Furius Camillus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cf. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> xxxii. 9; xxxiii. 1. </note> it was said,
                    a man whose exile would have been followed by the ruin of the city, had allowed
                    himself to be condemned by the angry citizens; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    that before his time the decemvirs, under whose laws they were then still
                    living, and later many leading men in the state, had submitted to the judgment
                    of the people in their cases; that Postumius of Pyrgi had wrested the vote from
                    the Roman people, had brought to naught an assembly of the plebs, reduced the
                    tribunes to the ranks, drawn up a battle-line against the Roman people, had
                    taken his position, to separate the tribunes from the people and to prevent the
                    tribes from being summoned to vote. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nothing
                    had restrained men from slaughter and battle but the forbearance of the
                    magistrates in yielding for the moment to the mad audacity of a few men, and in
                    allowing themselves and the Roman people to be worsted, also in that, as regards
                    the voting, which the defendant would have prevented by force of arms, they had
                    of their own accord suspended it, to avoid giving excuse to those eager for the
                    fray. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These words were interpreted by all the
                    best citizens as deserved by an outrageous occurrence, and the senate declared
                    that this violence had been employed against the state, setting a dangerous
                    precedent. Thereupon the Carvilii, tribunes of the people, in place of the
                    procedure to fix the amount of the fine, at once named a day for Postumius'
                    appearance on a capital charge, and ordered that if he did not furnish sureties
                    he should be seized by an attendant and taken to prison. Postumius furnished
                    sureties, but did not appear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.355"/> The tribunes put the question to the plebs and the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> plebs
                    ordained that, if Marcus Postumius should not appear before the first of May,
                    and on being summoned on that day should not reply nor be excused, it should be
                    understood that he was in exile, and be decided that his property should be sold
                    and himself refused water and fire. The tribunes then began to name a day for
                    the appearance on a capital charge of each of those who had been instigators of
                    riot and sedition, and to demand sureties from them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At first they threw into prison those who did not give
                    security, and then even those who were able to do so. Avoiding this danger many
                    went into exile. </p>
                <p> V. Such was the outcome of dishonesty on the part of the publicans and of
                    audacity seeking to cover dishonesty. Next was held an election for the choice
                    of a pontifex maximus. This election was conducted by a new pontiff, Marcus
                    Cornelius Cethegus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Three men canvassed with
                    great rivalry: Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, the consul, who had been consul twice
                    before and also censor, and Titus Manlius Torquatus, likewise distinguished by
                    two consulships and a censorship, and Publius Licinius Crassus, who was only
                    about to be a candidate for a curule aedileship. This young man defeated in that
                    contest old men who had held high offices. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Before him for a hundred and twenty years no one who had not occupied a curule
                    chair had been elected pontifex maximus, except Publius Cornelius Calussa. </p>
                <p> The consuls were finding it difficult to complete the levy, since the scant
                    supply of young men was hardly sufficient for the two purposes, enrollment of
                    new legions for the city and replacements for the old ones. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The senate accordingly forbade them to give <pb n="p.357"/>
                    up the attempt and ordered the appointment of two <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> commissions of three
                    officials each, to inspect in rural districts, market-towns and local centres
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For <hi rend="italics">for a</hi>
                        and <hi rend="italics">conciliabula,</hi> cf. xxii. 4; XXXIX. xiv. 7; xviii.
                        2; XL. xxxvii. 3 f.; XLIII. xiv. 10. <hi rend="italics">A forum</hi> was a
                        Roman settlement, usually on an important road (e.g. Forum Appii), but
                        lacking the status of a <hi rend="italics">colonia. A conciliabulum</hi> was
                        a petty administrative centre for rural districts ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >pagi</hi> ). </note> all possible freeborn men within fifty miles, the
                    other beyond that distance, and any that seemed to them strong enough to bear
                    arms, even if not yet of military age, they were to recruit. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The tribunes of the plebs, if they should see fit, were to
                    bring before the people a bill that, in the case of those who had taken the
                    military oath at less than seventeen years, their campaigns should run just as
                    if they had been recruited at seventeen years or older. In accordance with this
                    decree of the senate two commissions of three members each were appointed and
                    they conducted the search for freeborn men in the country. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At the same time a letter from Marcus
                    Marcellus in Sicily was read in the senate concerning demands of the soldiers
                    serving under Publius Lentulus. This army was the remnant of the disaster at
                    Cannae, and, as has been said above, was relegated to Sicily, not to be brought
                    back to Italy before the end of the Punic War. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXIII. xxv. 7; XXIV. xviii. 9.</note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These men with Lentulus' permission sent their
                    leading knights and centurions and picked men from the infantry of the legions
                    to Marcus Marcellus at his winter quarters as their representatives, and one of
                    them, receiving permission to speak, said: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> In your consulship, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> But at
                            the time of the <hi rend="italics">senatus consultum</hi> Marcellus was
                            not consul, but praetor, and the men in question were in his own army;
                            cf. XXIII. xxiv. 1; xxv. 7. </note> Marcus Marcellus, and in Italy we
                        should have come to you already, directly after the senate made in our case
                        a decree that, if not unjust, was surely severe, had it not been our hope
                        that we were being sent into a province thrown <pb n="p.359"/> into
                        confusion by the death of its kings, to carry on <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> a serious <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> war against Sicilians and Carthaginians
                        combined, and that by our blood and wounds we were to give satisfaction to
                        the senate, just as in the time of our fathers the <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> men who had been captured by Pyrrhus at Heraclea had
                        done by fighting against Pyrrhus himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        And yet for what desert of ours have you been angry at us, conscript
                        fathers, or are now angry? It seems that I am looking at both consuls and
                        the entire senate when I look at you, Marcus Marcellus. If we had had you as
                        consul at Cannae the lot of the state, and of ourselves as well, would be a
                        better one. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before I complain of our
                        plight, permit us, I pray, to clear ourselves of the offence of which we are
                        charged. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If it was not by anger of the
                        gods nor by Fate, according to whose law the chain of human events is
                        unalterably linked, but by a fault that we were undone at Cannae, whose
                        fault, pray, was it? Of the soldiers or of the generals? For my part I, a
                        soldier, will never say anything about my general, especially since I know
                        that he was thanked by the senate because he did not lose hope for the
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> state, and that after the flight
                        from Cannae his command was continued year after year. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The others too who survived that disaster, the men whom
                        we had as our tribunes of the soldiers, canvass for offices, we have heard,
                        and hold them, and govern provinces. Can it be, conscript fathers, that you
                        readily pardon yourselves and your sons, but are cruel to these creatures of
                        no account? And while it was no disgrace to the consul and other leading men
                        in the state to flee, since there was no other hope, did you send your
                        common soldiers into battle to die inevitably? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> At the Allia <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            >CF. V. xxxviii</note> almost the entire <pb n="p.361"/> army fled; at
                        the Caudine Forks, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. IX. iv. The
                            following phrase is exaggerated.</note> without even <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                        attempting a battle, the army surrendered its weapons to the enemy, not to
                        mention other shameful defeats of armies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        But so far were men from devising any disgrace for those armies that the
                        city of Rome was recovered by the army which <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> had fled from the Allia over to Veii, and the Caudine
                        legions, which had returned to Rome without their arms, were sent back armed
                        into Samnium and sent under the yoke that same enemy who had exulted in a
                        disgrace now their own. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But at Cannae can
                        any one accuse the army of panic and fright, where more than fifty thousand
                        men fell, whence the consul fled with seventy horsemen, and of which no one
                        survives except the man whom the enemy, tired of slaying, spared? <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> At the time when ransom was refused to captives,
                        men were everywhere praising us because we had saved ourselves for the
                        state, had returned to the consul at Venusia and had formed the semblance of
                        a regular army. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> But now we are in a worse
                        situation than in our fathers' time were captives. For in their case only
                        their arms and their rank and the position of their tents when in camp were
                        changed. These, however, they recovered by a single service rendered to the
                        state and one victory. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Not one of them
                        was sent into exile, not one of them was deprived of the hope of serving out
                        his term; in fine they were given an enemy, so that in battle with him they
                        might once for all end either life or disgrace. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> But we, against whom no charge can be brought except
                        that we are to blame for the survival of any Roman soldier from the
                        battle-line at Cannae, have been sent far away, not only from our native
                        city and Italy, but also from the enemy, that there <milestone n="18??"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <pb n="p.363"/> we may grow old in exile, that we may have no hope, <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> no
                        opportunity of wiping out disgrace, none of appeasing the anger of our
                        citizens, none even of dying bravely. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> It
                        is neither an end of our disgrace nor a reward for our courage that we ask.
                        Only let us prove our spirit and put our courage into practice. It is for
                        hardship and danger we are asking, that we may do the duty of men and
                        soldiers. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> The war in Sicily has now been
                        carried on with intensity for two years. Some cities are being stormed by
                        the Carthaginian, some by the Roman. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                        Infantry and cavalry clash in battle-line. At Syracuse the war goes on by
                        land and by sea. The cries of men in battle and the din of arms can be heard
                        by us, who are ourselves unemployed and listless, as if we had neither hands
                        nor weapons. With legions of slaves Tiberius Sempronius, the consul, has
                        engaged the enemy again and again in battle formation. <milestone n="22"
                            unit="section"/> As a reward for their service they have freedom <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified">XXIV. xvi. 9.</note> and
                        citizenship. Reckon us at least slaves purchased for this war; let us engage
                        the enemy and by fighting earn freedom. Do you wish, sir, to test our
                        courage on sea, on land, in battle-line, in besieging cities? <milestone
                            n="23" unit="section"/> We demand all the worst in hardship and danger,
                        in order that what should have been done at Cannae be done as soon as
                        possible, since every day that we have since lived has been marked for
                        disgrace. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of this speech they fell at
                    Marcellus' knees. Marcellus said the matter was neither within his competence
                    nor his authority; he would write to the senate and do everything, according to
                    the opinion of the fathers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The letter was
                    delivered to the new consuls and by them read in the senate. And after
                    discussion of the letter the senate decreed <pb n="p.365"/> as follows:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that to soldiers who had deserted their
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    comrades in battle at Cannae the senate saw no reason why the welfare of the
                    state should be entrusted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If Marcus Claudius,
                    the proconsul, should take a different view, he should do what he thought to
                    accord with the interest of the state and his own conscience, provided that no
                    one of them should be exempt from duties, or be decorated for valour, or be
                    brought back to Italy, so long as the enemy should be in the land of Italy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Elections were then held by the praetor
                    urbanus in accordance with a decision of the senate and a plebiscite, and at
                    these there were elected five commissioners for the restoration of the walls and
                    towers, and two boards of three, one to recover sacred vessels and register
                    temple gifts, the <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> other to rebuild the
                    Temple of Fortune and that of Mater Matuta inside Porta Carmentalis, and that of
                    Hope outside the gate —temples that had been destroyed by fire the preceding
                    year. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV. xlvii. 15 f.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were terrible storms; on the Alban Mount
                    it rained stones steadily for two days. Many things were struck by lightning:
                    two temples on the Capitol, the embankment of the camp above Suessula in many
                    places, and two sentries were killed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At Cumae
                    the wall and certain towers were not merely struck by the bolts but even thrown
                    down. At Reate a huge stone seemed to fly, the sun to be redder than usual and
                    of a bloody colour. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On account of these
                    prodigies there was a single day of prayer, and for several days the consuls
                    devoted themselves to religious rites; and about the same time there was a nine
                    days' observance. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While a revolt of the Tarentines had long
                    been <pb n="p.367"/> hoped for by Hannibal and suspected by the Romans, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> a reason
                    for expediting the same happened to come from without. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Phileas of Tarentum, a man of restless spirit and quite
                    unable to endure the long inactivity in which he seemed to be losing his powers,
                    had been at Rome for a long time, nominally as an ambassador. Thus he found
                    means of access to the hostages from Tarentum and Thurii. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> They were kept under guard in the Atrium Libertatis, with
                    less watchfulness because it was to the interest neither of the hostages
                    themselves nor of their states to outwit the Romans. Phileas worked upon them by
                    frequent conferences, and after bribing two temple-wardens brought them out of
                    confinement at nightfall. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then he himself
                    fled, sharing their secret journey. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> At
                    daybreak their flight was reported everywhere in the city, and the men sent to
                    pursue them arrested and brought them all back from Tarracina. They were led
                    into the Comitium, scourged with rods with the approval of the people, and
                    thrown down from the Rock. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As in XXIV.
                        xx. 6.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The relentlessness of this punishment outraged
                    two of the most important Greek cities in Italy, both as states and personally
                    as well, whenever <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> individuals were connected
                    either by relationship or friendship with those who were so cruelly executed.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of those so connected some thirteen noble
                    youths of Tarentum formed a conspiracy, and Nico and Philemenus were the
                    leaders. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thinking that they ought to confer
                    with Hannibal before taking any step, these men left the city by night under
                    pretext of hunting and set out to go to him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    And when they were not far from his camp, the rest concealed themselves in the
                    woods near the road; but Nico <pb n="p.369"/> and Philemenus advanced to the
                    outposts, were <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> seized and at their own request brought before Hannibal. After
                    explaining the reasons for their plan and what they were plotting, they were
                    warmly commended and loaded with promises. In order to make their
                    fellow-citizens believe they had left the city to forage, they were bidden to
                    drive to the city cattle belonging to the Carthaginians which had been turned
                    out to graze. Promise was given that they would do so in safety and without a
                    conflict. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The young men's booty attracted
                    attention, and less astonishment was caused by their making the same venture
                    again and again. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On meeting Hannibal again
                    they had his formal assurance that the Tarentines as free men should have their
                    own laws and all their possessions, and pay no tribute to the Carthaginians nor
                    admit a garrison against their own wish; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that
                    houses occupied by Romans should be handed over, together with the garrison, and
                    be assigned to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So much
                    agreed upon, Philemenus thereafter made it his more constant habit to leave the
                    city and return to it by night. In fact he was noted for his devotion to the
                    chase, and his hounds and other equipment would follow him. Usually he carried
                    back something he had taken or that the enemy had brought him by agreement, and
                    he would give it either to the commandant or to the gate-guards. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> They believed that he came and went preferably by
                    night for fear of the enemy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When the thing had become so habitual that
                    the gate was opened at whatever hour of the night he gave the signal by a
                    whistle, it seemed to Hannibal to be the time for action. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> He was at a distance of three days' march, and there he
                    played the invalid, that his <pb n="p.371"/> keeping a fixed camp so long in one
                    and the same <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> place might cause less wonder. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    ' The Romans also on garrison duty at Tarentum had ceased to find such prolonged
                    inaction suspicious. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Once he had determined, however, to go to
                    Tarentum, he picked ten thousand infantry and cavalry —the men whom he thought
                    best suited to the enterprise on account of swiftness of foot and lightness of
                    arms —and at the fourth watch of the night got in motion. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And he ordered some eighty Numidian horsemen, who were sent
                    in advance, to scour the country near the roads and keep an eye in every
                    direction, that no farmer in the distance might observe the column without being
                    noticed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were to hold up those ahead of
                    them and slay those they met, so that people living near by might have- the
                    impression of foragers rather than of an army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He himself, after a forced march, pitched camp at a distance of about fifteen
                    miles from Tarentum. And not even there did he announce whither they were going.
                    He merely summoned the soldiers and bade them all to keep to the road and not
                    allow anyone to turn aside or leave his place in the column; and to be
                    especially alert to hear commands and not to do anything without orders from
                    their officers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He would in due time inform
                    them what he wished to have done. About the same hour a rumour had preceded him
                    to Tarentum that a- few Numidian horsemen were ravaging the farms and had
                    inspired widespread alarm among the rustics. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    On receiving this news the Roman commandant was only so far aroused- as -to
                    command part of the cavalry to go out the next day at dawn, in order to prevent
                    depredations of the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For the rest his
                    attention was so little aroused that <pb n="p.373"/> on the contrary the raid of
                    the Numidians was to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 212</note> him a proof that Hannibal and the army had not stirred from
                    their camp. </p>
                <p> Hannibal broke camp early in the night. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> at the time of the first sound sleep, not yet
                            <hi rend="italics">intempesta</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">nocte</hi> (toward midnight); Cicero <hi rend="italics"
                            >de Div.</hi> I. 57; <hi rend="italics"/> Macrobius I. iii. 15. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His guide was Philemenus with his usual load
                    of game. The rest of the traitors were waiting for acts previously arranged.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It had been agreed, namely, that
                    Philemenus, as he brought in his game by the usual postern, should lead in armed
                    men, while on another side Hannibal should approach the Temenitis Gate.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That quarter is toward the inland, facing
                    east; tombs occupy a considerable space inside the walls. As he approached the
                    gate the fire signal was given by Hannibal according to agreement, and in reply
                    from Nico the same signal blazed; then on both sides the flames were
                    extinguished. Hannibal was leading his men silently to the gate. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Nico unexpectedly attacks the sleeping sentries in
                    their beds, slays them and opens the gate. Hannibal with his infantry column
                    enters, orders the cavalry to halt, so that <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                    they can meet the enemy in the open, in whatever direction the situation may
                    require. And Philemenus on another side of the city was approaching the postern
                    by which he was accustomed to come and go. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    His well-known voice and the now familiar signal having aroused a sentry, the
                    little gate was opened for Philemenus, just as he was saying they could scarcely
                    carry the weight of a huge beast. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> While two
                    young men were carrying in the boar, he himself followed them with a huntsman
                    who was unencumbered, and as the sentry, thrown off his guard by its marvellous
                    size, faced the men who were carrying it, Philemenus ran him through with a
                    hunting spear. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then about thirty armed men
                        <pb n="p.375"/> entered, cut down the rest of the sentries and broke <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> open the
                    neighbouring gate; and the column with its standards at once rushed in. Thence
                    they were marched in silence to the market-place and joined Hannibal. The
                    Carthaginian then sent two thousand Gauls, divided into three units, through the
                    city, and to each he attached two Tarentines as guides. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> He ordered them to occupy the most frequented streets, and
                    when the uproar had begun, to slay the Romans everywhere, to spare the
                    townspeople. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But to make this possible he
                    instructed the young Tarentines, whenever they saw one of their own people in
                    the distance, to bid him be quiet and say nothing and be of good cheer. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Already there was such uproar and shouting as
                    is usual in a captured city, but what it was about no one quite knew for
                    certain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Tarentines believed the Romans
                    had surprised them, in order to plunder the city; the Romans thought it was some
                    kind of uprising treacherously started by the townspeople. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The commandant, aroused by the first uproar, escaped to the
                    harbour; picked up by a skiff, he was rowed around from there to the citadel.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Confusion was caused also by the sound of
                    a trumpet from the theatre. For it was a Roman trumpet, furnished by the
                    traitors for this very purpose; and in addition, being unskillfully sounded by a
                    Greek, it left it uncertain who was giving the signal and to whom. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> When day broke the Punic and Gallic arms, now
                    recognized, relieved the Romans of their uncertainty, and at the same time the
                    Greeks, seeing slain Romans everywhere, were aware that the city had been
                    captured by Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When it was no longer
                    twilight and the Romans who survived the slaughter <pb n="p.377"/> had fled to
                    the citadel, and the uproar was gradually <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> being stilled, Hannibal
                    then gave orders to summon the Tarentines without arms. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They all assembled, except those who had followed the
                    Romans in their retreat to the citadel, to share with them any outcome.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thereupon Hannibal had kind words for the
                    Tarentines and called to mind what he had done for their fellow-citizens whom he
                    had captured at Lake Trasumennus or at Cannae. At the same time he inveighed
                    against the haughty rule of the Romans and ordered them to go each to his own
                    house and to write his name on the door. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> According to Polybius the legend was to be simply
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">;</foreign> VIII. xxxi. 4. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He would order that at a given signal such
                    houses as were not marked should at once be plundered. If any one should write
                    his name on the quarters of a Roman citizen —now they were occupying vacant
                    houses —he would regard such a man as an enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> After the assembly had been dismissed and the marking of doors had
                    distinguished the house of a citizen from that of an enemy, the signal was given
                    and they scattered in all directions to plunder the Roman dwellings; and the
                    booty was considerable. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the next day he led his men to an attack
                    upon the citadel. He saw that not only was this defended by very high cliffs on
                    the side towards the sea, which surrounds the larger part of it as a peninsula,
                    but on the side toward the city itself by a wall and a great fosse, and hence
                    could not be taken by assault nor by siege-works. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, to avoid either keeping himself from larger
                    operations in his effort to protect the Tarentines, or else letting the Romans,
                    whenever they pleased, make an attack from the citadel upon the Tarentines if he
                    left them without a strong garrison, he decided to wall off <pb n="p.379"/> the
                    city from the citadel by an earthwork. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> not
                    without the hope also that he could engage the Romans if they tried to prevent
                    the work, and that, if they should make a furious sally, the strength of the
                    garrison would be so reduced by serious losses that the Tarentines by themselves
                    could easily defend the city against them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    After fortification began, a gate was suddenly opened and the Romans made an
                    attack upon the men at work. And the outpost stationed in advance of the work
                    allowed itself to be driven back, that boldness might grow with success and a
                    larger number might pursue the repulsed and to a greater distance. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Then at a given signal the Carthaginians, whom
                    Hannibal had kept drawn up for this purpose, rose up on all sides. And the
                    Romans did not withstand the attack, but limited space and ground obstructed
                    partly by the work already begun, partly by preparations for the work, kept them
                    from a disorderly flight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Very many leaped
                    into the fosse, and more were slain in flight than in battle. Then even
                    fortification began to proceed, with no one attempting to prevent. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> A great fosse was carried along, and inside of it an
                    earthwork was raised; and at a short distance he prepared to add a stone wall
                    likewise in the same direction, so that even without a garrison they could
                    protect themselves against the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He did,
                    however, leave a garrison of moderate size, to aid as well in the completion of
                    the wall. He himself set out with the rest of his forces and pitched camp at the
                    river Galaesus, which is five miles from the city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On returning from this permanent camp to
                    inspect, inasmuch as the work had progressed with considerably more speed than
                    he had anticipated, he <pb n="p.381"/> hoped that the citadel also could be
                    taken by storm. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> And it is not defended by height, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> According to Strabo VI. iii. 1 the only elevation of
                        any consequence was the citadel. </note> as other citadels are, but is on
                    level ground and separated from the city merely by a wall and a fosse.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While the attack was now in progress with
                    engines of every kind and with siege-works, a garrison sent from Metapontum
                    encouraged the Romans to make a surprise attack by night upon the works of the
                    enemy. Some of these they pulled apart, others they ruined by fire; and this was
                    the end of Hannibal's attack upon the citadel from that side. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> His remaining hope was in a blockade, and that was not very
                    effectual, because the occupants of the citadel, which is situated on a
                    peninsula and commands the harbour mouth, had the sea at their disposal, while
                    the city on the other hand was shut off from supplies by sea and the besiegers
                    were nearer to starvation than the besieged. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Hannibal summoned the leading men of Tarentum and laid before them all the
                    difficulties of the situation, saying that he neither saw a way to take so well
                    fortified <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> a citadel by storm, nor had any
                    hope in a blockade, so long as the enemy had command of the sea. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> But if he should have ships with which to prevent
                    the bringing in of supplies, the enemy would at once either withdraw from the
                    citadel or surrender. The Tarentines assented, but thought that the giver of
                    advice must give aid also to carry it out. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For Carthaginian ships, summoned from Sicily, they said, could do it. As for
                    their own ships, which were shut up inside a very small bay, while the enemy
                    held the key to the harbour, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        mouth of the harbour was closed, as Strabo ( <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> )
                        says, by a large bridge. </note> how were they to get out into the open sea?
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>They will get out</quote> , said Hannibal; <quote> many things which are
                        naturally difficult are solved by ingenuity. You have a city <pb n="p.383"/>
                        situated in a plain. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Level streets of
                        ample breadth <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            212</note> lead in all directions. Along the street that is carried
                        across from the harbour through the centre of the city to the sea I shall
                        transport ships on wagons with no great difficulty, and the sea, which the
                        enemy now possess, will be ours, and we shall besiege the citadel on that
                        side by sea, on this side by land; or rather we shall soon either take it,
                        abandoned by the enemy, or take it enemy and all. </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> This speech produced not merely the hope of
                    success, but great admiration for the general as well. At once wagons were
                    assembled from everywhere and joined together, and the tackle brought to draw up
                    the ships, and the roadway paved, that the wagons might be easier to move, and
                    the difficulty of transport lessened. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Then
                    mules and men were brought together and the work was begun with energy. And so a
                    few days later a fleet furnished and equipped sailed around the citadel and cast
                    anchor at the very mouth of the harbour. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Such
                    was the state of things which Hannibal left at Tarentum when he himself returned
                    to his winter quarters. But whether the rebellion of the Tarentines took place
                    in the previous year or in this year, authorities differ. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> That <date when="-0213">213 B.C.</date> was the correct
                        date for their defection is shown by XXVII. xxv. 4. </note> More of them and
                    those nearer in time to men who remembered the events relate that it occurred in
                    this year. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Rome the consuls and praetors were detained
                    by the Latin festival until the 26th of April. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    After performing the rites on that day on the Mount, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Mons Albanus (Monte Cavo), where a sacrifice on the
                        fourth day brought the festival to an end. </note> each set out for his
                    assignment. Then fresh religious scruples were aroused by the verses of Marcius.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A noted seer had been this Marcius, and
                    when in the preceding year search was being made by decree of the senate for
                    such books, they had come <pb n="p.385"/> into the hands of Marcus Aemilius,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For the error cf. note on i.
                        11.</note> the praetor <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> urbanus, who was in charge of the matter. He
                    had immediately turned them over to the new praetor, Sulla. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Of the two prophecies <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The rough hexameters (probably translated from the
                        Greek) had been reduced to prose. </note> of this Marcius the authority of
                    one, made known after the event, was confirmed by the outcome and lent
                    credibility to the other also, whose time had not yet come. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> In the earlier prophecy the disaster at Cannae had been
                    predicted in such terms as these: <quote> Flee the river Canna, thou descendant
                        of Troy, that foreigners may not compel thee to do battle in the Plain of
                        Diomed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But thou wilt not believe me until
                        thou hast filled the plain with blood, and many thousands of thy slain will
                        the river bear from the fruitful land down to the great sea. To fishes and
                        birds and beasts that dwell on the land thy flesh shall be meat. For thus
                        hath Jupiter declared to me. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And those who had fought in that region
                    recognized the plains of the Argive Diomed and the river Canna no less than the
                    disaster itself. Then the second prophecy was read, being not only more obscure
                    because the future is more uncertain <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> than
                    the past, but more difficult also in the way it was written. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> If you wish, Romans, to drive out enemies, the sore which has come from
                        afar, I propose that a festival be vowed to Apollo, to be observed with good
                        cheer in honour of Apollo every year. When the people shall have given a
                        part out of the treasury, private citizens shall contribute on their own
                        behalf and that of their families. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In
                        charge of the conduct of that festival shall be the praetor who is then
                        chief judge for the people and <pb n="p.387"/> the commons. The decemvirs
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the <hi rend="italics">decemviri sacris
                                faciundis,</hi> charged with the oversight of sacrifices. </note>
                        shall offer the victims <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 212</note> according to Greek rite. If ye will do
                        this rightly ye shall forever rejoice, and your state will change for the
                        better. For that god who graciously nurtures your meadows will destroy your
                        enemies. </quote> For the interpretation of the prophecy they took one day.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the next day the senate made a decree
                    that in regard to the festival to be held and the sacrifices in honour of Apollo
                    the decemvirs should consult the books. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">libri Sibyllini,</hi> of which
                        the decemvirs were the custodians and authorized interpreters, but could not
                        refer to them unless empowered by a decree of the senate. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Those passages having been consulted and
                    reported to the senate, the fathers voted that a festival should be vowed and
                    held in honour of Apollo, and after the festival had been held the sum of twelve
                    thousand asses should be given to the praetor for the ceremonies, and two
                    full-grown victims. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A second decree of the
                    senate was made, that the decemvirs should offer sacrifice according to Greek
                    rite and with these victims: to Apollo an ox with gilded horns and two white
                    she-goats <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As she-goats would surely
                        be offered to Diana, not to Apollo, there is good reason to believe that her
                        name has been lost from the text, and before Macrobius' time, since he has
                        the same statement; <hi rend="italics">Saturnalia</hi> I. xvii. 29. </note>
                    with gilded horns, to Latona a cow with gilded horns. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> When the praetor was about to open the festival in the
                    Circus Maximus, he ordered by edict that during that feast the people should
                    make their contribution to Apollo according to their means. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Such is the origin of the festival of Apollo, vowed and
                    kept to secure victory, not health, as most think. The people wore garlands at
                    the spectacles, the matrons offered prayers, everybody feasted in the atrium
                    with open doors, and the day was kept with every kind of ceremony. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Hannibal was near Tarentum, and <pb
                        n="p.389"/> both consuls were in Samnium but seemed about to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> invest
                    Capua, already the Campanians were suffering hunger (the usual hardship of a
                    long investment), because the Roman armies had prevented them from sowing.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And so they sent legates to Hannibal,
                    praying that, before the consuls should lead the legions into their lands and
                    all the roads should be blocked by forces of the enemy, he should order grain to
                    be brought from neighbouring places to Capua. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Hannibal ordered Hanno to march with his army from the land of the Bruttii over
                    into Campania, and to see to it that the Campanians should have a supply of
                    grain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hanno set out from the land of the
                    Bruttii with his army, avoided camps of the enemy and the consuls, who were in
                    Samnium, and when he was now nearing Beneventum, pitched camp on high ground
                    three miles from the city itself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then he
                    ordered grain to be brought into camp from allied peoples of the neighbourhood,
                    among whom it had been garnered in the summer; and he furnished troops to escort
                    the supplies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then he sent word to Capua,
                    naming a day on which they should appear at the camp to get their grain, after
                    bringing together from the farms on all sides every kind of vehicle and beast of
                    burden. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This order was carried out by the
                    Campanians with their usual carelessness and indifference. Little more than four
                    hundred vehicles were sent, and a few beasts of burden besides. For this they
                    were censured by Hanno, that not even hunger, which, as he said, inflames even
                    dumb brutes, could spur their diligence; and another day was assigned for
                    getting their grain with ampler means of transport. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When all this was reported, just as it happened, to the
                    Beneventans, they at once <pb n="p.391"/> sent ten legates to the consuls, the
                    camp of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> Romans being near Bovianum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls, on hearing what was going on near Capua, mutually arranged that one of
                    them should lead his army into Campania, and Fulvius, to whom that assignment
                    had fallen, set out and entered the walls of Beneventum at night. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Being near now, he learned that Hanno had gone with
                    a part of his army to procure grain; that through his quaestor grain had been
                    furnished to the Campanians; that two thousand wagons and in addition a mixed
                    and unarmed multitude had arrived; that everything was being done in confusion
                    and excitement, and that the arrangement of the camp and military routine had
                    been broken down by the influx of rustics, foreigners <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> not Campanians. </note> at that. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These facts being sufficiently established,
                    the consul ordered the soldiers to make ready their standards and arms, and
                    nothing else, for the following night; they must attack the Carthaginian camp.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Setting out at the fourth watch, leaving
                    all their packs and baggage at Beneventum, they reached the camp shortly before
                    daylight and inspired such panic that, if the camp had been placed on level
                    ground, it could undoubtedly have been taken by the first assault. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> The lofty situation protected it, also the
                    fortifications, which could not be approached from any side except by a steep
                    and difficult slope. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> At daybreak a great
                    battle blazed up. And the Carthaginians not only defended the earthwork but, as
                    they had the more favourable situation, pushed down the enemy struggling up the
                    steep slope. <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nevertheless obstinate courage surmounted
                    everything, and so the earthwork and the trenches were reached in several places
                    at once, but with many wounds and heavy loss of <pb n="p.393"/> men. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly the consul called together his <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    lieutenants and tribunes of the soldiers and told them he must give up his rash
                    undertaking; that it seemed to him safer to lead the army back that day to
                    Beneventum, and then on the following day to pitch camp close to that of the
                    enemy, so that the Campanians might not be able to leave it nor Hanno to return.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To accomplish that more readily, he would
                    summon his colleague also and his army, and they would focus the entire war upon
                    that point. These plans of the general were disrupted, when he was already
                    sounding the recall, by the shouts of the soldiers rejecting an order so lacking
                    in spirit. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nearest to the enemy happened to be
                    a Paelignian cohort, whose prefect Vibius Accaus seized the banner and threw it
                    over the enemy's earthwork. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then, with a curse
                    upon himself and the cohort if the enemy should get possession of that banner,
                    he was himself the first to dash over the trench and wall into the camp.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And already the Paelignians were fighting
                    inside the wall, when from the other side of the camp, while Valerius Flaccus,
                    tribune of the soldiers of the third legion, was reproaching the Romans for
                    their cowardice in yielding to allies the honour of capturing the camp, Titus
                    Pedanius, first centurion of the <hi rend="italics">principes,</hi> took a
                    standard away from the standard-bearer and said <quote> This standard and this
                        centurion will in a moment be inside the enemy's wall. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Let those follow who are to prevent the standard from
                        being captured by the enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> First the men of his own maniple followed him
                    as he crossed the trench, then the whole legion. And now the consul at the sight
                    of men crossing the wall changed his plan, turned from recalling his soldiers to
                    arousing <pb n="p.395"/> and encouraging them, and pointed out to them in <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> what a
                    critical and perilous situation were the bravest cohort of the allies and a
                    legion of their fellow-citizens. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And so, each
                    doing his best, over ground favourable and unfavourable, while javelins were
                    being hurled from every side and the enemy were interposing weapons and their
                    bodies, they made their way and burst in. Many wounded men, even those whose
                    strength and blood were ebbing, strove to fall inside the enemy's wall.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And so in a moment's time the camp was
                    captured, just as if pitched on level ground and not strongly fortified. Then
                    came slaughter, no longer mere battle, since everything inside the wall was in
                    confusion. </p>
                <p> Over six thousand of the enemy were slain, over seven thousand men captured,
                    including the Campanians who came for grain, and the entire train of wagons and
                    mules. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In addition there was the immense
                    booty which Hanno, having set out to plunder far and wide, had taken from farms
                    of allies of the Roman people. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then after
                    destroying the enemy's camp they returned to Beneventum, and there the two
                    consuls —for Appius Claudius came there a few days late —sold and divided the
                    booty. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And the men by whose efforts the camp
                    of the enemy had been captured, were rewarded, first of all Accaus the
                    Paelignian and Titus Pedanius, first centurion of the third legion. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Hanno, leaving Cominium Ocritum, where he received
                    news of the disaster at the camp, with the few men he happened to have with him
                    to get grain, returned in what resembled a flight rather than a march to the
                    land of the Bruttii. <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And the Campanians, hearing of what was a
                    disaster as much to themselves as to their allies, sent legates to <pb n="p.397"
                    /> Hannibal to report that the two consuls were at <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> Beneventum, a day's march
                    from Capua; that the war was all but at their gates and walls; and that, if he
                    did not come to their aid in haste, Capua would fall into the power of the enemy
                    more promptly than Arpi. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV.
                        xlvi f.</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They said that not even Tarentum, to say
                    nothing of its citadel, ought to be of such importance that he should hand over
                    to the Roman people the deserted and undefended Capua, which he had usually
                    compared with Carthage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal, promising
                    that the Campanian cause would be his concern, for the present sent two thousand
                    horsemen with his lieutenants, that with this force they might be able to
                    protect their farms from devastation. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans meantime were concerned among other
                    things for the citadel of Tarentum and the garrison there besieged. Gaius
                    Servilius, who as lieutenant had been sent by Publius Cornelius, the praetor,
                    into Etruria by authority of the senate to purchase grain, made his way through
                    the enemy's blockade into the harbour of Tarentum with a number of shiploads.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thanks to his coming, the men who until
                    then in their faint hope had often been invited by the enemy in parleys to
                    change sides were actually inviting and urging the enemy to change sides. And
                    the garrison was in fact strong enough, now that soldiers who were at Metapontum
                    had been transferred to defend the citadel of Tarentum. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the Metapontines were at once relieved of the
                    fear by which they were restrained, and went over to Hannibal. </p>
                <p> The Thurians also, on the same coast, did the same. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> What impelled them was not more the <pb n="p.399"/> revolt
                    of the Tarentines and that of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> Metapontines, with whom they were linked by
                    blood as well, being sprung from the same Achaia than anger against the Romans
                    on account of the recent execution of the hostages. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Friends and relatives of these sent a letter and messengers
                    to Hanno and Mago, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not the brother of
                        Hannibal; xvi. 7 f., 24; xviii. 1; xxi. 4. </note> who were not far away in
                    the land of the Bruttii, saying that, if they should bring up an army to their
                    walls, they would themselves deliver the city into their power. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Marcus Atinius was in command at Thurii with a garrison of
                    moderate size, and they thought that he could easily be tempted to dash rashly
                    into battle, from his confidence not so much in his soldiers, of whom he had
                    very few, as in the young men of Thurii. He had purposely organized them in
                    centuries <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So in mustering old men
                        into the service in VI. ii. 6, and freedmen in X. xxi. 4. </note> and armed
                    them with a view to such emergencies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginian generals divided their forces between them and, on entering the
                    territory of Thurii, Hanno, with the infantry column ready to attack, proceeded
                    to the city. Mago with the cavalry halted under cover of hills conveniently
                    interposed to conceal an ambuscade. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Atinius,
                    informed of the infantry column alone by scouts, led his troops out into line,
                    he being unaware both of the conspiracy within and of the enemy's ambuscade.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The infantry battle was very lacking in
                    spirit, for only a few Romans were fighting in the front line, and the men of
                    Thurii were awaiting the outcome, rather than contributing to it. And the
                    Carthaginian line purposely retreated, in order to draw the heedless enemy to
                    the other side of the hill occupied by their own cavalry. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> When they reached the place, the cavalry, suddenly
                    attacking with a shout, at once put to flight the mass of the Thurians, which
                    was 399 <pb n="p.401"/> almost undisciplined and not entirely loyal to the side
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> on
                    which they were fighting. The Romans, though surrounded and hard pressed on one
                    side by the infantry, on the other by the cavalry, nevertheless kept on fighting
                    for some time. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Finally they also faced about
                    and fled to the city. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There the traitors
                    massed together and admitted the column of their citizens through wide-open
                    gates; but when they saw the routed Romans moving toward the city, they shouted
                    that the Carthaginian was upon them, and unless they hastily closed the gates
                    the enemy also, mingling with them, would make their way into the city.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Thus they shut out the Romans and left
                    them to be slain by the enemy. Atinius, however, with a few men was admitted.
                    Then for a short time dissension continued, the other party <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In contrast with those who by admitting
                        Atinius showed their preference for the Romans. </note> being of the opinion
                    that they must yield to destiny and surrender the city to the victors.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But, as usual, chance and bad advice
                    prevailed. Atinius and his men were brought down to the sea and ships, more
                    because they wished his personal safety, on account of his mild and just rule
                    over them, than out of regard for the Romans, and then they admitted the
                    Carthaginians to the city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The consuls led their legions from Beneventum
                    into the Campanian territory, not merely to ruin the grain, which was by now
                    green, but also to besiege Capua. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> They
                    thought to make theirs a notable consulship by the destruction of so rich a
                    city, and at the same time to remove a great disgrace from the empire, in that
                    the revolt of a city so near had been unpunished for three years. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It was really over three years, from
                            <date when="-0216">216 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> But, not to leave Beneventum without a
                    garrison, and, with a view to <pb n="p.403"/> emergencies, if Hannibal should
                    come to Capua, as <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> they had no doubt he would do, to lend aid to his allies, in
                    order that they might be able to withstand the attack of his cavalry, they
                    ordered Tiberius Gracchus to come from Lucania with his cavalry and light-armed
                    troops to Beneventum. He was to put some one in command of the legions and
                    permanent camps, in order to control the situation in Lucania. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As Gracchus was sacrificing before leaving
                    Lucania, an unfavourable portent occurred. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    After the slaying of the victim two snakes gliding stealthily up to the entrails
                    ate part of the liver, and on being noticed vanished suddenly from sight.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When for that reason the sacrifice was
                    repeated on the advice of the soothsayers, and while the entrails were being
                    kept with greater care, they relate that the snakes for the second and the third
                    time gliding up tasted the liver and went away unharmed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Although the soothsayers had warned in advance that that
                    portent applied to the general, and that he must beware of men in hiding and of
                    covert plans, still the impending fate could not be averted by any foresight.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was a Lucanian, Flavus, head of that
                    party of the Lucanians which remained on the Roman side, although the other
                    party had revolted to Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And he was now
                    in the second year of his office, having been elected praetor by that same
                    party. He suddenly changed his intention and, seeking to find favour with the
                    Carthaginian, was not satisfied to change sides himself nor to draw the
                    Lucanians into revolt without ratifying his agreement with the enemy by the
                    life-blood of the general, betrayed though at the same time his guest-friend.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He came <pb n="p.405"/> to Mago, who was
                    in command in the country of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> Bruttii, for a secret conference, and received
                    his promise that, if he should surrender the Roman commander into their hands,
                    the Lucanians as free men with their own laws would be accepted as friends.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then led the Carthaginian to a place to
                    which he said he would bring Gracchus with a few men; there Mago should conceal
                    armed infantry and cavalry; and the hiding-place had room, he said, for a very
                    large number. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After they had sufficiently
                    examined the spot and reconnoitred all around, a day was settled upon for the
                    execution of the plan. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Flavus came to the
                    Roman commander, saying that he had begun an important business for the
                    completion of which he needed Gracchus' own help; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> that he had persuaded the magistrates of all the peoples
                    which in that general commotion in Italy had gone over to the Carthaginians, to
                    return to the friendship of the Romans, since the Roman state also, which had
                    been nearly destroyed by the disaster at Cannae, was daily improving and
                    increasing, while Hannibal's power was growing feebler and had been reduced
                    almost to nothing. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To their old offence, he
                    said, the Romans would not be implacable; no people had ever been more easily
                    entreated and readier to grant forgiveness. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    How often had a rebellion even of their own ancestors been pardoned! These
                    things he said he had told them; but that they preferred to hear these same
                    statements from Gracchus himself, and to take hold of his right hand there
                    before them, and to carry with them that pledge of his honour. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> He had appointed for their council a place out of sight,
                    not far from the Roman camp; there in a few words it could be <pb n="p.407"/>
                    settled that the whole Lucanian people should be <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> under the protection of
                    the Romans and in alliance with them. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Gracchus, thinking that both speech and proposal were free from guile, and
                    misled by the plausibility of it, set out from the camp with his lictors and a
                    troop of cavalry, and with a guest-friend as his guide fell into the ambush.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The enemy suddenly came out, and, to
                    leave no doubt about his treachery, Flavus joined them. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> Javelins assail Gracchus and his horsemen from every side.
                    He springs from his horse, bids the rest to do the same and urges them to
                    ennoble by courage the one thing fortune has left open to them. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> But to a few men surrounded by a multitude, in a
                    valley hedged about by forest and mountains, what was left, he asked, but death?
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The one thing that mattered was whether
                    they were to submit themselves like sheep to be slaughtered unavenged, or, far
                    from calmly awaiting the outcome, were to be altogether bent on angry attack,
                    and then, daring and doing, drenched by the blood of the enemy, among the heaps
                    of arms and bodies of their dying foes, were to fall. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> They must all attack the Lucanian traitor and deserter. The
                    man who sent that victim before him to the lower world would find great
                    distinction and for his own death an extraordinary consolation. <milestone
                        n="21" unit="section"/> While thus speaking he wound his general's cloak
                    around his left arm —for they had not taken even shields with them —and attacked
                    the enemy. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> The battle was out of all
                    proportion to the number of men engaged. The bodies of the Romans were
                    especially unprotected against javelins, and were pierced by them, as they could
                    be thrown from higher ground all around into the hollow valley. <milestone
                        n="23" unit="section"/> Gracchus, who <pb n="p.409"/> was by this time
                    stripped of his defenders, the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> Carthaginians strove to capture alive. But
                    catching sight of his Lucanian guest-friend among the enemy, he dashed into the
                    dense ranks with such animosity that he could not be spared without the loss of
                    many lives. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> Mago at once sent the corpse to
                    Hannibal and ordered it to be placed before the general's tribune together with
                    the captured fasces. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> If this is the true report, Gracchus perished
                    in Lucania, on the Old Plains, as they are called. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There are some who maintain that in the region
                    of Beneventum, by the river Calor, he had gone out of the camp with his lictors
                    and three slaves to bathe, while enemies, as it <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> happened, were hiding among the willows growing on the
                    banks, and was slain, naked and unarmed and defending himself with stones which
                    the river rolls along. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There are some writers
                    who say that on the advice of the soothsayers he had gone five hundred paces
                    from the camp to make atonement on an uncontaminated spot for the prodigies
                    mentioned above, and was overpowered by two troops of Numidians who chanced to
                    be in ambush there. So far are both the place and the manner of his death from
                    being established, in spite of his eminence and distinction. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In regard to Gracchus's funeral also reports vary. Some
                    relate that he was buried in the Roman camp by his own men, others —and this is
                    the prevalent report —that <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> by Hannibal's order
                    a pyre was erected directly outside the gate of the Carthaginian camp, and that
                    the army defiled under arms, with dances by the Spanish troops and such
                    movements of weapons and bodies as were customary for each tribe, while Hannibal
                    himself <pb n="p.411"/> honoured the obsequies with every tribute in act <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> and word.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These are the statements of those who
                    vouch for its occurrence in Lucania. If you incline to believe those who state
                    that he was slain at the river Calor, the enemy gained possession of Gracchus'
                    head only. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This being brought to Hannibal,
                    Carthalo was at once sent by him to bring it to the Roman camp and Gnaeus
                    Cornelius the quaestor. He conducted the funeral of the general in the camp,
                    while the people of Beneventum joined with the army in doing him honour. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the consuls, on entering the Campanian
                    region, were devastating it far and wide, being alarmed and dismayed by a sally
                    of the Capuans and of Mago with his cavalry, they recalled their widely
                    scattered soldiers to the standards, and being routed almost before their line
                    was formed, lost over fifteen hundred men. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Upon this the great overconfidence of a people naturally proud was greatly
                    increased, and they sought to provoke the Romans by many battles. But a single
                    engagement incautiously and imprudently begun had made the consuls more careful
                    to be on their guard. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> One small occurrence,
                    however, restored the courage of one army and lessened the boldness of the
                    other. But in war nothing is so slight as not at times to bring about a great
                    result. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius Crispinus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not to be confused with another man of
                        the same name in xxvi. 4; XXIV. xxxix. 12; and frequently in XXVII. </note>
                    had one Badius, a Campanian, as his guest-friend, linked to him by intimate
                    hospitality. Friendship had grown because in an illness Badius had been
                    generously and kindly nursed at the house of Crispinus at Rome before the
                    rebellion of Campania. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This Badius at the time
                    came up to the outposts stationed before the gate and bade them call <pb
                        n="p.413"/> Crispinus. When this was reported to Crispinus, he <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> went a
                    little beyond the others, thinking a friendly and intimate conversation was
                    wanted, since the memory of a personal tie lingered in spite of the rupture of
                    public treaties. When they had come in sight of each other, <quote>I challenge
                        you to battle, Crispinus,</quote> said Badius. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Let us mount our horses and, with others kept at a distance, decide
                        which is the better warrior. </quote> In reply Crispinus said that neither
                    he nor Badius lacked enemies on whom to show his courage. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> For himself, even if he should meet the other in
                    battle-line, he would avoid him, lest he stain his right hand with the blood of
                    a guest-friend. And he turned and was walking away. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Then in truth the Campanian more fiercely reviled the
                    effeminacy and cowardice of Crispinus and hurled reproaches which he himself
                    deserved against an innocent man, calling him a guest-enemy and a man who
                    pretended to spare one to whom he knew he was not equal. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> If he thought that with the rupture of public treaties
                    private ties had not also been broken, then, he said, Badius the Campanian,
                    openly in the hearing of two armies, renounced the guest-friendship of Titus
                    Quinctius Crispinus the Roman. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For himself,
                    an enemy, nothing was hallowed by association, nothing by compact, with him, an
                    enemy, since he had come to attack his native city and the Penates of the state
                    and of the household. If he was a man, let him come on. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Crispinus, after long hesitation, was prevailed upon by his
                    comrades not to allow the Campanian to revile him with impunity. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> And so he delayed only long enough to consult the
                    generals as to whether they permitted him to fight out of ranks against an enemy
                    who challenged him. <pb n="p.415"/> With their permission he took his arms and
                    mounted <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    his horse, and addressing Badius by name called him out to battle. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> The Campanian made no delay; riding directly at each
                    other they clashed. Crispinus with his spear pierced Badius' left shoulder above
                    the shield; and after he fell wounded, leaped upon him from his horse, that, now
                    dismounted, he might despatch the fallen. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Badius, not to be overpowered, left shield and horse and fled to his own men.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Crispinus, decked with spoils and
                    displaying the horse and captured arms and his bloody spear, was conducted with
                    much praise and congratulation on the part of the soldiers to the consuls, and
                    there he was highly praised and rewarded with gifts. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, having moved his camp from the
                    region of Beneventum to the vicinity of Capua, led his troops out into
                    battle-line on the third day after his arrival. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Since in his absence the Campanians had had a successful battle a few days
                    before, he had no doubt whatever that the Romans would be much less able to
                    withstand himself and his repeatedly victorious army. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But once the battle had begun, the Roman line was hard
                    pressed, especially by the cavalry charge, being overwhelmed by their darts,
                    until the signal was given to the cavalry to urge their horses against the
                    enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thus a cavalry battle was in progress
                    when the distant sight of the Sempronian army, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">For the forces Gracchus had commanded cf. xv. 20.</note>
                    commanded by Gnaeus Cornelius, the quaestor, inspired in both armies the same
                    fear that fresh enemies were approaching. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As
                    if by agreement the signal for recall was given on both sides, and marching back
                    to the camp they separated on almost even terms. Yet a larger number fell on the
                        <pb n="p.417"/> Roman side because of the first charge of the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> horsemen.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thereupon the consuls, in order to draw
                    Hannibal away from Capua, marched off the following night in different
                    directions, Fulvius into the region of Cumae, Claudius into Lucania. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The next day Hannibal, on being informed that the
                    Roman camp was empty and that they had marched away in different directions in
                    two columns, was at first uncertain which to follow, but pushed on <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> in pursuit of Appius, who after leading the enemy
                    around wherever he pleased, returned by a different road to Capua. </p>
                <p> Hannibal had another opportunity for success presented to him in this region.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There was one Marcus Centenius, with the
                    cognomen Paenula, conspicuous among the centurions of the highest rank <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A <hi rend="italics">primi pili
                            centurio</hi> (or <hi rend="italics">primus pilus</hi> ) was the ranking
                        centurion of his legion, commanding the first century of the first maniple
                        of the <hi rend="italics">triarii.</hi>
                    </note> for his huge body and his courage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Having finished his military service, he was brought into the senate by Publius
                    Cornelius Sulla, a praetor, and begged the fathers to give him five thousand
                    soldiers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He, being well-acquainted, he said,
                    both with the enemy and the country, would soon accomplish something worth
                    while, and as for the arts by which both our generals and our armies had till
                    then been ensnared, he would use them against their inventor. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> This was not more stupidly promised than stupidly believed,
                    as if the qualities of soldier and general were the same. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Instead of five thousand, eight thousand soldiers were
                    given him, half of them citizens, half allies. And he himself on his march
                    raised a considerable number of volunteers from the farms, and with his army
                    nearly doubled reached Lucania, where Hannibal had halted after vainly pursuing
                    Claudius. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The result was never in doubt, <pb
                        n="p.419"/> as between Hannibal as commander and a centurion, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> and
                    between armies one of which was a veteran in victory and the other altogether
                    raw, in large part also irregular and half-armed. When the columns were in sight
                    of each other and neither side refused battle, the lines were immediately drawn
                    up. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> They fought, however, as was to be
                    expected where nothing was fairly matched. For more than two hours the battle
                    continued, since hope inspired the Roman line so long as their commander held
                    his ground. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Not only in keeping with his old
                    reputation, but also for fear of future disgrace, if he should survive a
                    disaster brought on by his own rashness, he threw himself upon the weapons of
                    the enemy and fell, whereupon the Roman line was at once routed. <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> But, as all the roads were occupied by cavalry, so
                    far were they from having any route open even for flight that out of so great a
                    multitude barely a thousand escaped, while the rest scattering met death in
                    various forms. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The siege of Capua was resumed with intensity
                    by the consuls, and all that was needed for the purpose was being brought
                    together and made ready. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Casilinum was the
                    depot for grain. At the mouth of the Volturnus, where there is now a city, a
                    stronghold was fortified, and there and at Puteoli, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV. vii. 10.</note> which Fabius Maximus had
                    previously fortified, a garrison was placed, that the sea in that neighbourhood
                    and the river might be in their power. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To
                    these two strongholds by the sea the grain which had been sent recently from
                    Sardinia and that which the praetor Marcus Junius had purchased in Etruria was
                    transported from Ostia, so that the army might have a supply through the winter.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But in addition to the disaster incurred
                    in Lucania, the army of <pb n="p.421"/> slavevolunteers also, which had served
                    with the utmost <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> loyalty while Gracchus lived, abandoned its standards, as if
                    discharged by the death of the general. </p>
                <p> Hannibal did not wish that Capua should be neglected nor his allies abandoned in
                    such a crisis. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But in view of a success due to
                    the rashness of one Roman general he was eager for an opportunity to surprise a
                    second general and army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Apulian legates were
                    informing him that the praetor Gnaeus Fulvius had at first been very active
                    while besieging some Apulian cities which had revolted to Hannibal; but that
                    later, owing to unmerited success, both he himself and his soldiers, who were
                    loaded with booty, had gone to such lengths in licence and indifference that
                    there was no military discipline. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hannibal,
                    who frequently at other times, and particularly within a few days, had
                    discovered what an army is under an incompetent general, moved his camp into
                    Apulia. <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Near Herdonea <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV. xx. 8.</note> were Roman legions and the
                    praetor Fulvius. When the news reached them there that the enemy were
                    approaching, they barely refrained from catching up their standards and going
                    out into battle-line without orders from the praetor. And nothing restrained
                    them more than the hope, now beyond question, that they would do so at their own
                    discretion whenever they pleased. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    following night Hannibal, knowing that there had been an uproar in the camp and
                    that many, calling to arms, had over-confidently pressed the commander to give
                    the signal, had no doubt that an opportunity for a victory was offered.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He accordingly posted three thousand
                    lightly equipped soldiers in farmhouses near by and in the thickets and the
                    woods, to come out of their hiding-places all at once, <pb n="p.423"/> when the
                    signal was given. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And he ordered Mago <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> and about
                    two thousand horsemen to lie in wait along all the roads in the direction which
                    he believed the flight would take. After making these preparations at night, he
                    led his troops out into line at daybreak. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor
                    did Fulvius hesitate, dragged into it not so much by any hope of his own as by
                    the haphazard impulse of the soldiers. And so, with the same recklessness with
                    which they went out to form, they drew up even the line of battle according to
                    the whim of soldiers who happened to dash forward and take their stand wherever
                    their own fancy had carried them, and then capriciously or in fear abandoned
                    their positions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The first legion and the left
                        <hi rend="italics">ala</hi> were placed in front, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">alae</hi> were auxiliaries of
                        the allies, each <hi rend="italics">ala</hi> equal in strength to a legion
                        (4200 men). When drawn up as here the second line would be made up of the
                        other legion and the <hi rend="italics">ala dextra.</hi> Such a formation
                        was at times employed instead of the usual three lines, <hi rend="italics"
                            >hastati, principes, triarii,</hi> of the legionaries. Cf. XXVII. i. 8;
                        ii. 6. </note> and the line was made very long. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Although the tribunes shouted that in depth it had no power
                    to resist, and that wherever the enemy should make their attack they would
                    pierce it, the men in line allowed no advice that was helpful to reach even
                    their ears, not to say their attention. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And
                    there was Hannibal, surely not that sort of a general, nor with that sort of an
                    army, drawn up in that fashion. Consequently the Romans did not withstand even
                    their shout and the first onset. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The general,
                    a match for Centenius in folly and recklessness, but in courage by no means to
                    be compared with him, seeing that the line was giving way and his own men in
                    confusion, seized a horse and with about two hundred horsemen made his escape.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The rest of the line, beaten back in
                    front and then surrounded in the rear and on the wings, was so cut to pieces
                    that out of eighteen thousand men not more than two thousand escaped. The camp
                    was occupied by the enemy. </p>
                <pb n="p.425"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of these disasters one after
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    another had reached Rome, great sorrow and alarm, it is true, took possession of
                    the state. Nevertheless because the consuls, to whom fell the supreme command,
                    were up to that time successful, they were less disturbed by these disasters.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the senate. </note> sent Gaius Laetorius and
                    Marcus Metilius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In XXII. xxv. 3 he
                        was <hi rend="italics">tribunus plebis.</hi>
                    </note> as legates to the consuls, to inform them that they should carefully
                    gather up the remnants of the two armies, and see to it that in fear and despair
                    they did not surrender to the enemy, as had happened after the disaster at
                    Cannae; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> also that they should search for the
                    deserters from the army of slave-volunteers. The same duty was given to Publius
                    Cornelius, to whom the levy also had been assigned. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And he issued an edict in the market-towns and local
                    centres, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. above, note on v.
                        6.</note> that search should be made for the slave-volunteers, and that they
                    be brought back to their standards. All these things were done with the utmost
                    diligence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius, the consul, placed Decimus
                    Junius in command at the mouth of the Volturnus and Marcus Aurelius Cotta at
                    Puteoli, in order that, as fast as ships came in from Etruria and Sardinia, they
                    should send the grain at once to the camps. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                    himself, on returning to Capua, found his colleague Quintus Fulvius transporting
                    everything from Casilinum and making every preparation for the siege of Capua.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then they both invested the city and
                    summoned the praetor, Claudius Nero, from the Claudian camp at Suessula. He,
                    leaving there only a garrison of moderate size to hold the place, likewise came
                    down with all the rest of his forces to Capua. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Thus three headquarters were set up around Capua. There were three armies too
                    that, <pb n="p.427"/> fell to work on different sides, made ready to encircle
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> the
                    city with a ditch and an earthwork, and erected redoubts at moderate intervals;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and at many points at the same time they
                    fought with such success against the Campanians who endeavoured to hinder the
                    works that finally the Campanians remained inside the gates and the wall.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But before these siege-works could be
                    made continuous, legates were sent to Hannibal, to complain that Capua had been
                    deserted by him and almost given back to the Romans, and to implore him to bring
                    aid, then at least, to men not only besieged but also encircled by
                    entrenchments. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consuls received a letter
                    from Publius Cornelius, the praetor, ordering <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">In the name of the senate.</note> that, before enclosing
                    Capua with their works, they should permit such of the Campanians as wished to
                    do so to leave Capua and carry their possessions with them. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Those who should leave before the fifteenth of March were
                    to be free men and to keep all their property; those who left after that date
                    and those who remained there were to be reckoned enemies. These terms were
                    published to the Campanians, and were received with such contempt by them that
                    they were actually insulting and made threats. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Hannibal had led his legions from Herdonea to
                    Tarentum in the hope of getting possession of the citadel of Tarentum either by
                    force or by ruse. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When this did not succeed,
                    he turned aside to Brundisium, thinking that town would certainly be betrayed.
                    While there also he was wasting time, the Campanian legates came to him with
                    complaints and at the same time entreaties. Hannibal replied to them grandly
                    that he had previously raised a siege, and that now also the consuls would not
                        <pb n="p.429"/> withstand his coming. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    With this hope the legates were <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> sent away, and it was with difficulty
                        <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> that they were able to return to Capua,
                    now surrounded by two trenches and a double earthwork. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just as Capua was being encircled the siege of
                    Syracuse came to an end, expedited not only by the vigour and valour of the
                    general and the army but also by treachery within. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For Marcellus, who at the beginning of the spring had been
                    uncertain whether to shift the war to Agrigentum against Himilco and
                    Hippocrates, or to press the siege <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> of
                    Syracuse, saw indeed that the city, impregnable in its position both on the
                    landward and the seaward side, could not be taken by assault, nor by starvation,
                    inasmuch as it was sustained by almost unhampered supplies from Carthage.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, to leave nothing untried,
                    deserters from Syracuse —and there were in the Roman lines some men of highest
                    rank who during the estrangement from the Romans had been driven out because
                    they were averse to a change of policy —were ordered by him to sound men of
                    their faction in conferences, and to give them a pledge that, if Syracuse should
                    be surrendered, they should live as free men and under their own laws.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For a conference there was no opportunity,
                    because the suspicious attitude of many men had attracted the attention and the
                    eyes of all, to prevent such an offence from passing unnoticed. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> A single slave belonging to the exiles was admitted to the
                    city as a deserter and by meeting a few men made a beginning of parleys on a
                    matter of such moment. Then some men were hidden under nets on a fishing vessel,
                    and thus sailed around to the Roman camp <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Beyond the northern Wall of Dionysius, not far from the
                        Hexapylon. </note> and talked with the deserters. And <pb n="p.431"/> the
                    same men did this repeatedly in the same way, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> also others and again
                    others. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Finally they amounted to about eighty.
                    And when now everything had been arranged for the betrayal, information was
                    brought to Epicydes by one Attalus, who was outraged that the matter had not
                    been confided to him, and they were all put to death with torture. </p>
                <p> This hope having proved false, another at once took its place. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Damippus a Lacedaemonian, who had been sent from Syracuse
                    to King Philip, had been captured by Roman ships. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Epicydes was very much concerned to ransom him at any cost,
                    and Marcellus also was not averse, since the Romans were already courting the
                    friendship of the Aetolians, whose allies the Lacedaemonians were. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The men sent to confer in regard to the man's ransom
                    thought that the most convenient place for both sides, and just half-way, was at
                    the Trogili Harbour, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Merely a small
                        bay, of no value for large vessels.</note> near the tower called Galeagra.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The tower was probably beyond the
                        wall in the open country. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As they came there repeatedly, one of the
                    Romans, observing the wall from near at hand, by counting the courses and making
                    his own estimate of the height of each on its face, measured the height of the
                    wall as nearly as he could by guesswork. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And
                    thinking it considerably lower than his own previous estimate of it and that of
                    all the rest, and that it could be scaled by ladders even of moderate length, he
                    reported to Marcellus. It did not seem a matter to be despised. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> But since the place, being more closely guarded for
                    the very reason mentioned, could not be approached, they cast about for an
                    opportunity. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And this was offered by a
                    deserter, reporting that the feast of Diana was being observed for three days,
                    and that, since other things were lacking during the siege, it was with wine
                    that the <pb n="p.433"/> banquets were more lavishly provided, this being <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> furnished
                    to the entire populace by Epicydes and distributed among the tribes <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the <foreign xml:lang="greek">,</foreign>
                        corresponding in a way to the Roman tribes. </note> by leading citizens. </p>
                <p> On learning of this, Marcellus conferred with a few tribunes of the soldiers,
                    and after these had chosen centurions and soldiers able to dare and do a thing
                    of such importance, and after ladders had been secretly made ready, he ordered
                    the signal to be given to the others to eat early and then rest. In the night,
                    he said, they must go on a raid. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then, when
                    it seemed to be late enough for <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> those who
                    had begun their feast during the day to be sated, he thought, with their wine
                    and now to be falling asleep, he ordered the soldiers of one maniple to carry
                    the ladders. And about a thousand armed men were led in a thin column to the
                    place in silence. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> When the first men without
                    noise and confusion had made their way to the top of the wall, the others
                    followed one after another, since the boldness of those ahead of them gave
                    courage even to the wavering. <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The thousand armed men had already taken a
                    part of the wall, when the rest of the forces were brought up, and on more
                    ladders they were making their way to the top of the wall, a signal having been
                    given from the Hexapylon. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For this,
                        the most important gate to the north, cf. XXIV. xxi. 7; xxxii. 5, etc. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To that point they had advanced without
                    encountering a soul, since many of the enemy, after feasting in the towers,
                    either had been put to sleep by their wine or, while half-intoxicated, were
                    still drinking. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A few of them, however, they
                    surprised and slew in their beds. Near the Hexapylon there is a postern. This
                    they had begun to break open with great force, and from the wall the signal had
                    been given by a trumpet, as agreed; and now the fighting was from every side, no
                    longer by stealth, but with open violence. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For
                        <pb n="p.435"/> they had reached Epipolae, a well-guarded region, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> and the
                    enemy had rather to be terrified than deceived, as they were in fact terrified.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For as soon as they heard the notes of the
                    trumpet and the shouting of the men holding the walls and a part of the city,
                    the guards, thinking the whole city was occupied, fled, some of them along the
                    wall; others leaped from the wall or were pushed over by the panic-stricken
                    crowd. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A large part of the people, however,
                    were unaware of the great danger; for all were heavy with wine and sleep, and in
                    a city of immense size knowledge concerning its quarters failed to reach the
                    whole. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At daybreak Marcellus burst open the
                    Hexapylon, and entering the city with his entire force awakened everybody and
                    set them to arming themselves and bringing aid, if possible, to a city now all
                    but captured. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Epicydes came out from the Island, which they
                    themselves call Nasos, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Doric for
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">,</foreign> Insula. </note> with a quickly
                    moving column, not doubting that he would drive out a few men who, owing to the
                    carelessness of the guards had got over the wall. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When men met him in alarm, he would say that they were
                    adding to the confusion and bringing exaggerated and unduly alarming news. On
                    discovering that in and near Epipolae armed men were everywhere, he merely
                    challenged the enemy by a few missiles and then marched his column back into
                    Achradina. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He feared, not so much the attack
                    of the enemy and their great numbers, as that some treachery within the city
                    might have opportunity to break out, and he might find the gates of Achradina
                    and the Island closed during the disturbance. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Marcellus, on entering the walls and from the higher ground viewing one of the
                    most beautiful of all cities <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Timaeus,
                        the historian of Sicily, had called Syracuse the greatest of Greek cities,
                        the most beautiful of all cities; Cicero, <hi rend="italics">de Re
                            Publica</hi> III. 43; <hi rend="italics">in Verrem</hi> IV. 117. </note>
                    in <pb n="p.437"/> that age lying before his eyes, is said to have wept, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> partly for
                    joy over his great achievement, partly for the ancient glory of the city.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The sinking of the fleets of the
                    Athenians and the destruction of two mighty armies along with two very
                    distinguished generals <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Nicias and Demosthenes. </note> came to his
                    mind, and so many wars waged with so great a risk against the Carthaginians;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> tyrants and kings, so many and so
                    wealthy, above all Hiero, a king vividly remembered and also, above all that his
                    own merit and success had given him, conspicuous for his favours to the Roman
                    people. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Since all that came to mind and the
                    thought suggested itself that now in the course of an hour everything there
                    would be in flames and reduced to ashes, before <milestone n="15??"
                        unit="section"/> advancing his standards into Achradina, he sent forward the
                    Syracusans who had been within the Roman lines, as has been said before, in
                    order to entice the enemy by mild words to surrender the city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Holding the gates and walls of Achradina were
                    chiefly deserters, who had no hope of pardon if terms were made. They did not
                    allow the men either to approach the walls or to speak to any one. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And so Marcellus, now that this attempt was
                    fruitless, ordered the standards to be carried back to Euryalus. This is a hill
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At the western apex of the
                        triangle; a narrow ridge nearly 500 feet above the sea, with a commanding
                        view. </note> in the most distant part of the city, facing away from the
                    sea, and commanding the road which leads to the country and the interior of the
                    island, very conveniently placed for receiving supplies. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In command of this citadel <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The crowning point of Dionysius' great fortifications,
                        and still accounted the strongest of Greek fortresses, with its three
                        fosses, its towers, and a complicated system of tunnels cut through solid
                        rock. </note> was Philodemus the Argive, posted there by Epicydes. Sosis,
                    one of the slayers <pb n="p.439"/> of the tyrant, was sent to him by Marcellus,
                    and after <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> being balked and put off by the delivery of a long speech, he
                    reported to Marcellus that Philodemus had taken time to consider. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Philodemus was postponing from day to day, waiting
                    for Hippocrates and Himilco to move up their camp and legions, and not doubting
                    that, if he should get them into the citadel, the Roman army, shut up within the
                    city walls, could be destroyed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Consequently
                    Marcellus, seeing that Euryalus could neither be won by surrender nor by
                    assault, pitched his camp between Neapolis and Tycha, these being the names of
                    quarters of the city, virtually cities in themselves. For he feared that, if he
                    should enter thickly settled parts, the soldiers in their eagerness for booty
                    could not be restrained from scattering. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To
                    this camp came legates from Tycha and Neapolis with fillets and woollen bands,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV. xxx. 14.</note> praying
                    that they be spared bloodshed and fires. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Marcellus held a council in regard to their prayers —such they were rather than
                    demands —and with the approval of all gave an order to the soldiers that no one
                    should injure a free person; everything else would be spoil. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The camp was enclosed by bricks from house-walls <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Here the text is very uncertain, but
                        most of the emendations are open to serious objections, as involving
                        Marcellus' use of more or less continuous house-walls —a feeble defence, and
                        not easily to be reconciled with the idea of an open space lying between two
                        built-up quarters of the city. </note> to serve as a wall of defence. At
                    those camp gates which opened toward the streets outposts and detachments were
                    stationed by Marcellus, that no attack upon the camp might occur while the
                    soldiers were <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> dispersed. Then at a given
                    signal the soldiers scattered. And although doors were forced and everywhere
                    were the sounds of panic and uproar, they nevertheless refrained from bloodshed.
                    To plundering there was no limit until they had carried away all the possessions
                    accumulated in a long-continued <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.441"/> prosperity. Meanwhile even Philodemus, having <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> no hope of
                    assistance and receiving assurance that he might return unharmed to Epicydes,
                    led his garrison out and surrendered the hill to the <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Romans. While the attention of all was diverted in the
                    direction of the uproar of a city in part captured, Bomilcar, favoured by such a
                    night that on account of a violent storm the Roman fleet could <milestone
                        n="12??" unit="section"/> not ride at anchor in open water, came out of the
                    harbour of Syracuse with thirty-five ships, and with no enemy to prevent, put to
                    sea, leaving fifty-five ships to Epicydes and the <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Syracusans. And after informing the Carthaginians how
                    critical was the situation at Syracuse, he returned after a few days with a
                    hundred ships. He was presented with many gifts, it is reported, by Epicydes out
                    of the royal treasures of Hiero. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus, after getting possession of
                    Euryalus and garrisoning it, was relieved of one fear, that some troops of the
                    enemy in the rear might be admitted to the citadel and embarrass his men, hemmed
                    in and hampered by the walls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He thereupon
                    laid siege to Achradina with three camps placed in suitable positions, in the
                    hope of reducing the beleaguered to absolute want. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When the outposts on both sides had been inactive for some
                    days, suddenly the arrival of Hippocrates and Himilco had the effect that the
                    Romans were actually besieged on all sides. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For Hippocrates, after fortifying a camp by the Great Harbour and giving the
                    signal to the forces occupying Achradina, attacked the old Roman camp, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV. xxxiii. 3; xxxix. 12.</note>
                    which was commanded by Crispinus, at the same time that Epicydes made a sally
                    against Marcellus' outposts, and just when the Carthaginian fleet put in to the
                    shore lying between the city and <pb n="p.443"/> the Roman camp, to make it
                    impossible for any force <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 212</note> to be sent to the aid of Crispinus by Marcellus. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> However, it was more of an uproar than a battle that
                    the enemy offered. For Crispinus not only drove Hippocrates back from his
                    fortifications, but also pursued him as he fled in disorder, and Marcellus
                    likewise forced Epicydes into the city. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And
                    now, even for the future, he seemed to have sufficiently insured that there
                    should be no danger from their sudden raids. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Then in addition pestilence brought to both sides a calamity which forthwith
                    diverted the attention of the two armies from strategy. For owing to the autumn
                    season and places naturally unhealthy, unendurable heat affected the health of
                    nearly all the men in both camps, but much more outside the city than within.
                    And at first they sickened and died owing to the season and their position.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Later the mere care of the ill and
                    contagion spread the disease, so that those who had fallen ill died neglected
                    and abandoned, or else they carried off with them those who sat by them and
                    those who nursed, having caught the same malignant disease. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> And so every day funerals and death were before their eyes,
                    and wailings were heard on all sides day and night. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Finally, from habituation to misery they had so lost their
                    humane feelings that, so far from escorting the dead with tears and the wailing
                    that was their due, they did not even carry them out and bury them; and dead
                    bodies lay strewn about before the eyes of men awaiting a like death, and the
                    dead seriously affected the ill, the ill the sound, not only through fear, but
                    also by putrefaction and the pestilent odour of corpses. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> And some choosing to die by the sword, dashed into the
                    outposts of <pb n="p.445"/> the enemy single-handed. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> A much more violent <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> epidemic, however, had
                    attacked the Carthaginian camp than the Roman. For the Romans in their long
                    blockade of Syracuse had grown more accustomed to the climate and the water.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Of the enemy's army, the Sicilians
                    scattered, each to his own neighbouring city, as soon as they saw that the
                    disease <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> was spreading owing to the
                    unwholesomeness of the place, while the Carthaginians, who had no refuge
                    anywhere, with even their generals, Hippocrates and Himilco, perished to the
                    last man. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Marcellus, as soon as the
                    pestilence began to be so serious, had transferred his soldiers into the city,
                    and shelter and shade had revived the invalids. Nevertheless many in the Roman
                    army were carried off by the same pestilence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian land-army having been
                    destroyed, the Sicilians who had been Hippocrates' soldiers had occupied . . .,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> One of the two omitted towns was
                        perhaps Bidis, mentioned by Cicero <hi rend="italics">in Verrem</hi> II. 53.
                        Rossbach and Conway thought that the other might be Dascon (Thucydides and
                        Diodorus). </note> not large towns, but defended both by situation and
                    fortifications. One of them is three miles from Syracuse, the other fifteen
                    miles. To these they were bringing supplies from their own communities and also
                    summoning auxiliaries. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Meanwhile Bomilcar left
                    for Carthage a second time with his fleet, and he set forth the situation of
                    their allies in such terms as to inspire hope, not only that effectual aid could
                    be lent to them, but also that the Romans could be captured in the virtually
                    captured city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He thus prevailed upon them to
                    send with him as many transports as possible, laden with all kinds of supplies,
                    and to enlarge his fleet. Accordingly, setting out from Carthage with a hundred
                    and thirty warships and seven hundred transports, he had winds quite favourable
                    for the <pb n="p.447"/> crossing to Sicily. But the same winds did not allow
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> him
                    to round Pachynum. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The report at first of
                    Bomilcar's coming, and then its unexpected delay, brought rejoicing and fear by
                    turns to Romans and Syracusans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Upon that
                    Epicydes, fearing that, if the same winds which were then holding should
                    continue <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> to blow from the east for several
                    days, the Carthaginian fleet would make for Africa again, turned over Achradina
                    to the commanders of the mercenaries and sailed to meet Bomilcar, who <milestone
                        n="7??" unit="section"/> was keeping his fleet in a roadstead facing Africa.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He feared a naval battle, not so much
                    because he was inferior in his forces and the number of his ships —in fact he
                    had even more —as because the winds then blowing were more favourable to the
                    Roman fleet than to his own. Nevertheless Epicydes gained his consent to try the
                    fortune of a naval engagement. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And Marcellus
                    too, seeing that a Sicilian army was being brought together from the entire
                    island and at the same time a Carthaginian fleet was approaching with unlimited
                    supplies, and fearing that he might be hard pressed by land and sea, being shut
                    up within the enemies' city, decided, although he was inferior in the number of
                    his ships, to prevent Bomilcar from reaching Syracuse. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The two opposing fleets lay on this side and that of the
                    promontory of Pachynum, ready to engage as soon as calm weather should enable
                    them to put to sea. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And so, as the southeast
                    wind, which had been blowing hard for some days, was now dropping, Bomilcar was
                    the first to get under weigh. And at first his fleet appeared to be heading out
                    to sea, the more readily to round the promontory. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> But on seeing that the Roman ships were steering towards
                        <pb n="p.449"/> him, Bomilcar, alarmed by something unforeseen, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> made sail
                    for open water, and after sending messengers to Heraclea <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXIV. xxxv. 3.</note> to command the transports to
                    return thence to Africa, he himself sailed along the coast of Sicily and made
                    for Tarentum. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Epicydes, suddenly bereft of a
                    hope so high, in order not to return, only to share the siege of a city in large
                    part captured, sailed to Agrigentum, intending to await the outcome, rather than
                    to set anything in motion from there. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these things were reported to the camp of
                    the Sicilians, that Epicydes had left Syracuse, that the island had been
                    abandoned by the Carthaginians and almost handed over a second time to the
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Romans, after first ascertaining by
                    conferences the wish of the besieged, they sent legates to Marcellus to make
                    terms for the surrender of the city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was
                    virtually agreed that all that had anywhere belonged to the kings should belong
                    to the Romans, that everything else should be secured to the Sicilians along
                    with freedom and their own laws. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly
                    the legates summoned to a conference the men to whom power had been entrusted by
                    Epicydes, and said that they had been sent by the army of the Sicilians at the
                    same time to Marcellus and to them, in order that all, the besieged and those
                    who had been outside of the operations, might share the same lot and neither
                    party make any special terms for itself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And
                    then, being admitted by them, that they might speak with their relatives and
                    guest-friends, they explained the terms which they had already settled with
                    Marcellus, and by holding out assurances of safety prevailed upon them to join
                    with themselves in an attack upon Epicydes' prefects, Polyclitus and Philistion
                    and an Epicydes surnamed Sindon. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After slaying
                    them and <pb n="p.451"/> calling the populace to an assembly, they complained
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> of
                    privation and other things at which among themselves they had been in the habit
                    of murmuring in secret. And they said that, although so many hardships were a
                    burden to them, they ought not to blame fortune, because it was in their own
                    power to say how long they would endure them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans, they said, had had as their ground for besieging Syracuse their
                    love, not hatred, of the Syracusans. For on learning that the power had been
                    seized by Hippocrates and Epicydes, minions of Hannibal and later of Hieronymus,
                    it was then that they had made war and had begun to besiege the city, in order
                    to capture, not the city itself, but its cruel tyrants. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> But now that Hippocrates had perished, that Epicydes had
                    been cut off from Syracuse and his prefects slain, now that the Carthaginians
                    had everywhere been driven by land and sea from their occupation of Sicily, what
                    reason remained for the Romans not to wish Syracuse to be preserved, just as if
                    Hiero himself, who was unrivalled in maintaining friendship with Rome, were
                    still alive? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly both for the city and
                    for individuals there was no other danger than from themselves, if they should
                    let slip the opportunity of a reconciliation with the Romans. Moreover so
                    favourable an opportunity as there was at that moment, if it should be evident
                    that Syracuse, once it had been freed from insolent tyrants,. . . , <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Madvig's restoration is based upon the
                        idea of an immediate return to their former friendship ( <quote>and was
                            taking the Roman side</quote> ). Walters supplied the thought that the
                        Romans might even reject such advances. </note> would never come again. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The speech was heard with great and unanimous
                    approval. It was decided, however, to elect magistrates before naming legates.
                    Then out of the number of these magistrates' representatives <pb n="p.453"/>
                    were sent to Marcellus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The foremost of these
                    said: <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    <quote> In the beginning it was not we Syracusans who forsook your friendship,
                        but Hieronymus, who was by no means so conscienceless toward you as toward
                        us. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And later the peace concluded on the
                        assassination of the tyrant was broken, not by any Syracusan, but by the
                        king's minions, Hippocrates and Epicydes, after they had subdued us, now by
                        terrorizing, now by treason. Nor can any man say that there has ever been
                        any time of freedom for us that was not a time of peace with you. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Certain it is that now, when through the slaying
                        of those who were holding Syracuse in subjection we have begun for the first
                        time to be our own masters, we have come forthwith to give up our arms, to
                        surrender ourselves, the city, the walls, to reject no lot which shall be
                        imposed by you Romans. The glory of capturing the most notable and most
                        beautiful of Greek cities the gods have given to you, Marcellus. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> All that we have ever accomplished on land and
                        sea that is worthy of record is added to the distinction of your triumph.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Would you wish men merely to believe
                        tradition as to the greatness of the city you have captured, rather than
                        that it be a sight even to posterity, a city which shall show to every man
                        who comes by land or by sea, at one spot our trophies won from the Athenians
                        and the Carthaginians, at another your trophies won from us, and that you
                        hand over Syracuse intact to your house, to be kept under the clientship and
                        tutelage of those who bear the name Marcellus? <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Let not the memory of Hieronymus have more weight with
                        you Romans than that of Hiero. The latter was much longer your friend than
                        the former your enemy; and you <pb n="p.455"/> have had positive experience
                        of the good deeds of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                            >B.C. 212</note> the one, while the other's folly resulted only in his
                        own destruction. </quote> Everything could be obtained from the Romans and
                    was already assured. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was among the
                    Sicilians themselves that war and danger chiefly lay. For the deserters,
                    thinking that they would surely be handed over to the Romans, aroused the
                    mercenary auxiliaries also to the same fear. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    And seizing arms they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e</hi> the mercenaries. </note> first slew the
                    magistrates and then dispersed to massacre the Syracusans, and in anger they
                    slew all whom chance threw in their way and carried off everything on which they
                    could lay hands. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then, not to be without
                    commanders, they chose six prefects, three to be in charge of Achradina and
                    three of Nasus. When the uproar was at last stilled and they were diligently
                    enquiring what terms had been made with the Romans, the truth began to dawn upon
                    them, that their case was different from that of the deserters. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just at the right moment the legates returned
                    from Marcellus, stating that the mercenaries had been aroused by an unfounded
                    suspicion, and that the Romans had no reason for demanding their punishment.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One of the three prefects of Achradina was
                    a Spaniard, Moericus by name. To him, among the- retinue of the legates, one
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> We learn from XXVI. xxi. 13 that
                        his name was Belligenes. </note> of the Spanish auxiliaries was sent on
                    purpose. Finding Moericus alone, he first explained the condition in which he
                    had left Spain, from which he had recently come. The whole of that country, he
                    said, was held by Roman arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If he should do
                    something worth while, he could be a chief among his own people, whether he
                    preferred to serve on the Roman side or to return to his native town. On the
                    other hand, if he <pb n="p.457"/> continued to prefer to be besieged, what hope
                    was <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    there for a man shut in by land and sea? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Moericus was impressed by these words, and when it was decided to send legates
                    to Marcellus, sent his brother as one of them. He was escorted separately from
                    the rest to Marcellus by that same Spaniard, and after receiving a promise and
                    arranging the steps to be taken, returned to Achradina. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Then Moericus, to divert the attention of everybody from
                    the suspicion of treason, said he did not approve of having legates going back
                    and forth; that none should be admitted or sent; and that, in order to keep a
                    closer guard, suitable positions should be divided among the prefects, so that
                    each should be responsible for the defence of his own section. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> All agreed. In the assignment of sections the region
                    extending from the Fountain of Arethusa to the entrance of the Great Harbour
                    fell to Moericus himself. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He saw to it that
                    the Romans knew that. Accordingly Marcellus ordered a transport with armed men
                    to be towed at night by a four-banker to Achradina, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> An evident error for the Island (Nasus), due possibly
                        to Livy's attempt to combine several different accounts. There is further
                        confusion in the passage which follows. </note> and the soldiers to be
                    landed near the gate which is by the Fountain of Arethusa. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> This done at the fourth watch, and the soldiers landed
                    there having been admitted according to agreement by Moericus through the gate,
                    Marcellus at daybreak with all his forces assailed the walls of Achradina.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The result was that not only did he turn
                    the attention of the defenders of Achradina to himself, but from Nasus also
                    columns of armed men, leaving their posts, united in haste, to ward off the
                    violent attack of the Romans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During this
                    confusion light vessels, previously equipped, sailed around to Nasus and landed
                    their troops. These made an unexpected attack upon <pb n="p.459"/> the
                    half-manned outposts and the open doors of the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> gate through which the
                    armed men had dashed out a little while before, and with no great resistance
                    captured Nasus, deserted by the excitement and flight of the guards. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> And no others showed less capacity to defend or
                    determination to hold out than the deserters, since they did not quite trust
                    even their own men and fled out of the midst of the conflict. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Marcellus, on learning that Nasus had been captured and one
                    section of Achradina occupied, also that Moericus with his force had joined the
                    Romans, sounded the recall, to prevent the royal treasures, which were reported
                    to be larger than they really were, from being plundered. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The onslaught of the soldiers being checked
                    and time and place for their flight given to the deserters who were in
                    Achradina, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the Syracusans, at last relieved
                    of their fear, open the gates of Achradina and send representatives to
                    Marcellus, asking nothing else than their own lives and those of their children.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Marcellus, calling a council and admitting
                    also those Syracusans who, after being driven from home during the uprisings,
                    had been inside the Roman lines, replied that the good acts of Hiero toward the
                    Roman people during fifty years had not been more numerous than the evil deeds
                    done in the last few years by those who held Syracuse. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But most of the misdeeds, he said, had reacted just as they
                    should, and the men had exacted from themselves much more serious penalties for
                    the broken treaties than the Roman people wished. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> For his part, he was besieging Syracuse for the third year,
                    not that the Roman people might keep the city enslaved, but to prevent the
                    commanders of deserters <pb n="p.461"/> and foreigners from holding it in
                    captivity and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        212</note> subjection. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What the Syracusans
                    could have done was shown by the example either of those Syracusans inside the
                    Roman lines, or of the Spanish commander Moericus, who surrendered his post, or
                    finally of the belated but courageous resolution of the Syracusans themselves.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To his mind it was by no means a
                    sufficient reward for all the hardships and dangers, so long endured on land and
                    sea about the Syracusan walls, that he had been able to capture Syracuse.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thereupon the quaestor was sent from Nasus
                    with a force to receive and guard the royal funds. The city was given over to
                    the soldiers to plunder, guards being first assigned to the houses of the men
                    who had been inside the Roman lines. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> While
                    many shameful examples of anger and many of greed were being given, the
                    tradition is that Archimedes, in all the uproar which the alarm of a captured
                    city could produce in the midst of plundering soldiers dashing about, was intent
                    upon the figures which he had traced in the dust and was slain by a soldier, not
                    knowing who he was; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. Plutarch's
                        account, <hi rend="italics">Marcellus</hi> 19; Valerius Maximus VIII. 7.
                        Ext. 7; Cicero <hi rend="italics">de Finibus</hi> V. 50. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that Marcellus was grieved at this, and his
                    burial duly provided for; and that his name and memory were an honour and a
                    protection to his relatives, search even being made for them. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Such in the main was the capture of Syracuse, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Actually the fall of Syracuse appears
                        to have taken place in the following year, <date when="-0211">211
                            B.C.</date>
                    </note> in which there was booty in such quantity as there <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> would scarcely have been <pb n="p.463"/> if Carthage, with
                    which the conflict was on even <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> terms, had at that time been captured. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A few days before Syracuse was taken, Titus
                    Otacilius with eighty five-bankers crossed over from Lilybaeum to Utica. And
                    having entered the harbour before daylight, he captured cargo-ships laden with
                    grain, and disembarking ravaged a considerable area around Utica and drove booty
                    of every kind back to the ships. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> On the third
                    day after he had left Lilybaeum he returned thither with a hundred and thirty
                    cargo-ships laden with grain and booty, and sent the grain at once to Syracuse.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Had it not arrived so opportunely, a
                    famine equally destructive to victors and vanquished was impending. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Spain in the same summer, when for about
                    two years <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This apparently from a
                        source which placed the defeat and death of the Scipios in <date
                            when="-0211">211 B.C.</date> ; cf. note on xxxvi. 14. </note> nothing
                    very notable had occurred and the war was being waged more by diplomacy than by
                    arms, the Roman generals, on leaving their winter-quarters, united their forces.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thereupon a council was called and all
                    were of one mind, that, since up to that time they had accomplished nothing
                    except to hold Hasdrubal back from pushing on into Italy, it was time that their
                    task should now be to end the war in Spain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    And they believed they had sufficient reinforcements for that purpose in twenty
                    thousand Celtiberians who had been called to arms that winter. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The enemy had three armies. Hasdrubal, the son of Gisgo,
                    and Mago with adjoining camps were about five days' march from the Romans.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nearer was Hasdrubal, the son of Hamilcar,
                    a veteran commander in Spain. He had his army near a city called Amtorgis.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was he that the <pb n="p.465"/> Roman
                    generals wished first to overpower; and they <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> hoped they had quite ample
                    forces for that end. The one remaining concern was the fear that, if he was
                    defeated, the other Hasdrubal and Mago might in alarm withdraw to pathless
                    forests and mountains and prolong the war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They thought it best therefore to divide their forces into two armies and
                    include the whole of Spain in their plan of operations. And they divided in such
                    manner that Publius Cornelius should lead two-thirds of the army of Romans and
                    allies against Mago and Hasdrubal, and <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> that
                    Gnaeus Cornelius with one-third of the old army and the Celtiberians in addition
                    should carry on the war with Hasdrubal Barca. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Setting out together, with the Celtiberians in the van, both generals and armies
                    pitched camp near the city of Amtorgis, in sight of the enemy, but separated by
                    a river. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably the Baetis, as
                        Iliturgi was not far away; cf. XXVIII. xix. 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There Gnaeus Scipio remained with the
                    above-mentioned forces, while Publius Scipio set out for his previously
                    appointed share of the war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal first noted that there was only a
                    small army of Romans in the camp and that all their hope was in the Celtiberian
                    auxiliaries. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then, as he was well acquainted
                    with every form of treachery practised by barbarians and particularly by those
                    tribes among which he had been campaigning for so many years, and <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> as oral communication was easy, since both camps
                    were full of Spaniards, by means of secret conferences he made an agreement with
                    the chief men of the Celtiberians at a high price that they should withdraw
                    their troops. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor did it seem an outrageous
                    act —for it was not urged that they should turn their arms against the Romans
                    —and a price which would have been ample even for engaging <pb n="p.467"/> in
                    the war was offered them not to wage war. Again, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> not only peace itself, but
                    also a return home and the advantage of seeing their families and their property
                    were attractions to the mass of them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly their leaders were not more easily persuaded than the rank and file.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At the same time they had no fear from the
                    Romans either, if they, being so few in number, should try to hold them by
                    force. It will always be a necessary precaution for Roman generals, and these
                    instances must really be accounted warnings, not so to trust their foreign
                    auxiliaries as not to have in camp more of their own strength and of forces that
                    are absolutely their own. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians
                    suddenly took up their standards and departed, and when Romans asked the reason
                    and implored them to remain, they gave no other answer than that they were
                    called away by a war at home. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio, now that
                    his allies could not be held either by entreaties or by force, saw that he could
                    neither be a match for the enemy without them nor rejoin his brother, and that
                    no other promising plan was available. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Thereupon he decided to retire as far as possible, taking every care and being
                    on the alert not to expose himself anywhere on level ground to the enemy, who
                    crossed the river and kept almost at their heels as they withdrew. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time Publius Scipio was beset
                    by a fear no less grave and a danger that was greater from a new enemy.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was the young Masinissa, at that
                    time an ally of the Carthaginians, a man whom friendship with the Romans later
                    made famous and powerful. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> With his Numidian
                    cavalry he now encountered Publius Scipio on his advance, and also was
                    continually at hand day and night, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> ready <pb
                        n="p.469"/> to attack, so that he not only captured soldiers <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> who had
                    wandered far from the camp in search of wood and fodder, but also rode up to the
                    camp itself, and often dashing into the midst of the outposts threw everything
                    into great confusion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By night also there was
                    often alarm at the gates and on the earthwork owing to a sudden attack, nor was
                    any place or time free from fear and anxiety for the Romans, and they were
                    confined within their earthwork, unable to obtain anything. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> It was almost a regular blockade, and this would evidently
                    be stricter if Indibilis, who was reported as approaching with seven thousand
                    five hundred Suessetani, should join the Carthaginians. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Consequently Scipio, though a general marked by caution and
                    foresight, being forced by his straits, adopted the rash plan of going by night
                    to meet Indibilis and giving battle wherever he should encounter him. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Therefore, leaving a moderate garrison at the camp
                    and putting his lieutenant, Tiberius Fonteius, in command of it, he set out at
                    midnight, and on meeting the enemy engaged them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> It was a battle of columns rather than lines; yet, so far as could be in an
                    engagement without order, the Roman had the advantage. But the Numidian cavalry,
                    whose notice the general had thought he had escaped, by outflanking them
                    inspired great alarm, and in addition, when they had entered a fresh battle with
                    the Numidians, a third enemy also arrived, the Carthaginian generals, who from
                    the rear overtook them when already engaged. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And the Romans found themselves between two battles, uncertain against which
                    enemy and in which direction they should choose to break through in a mass.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As the general was fighting and
                    exhorting, <pb n="p.471"/> and exposing himself where there was most to be <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> done, his
                    right side was pierced by a lance. And those of the enemy who in a wedge had
                    made an attack upon the men pressing close about the general, on seeing the
                    dying Scipio slipping from his horse, dashed everywhere along the line, wild
                    with delight, shouting and announcing that the Roman commander had fallen.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The broadcasting of that announcement far
                    and wide made the enemy as good as victors beyond a doubt and the Romans as good
                    as vanquished. Flight directly from the battle-line began, once they had lost
                    their general. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But while, so far as bursting
                    through the Numidians and the light-armed auxiliaries as well was concerned,
                    flight was not difficult, yet it was hardly possible for them to escape such
                    numbers of horsemen and infantry who by their speed kept up with the horses.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And almost more were slain in flight than
                    in battle, nor would anyone have survived but for the coming on of night, as the
                    day was now rapidly drawing to a close. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the Carthaginian generals directly after
                    the battle, making no indifferent use of their success, barely allowed their
                    soldiers necessary rest, and rushed their column with all speed in the direction
                    of Hasdrubal, the son of Hamilcar, with the certain hope that, when they should
                    unite with him, the war could be finished. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Upon their arrival there was great congratulation between the armies and
                    generals rejoicing in the recent victory, since so great a general and his
                    entire army had been destroyed, and they were looking for just such another
                    victory as beyond question. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As for the Romans,
                    not yet indeed had a report of the great disaster reached them, but there was a
                    gloomy silence and an unexpressed foreboding, <pb n="p.473"/> such as is usually
                    the forecast of impending <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> misfortune when men already have
                    presentiments. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The general himself, in
                    addition to the knowledge that he had been deserted by his allies and that the
                    enemy's forces had been so greatly increased, was more inclined by logical
                    inference to suspect that a disaster had occurred than to entertain any good
                    hope. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For how, he thought, could Hasdrubal and
                    Mago, unless they had quite finished their own war, have been able to bring up
                    their army without an engagement? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And how had
                    his brother failed to confront them or to follow in their rear, so that, if
                    unable to prevent the generals and armies of the enemy from uniting, he might
                    himself at least combine his forces with those of his brother? <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Troubled by these anxieties, he believed that the one safe
                    course at present was to retreat as faraway as possible. Then in one night,
                    while the enemy were unaware of it and hence made no move, he marched a
                    considerable distance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the morning the
                    enemy, on discovering that they had gone, sent the Numidians in advance and
                    began to follow them in a column at its utmost speed. Before night the Numidians
                    had overtaken them, and charging now in the rear, now on the flanks, compelled
                    them to halt and defend their column. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio
                    kept encouraging them to fight and advance at the same time, so far, that is, as
                    they could do so with safety, before the infantry forces should overtake them.
                        <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But while he now urged his column forward, now
                    ordered it to halt, for a long time little progress was being made and night was
                    now at hand. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Scipio therefore recalled his men
                    from battle, concentrated them and led them up a hill that was not indeed quite
                    safe, especially <pb n="p.475"/> for a terrified column, but still was higher
                    than the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    country around it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There the infantry,
                    surrounding the baggage and cavalry placed in the centre, at first kept off the
                    charges of the Numidians without difficulty. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Then, when three generals arrived in full force with three regular armies, and
                    it was evident that they would be unable by arms to defend an unfortified
                    position, the general began to cast about and consider whether he could in some
                    way surround it with an earthwork.. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the
                    hill was so bare and rocky that neither could thickets be found for the cutting
                    of stakes nor ground such that they could get turf or carry a trench in it or
                    any other earthwork. And yet no spot was naturally so elevated or rugged as to
                    make approach or ascent difficult for the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Everywhere the ground rose at a gentle slope. However, in order to interpose
                    some semblance of an earthwork, they laid <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    up, as it were, to the usual height all around them, pack-saddles still tied to
                    their loads, while, wherever the pack-saddles failed to make a barricade, they
                    piled on top lighter baggage of every kind. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian armies, on arriving, very
                    easily marched in column up the hill; but the strange appearance of the defences
                    at first checked them in a certain amazement, while their commanders kept
                    shouting from all sides, asking why they stood still and did not pull apart and
                    scatter that pretence, hardly strong enough to delay women or children. The
                    enemy, they said, was held captive, lurking behind his baggage. Such were the
                    scornful taunts of the commanders. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But it was
                    not easy to leap over or clear away <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the
                    baggage in front of them, nor to cut apart the mass of pack-saddles, buried
                    under <pb n="p.477"/> the added loads. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But
                    after they had cleared away <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> the baggage in front of them with hooked poles
                    and made a way for the armed men, and the same thing was being done in different
                    places, the camp had by this time been captured from all sides. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Everywhere there was slaughter of the few by the
                    many, of the panic-stricken by the victorious. A large part of the soldiers,
                    however, after fleeing into the neighbouring forest, made their escape to
                    Publius Scipio's camp, of which Tiberius Fonteius, his lieutenant, was
                    commander. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As for Gnaeus Scipio, some relate
                    that he was slain on the hill in the first onset of the enemy, others that with
                    a few men he made his escape to a tower near the camp; that fire was lighted
                    around this, and so, by burning the doors which they had been unable to force in
                    any way, they captured the tower and all were slain in it along with the
                    commander himself. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> In the eighth year <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Correct, though inconsistent with Livy's general
                        chronology, which would make it the seventh year; cf. XXI. xxxii. 3. In
                        xxxviii. 6 also Livy has followed an authority who placed the disasters in
                        Spain in <date when="-0211">211 B.C.</date> ; cf. note on xxxii. 1. </note>
                    after his arrival in Spain Gnaeus Scipio was killed, on the twenty-ninth day
                    after the death of his brother. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Grief for
                    their deaths was not greater in Rome than throughout Spain; in fact among the
                    citizens the destruction of armies and the loss of a province and the national
                    disaster claimed a part in their sorrow, while all Spain mourned for the
                    generals <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> themselves and missed them, Gnaeus
                    more than Publius, because he had been longer in command and had earlier won
                    their favour, and had given for the first time an example of Roman justice and
                    self-control. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While it seemed that the armies had been wiped
                    out and all Spain lost, a single man repaired their shattered fortunes.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the army was Lucius Marcius, son of
                    Septimus, a Roman knight, an active <pb n="p.479"/> young man of much more
                    spirit and talent than was <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> to be expected in the station in which he had
                    been born. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In addition to his high promise he
                    had had the training of Gnaeus Scipio, in which during so many years he had
                    mastered all the arts of the soldier. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This man
                    had made an army that was not to be despised out of soldiers gathered up from
                    the flight and in part withdrawn from garrison towns, and he had united it with
                    that of Tiberius Fonteius, the lieutenant of Publius Scipio. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> But so preeminent was a mere Roman knight in his personal
                    influence with the soldiers and in the respect they paid him that, after they
                    had fortified a camp on this side of the Hiberus <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> and decided that a commander of the army should be chosen
                    in an election by the soldiers, relieving each other as sentries on the wall and
                    in outpost duty until all had cast their votes, they unanimously conferred the
                    high command upon Lucius Marcius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then
                    spent the whole time —and it was very short —in fortifying the camp and bringing
                    up supplies. And the soldiers carried out all his commands, not only with
                    energy, but also in no dejected spirit. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                    when the news came that Hasdrubal the son of Gisgo, on his way to wipe out the
                    last remains of the war, had crossed the Hiberus and was approaching, and the
                    soldiers <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> saw the signal for battle raised by
                    a new general, they remembered what commanders they had had a short time before,
                    and upon what generals and forces they had usually relied as they went into
                    battle. Suddenly they all were weeping and dashing their heads against
                    obstacles; and some raised their hands to heaven, blaming the gods, others lying
                    on the ground invoked their respective generals by name. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> And the wailing <pb n="p.481"/> could not be stilled,
                    although the centurions tried to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> arouse the men of their maniples and Marcius
                    himself to calm them and upbraided them for having given themselves up to
                    womanish and useless weeping, instead of whetting their courage to defend
                    themselves and with them the state, and begged them not to let their commanders
                    lie unavenged, when suddenly —for the enemy were now near the earthwork —a shout
                    and the sound of trumpets were heard. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Upon
                    that, their grief instantly changing to anger, they scatter to arms, and as if
                    fired by frenzy, to the different gates, and dash into the enemy coming on
                    carelessly and in disorder. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At once the
                    unexpected act inspired alarm among the Carthaginians, and they wondered whence
                    so many enemies had suddenly appeared after the army had been almost wiped out,
                    whence came such boldness and self-confidence so great in men beaten and put to
                    flight, what commander had arisen after the two Scipios had been slain, who was
                    in command of the camp, who had given the signal for battle. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> In the face of all that —so many things so unexpected —they
                    at first retreated, completely at a loss and dumbfounded; then beaten back by
                    the strength of the attack they took to flight. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> And there would have been either a terrible slaughter of the fleeing or a
                    reckless and dangerous attack on the part of the pursuers, had not Marcius
                    promptly given the signal for the recall and kept back his own excited line,
                    facing his men in the front line and laying hold of some with his own hands. He
                    then led them back to camp still thirsting for slaughter and bloodshed.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians were at first forced
                    away in confusion from the enemies' earthwork; then, when they saw that no one
                    was pursuing, <pb n="p.483"/> they thought they had halted for fear, and with
                    fresh <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    contempt and at a slow pace they retired to their camp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> There was just as much carelessness in
                    guarding the camp. For, although the enemy was near, still they kept reflecting
                    that it was only a remnant of the two armies wiped out a few days before.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Since for this reason every precaution
                    had been omitted on the enemy's side, Marcius, informed of the facts, turned his
                    attention to a plan at first sight reckless rather than bold, actually to attack
                    the camp of the enemy, in the <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> belief that
                    it was easier to storm the camp of Hasdrubal alone than to defend his own, if
                    the three armies and three generals should again unite. <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time he thought that, if his efforts should
                    prove successful, he would relieve his critical situation or, even if defeated,
                    by venturing to attack he would at least take away their contempt for himself.
                        <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But for fear an unexpected action, and alarm
                    in the night and a plan no longer in keeping with his present situation, might
                    bring confusion, he thought he must address his soldiers and encourage them,
                    called an assembly and spoke as follows: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    "Either my devotion to our commanders, living and dead, or the present situation
                    of us all, soldiers, can convince any one that this high command, though a great
                    honour as your tribute, is yet in fact a burden to me and an anxious care.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For at a time when, if fear did not
                    paralyse grief, I should scarcely have such self-control as would enable me to
                    find some comfort for distress of mind, I am compelled —a most difficult thing
                    in sorrow —alone to plan for all of you. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And
                    even when I must consider how I may be able to save these remnants of two armies
                        <pb n="p.485"/> for our country, I may not turn my thoughts away <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> from
                    unremitting grief. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For a bitter memory is
                    present with me, and both Scipios trouble me all day and all night with anxiety
                    and loss of sleep, and often arouse me from slumber, bidding me not to allow
                    either themselves or their soldiers, your comrades, undefeated in this land for
                    eight years, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. xxxvi. 14 and
                        note.</note> or the state, to go unavenged. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> And they command me to follow their teachings and their methods, and, just as
                    while they lived not a man was more obedient to their <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> orders than I, so after their death to hold that to be the
                    best course which in each case I am confident they would have done. As for you,
                    soldiers, I would have you also honour them, not with lamentations and tears as
                    though dead. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They live and work by the glory
                    of their achievements. But whenever you shall remember them, just as if you saw
                    them encouraging you and giving the signal, —in that spirit would I have you go
                    into battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was surely no other image
                    which presented itself yesterday to your eyes and minds and brought about that
                    notable battle, by which <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> you gave the enemy
                    proof that the Roman name has not been extinguished with the Scipios, and that
                    the people whose might and courage were not overwhelmed by the disaster at
                    Cannae will surely survive any cruelty of Fortune. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> At present, because you have of your own accord shown such daring, I
                        should like to find how much you have when your general gives the command.
                        For yesterday, when I sounded the recall, as you in disorder were pursuing
                        the routed enemy, it was not my wish to crush your boldness, but to reserve
                        it for higher fame and a more favourable situation, that <pb n="p.487"/>
                        later, being <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> well prepared and armed,
                        you might be <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            212</note> able, as opportunity offered, to attack the unprepared and
                        unarmed, and even the sleeping. And not haphazard or at random do I cherish
                        a hope of this opportunity, soldiers, but from the actual situation.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> You too, if someone should ask how
                        you, a few men, have defended your camp against many, the vanquished against
                        the victors, would surely give no other answer than that, fearing just that,
                        you had kept everything in a state of defence and also had been in readiness
                        yourselves and inline. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And the fact is
                        this: men are least protected against the thing which success leads them not
                        to fear, since what one has made light of remains unguarded and uncovered.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There is nothing in the world which
                        the enemy now fear less than that we, who have ourselves just been beset and
                        attacked, may venture to attack their camp. Let us dare what it is
                        incredible that we should dare; for the very reason that it appears most
                        difficult it will be easier. In the third watch of the night I shall lead
                        you in a silent column. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> I am assured that
                        there is no relieving of sentries, no regular outposts. The sound of a shout
                        at the gate and a first assault will at once capture the camp. <milestone
                            n="17" unit="section"/> Then, among men dazed with sleep and alarmed at
                        the unexpected uproar and surprised unarmed in their beds, let there be the
                        slaughter from which you were recalled yesterday under protest. I know it
                        seems a bold plan. But in dangerous and desperate situations the bravest
                        decisions are always the safest. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> For if
                        at the opportune moment, whose advantage swiftly passes, one hesitates even
                        a little, it is vain for one to look later for the neglected opportunity.
                        One army is near, two not far away. If we attack now there is <pb n="p.489"
                        /> no little hope, and already you have tried your strength <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> and
                        theirs. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> If we put off the day and owing
                        to the report of yesterday's sally come to be no longer despised, there is
                        danger that all the generals and all the forces may combine. <milestone
                            n="20" unit="section"/> Shall we then withstand the enemy's three
                        generals, three armies, which Gnaeus Scipio with his army still undiminished
                        did not withstand? Just as through dividing their forces our generals
                        perished, so the enemy, if divided and in different places, can be
                        overpowered. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> There is no other way of
                        conducting the war. Therefore let us wait for nothing beyond the favourable
                        moment to-night. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Go with the kind aid of
                        the gods, put yourselves in condition, that, sound and strong, you may burst
                        into the camp of the enemy with the same spirit with which you defended
                        yours. </quote>
                </p>
                <p> With joy they heard of the new plan from their new commander, and the bolder it
                    was the more it pleased them. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> The rest of the
                    day was spent in putting their arms in order and themselves in condition; and
                    the larger part of the night was given to rest. At the fourth watch they
                    started. <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Beyond the nearest camp and at a distance of
                    six miles from it were other forces of the Carthaginians. Between them there was
                    a deep valley, densely wooded. About the middle of this wood a Roman cohort and
                    cavalry were concealed after the Punic method. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The road being thus cut off at the half-way, the rest of the forces were led in
                    a silent column to the nearest enemy. And as there was no outpost before the
                    gates nor sentinels on the earthwork, and no one anywhere opposed them, they
                    made their way into the camp as if it were their own. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Then the trumpets sound and a shout is raised. Some slay
                        <pb n="p.491"/> the enemy half-asleep, some throw firebrands on <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> the dry,
                    thatched huts, some seize the gates, to block escape. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> As for the enemy, fire, shouting and slaughter, all at
                    once, make them virtually senseless and do not allow them to hear any orders or
                    to look out for themselves. Unharmed they encounter bodies of armed men.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some rush to the gates, others, since the
                    roads are blocked, leap over the earthwork. And everyone who escaped fled at
                    once in the direction of the other camp; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    whereupon they were surrounded by the cohort and cavalry dashing out of their
                    hiding place and were slain to the last man. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Yet, even if a man had escaped from that slaughter, so swiftly did the Romans
                    hasten from the captured nearer camp to the other camp that news of the disaster
                    could not anticipate them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But there, the
                    farther it was from their enemy, and since some had scattered just before
                    daylight to bring in fodder and firewood and booty, the more neglect and
                    disorder did they find everywhere; only stacked arms at the outposts, the
                    soldiers unarmed, either sitting and lying on the ground or strolling outside
                    the wall and the gates. Against these men, so care-free and regardless of order,
                    the Romans, who were still fired by their recent battle and made confident by
                    victory, went into battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And so no
                    resistance whatever could be offered at the gates. Inside the gates there was a
                    rush from every part of the camp at the first shouting and commotion, and a
                    fierce battle began. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It would have lasted
                    long too, had not the sight of the Romans' bloody shields given the
                    Carthaginians evidence of the other disaster and consequently inspired alarm.
                    This terror made them all take to flight, and pouring out wherever a way could
                    be found <pb n="p.493"/> —except those overtaken by the sword —they lost <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> possession
                    of the <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> camp. Thus in a night and a day two
                    camps of the enemy were taken by assault under the command of Lucius <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Marcius. That about thirty-seven thousand of the
                    enemy were slain is the statement of Claudius, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Q. Claudius Quadrigarius, who wrote in the time
                        of Sulla. His history, in at least 23 books, began with the capture of the
                        city by the Gauls. Acilius' Greek history of Rome had begun with the
                        founding of the city. In <date when="-0155">155 B.C.</date> Acilius acted as
                        interpreter when the three Greek philosophers, Carneades among them,
                        appeared before the senate. </note> who translated Acilius' annals out of
                    Greek into the Latin language; that about one thousand eight hundred and thirty
                    were captured and a vast amount of booty <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    taken. And in this he says that there was a silver shield weighing a hundred and
                    thirty-seven pounds, bearing the likeness of Hasdrubal <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Barca. Valerius of Antium <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Valerius, a contemporary of Claudius, wrote a
                        voluminous history from the founding of Rome in upwards of 75 books. Here by
                        exception his figures for the enemy slain are very moderate. </note> relates
                    that one camp was captured, that of Mago, and seven thousand of the enemy slain;
                    that in a second battle they sallied out and fought with Hasdrubal; that ten
                    thousand were slain, four thousand three hundred and thirty <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> captured. Piso <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        L. Calpurnius Piso Frugi, the annalist, was consul in <date when="-0133">133
                            B.C.</date> His work, here cited for the last time in the extant Livy,
                        probably consisted of seven books, beginning with the founding of the city.
                    </note> states that five thousand men were slain from an ambush, while Mago was
                    pursuing in disorder our retreating <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> men. In
                    all of them great is the name of Marcius the general. And to his real fame they
                    add even marvels: that as he was speaking a flame burst from his head without
                    his knowledge, causing great alarm among the soldiers who stood around
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> him. They say that as a memorial of his
                    victory over the Carthaginians, down to the burning of the Capitol there was in
                    the temple a shield called the Marcian, bearing a likeness of <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> Hasdrubal. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Pliny
                        ( <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> XXXV. 14) says this shield hung above the
                        door of the Capitoline temple until the fire of <date when="-0084">84
                            B.C.</date>
                    </note> —Thereafter the situation in Spain was quiet for a long time, since both
                    sides, after receiving and inflicting such losses <pb n="p.495"/> upon each
                    other, hesitated to risk a decisive <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> engagement. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were being done in Spain,
                    it is true that Marcellus, after the capture of Syracuse, had settled matters in
                    general in Sicily with such conscientiousness and honesty that he added not only
                    to his own fame, but also to the dignity of the Roman people. But as regards the
                    adornments of the city, the statues and paintings which Syracuse possessed in
                    abundance, he carried them away to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                    were spoils of the enemy, to be sure, and acquired by right of war. Yet from
                    that came the very beginning of enthusiasm for Greek works of art and
                    consequently of this general licence to despoil all kinds of buildings, sacred
                    and profane, a licence which finally turned against Roman gods, and first of all
                    against the very temple which was magnificently adorned by Marcellus. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> For temples dedicated by Marcus Marcellus near the
                    Porta Capena <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Temples of Honos and
                        Virtus were outside the gate, on the Appian Way; XXVI. xxxii. 4; XXVII. xxv.
                        7-9; Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Marcellus</hi> 28. Dedicated in <date
                            when="-0205">205 B.C.</date> by Marcellus' son; XXIX. xi. 13. In the
                        Temple of Virtus stood the famous <hi rend="italics">sphaera</hi> (orrery)
                        of Archimedes; Cicero <hi rend="italics">de Re Publica</hi> I. 21. </note>
                    used to be visited by foreigners on account of their remarkable adornments of
                    that kind; but of these a very small part is still to be seen. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Embassies from nearly all the states in Sicily
                    kept coming to him. As their pleas were different, so was their status. Those
                    who before the capture of Syracuse either had not rebelled or had returned to
                    friendly relations were admitted and honoured as faithful allies. Those whom
                    fear had led to surrender after the capture of Syracuse, as vanquished received
                    terms from the victor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was left to the
                    Romans, however, no small remainder of the war around Agrigentum, namely,
                    Epicydes and Hanno, the surviving commanders in the previous war, and a third
                    new general sent by Hannibal in place of <pb n="p.497"/> Hippocrates. He was of
                    Libyphoenician race, from <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 212</note> Hippacra, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Hippo Diarrhytus, northwest of Utica, on the
                        coast. </note> and called Muttines by his countrymen, a man of energy who
                    under Hannibal's teaching had mastered all the arts of war. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He was furnished by Epicydes and Hanno with Numidian
                    auxiliaries, with which he so thoroughly scoured the enemy's lands and sought
                    out allies, in order to retain their loyalty by lending aid to each man at the
                    right <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> moment, that in a short time he filled
                    all Sicily with his name and was the highest hope of those supporting the
                    Carthaginian cause. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And so, after being
                    confined until then within the walls of Agrigentum, the Carthaginian general and
                    the Syracusan, emboldened not more by the advice of Muttines than by their
                    confidence in him to go outside the walls, pitched their camp by the river
                    Himera. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When news of this reached Marcellus,
                    he at once set his troops in motion and established himself at a distance of
                    about four miles from the enemy, to wait and see what they were doing or
                    intending. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But Muttines gave no occasion or
                    time for hesitation, or for a plan of action; for he crossed the river and
                    attacked the outposts of the enemy, causing great alarm and confusion.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The next day by an engagement almost in
                    regular form he drove the enemy inside their fortifications. Then he was
                    recalled by a mutiny of the Numidians breaking out in the camp, after about
                    three hundred of them had retired to Heraclea Minoa. On leaving, to pacify and
                    recall these men, he is said to have expressly warned the generals not to engage
                    the enemy in his absence. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At that both
                    generals were indignant, especially Hanno, already uneasy because of the man's
                    fame. To think that Muttines, a degenerate African, should set a limit <pb
                        n="p.499"/> for him, a Carthaginian commander, sent by senate <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note> and
                    people! <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He prevailed upon the hesitating
                    Epicydes to cross the river and form their battle-line. For if they should wait
                    for Muttines and the fortune of battle should favour, the glory, he said, would
                    unquestionably fall to Muttines. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus, thinking it was a veritable outrage
                    for him, a man who had driven Hannibal, backed by his victory at Cannae, from
                    Nola, to yield to these enemies whom he had himself defeated on land and sea,
                    ordered his soldiers to take up their arms in haste and the standard-bearers to
                    set out. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As he was drawing up his army, ten
                    Numidians rode out of the enemy's ranks and at full speed up to him, reporting
                    that their countrymen were aroused, first by the mutiny in which <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> three hundred of their number had retired to
                    Heraclea, and then by seeing their commander sent away just on the eve of battle
                    by generals who belittled his reputation, and that in the fight they would
                    remain inactive. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A deceitful race kept its
                    promise faithfully. And so the Romans' spirits rose when the message was sent
                    swiftly through the ranks that the enemy had been deserted by his cavalry, which
                    they had particularly dreaded; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> at the same
                    time the enemy were terrified not only because they were having no help from the
                    largest part of their forces, but also by the fear thus aroused that they might
                    themselves be attacked by their own cavalry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly it was no great struggle; the first shout, the first onset, decided
                    the matter. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Numidians, having remained
                    motionless on the wings at the beginning of the battle, seeing their men
                    retreating, shared only the flight with them for a short time. When they saw
                    them all making for <pb n="p.501"/> Agrigentum in a panic-stricken column, they
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 212</note>
                    themselves scattered in every direction to the neighbouring cities, fearing a
                    siege. Many thousand men were slain . . . thousand captured, also eight
                    elephants. This was Marcellus' last battle in Sicily; from it he returned as
                    victor to Syracuse. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By this time the year was nearly at an end.
                    Accordingly the senate at Rome decreed that Publius Cornelius, the praetor,
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> should send a letter to the consuls at
                    Capua, saying that, while Hannibal was far away and there was no decisive action
                    around Capua, one of them, if they thought it best, should come to Rome for the
                    replacement of magistrates. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On receiving the
                    letter the consuls arranged between them that Claudius should conduct the
                    elections, and Fulvius remain near Capua. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For
                    the consulship Claudius announced the election of Gnaeus Fulvius Centumalus and
                    Publius Sulpicius Galba, son of Servius, although he had previously held no
                    curule office. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As praetors the following were
                    then elected: Lucius Cornelius Lentulus, Marcus Cornelius Cethegus, Gaius
                    Sulpicius, Gaius Calpurnius Piso. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The duties
                    of the city praetor fell to Piso, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Evidently the duties of the praetor peregrinus also were assigned to the
                        praetor urbanus, as for the two preceding years; cf. notes on i. 11 and iii.
                        2. </note> Sicily to Sulpicius, Apulia to Cethegus, Sardinia to Lentulus. As
                    for the consuls, their military authority was continued for one year. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
