<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six - 25</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp> literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by </resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>

                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1849</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="956" xml:id="p.956"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXV.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Publius Cornelius Scipio, afterwards called Africanus, elected aedile before
                        he had attained the age required by the law. The citadel of Tarentum, in
                        which the Roman garrison had taken refuge, betrayed to Hannibal. Games
                        instituted in honour of Apollo, called Apollinarian. Quintus Ful- vius and
                        Appius Claudius, consuls, defeat Hanno the Carthaginian ge- neral. Tiberius
                        Sempronius Gracchus betrayed by a Lucanian to Mago, and slain. Centenius
                        Penula, who had been a centurion, asks the senate for the command of an
                        army, promising to engage and vanquish Han- nibal; is cut off with eight
                        thousand men. Cneius Fulvius engages Han- nibal; and is beaten, with the
                        loss of sixteen thousand men slain; he himself escapes with only two hundred
                        horsemen. Quintus Fulvius and Appius Claudius, consuls, lay siege to Capua.
                        Syracuse taken by Clau- dius Marcellus after a siege of three years. In the
                        tumult occasioned by taking the city, Archimedes is killed while intently
                        occupied on some figures which he had drawn in the sand. Publius and
                        Cornelius Scipio, after having performed many eminent services in Spain, are
                        slain, toge- ther with nearly the whole of their armies, eight years after
                        their arrival in that country; and the possession of that province would
                        have been en- tirely lost, but for the valour and activity of Lucius
                        Marcius, a Roman knight, who, collecting the scattered remains of the
                        vanquished armies, utterly defeats the enemy; storming their two camps,
                        killing thirty-seven thousand of them, and taking eighteen hundred together
                        with an im- mense booty. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> HANNIBAL passed the summer during which these
                    events occurred in Africa and Italy, in the Tarentine territory, with the hope
                    of having the city of the Tarentines betrayed to him. Meanwhile some
                    inconsiderable towns belonging to them, and to the Sallentines, revolted to him.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the same time, of the twelve states of
                    the Bruttians, which had in a former year gone over to the Carthaginians, the
                    Consentians and Thurians returned to the protection of the Roman people.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And more would have done the same, had not
                    Titus Pomponius Veientanus, praefect of the allies, having acquired the
                    appearance of a regular general, in consequence of several successful predatory
                    expeditions in the Bruttian territory, got together a tumultuary band, and
                    fought a battle with Hanno. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In that battle, a
                    great number of men, consisting, however, of a disorderly rabble of slaves and
                    rustics, were slain or captured. The least part of the loss was, that the
                    prefect himself was taken prisoner; for he was not only in the present instance
                    guilty of having rashly engaged the enemy, but previously, in <pb n="957"
                        xml:id="p.957"/> the capacity of farmer of the revenue, by iniquitous
                    practices of every description, had shown himself faithless and injurious to the
                    state, as well as the companies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Among the
                    Lucanians, the consul, Sempronius, fought several small battles, but none worthy
                    of being recorded; he also took several inconsiderable towns. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> In proportion as the war was protracted, and the sentiments
                    no less than the circumstances of men fluctuated accordingly as events flowed
                    prosperously or otherwise, the citizens were seized with such a passion for
                    superstitious observances, and those for the most part introduced from foreign
                    countries, that either the people or the gods appeared to have undergone a
                    sudden change. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And now the Roman rites were
                    growing into disuse, not only in private, and within doors, but in public also;
                    in the forum and Capitol there were crowds of women sacrificing, and offering up
                    prayers to the gods, in modes unusual in that country. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A low order of sacrificers and soothsayers had enslaved
                    men's understandings, and the numbers of these were increased by the country
                    people, whom want and terror had driven into the city, from the fields which had
                    lain uncultivated during a protracted war, and had suffered from the incursions
                    of the enemy, and by the profitable trading in the ignorance of others which
                    they carried on like an allowed and customary trade. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> At first, good men gave utterance in private to the
                    indignation they felt at these proceedings; but afterwards the thing came before
                    the fathers, and formed a matter of public complaint. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The aediles and triumviri, appointed for the execution of
                    criminals, were severely reprimanded by the senate for not preventing these
                    irregularities; but when they attempted to remove the crowd of persons thus
                    employed from the forum, and to overthrow their preparations for their sacred
                    rites, they narrowly escaped personal injury. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    It being now evident, that the evil was too powerful to be checked by inferior
                    magistrates, the senate commissioned Marcus Atilius, the city praetor, to rid
                    the people of these superstitions. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He called
                    an assembly, in which he read the decree of the senate, and gave notice, that
                    all persons who had any books of divination, or forms of prayer, or any written
                    system of sacrificing, should lay all the aforesaid books and writings before
                    him before the calends of April; and that no person should sacrifice in any
                    public or consecrated place according to new or foreign rites. <pb n="958"
                        xml:id="p.958"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Several of the public priests too died this
                    year: Lucius Cornelius Lentulus, chief pontiff, Caius Papirius Maso, son of
                    Caius, a pontiff, Publius Furius Philo, an augur, and Caius Papirius Maso, son
                    of Lucius, a decemvir for the superintendence of sacred rites. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> In lieu of Lentulus, Marcus Cornelius Cethegus, in lieu of
                    Papirius Cnaeius, Servilius Caepio, were created pontiffs. Lucius Quinctius
                    Flaminius was created augur, and Lucius Cornelius Lentulus decemvir for the
                    superintendence of sacred rites. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The time for
                    the election of consuls was now approaching; but as it was not thought proper to
                    call the consuls away from the war with which they were intently occupied,
                    Tiberius Sempronius, the consul, nominated Caius Claudius Centho as dictator to
                    hold the election. He appointed Quintus Fulvius Flaccus as his master of the
                    horse. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the first day on which the election
                    could be held, the dictator appointed as consuls, Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, his
                    master of the horse, and Appius Claudius Pulcher, who had held the government of
                    Sicily as praetor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The praetors created were
                    Cneius Fulvius Flaccus, Caius Claudius Nero, Marcus Junius Silanus, Publius
                    Cornelius Sulla. The election completed, the dictator retired from his office.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This year, Publius Cornelius Scipio,
                    afterwards surnamed Africanus, held the office of curule aedile, with Marcus
                    Cornelius Cethegus; and when the tribunes of the people opposed his pretensions
                    to the aedileship, alleging, that no notice ought to be taken of him, because he
                    had not attained the legal age for candidateship, he observed, <quote>if the
                        citizens in general are desirous of appointing me aedile, I am old
                        enough.</quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Upon this the people ran to their respective
                    tribes to give their votes, with feelings so strongly disposed in his favour,
                    that the tribunes on a sudden abandoned their attempt. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The largesses bestowed by the aediles were the following:
                    the Roman games were sumptuously exhibited, considering the present state of
                    their resources; they were repeated during one day, and a gallon of oil was
                    given to each street. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lucius Villius Tapulus,
                    and Marcus Fundanius Fundulus, the plebeian aediles, accused some matrons of
                    misconduct before the people, and some of them they convicted and sent into
                    exile. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The plebeian games were repeated
                    during two days, and a feast in honour of Jupiter was celebrated on occasion of
                    the games. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, for the third time,
                    and Appius <pb n="959" xml:id="p.959"/> Claudius entered upon the office of
                    consuls. The praetors determined their provinces by lot. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Cornelius Sulla received both the city and the
                    foreign jurisdiction, formerly allotted to two persons; Cneius Fulvius Flaccus,
                    Apulia, Caius Claudius Nero, Suessula, and Marcus Junius Silanus, Tuscany.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the consuls the conduct of the war with
                    Hannibal was decreed with two legions each; one taking the troops of Quintus
                    Fabius, the consul of the former year, the other those of Fulvius Centumalus.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of the praetors, Fulvius Flaccus was to
                    have the legions which were in Luceria under Aemilius the praetor, Nero Claudius
                    those in Picenum under Caius Terentius; each raising recruits for himself to
                    fill up the number of his troops. To Marcus Junius the city legions of the
                    former year were assigned, to be employed against the Tuscans. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus and Publius Sempronius
                    Tuditanus were continued in command in their provinces of Lucania and Gaul with
                    the armies they had, as was also Publius Lentulus in that part of Sicily which
                    formed the ancient Roman province. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Marcellus had Syracuse, and that which was the kingdom of Hiero. Titus Otacilius
                    was continued in the command of the fleet, Marcus Valerius in that of Greece,
                    Quintus Mucius Scaevola in that of Sardinia. The Cornelii, Publius and Cneius,
                    were continued in the command of Spain. In addition to the armies already
                    existing, two legions for the service of the city were levied by the consuls,
                    and a total of twenty-three legions was made up this year. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The levy of the consuls was impeded by the conduct of
                    Marcus Posthumius Pyrgensis, almost accompanied with a serious disturbance.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Posthumius was a farmer of the revenue,
                    who, for knavery and rapacity, practised through a course of many years, had no
                    equal except Titus Pomponius Veientanus, who had been taken prisoner the former
                    year by the Carthaginians under the conduct of Hanno, while carelessly ravaging
                    the lands in Lucania. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As the state had taken
                    upon itself the risk of any loss which might arise from storms to the
                    commodities conveyed to the armies, not only had these two men fabricated false
                    accounts of shipwrecks, but even those which had really occurred were occasioned
                    by their own knavery, and not by accident. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Their plan was to put a few goods of little value into old and shattered
                    vessels, which they sank in the deep, taking up the sailors in boats prepared
                    for <pb n="960" xml:id="p.960"/> the purpose, and then returning falsely the
                    cargo as many times more valuable than it was. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> This fraudulent practice had been pointed out to Marcus Atilius, the praetor
                    in a former year, who had communicated it to the senate; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> no decree, however, had been passed censuring it, because
                    the fathers were unwilling that any offence should be given to the order of
                    revenue farmers while affairs were in such a state. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The people were severer avengers of the fraud; and at
                    length two tribunes of the people, Spurius and Lucius Carvilius, being moved to
                    take some active measure, as they saw that this conduct excited universal
                    disgust, and had become notorious, proposed that a fine of two hundred thousand
                    asses should be imposed on Marcus Posthumius. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    When the day arrived for arguing the question, the people assembled in such
                    numbers, that the area of the Capitol could scarcely contain them; and the cause
                    having been gone through, the only hope of safety which presented itself was,
                    that Caius Servilius Casca, a tribune <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> of
                    the people, a connexion and relation of Posthumius, should interpose his protest
                    before the tribes were called to give their votes. The witnesses having been
                    produced, the tribunes caused the people to withdraw, and the urn was brought,
                    in order that the tribes should draw lots which should give the vote first.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, the farmers of the revenue
                    urged Casca to stop the proceedings for that day. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> The people, however, loudly opposed it; and Casca happened
                    to be sitting on the most prominent part of the rostrum, whose mind fear and
                    shame were jointly agitating. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Seeing that no
                    dependence was to be placed in him for protection, the farmers of the revenue,
                    forming themselves into a wedge, rushed into the void space occasioned by the
                    removal of the people for the purpose of causing disturbance, wrangling at the
                    same time with the people and the tribunes. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The affair had now almost proceeded to violence, when Fulvius Flaccus, the
                    consul, addressing the tribunes, said, <quote> Do you not see that you are
                        degraded to the common rank, and that an insurrection will be the result,
                        unless you speedily dismiss the assembly of the commons. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commons being dismissed, the senate was
                    assembled, when the consuls proposed the consideration of the interruption
                    experienced by the assembly of the commons, in consequence of the violence and
                    audacity of the farmers of the <pb n="961" xml:id="p.961"/> revenue. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> They said, that <quote> Marcus Furius Camillus, whose
                        banishment was followed by the downfal of the city, had suffered himself to
                        be condemned by his exasperated countrymen. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> That before him, the decemviri, according to whose laws they lived up to
                        the present day, and afterwards many men of the first rank in the state, had
                        submitted to have sentence passed upon them by the people. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> But Posthumius Pyrgensis had wrested from the Roman
                        people their right of suffrage, had dissolved the assembly of the commons,
                        had set at nought the authority of the tribunes, had drawn up a body of men
                        in battle-array against the Roman people; and seized upon a post, in order
                        to cut off the tribunes from the commons, and prevent the tribes being
                        called to give their votes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That the only
                        thing which had restrained the people from bloodshed and violence, was the
                        forbearance of the magistrates in giving way for the moment to the fury and
                        audacity of a few individuals, and suffering themselves and the Roman people
                        to be overcome; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and that no opportunity
                        might be afforded those who were seeking an occasion of violence, in
                        dissolving, agreeably to the wish of the defendant himself, that assembly
                        which he was about to interrupt by force of arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Observations of this kind having been urged
                    with a warmth proportioned to the atrocity of the conduct which called them
                    forth, by all the most respectable persons, and <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> the senate having passed a decree to the effect that the
                    violence offered was prejudicial to the state, and a precedent of pernicious
                    tendency, immediately the Carvilii, tribunes of the people, giving up the action
                    for a fine, appointed a day on which Posthumius should be tried capitally, and
                    ordered, that unless he gave bail, he should be apprehended by the beadle, and
                    carried to prison. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Posthumius gave bail, but
                    did not appear. The tribunes then proposed to the commons, and the commons
                    resolved, that if Marcus Posthumius did not appear before the calends of May,
                    and if on being cited on that day he did not answer, and sufficient cause were
                    not shown why he did not, he would be adjudged an exile, his goods would be
                    sold, and himself interdicted from water and fire. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> They then proceeded to indict capitally, and demand bail of
                    each of the persons who had been the promoters of the disorder and riot.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At first they threw into prison those who
                    did not give bail, and afterwards even such as could; upon which the greater
                    part <pb n="962" xml:id="p.962"/> of them went into exile, to avoid the danger
                    to which this proceeding exposed them. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The knavery of the revenue farmers, and their
                    subsequent audacious conduct to screen themselves from its effects, thus
                    terminated. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> An assembly was then held for the
                    creation of a chief pontiff. The new pontiff, Marcus Cornelius Cethegus,
                    presided. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The election was contested with the
                    greatest obstinacy by three candidates, Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, the consul, who
                    had been twice consul before and censor; Titus Manlius Torquatus, who had
                    himself also been distinguished by two consulships and the censorship; and
                    Publius Licinius Crassus, who was about to stand for the office of curule
                    aedile. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In this contest, the last-mentioned
                    candidate, though a young man, beat the others, who were his superiors in years,
                    and had filled offices of honour. Before him there had not been a man for a
                    hundred and twenty years, except Publius Cornelius Calussa, who had been created
                    chief pontiff without having sat in the curule chair. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Though the consuls found great difficulty in completing the
                    levy, for in consequence of the scarcity of young men, it was not easy to
                    procure enough for the two purposes of forming the new city legions, and
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> recruiting the old ones, the senate
                    forbade them to desist from the attempt, and ordered two triumvirates to be
                    appointed, one of which within, the other without the fiftieth mile from the
                    city, might ascertain the utmost number of free-born men which were to be found
                    in <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the villages, and market towns, and
                    hamlets, and enlist whom they thought strong enough to bear arms, though they
                    had not attained the military age. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That the
                    tribunes of the people, if they thought proper, should propose to the people,
                    that such as should take the military oath being under seventeen years, should
                    be allowed to reckon their period of service in the same manner as if they had
                    enlisted at seventeen or older. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two
                    triumvirates, created agreeably to this decree of the senate, enlisted free-born
                    men throughout the country. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the same time
                    a letter from Marcellus from Sicily, respecting the petition of the troops who
                    served with Publius Lentulus, was read in the senate. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> These troops were the relics of the disaster at Cannae, and
                    had been sent out of the way into Sicily, as has been mentioned before, on an
                    understanding that they should not be brought home before the conclusion of the
                    Carthaginian war. <pb n="963" xml:id="p.963"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the permission of Lentulus, these men
                    sent the most distinguished of the cavalry and centurions, and a select body of
                    the legionary infantry, as ambassadors to Marcellus, to his winter quarters.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Having obtained leave to speak, one of
                    them thus addressed him: <quote> We should have approached you, Marcus
                        Marcellus, when consul in Italy, as soon as that decree of the senate was
                        passed respecting us, which, though not unjust, was certainly severe, had we
                        not hoped, that being sent into a province which was in a state of disorder
                        in consequence of the death of its kings, to carry on an arduous war against
                        the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> Sicilians and Carthaginians
                        together, we should make atonement to the state by our blood and wounds, in
                        the same manner as, within the memory of our fathers, those who were taken
                        prisoners <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> by Pyrrhus at Heraclea, made
                        atonement by fighting against the same Pyrrhus. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> And yet, for what fault of ours, conscript fathers, did
                        you then, or do you now, feel displeasure towards us; for when I look upon
                        you, Marcus Marcellus, I seem to behold both the consuls and the whole body
                        of the senate; and had you been our consul at Cannae, a better fate would
                        have attended the state as well as ourselves. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Permit me, I entreat you, before I complain of the
                        hardship of our situation, to clear ourselves of the guilt with which we are
                        charged. If it was neither by the anger of the gods, nor by fate, according
                        to whose laws the course of human affairs is unalterably fixed, but by
                        misconduct that we were undone at Cannae; but whose was that misconduct; the
                        soldiers', or that of their generals? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For
                        my own part, I, as a soldier, will never say a word of my commander,
                        particularly when I know that he received the thanks of the senate for not
                        having despaired of the state; and who has been continued in command through
                        every year since his flight from Cannae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        We have heard that others also who survived that disaster, who were military
                        tribunes, solicit and fill offices of honour, and have the command of
                        provinces. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Do you then, conscript fathers,
                        pardon yourselves and your children, while you exercise severity towards
                        such insignificant persons as we are? It was no disgrace to a consul and
                        other leading persons in the state, to fly when no other hope remained; and
                        did you send your soldiers into the field as per- sons who must of necessity
                        die there? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the Allia nearly the whole
                        army fled; at the Caudine Forks the troops de- <pb n="964" xml:id="p.964"/>
                        livered up their arms to the enemy, without even making an effort; not to
                        mention other disgraceful defeats of our armies. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Yet, so far from any mark of infamy being sought for,
                        which might be fixed upon these troops, the city of Rome was recovered by
                        means of those very troops who had fled to Veii from the Allia; <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> and the Caudine legions, which had returned to
                        Rome without their arms, being sent back armed to Samnium, brought under the
                        yoke that very enemy who had exulted in the disgrace which, in this
                        instance, attached to them. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But is there
                        a man who can bring a charge of cowardice or running away against the army
                        which fought at Cannae, where more than fifty thousand men fell; from whence
                        the consul fled with only seventy horsemen; where not a man survived, except
                        perchance those whom the enemy left, being wearied with killing? <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> When the proposal to ransom the prisoners was
                        negatived, we were the objects of general commendation, because we reserved
                        ourselves for the service of the state; because we returned to the consul to
                        Venusia, and exhibited an appearance of a regular army. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Now we are in a worse condition than those who were
                        taken prisoners in the time of our fathers; for they only had their arms,
                        the nature of their service, and the place where they might pitch their
                        tents in the camp altered; all which, however, they got restored by one
                        service rendered to the state, and by one successful battle. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> Not one of them was sent away into banishment;
                        not one was deprived of the hope of completing the period of his service; in
                        short, an enemy was assigned to them, fighting with whom they might at once
                        terminate their life or their disgrace. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        We, to whom nothing can be objected, except that it is owing to us that any
                        Roman soldier has survived the battle of Cannae, are removed far away, not
                        only from our country and Italy, but even from an enemy; <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> where we may grow old in exile, where we can have no
                        hope or opportunity of obliterating our disgrace, of appeasing the
                        indignation of our countrymen, or, in short, of obtaining an honourable
                        death. We seek neither to have our ignominy terminated, nor our virtue
                        rewarded, we only ask to be allowed to make trial of our courage, and to
                        exercise our virtue. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> We seek for labour
                        and danger that we may discharge the duty of men and soldiers. A war is
                        carrying on in Sicily, now for the second year, with the utmost vigour on
                        both sides. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> The Cartha- <pb n="965"
                            xml:id="p.965"/> ginians are storming some cities, the Romans others;
                        armies of infantry and horse are engaging in battle; at Syracuse the war is
                        prosecuted by sea and by land. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> We hear
                        distinctly the shout of the combatants, and the din of arms, while we
                        ourselves lie inactive and unemployed, as if we had neither hands nor arms.
                        The consul, Sempronius, has now fought many pitched battles with the enemy
                        with legions of slaves. They receive as the fruits of their exertion their
                        liberty, and the rights of citizens. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Let
                        us at least be employed by you as slaves purchased for the service of this
                        war; let us be allowed to combat with the enemy and acquire our freedom by
                        fighting. Do you wish to make trial of our valour by sea, by land, in a
                        pitched battle, or in the assault of towns? <milestone n="23" unit="section"
                        /> We ask as our portion all those enterprises which present the greatest
                        difficulty and danger, that what ought to have been done at Cannae may be
                        done as soon as possible; for the whole of our subsequent lives has been
                        doomed to ignominy. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the conclusion of this speech they
                    prostrated themselves at the knees of Marcellus. Marcellus replied, that the
                    question was neither within his authority nor his power; that he would, however,
                    write to the senate, and be guided in every thing he did by the judgment of the
                    fathers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This letter was brought to the new
                    consuls, and by them read in the senate; and, on the question being put relative
                    to this letter, they decreed, <quote> that the senate saw no reason why the
                        interests of <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> the republic should be
                        intrusted to the hands of soldiers who had deserted their comrades, in
                        battle, at Cannae. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If Marcus Marcellus,
                        the proconsul, thought otherwise, that he should act as he deemed consistent
                        with the good of the republic and his own honour; with this proviso,
                        however, that none of these men should be exempt from service, nor be
                        presented with any military reward in consideration of valour, or be
                        conveyed back to Italy, while the enemy was in that country. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After this, agreeably to the decree of the
                    senate, and the order of the people, an election was held by the city praetor,
                    at which five commissioners were created for the purpose of repairing the walls
                    and turrets, and two sets of triumviri; one to search for the property belonging
                    to the temples, and to register the offerings; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    the other for repairing the temples of Fortune and Mother Matuta within the Car-
                    mental gate, and also that of Hope without the gate, which <pb n="966"
                        xml:id="p.966"/> had been destroyed by fire the year before. Dreadful storms
                    occurred at this time. It rained stones for two days without intermission in the
                    Alban mount. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Many places were struck by
                    lightning; two buildings in the Capitol, the rampart in the camp above Suessula
                    in many places, and two of the men on guard were killed. A wall and certain
                    towers at Cumae were not only struck with lightning, but demolished. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> At Reate, a vast rock was seen to fly about; the sun
                    appeared unusually red and blood-like. On account of these prodigies there was a
                    supplication for one day, and the consuls employed themselves for several days
                    in sacred rites; at the same time there was a sacred rite performed through nine
                    days. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> An accidental circumstance which
                    occurred at a distance, hastened the revolt of Tarentum, which had now for a
                    long time been the object of the hopes of Hannibal and of the suspicion of the
                    Romans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Phileas, a native of Tarentum, who
                    had been a long time at Rome under the pretence of an embassy, being a man of a
                    restless mind, and ill brooking that inactive state in which he considered that
                    his powers had been for too long a time sinking into imbecility, discovered for
                    himself a means of access to the Tarentine hostages. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They were kept in the court of the temple of Liberty, and
                    guarded with less care, because it was neither the interest of themselves nor of
                    their state to escape from the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> By
                    corrupting two of the keepers of the temple, he was enabled to hold frequent
                    conferences with them, at which he solicited them to come into this design;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and having brought them out of their
                    place of confinement as soon as it was dark, he became the companion of their
                    clandestine flight, and got clear away. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As
                    soon as day dawned, the news of their escape spread through the city, and a
                    party sent in pursuit, having seized them all at Tarracina, brought them back.
                    They were led into the Comitium, and after being scourged with rods, with the
                    approbation of the people, were thrown down from the rock. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The severity of this punishment exasperated
                    the inhabitants of two of the most distinguished Greek states in Italy, not only
                    publicly as communities, but privately <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> as
                    individuals, according as each was connected, either by relationship or
                    friendship, with those who had been so disgracefully put to death. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Of these about thirteen noble Tarentine youths formed
                        <pb n="967" xml:id="p.967"/> a conspiracy, the chief of whom were Nico and
                    Philemenus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Concluding that it would be right
                    to confer with Hannibal before they took any step, they went to him, having been
                    allowed to go out of the city by night on pretence of hunting. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> When they were now not far from the camp, all the rest hid
                    themselves in a wood by the road side; but Nico and Philemenus, proceeding to
                    the advanced guard, were seized, and at their own request brought before
                    Hannibal. Having laid before him the motives of their plan, and the object they
                    had in view, they received the highest commendation, and were loaded with
                    promises; and that their countrymen might believe that they had gone out of the
                    city to obtain plunder, they were desired to drive to the city some cattle of
                    the Carthaginians which had been sent out to graze. A promise was given them
                    that they might do this without danger or interruption. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The booty of the young men attracted notice, and less
                    astonishment was therefore felt that they should frequently repeat the attempt.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At a second meeting with Hannibal they
                    entered into a solemn engagement, that the Tarentines should be free, enjoying
                    their own laws, and all their rights uninterfered with; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> that they should neither pay any tribute to the
                    Carthaginians, nor receive a garrison against their will; that their present
                    garrison should be delivered up to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> These points being agreed upon, Philemenus then began to
                    repeat more frequently his customary practice of going out and returning to the
                    city followed by his dogs, and furnished with the other requisites for hunting;
                    for he was remarkable for his fondness of hunting; and generally bringing home
                    something which he had captured or taken away from the enemy, who had purposely
                    placed it in his way, he presented it to the commander or the guards of the
                    gates. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They supposed that he preferred going
                    and returning by night through fear of the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> After this practice had become so familiar, that at
                    whatever time of the night he gave a signal, by whistling, the gate was opened,
                    Hannibal thought that it was now time to put the plan in execution. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> He was at the distance of three days' journey, and
                    to diminish the wonder which would be felt at his keeping his camp fixed in one
                    and the same place so long, he feigned himself ill. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Even to the Romans who formed the garrison of Tarentum, his
                    protracted inactivity had ceased to be an object of suspicion. <pb n="968"
                        xml:id="p.968"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But after he determined to proceed to
                    Tarentum, selecting from his infantry and cavalry ten thousand men, whom, from
                    activity of body, and lightness of arms, he judged best adapted for the
                    expedition, he began his march in the fourth watch of the night; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> and sending in advance about eighty Numidian
                    horsemen, ordered them to scour the country on each side of the road, and
                    narrowly examine every place, lest any of the rustics who might have observed
                    his army at a distance should escape; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> to bring
                    back those who were got before, and kill those whom they met, that they might
                    appear to the neighbouring inhabitants to be a plundering party, rather than a
                    regular army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal himself, marching at a
                    rapid pace, pitched his camp about fifteen miles from Tarentum; and without
                    telling his soldiers even there, what was their destination, he only called them
                    together and admonished them to march all of them in the road, and not to suffer
                    any one to turn aside or deviate from the line; and above all, that they would
                    be on the watch, so as to catch the word of command, and not do any thing
                    without the order of their leaders; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that in
                    due time he would issue his commands as to what he wished to be done. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> About the same hour a rumour reached Tarentum, that a
                    few Numidian horsemen were devastating the fields, and had terrified the rustics
                    through a wide extent of country; at which intelligence the Roman prefect took
                    no further step than to order a division of his cavalry to go out the following
                    day at sunrise to check the depredations of the enemy; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> and so far was he from directing his attention to any thing
                    else on this account, that on the contrary, this excursion of the Numidians was
                    a proof to him that Hannibal and his army had not moved from his camp.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Early in the night Hannibal put his troops
                    in motion, and Philemenus, with his customary burden of prey taken in hunting,
                    was his guide. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The rest of the conspirators
                    waited the accomplishment of what had been concerted; and the agreement was,
                    that Philemenus, while bringing in his prey through the small gate by which
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> he was accustomed to pass, should
                    introduce some armed men, while Hannibal in another quarter approached the gate
                    called Temenis, which faced the east, in that quarter which was towards the
                    continent, near the tombs which were within the walls. When he drew near to the
                    gate, Hannibal raised a fire according to agreement, which made a blaze; the
                    same signal was returned <pb n="969" xml:id="p.969"/> by Nico, and the fires
                    were extinguished on both sides. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hannibal led
                    his troops on in silence to the gate. Nico suddenly fell upon the guards while
                    asleep, slew them in their beds, and opened the gate. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal then entered with his infantry, ordering his
                    cavalry to stay behind, that they might be able to bring their assistance
                    wherever it was required without obstruction. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Philemenus also in another quarter approached the small gate by which he was
                    accustomed to pass and repass. His voice, which was well known, for he said he
                    could scarcely bear the weight of the huge beast he had gotten, and his signal,
                    which had now become familiar, having roused the guard, the small gate was
                    opened. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Two youths carrying in a boar,
                    Philemenus himself followed, with a huntsman, unencumbered, and while the
                    attention of the guard was incautiously turned upon those who carried the boar,
                    in consequence of its astonishing size, he transfixed him with a hunting spear.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> About thirty armed men then entering,
                    slew the rest of the guards, and broke open the adjoining gate, when a body of
                    troops, in regular array, instantly rushed in. Being conducted thence in silence
                    to the forum, they joined Hannibal. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginian then sent the Tarentines, with two thousand Gauls formed into three
                    divisions, in different directions through the city, with orders to occupy the
                    most frequented streets. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> A confusion arising,
                    the Romans were put to the sword on all hands. The townsmen were spared; but in
                    order to insure this, he instructed the Tarentine youths, when they saw any of
                    their friends at a distance, to bid them be quiet and silent, and be of good
                    courage. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The tumult and clamour was now such as usually
                    takes place in a captured city, but no man knew for certain what was the
                    occasion. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Tarentines supposed that the
                    Romans had suddenly risen to plunder the city. To the Romans it appeared, that
                    some commotion had been set on foot by the townsmen with a treacherous design.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The prefect, who was awakened at the first
                    alarm, escaped to the port, whence getting into a boat he was conveyed round to
                    the citadel. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The sound of a trumpet also from
                    the theatre excited alarm; for it was a Roman trumpet, prepared by the
                    conspirators for this very purpose; and as it was blown unskilfully by a
                    Grecian, it could not be ascertained who gave the signal, or to whom it was
                    given. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At dawn of the day, the Romans
                    recognised the <pb n="970" xml:id="p.970"/> Carthaginian and Gallic arms, which
                    removed all doubt; and the Greeks, seeing the bodies of slain Romans spread
                    about in all directions, perceived that the city had been taken by Hannibal.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the light had increased, so that they
                    could discriminate with greater certainty, and the Romans who survived the
                    carnage had taken refuge in the citadel, the tumult now beginning to subside a
                    little, Hannibal gave orders to assemble the Tarentines without their arms.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All of them attended the assembly, except
                    those who had accompanied the Romans in their retreat to the citadel, to share
                    every fortune with them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Here Hannibal having
                    addressed the Tarentines in terms of kindness, and appealed to the services he
                    had rendered to those of their countrymen whom he had captured at the Trasimenus
                    and at Cannae, and having at the same time inveighed against the haughty
                    domination of the Romans, desired that they would every one of them retire to
                    their respective houses, and inscribe their names upon their doors; declaring,
                    that he should give orders that those houses which had not the names written
                    upon them should be plundered. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That if any man
                    should write his name upon the house of a Roman, (and the Romans occupied houses
                    by themselves,) he should treat him as an enemy. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Having dismissed the assembly, and the names inscribed upon
                    the doors having made it easy to distinguish the house of an enemy from that of
                    a friend, on a signal given, the troops ran in every direction to plunder the
                    lodgings of the Romans, and a considerable booty was found. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day he led his troops to assault the
                    citadel; but seeing that it was protected by very high rocks towards the sea,
                    which washed the greater part of it, and formed it into a sort of peninsula, and
                    towards the city by a wall and ditch, and consequently that it could not be
                    taken by assault or by works; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> lest the design
                    to protect the Tarentines should detain him from the prosecution of more
                    important objects, and lest the Romans should have the power of sallying from
                    the citadel whenever they pleased against the Tarentines, if left without a
                    strong protecting force, he resolved to cut off the communication between the
                    citadel and city by a rampart; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> not without a
                    hope that he might have an opportunity of fighting with the Romans, when
                    attempting to obstruct the work; and if they should sally forth too eagerly,
                    that by killing many of <pb n="971" xml:id="p.971"/> them the strength of the
                    garrison would be so far reduced, that the Tarentines alone would be easily able
                    to defend themselves from them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After they had
                    begun, the Romans, suddenly throwing open the gate, rushed in upon the workmen.
                    The guard stationed before the works allowed itself to be driven back, in order
                    that their boldness might be increased by success, and that they might pursue
                    them when driven back, in greater numbers, and to a greater distance. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Then on a signal given, the Carthaginians, whom
                    Hannibal kept in readiness for this purpose, sprang up on all sides; nor could
                    the Romans sustain the attack, but were prevented from precipitate flight by the
                    narrowness of the ground, by impediments occasioned in some places by the works
                    already commenced, in others by the preparations for the work. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Most of them were driven headlong into the ditch, and more
                    were killed in the flight than in the battle. After this the work was commenced
                    without any attempt to obstruct it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A large
                    ditch was formed, within which a rampart was thrown up. He prepared also to add
                    a wall at a small distance, and on the same side, that they might defend
                    themselves from the Romans even without a garrison. He, however, left them a
                    small force, at once for their protection and to assist in building the wall.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The general himself, setting out with the
                    rest of his forces, pitched his camp at the river Galaesus, five miles from the
                    city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Returning from this position to inspect
                    the work, which had gone on somewhat faster than he had anticipated, he
                    conceived a hope that the citadel might even be taken by storm; for it was not
                    protected by an elevated situation as the other parts were, but placed upon a
                    plain, and separated from the city only by a wall and ditch. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> While subjected to an attack from every kind of military
                    engine and work, a reinforcement sent from Metapontum inspired the Romans with
                    courage to assault the works of the enemy, by a sudden attack, under cover of
                    the night. Some of them they threw down, others they destroyed by fire, and thus
                    there was an end to Hannibal's attempts against the citadel in that quarter.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> His only remaining hope was in a siege;
                    nor did that afford a good prospect of success, because, occupying a citadel
                    which was placed on a peninsula and commanded the entrance of the harbour, they
                    had the sea open to them, while the city, on the contrary, was deprived of any
                    supplies by <pb n="972" xml:id="p.972"/> sea; and thus the besiegers were in
                    greater danger of want than the besieged. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Hannibal assembled the chief men of the Tarentines, and laid before them all the
                    present difficulties. He said, <quote> That he could neither discover any method
                        by which a citadel so well fortified could be taken, nor could he hope for
                        any favourable result from a siege, while the enemy was master of the sea;
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> but that if ships could be obtained,
                        by which the introduction of supplies might be prevented, the enemy would
                        either immediately evacuate it, or surrender themselves. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The Tarentines agreed with him; but were of
                    opinion, that <quote> he who gave the advice ought also to assist in carrying it
                        into execution; for if the Carthaginian ships were brought there from
                        Sicily, they would be able to effect it; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        but by what means could their own ships, shut up as they were in a confined
                        harbour, the mouth of which was in the command of the enemy, be brought out
                        into the open sea. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>They shall be brought out,</quote> said Hannibal. <quote> Many things
                        which are difficult in themselves, are easily effected by contrivance. You
                        have a city situated upon a plain; you have level and sufficiently wide
                        roads extending in every direction. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> By
                        the road which runs through the midst of the city from the harbour to the
                        sea I will convey your ships in waggons without any great difficulty, and
                        the sea will be ours which the enemy now commands. We will invest the
                        citadel on one side by sea, on the other by land; nay, rather, in a short
                        time, we will take it either abandoned by the enemy, or with the enemy in
                        it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> This speech not only inspired hopes of
                    accomplishing the object, but excited the greatest admiration of the general.
                    Waggons were immediately collected from every quarter and joined together;
                    machines were employed to haul the ships on shore, and the road was prepared, in
                    order that the waggons might run more easily, and thus the difficulty of passing
                    be diminished. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Beasts of burden and men were
                    next collected, and the work was actively commenced. After the lapse of a few
                    days, the fleet, equipped and ready for action, sailed round the citadel, and
                    cast anchor just before the mouth of the harbour. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> Such was the state of things at Tarentum, when Hannibal
                    left it and returned to his winter quarters. Authors, however, are divided as to
                    whether the defection of the Tarentines took place in the present or former
                    year. The greater number, and those who, from their age, were more <pb n="973"
                        xml:id="p.973"/> able to recollect these events, represent it to have
                    occurred in the present year. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Latin holidays detained the consuls and
                    praetors at Rome till the fifth of the calends of May; on which day, having
                    completed the solemnities on the mount, they proceeded to their respective
                    provinces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Afterwards a new difficulty
                    respecting religious matters arose out of the prophetic verses of Marcius, who
                    had been a distinguished soothsayer; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and on a
                    search being made the year before, for books of this description, agreeably to a
                    decree of the senate, these verses had fallen into the hands of Marcus Atilius,
                    the city praetor, who had the management of that business, and he had
                    immediately handed them over to the new praetor, Sulla. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The importance attached to one of the two predictions of
                    Marcius, which was brought to light after the event to which it related had
                    occurred, and the truth of which was confirmed by the event, attached credence
                    to the other, the time of whose fulfilment had not yet arrived. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> In the former prophecy, the disaster at Cannae was
                    predicted in nearly these words: <quote> Roman of Trojan descent, fly the river
                        Canna, lest foreigners should compel thee to fight in the plain of Diomede.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But thou wilt not believe me until
                        thou shalt have filled the plain with blood, and the river carries into the
                        great sea, from the fruitful land, many thousands of your slain countrymen,
                        and thy flesh becomes a prey for fishes, birds, and beasts inhabiting the
                        earth. For thus hath Jupiter declared to me. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Those who had served in that quarter
                    recognised the correspondence with respect to the plains of the Argive Diomede
                    and the river Canna, as well as the defeat itself. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The other prophecy was then read, which was more obscure,
                    not only because future events are more uncertain than past, but also from being
                    more perplexed in its style of composition. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Romans, if you wish to expel the enemy and the ulcer which has come from
                        afar, I advise, that games should be vowed, which may be performed in a
                        cheerful manner annually to Apollo; when the people shall have given a
                        portion of money from the public coffers, that private individuals then
                        contribute, each according to his ability. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> That the praetor shall preside in the celebration of these games, who
                        holds the supreme administration of justice to the people and commons. Let
                        the decemviri perform sacrifice with victims after the Grecian fashion. If
                        you do these things properly you will <pb n="974" xml:id="p.974"/> ever
                        rejoice, and your affairs will be more prosperous, for that deity will
                        destroy your enemies who now, composedly, feed upon your plains. </quote>
                    They took one day to explain this prophecy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The next day a decree of the senate was passed, that the decemviri should
                    inspect the books relating to the celebration of games and sacred rites in
                    honour of Apollo. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After they had been
                    consulted, and a report made to the senate, the fathers voted, that <quote>
                        games should be vowed to Apollo and celebrated; and that when the games were
                        concluded, twelve thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> should be given to
                        the praetor to defray the expense of sacred ceremonies, and also two victims
                        of the larger sort. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A second decree was passed, that <quote> the
                        decemviri should perform sacrifice in the Grecian mode, and with the
                        following victims: to Apollo, with a gilded ox, and two white goats gilded;
                        to Latona, with a gilded heifer. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When the praetor was about to celebrate the
                    games in the Circus Maximus, he issued an order, that during the celebration of
                    the games, the people should pay a contribution, as large as was convenient, for
                    the service of Apollo. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> This is the origin of
                    the Apollinarian games, which were vowed and celebrated in order to victory, and
                    not restoration to health, as is commonly supposed. The people viewed the
                    spectacle in garlands; the matrons made supplications; the people in general
                    feasted in the courts of their houses, throwing the doors open; and the day was
                    distinguished by every description of ceremony. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Hannibal was in the neighbourhood of
                    Tarentum, and both the consuls in Samnium, though they seemed as if they were
                    about to besiege Capua, the Campanians were experiencing famine, that calamity
                    which is the usual attendant of a protracted siege. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It was occasioned by the Roman armies' having prevented the
                    sowing of the lands. They therefore sent ambassadors to Hannibal, imploring him
                    to give orders that corn should be conveyed to Capua from the neighbouring
                    places, before both the consuls led their legions into their fields, and all the
                    roads were blocked up by the troops of the enemy. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal ordered Hanno to pass with his army from Bruttium
                    into Campania, and to take care that the Campanians were supplied with corn.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hanno, setting out from Bruttium with his
                    army, and carefully avoiding the camp of the enemy and the consuls who were in
                    Samnium, when he drew near to Beneventum, pitched his camp on an eminence three
                        <pb n="975" xml:id="p.975"/> miles from the city. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He next ordered that the corn which- had been collected
                    during the summer, should be brought from the neighbouring people in alliance
                    with him, into his camp, assigning a guard to escort those supplies. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> He then sent a messenger to the Capuans, fixing a day
                    when they should attend at his camp to receive the corn, bringing with them
                    vehicles and beasts of every description, collected from every part of their
                    country. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Campanians executed this business
                    with their usual indolence and carelessness. Somewhat more than four hundred
                    vehicles, with a few beasts of burden besides, were sent. After receiving a
                    reproof from Hanno for this conduct, who told them, that not even hunger, which
                    excited dumb animals to exertion, could stimulate them to diligence, another day
                    was named when they were to fetch the corn after better preparation. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> All these transactions being reported to the
                    Beneventans, just as they occurred, they lost no time in sending ten ambassadors
                    to the Roman consuls, who were encamped in the neighbourhood of Bovianum.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consuls, hearing what was going on at
                    Capua, arranged it so that one of them should lead an army into Campania; and
                    Fulvius, to whose lot that province had fallen, setting out by night, entered
                    the walls of Beneventum. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Being now near the
                    enemy, he obtained information that Hanno had gone out to forage with a portion
                    of his troops; that the Campanians were supplied with corn by a quaestor; that
                    two thousand waggons had arrived together with an undisciplined and unarmed
                    rabble; that every thing was done in a disorderly and hurried manner; and that
                    the form of a camp, and all military subordination, were destroyed by the
                    intermixture of rustics out of the neighbourhood. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> This intelligence being sufficiently, authenticated, the
                    consul ordered his soldiers to get ready only their standards and arms against
                    the next night, as he must attack the Carthaginian camp. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> They set out at the fourth watch of the night, leaving all
                    their packages and baggage of every description at Beneventum; and arriving a
                    little before daylight at the camp, they occasioned such a panic, that, had the
                    camp been situated on level ground, it might doubtlessly have been taken on the
                    first assault. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The height of its situation
                    and the works defended it; for they could not be approached on any side except
                    by a steep and difficult ascent. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> At break of
                    day a hot engagement commenced, when <pb n="976" xml:id="p.976"/> the
                    Carthaginians not only defended their rampart, but having more even ground,
                    threw down the enemy as they attempted to ascend the steep. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Persevering courage, however, at length
                    prevailed over every impediment, and they made their way up to the ditch and
                    rampart in several parts at the-same time, but with many wounds and much loss of
                    soldiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul, therefore, assembling
                    the military tribunes, said they must desist from this inconsiderate enterprise;
                    and that it appeared to him to be the safer course, that the troops should be
                    led back to Beneventum for that day, and then on the following day to pitch his
                    camp close to that of the enemy, so that the Campanians could not quit it, nor
                    Hanno return to it; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and in order that that
                    object might be attained with the greater ease, that he should send for his
                    colleague and his army; and that they would direct their whole force on that
                    point. This plan of the general was disconcerted, after the signal began to
                    sound for a retreat, by the clamours of the soldiery, who despised so
                    pusillanimous an order. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nearest to the gate of
                    the enemy's camp was a Pelignian cohort, whose commander, Vibius Accuaeus,
                    seizing the standard, threw it over the rampart. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Then pronouncing a curse upon himself and his cohort, if the enemy got
                    possession of that standard, he rushed forward before the rest, and crossing the
                    ditch and rampart, burst into the camp of the enemy. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Pelignians were now fighting within the rampart, when
                    in another quarter Valerius Flaccus, a military tribune of the third legion,
                    taunting the Romans with cowardice for conceding to allies the honour of taking
                    the camp, Titus Pedanius, first centurion of the first century, snatched the
                    standard out of the hands of the standard-bearer, and cried out, <quote> Soon
                        shall this standard, and this centurion, be within the rampart of the enemy;
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> let those follow who would prevent the
                        standard's being captured by the enemy. </quote> Crossing the ditch, he was
                    followed first by the men of his own maniple, and then by the whole legion.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By this time the consul also, changing his
                    plan on seeing them crossing the rampart, began to incite and encourage his
                    soldiers, instead of calling them off; representing to them, how critical and
                    perilous was the situation of the bravest cohort of their allies, and a legion
                    of their countrymen. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> All, therefore, severally
                    exerting themselves to the utmost, regardless whether the <pb n="977"
                        xml:id="p.977"/> ground were even or uneven, while showers of weapons were
                    thrown against them from all sides, the enemy opposing their arms and their
                    persons to obstruct them, made their way and burst in. Many who were wounded,
                    even those whose blood and strength failed them, pressed forward, that they
                    might fall within the rampart of the enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The camp, therefore, was taken in an instant, as if it had been situated upon
                    level ground, and not completely fortified. What followed was a carnage rather
                    than a battle. The troops of both sides being huddled together within the
                    rampart, above six thousand of the enemy were slain; above seven thousand,
                    together with the Campanians who fetched the corn, and the whole collection of
                    waggons and beasts of burden, were captured. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There was also a great booty, which Hanno in his predatory excursions, which he
                    had been careful to make in every quarter, had drawn together from the lands of
                    the allies of the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After throwing down
                    the camp of the enemy, they returned thence to Beneventum; and there both the
                    consuls (for Appius Claudius came thither a few days after) sold the booty and
                    distributed <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> it, making presents to those by
                    whose exertions the camp of the enemy had been captured; above all, to Accuaeus
                    the Pelignian, and Titus Pedanius, first centurion of the third legion.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Hanno, setting off from Cominium in the
                    territory of Cere, whither intelligence of the loss of the camp had reached him,
                    with a small party of foragers, whom he happened to have with him, returned to
                    Bruttium, more after the manner of a flight than a march. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Campanians, when informed of the disaster
                    which had befallen themselves and their allies, sent ambassadors to Hannibal to
                    inform him, that <quote> the two consuls were at Beneventum, which was a day's
                        march from Capua; that the war was all but at their gates and their walls;
                        and that if he did not hasten to their assistance, Capua would fall into the
                        power of the enemy sooner than Arpi had; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        that not even Tarentum itself, much less its citadel, ought to be considered
                        of so much consequence as to induce him to deliver up to the Roman people,
                        abandoned and undefended, Capua, which he used to place on an equal footing
                        with Carthage. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal, promising that he would not neglect
                    the interest of the Campanians, sent, for the present, two thousand horse, with
                    the ambassadors, aided by which, they might secure their lands <pb n="978"
                        xml:id="p.978"/> from devastation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    Romans, meanwhile, among the other things which engaged their attention, had an
                    eye to the citadel of Tarentum, and the garrison besieged therein. Caius
                    Servilius, lieutenant-general, having been sent, according to the advice of the
                    fathers, by Publius Cornelius, the praetor, to purchase corn in Etruria, made
                    his way into the harbour of Tarentum, through the guard-ships of the enemy, with
                    some ships of burden. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At his arrival, those
                    who before, having very slight hopes of holding out, were frequently invited by
                    the enemy, in conferences, to pass over to them, now, on the contrary, were the
                    persons to invite and solicit the enemy to come over to them; and now, as the
                    soldiers who were at Metapontum had been brought to assist in guarding the
                    citadel of Tarentum, the garrison was sufficiently powerful. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> In consequence of this measure, the Metapontines, being
                    freed from the fears which had influenced them, immediately revolted to
                    Hannibal. The people of Thurium, situated on the same coast, did the same.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were influenced not more by the
                    defection of the Metapontines and Tarentines, with whom they were connected,
                    being sprung from the same country, Achaia, than by resentment towards the
                    Romans, in consequence of the recent execution of the hostages. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The friends and relations of these hostages sent a letter
                    and a message to Hanno and Mago, who were not far off among the Bruttii, to the
                    effect, that if they brought their troops up to the walls, they would deliver
                    the city into their hands. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcus Atinius was
                    in command at Thurium, with a small garrison, who they thought might easily be
                    induced to engage rashly in a battle, not from any confidence which he reposed
                    in his troops, of which he had very few, but in the youth of Thurium, whom he
                    had purposely formed into centuries, and armed against emergencies of this kind.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The generals, after dividing their forces
                    between them, entered the territory of Thurium; and Hanno, with a body of
                    infantry, proceeded towards the city in hostile array. Hanno staid behind with
                    the cavalry, under the cover of some hills, conveniently placed for the
                    concealment of an ambush. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Atinius, having by
                    his scouts discovered only the body of infantry, led his troops into the field,
                    ignorant both of the domestic treachery and of the stratagem of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The engagement with the infantry was
                    particularly dull, a few Romans in the first rank engaging, <pb n="979"
                        xml:id="p.979"/> while the Thurians rather waited than helped on the issue.
                    The Carthaginian line retreated, on purpose that they might draw the incautious
                    enemy to the back of the hill, where their cavalry were lying in ambush; and
                    when they had come there, the cavalry rising up on a sudden with a shout,
                    immediately put to flight the almost undisciplined rabble of the Thurians, not
                    firmly attached to the side on which they fought. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans, notwithstanding they were surrounded and hard
                    pressed on one side by the infantry, on the other by the cavalry, yet prolonged
                    the battle for a considerable time; but at length even they were compelled to
                    turn their backs, and fled towards the city. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    There the conspirators, forming themselves into a dense body, received the
                    multitude of their countrymen with open gates; <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                    /> but when they perceived that the routed Romans were hurrying towards the
                    city, they exclaimed that the Carthaginian was close at hand, and that the enemy
                    would enter the city mingled with them, unless they speedily closed the gates.
                    Thus they shut out the Romans, and left them to be cut up by the enemy.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Atinius, however, and a few others were
                    taken in. After this for a short time there was a division between them, some
                    being of opinion that they ought to defend the city, others that they ought,
                    after all that had happened, to yield to fortune, and deliver up the city to the
                    conquerors; but, as it generally happens, fortune and evil counsels prevailed.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Having conveyed Atinius and his party to
                    the sea and the ships, more because they wished that care should be taken of
                    him, in consequence of the mildness and justice of <milestone n="18??"
                        unit="section"/> his command, than from regard to the Romans, they received
                    the Carthaginians into the city. The consuls led their legions from Beneventum
                    into the Campanian territory, with the intention not only of destroying the
                    corn, which was in the blade, but of laying siege to Capua; <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/> considering that they would render their consulate
                    illustrious by the destruction of so opulent a city, and that they would wipe
                    away the foul disgrace of the empire, from the defection of a city so near
                    remaining unpunished for three years. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Lest,
                    however, Beneventum should be left without protection, and that in case of any
                    sudden emergency, if Hannibal should come to Capua, in order to bring assistance
                    to his friends, which they doubted not he would do, the cavalry might be able to
                    sustain his attack, they ordered Tiberius Gracchus to come from Lu- <pb n="980"
                        xml:id="p.980"/> cania to Beneventum with his cavalry and light-armed
                    troops, and to appoint some person to take the command of the legions and
                    stationary camp, for the defence of Lucania. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An unlucky prodigy occurred to Gracchus, while
                    sacrificing, previous to his departure from Lucania. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Two snakes gliding from a secret place to the entrails,
                    after the sacrifice was completed, ate the liver; and after having been
                    observed, suddenly vanished out of sight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    sacrifice having been repeated according to the admonition of the aruspices, and
                    the vessel containing the entrails being watched with increased attention, it is
                    reported that the snakes came a second, and a third time, and, after tasting the
                    liver, went away untouched. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Though the
                    aruspices forewarned him that the portent had reference to the general, and that
                    he ought to be on his guard against secret enemies and machinations, yet no
                    foresight could avert the destiny which awaited him. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> There was a Lucanian, named Flavius, the leader of that
                    party which adhered to the Romans when the others went over to Hannibal; he was
                    this year in the magistracy, having been created praetor by the same party.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Suddenly changing his mind, and seeking to
                    ingratiate himself with the Carthaginians, he did not think it enough that he
                    himself should pass over to them, or that he should induce the Lucanians to
                    revolt with him, unless he ratified his league with the enemy with the head and
                    blood of the general, betrayed to them, though his guest. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He entered into a secret conference with Mago, who had the
                    command in Bruttium, and receiving a solemn promise from him, that he would take
                    the Lucanians into his friendship, without interfering with their laws, if he
                    should betray the Roman general to the Carthaginians, he conducted Mago to a
                    place to which he was about to bring Gracchus with a few attendants. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> He then directed Mago to arm his infantry and
                    cavalry, and to occupy the retired places there, in which he might conceal a
                    very large number of troops. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After thoroughly
                    inspecting and exploring the place on all sides, a day was agreed upon for the
                    execution of the affair. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Flavius came to the
                    Roman general, and said, that <quote> he had begun a business of great
                        importance, for the completion of which, it was necessary to have the
                        assistance of Gracchus himself. That he had persuaded the praetors of all
                        the states which had revolted to the Carthaginians in the general defection
                        of Italy, to return into <pb n="981" xml:id="p.981"/> the friendship of
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> the Romans, since now the Roman
                        power too, which had almost come to ruin by the disaster at Cannae, was
                        daily improving and increasing, while the strength of Hannibal was sinking
                        into decay, and was almost reduced to nothing. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> He had told them that the Romans would be disposed to
                        accept an atonement for their former offence; that there never was any state
                        more easy to be entreated, or more ready to grant pardon; how often, he had
                        observed to them, had they forgiven rebellion even in their own ancestors!
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These considerations, </quote> he
                    said, <quote> he had himself urged, but that they would rather hear the same
                        from Gracchus himself in person, and touching his right hand, carry with
                        them that pledge of faith. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> That he had
                        agreed upon a place with those who were privy to the transaction, out of the
                        way of observation, and at no great distance from the Roman camp; that there
                        the business might be settled in few words, so that all the Lucanian states
                        might be in the alliance and friendship of the Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Gracchus, not suspecting any treachery either
                    from his words or the nature of the proposal, and being caught by the
                    probability of the thing, set out from the camp with his lictors and a troop of
                    horse, under the guidance of his host, and fell headlong into the snare.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The enemy suddenly arose from their
                    lurking-place, and Flavius joined them; which made the treachery obvious. A
                    shower of weapons was poured from all sides on Gracchus and his troop.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> He immediately leaped from his horse, and
                    ordering the rest to do the same, exhorted them, that <quote> as fortune had
                        left them only one course, they would render it glorious by their valour.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> And what is there left, </quote> said
                    he, <quote> to a handful of men, surrounded by a multitude, in a valley hemmed
                        in by a wood and mountains, except death? <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        The only question was, whether, tamely exposing themselves to be butchered
                        like cattle, they should die unavenged; or whether, drawing the mind off
                        from the idea of suffering and anticipation of the event, and giving full
                        scope to fury and resentment, they should fall while doing and daring,
                        covered with hostile blood, amid heaps of arms and bodies of their expiring
                        foes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> He desired that <quote>all would aim at the
                        Lucanian traitor and deserter;</quote> adding, that <quote> the man who
                        should send that victim to the shades before him, would acquire the most
                        distinguished glory, and furnish the highest consolation for his own death. </quote>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> While thus speaking, <pb n="982"
                        xml:id="p.982"/> he wound his cloak round his left arm, for they had not
                    even brought their shields out with them, and then rushed upon the enemy.
                        <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> The exertion made in the fight was
                    greater than could be expected from the smallness of the number. The bodies of
                    the Romans were most exposed to the javelins, with which, as they were thrown on
                    all sides from higher ground into a deep valley, they were transfixed.
                        <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians seeing Gracchus now
                    bereft of support, endeavoured to take him alive; but he having descried his
                    Lucanian host among the enemy, rushed with such fury into their dense body that
                    it became impossible to save his life without a great loss. <milestone n="24"
                        unit="section"/> Mago immediately sent his corpse to Hannibal, ordering it
                    to be placed, with the fasces which were taken at the same time, before the
                    tribunal of the general. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> This is the true
                    account; Gracchus fell in Lucania, near the place called the Old Plains. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There are some who have put forth an account,
                    stating, that when in the territory of Beneventum, near the river Calor, having
                    gone out from his camp with his lictors and three servants, for the <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> purpose of bathing, he was slain while naked and
                    unarmed, and endeavouring to defend himself with the stones which the river
                    brought down, by a party of the enemy which happened to be concealed among the
                    osiers which grew upon the banks. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Others
                    state, that having gone out five hundred paces from the camp, at the instance of
                    the aruspices, in order to expiate the prodigies before mentioned on unpolluted
                    ground, he was cut off by two troops of Numidians who happened to be lying in
                    ambush there. So different are the accounts respecting the place and manner of
                    the death of so illustrious and distinguished a man. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Various also are the accounts of the funeral of Gracchus.
                    Some say that he was buried by his own friends in the Roman camp; others relate,
                    and this is the more generally received account, that a funeral pile was erected
                    by Hannibal, in the entrance of the Carthaginian camp; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> that the troops under arms performed evolutions, with the
                    dances of the Spaniards, and motions of the arms and body, which were customary
                    with the several nations; while Hannibal himself celebrated his obsequies with
                    every mark of respect, both in word and deed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Such is the account of those who assert that the affair occurred in Lucania.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If you are disposed to credit the
                    statement of those who re- <pb n="983" xml:id="p.983"/> late that he was slain
                    at the river Calor, the enemy got possession only of the head of Gracchus; which
                    being brought to Hannibal, he immediately despatched Carthalo to convey it into
                    the Roman camp to Cneius Cornelius, the quaestor, who buried the general in the
                    camp, the Beneventans joining the army in the celebration. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls having entered the Campanian
                    territory, while devastating the country on all sides, were alarmed, and thrown
                    into confusion, by an eruption of the townsmen and Mago with his cavalry. They
                    called in their troops to their standards from the several quarters to which
                    they were dispersed, but having been routed when they had scarcely formed their
                    line, they lost above fifteen hundred men. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    confidence of the Campanians, who were naturally presumptuous, became excessive
                    in consequence of this event, and in many battles they challenged the Romans;
                    but this one battle, which they had been incautiously and imprudently drawn
                    into, had increased the vigilance of the consuls. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Their spirits were restored, while the presumption of the
                    other party was diminished, by one trifling occurrence; but in war nothing is so
                    inconsiderable as not to be capable, sometimes, of producing important
                    consequences. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius Crispinus was a
                    guest of Badius, a Campanian, united with him by the greatest intimacy. Their
                    acquaintance had increased from the circumstance of Badius having received the
                    most liberal and kind attentions at the house of Crispinus, in a fit of illness,
                    at Rome, before the Campanian revolt. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the
                    present occasion, Badius, advancing in front of the guards, which were stationed
                    before the gate, desired Crispinus to be called; and Crispinus, on being
                    informed of this, thinking that a friendly and familiar interview was requested,
                    and the memory of their private connexion remaining even amidst the disruption
                    of public ties, advanced a little from the rest. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> When they had come within view of each other, Badius exclaimed, <quote> I
                        challenge you to combat, Crispinus; let us mount our horses, and making the
                        rest withdraw, let us try which is the better soldier. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In reply, Crispinus said, that <quote> neither
                        of them were in want of enemies to display their valour upon; for his own
                        part, even if he should meet him in the field he would turn aside, lest he
                        should pollute his right-hand with the blood of a guest; </quote> and then
                    turning round, was going away. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the <pb
                        n="984" xml:id="p.984"/> Campanian, with increased presumption, began to
                    charge him with cowardice and effeminacy, and cast upon him reproaches which he
                    deserved himself, calling him <quote> an enemy who sheltered himself under the
                        title of host, and one who pretended to spare him for whom he knew himself
                        not to be a match. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If he considered, that
                        when public treaties were broken, the ties of private connexion were not
                        severed with them, then Badius the Campanian openly, and in the hearing of
                        both armies, renounced his connexion of hospitality with Titus Quinctius
                        Crispinus the Roman. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He said, that there
                        could exist no fellowship or alliance with him and an enemy whose country
                        and tutelary gods, both public and private, he had come to fight against. If
                        he was a man, he would meet him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Crispinus hesitated for a long time; but the
                    men of his troop at length prevailed upon him not to allow the Campanian to
                    insult him with impunity. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Waiting, therefore,
                    only to ask his generals whether they would allow him to fight, contrary to
                    rule, with an enemy who had challenged him; having obtained their permission, he
                    mounted his horse, and addressing Badius by name, called him out to the combat.
                    The Campanian made no delay. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They engaged
                    with their horses excited to hostility. Crispinus transfixed Badius with his
                    spear in the left shoulder, over his shield. He fell from his horse in
                    consequence of the wound; and Crispinus leaped down to despatch him as he lay,
                    on foot. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But Badius, before his enemy was
                    upon him, ran off to his friends, leaving his horse and buckler. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Crispinus, decorated with the spoils, and displaying
                    the horse and arms which he had seized together with the bloody spear, was
                    conducted amid the loud plaudits and congratulations of the soldiery into the
                    presence of the consuls, where he was highly commended, and was presented with
                    gifts. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, having moved his camp from the
                    territory of Beneventum to Capua, drew out his troops in order of battle the
                    third day after his arrival; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> not entertaining
                    the least doubt but that, as the Campanians had fought successfully a few days
                    ago when he was absent, the Romans would be still less able to withstand him and
                    his army, which had been so often victorious. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    After the battle had commenced, the Roman line was distressed chiefly from the
                    attack of the cavalry, being overwhelmed with their darts, till the signal was
                    given to <pb n="985" xml:id="p.985"/> the Roman cavalry to direct their horses
                    against the enemy; thus it was a battle of the cavalry. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But at this time the Sempronian army, commanded by Cneius
                    Cornelius the quaestor, being descried at a distance, excited alarm in both
                    parties equally, lest those who were approaching should be fresh enemies.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As if by concert, therefore, both sounded
                    a retreat; and the troops were withdrawn from the field to their camps, in an
                    equal condition; a greater number, however, of the Romans fell in the first
                    charge of the cavalry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls, to divert
                    the attention of Hannibal from Capua, departed thence on the following night in
                    different directions, Fulvius into the territory of Cuma, Claudius into Lucania.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The next day Hannibal, having received
                    intelligence that the camp of the Romans was deserted, and that they had gone
                    off in different directions in two divisions, doubtful at first which he should
                    follow, commenced the pursuit of Appius; who, after leading him about whichever
                    way he pleased, returned by another route to Capua. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal, while in this quarter, had another opportunity of
                    gaining an advantage. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcus Centenius,
                    surnamed Penula, was distinguished among the centurions of the first rank by the
                    size of his person, and his courage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having
                    gone through his period of service, he was introduced to the senate by Publius
                    Cornelius Sulla, when he requested of the fathers that five thousand men might
                    be placed at his disposal. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He said, that
                        <quote> as he was acquainted with the character of the enemy, and the nature
                        of the country, he should speedily perform some service; and that he would
                        employ those arts by which our generals and armies had been hitherto
                        insnared against the inventor of them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This was not promised more foolishly than it
                    was believed; as if the qualifications of a soldier and a general were the same.
                    Instead of five, eight thousand men were given him, half Romans, half allies.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He himself also got together a
                    considerable number of volunteers, in the country, on his march; and having
                    almost doubled his force, arrived in Lucania, where Hannibal had halted after
                    having in vain pursued Claudius. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> No doubt
                    could be entertained of the issue of a contest which was to take place between
                    Hannibal, as general on one side, and a centurion on the other; between armies,
                    one of which had grown old in victory, the other entirely inexperienced, and for
                    the most part even tumultuary and half-armed. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    As soon <pb n="986" xml:id="p.986"/> as the troops came within sight of each
                    other, and neither of them declined an engagement, the lines were formed. The
                    battle, notwithstanding the utter disparity of the contending parties, lasted
                    more than two hours, the Roman troops acting with the greatest spirit as long as
                    their general survived. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But after that he had
                    fallen, for he continually exposed himself to the weapons of the enemy, not only
                    from regard to his former character, but through fear of the disgrace which
                    would attach to him if he survived a disaster occasioned by his own temerity,
                    the Roman line was immediately routed. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But so
                    completely were they prevented from flying, every way being beset by the
                    cavalry, that scarcely a thousand men escaped out of so large an army; the rest
                    were destroyed on all hands, in one way or other. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The siege of Capua was now resumed by the
                    consuls with the utmost energy. Every thing requisite for the business was
                    conveyed thither and got in readiness. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A store
                    of corn was collected at Casilinum; at the mouth of the Vulturnus, where a town
                    now stands, a strong post was fortified; and a garrison was stationed in
                    Puteoli, which Fabius had formerly fortified, in order to have the command of
                    the neighbouring sea and the river. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Into these
                    two maritime forts, the corn recently sent from Sicily, with that which Marcus
                    Junius, the praetor, had bought up in Etruria, was conveyed from Ostia, to
                    supply the army during the winter. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But, in
                    addition to the disaster sustained in Lucania, the army also of volunteer
                    slaves, who had served during the life of Gracchus with the greatest fidelity,
                    as if discharged from service by the death of their general, left their
                    standards. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal was not willing that Capua
                    should be neglected, or his allies deserted, at so critical a juncture; but,
                    having obtained such success from the temerity of one Roman general, his
                    attention was fixed on the opportunity which presented itself of crushing the
                    other general and his army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Ambassadors from
                    Apulia reported that Cneius Fulvius, the praetor, had at first conducted his
                    measures with caution, while engaged in besieging certain towns of Apulia, which
                    had revolted to Hannibal; but that afterwards, in consequence of extraordinary
                    success, both himself and his soldiers, being glutted with booty, had so given
                    themselves up to licentiousness and indolence, that all military discipline was
                    disregarded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having frequently on <pb n="987"
                        xml:id="p.987"/> other occasions, as well as but a few days ago, experienced
                    what an army was good for, when conducted by an unskilful commander, he moved
                    his camp into Apulia. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman legions, and the praetor, Fulvius,
                    were in the neighbourhood of Herdonia, where, receiving intelligence of the
                    approach of the enemy, they had nearly torn up the standards and gone out to
                    battle without the praetor's orders; nor did any thing tend more to prevent it
                    than the assured hope they entertained that they could do so whenever they
                    pleased, consulting only their own will. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    following night, Hannibal having obtained information that the camp was in a
                    state of tumult, and that most of the troops were in a <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> disorderly manner urging the general to give the signal,
                    and calling out to arms, and therefore feeling convinced that an opportunity
                    presented itself for a successful battle, distributed three thousand light
                    troops in the houses in the neighbourhood, and among the thorns and woods.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These, on a signal being given, were to
                    rise up from their lurking-place with one accord; and Mago, with about two
                    thousand horse, was ordered to occupy all the roads in the direction in which he
                    supposed their flight would be directed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Having made these preparations during the night, he led his troops into the
                    field at break of day. Nor did Fulvius decline the challenge; not so much from
                    any hope of success entertained by himself, as drawn by the blind impetuosity of
                    his soldiers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly, the line itself was
                    formed with the same want of caution with which they entered the field,
                    agreeably to the whim of the soldiers, who came up as chance directed, and took
                    their stations just where they pleased; which they afterwards abandoned, as fear
                    or caprice suggested. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The first legion and the
                    left wing of the allied troops were drawn up in front. The line was extended to
                    a great length, the tribunes remonstrating, that there was no strength in it,
                    and that wherever the enemy made the charge they would break through it: but no
                    salutary advice reached their minds, nor even their ears. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal was now come up, a general of a totally different
                    character, with an army neither similar in its nature, nor similarly marshalled.
                    The consequence was, that the Romans did not so much as sustain their shout and
                    first attack. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Their general, equal to
                    Centenius in folly and temerity, but by no means to be compared with him in
                    courage, when he saw <pb n="988" xml:id="p.988"/> things going against him, and
                    his troops in confusion, hastily mounting his horse, fled from the field with
                    about two hundred horsemen. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The rest of the
                    troops, beaten in front, and surrounded on the flank and rear, were slaughtered
                    to such a degree, that out of eighteen thousand men, not more than two thousand
                    escaped. The enemy got possession of the camp. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these disastrous defeats, happening one
                    upon another, were reported at Rome, great grief and consternation seized the
                    city. But still, as the consuls had been hitherto successful when it was most
                    important, they were the less affected by these disasters. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Caius Laetorius and Marcus Metilius were sent as
                    ambassadors to the consuls, with directions carefully to collect the remains of
                    the two armies, and use every endeavour to prevent their surrendering themselves
                    to the enemy, through fear or despair, (which was the case after the battle of
                    Cannae,) and to search for the deserters from the army of volunteer slaves.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Publius Cornelius was charged with the
                    same business; to him also the levy was intrusted. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He caused an order to be issued throughout the market and
                    smaller towns, that search should be made for the volunteer slaves, and that
                    they should be brought back to their standards. All these things were executed
                    with the most vigilant care. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul,
                    Appius Claudius, having placed Decius Junius in command at the mouth of the
                    Vulturnus, and Marcus Aurelius Cotta at Puteoli, with directions to send off the
                    corn immediately to the camp, as each of the ships from Etruria and Sardinia
                    arrived with it, returned himself to Capua, and found his colleague <milestone
                        n="6??" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius at Casilinum, conveying every
                    requisite thence, and making every preparation for the siege of Capua.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Both of them then joined in besieging the
                    city, summoning Claudius Nero, the praetor, from the Claudian camp at Suessula;
                    who, leaving a small garrison there, marched down to Capua with all the rest of
                    his forces. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thus there were three generals'
                    tents erected round Capua; and three armies, applying themselves to the work in
                    different parts, proceeded to surround the city with a ditch and rampart,
                    erecting forts at moderate intervals. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    Campanians attempting to obstruct the work, a battle was fought in several
                    places at once; the consequence of which was, that at length the Campanians
                    confined themselves within their gates and walls. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Before, however, these works were carried quite <pb n="989"
                        xml:id="p.989"/> round, ambassadors were sent to Hannibal to complain that
                    Capua was abandoned, and almost given up to the Romans; and to implore him, that
                    he would now, at least, bring them assistance, when they were not only besieged,
                    but surrounded by a rampart. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A letter was
                    sent to the consuls from Publius Cornelius, the praetor, directing that before
                    they completely enclosed Capua with their works, they should grant permission to
                    such of the Campanians as chose to quit Capua, and take their property with
                    them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That those should retain their liberty,
                    and all their possessions, who quitted it before the ides of March; but that
                    those who quitted it after that day, as well as those who continued there, would
                    be considered as enemies. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Proclamation was
                    made to the Campanians to this effect; but it was received with such scorn, that
                    they spontaneously used insulting language and menaces. Hannibal had marched his
                    legions from Herdonea to Tarentum, with the hope of getting possession of the
                    citadel of that place, by force or stratagem. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    But not succeeding there, he turned his course to Brundusium, thinking that town
                    would be betrayed to him; but, while fruitlessly spending time there also, the
                    Campanian ambassadors came to him with complaints and entreaties. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Hannibal answered them in a proud manner, that he
                    had before raised the siege of Capua, and that now the consuls would not sustain
                    his approach. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The ambassadors, dismissed with
                    these hopes, with difficulty effected their return to Capua, which was by this
                    time surrounded by a double trench and rampart. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the time when the circumvallation of Capua
                    was carrying on with the greatest activity, the siege of Syracuse, which had
                    been forwarded by intestine treachery, in addition to the efforts and bravery of
                    the general and his army, was brought to a conclusion. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For in the beginning of spring, Marcellus being in doubt
                    whether he should direct the operations of the war against Himilco and
                    Hippocrates at Agrigentum, or press the siege of Syracuse; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> though he saw that it was impossible to take the city by
                    force, which, from its situation, both with respect to sea and land, was
                    impregnable; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> nor by famine, as it was
                    supported by an uninterrupted supply of provisions from Carthage; yet that he
                    might leave no course untried, directed the Syracusan deserters (and there were
                    in the Roman camp some men in this situation of the highest <pb n="990"
                        xml:id="p.990"/> rank, who had been driven out of the city during the
                    defection from the Romans, because they were averse to a change of measures) to
                    sound the feelings of those who were of the same party in conferences, and to
                    promise them, that if Syracuse was delivered up, they should have their liberty,
                    and be governed by their own laws. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was
                    no opportunity, however, of having a conference; for as many were suspected of
                    disaffection, the attention and observation of all were exerted, lest any thing
                    of the kind should occur unknown to them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> One
                    of the exiles, who was a servant, having been allowed to enter the city in the
                    character of a deserter, assembled a few persons, and opened a conversation upon
                    the subject. After this, certain persons, covering themselves with nets in a
                    fishing smack, were in this way conveyed round to the Roman camp, and conferred
                    with the fugitives. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same was frequently
                    repeated by different parties, one after another; and at last they amounted to
                    eighty. But after every thing had been concerted for betraying the city, the
                    plot was reported to Epicydes, by one Attalus, who felt hurt that he had not
                    been intrusted with the secret; and they were all put to death with torture.
                    This attempt having miscarried, another hope was immediately raised. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> One Damippus, a Lacedaemonian, who had been sent from
                    Syracuse to king Philip, had been taken prisoner by the Roman fleet. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Epicydes was particularly anxious to ransom this man
                    above any other; nor was Marcellus disinclined to grant it; the Romans, even at
                    this time, being desirous of gaining the friendship of the Aetolians, with whom
                    the Lacedaemonians were in alliance. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Some
                    persons having been sent to treat respecting his ransom, the most central and
                    convenient place to both parties for this purpose appeared to be at the
                    Trogilian port, near the tower called Galeagra. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> As they went there several times, one of the Romans, having a near view of
                    the wall, and having determined its height, as nearly as it could be done by
                    conjecture, from counting the stones, and by forming an estimate, in his own
                    mind, what was the height of each stone in the face of the work; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> and having come to the conclusion that it was
                    considerably lower than he himself and all the rest had supposed it, and that it
                    was capable of being scaled with ladders of moderate size, laid the matter
                    before Marcellus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It appeared a thing not to
                    be neglected; but as the spot could not be ap- <pb n="991" xml:id="p.991"/>
                    proached, being on this very account guarded with extraordinary care, a
                    favourable opportunity of doing it was sought for. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> This a deserter suggested, who brought intelligence that
                    the Syracusans were celebrating the festival of Diana; that it was to last three
                    days, and that as there was a deficiency of other things during the siege, the
                    feasts would be more profusely celebrated with wine, which was furnished by
                    Epicydes to the people in general, and distributed through the tribes by persons
                    of distinction. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When Marcellus had received
                    this intelligence, he communicated it to a few of the military tribunes; then
                    having selected, through their means, such centurions and soldiers as had
                    courage and energy enough for so important an enterprise, and having privately
                    gotten together a number of scaling-ladders, he directed that a signal should be
                    given to the rest of the troops to take their refreshment, and go to rest early,
                    for they were to go upon an expedition that night. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> Then the time, as it was supposed, having arrived, when,
                    after having feasted from the middle of the day, they would have had their fill
                    of wine, and have begun to sleep, he ordered the soldiers of one company to
                    proceed with the ladders, while about a thousand armed men were in silence
                    marched to the spot in a slender column. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The
                    foremost having mounted the wall, without noise or confusion, the others
                    followed in order; the boldness of the former inspiring even the irresolute with
                    courage. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The thousand armed men had now taken a part of
                    the city, when the rest, applying a greater number of ladders, mounted the wall
                    on a signal given from the Hexapylos. To this place the former party had arrived
                    in entire solitude; as the greater part of them, having feasted in the towers,
                    were either asleep from the effects of wine, or else, half asleep, were still
                    drinking. A few of them, however, they surprised in their beds, and put to the
                    sword. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They began then to break open a postern
                    gate near the Hexapylos, which required great force; and a signal was given from
                    the wall by sounding a trumpet, as had been agreed upon. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> After this, the attack was carried on in every quarter, not
                    secretly, but by open force; for they had now reached Epipolae, a place
                    protected by numerous guards, where the business was to terrify the enemy, and
                    not to escape their notice. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In effect they
                    were terrified; for as soon as the sound of the trumpets was heard, <pb n="992"
                        xml:id="p.992"/> and the shouts of the men who <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> had got possession of the walls and a part of the city, the
                    guards concluded that every part was taken, and some of them fled along the
                    wall, others leaped down from it, or were thrown down headlong by a crowd of the
                    terrified townsmen. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A great part of the
                    inhabitants, however, were ignorant of this disastrous event, all of them being
                    overpowered with wine and sleep; and because, in a city of so wide extent, what
                    was perceived in one quarter was not readily made known through the whole city.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A little before day, Marcellus having
                    entered the city with all his forces, through the Hexapylos, which was forced
                    open, roused all the townsmen; who ran to arms, in order, if possible, by their
                    efforts, to afford succour to the city, which was now almost taken. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Epicydes advanced with a body of troops at a rapid
                    pace from the Insula, which the Syracusans themselves call Nasos, not doubting
                    but that he should be able to drive out what he supposed a small party, which
                    had got over the wall through the negligence of the guards. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He earnestly represented to the terrified inhabitants who
                    met him, that they were increasing the confusion, and that in their accounts
                    they made things greater and more important than they really were. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> But when he perceived that every place around
                    Epipolae was filled with armed men, after just teazing the enemy with the
                    discharge of a few missiles, he marched back to the Achradina, not so much
                    through fear of the number and strength of the enemy, as that some intestine
                    treachery might show itself, taking advantage of the opportunity, and he might
                    find the gates of the Achradina and island closed upon him in the confusion.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When Marcellus, having entered the walls,
                    beheld this city as it lay subjected to his view from the high ground on which
                    he stood, a city the most beautiful, perhaps, of any at that time, he is said to
                    have shed tears over it; partly from the inward satisfaction he felt at having
                    accomplished so important an enterprise, and partly in consideration of its
                    ancient renown. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The fleets of the Athenians
                    sunk there, and two vast armies destroyed, with two generals of the highest
                    reputation, as well as the many wars waged with the Carthaginians with so much
                    peril, arose before his mind; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> the many and
                    powerful tyrants and kings; but above all Hiero, a king who was not only fresh
                    in his memory, but who was distinguished for the signal <pb n="993"
                        xml:id="p.993"/> services he had rendered the Roman people, and more than
                    all by the endowments which his own virtues and good fortune had conferred.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> All these considerations presenting
                    themselves at once to his recollection, and reflecting, that in an instant every
                    thing before him would be in flames, and reduced to ashes; <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> before he marched his troops to the Achradina, he sent
                    before him some Syracusans, who, as was before observed, were among the Roman
                    troops, to induce the enemy, by a persuasive address, to surrender the city. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The gates and walls of the Achradina were
                    occupied principally by deserters, who had no hopes of pardon in case of
                    capitulation. These men would neither suffer those who were sent to approach the
                    walls, nor to address them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Marcellus,
                    therefore, on the failure of this attempt, gave orders to retire to the
                    Euryalus, which is an eminence at the extremity of the city, at the farthest
                    point from the sea, and commanding the road leading into the fields and the
                    interior of the island, and is conveniently situated for the introduction of
                    supplies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This fort was commanded by
                    Philodemus, an Argive, who was placed in this situation by Epicydes. Marcellus
                    sent Sosis, one of the regicides, to him. After a long conversation, being put
                    off for the purpose of frustrating him, he brought back word to Marcellus, that
                    Philodemus had taken time to deliberate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This
                    man postponing his answer day after day, till Hippocrates and Himilco should
                    quit their present position, and come up with their legions; not doubting but
                    that if he should receive them into the fort, the Roman army, shut up as it was
                    within the walls, might be <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> annihilated,
                    Marcellus, who saw that the Euryalus would neither be delivered up to him, nor
                    could be taken by force, pitched his camp between Neapolis and Tycha, which are
                    names of divisions of the city, and are in themselves like cities; fearful lest
                    if he entered populous parts of the city, he should not be able to restrain his
                    soldiers, greedy of plunder, from running up and down after it. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When three ambassadors came to him from Tycha and Neapolis
                    with fillets and other badges of supplicants, imploring him to abstain from fire
                    and slaughter, Marcellus, having held a <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    council respecting these entreaties, for so they were, rather than demands,
                    ordered his soldiers, according to the unanimous opinion of the council, not to
                    offer violence to any free person, but told them that every thing <pb n="994"
                        xml:id="p.994"/> else might be their booty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> The walls of the houses forming a protection for his camp, he posted guards
                    and parties of troops at the gates, which were exposed, as they faced the
                    streets, lest any attack should be made upon his camp while the soldiers were
                    dispersed in pursuit of plunder. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After these
                    arrangements, on a signal given, the soldiers dispersed for that purpose; and
                    though they broke open doors and every place resounded in consequence of the
                    alarm and confusion created, they nevertheless refrained from blood. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> They did not desist from plunder till they had
                    gutted the houses of all the property which had been accumulated during a long
                    period of prosperity. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, Philodemus
                    also, who despaired of obtaining assistance, having received a pledge that he
                    might return to Epicydes in safety, withdrew the garrison, and delivered up the
                    fortress to the Romans. While the attention of all was engaged by the tumult
                    occasioned in that part of the city which was captured, Bomilcar, taking
                    advantage of the night, when, from <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> the
                    violence of the weather the Roman fleet was unable to ride at anchor in the
                    deep, set out from the bay of Syracuse, with thirty-five ships, and sailed away
                    into the main without interruption; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> leaving
                    fifty-five ships for Epicydes and the Syracusans; and having informed the
                    Carthaginians in what a critical situation Syracuse was placed, returned, after
                    a few days, with a hundred ships; having, as report says, received many presents
                    from Epicydes out of the treasure of Hiero. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus, by gaining possession of the
                    Euryalus, and placing a garrison in it, was freed from one cause of anxiety;
                    which was, lest any hostile force received into that fortress on his rear might
                    annoy his troops, shut up and confined as they were within the walls. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> He next invested the Achradina, erecting three camps
                    in convenient situations, with the hope of reducing those enclosed within it to
                    the want of every necessary. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The outposts of
                    both sides had remained inactive for several days, when the arrival of
                    Hippocrates and Himilco suddenly caused the Romans to be attacked aggressively
                    on all sides; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> for Hippocrates, having
                    fortified a camp at the great harbour, and given a signal to those who occupied
                    the Achradina, attacked the old camp of the Romans, in which Crispinus had the
                    command; and Epicydes sallied out against the outposts of Marcellus, the
                    Carthaginian fleet coming up to that <pb n="995" xml:id="p.995"/> part of the
                    shore which lay between the city and the Roman camp, so that no succour could be
                    sent by Marcellus to Crispinus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The enemy,
                    however, produced more tumult than conflict; for Crispinus not only drove back
                    Hippocrates from his works, but pursued him as he fled with precipitation, while
                    Marcellus drove Epicydes into the city; and it was considered that enough was
                    now done even to prevent any danger arising in future from their sudden sallies.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were visited too by a plague; a
                    calamity extending to both sides, and one which might well divert their
                    attention from schemes of war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For as the
                    season' of the year was autumn, and the situation naturally unwholesome, though
                    this was much more the case without than within the city, the intolerable
                    intensity of the heat had an effect upon the constitution of almost every man in
                    both the camps. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At first they sickened and
                    died from the unhealthiness of the season and climate; but afterwards the
                    disease was spread merely by attending upon, and coming in contact with, those
                    affected; so that those who were seized with it either perished neglected and
                    deserted, or else drew with them those who sat by them and attended them, by
                    infecting them with the same violence of disease. Daily funerals and death were
                    before the eye; and lamentations were heard from all sides, day and night.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At last, their feelings had become so
                    completely brutalized by being habituated to these miseries, that they not only
                    did not follow their dead with tears and decent lamentations, but they did not
                    even carry them out and bury them; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> so that
                    the bodies of the dead lay strewed about, exposed to the view of those who were
                    awaiting a similar fate; and thus the dead were the means of destroying the
                    sick, and the sick those who were in health, both by fear and by the filthy
                    state and the noisome stench of their bodies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Some preferring to die by the sword, even rushed alone upon the out-posts of the
                    enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The violence of the plague, however,
                    was much greater in the Carthaginian than the Roman army; for the latter, from
                    having been a long time before Syracuse, had become more habituated to the
                    climate and the water. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Of the army of the
                    enemy, the Sicilians, as soon as they perceived that diseases had become very
                    common from the unwholesomeness of the situation, dispersed to their respective
                    cities in the neighbourhood; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> but the
                    Carthaginians, who had no place to retire to, perished, together <pb n="996"
                        xml:id="p.996"/> with their generals, Hippocrates and Himilco, to a man.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Marcellus, on seeing the violence with
                    which the disease was raging, had removed his troops into the city, where their
                    debilitated frames were recruited in houses and shade. Many, however, of the
                    Roman army were cut off by this pestilence. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The land forces of the Carthaginians being
                    thus destroyed, the Sicilians, who had served under Hippocrates, retired to two
                    towns of no great size, but well secured by natural situation and
                    fortifications; one was three miles, the other fifteen, from Syracuse. Here they
                    collected a store of provisions from their own states, and sent for
                    reinforcements. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, Bomilcar, who had
                    gone a second time to Carthage, by so stating the condition of their allies as
                    to inspire a hope that they might not only render them effectual aid, but also
                    that the Romans might in a manner be made prisoners in the city which they had
                    captured, induced the Carthaginians to send with him as many ships of burden as
                    possible, laden with every kind of provisions, and to augment the number of his
                    ships. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Setting sail, therefore, from Carthage
                    with a hundred and thirty men of war and seven hundred transports, he had
                    tolerably fair winds for crossing over to Sicily, but was prevented by the same
                    wind from doubling Cape Pachynum. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The news of
                    the approach of Bomilcar, <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and afterwards his
                    unexpected delay, excited alternate fear and joy in the Romans and Syracusans.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Epicydes, apprehensive lest if the same
                    wind which now detained him should continue to blow from the east for several
                    days, the Carthaginian fleet would return to Africa, put the Achradina in the
                    hands of the generals of the mercenary troops, and sailed to Bomilcar;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> whom he at length prevailed upon to try
                    the issue of a naval battle, though he <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> found
                    him with his fleet stationed in the direction of Africa, and afraid of fighting,
                    not so much because he was unequal in the strength or the number of his ships,
                    for he had more than the Romans, as because the wind was more favourable to the
                    Roman fleet than to his own. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcellus also
                    seeing that an army of Sicilians was assembling from every part of the island,
                    and that the Carthaginian fleet was approaching with a great want of supplies,
                    though inferior in the number of his ships, resolved to prevent Bomilcar from
                    coming to Syracuse, lest, blocked up in the city of his enemies, he should be
                    pressed both by sea and land. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The <pb n="997"
                        xml:id="p.997"/> two hostile fleets were stationed near the promontory of
                    Pachynum, ready to engage as soon as the sea should become calm enough to admit
                    of their sailing out into the deep. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, the east wind, which had blown violently for several days, now
                    subsiding, Bomilcar got under sail first, his van seeming to make for the main
                    sea, in order to double the promontory with greater ease; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> but seeing the Roman ships bearing down upon him, terrified
                    by some unexpected occurrence, it is not known what, he sailed away into the
                    main sea; and sending messengers to Heraclea, to order the transports to return
                    to Africa, he passed along the coast of Sicily and made for Tarentum. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Epicydes, thus suddenly disappointed in such great
                    expectations, to avoid returning to endeavour to raise the siege of a city, a
                    great part of which was already in the hands of the enemy, sailed to Agrigentum,
                    intending to wait the issue of the contest, rather than take any new measures
                    when there. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Intelligence of these events having been
                    carried into the camp of the Sicilians, that Epicydes had departed from
                    Syracuse, that the island was deserted by the Carthaginians, and almost again
                    delivered up to the Romans; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> after sounding the
                    inclinations of the besieged in conferences, they sent ambassadors to Marcellus,
                    to treat about terms of capitulation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They had
                    not much difficulty in coming to an agreement, that all the parts of the island
                    which had been under the dominion of their kings should be ceded to the Romans;
                    that the rest, with their liberty and their own laws, should be preserved to the
                    Sicilians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They then invited to a conference
                    the persons who had been intrusted with the management of affairs by Epicydes;
                    to whom they said, that they were sent from the army of the Sicilians, at once
                    to Marcellus and to them, that both those who were besieged and those who were
                    not might share the same fortune; and that neither of them might stipulate any
                    thing for themselves separately. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They were
                    then allowed to enter, in order to converse with their relations and friends;
                    when, laying before them the terms which they had made with Marcellus, and
                    holding out to them a hope of safety, they induced them to join with them in an
                    attack upon the praefects of Epicydes, Polyclitus, Philistion, and Epicydes,
                    surnamed Sindon. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having put them to death,
                    they summoned the multitude to an assembly; and after complaining <pb n="998"
                        xml:id="p.998"/> of the famine, at which they had been accustomed to express
                    their dissatisfaction to each other in secret, they said, that <quote> although
                        they were pressed by so many calamities, they had no right to accuse
                        Fortune, because it was at their own option how long they should continue to
                        suffer them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the motive which the
                        Romans had in besieging Syracuse was affection for the Syracusans, and not
                        hatred; for when they heard that the government was usurped by Hippocrates
                        and Epicydes, the creatures first of Hannibal and then of Hieronymus, they
                        took arms and began to besiege the city, in order to reduce not the city
                        itself, but its cruel tyrants. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But now
                        that Hippocrates is slain, Epicydes shut out of Syracuse, his praefects put
                        to death, and the Carthaginians driven from the entire possession of Sicily
                        by sea and land, what reason can the Romans have left why they should not
                        desire the preservation of Syracuse, in the same manner as they would if
                        Hiero were still living, who cultivated the friendship of Rome with
                        unequalled fidelity? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That, therefore,
                        neither the city nor its inhabitants were in any danger, except from
                        themselves, if they neglected an opportunity of restoring themselves to the
                        favour of the Romans; and that no so favourable a one would ever occur as
                        that which presented itself at the present instant, immediately upon its
                        appearing that they were delivered from their insolent tyrants. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This speech was received with the most
                    unqualified approbation of all present. It was resolved, however, that praetors
                    should be elected before the nomination of deputies; which being done, some of
                    the praetors themselves were sent as deputies to Marcellus, the chief of whom
                    thus addressed him: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Neither in the first instance did we Syracusans revolt from you, but
                        Hieronymus, whose impiety towards you was by no means so great as towards
                        us; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> nor afterwards was it any Syracusan
                        who disturbed the peace established by the death of the tyrant, but
                        Hippocrates and Epicydes, creatures of the tyrant; while we were
                        overpowered, on the one hand by fear, and on the other by treachery. Nor can
                        any one say that there ever was a time when we were in possession of our
                        liberty, when we were not also at peace with you. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In the present instance, manifestly, as soon as ever we
                        became our own masters, by the death of those persons who held Syracuse in
                            <pb n="999" xml:id="p.999"/> subjection, we lost no time in coming to
                        deliver up our arms, to surrender ourselves, our city, and our walls, and to
                        refuse no conditions which you shall impose upon us. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> To you, Marcellus, the gods have given the glory of
                        having captured the most renowned and beautiful of the Grecian cities. Every
                        memorable exploit which we have at any time achieved by land or sea accrues
                        to the splendour of your triumph. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Would
                        you wish that it should be known only by fame, how great a city has been
                        captured by you, rather than that she should stand as a monument even to
                        posterity; so that to every one who visits her by sea or land, she may point
                        out at one time our trophies gained from the Athenians and Carthaginians, at
                        another time those which you have gained from us; and that you should
                        transmit Syracuse unimpaired to your family, to be kept under the protection
                        and patronage of the race of the Marcelli? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Let not the memory of Hieronymus have greater weight with you than that of
                        Hiero. The latter was your friend for a much longer period than the former
                        was your enemy. From the latter you have realized even benefits, while the
                        frenzy of Hieronymus only brought ruin upon himself. </quote> At the hands
                    of the Romans all things were obtainable and secure. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> There was a greater disposition to war, and more danger to
                    be apprehended among themselves; for the deserters, thinking that they were
                    delivered up to the Romans, induced the mercenary auxiliaries to entertain the
                    same apprehension; and hastily seizing their arms, they first put the praetors
                    to death, and then ran through the city to massacre the Syracusans. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> In their rage they slew all whom chance threw in
                    their way, and plundered every thing which presented itself; and then, lest they
                    should have no leaders, they elected six praetors, so that three might have the
                    command in the Achradina, and three in the island. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> At length, the tumult having subsided, and the mercenary
                    troops having ascertained, by inquiry, what had been negotiated with the Romans,
                    it began to appear, as was really the case, that their cause and that of the
                    deserters were different. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassadors returned from Marcellus very
                    opportunely. They informed them that they had been influenced by groundless
                    suspicions, and that the Romans saw no reason why they should inflict punishment
                    upon them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of the three praefects of the
                    Achradina one was a Spaniard, named Me- <pb n="1000" xml:id="p.1000"/> ricus. To
                    him one of the Spanish auxiliaries was designedly sent, among those who
                    accompanied the ambassadors. Having obtained an interview with Mericus in the
                    absence of witnesses, he first explained to him the state in which he had left
                    Spain, from which he had lately returned: <quote> That there every thing was in
                        subjection to the Roman arms; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that it was
                        in his power, by doing the Romans a service, to become the first man among
                        his countrymen, whether he might be inclined to serve with the Romans, or to
                        return to his country. On the other hand, if he persisted in preferring to
                        hold out against the siege, what hope could he have, shut up as he was by
                        sea and land? </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Mericus was moved by these suggestions, and
                    when it was resolved upon to send ambassadors to Marcellus, he sent his brother
                    among them; who, being brought into the presence of Marcellus, apart from the
                    rest, by means of the same Spaniard, after receiving an assurance of protection,
                    arranged the method of carrying their object into effect, and then returned to
                    the Achradina. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Mericus then, in order to
                    prevent any one from conceiving a suspicion of treachery, declared, that he did
                    not like that deputies should be passing to and fro; he thought that they should
                    neither admit nor send any; and in order that the guards might be kept more
                    strictly, that such parts as were most exposed should be distributed among the
                    praefects, each being made responsible for the safety of his own quarter.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All approved of the distribution of the
                    posts. The district which fell to the lot of Mericus himself extended from the
                    fountain Arethusa to the mouth of the large harbour, of which he caused the
                    Romans to be informed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Accordingly, Marcellus
                    ordered a transport with armed men to be towed by a quadrireme to the Achradina
                    during the night, and the soldiers to be landed in the vicinity of that gate
                    which is near the fountain of Arethusa. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This
                    order having been executed at the fourth watch, and Mericus having received the
                    soldiers when landed at the gate, according to the agreement, Marcellus
                    assaulted the walls of the Achradina with all his forces at break of day, so
                    that he not only engaged the attention of those who <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> occupied the Achradina, but also bands of armed men,
                    quitting their own posts, ran to the spot from the island, in order to repel the
                    furious attack of the Romans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During this
                    confusion, some light ships which had been prepared beforehand, and had sailed
                        <pb n="1001" xml:id="p.1001"/> round, landed a body of armed men at the
                    island; these suddenly attacking the half-manned stations and the opened door of
                    the gate at which the troops had a little before run out, got possession of the
                    island without much opposition, abandoned as it was, in consequence of the
                    flight and trepidation of its guards. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Nor
                    were there any who rendered less service, or showed less firmness in maintaining
                    their posts, than the deserters; for as they did not repose much confidence even
                    in those of their own party, they fled in the middle of the contest. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> When Marcellus learnt that the island was taken, one
                    quarter of the Achradina in the hands of his troops, and that Mericus, with the
                    men under his command, had joined them, he sounded a retreat, lest the royal
                    treasure, the fame of which was greater than the reality, should be plundered. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The impetuosity of the soldiers having been
                    checked, time and opportunity to escape were given to the deserters in the
                    Achradina; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and the Syracusans, at length
                    delivered from their fears, threw open the gates of the Achradina, and sent
                    deputies to Marcellus, requesting only safety for themselves and children.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Having summoned a council, to which the
                    Syracusans were invited who were among the Roman troops, having been driven from
                    home during the disturbances, Marcellus replied, <quote> that the services
                        rendered by Hiero through a period of fifty years, were not more in number
                        than the injuries committed against the Roman people in these few years by
                        those who had had possession of Syracuse; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        but that most of these injuries had justly recoiled upon their authors, and
                        that they had inflicted much more severe punishment upon themselves for the
                        violation of treaties, than the Roman people desired. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> That he was indeed now besieging Syracuse for the third
                        year, but not that the Romans might hold that state in a condition of
                        slavery, but that the ringleaders of the deserters might not keep it in a
                        state of thraldom and oppression. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What the
                        Syracusans could do was exemplified, either by the conduct of those
                        Syracusans who were among the Roman troops, or that of the Spanish general,
                        Mericus, who had delivered up the post which he was appointed to command,
                        or, lastly, by the late but bold measure adopted by the Syracusans
                        themselves. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the greatest possible
                        recompence for all the evils and dangers which he had for so long a time
                        undergone, both by sea and land, around the walls <pb n="1002"
                            xml:id="p.1002"/> of Syracuse, was the reflection, that he had been able
                        to take that city. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The quaestor was then sent with a guard to the
                    island, to receive and protect the royal treasure. The city was given up to be
                    plundered by the soldiery, after guards had been placed at each of the houses of
                    those who had been with the Roman troops. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    While many acts exhibited horrid examples of rage and rapacity, it is recorded
                    that Archimedes, while intent on some figures which he had described in the
                    dust, although the confusion was as great as could possibly exist in a captured
                    city, in which soldiers were running up and down in search of plunder, was put
                    to death by a soldier, who did not know who he was; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> that Marcellus was grieved at this event, and that pains
                    were taken about his funeral, while his relations also, for whom diligent
                    inquiry was made, derived honour and protection from his name and memory.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such, for the most part, was the manner
                    in which Syracuse was captured. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The quantity
                    of booty was so great, that had Carthage itself, which was carrying on a contest
                    on equal terms, been captured, it would scarcely have afforded so much.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A few days before the taking of Syracuse,
                    Titus Otacilius passed over from Lilybaeum to Utica with eighty quinqueremes,
                    and entering the harbour before it was light, took some transports laden with
                    corn; then landing, he laid waste a considerable portion of the country around
                    Utica, and brought back to his ships booty of every description. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> He returned to Lilybaeum, the third day after he set
                    out, with a hundred and thirty transports laden with corn and booty. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> The corn he sent immediately to Syracuse; and had it
                    not been for the very seasonable arrival of this supply, a destructive famine
                    threatened alike the victors and the vanquished. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nothing very memorable had been done in Spain
                    for about two years, the operations of the war consisting more in laying plans
                    than in fighting; but during the same summer in which the events above recorded
                    took place, the Roman generals, quitting their winter quarters, united their
                    forces; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> then a council was summoned; and the
                    opinions of all accorded, that since their only object hitherto had been to
                    prevent Hasdrubal from pursuing his march into Italy, it was now time that an
                    effort should be made to bring the war in Spain to a termination; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> and they thought that the twenty thousand
                    Celtiberians, who had been induced to take arms <pb n="1003" xml:id="p.1003"/>
                    that winter, formed a sufficient accession to their strength. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> There were three armies of the enemy. Hasdrubal, son of
                    Gisgo, and Mago, who had united their forces, were about a five days' journey
                    from the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, son of Ha- milcar,
                    who was the old commander in Spain, was nearer to them: he was with his army
                    near the city Anitorgis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman generals
                    were desirous that he should be overpowered first; and they hoped that they had
                    enough and more than enough strength for the purpose. Their only source of
                    anxiety was, lest the other Hasdrubal and Mago, terrified at his discomfiture,
                    should protract the war by withdrawing into trackless forests and mountains.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thinking it, therefore, the wisest course
                    to divide their forces and embrace the whole Spanish war, they arranged it so
                    that Publius Cornelius should lead two-thirds of the Roman and allied troops
                    against Mago and Hasdrubal, and that Cneius <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    Cornelius, with the remaining third of the original army, and with the
                    Celtiberians added to them, should carry on the war with the Barcine Hasdrubal.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two generals and their armies, setting
                    out together, preceded by the Celtiberians, pitched their camp near the city
                    Anitorgis, within sight of the enemy, the river only separating them. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Here Cneius Scipio, with the forces above mentioned,
                    halted, but Publius Scipio proceeded to the portion of the war assigned to him. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal perceiving that there were but few
                    Roman troops in the camp, and that their whole dependence was on the Celtiberian
                    auxiliaries; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and having had experience of the
                    perfidy of the barbarian nations in general, and particularly of all those
                    nations among which he had served for so many years; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> as there was every facility of intercourse, for both camps
                    were full of Spaniards, by secret conferences with the chiefs of the
                    Celtiberians, he agreed with them, for a large consideration, to take their
                    forces away. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor did they conceive it to be
                    any great crime; for the object was not that they should turn their arms against
                    the Romans, while the reward which they were to receive to abstain from the war
                    was large enough to remunerate them for their service in it. At the same time
                    the mere rest from labour, the return to their homes, with the pleasure of
                    seeing their friends and property, were pleasing to the generality. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly, the multitude were prevailed upon as
                    easily as their leaders. They <pb n="1004" xml:id="p.1004"/> had, moreover,
                    nothing to fear from the Romans, in consequence of the smallness of their
                    numbers, should they endeavour to detain them by force. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> It will indeed be the duty of all Roman generals to take
                    care, and the instances here recorded should be considered as strong arguments,
                    never to place so much confidence in foreign auxiliaries, as not to retain in
                    their camps a preponderance of their own strength, and of that force which is
                    properly their own. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians, suddenly
                    taking up their standards, marched away, replying only to the Romans, who asked
                    the cause of their departure and entreated them to stay, that they were called
                    away by a war at home. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio seeing that his
                    allies could be detained neither by prayers nor force, and that he was neither a
                    match for his enemy without them, nor could again effect a junction with his
                    brother, no other course which promised safety offering itself, resolved to
                    retire <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> as far as possible, carefully using
                    every caution not to encounter the enemy any where on level ground. On his
                    departing, the enemy, crossing the river, pursued him almost in his footsteps. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same period an equal terror and a
                    greater danger pressed upon Publius Scipio. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa was a young man at that time an ally of the Carthaginians, whom
                    afterwards the friendship of the Romans rendered illustrious and powerful.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He not only opposed himself with his
                    Numidian cavalry to Scipio on his approach, but afterwards harassed him
                    incessantly day and night, so as both to cut off his stragglers, who had gone
                    out <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> to a distance from the camp in search of
                    wood and forage, and riding up to the very gates of his camp, and charging into
                    the midst of his advanced guards, to fill every quarter with the utmost
                    confusion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By night also alarm was frequently
                    occasioned in the gates and rampart by his sudden attacks. Nor was there any
                    time or place at which the Romans were exempt from fear and anxiety; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> and driven within their rampart, and deprived of
                    every necessary, they suffered in a manner a regular siege; and it appeared that
                    it would have been still straiter, if Indibilis, who it was reported was
                    approaching with seven thousand five hundred Suessetani, should form a junction
                    with the Carthaginians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Scipio, though a wary
                    and provident general, overpowered by difficulties, adopted the rash measure of
                    going to meet Indibilis by night, with the intention of fighting him wherever he
                        <pb n="1005" xml:id="p.1005"/> should meet him. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Leaving, therefore, a small force in his camp, under the
                    command of Titus Fonteius, lieutenant-general, he set out at midnight, and
                    meeting with the enemy, came to battle with him. The troops fought in the order
                    of march rather than of battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Romans,
                    however, had the advantage, though in an irregular fight; but the Numidian
                    cavalry, whose observation the general supposed that he had escaped, suddenly
                    spreading themselves round his flanks, occasioned great terror. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> After a new contest had been entered into with the
                    Numidians, a third enemy came up in addition to the rest, the Carthaginian
                    generals having come up with their rear when they were now engaged in fighting.
                    Thus the Romans were surrounded on every side by enemies; nor could they make up
                    their minds which they should attack first, or in what part, forming themselves
                    into a close body, they should force their way through. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The general, while fighting and encouraging his men,
                    exposing himself wherever the strife was the hottest, was run through the right
                    side with a lance; and when the party of the enemy, which, formed into a wedge,
                    had charged the troops collected round the general, perceived Scipio falling
                    lifeless from his horse, elated with joy, they ran shouting through the whole
                    line with the news that the Roman general had fallen. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> These words spreading in every direction, caused the enemy
                    to be considered as victors, and the Romans as vanquished. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> On the loss of the general the troops immediately began to
                    fly from the field; but though it was not difficult to force their way through
                    the Numidians and the other light-armed auxiliaries, yet it was scarcely
                    possible for them to escape so large a body of cavalry, and infantry equal to
                    horses in speed. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Almost more were slain in
                    the flight than in the battle; nor would a man have survived, had not night put
                    a stop to the carnage, the day by this time rapidly drawing to a close. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this, the Carthaginian generals, who
                    were not slow in following up their victory, immediately after the battle,
                    scarcely giving their soldiers necessary rest, hurry their army to Hasdrubal,
                    son of Hamilcar; confidently hoping, that after uniting their forces with his,
                    the war might be brought to a conclusion. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On
                    their arrival, the warmest congratulations passed between the troops and their
                    generals, who were delighted with their recent victory; for they had not only
                    de- <pb n="1006" xml:id="p.1006"/> stroyed one distinguished general and all his
                    men, but looked forward to another victory of equal magnitude as a matter of
                    certainty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The intelligence of this great
                    disaster had not yet reached the Romans; but there prevailed a kind of
                    melancholy silence and mute foreboding, such as is usually found in minds which
                    have a presentiment of impending calamity. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    general himself, besides feeling that he was deserted by his allies, and that
                    the forces of the enemy were so much augmented, was disposed from conjecture and
                    reasoning rather to a suspicion that some defeat had been sustained, than to any
                    favourable hopes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> For how could Hasdrubal and Mago bring up their troops without
                        opposition, unless they had terminated their part of the war? <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> How was it that his brother had not opposed his
                        progress or followed on his rear? in order that, if he could not prevent the
                        armies and generals of the enemy from forming a junction, he might himself
                        join his forces with his brother's. </quote> Disturbed with these cares, he
                    believed that the only safe policy for the present was to retire as far as
                    possible; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and, accordingly, he marched a
                    considerable distance thence in one night, the enemy not being aware of it, and
                    on that account continuing quiet. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At dawn,
                    perceiving that their enemy had decamped, they sent the Numidians in advance,
                    and began to pursue them as rapidly as possible. The Numidians overtook them
                    before night, and charged, sometimes their rear, at other times their flanks.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They then began to halt and defend
                    themselves as well as they could; but Scipio exhorted them at once to fight so
                    as not to expose themselves, and march at the same time, lest the infantry
                    should overtake them. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But having made but little progress for a long
                    time, in consequence of his making his troops sometimes advance and at others
                    halt, and night now <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> drawing on, Scipio
                    recalled his troops from the battle, and collecting them, withdrew to a certain
                    eminence, not very safe, indeed, particularly for dispirited troops, but higher
                    than any of the surrounding places. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There, at
                    first, his infantry, drawn up around his baggage and cavalry, which were placed
                    in their centre, had no difficulty in repelling the attacks of the charging
                    Numidians; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but afterwards, when three generals
                    with three regular armies marched up in one entire body, and it was evident that
                    his men would not be able to do much by arms in defending the <pb n="1007"
                        xml:id="p.1007"/> position without fortifications, the general began to look
                    about, and consider whether he could by any means throw a rampart around;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but the hill was so bare, and the soil so
                    rough, that neither could a bush be found for cutting a palisado, nor earth for
                    making a mound, nor the requisites for making a trench or any other work;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> nor was the place naturally steep or
                    abrupt enough to render the approach and ascent difficult to the enemy, as it
                    rose on every side with a gentle acclivity. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    However, that they might raise up against them some semblance of a rampart, they
                    placed around them the panniers tied to the burdens, building them up as it were
                    to the usual height, and when there was a deficiency of panniers for raising it,
                    they presented against the enemy a heap of baggage of every kind. The
                    Carthaginian armies coming up, very easily marched up the eminence, but were
                    stopped by the novel appearance of the fortification, as by something
                    miraculous, when their leaders called out from all sides, asking <quote> what
                        they stopped at? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and why they did not tear
                        down and demolish that mockery, which was scarcely strong enough to impede
                        the progress of women and children; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that
                        the enemy, who were skulking behind their baggage, were, in fact, captured
                        and in their hands. </quote> Such were the contemptuous reproofs of their
                    leaders. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But it was not an easy task either
                    to leap over or remove the burdens raised up against them, or to cut through the
                    panniers, closely packed together and covered completely with baggage.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When the removal of the burdens had
                    opened a way to the troops, who were detained by them for a long time, and the
                    same had been done in several quarters, the camp was now captured on all sides;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> the Romans were cut to pieces on all
                    hands, the few by the many, the dispirited by the victorious. A great number of
                    the men, however, having fled for refuge into the neighbouring woods, effected
                    their escape to the camp of Publius Scipio, which Titus Fonteius commanded.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Some authors relate that Cneius Scipio
                    was slain on the eminence on the first assault of the enemy; others that he
                    escaped with a few attendants to a castle near the camp; this, they say, was
                    surrounded with fire, by which means the doors which they could not force were
                    consumed; that it was thus taken, and all within, together with the general
                    himself, put to death. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Cneius Scipio was
                    slain in the eighth year after his arrival in Spain, and on the twenty-ninth day
                    after the death <pb n="1008" xml:id="p.1008"/> of his brother. At Rome the grief
                    occasioned by their death was not more intense than that which was felt
                    throughout Spain. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The sorrow of the citizens,
                    however, was partly distracted by the loss of the armies, the alienation of the
                    province, and the public disaster; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> while in
                    Spain they mourned and regretted the generals themselves; Cneius, however, the
                    more, because he had been longer in command of them, had first engaged their
                    affections, and first exhibited a specimen of Roman justice and forbearance. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When it seemed that the Roman armies were
                    annihilated, and Spain lost, one man recovered this desperate state of affairs.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was in the army one Lucius Marcius,
                    the son of Septimus, a Roman knight, an enterprising youth, and possessing a
                    mind and genius far superior to the condition in which he had been born.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To his high talents had been added the
                    discipline of Cneius Scipio, under which he had been thoroughly instructed
                    during a course of so many years in all the qualifications of a soldier.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This man, having collected the troops
                    which had been dispersed in the flight, and drafted some from the garrisons, had
                    formed an army not to be despised, and united it with Titus Fonteius, the
                    lieutenant-general of Publius Scipio. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But so
                    transcendent was the Roman knight in authority and honour among the troops, that
                    when, after fortifying a camp on this side of the Iberus, it had been resolved
                    that a general of the two armies should be elected in an <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> assembly of the soldiers, relieving each other in the guard
                    of the rampart, and in keeping the outposts until every one had given his vote,
                    they unanimously conferred the supreme command upon Lucius Marcius. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> All the intervening time, which was but short, was
                    occupied in fortifying their camp and collecting provisions; and the soldiers
                    executed every order not only with vigour, but with feelings by no means
                    depressed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But when intelligence was brought
                    them that Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, who was coming to put the finishing stroke to
                    the war, had crossed the Iberus and was drawing near, and when they saw the
                    signal for battle displayed by a new commander; <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> then calling to mind whom they had had for their leaders a little while ago,
                    relying on what leaders and what forces they used to go out to fight, they all
                    suddenly burst into tears and beat their heads; some raising their hands to
                    heaven and arraigning the gods; <pb n="1009" xml:id="p.1009"/> others
                    prostrating themselves upon the ground and invoking by name each his own former
                    commander. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor could their lamentations be
                    restrained, though the centurions endeavoured to animate their companies, and
                    though Marcius himself soothed and remonstrated with them, asking them <quote>
                        why they had given themselves up to womanish and unavailing lamentations
                        rather than summon up all their courage to protect themselves and the
                        commonwealth together, and not suffer their generals to lie unavenged?
                    </quote> But suddenly a shout and the sound of trumpets were heard; for by this
                    time the enemy were near the rampart. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Upon
                    this, their grief being suddenly converted into rage, they hastily ran to arms,
                    and, as it were, burning with fury, rushed to the gates and charged the enemy,
                    while advancing in a careless and disorderly manner. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> This unexpected event instantly struck terror into the
                    Carthaginians, who wondering whence so many enemies could have sprung up so
                    suddenly, as the army had been almost annihilated; what could have inspired men
                    who had been vanquished and routed with such boldness and confidence in
                    themselves; what general could have arisen now that the two Scipios were slain;
                    who could command the camp, and who had given the signal for battle; in
                    consequence of these so many and so unexpected circumstances, at first, being in
                    a state of complete uncertainty and amazement, they gave ground; <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> but afterwards, discomfited by the violence of the
                    charge, they turned their backs; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and either
                    there would have been a dreadful slaughter of the flying enemy, or a rash and
                    dangerous effort on the part of the pursuers, had not Marcius promptly given the
                    signal for retreat, and by throwing himself in the way of the front rank, and
                    even holding some back with his own hands, repressed the infuriated troops. He
                    then led them back to the camp, still eager for blood and slaughter. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> When the Carthaginians, who were at first compelled
                    to fly with precipitation from the rampart of their enemy, saw that no one
                    pursued them, concluding that they had stopped from fear, now on the other hand
                    went away to their camp at an easy pace, with feelings of contempt for the
                    enemy. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> There was a corresponding want of care
                    in guarding their camp; for though the enemy were near, yet it seemed that they
                    were but the remains of the two armies which had been cut to pieces a few days
                    before. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> As in consequence of this all things
                    were neglected <pb n="1010" xml:id="p.1010"/> in the enemy's camp, Marcius
                    having ascertained this, addressed his mind to a measure which on the first view
                    of it might appear rather rash than bold: <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> it
                    was, aggressively to assault the enemy's camp, concluding that the camp of
                    Hasdrubal, while alone, might be carried with less difficulty than his own could
                    be defended, if the three armies and as many generals should again unite;
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> taking into consideration also, that
                    either if he succeeded he would retrieve their prostrate fortune, or if
                    repulsed, still, by making the attack himself, he would rescue himself from
                    contempt. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lest, however, the suddenness of the affair,
                    and the fear of night, should frustrate a measure which was in itself ill
                    adapted to his condition, he thought it right that his soldiers should be
                    addressed and exhorted; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and having called an
                    assembly, he discoursed as follows: <quote> Soldiers, either my veneration for
                        our late commanders, both living and dead, or our present situation, may
                        impress on every one the belief that this command, as it is highly
                        honourable to me, conferred by your suffrages, so is it in its nature a
                        heavy and anxious charge. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For at a time
                        when I should be scarcely so far master of myself as to be able to find any
                        solace for my afflicted mind, did not fear deaden the sense of sorrow, I am
                        compelled to take upon myself alone the task of consulting for the good of
                        you all; a task of the greatest difficulty when under the influence of
                        grief. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And not even at that critical
                        moment, when I ought to be considering in what manner I may be enabled to
                        keep together for my country <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> these
                        remains of two armies, can I divert my mind from the affliction which
                        incessantly preys upon me. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For bitter
                        recollection is ever present, and the Scipios ever disturb me with anxious
                        cares by day and dreams by night, frequently rousing me from my sleep, and
                        imploring me not to suffer themselves nor their soldiers, your companions in
                        war, who had been victorious in this country for eight years, nor the
                        commonwealth to remain unrevenged; enjoining me also to follow their
                        discipline and their plans; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and desiring
                        that as there was no one more obedient to their commands while they were
                        alive than I, so after their death I would consider that conduct as best,
                        which I might have the strongest reason for believing they would have
                        adopted in each case. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I could wish also
                        that you, my soldiers, should not show your respect for them by lamenta- <pb
                            n="1011" xml:id="p.1011"/> tions and tears, as if they were dead; (for
                        they still live and flourish in the fame of their achievements;) <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> but that whenever the memory of those men shall
                        occur to you, you would go into battle as though you saw them encouraging
                        you and giving you the signal. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor
                        certainly could anything else than their image presenting itself yesterday
                        to your eyes and minds, have enabled you to fight that memorable battle, in
                        which you proved to the enemy that the Roman name had not become extinct
                        with the Scipios; and that the energy and valour of that people, which had
                        not been overwhelmed by the disaster at Cannae, would, doubtlessly, emerge
                        from the severest storms of fortune. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Now
                        since you have dared so much of your own accord, I have a mind to try how
                        much you will dare when authorized by your general: for yesterday, when I
                        gave the signal for retreat while you were pursuing the routed enemy with
                        precipitation, I did not wish to break your spirit, but to reserve it for
                        greater glory and more advantageous opportunities; <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> that you might afterwards, when prepared and armed,
                        seize an occasion of attacking your enemy while off their guard, unarmed,
                        and even buried in sleep. Nor do I entertain the hope of gaining an
                        opportunity of this kind rashly, but from the actual state of things.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Doubtless, if any one should ask even
                        himself, by what means, though few in number and disheartened by defeat, you
                        defended your camp against troops superior in number and victorious, you
                        would give no other answer than that, as this was the very thing you were
                        afraid of, you had kept every place secured by works and yourselves ready
                        and equipped. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And so it generally
                        happens: men are least secure against that which fortune causes not to be
                        feared; because you leave unguarded and exposed what you think is not
                        necessary to be cared about. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There is
                        nothing whatever which the enemy fear less at the present time, than lest
                        we, who were a little while ago besieged and assaulted, should aggressively
                        assault their camp ourselves. Let us dare, then, to do that which it is
                        incredible we should have the courage to attempt; it will be most easy from
                        the very fact of its appearing most difficult. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> At the third watch of the night I will lead you thither
                        in silence. I have ascertained by means of scouts that they have no regular
                        succession of watches, no proper outposts. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                        /> Our shout at their gates, when heard, and the first assault, will carry
                        their camp. Then let that car- <pb n="1012" xml:id="p.1012"/> nage be made
                        among men, torpid with sleep, terrified at the unexpected tumult, and
                        overpowered while lying defenceless in their beds, from which you were so
                        grieved to be recalled yesterday. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> I know
                        that the measure appears to you a daring one; but in difficult and almost
                        desperate circumstances the boldest counsels are always the safest. For if
                        when the critical moment has arrived, the opportunity of seizing which is of
                        a fleeting nature, you delay ever so little, in vain do you seek for it
                        afterwards when it has been neglected. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        One army is near us; two more are not far off. We have some hopes if we make
                        an attack now; and you have already made trial of your own and their
                        strength. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> If we postpone the time and
                        cease to be despised in consequence of the fame of yesterday's irruption,
                        there is danger lest all the generals and all the forces should unite. Shall
                        we be able then to withstand three generals and three armies, whom Cneius
                        Scipio with his army unimpaired could not withstand? <milestone n="21"
                            unit="section"/> As our generals have perished by dividing their forces,
                        so the enemy may be overpowered while separated and divided. There is no
                        other mode of maintaining the war; let us, therefore, wait for nothing but
                        the opportunity of the ensuing night. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Now
                        depart, with the favour of the gods, and refresh yourselves, that,
                        unfatigued and vigorous, you may burst into the enemy's camp with the same
                        spirit with which you have defended your own. </quote> This new enterprise,
                    proposed by their new general, they received with joy; and the more daring it
                    was the more it pleased them. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> The remainder
                    of the day was spent in getting their arms in readiness and recruiting their
                    strength, the greater part of the night was given to rest, and at the fourth
                    watch they were in motion. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At a distance of six miles beyond their
                    nearest camp lay other forces of the Carthaginians. A deep valley, thickly
                    planted with trees, intervened. Near about the middle of this wood a Roman
                    cohort and some cavalry were placed in concealment with Punic craft. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The communication between the two armies being thus
                    cut off, the rest of the forces were marched in silence to the nearest body of
                    the enemy; and as there were no outposts before the gates, and no guards on the
                    rampart, they entered quite into the camp, as though it had been their own, no
                    one any where opposing them. The signals were then sounded and a shout raised.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some put the <pb n="1013" xml:id="p.1013"
                    /> enemy to the sword when half asleep; others threw fire upon the huts, which
                    were covered in with dry straw; others blocked up the gates to intercept their
                    escape. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The enemy, who were assailed at once
                    with fire, shouting, and the sword, were in a manner bereaved of their senses,
                    and could neither hear each other, nor take any measures for their security.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Unarmed, they fell into the midst of
                    troops of armed men: some hastened to the gates; others, as the passes were
                    blocked up, leaped over the rampart, and as each escaped they <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> fled directly towards the other camp, where they were cut
                    off by the cohort and cavalry rushing forward from their concealment, and were
                    all slain to a man. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And even had any escaped
                    from that carnage, the Romans, after taking the nearer camp, ran over to the
                    other with such rapidity, that no one could have arrived before them with news
                    of the disaster. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In this camp, as they were
                    far distant from the enemy, and as some had gone off just before day-light for
                    forage, wood, and plunder, they found every thing in a still more neglected and
                    careless state. Their arms only were placed at the outposts, the men being
                    unarmed, and either sitting and reclining upon the ground, or else walking up
                    and down before the rampart and the gates. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On
                    these men, thus at their ease and unguarded, the Romans, still hot from the
                    recent battle, and flushed with victory, commenced an attack; no effectual
                    opposition therefore could be made to them in the gates. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Within the gates, the troops having rushed together from
                    every part of the camp at the first shout and alarm, a furious conflict arose;
                    which would have continued for a long time, had not the bloody appearance of the
                    Roman shields discovered to the Carthaginians the defeat of the other forces,
                    and consequently struck them with dismay. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    This alarm produced a general flight; and all except those who were overtaken
                    with the sword, rushing out precipitately wherever they could find a passage,
                    abandoned their camp. Thus, in a night and a day, two camps of the enemy were
                    carried, under the conduct of Lucius Marcius. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Claudius, who translated the annals of Acilius out of Greek into Latin, states
                    that as many as thirty-seven thousand men were slain, one thousand eight hundred
                    and thirty made prisoners, and a great booty obtained; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> among which was a silver shield of a hundred and
                    thirty-eight pounds' weight, with an image upon it of the Bar- <pb n="1014"
                        xml:id="p.1014"/> cine Hasdrubal. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Valerius Antias states, that the camp of Mago only was captured, and seven
                    thousand of the enemy slain; and that in the other battle, when the Romans
                    sallied out and fought with Hasdrubal, ten thousand were slain, and four
                    thousand three hundred captured. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Piso writes,
                    that five thousand were slain in an ambuscade when Mago incautiously pursued our
                    troops who retired. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> With all, the name of the
                    general, Marcius, is mentioned with great honour, and to his real glory they add
                    even miracles. They say, that while he was haranguing his men a stream of fire
                    poured from his head without his perceiving it, to the great terror of the
                    surrounding soldiers; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> and that a shield,
                    called the Marcian, with an image of Hasdrubal upon it, remained in the temple
                    up to the time of the burning of the Capitol, a monument of his victory over the
                    Carthaginians. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> After this, affairs continued
                    for a considerable time in a tranquil state in Spain, as both parties, after
                    giving and receiving such important defeats, hesitated to run the hazard of a
                    general battle. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these transactions in Spain, Marcellus,
                    after the capture of Syracuse, having settled the other affairs in Sicily with
                    so much honour and integrity as not only to add to his own renown, but also to
                    the majesty of the Roman people, conveyed to Rome the ornaments of the city,
                    together with the statues and pictures with which Syracuse abounded. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> These were certainly spoils taken from enemies, and
                    acquired according to the laws of war; but hence was the origin of the
                    admiration of the products of Grecian art, and to that freedom with which at
                    present all places, both sacred and profane, are despoiled; which at last
                    recoiled upon the Roman gods, and first upon that very temple which was so
                    choicely adorned by Marcellus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For foreigners
                    were in the habit of visiting the temples dedicated by Marcellus near the Capuan
                    gate, on account of their splendid ornaments of this description, of which a
                    very small portion can be found. Embassies from almost all the states of Sicily
                    came to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As their cases were different, so
                    were also the terms granted to them. Those who had either not revolted or had
                    returned to the alliance before the capture of Syracuse, were received and
                    honoured as faithful allies. Those who had been induced to submit through fear
                    after the capture of Syracuse, as vanquished, received laws from the conqueror.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans, however, had still <pb
                        n="1015" xml:id="p.1015"/> remaining a war of no small magnitude at
                    Agrigentum, headed by Epicydes and Hanno, generals in the late war, and a third
                    new one sent by Hannibal in the room of Hippocrates, a Libyphnician by nation,
                    and a native of Hippo, called by his countrymen Mutines; an energetic man, and
                    thoroughly instructed in all the arts of war under the tuition of Hannibal. To
                    this man the Numidian auxiliaries were assigned by Epicydes and Hanno.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With these he so thoroughly overran the
                    lands of his enemies, and visited his allies with such activity, in order to
                    retain them in their allegiance, and for the purpose of bringing them seasonable
                    aid as each required it, that in a short time he filled all Sicily with his
                    fame, nor <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> was greater confidence placed in
                    any one else by those who favoured the Carthaginian interest. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the Carthaginian and Syracusan generals, who
                    had been hitherto compelled to keep within the walls of Agrigentum, not more at
                    the advice of Mutines than from the confidence they reposed in him, had the
                    courage to go out from the walls, and pitched a camp near the river Himera.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When this was announced to Marcellus, he
                    immediately advanced and sat down at a distance of about four miles from the
                    enemy, with the intention of waiting to see what steps they took, and what they
                    meditated. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But Mutines allowed no room or
                    time for delay or deliberation, but crossed the river, and, charging the
                    outposts of his enemy, created the greatest terror and confusion. The next day,
                    in an engagement which might almost be called regular, he compelled his enemy to
                    retire within their works. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Being called away
                    by a mutiny of the Numidians, which had broken out in the camp, and in which
                    about three hundred of them had retired to Heraclea Minoa, he set out to appease
                    them and bring them back; and is said to have earnestly warned the generals not
                    to engage with the enemy during his absence. Both the generals were indignant at
                    this conduct, but particularly Hanno, who was before disturbed at his
                    reputation. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Is it to be borne,</quote> said he, <quote> that a mongrel African should
                        impose restraints upon me, a Carthaginian general, commissioned by the
                        senate and people? </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Epicydes, who wished to wait, was prevailed
                    upon by him to agree to their crossing the river and offering battle; for, said
                    he, if they should wait for Mutines, and the battle should terminate
                    successfully, Mutines would certainly have the credit of it. <pb n="1016"
                        xml:id="p.1016"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But Marcellus, highly indignant that he who
                    had repulsed Hannibal from Nola, when rendered confident by his victory at
                    Cannae, should succumb to enemies whom he had vanquished by sea and land,
                    ordered his soldiers immediately to take arms and raise the standards.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> While marshalling his army, ten Numidians
                    rode up rapidly from the enemy's line with information that their countrymen,
                    first induced by the same causes which brought on the mutiny, in which three
                    hundred of their number retired to Heraclea, and secondly, because <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> they saw their commander, just on the approach of a
                    battle, sent out of the way by generals who wished to detract from his glory,
                    would not take any part in the battle. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This
                    deceitful nation made good their promise in this instance. Accordingly the
                    spirits of the Romans were increased by the intelligence, which was speedily
                    conveyed through the lines, that the enemy were abandoned by the cavalry, which
                    the Romans principally feared; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> while at the
                    same time the enemy were dispirited, not only because they were deprived of the
                    principal part of their strength, but further, because they were afraid lest
                    they should themselves be attacked by their own cavalry. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, there was no great resistance made: the first
                    shout and onset determined the business. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    Numidians who stood quiet in the wings during the action, when they saw their
                    party turning their backs, accompanied them in their flight only for a short
                    time; but when they perceived that they were all making for Agrigentum with the
                    most violent haste, they turned off to the neighbouring towns round about,
                    through fear of a siege. Many thousand men were slain and captured, together
                    with eight elephants. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This was the last battle
                    which Marcellus fought in Sicily, after which he returned victorious to
                    Syracuse. The year was now about closing; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the
                    senate therefore decreed that Publius Cornelius, the praetor, should send a
                    letter to Capua to the consuls, with directions that while Hannibal was at a
                    distance, and nothing of any great importance was going on at Capua, one of
                    them, if <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> they thought fit, should come to
                    Rome to elect new magistrates. On the receipt of the letter, the consuls
                    arranged it between themselves, that Claudius should hold the election, and
                    Fulvius remain at Capua. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consuls created
                    by Claudius were Cneius Fulvius Centumalus, and Publius Sulpicius Galba, the son
                    of Servius, who had never exercised <pb n="1017" xml:id="p.1017"/> any curule
                    magistracy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After this Lucius Cornelius
                    Lentulus, Marcus Cornelius Cethegus, Caius Sulpicius, and Caius Calpurnius Piso,
                    were created praetors. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Piso had the city
                    jurisdiction; Sulpicius, Sicily; Cethegus, Apulia; Lentulus, Sardinia. The
                    consuls were continued in command for a year longer. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
