<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 25</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="book">
                <head>The Fall of Syracuse</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these operations in Spain and Africa
                        were going on, Hannibal spent the whole summer in the Sallentine territory
                        in the hope of securing the city of Tarentum by treachery, and whilst he was
                        there some unimportant towns seceded to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Out of the twelve communities in Bruttium who had gone over to the
                        Carthaginians the year before, two, namely Consentia and Thurii, returned to
                        their old allegiance to Rome, and more would have done so had it not been
                        for T. Pomponius Veientanus, an officer of allies. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He had made several successful raids in Bruttium and
                        had in consequence began to be regarded as a regularly commissioned general.
                        With the raw and undisciplined army which he had got together he engaged
                        Hanno. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In that battle a great number of
                        men, who were simply a confused crowd of peasants and slaves, were killed or
                        made prisoners; the least important loss was that of the officer himself,
                        who was made prisoner. For not only was he responsible for such a reckless
                        and ill-advised battle, but in his capacity as a public contractor he had
                        previously been guilty of all sorts of dishonest practices and robbed both
                        the State and the City guilds. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul
                        Sempronius fought several trifling actions in Lucania, none of which are
                        worth recording, and took some unimportant towns belonging to the Lucanians. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The longer the war continued, and the more
                        men's minds as well as their fortunes were affected by the alternations of
                        success and failure, so much the more did the citizens become the victims of
                        superstitions, and those for the most part foreign ones. It seemed as though
                        either the characters of men or the nature of the gods had undergone a
                        sudden change. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Roman ritual was
                        growing into disuse not only in secret and in private houses; even in public
                        places, in the Forum and the Capitol, crowds of women were to be seen who
                        were offering neither sacrifices nor prayers in accordance with ancient
                        usage. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Unauthorised sacrificers and
                        diviners had got possession of men's minds and the numbers of their dupes
                        were swelled by the crowds of country people whom poverty or fear had driven
                        into the City, and whose fields had lain untilled owing to the length of the
                        war or had been desolated by the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        These impostors found their profit in trading upon the ignorance of others,
                        and they practiced their calling with as much effrontery as if they had been
                        duly authorised by the State. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Respectable
                        citizens protested in private against the state of things, and ultimately
                        the matter became a public scandal and formal complaint was made to the
                        senate. The aediles and commissioners of police were severely reprimanded by
                        the senate for not preventing these abuses, but when they attempted to
                        remove the crowds from the Forum and destroy the altars and other
                        preparations for their rites they narrowly escaped being roughly handled.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As the mischief appeared to be too
                        much for the inferior magistrates to deal with, M. Aemilius, the City
                        praetor, was entrusted with the task of delivering the people from these
                        superstitions. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He read the resolution of
                        the senate before the Assembly and gave notice that all those who had in
                        their possession any manuals of divination or forms of prayers or
                        sacrificial ritual in writing were to bring all their books and writings to
                        him before the first of April, and no one was to use any strange or foreign
                        form of sacrifice in any public or consecrated place. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Several officials connected with the State
                        religion died this year: L. Cornelius Lentulus the chief pontiff, C.
                        Papirius, son of C. Masso, one of the pontiffs, P. Furius Philus the augur,
                        and C. Papirius, son of L. Maso, one of the Keepers of the Sacred Books.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> M. Cornelius Cethegus was appointed
                        chief pontiff in place of Lentulus, and Cn. Servilius Caepio in place of
                        Papirius. L. Quintius Flamininus was appointed augur and L. Cornelius
                        Lentulus Keeper of the Sacred Books. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        time for the consular elections was now drawing near, and as it was decided
                        not to recall the consuls who were engaged in the war, Tiberius Sempronius
                        nominated C. Claudius Cento Dictator for the purpose of conducting the
                        elections. He appointed Q. Fulvius Flaccus as his Master of the Horse.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The elections were completed on the
                        first day; the Dictator returned as duly elected consuls Q. Fulvius Flaccus,
                        Master of the Horse, and Appius Claudius Pulcher, who was at the time
                        praetor in Sicily. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then the praetors were
                        elected; Cn. Fulvius Flaccus, C. Claudius Nero, M. Junius Silanus, and P.
                        Cornelius Sulla. When the elections were over the Dictator resigned.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The curule aediles for the year were
                        M. Cornelius Cethegus and P. Cornelius Scipio, who was subsequently known as
                        Africanus. When the latter offered himself as a candidate, the tribunes of
                        the plebs objected to him, and said that he could not be allowed to stand
                        because he had not yet reached the legal age. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> His reply was: "If the Quirites are unanimous in their
                        desire to appoint me aedile, I am quite old enough." On this the people
                        hurried to give their tribal votes for him with such eagerness that the
                        tribunes abandoned their opposition. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        new aediles discharged their functions with great munificence; the Roman
                        Games were celebrated on a grand scale considering their resources at the
                        time; they were repeated a second day and a congius of oil was distributed
                        in each street. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> L. Villius Tappulus and M.
                        Fundanius Fundulus, the plebeian aediles, summoned several matrons before
                        the people on a charge of misconduct; some of them were convicted and sent
                        into exile. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The celebration of the
                        Plebeian Games lasted two days and there was a solemn banquet in the Capitol
                        on the occasion of the Games. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Q. Fulvius Flaccus and Appius Claudius
                        entered on their consulship, the former for the third time. The praetors
                        drew lots for their provinces; P. Cornelius Sulla had assigned to him both
                        the home and foreign jurisdiction, which had previously been held
                        separately; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Apulia fell to Cn. Fulvius
                        Flaccus; Suessula to C. Claudius Nero; Etruria to M. Junius Silanus.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Two legions were decreed for each of
                        the consuls in the operations against Hannibal; one consul took over the
                        army from Q. Fabius, the consul of the previous year, the other that of
                        Fulvius Centumalus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With regard to the
                        praetors, Fulvius Flaccus was to have the legions which were at Luceria
                        under Aemilius, Claudius Nero those which were serving in Picenum under C.
                        Terentius, and they were each to raise their force to its full complement.
                        The City legions raised the previous year were assigned to M. Junius to meet
                        any movement from Etruria. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Ti. Sempronius
                        Gracchus and P. Sempronius Tuditanus had their commands extended in their
                        respective provinces of Lucania and Cis-Alpine Gaul, as also had P. Lentulus
                        in the Roman province of Sicily and M. Marcellus in Syracuse and that part
                        of the island over which Hiero had reigned. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> The command of the fleet was left in the hands of T. Otacilius, the
                        operations in Greece in those of M. Valerius, the campaign in Sardinia was
                        still to be under the conduct of Q. Mucius Scaevola, whilst the two Scipios
                        were to continue their work in Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In
                        addition to the existing armies two fresh legions were raised in the City by
                        the consuls, thus bringing up the total number to twenty-three legions for
                        the year. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The enrolment was interrupted by the
                        conduct of M. Postumius Pyrgensis which might have endangered the stability
                        of the republic. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This man was a public
                        contractor and for many years had had only one man to match him in
                        dishonesty and greed, and that was T. Pomponius Veientanus, whom the
                        Carthaginians under Hanno got hold of while he was recklessly raiding
                        Lucania. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The State had made itself
                        responsible where supplies intended for the armies were lost through storms
                        at sea, and these men invented stories of shipwrecks, and when they did not
                        invent, the shipwrecks which they reported were due to their dishonesty, not
                        to accident. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They placed small and
                        worthless cargoes on old shattered ships, which they sank when out at sea,
                        the sailors being taken into boats which were kept in readiness, and then
                        they made a false declaration as to the cargo, putting it at many times its
                        real value. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This fraud had been disclosed
                        to M. Aemilius, the praetor, and he laid the matter before the senate, but
                        they had taken no action because they were anxious not to offend the body of
                        public contractors at such a time as that. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> The people, however, took a much severer view of the case, and at length
                        two tribunes of the plebs, Spurius Carvilius and L. Carvilius, seeing the
                        public indignation and disgust aroused, demanded that a fine of 200,000 ases
                        should be imposed on them. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When the day
                        came for the question to be decided, the plebs were present in such great
                        numbers that the space on the Capitol hardly held them, and after the case
                        had been gone through, the only hope left to the defence was the chance of
                        C. Servilius Casca, <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> a tribune of the
                        plebs and a near relative of Postumius, interposing his veto before the
                        tribes proceeded to vote. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> When the
                        evidence had been given, the tribunes ordered the people to withdraw and the
                        voting urn was brought in, in order that it might be determined in what
                        tribe the Latins were to vote. While this was being done the contractors
                        urged Casca to stop the proceedings for the day, and the people loudly
                        opposed that step. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Casca happened to be
                        sitting in front at the end of the tribunal seats, and he was labouring
                        under the conflicting emotions of fear and shame. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> Seeing that no dependence was to be placed upon him,
                        the contractors determined to create a disturbance and rushed in a compact
                        body into the space left vacant by the withdrawal of the Assembly, loudly
                        abusing both the people and the tribunes. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        As there was every prospect of a hand-to-hand fight the consul Fulvius said
                        to the tribunes: "Do you not see that your authority has gone, and that
                        there will certainly be a riot if you do not dismiss the meeting?" </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Assembly of the plebs was
                        dismissed a meeting of the senate was called, and the consuls brought
                        forward the question of "the disturbance of a <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> meeting of the plebs through the violence and audacity
                        of the public contractors." "M. Furius Camillus," they said, "whose exile
                        was followed by the downfall of Rome, submitted to condemnation at the hands
                        of the irate citizens; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> before his time the
                        decemvirs-whose laws are in force today-and after him many of our foremost
                        citizens have bowed to the sentence of the people. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Whereas Postumius Pyrgensis has deprived the people of
                        their right to vote, broken up a meeting of the plebs, destroyed the
                        authority of the tribunes, levied war upon the people of Rome, made forcible
                        seizure of a position in the City to cut off the plebs from its tribunes,
                        and prevented the tribes from being called to vote. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> There was nothing to restrain men from fighting and
                        bloodshed except the forbearance of the magistrates, who for the time being
                        yielded to the furious audacity of a few men and allowed themselves and the
                        Roman people to be successfully defied, and, <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> rather than give any occasion for a conflict to those
                        who were seeking one, they voluntarily closed the elections which the
                        accused was going to stop by armed force." <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        This indictment was listened to by all good citizens with feelings of
                        indignation proportioned to the atrocity of the outrage, and the senate
                        passed a decree affirming that "that violent conduct was an offence against
                        the republic and set a most vicious precedent." <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Immediately on this the two Carvilii dropped the
                        proposal for a fine and indicted Postumius for high treason, and ordered him
                        to find sureties for his appearance on the day of trial, or failing that to
                        be at once arrested and taken to prison. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        He found sureties, but did not appear. The resolution proposed by the
                        tribunes and adopted by the plebs was in the following terms: "If M.
                        Postumius does not enter an appearance before the first day of May and when
                        cited into court does not answer his name on that day, and has not been
                        lawfully excused from so appearing, he shall be deemed to be an exile, his
                        goods shall be sold, and he himself placed under outlawry." <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Then all those who had taken the lead in the
                        riotous disturbance were one by one indicted on the same charge and ordered
                        to find sureties. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Those who did not find
                        them and afterwards even those who could find them were alike cast into
                        prison. Most of them, to escape the danger, went into exile. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the issue of the dishonesty of
                        the State contractors, and their daring attempt to screen themselves.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The next thing was the election of the
                        chief pontiff. The new pontiff, M. Cornelius Cethegus, conducted the
                        election, which was very keenly contested. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        There were three candidates: Q. Fulvius Flaccus, the consul, who had
                        previously been twice consul as well as censor; T. Manlius Torquatus, who
                        could also point to two consulships and the censorship; and P. Licinius
                        Crassus, who was about to stand for the curale aedileship. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> This young man defeated his old and distinguished
                        competitors; before him there had been no one for a hundred and twenty
                        years, with the sole exception of P. Cornelius Calussa, who had been elected
                        chief pontiff without having first sat in a curule chair. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The consuls found the levying of troops a difficult
                        task, for there were not sufficient men of the required age to answer both
                        purposes, that of raising the new City legions and also bringing the
                        existing armies up to their full strength. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The senate, however, would not allow them to give up the attempt, and
                        ordered two commissions, each consisting of three members, to be appointed,
                        one to work within a radius of fifty miles from the City, the other outside
                        that radius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were to inspect all the
                        villages, market towns, and boroughs, and ascertain the total number of
                        free-born men in each, and were to make soldiers of all who appeared strong
                        enough to bear arms, even though they were below the military age.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the plebs might, if
                        they thought good, make a proposal to the people that those who had taken
                        the military oath when under seventeen years of age should have their pay
                        reckoned to them on the same scale as if they had been enlisted at
                        seventeen, or older. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The commissions so
                        appointed recruited all the free-born men in the country districts.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> About this time a despatch was read
                        in the senate from M. Marcellus in Sicily, in which he put forward the
                        request made to him by the soldiers who were serving with P. Lentulus.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These were the remains of the army of
                        Cannae, they had been sent away to Sicily, as has been stated above, and
                        were not to be brought back to Italy before the Punic war had come to an
                        end. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The principal officers of the cavalry,
                        with the centurions of highest rank and the pick of the legionaries, had
                        been allowed by Lentulus to send a deputation to M. Marcellus in Italy.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One was allowed to speak on behalf of
                        the rest, and this is what he said: "We should have approached you,
                        Marcellus, when you were consul, in Italy, as soon as that severe if not
                        unjust resolution of the senate was passed concerning us, had we not hoped
                        that after being sent into a province thrown into confusion by the death of
                        its kings, to take part in a serious war against <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> Sicilians and Carthaginians combined, we should have
                        made reparation to the senate by our blood and our wounds in the same way
                        that those who were taken by Pyrrhus at Heraclea, <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> within the memory of our fathers, made reparation by
                        fighting against Pyrrhus afterwards. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And
                        yet, what have we done, senators, that you should be wrath with us then or
                        that we should deserve your anger now? I seem to myself to be gazing on the
                        faces of both the consuls and of the whole senate when I look at you,
                        Marcellus; if we had had you as our consul at Cannae, both we and the
                        republic would have met with better fortune. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "Allow me, I pray you, before I complain
                        of our treatment, to clear ourselves of the guilt which is laid to our
                        charge. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If it was not through the anger of
                        the gods or through the ordering of that destiny by whose laws the chain of
                        human affairs is immutably linked together, but by the fault of man that we
                        perished at Cannae, whose fault, pray, was it? The fault of the soldiers or
                        of their commanders? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As a soldier I will
                        never say a word about my commander, though I know that he was specially
                        thanked by the senate because he did not despair of the republic, and has
                        had his command extended every year since his flight from Cannae. Those of
                        the survivors from that disaster, who were our military tribunes at the
                        time, solicited and obtained office, as we have heard, and are in command of
                        provinces. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Do you lightly forgive
                        yourselves and your children, senators, whilst you reserve your anger for
                        poor wretches like us? While it was no disgrace for the consul and the
                        foremost men in the State to flee when all hope was lost, did you send us,
                        the common soldiers, to meet certain death in the battle field? <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> At the Alia almost the entire army fled, at the
                        Caudine Forks they delivered up their arms to the enemy without even
                        attempting to fight, not to mention other shameful defeats that our armies
                        have suffered. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But so far were those
                        armies from having any humiliation inflicted upon them, that the City of
                        Rome was recovered by the very army which had fled from <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> the Alia to Veii, and the Caudine legions who had
                        returned to Rome without their arms were sent back armed to Samniun, and
                        made that same enemy pass under the yoke who had enjoyed seeing them undergo
                        that humiliation. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Can any man charge the
                        army at Cannae with flight or cowardice when more than 50,000 men fell
                        there, when the consul fled with only seventy horsemen, when not one
                        survives who fought there except those whom the enemy, wearied with
                        slaughter, left alone. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When the ransom of
                        the prisoners was vetoed we were universally praised because we had saved
                        ourselves for our country, because we returned to the consul at Venusia and
                        presented the appearance of a regular army. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                        /> But as it is, we are in a worse case than those prisoners in our fathers'
                        days; for all that they had to endure was a change in their arms, in their
                        military status, in their quarters in camp, and these they recovered by the
                        one service they rendered to the State in fighting a successful battle. Not
                        one of them was sent into exile, not one was deprived of the prospect of
                        obtaining his discharge, and above all they had the chance of putting an end
                        either to their life or their disgrace by fighting the enemy. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> But we, against whom no charge can be brought
                        except that it is through our fault that a single Roman soldier is
                            <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> left alive after the battle of
                        Cannae-we, I say, have not only been sent far away from our native soil and
                        from Italy, but we have been placed out of reach of the enemy, we are to
                        grow old in exile, <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> with no hope, no
                        chance, of wiping out our shame, or of appeasing our fellow-citizens, or
                        even of dying an honourable death. We are not asking for an end to our
                        ignominy or for the rewards of valour, we only ask to be allowed to prove
                        our mettle and to show our courage. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> We
                        ask for labours and dangers, for a chance of doing our duty as men and as
                        soldiers. This is the second year of the war in Sicily with all its
                        hard-fought battles. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians
                        are capturing some cities, the Romans are taking others, infantry and
                        cavalry meet in the shock of battle, at Syracuse a great struggle is going
                        on <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/> by land and sea, we hear the shouts
                        of the combatants and the clash of their arms, and we are sitting idly by,
                        as though we had neither weapons nor hands to use them. The legions of
                        slaves have fought many pitched battles under Tiberius Sempronius; they have
                        as their reward freedom and citizenship, we implore you to treat us at least
                        as slaves who have been purchased for this war, and to allow us to meet and
                        fight the enemy and so win our freedom. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                        Are you willing to make proof of our courage by sea or by land, in the open
                        field or against city walls? <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> We ask for
                        whatever brings the hardest toil and the greatest danger, if only what ought
                        to have been done at Cannae may be done as soon as we can do it, now. For
                        all our life since has been but one long agony of shame." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had finished speaking they
                        prostrated themselves at the knees of Marcellus. He told them that he had
                        not the authority or the power to grant their request, but said that he
                        would write to the senate and would be guided entirely by their decision.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The despatch was delivered into the
                        hands of the new consuls and read by them to the senate. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> After discussing its contents, the senate decided that
                        they saw no reason why the safety of the republic should be entrusted to
                        soldiers who had deserted their comrades at Cannae. If M. Claudius, the
                        propraetor, thought otherwise, he was to act as he thought best <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> in the interests of the State, but only on this
                        condition, that none of them should get their discharge or receive any
                        reward for valour or be conveyed back to Italy as long as the enemy remained
                        on Italian soil. After this an election was held by the City praetor, in
                        accordance with a decision of the senate and a resolution of the plebs, for
                        the appointment of special commissioners of works. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Five commissioners were chosen to undertake the repair
                        of the walls and towers of the City, and two boards, each consisting of
                        three members, were selected; one to inspect the contents of the temples and
                        to make an inventory of the offerings; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the
                        other to rebuild the temples of Fortune and Mater Matuta inside the Porta
                        Carmentalis and the temple of Spes outside, all of which had been destroyed
                        by fire the previous year. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Frightful
                        storms occurred: on the Alban Mount it rained stones incessantly for two
                        days. Many places were struck by lightning, two buildings in the Capitol,
                        the rampart of the camp above Suessula in many places, two sentinels being
                        killed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The wall and some of the towers at
                        Cumae were not only struck, but even thrown down by the lightning. At Reate
                        a huge rock was seen to fly about, and the sun was unusually red, in fact
                        the colour of blood. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By reason of these
                        portents a day was set apart for special intercessions, and for several days
                        the consuls devoted their attention to religious matters, and special
                        services were held for nine days. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        betrayal of Tarentum had long been an object of hope with Hannibal and of
                        suspicion with the Romans, and now an incident which occurred outside its
                        walls hastened its capture. Phileas had been a long time in Rome, ostensibly
                        as the Tarentine envoy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He was a restless
                        character and chafed under the inaction in which he seemed likely to spend
                        the greater part of his life. The hostages from Tarentum and Thurii were
                        kept in the Hall of Liberty, but not under strict surveillance, because it
                        was neither for their own interest nor for that of their city to play the
                        Romans false. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Phileas found means of
                        access to them and had frequent interviews, in which he won them over to his
                        design, and by bribing two of the watchmen he brought them <milestone
                            n="13??" unit="section"/> out of confinement as soon as it was dark, and
                        they made their secret escape from Rome. As soon as it was light their
                        flight became known throughout the City, and a party was sent in pursuit.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> They were caught at Tarracina and
                        brought back; then they were marched into the Comitium and, with the
                        approval of the people, scourged with rods and thrown from the Rock. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The cruelty of this punishment produced a
                        feeling of bitter resentment in the two most important Greek cities in
                        Italy, not only amongst the population <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                        at large, but especially amongst those who were connected by ties of
                        relationship or friendship with the men who had met with such a horrible
                        fate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Amongst these there were thirteen
                        young nobles of Tarentum who entered into a conspiracy; the ringleaders were
                        Nico and Philemenus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before taking any
                        action they thought that they ought to have an interview with Hannibal. They
                        left the city by night on the presence that they were going on a hunting
                        expedition and took the direction of his camp. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> When they were not far from it, the others concealed
                        themselves in a wood near the road while Nico and Philemenus went on to the
                        outposts. They were seized, as they intended to be, and were conducted to
                        Hannibal. After explaining to him the motives which had prompted them and
                        the nature of the step they were contemplating they were warmly thanked and
                        loaded with promises, and Hannibal advised them to drive to the city some
                        cattle belonging to the Carthaginians which had been turned out to pasture,
                        so that they might make their fellow-townsmen believe that they had really
                        gone out, as they said, to get plunder. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        promised that they should be safe and unmolested while so engaged.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Every one saw the plunder which the
                        young men had brought, and as they did the same thing over and over again
                        people wondered less at their daring. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At
                        their next interview with Hannibal they obtained from him a solemn promise
                        that the Tarentines should preserve their freedom and retain their own laws
                        and all that belonged to them, they were to pay no taxes or tribute to
                        Carthage, nor be required to admit a Carthaginian garrison against their
                        will. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Roman garrison was to be at the
                        mercy of the Carthaginians. When this understanding had been arrived at,
                        Philemenus made a regular habit of leaving the city and returning to it by
                        night. He was noted for his passion for hunting and he had his dogs and
                        other requisites for the sport with him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Generally he brought back something which had purposely been placed in his
                        way and gave it either to the commanders or the men on guard. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> They imagined that he chose night time for his
                        expeditions through fear of the enemy. When they had become so accustomed to
                        his movements that the gate was opened at whatever hour of the night he gave
                        the signal by whistling, Hannibal thought the time had come for action.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He was three days' march distant, and
                        in order to lessen any surprise that might be felt at his remaining encamped
                        on one and the same spot so long he feigned illness. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans who were garrisoning Tarentum had ceased to
                        view his remaining there with suspicion. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had made up his mind to march to
                        Tarentum, he picked out a force of 10,000 infantry and cavalry, who, from
                        their agility and the lightness of their armour, would be most suitable for
                        a dash upon the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the fourth watch
                        of the night he made his advance and sent forward about eighty Numidian
                        troopers with orders to patrol the roads in the neighbourhood and keep a
                        sharp look out so that none of the rustics might espy his movements from a
                        distance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Those in front of them they were
                        to bring back, any whom they met they were to kill in order that the
                        inhabitants of the district might take them for a marauding force rather
                        than an army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marching his men rapidly
                        forward he encamped about fifteen miles from Tarentum, and without saving a
                        word as to where they were going he called his men together and warned them
                        all to keep in the line of march and not to allow any one to fall out or
                        leave the ranks. They were above all things to listen to orders with
                        attention and not to do anything that they were not told to do. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He would tell them, when the time came, what he
                        wanted them to do. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Almost at the same hour
                        a rumour reached Tarentum that a small body of Numidian horse were ravaging
                        their fields and creating a panic far and wide amongst the peasantry. This
                        news did not disturb the Roman commandant farther than that he ordered a
                        portion of his cavalry to ride out the next morning early to drive off the
                        enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As to guarding against any other
                        contingency, so little care was shown that this movement on the part of the
                        Numidians was actually taken as a proof that Hannibal and his army had not
                        stirred from their camp. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hannibal resumed his advance soon after
                        dark; Philemenus leading the way with the usual load of game on his
                        shoulders, the rest of the conspirators waiting inside the town to carry out
                        their part in the plot. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The arrangement
                        was that Philemenus should carry his prey through the wicket gate which he
                        always used and at the same time admit some armed men; Hannibal was to
                        approach the Temenide gate from another direction. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> This gate was on the landward part of the city and
                        looked eastwards near the public cemetery inside the walls. As he approached
                        the gate Hannibal gave the signal by showing a light, the signal was
                        answered in the same way by Nico; then both lights were extinguished.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hannibal marched up to the gate in
                        silence; Nico made a sudden attack upon the sentinels who were sleeping
                        soundly in their beds and killed them, then he opened the gate. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Hannibal entered with his infantry, but the
                        cavalry were ordered to remain outside, ready to meet any attack in the open
                        plain. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In the other direction Philemenus
                        also reached the wicket gate which he had been in the habit of using, and
                        whilst he was calling out that they could hardly stand the weight of the
                        huge beast they were carrying, his voice and well-known signal roused the
                        sentry and the gate was opened. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Two young
                        men carrying a wild boar entered, Philemenus and a lightly equipped huntsman
                        followed close after, and whilst the sentinel, astonished at its size,
                        turned unsuspectingly towards those who were carrying it, Philemenus ran him
                        through with a hunting spear. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then about
                        thirty armed men ran in and massacred the rest of the sentinels and broke
                        open the large gate adjoining and the army at once entered in fighting order
                        and marched in perfect silence to the forum where they joined Hannibal.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian general formed 2000
                        of his Gauls into three divisions, furnishing each with Tarentines to guide
                        them, and sent them into different parts of the city with orders to occupy
                        the main streets, and if a tumult arose they were to cut down the Romans and
                        spare the townsfolk. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> To secure this
                        latter object he gave instructions to the conspirators to tell any of their
                        people whom they saw at a distance to keep quiet and silent and fear
                        nothing. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time there was as much shouting
                        and uproar as usually happens when a city is taken, but nobody knew for
                        certain what had happened. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Tarentines
                        thought that the Roman garrison had started to pillage the town; the Romans
                        were under the impression that the townsfolk had got up a disturbance with
                        some treacherous design. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The commandant,
                        awakened by the tumult, hurried away to the harbour, and getting into a boat
                        was rowed round to the citadel. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To add to
                        the confusion the sound of a trumpet was heard from the theatre. It was a
                        Roman trumpet which the conspirators had procured for the purpose, and being
                        blown by a Greek who did not know how to use it, no one could make out who
                        gave the signal or for whom it was intended. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> When it began to grow light, the Romans recognised the arms of the
                        Carthaginians and Gauls, and all doubt was removed; the Greeks, too, seeing
                        the bodies of the Romans lying about everywhere, became aware that the city
                        had been taken by Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the light
                        grew clearer and the Romans who survived the massacre had taken refuge in
                        the citadel, the tumult having somewhat subsided, Hannibal ordered the
                        Tarentines to assemble without their arms. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        After they had all assembled, with the exception of those who had
                        accompanied the Romans into the citadel to share their fate whatever it
                        might be, Hannibal addressed some kind words to them, and reminded them of
                        the way he had treated their compatriots whom he had taken in the battle of
                        Cannae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He went on to inveigh bitterly
                        against the tyranny of Roman domination, and ended by ordering them each to
                        return to their homes and write their names over their doors; <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> if any houses were not so inscribed he should at
                        once give the signal for them to be plundered, and if any one placed an
                        inscription on a house occupied by a Roman-they were in a separate
                        quarter-he should treat him as an enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The people were dismissed, and after the inscriptions had been placed on the
                        doors, so that the houses could be distinguished from those of the enemy,
                        the signal was given and the troops dispersed in all directions to plunder
                        the Roman houses. There was a considerable amount of plunder seized. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day he advanced to attack the
                        citadel. It was protected by lofty cliffs on the side of the sea which
                        surrounded the greater part of it like a peninsula, and on the side of the
                        city it was enclosed by a wall and a very deep moat; Hannibal saw at once
                        that it could successfully defy any attack either by storm or by siege
                        works. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As he did not wish to be delayed
                        from undertaking more important operations by having to protect the
                        Tarentines nor to leave them without adequate defence against any attacks
                        which the Romans might make at their pleasure from the citadel, he decided
                        to cut off communication between the city and the citadel by earthworks.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He rather hoped, too, that the Romans
                        might attempt to interfere whilst these were being constructed and give him
                        a chance of fighting, and in case they made a sortie in force he might
                        inflict such heavy loss upon them and so weaken them that the Tarentines
                        could easily hold their own against them unaided. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> No sooner was the work commenced than the Romans
                        suddenly flung open the citadel gates and attacked the working party. The
                        detachment who were on guard along the front allowed themselves to be driven
                        in, and the Romans, emboldened by success, followed them up in greater
                        numbers and to a greater distance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then a
                        signal was given and the Carthaginians whom Hannibal had drawn up in
                        readiness rushed upon them from all sides. The Romans could not withstand
                        their attack, but their flight was checked by the narrow space and the
                        obstructions caused by the work which had been begun and the preparations
                        made for continuing it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A great many flung
                        themselves headlong into the fosse, and more were killed in the flight than
                        in the fighting. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After this the work
                        proceeded without molestation. An enormous fosse was dug and on its inner
                        side a breastwork and parapet thrown up, and a little further off in the
                        same direction he made preparations for adding a wall, so that the town
                        could protect itself against the Romans without his aid. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He left, however, a small detachment to garrison the
                        place and also help to complete the wall, while he himself with the rest of
                        his force fixed his camp by the river Galaesus about five miles from
                        Tarentum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Returning from this position to
                        inspect the work, and finding it much more advanced than he expected, he
                        became hopeful of successfully attacking the citadel. It was not, like other
                        similar places, protected by its lofty position, as it stood on level ground
                        and was separated from the city by a moat and a wall. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> While the attack was being pressed with siege works,
                        machines, and artillery of every kind, reinforcements arrived from
                        Metapontum, and thus strengthened, the Romans were encouraged to make a
                        night attack upon the enemies' works. Some they broke up, others they burnt,
                        and that was the end of Hannibal's attempts to storm the walls. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> His only hope now was to invest the citadel, but
                        that seemed useless, for standing as it did on a promontory and overlooking
                        the mouth of the harbour, those who held it could make free use of the sea.
                        The city, on the other hand, was cut off from all sea-borne supplies, and
                        the besiegers were more likely to starve than the besieged. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hannibal called the principal men of the
                        place together and explained all the difficulties of the situation. He told
                        them that he saw no way of carrying a citadel so strongly fortified by
                        storm, and there was nothing to hope for from a blockade as long as the
                        enemy were masters of the sea. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If he had
                        ships, so that all supplies could be stopped from reaching them, they would
                        then have to evacuate the citadel or surrender. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The Tarentines quite agreed with him, but they thought
                        that the man who gave the advice ought to help in carrying it out.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> If he sent for Carthaginian vessels
                        from Sicily the thing could be done, but their own ships were locked up in a
                        narrow bay; so how could they escape into the open sea as long as the enemy
                        held the mouth of the harbour? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> "They
                        shall escape," Hannibal replied. "Many things which nature makes difficult
                        become easy to the man who uses his brains. You have a city situated in a
                        flat country; broad and level roads lead in all directions. <milestone
                            n="17" unit="section"/> I will transport your ships without much trouble
                        on wagons and along the road which leads from the harbour through the heart
                        of the city to the sea. Then the sea which the enemy are now masters of will
                        be ours, we shall invest the citadel by sea on the one side, by land on the
                        other, or rather I would say we shall very soon capture it, either after the
                        enemy have evacuated it or with the enemy inside as well." <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> These words excited not only hopes of success but also
                        an intense feeling of admiration for the general. Wagons were speedily
                        collected from all sides and fastened together; machines were employed for
                        hauling the ships ashore, and the surface of the road was made good so that
                        the wagons could be drawn more easily and the transport effected with less
                        difficulty. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Then draught animals and men
                        were got together, and the work promptly began. After a few days a
                        completely equipped fleet sailed round the citadel and cast anchor off the
                        very mouth of the harbour. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Such was the
                        condition of affairs which Hannibal left behind him at Tarentum when he
                        returned to his winter quarters. Authorities, however, are divided on the
                        question whether the defection of Tarentum occurred this year or last, but
                        the majority, including those who lived nearest to the time of the events,
                        assert that it happened this year. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls and praetors were detained in
                        Rome by the Latin Festival until the 27th of April. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> That day the sacred rites were completed on the Alban
                        Mount, and they all set out for their various provinces. Subsequently the
                        need of fresh religious observances was brought to their notice in
                        consequence of the prophetic utterances of Marcius. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> This Marcius was a famous seer and his prophecies had
                        come to light the previous year when by order of the senate an inspection
                        was made of all books of a similar character. They first came into the hands
                        of M. Aemilius who, as City praetor, was in charge of the business, and he
                        at once handed them to the new praetor, Sulla. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> One of the two referred to events which had already
                        happened before it saw the light, and the authority thus acquired by its
                        fulfilment gained more credence for the other, which had yet to be
                        fulfilled. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the first the disaster of
                        Cannae was foretold in words to this effect: </p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">Thou who art sprung from Trojan blood, beware</l>
                        <l part="N"> The stream by Canna. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Let not
                            aliens born </l>
                        <l part="N">Force thee to battle on the fatal plain</l>
                        <l part="N">Of Diomed. But thou wilt give no heed</l>
                        <l part="N">To this my rede until that all the plain</l>
                        <l part="N">Be watered by thy blood, and mighty hosts</l>
                        <l part="N">The stream shall bear into the boundless deep</l>
                        <l part="N">From off the fruitful earth, and they who till</l>
                        <l part="N">Its soil shall be for food to birds and beasts</l>
                        <l part="N"> And fishes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such is Great
                            Jove's word to me. </l>
                    </quote>
                    <p> Those who had fought there recognised the truth of the description-the
                        plains of Argive Diomed and the river Canna and the very picture of the
                        disaster. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the second prophecy was
                        read. It was not only more obscure than the first because the future is more
                        uncertain than the past, but it was also more unintelligible owing to its
                        phraseology. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It ran as follows: </p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">If, Romans, ye would drive the foemen forth</l>
                        <l part="N">Who come from far to mar your land, then see</l>
                        <l part="N">That Games be held as each fourth year comes round</l>
                        <l part="N">In honour of Apollo and your State</l>
                        <l part="N">Shall bear its part and all your folk shall share</l>
                        <l part="N">The holy work, each for himself and his.</l>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        <l part="N">Your praetor, who shall justice do for each</l>
                        <l part="N">And all, shall have the charge. Then let there be</l>
                        <l part="N">Ten chosen who shall offer sacrifice</l>
                        <l part="N">In Grecian fashion. This if ye will do</l>
                        <l part="N">Then shall ye evermore rejoice and all</l>
                        <l part="N">Your State shall prosper; yea, the god shall bring</l>
                        <l part="N">Your foes to nought, who now eat up your land.</l>
                    </quote>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They spent one day interpreting this
                        prophecy. The day following, the senate passed a resolution that the Ten
                        should inspect the sacred books with reference to the institution of Games
                        to Apollo and the proper form of sacrifice. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> After they had made their investigations and reported to the senate, a
                        resolution was passed "that Games be vowed and celebrated in honour of
                        Apollo, and that when they were finished, 12,000 ases were to be given to
                        the praetor for the expenses of the sacrifice and two victims of large
                        size." <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A second resolution was passed
                        that "the Ten should sacrifice according to Greek ritual the following
                        victims: to Apollo, an ox with gilded horns and two white she-goats with
                        gilded horns, and to Latona a heifer with gilded horns." <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> When the praetor was about to celebrate the Games in
                        the Circus Maximus he gave notice that during the Games the people should
                        contribute a gift to Apollo, according to each man's convenience. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Such is the origin of the Apollinarian Games,
                        which were instituted for the cause of victory and not, as is generally
                        thought, in the interests of the public health. The people wore garlands
                        whilst witnessing them, the matrons offered up intercessions; feasting went
                        on in the forecourts of the houses with open doors, and the day was observed
                        with every kind of ceremonious rite. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal was still in the neighbourhood of
                        Tarentum and both the consuls were in Samnium apparently making preparations
                        for besieging Capua. Famine, generally the result of a long siege, was
                        already beginning to press upon the Campanians, as they had been prevented
                        by the Roman armies from sowing their crops. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> They sent a message to Hannibal asking him to give orders for corn to be
                        conveyed to Capua from places in the neighbourhood before the consuls sent
                        their legions into their fields and all the roads were rendered impassable
                        by the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal ordered Hanno who
                        was in Bruttium to march his army into Campania and see to it that the
                        people of Capua were plentifully supplied with corn. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Hanno accordingly marched into Campania and, carefully
                        avoiding the consuls who were both encamped in Samnium, he selected a
                        position for his camp on some rising ground about three miles from
                        Beneventum. He then issued orders for the corn which had been stored in the
                        friendly cities round to be carried to his camp, and assigned detachments to
                        guard the convoys. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A message was
                        despatched to Capua stating the day on which they were to appear in the camp
                        to receive the corn, bringing with them all the vehicles and beasts they
                        could collect. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Campanians carried out
                        his instructions with the same slackness and carelessness that they showed
                        in everything else. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hardly more than four
                        hundred country carts were sent and a few draught cattle. Hanno scolded them
                        severely, telling them that even the hunger which rouses the energies of
                        dumb animals failed to stimulate them to exertion. He then fixed another day
                        for them to come for corn provided with much more efficient means of
                        transport. </p>
                    <p> Everything was reported to the people of Beneventum exactly as it happened.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They at once sent a deputation of ten
                        of their principal citizens to the consuls, both of whom were near Bovianum.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On hearing what was going on at Capua
                        they arranged that one of them should march into Campania. Fulvius, to whom
                        that province had been assigned, made a night march and entered Beneventum.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He was now in Hanno's immediate
                        neighbourhood and was informed that he had left with a portion of his army
                        on a foraging expedition, that corn was supplied to Capua under the
                        superintendence of the head of his commissariat, that two thousand wagons
                        with a disorderly and unarmed crowd had arrived at his camp, that haste and
                        confusion prevailed everywhere, and that the rustics had invaded the camp
                        from all the country round and destroyed all semblance of military order and
                        all chance of military discipline. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When
                        he had satisfied himself that this information was correct, he issued an
                        order for his men to get ready their standards and arms against
                        nightfall-and nothing else-as they would have to attack the Carthaginian
                        camp. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Leaving their kits and all their
                        baggage in Beneventum, they started at the fourth watch and reached the camp
                        just before dawn. Their appearance created such alarm that, had the camp
                        been on level ground, it could undoubtedly have been carried at the first
                        assault. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Its elevated position and its
                        entrenchments saved it; in no direction could it be approached except by
                        steep and difficult climbing. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When day
                        broke a hot fight commenced; the Carthaginians did not confine themselves to
                        defending their lines; but being on more even ground themselves they threw
                        down the enemy who were struggling up the heights. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Courage and resolution, however, overcame
                        all difficulties, and in some places the Romans had forced their way to the
                        breastwork and fosse, but with heavy loss in killed and wounded, when the
                        consul, calling round him the superior officers, told them that they must
                        desist from the hazardous attempt. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                        thought it would be wiser to march back to Beneventum for that day, and on
                        the next day to bring their camp close up to the enemy's camp, so that the
                        Campanians could not quit it and Hanno would be unable to return to it.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To make more certain of this, he
                        prepared to send for his colleague and his army and direct their joint
                        operations against Hanno and the Campanians. The "retire" was already being
                        sounded when the general's plans were shattered by the angry shouts of the
                        soldiers who spurned such feeble tactics. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The Paelignian cohort happened to be in closest touch with the enemy, and
                        their commanding officer, Vibius Accaus, snatched <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> up a standard and flung it across the enemies' rampart,
                        at the same time invoking a curse on himself and his cohort if the enemy got
                        possession of the standard. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He was the
                        first to dash over fosse and rampart into the camp. Now the Paelignians were
                        fighting inside the lines, and Valerius Flaccus, the commanding officer of
                        the third legion, was rating the Romans for their cowardice in letting the
                        allies have the glory of capturing the camp, when T. Pedanius, a centurion
                        in command of the leading maniples' took a standard out of the bearer's
                        hands and shouted, "This standard <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> and
                        this centurion will be inside the rampart in a moment, let those follow who
                        will prevent its capture by the enemy." <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        His own maniples followed him as he sprang across the fosse, then the whole
                        of the legion pressed hard after. By this time even the consul, when he saw
                        them climbing over the rampart, changed his mind, and instead of recalling
                        the troops began to urge them on by pointing to the dangerous position of
                        their gallant allies and their own fellow citizens. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Every man did his best to push on; over smooth and
                        rough ground alike, amidst missiles showered upon them from all directions,
                        against the desperate resistance of the enemy who thrust their persons and
                        their weapons in the way, they advanced step by step and broke into the
                        camp. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Many who were wounded, even those
                        who were faint from loss of blood, struggled on that they might fall within
                        the enemies' camp. In this way the camp was taken, and taken too as quickly
                        as though it lay on level ground, entirely unfortified. It was no longer a
                        fight but a massacre, for they were all crowded together inside the lines.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Over l0,000 of the enemy were killed
                        and over 7000 made prisoners, including the Campanians who had come for
                        corn, and all the wagons and draught animals were captured. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> There was also an immense quantity of plunder
                        which Hanno, who had been raiding everywhere, had carried off from the
                        fields of the allies of Rome. After totally destroying the enemies' camp
                        they returned to Beneventum. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There the
                        two consuls-Appius Claudius had arrived a few days before-sold and
                        distributed the spoil. Those to whose exertions the capture of the camp was
                        due were rewarded, especially Accaus the Paelignian and T. Pedanius the
                        centurion who headed the first legion. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Hanno was at Cominium-Ocritum with a small foraging party when he heard of
                        the disaster to his camp, and he retreated to Bruttium in a way which
                        suggested flight rather than an orderly march. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Campanians, in their turn, heard
                        of the disaster which had overtaken them and their allies, they sent to
                        Hannibal to inform him that the two consuls were at Beneventum, a day's
                        march from Capua, and that the war had all but reached their walls and
                        gates. If he did not come with all speed to their help Capua would fall into
                        the hands of the enemy more rapidly than Arpi had done. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Not even Tarentum, much less its citadel, ought to be
                        of so much importance in his eyes as to make him give up to Rome, abandoned
                        and defenceless, the Capua which he always used to say was as great as
                        Carthage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal promised that he would
                        take care of Capua, and sent a force of 2000 cavalry by whose aid they would
                        be able to keep their fields from being devastated. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans, meanwhile, amongst their other cares, had
                        not lost sight of the citadel of Tarentum and its beleaguered garrison. P.
                        Cornelius, one of the praetors, had, acting on the instructions of the
                        senate, sent his lieutenant, C. Servilius, to purchase corn in Etruria, and
                        after loading some ships sailed to Tarentum and made his way through the
                        enemies' guard ships into the harbour. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His
                        arrival produced such a change that the very men who, having lost almost all
                        hope, had been frequently invited by the enemy in their colloquies with them
                        to go over to them, now actually invited and tried to persuade the enemy to
                        come over to them. Soldiers, too, had been sent from Metapontum, so the
                        garrison was now strong enough for the defence of the citadel. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The Metapontines, on the other hand, relieved
                        from their fears by the departure of the Romans, promptly went over to
                        Hannibal. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The people of Thurii, on the
                        same part of the coast, took the same step. Their action was due in some
                        measure to the defection of Tarentum and Metapontum, but it was due quite as
                        much to their feeling of exasperation against the Romans at the recent
                        massacre of their hostages. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was the
                        relations and friends of these who sent messengers with despatches to
                        Hannibal and Mago, who were in the neighbourhood, promising to put the city
                        in their power if they would march up to the walls. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> M. Atinius was in command at Thurii with a small
                        garrison, and they thought that he would easily be drawn into a precipitate
                        engagement, not because he trusted to his own small garrison, but because he
                        relied upon the soldiery of Thurii, whom he had carefully drilled and armed
                        against such an emergency. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the Carthaginian generals had
                        entered the country of Thurii they divided their forces: Hanno proceeded
                        with the infantry in battle order up to the city; Mago and his cavalry
                        halted and took up a position behind some hills admirably adapted for
                        concealing his movements. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Atinius
                        understood from his scouts that the hostile force consisted entirely of
                        infantry, accordingly he went into battle quite unaware of the treachery of
                        the citizens or the maneuver of the enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> The contest was a very spiritless one, only a few Romans were in the
                        fighting line, and the Thurians were awaiting the issue rather than helping
                        to decide it. The Carthaginian line purposely fell back in order to draw
                        their unsuspecting enemy behind the hill where the cavalry were waiting. No
                        sooner had they reached the place than the cavalry dashed forward with their
                        battle cry. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Thurians, an
                        ill-disciplined crowd, disloyal to the side on which they fought, were at
                        once put to flight; the Romans kept up the fight for some time in spite of
                        their being attacked on one side by the infantry and on the other by the
                        cavalry, but at last they, too, turned and fled to the city. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> There a body of the traitors admitted the stream
                        of their fellow townsmen through the open gate, but when they saw the Romans
                        routed and <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> running towards the city
                        they shouted that the Carthaginians were at their heels and the enemy would
                        enter the city pell mell with the Romans unless they instantly closed the
                        gates. The Romans accordingly were shut out for slaughter by the enemy,
                        Atinius and a few others being alone allowed to enter. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> A heated discussion thereupon arose amongst the
                        townsmen; some were for maintaining their loyalty to Rome, others thought
                        they ought to yield to fate and surrender the city to the victors.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> As usual, evil counsels and the
                        desire to be on the winning side carried the day. Atinius and his men were
                        conducted down to the sea and placed on board ship, not because they were
                        Romans, but because, after Atinius' mild and impartial administration, they
                        wished to provide for his safety. Then the Carthaginians were admitted into
                        the city. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The consuls left Beneventum and
                        marched their legions into the territory of Capua, partly to destroy the
                        crops of corn which were now in the blade, and partly with the view of
                        making an attack upon the city. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> They
                        thought that they would make their consulship illustrious by the destruction
                        of so wealthy and prosperous a city and at the same time they would wipe out
                        a great stain from the republic which had allowed the defection of so close
                        a neighbour to go for three years unpunished. They could not, however, leave
                        Beneventum unguarded. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> If, as they felt
                        certain would be the case, Hannibal came to Capua to help his friends, it
                        would be necessary, in view of the sudden emergency, to provide against the
                        attacks of his cavalry. They sent orders, therefore, to Tiberius Gracchus,
                        who was in Lucania, to come to Beneventum with his cavalry and light
                        infantry, and to leave some one in command of the legions in the standing
                        camp who were protecting Lucania. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before he left Lucania a most ill-omened
                        portent happened to Gracchus whilst he was offering sacrifice. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The sacrifice itself was just finished when two
                        snakes glided unobserved up to the reserved parts of the victim and devoured
                        the liver; as soon as they were seen they suddenly disappeared. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> On the advice of the augurs a fresh sacrifice was
                        offered and the parts reserved with greater care, but according to the
                        tradition the same thing happened a second and even a third time; <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> the snakes glided up and after tasting the liver
                        slipped away untouched. The augurs warned the commander that the portent
                        concerned him and they bade him be on his guard against secret foes and
                        secret plots. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But no foresight could avert
                        the impending doom. There was a Lucanian named Flavus, the head of that
                        section of the Lucanians who stood by Rome-one section had gone over to
                        Hannibal-and they elected him praetor. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        had already been a year in office when suddenly he changed his mind and
                        began to look out for an opportunity of ingratiating himself with the
                        Carthaginians. He did not think it enough to go over himself and draw the
                        Lucanians with him into revolt, unless he could make his league with the
                        enemy sure by the life-blood of the very man who was his guest-friend, and
                        betray the Roman commander. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He had a
                        secret interview with Mago, who was commanding in Bruttium, and obtained his
                        solemn pledge that if he would betray the Roman commander to the
                        Carthaginians the Lucanians should be taken into friendship and allowed to
                        live as a free people under their own laws. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> He then took Mago to the spot where he said he would bring Gracchus with
                        a small escort. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Mago was to bring foot and
                        horse fully armed to the place and place a large force in concealment. After
                        the spot had been thoroughly examined and an investigation made of every
                        part, a day was fixed for carrying out the project. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Flavus went to the Roman commander and told him that he
                        had an important enterprise on hand and required Gracchus' help for its
                        accomplishment. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He had persuaded the
                        chief magistrates of all the communities which in the general disturbance of
                        Italy had seceded to the Carthaginians to return to friendship with Rome,
                        since the cause of Rome which had been all but ruined at Cannae was every
                        day becoming stronger and more popular, whilst the strength of Hannibal was
                        waning and had almost reached the vanishing point. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans, he knew, would not be implacable to those
                        who had formerly offended, there had never been a nation more ready to
                        listen to prayers and more quick to grant forgiveness. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> How often had they pardoned even their own ancestors
                        after their repeated renewal of hostilities! This was the language he had
                        addressed to them. "But," he went on, "they would rather hear all this from
                        Gracchus himself in person, and touch his right hand, and carry away with
                        them that pledge of good faith." <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He
                        explained that he had mentioned a place to those whom he had taken into
                        confidence not far from the Roman camp, and only a few words would be needed
                        so to arrange matters there that the entire Lucanian nation would become
                        faithful allies of Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Gracchus, impressed by the apparent
                        sincerity of the man's language and the proposal he made, and carried away
                        by his smooth and plausible address, started from camp with his lictors and
                        a troop of cavalry under the guidance of his guest-friend. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> He rode straight into the snare; suddenly enemies
                        showed themselves on all sides, and to take away all doubt as to his being
                        betrayed Flavus joined them. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Missiles
                        were hurled from every quarter upon Gracchus and his cavalry. <milestone
                            n="18" unit="section"/> He sprung from his horse, and ordered the rest
                        to do the same, and called upon them to make the one thing which Fortune had
                        left them glorious by their courage. "For what is left," he cried, "to a
                        little band surrounded by an enormous host in a valley shut in by forest and
                        mountain, except death? <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The one question
                        is, are you going to offer yourselves like cattle to be butchered without
                        striking a blow, or are you going to turn all your thoughts from passively
                        awaiting the end and make a fierce and furious onslaught, doing and daring,
                        until you fall, covered with your enemies blood, amidst the heaped-up bodies
                        and arms of your dying foes? <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Make, every
                        one of you, for the Lucanian traitor and renegade! The man who sends him
                        beforehand as a victim to the gods below will find in his own death a
                        glorious honour and unspeakable consolation." <milestone n="21"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst saying this he wound his paludamentum round his
                        left arm-for they had not even brought their shields with them-and charged
                        the enemy. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> There was more fighting than
                        might have been expected from the number of the combatants. The Romans were
                        most exposed to the darts, and as they were hurled from the higher ground
                        all round they were pierced by them. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                        Gracchus was now left without any defence and the Carthaginians tried to
                        take him alive, but catching sight of his Lucanian guest-friend amongst the
                        enemy, he made such a furious onslaught on their serried ranks that it
                        became impossible to save his life without incurring heavy loss. <milestone
                            n="24" unit="section"/> Mago sent his dead body to Hannibal and ordered
                        it and the captured fasces to be placed before the general's tribunal.
                            <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> If this is the true story, Gracchus
                        perished in Lucania at the place called the "Old Fields." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There are some who point to a place in the
                        neighbourhood of Beneventum, near the river Calor, as the scene of his
                        death. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had left the camp with his
                        lictors and three attendants to bathe in the river, whilst the enemy were
                        concealed in osier beds on the bank, and whilst naked and defenceless was
                        killed, after vainly endeavouring to drive off the enemy by stones from the
                        bed of the river. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Others say that, acting
                        on the advice of the augurs, he had gone about half a mile from the camp for
                        the purpose of averting the above-mentioned portents in a place free from
                        defilement, when he was surrounded by two squadrons of Numidians who
                        happened to have taken up their position there. So little agreement is there
                        as to the place and circumstances of the death of this brilliant and famous
                        man. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And there are different versions of
                        the account of his funeral. Some say that his men buried him in his own
                        camp; others say that he was buried by Hannibal, and this is the more
                        generally accepted account. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> According to
                        this version, a funeral pyre was erected on the open space in front of the
                        camp and the whole army fully accoutred went through various evolutions with
                        Spanish dances and the movements of limbs and weapons peculiar to each
                        tribe, Hannibal doing honour to the dead in every way by his acts and words.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This is the account given by those who
                        say that his death took place in Lucania. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        If you choose to believe those who place it at the river Calor, it would
                        appear that the enemy only got possession of the head; this was sent to
                        Hannibal, and he at once despatched Carthalo to carry it to Cn. Cornelius,
                        the quaestor, who carried out the obsequies in the Roman camp, the people of
                        Beneventum taking their part in the ceremony as well as the soldiers. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls had invaded the territory of
                        Capua and were devastating it far and wide when great alarm and confusion
                        were caused by a sudden sortie of the townsmen supported by Mago and his
                        troopers. They hurriedly recalled to the standards the men who were
                        scattered in all directions, but they had hardly time to form their line
                        before they were routed and lost more than 1500 men. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The self-confidence and arrogance of the people of
                        Capua were immensely strengthened by this success and they were continually
                        challenging the Romans to fight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But that
                        one engagement brought about by want of caution and foresight put the
                        consuls much more on their guard. An incident occurred, however, which put
                        heart into the Romans and lessened the confidence of the other side, an
                        insignificant one it is true, but in war nothing is so insignificant as not
                        sometimes to involve serious consequences. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        T. Quinctius Crispinus had a friend in Capua called Badius, and their
                        friendship was a very close and intimate one. The intimacy had been formed
                        before the defection of Capua when Badius was lying ill in Rome at
                        Crispinus' house and received the kindest and most careful attention from
                        his host. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> One day this Badius walked up to
                        the sentinels on duty before the camp gate and asked them to call Crispinus.
                        Crispinus, on receiving the message, imagined that he had not forgotten the
                        old ties of friendship even though public treaties were torn up, and that he
                        wanted a friendly and familiar talk, and accordingly he went on a short
                        distance from his comrades. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as
                        they came in sight of one another Badius called out: "I, Badius, challenge
                        you, Crispinus, to battle. Let us mount our horses and, when the others have
                        withdrawn, decide who of us is the better fighter." <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Crispinus replied that neither he nor his challenger
                        lacked enemies upon whom they could display their courage, but as for
                        himself, even if he met Badius on the field of battle, he would avoid him
                        sooner than pollute his right hand with a friend's blood. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Then he turned round and was in the act of departing
                        when Badius became more insolent and began to taunt him with effeminacy and
                        cowardice and hurled at him abusive epithets which he himself more properly
                        deserved. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He said that he was an enemy
                        masquerading as a friend and pretending to spare a man for whom he knew he
                        was no match. If he were under the impression that when the bonds which held
                        states together were broken the bonds of private friendship were not broken
                        at the same time, then he, Badius of Capua, openly renounced in the hearing
                        of both armies the friendship of T. Quinctius Crispinus the Roman.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "There is," he went on, "no
                        fellowship, no bond of alliance between foe and foe, between me and the man
                        who <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> has come to attack my home, my
                        country, and my country's gods. If you are a man, meet me!" <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> For a long time Crispinus hesitated, but the men
                        of his troop at last prevailed upon him not to let the Campanian insult him
                        with impunity, and so, only waiting till he could ask his commanders if they
                        would allow him, against regulations, to fight an enemy who challenged him,
                        he mounted his horse with their permission and called upon Badius by name to
                        come out and fight. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Campanian showed
                        no hesitation; they spurred their horses against each other and met.
                        Crispinus with his lance wounded Badius in his left shoulder above his
                        shield. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He fell from his horse and
                        Crispinus leaped down from the saddle to despatch him as he lay. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Badius, before he was overpowered, escaped to
                        his comrades, leaving shield and horse behind. Crispinus, proudly displaying
                        his spoils, the horse and shield which he had taken, was conducted amid the
                        cheers and congratulations of the soldiers to the consuls. Here he was
                        addressed in terms of high praise and loaded with gifts. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal left the neighbourhood of
                        Beneventum and encamped close to Capua. Three days afterwards he led out his
                        force to battle, feeling quite certain that as <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> the Campanians had fought a successful action a short
                        time before in his absence, the Romans would be far less able to withstand
                        him and the army which had been so often victorious. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as the battle commenced the Roman line was in
                        difficulties, chiefly owing to the attack of cavalry, as they were almost
                        overwhelmed by their darts. The signal was given for the Roman cavalry to
                        charge the enemy at full gallop, and now it had become simply a cavalry
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> engagement when the sight of
                        Sempronius' army in the distance commanded by Cn. Cornelius created equal
                        alarm on both sides, as each feared that a fresh enemy was coming on.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The signal to retire was given in both
                        armies as if by mutual consent, and the combatants separated on almost equal
                        terms and returned to camp. The loss on the Roman side was, however,
                        somewhat the greater owing to the cavalry attack at the beginning.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In order to draw Hannibal away from
                        Capua the consuls left in the night after the battle for different
                        destinations; Fulvius went into the neighbourhood of Cumae and Claudius into
                        Lucania. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On being informed the next day
                        that the Roman camp was evacuated, and that they had gone in two divisions
                        by different routes, Hannibal was at first undecided which he should follow;
                        he decided to follow Appius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After leading
                        his enemy about just as he pleased, Appius returned by a circuitous route to
                        Capua. </p>
                    <p> Another chance of achieving success in this country presented itself to
                        Hannibal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There was a certain M.
                        Centenius, surnamed Paenula, who was conspicuous among the centurions of the
                        first rank for his physical stature and his courage. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> After completing his period of service he was
                        introduced by P. Cornelius Sulla, the praetor, to the senate. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> He requested the senators to allow him 5000 men;
                        he was well acquainted with the enemy and the country where he was operating
                        and would very soon do something worth the doing; the tactics by which our
                        generals and their armies had been outwitted up to that time he would employ
                        against the man who invented them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Stupid
                        as the promise was it was quite as stupidly given credence to, as though the
                        qualifications of a soldier were the same as those of a general. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Instead of 5000 he was given 8000 men, half of
                        them Romans and half troops furnished by the allies. He himself, too, picked
                        up a considerable number of volunteers in the country through which he was
                        marching, and he arrived in Lucania with double the army he started with.
                        Here Hannibal had come to a halt after his fruitless pursuit of Claudius.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The result could not be doubtful,
                        seeing it was a contest between armies one of which consisted of veterans
                        habituated to victory, the other a hastily raised and half-armed force.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> As soon as they caught sight of each
                        other, neither side declined battle and they at once got into fighting
                        order. For more than two hours, however, in spite of the utterly unequal
                        conditions, the Roman army kept up the fighting as long as their leader
                        stood his ground. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> At last, out of regard
                        for his former reputation and also fearing the disgrace he would incur if he
                        survived a defeat brought on by his own headlong folly, he rushed upon the
                        weapons of the foe and fell, and the Roman army was instantly routed.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But even when they fled they found no
                        way of escape, for all avenues were closed by the cavalry, so that out of
                        that multitude of men only a thousand escaped, all the rest perished in one
                        way or another. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls now resumed the siege of Capua
                        in earnest, and everything necessary for the task was brought together and
                        got into readiness. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Corn was stored at
                        Casilinum; at the mouth of the Vulturnus, where the town of Vulturnum now
                        stands, a fort was constructed and a garrison was placed in it and in
                        Puteoli also, which Fabius had previously fortified, so that they might
                        command both the river and the adjacent sea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> The corn which had lately been sent from Sardinia as well as that which
                        M. Junius had purchased in Etruria was conveyed from Ostia into these two
                        maritime fortresses, that the army might have a supply throughout the
                        winter. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Meantime the disaster which had
                        overtaken Centenius in Lucania was aggravated by another which resulted from
                        the death of Gracchus. The volunteer slaves who had done excellent service
                        when he was alive to lead them, looked upon his death as discharging them
                        from further military duties and accordingly disbanded themselves.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal was anxious not to neglect
                        Capua or desert friends who were in such a critical position, but after his
                        easy victory through the foolhardiness of one Roman general he was watching
                        for an opportunity of crushing another. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Envoys from Apulia had informed him that Cn. Fulvius, who was attacking some
                        of their cities which had seceded to him, had at first conducted his
                        operations with care and prudence, but afterwards, intoxicated with success
                        and loaded with plunder, he and his men had given themselves up to such
                        idleness and self-indulgence that all military discipline had disappeared.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hannibal knew by repeated experience,
                        and especially within the last few days, what state an army gets into under
                        an incompetent commander and he at once moved into Apulia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fulvius and his legions were in the
                        neighbourhood of Heraclea. When they heard that the enemy were approaching
                        they were almost on the point of dragging up the standards and going into
                        battle without waiting for orders. In fact the one thing that restrained
                        them more than anything else was the confidence they felt of being able to
                        choose their own time for fighting. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        following night, when Hannibal became aware that the camp was in a state of
                        tumult and that most of the men were defying their commander and insisting
                        that he should give the signal, and that there was a general cry, "To arms!"
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> he was quite certain that the
                        opportunity was presented of a successful battle. He quietly disposed some
                        three thousand of his light infantry in the surrounding homesteads and in
                        the woods and copses. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were all to
                        spring from their concealment at the same moment when the signal was given,
                        and Mago had orders to place about two thousand cavalry along all the roads
                        which he thought the direction of the flight might take. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After making these dispositions during the night, he
                        marched out to battle at dawn. Fulvius did not hesitate, though he was not
                        drawn on so much by any hopes of success on his own part as by the blind
                        impetuosity of his men. The same recklessness which sent them on to the
                        field appeared in the formation of their line. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They went forward in a haphazard way and took their
                        places in the ranks just where they chose, and left them again as their
                        caprices or fears dictated. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The first
                        legion and the left wing of the allies were drawn up in front and the line
                        was extended far beyond its proper length. The officers called out that it
                        possessed neither strength nor depth and wherever the enemy made their
                        attack they would break through, but the men would not even listen to, much
                        less attend to anything that was for their good. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> And now Hannibal was upon them; a general so different
                        from their own, with an army so different and in such different order!
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As might be expected, the Romans were
                        unable to withstand the very first attack; their general, quite as foolish
                        and reckless as Centenius, though not to be compared with him in courage, no
                        sooner saw the day going against him and his men in confusion than he seized
                        a horse and made his escape with about two hundred of his cavalry.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The rest of the army, repulsed in
                        front and then surrounded in rear and flanks, was so completely cut up that
                        out of 12,000 men not more than 2000 escaped. The camp was taken. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The news of these disasters, one after
                        another, created very great grief and alarm amongst the citizens in Rome,
                        still, as they knew that the consuls were so far successful where success
                        was most important, they were not so much disturbed by the tidings as they
                        might have been. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate despatched C.
                        Laetorius and M. Metilius with instructions to the consuls, telling them to
                        carefully get together the remains of the two armies and to see to it that
                        the survivors were not driven by fear and despair to surrender to the enemy,
                        as had happened after the disaster at Cannae. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They were also to find out who had deserted amongst the
                        volunteer slaves. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Publius Cornelius also
                        was charged with this latter task, as he was with the raising of fresh
                        troops, and he caused notices to be published through the market-towns and
                        boroughs, ordering that search should be made for the volunteer slaves, and
                        that they should be brought back to their standards. These instructions were
                        all most carefully carried out. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Appius
                        Claudius placed D. Junius in command at the mouth of the Vulturnus, and M.
                        Aurelius Cotta at Puteoli; whenever the vessels arrived from Etruria and
                        Sardinia they were at once to have the corn sent on to the camp. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Claudius then returned to Capua and found his
                        colleague Q. Fulvius bringing everything from Casilinum and making
                        preparations to attack the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Both of
                        them now commenced the investment of the place, and they summoned the
                        praetor, Claudius Nero, who was in Claudius' old camp at Suessula.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He, too, leaving a small force to hold
                        the position, came down with the rest of his army to Capua. So three
                        commanders had their headquarters now established round Capua, and three
                        armies working on different sides were preparing to ring the city round with
                        fosse and dyke. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They erected blockhouses
                        at certain intervals, and battles took place in several places at once with
                        the Campanians as they tried to stop the work, the result being that at last
                        the Campanians kept within their walls and gates. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Before, however, the circle of investment
                        was completed, envoys were despatched to Hannibal to remonstrate with him
                        for having abandoned Capua which was now almost restored to the Romans, and
                        to implore him to bring them succour now, at all events, as they were no
                        longer merely besieged but completely blockaded. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> A despatch was sent to the consuls by P. Cornelius
                        bidding them give an opportunity to the inhabitants, before they completed
                        the investment, of leaving the place and carrying away their property with
                        them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Those who left before the 15th of
                        March would be free and remain in possession of all their property; after
                        that date those who left and those who remained would be alike treated as
                        enemies. When this offer was announced to the Campanians they treated it not
                        only with scorn but with gratuitous insults and threats as well. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Shortly before this Hannibal had left Herdonea
                        for Tarentum in the hope of acquiring the place either by treachery or by
                        force, and as he failed to do so he bent his course towards Brundisium,
                        under the impression that the town would surrender. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> It was whilst he was spending time here to no purpose
                        that the envoys from Capua came to him with their remonstrances and appeals.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Hannibal answered them in
                        high-sounding words; "he had raised the siege of Capua once already, and the
                        consuls would not wait for his approach even now." <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Dismissed with this hope the envoys had considerable
                        difficulty in getting back to Capua, surrounded as it now was with a double
                        fosse and rampart. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just when the circumvallation of Capua was
                        being completed the siege of Syracuse came to an end. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> This result was due in a large measure to the energy
                        and courage of the general and his army, but it had been helped on by
                        domestic treachery. At the commencement of the spring Marcellus was
                        undecided whether to turn the stress of war to Agrigentum against Himilco
                        and Hippocrates, or whether he should press the siege of Syracuse.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He saw that this place could not be
                        carried by assault, as it was unassailable by sea or land owing to its
                        position, nor could it be reduced by famine, since it was nourished by a
                        free supply of provisions from Carthage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        However, he determined to leave nothing untried. There were with the Romans
                        some leading members of the Syracusan nobility who had been expelled when
                        the defection took place, and Marcellus told these refugees to sound the
                        feelings of the men of their own party, and give them an assurance that if
                        Syracuse were surrendered they should be free and live under their own laws.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was impossible to get any chance of
                        interviews, for the fact of many being suspected made all more careful and
                        watchful, so that no attempt of the kind should escape detection. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> A slave belonging to the exiles was admitted into
                        the city as a deserter, and after getting a few men together, broached the
                        subject in conversation. Subsequently some were hidden under the nets in a
                        fishing boat and in that way taken round to the Roman camp where they had
                        conversations with the refugees. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Different
                        people, one after another, did the same thing, until at last there were as
                        many as eighty concerned in the matter. When all the arrangements for
                        surrender had been made, information was given to Epicydes by a certain
                        Attalus who resented not having been intrusted with the secret, and they
                        were all tortured to death. </p>
                    <p> This hope, which had proved so illusory, was soon succeeded by another.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A certain Damippus, a Lacedaemonian,
                        had been sent from Syracuse on a mission to King Philip and was captured by
                        some Roman ships. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Epicydes was
                        particularly anxious to ransom this man, and Marcellus raised no objection,
                        as just at that time the Romans were bidding for the friendship of the
                        Aetolians with whom the Lacedaemonians were in alliance. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Those who were sent to discuss the terms of the ransom
                        thought that the most central place for the conference, and the one most
                        convenient to both sides, was a spot near the tower called Galeagra, at the
                        Trogilian port. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As they went to and fro
                        there several times, one of the Romans took a near view of the wall, counted
                        the stones and formed an estimate in his mind of the thickness of each
                        stone. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Having thus calculated the height
                        of the wall as well as he could by conjecture, and finding it lower than he
                        or any one else had supposed and capable of being scaled by a ladder of even
                        moderate length, he made a report to the consul. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Marcellus attached considerable importance to his
                        suggestion, but as that part of the wall, being lower, was for that very
                        reason more carefully guarded, it was impossible to approach it and they had
                        to watch their opportunity, which soon came. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> A deserter brought word that the townspeople were
                        keeping the festival of Diana which lasted three days, and that, through
                        lack of other things, owing to the siege, they were celebrating the feast
                        mostly with wine, which Epicydes had distributed amongst the populace, and
                        the leading citizens amongst the tribes. On hearing this, Marcellus talked
                        the matter over with a few of the military tribunes, and through them
                        selected the centurions and private soldiers who were fittest for such a
                        daring enterprise. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Scaling ladders were
                        quietly got ready, and then all the rest of the men were ordered to seek
                        refreshment and rest as soon as they could, as a nocturnal expedition was in
                        front of them. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> As soon as he thought the
                        time had come when, after feasting all day, the men would have their fill of
                        wine and be in their first sleep, the consul ordered one maniple to carry
                        scaling ladders, and about a thousand men were silently marched in a narrow
                        column up to the spot. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> They got up on to
                        the wall without any confusion or noise and others at once followed in
                        order; even those who felt nervous were reassured by the daring of those in
                        front. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time a thousand men had got
                        possession of that section of the wall. They went on as far as the Hexapylon
                        without meeting a soul, as the majority of those on guard in the bastions
                        were either stupid with wine after their revels or were drinking themselves
                        drunk. They killed a few, however, whom they surprised in their beds.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they reached the Hexapylon they
                        gave the signal, and the rest of the troops marched up to the walls bringing
                        more scaling ladders with them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        postern gate near the Hexapylon was giving way to the violence of the blows,
                        and the agreed signal was given from the wall. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> They no longer attempted to conceal their movements,
                        but commenced an open attack, as they had now reached Epipolae, where there
                        was a large force on guard, and their object was now to frighten rather than
                        elude the enemy. They succeeded perfectly. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        For no sooner were the notes of the trumpets heard and the shouts of those
                        who held the wall and a part of the city, than the men on guard thought that
                        every part was taken, and some fled along the wall, others leaped from it,
                        and a crowd of panic-struck citizens took to headlong flight. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> A great many, however, were ignorant of the great
                        disaster that had befallen them, for everybody was heavy with, wine and
                        sleep, and in a city of such vast extent what was happening in one part was
                        not known to the population generally. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At daybreak Marcellus forced the gates of
                        the Hexapylon and entered the city with his entire force, rousing the
                        citizens who all betook themselves to arms, prepared to render what help
                        they could to a city which was all but captured. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Epicydes made a hurried march from the Island-its local
                        name is Nasos-under the impression that a few men had succeeded in scaling
                        the walls owing to the negligence of the guards and that he would soon drive
                        them out. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He told the terrified fugitives
                        whom he met that they were adding to the confusion and making things out to
                        be more serious and alarming than they really were. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> When, however, he saw every place round Epipolae full
                        of armed men, he simply discharged a few missiles at the enemy and marched
                        back to the Achradina, not so much through fear of the strength and numbers
                        of the enemy as of some opening for treason from within, which might close
                        the gates of Achradina and the Island against him in the confusion.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When Marcellus mounted the
                        fortifications and saw from his higher ground the city below him, the
                        fairest city of the time, he is said to have shed <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> tears at the sight, partly through joy at his great
                        achievement, partly at the memory of its ancient glories. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> He thought of the Athenian fleets which had been sunk
                        in that harbour, of the two great armies with their famous generals which
                        had been annihilated there, of all of its many powerful kings and tyrants,
                        above all, of Hiero, whose memory was so fresh, and who, in addition to all
                        his endowments of fortune and character, had distinguished himself by his
                        services to Rome. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As all this passed
                        through his mind and with it the thought that in one short hour all he saw
                        round him would be burnt and reduced to ashes, he <milestone n="15??"
                            unit="section"/> decided, before advancing against Achradina, to send
                        the Syracusans, who, as already stated, were with the Roman troops, into the
                        city to try if kind words could induce the enemy to surrender the place.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The gates and walls of Achradina were
                        mostly held by the deserters who were hopeless of obtaining mercy on any
                        terms, and they allowed no one to approach the walls or to speak to them.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> So Marcellus, finding that his project
                        had failed, ordered the troops to return to Euryalus. This was a hill in the
                        furthest part of the city, away from the sea, and overlooking the road which
                        leads into the country and the inland part of the island. It was, therefore,
                        admirably adapted for the reception of supplies from the interior.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The command of the citadel here had
                        been entrusted by Epicydes to Philodemus an Argive. Sosis, one of the
                        regicides, had been sent by Marcellus to open up negotiations, but after a
                        long conversation in which he found himself put off with evasive replies he
                        reported to Marcellus that Philodemus was taking time for consideration.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He continued to procrastinate from day
                        to day, to allow time for Hippocrates and Himilco to bring up their legions,
                        feeling quite sure that if he had them in his stronghold the Romans would be
                        shut up within the walls and annihilated. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        As Marcellus saw that Euryalus could not be taken by either treachery or
                        force, he established his camp between Neapolis and Tycha-parts of the city,
                        and almost cities in themselves-as he was afraid if he entered the more
                        populous parts he would not be able to keep his soldiers from dispersing in
                        their eagerness for plunder. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Envoys came
                        to him from these two places with olive branches and woollen fillets,
                        imploring him that they might be spared from fire and sword. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Marcellus held a council of war to consider this
                        request, or rather this entreaty, and in accordance with the wish of all
                        present he gave notice to the soldiers that they were not to lay hands on
                        any free citizen; everything else they were at liberty to appropriate.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Instead of fosse and rampart the camp
                        was protected by the private houses which served it for walls, and sentinels
                        and pickets were posted at the gates of the houses which stood open to the
                        street to secure the camp against attack while the soldiers were dispersed
                        in the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After this the signal was
                        given and the soldiers ran in all directions, breaking open the house doors
                        and filling everything with uproar and panic, but they refrained from
                        bloodshed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There was no limit to the work
                        of rapine until they had cleared the houses of all the goods and possessions
                        which had been accumulating during the long spell of prosperity. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Whilst this was going on, Philodemus saw that
                        there was no hope of succour, and after getting the promise of a safe
                        conduct for him to return to Epicydes, he withdrew his garrison and handed
                        the position over to the Romans. Whilst everybody was preoccupied with the
                        tumult in the captured part of the city, Bomilcar seized the opportunity to
                        escape. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The night was a tempestuous one,
                        and the Roman fleet were unable to keep their anchorage off the harbour, so
                        he slipped out with thirty-five ships, and finding the sea clear set sail
                        for Carthage, leaving fifty-five ships for Epicydes and the Syracusans.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After making the Carthaginians
                        realise the critical state of affairs at Syracuse he returned with a hundred
                        ships a few days later and was rewarded-so they say-by Epicydes with gifts
                        from Hiero's treasury. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The capture of Euryalus and its occupation
                        by a Roman garrison relieved Marcellus of one cause of anxiety; he had no
                        longer to dread an attack from the rear which might have created confusion
                        amongst his men, shut in and hampered as they were by walls. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> His next move was against Achradina. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> He established three separate camps in suitable
                        positions and sat down before the place, hoping to reduce it by famine. For
                        some days the outposts were undisturbed, when the sudden arrival of
                        Hippocrates and Himilco led to a general attack upon the Roman lines.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hippocrates had formed an entrenched
                        camp at the Great Harbour, and after giving a signal to the troops in
                        Achradina he made an attack on the old camp of the Romans which Crispinus
                        commanded. Epicydes made a sortie against Marcellus and the Carthaginian
                        fleet which lay between the city and the Roman camp was brought ashore and
                        so prevented Crispinus from sending any help to Marcellus. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The excitement which the enemy caused was, however,
                        much more alarming than the fighting, for Crispinus not only drove
                        Hippocrates back from his entrenchments, but actually went in pursuit as he
                        fled hurriedly away, whilst Marcellus drove Epicydes back into the city.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And now, apparently, ample provision
                        was made against danger arising from any sudden attacks in the future. </p>
                    <p> To add to their troubles both sides were visited by pestilence, a calamity
                        almost heavy enough to turn them from all thoughts of war. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> It was the time of autumn and the locality was
                        naturally unhealthy, more so, however, outside the city than within it, and
                        the insupportable heat affected the constitutions of almost all who were in
                        the two camps. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the beginning people
                        fell ill and died through the effects of the season and the unhealthy
                        locality; later, the nursing of the sick and contact with them spread the
                        disease, so that either those who had caught it died neglected and
                        abandoned, or else they carried off with them those who were waiting on them
                        and nursing them, and who had thus become infected. Deaths and funerals were
                        a daily spectacle; on all sides, day and night, were heard the wailings for
                        the dead. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At last familiarity with misery
                        so brutalised men that not only would <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                        they not follow the dead with tears and the lamentations which custom
                        demanded, but they actually refused to carry them out for burial, and the
                        lifeless bodies were left lying about before the eyes of those who were
                        awaiting a similar death. So what with fear and the foul and deadly miasma
                        arising from the bodies, the dead proved fatal to the sick and the sick
                        equally fatal to those in health. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Men
                        preferred to die by the sword; some, single-handed, attacked the enemies'
                        outposts. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The epidemic was much more
                        prevalent in the Carthaginian camp than in that of the Romans, for their
                        long investment of Syracuse had made them more accustomed to the climate and
                        to the water. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Sicilians who were in
                        the hostile ranks deserted as soon as they saw that the disease was
                        spreading through the unhealthiness of the place, and went off to their own
                        cities. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians, who had
                        nowhere to go to, perished to a man together with their generals,
                        Hippocrates and Himilco. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When the disease
                        assumed such serious proportions Marcellus transferred his men to the city,
                        and those who had been weakened by sickness were restored by shade and
                        shelter. Still, many of the Roman soldiers, too, were carried off by that
                        pestilence. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the land army of the Carthaginians
                        had been thus wiped out, the Sicilians who had been with Hippocrates took
                        possession of two walled towns, not large ones certainly, but made safe by
                        their situation and strong fortifications. One was three miles from
                        Syracuse, the other fifteen. They carried supplies to these towns from their
                        own states and asked for reinforcements. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Bomilcar had in the meantime paid a second visit to Carthage with his fleet
                        and had drawn such a picture of the state of things in Syracuse as to lead
                        the government to hope that they might not only render effectual assistance
                        to their friends, but even succeed in capturing the Romans inside that city,
                        which they had in some measure captured. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        He persuaded them to despatch as many cargo ships as they could, laden with
                        stores of all kinds, and also to augment his force of fighting ships. The
                        result was that he left Carthage with 130 ships of war and 700 transports.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The winds were favourable for him
                        whilst sailing for Sicily, but they prevented him from rounding the
                        promontory of Pachinus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The news of
                        Bomilcar's approach and then his unexpected delay excited first hope and
                        then fear amongst the Syracusans and just the reverse among the Romans.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Epicydes was afraid that if the east
                        wind lasted much longer the Carthaginian fleet would return to Africa, and
                        he handed <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Achradina over to the
                        commanders of the mercenaries and put off to meet Bomilcar. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He found him at anchor with his ships headed for the
                        African coast and anxious to avoid a naval engagement, not because he was
                        inferior in the strength or number of his ships-he really had more than the
                        Romans-but because the winds were more favourable to them than to him;
                        Epicydes, however, persuaded him to try his chance in a sea fight.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When Marcellus became aware that an
                        army of Sicilians was being raised from the whole of the island, and that a
                        Carthaginian fleet was approaching with vast supplies, he determined, though
                        inferior in the number of ships to prevent Bomilcar from reaching Syracuse,
                        lest he should be shut in by sea and land whilst he was confined and
                        hampered in a hostile city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The two
                        fleets lay facing each other off the promontory of Pachinus, ready to engage
                        as soon as the sea was calm enough to allow them to sail into deep water.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as the east wind, which had
                        been blowing strongly for some days, dropped Bomilcar made the first move.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It seemed as though he was making for
                        the open sea in order the better to round the promontory, but when he saw
                        the Roman ships sailing straight for him he crowded on all sail and skirting
                        the coast of Sicily made for Tarentum, having previously sent a message to
                        Heraclea ordering the transports to return to Africa. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Finding all his hopes suddenly crushed, Epicydes did
                        not care to go back to a city which was in a state of siege and a large part
                        of which was already taken. He sailed for Agrigentum, to watch events rather
                        than to control them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of what had happened reached
                        the camp of the Sicilians, viz. that Epicydes had left Syracuse and that the
                        island had been abandoned by the Carthaginians and almost surrendered a
                        second <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> time to the Romans, they sent
                        envoys to Marcellus to treat for the surrender of the city, having
                        previously sounded in frequent interviews the feelings of those who were
                        undergoing the siege. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were
                        practically united on these two points, that all that had been included in
                        the king's dominions should belong to Rome, and that all else was to be
                        retained by the Sicilians together with their liberty and their laws.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They then invited those who had been
                        left in charge by Epicydes to a conference, the envoys telling them that the
                        army of the Sicilians had sent them to them as well as to Marcellus, so that
                        those who were within and those who were outside of the beleaguered city
                        might share the same fortune, and neither should make separate terms for
                        themselves. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Admission was granted to them
                        that they might converse with their friends and relatives. After explaining
                        the nature of their understanding with Marcellus and holding out a prospect
                        of safety, they persuaded them to join in an attack upon those to whom
                        Epicydes had committed the government-Polyclitus, Philistio, and Epicydes,
                        surnamed Sindon. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were put to death
                        and the citizens were summoned to a public meeting. Here the envoys
                        complained bitterly of the straits they were in for food, and the other
                        evils which they had been in the habit of grumbling about in secret; they
                        said that although they had so much to distress them, they must not throw
                        the blame on Fortune; it was in their own power to decide how long they
                        would endure it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The motives which led the
                        Romans to attack Syracuse were those of affection, not animosity. When they
                        heard that the reins of government had been seized by Hippocrates and
                        Epicydes, who had been first creatures of Hannibal and then of Hieronymus,
                        they set their armies in motion and began the siege, not for the purpose of
                        destroying the city but of crushing those who were tyrannising over it.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But now that Hippocrates was disposed
                        of and Epicydes shut out from Syracuse and his officers put to death, what
                        was there left to prevent the Romans from wishing that Syracuse should be
                        free from all harm, just as they would have wished it had Hiero, that
                        eminently loyal friend of Rome, been still alive? <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> There was, then, no danger either to the city or its
                        people other than what would arise from their own action if they let slip
                        that chance of reconciliation with Rome. There would never be another so
                        favourable as the one they had at that moment, just when it was plain to all
                        that Syracuse had been delivered from an impotent tyranny. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This address was received with universal
                        approval. It was, however, decided to elect magistrates before sending the
                        envoys. From amongst the magistrates so elected they selected the envoys who
                        were to be sent to Marcellus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Their leader
                        addressed him in the following terms: "It is not we, the people of Syracuse,
                        who have revolted from you, but Hieronymus, who acted much more wickedly
                        towards us than towards you. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when
                        peace had been restored by the tyrant's death it was no Syracusan, but the
                        king's creatures Hippocrates and Epicydes, who disturbed it, by crushing us
                        on the one hand by fear, on the other by treachery. No man can say that
                        there was ever a time during which we enjoyed liberty when we were not at
                        peace with you. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now, at all events, no
                        sooner have we become our own masters through the death of the oppressors of
                        Syracuse than we come to you to give up our arms, to surrender ourselves,
                        our city and its fortifications, to accept any condition which you may lay
                        upon us. To you, Marcellus, the gods have vouchsafed the glory of capturing
                        the noblest and fairest of Grecian cities. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Whatever memorable achievement we have wrought by sea or land enhances the
                        splendour of your triumph. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Would you wish
                        that it should be only a glorious tradition how great a city you have
                        captured, rather than that it should be a spectacle for the eyes of
                        posterity to rest upon? That it should exhibit to all who visit it by land
                        or sea the trophies we have won from Athenians and Carthaginians, which are
                        now the trophies you have won from us? That you should hand down to your
                        house an unharmed Syracuse to be kept under the patronage and protection of
                        all who bear the name of Marcellus? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Let
                        not the memory of Hieronymus weigh more with you than that of Hiero. He was
                        your friend for a far longer time than the other was your enemy. You found
                        in him a real benefactor; this man's madness only availed to his own
                        destruction." As far as the Romans were concerned they could have gained all
                        they wanted in perfect security. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was
                        amongst the besieged themselves that war existed with all its perils. The
                        deserters, thinking that they were being betrayed, communicated their fears
                        to the mercenaries; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> they all flew to arms,
                        and beginning with the murder of the magistrates they commenced a general
                        massacre of the citizens, killing in their desperate madness everybody they
                        met, and plundering all they could lay hands on. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Then, that they might not be without officers, they
                        elected six, three to command in Achradina and three in Nasos. When the
                        tumult had somewhat subsided and the mercenaries found out on inquiry what
                        agreement had been come to with the Romans, the truth began to dawn upon
                        them, and they realised that their case was quite distinct from that of the
                        deserters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys came back from their interview
                        with Marcellus just at the right moment, and were able to assure them that
                        their suspicions were groundless and that the Romans saw no reason why they
                        should visit them with punishment. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One of
                        the three commanders in Achradina was a Spaniard named Moericus, and amongst
                        those who accompanied the envoys a soldier from the Spanish auxiliaries had
                        designedly been introduced. When they had entered Achradina this man
                        obtained a private interview with Moericus and described to him the state of
                        affairs in Spain, which he had quite recently left, and how everything there
                        was under the power of Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If Moericus
                        chose to make himself of use to the Romans, he might be a leading man among
                        his countrymen, and either take service under the Roman standard or return
                        to his own country, whichever he chose. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        But if on the other hand he preferred to remain under siege, what hope had
                        he of relief, shut in as he was by sea and land? Moericus was impressed by
                        the force of these arguments, and after it had been decided to send envoys
                        to Marcellus, he sent his brother as one of them. The same Spanish soldier
                        conducted him by himself to Marcellus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In
                        this interview the details were settled and Marcellus pledged himself to
                        observe the conditions, after which the envoys returned to Achradina. In
                        order to avoid the least chance of suspicion Moericus made it known that he
                        disapproved of envoys going to and fro, and gave orders that none were to be
                        admitted and none sent. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Also, with a view
                        to greater security, he thought that the conduct of the defence ought to be
                        properly distributed amongst the three commanders, so that each might be
                        responsible for his own section of the fortifications. They all agreed.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the division, his command extended
                        from the fountain of Arethusa to the mouth of the Great Harbour, and he
                        managed to let the Romans know that. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So
                        Marcellus ordered a cargo ship filled with troops to be towed by a
                        quadrireme to the Island, and the men to land near the gate adjoining the
                        fountain. This order was carried out in the fourth watch, and Moericus, as
                        previously arranged, admitted the soldiers through the gate. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> At dawn Marcellus attacked Achradina with his
                        full strength, and not only those who were actually holding it, but the
                        troops in Nasos also, left their posts and ran to defend Achradina from the
                        assault of the Romans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the confusion
                        of the attack some swift vessels, which had previously been brought round to
                        Nasos, landed troops. These making an unexpected attack upon the half-manned
                        posts, and rushing through the gates, still open, out of which the garrison
                        had just sallied to defend Achradina, had little trouble in capturing a
                        position which had been abandoned owing to the flight of its defenders.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There were none who did less to
                        defend the place or to maintain their ground with any spirit than the
                        deserters; they did not even trust their own comrades, and fled in the
                        middle of the fighting. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When Marcellus
                        learnt that Nasos was captured and one district of Achradina occupied, and
                        that Moericus with his men had joined the Romans, he ordered the retreat to
                        be sounded, for he was afraid that the royal treasure, the fame of which
                        exceeded the reality, might fall into the hands of plunderers. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The impetuosity of the soldiers being thus
                        checked and time and opportunity given for the deserters in Achradina to
                        effect their escape, the Syracusans were at last relieved of their
                        apprehensions and opened the gates. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                        at once sent a deputation to Marcellus with the one request that they and
                        their children might remain unharmed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                        called a council of war, to which he summoned the Syracusan refugees in the
                        Roman camp, and made the following reply to the deputation: "The crimes
                        committed against the people of Rome during these last few years by those
                        who have held Syracuse quite outweigh all the good services which Hiero
                        rendered us during his fifty years' reign. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Most of these, it is true, have recoiled on the heads of those who were
                        guilty of them, and they have punished themselves for their breach of
                        treaties far more severely than the Roman people could have wished.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I have been for three years investing
                        Syracuse, not that Rome may make the city her slave, but that the leaders of
                        deserters and renegades may not keep it in a state of oppression and
                        bondage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What the Syracusans could have
                        done has been shown by those amongst them who have been living within the
                        Roman lines, by the Spaniard Moericus who brought over his men, and last of
                        all by the belated but courageous resolution which the Syracusans have now
                        taken. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After all the toils and dangers
                        which have endured for so long a time round the walls of Syracuse by sea and
                        land, the fact that I have been able to capture the city is nothing like
                        such a reward as I should have received had I been able to save it."
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After giving this reply he sent the
                        quaestor with an escort to Nasos to receive the royal treasure into his
                        custody. Achradina was given up for plunder to the soldiers, after guards
                        had been placed at the houses of the refugees who were within the Roman
                        lines. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Amongst many horrible instances of fury
                        and rapacity the fate of Archimedes stands out. It is recorded that amidst
                        all the uproar and terror created by the soldiers who were rushing about the
                        captured city in search of plunder, he was quietly absorbed in some
                        geometrical figures which he had drawn on the sand, and was killed by a
                        soldier who did not know who he was. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Marcellus was much grieved and took care that his funeral was properly
                        conducted; and after his relations had been discovered they were honoured
                        and protected by the name and memory of Archimedes. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Such, in the main, were the circumstances under which
                        Syracuse was captured, and the amount of plunder was almost greater
                            <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> than if Carthage had been taken,
                        the city which was waging war on equal terms with Rome. A few days prior to
                        the capture of Syracuse, T. Otacilius crossed over from Lilybaeum to Utica
                        with eighty quinqueremes. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He entered the
                        harbour before daylight and captured some transports laden with corn, and
                        then landing his men ravaged a considerable portion of the country round
                        Utica and carried back to his ships every description of plunder. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> He returned to Lilybaeum three days after he had
                        started with a hundred and thirty transports laden with corn and booty.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The corn he at once sent on to
                        Syracuse; had it not been for that timely assistance, victors and vanquished
                        alike would have been in danger of a very serious famine. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For two years nothing very remarkable had
                        happened in Spain; the contest was carried on by diplomacy more than by
                        arms. This summer the Roman commanders on leaving their winter quarters
                        united their forces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A council of war was
                        called and they came to a unanimous decision that as up to that time all
                        they had done was to keep Hasdrubal from marching to Italy, it was now high
                        time to make an effort to finish the war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        During the winter they had raised a force of 20,000 Celtiberians, and with
                        this reinforcement they considered themselves strong enough for the task.
                        The enemies' force consisted of three armies. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, the son of Gisgo, had united his army with
                        Mago, and their joint camp was about a five days' march from the Romans.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Somewhat nearer to them was Hasdrubal,
                        the son of Hamilcar, an old commander in Spain, who was in camp at a city
                        called Amtorgis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman commanders
                        wanted to dispose of him first, and they believed that they had more than
                        enough strength for the purpose; the only doubt in their minds was whether,
                        after his defeat, the other Hasdrubal and Mago would not retreat into the
                        trackless forest and mountains and keep up a guerilla warfare. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The best plan, they thought, would be to form
                        their force into two armies and finish the war in Spain at one stroke. They
                        arranged accordingly that P. Cornelius was to advance against Mago and
                        Hasdrubal with two-thirds of the army of Romans and allied <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> troops, and Cn. Cornelius with the remaining
                        third of the old army and the recently raised Celtiberians was to oppose the
                        Barcine Hasdrubal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Both generals with
                        their armies advanced together as far as the town of Amtorgis where they
                        encamped in full view of the enemy with the river between them. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Here Cn. Scipio took his stand with the force
                        above mentioned, while Publius Scipio went on to execute his share of the
                        operations. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hasdrubal became aware that the
                        Romans formed only a small portion of the army and that they were depending
                        entirely upon their Celtiberian auxiliaries, he determined to detach the
                        latter from their Roman service. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He was
                        quite at home with every form of treachery known to barbarians, and
                        especially those practised by the tribes amongst whom he had for so many
                        years been campaigning. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both camps were
                        full of Spaniards, who had no difficulty in understanding each other's
                        language, and secret interviews were held, in the course of which he made an
                        agreement with the Celtiberian chieftains, by the offer of a large bribe,
                        that they should withdraw their forces. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        They did not look upon this as very atrocious conduct, for it was not a
                        question of turning their arms against the Romans, and though the money was
                        quite equal to the pay they received in war, it was given them to abstain
                        from war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then, too, the mere rest from
                        the toils of the campaign, the thought of returning home, the delight of
                        seeing their friends and their possessions were universally welcomed. So the
                        mass of the troops were quite as easily persuaded as their chiefs, and they
                        had nothing to fear from the Romans who were too few in number to keep them
                        lack by force. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This is a thing against
                        which Roman generals will always have to be on their guard, and instances
                        such as these ought to serve as warnings that they must not depend upon
                        foreign auxiliaries to such an extent as not to have in their camp a
                        preponderance of that solidity and fighting power which native troops can
                        alone supply. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians took up
                        their standards and marched off. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        Romans asked them why they were going, and appealed to them to stay where
                        they were, but the only answer they got was that they were called away by a
                        war at home. When Scipio saw that his allies could not be detained by either
                        appeals or force and that without them he was no match for the enemy, whilst
                        a junction with his brother was out of the question, he determined to
                        retreat as far as he could; this seemed the only safe measure to adopt.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> His one object was to avoid an
                        encounter on open ground with the enemy who had crossed the river and were
                        pressing closely at his heels. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> P. Scipio was at the same time placed in a
                        position quite as alarming but fraught with much greater danger by the
                        appearance of a new enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was young
                        Masinissa, at that time an ally of the Carthaginians, but afterwards raised
                        to fame and power by his friendship with Rome. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He first sought to check Scipio's advance with a body
                        of Numidian horse, and he kept up incessant attacks upon him day and night.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He not only cut off all who had
                        wandered too far from camp in search of wood and fodder, but he actually
                        rode up to the camp and charged into the middle of the outposts and pickets,
                        creating alarm and confusion everywhere. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        In the night he frequently upset the camp by making a sudden rush at the
                        gates and the stockade; there was no place and no time at which the Romans
                        were free from anxiety and fear, and they were compelled to keep within
                        their lines, unable to obtain anything they wanted. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was fast becoming a regular siege and would
                        evidently become a still closer one if Indebilis, who was reported to be
                        approaching with 7500 Suessetanians, should join the Carthaginians.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cautious and prudent general though he
                        was, Scipio was compelled by his position to take the hazardous step of
                        making a night march to oppose Indebilis' advance and to fight him wherever
                        he met him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Leaving a small force to guard
                        the camp and placing Tiberius Fonteius in command, he started at midnight
                        and encountered the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They fought in
                        order of march rather than of battle; the Romans, however, had the
                        advantage, in spite of its being an irregular battle. But the Numidian
                        horse, whom Scipio thought he had eluded, swept round both flanks and
                        created the greatest alarm. A fresh action had now begun against the
                        Numidians when a third enemy appeared; the Carthaginian generals had come up
                        and were attacking the rear. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Romans
                        had to face a battle on both flanks and on their rear, and could not make up
                        their minds against what enemy to make their main attack or in what
                        direction to close their line and charge. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Whilst their commander was fighting and encouraging his men and exposing
                        himself in the hottest of the turmoil he was run through by a lance in his
                        left side. The massed body of the enemy who had charged the closed ranks
                        round their general, as soon as they saw Scipio falling lifeless from his
                        horse were wild with joy and ran in all directions shouting that the Roman
                        commander had fallen. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The news spread
                        over the whole field, and the enemy at once regarded themselves as
                        unquestionably victorious, while the Romans equally felt themselves
                        vanquished. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> With the loss of the general
                        there began at once a flight from the field. It was not difficult to break
                        through the Numidians and other light-armed troops, but it was almost
                        impossible to make one's escape amidst such numbers of cavalry and of foot
                        soldiers who rivalled horses in speed. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Almost more were killed in flight than in battle, and not a man would have
                        survived had not the day been rapidly drawing to a close so that night put
                        an end to the carnage. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian generals were not slow to
                        take advantage of their success. After allowing their men the needful rest,
                        they proceeded straight from the battle-field by forced marches to
                        Hasdrubal, fully expecting that when they had joined forces the war could be
                        brought to a close. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they reached his
                        camp, the generals and the soldiers, in high spirits over their recent
                        victory, exchanged hearty congratulations at the destruction of so great a
                        commander and his entire army, and looked forward with confidence to winning
                        another victory as complete. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The report of
                        the terrible disaster had not reached the Romans, but there was a gloomy
                        silence, a secret foreboding, such as usually happens when men feel a
                        presentiment of coming misfortune. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        general, who saw himself deserted by his allies and knew that the forces of
                        the enemy were so largely augmented, was led still further by his own
                        conjectures and inferences to suspect the occurrence of some disaster much
                        sooner than to entertain any hopes of success. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> "How," he asked himself, "could Hasdrubal and Mago have
                        brought up their army without opposition if they had not brought their own
                        share of the war to a successful close? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        How could his brother have failed to stop them or to follow them up so that
                        if he could not prevent their forming a junction he could at least have
                        united his own forces with those of his brother?" <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Filled with these anxieties he believed that the only
                        safe course for him for the time being was to retreat from his present
                        position as far as he could. He accordingly accomplished a considerable
                        march in a single night, unobserved by the enemy and therefore unmolested.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When it grew light the enemy became
                        aware of his departure, and sending on the Numidians in advance, commenced
                        the pursuit with the utmost speed of which they were capable. The Numidians
                        came up with them before nightfall, and by making repeated charges on flank
                        and rear compelled them to come to a halt and defend themselves. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio, however, urged them to fight as well as
                        they could and keep moving forward before they were overtaken by the
                        infantry. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As, however, what with fighting and
                        halting, they had for some time been making very little progress and night
                        was close at hand, Scipio called his men <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                        off from battle, massed them in close order, and led them to some rising
                        ground, not, indeed, a very safe position, especially for unnerved troops,
                        but still somewhat more elevated than the ground round it. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The baggage and the cavalry were placed in the centre
                        and the infantry drawn up round them, and at first they had no difficulty in
                        repelling the attacks of the Numidians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        But when the three commanders appeared in full force with three regular
                        armies it was obvious that they would be unable to defend the position by
                        arms alone in the absence of entrenchments. The general began to look round
                        him and consider whether it were in any way possible to surround himself
                        with an earthwork. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the hill was so
                        bare and the ground so rocky that there was no brushwood to cut for a
                        stockade nor earth for constructing a rampart or carrying a fosse or for any
                        other work. No part was naturally so steep or precipitous as to render the
                        approach or ascent difficult for the enemy; the whole surface of the hill
                        rose in a gentle slope. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In order, however,
                        to present to the enemy something which might look like <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> a rampart they tied together their saddles and the
                        packs which the animals carried and piled them up all round them as if they
                        were building up a rampart to the usual height, and where there were not
                        enough saddles they made it up by throwing all the kits and packages of
                        every kind into the gaps, as a barricade. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the Carthaginian armies came up,
                        their column had no difficulty in mounting the hill, but they stopped short
                        at the sight of the novel defence as though it were something uncanny. Their
                        officers shouted out on all sides: "Why are you stopping? Why do you not
                        tear down and demolish that juggler's trick, which is hardly strong enough
                        to stop women and children? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The enemy,
                        hiding behind his baggage, is caught and held!" <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> But in spite of the taunts and sarcasms of the
                        officers, it was anything but easy either to clamber over or to push away
                        the heavy obstacles in front of them, or to cut through the tightly packed
                        saddles, buried as they were beneath the baggage. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> After a considerable time they succeeded in forcing
                        away the heavy obstacles and opened a way for the troops, and when they had
                        done this in several places the camp was rushed on all sides and captured;
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> the little band of defenders were
                        slaughtered by the masses of the enemy, helpless in the hands of their
                        victors. Still a good many found refuge in the neighbouring woods and
                        escaped to P. Scipio's camp where Ti. Fonteius was in command. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Some traditions assert that Cn. Scipio was
                        killed in the first onset of the enemy on the hill; according to others he
                        escaped to a tower near the camp, and as they were unable to break down the
                        door with all their efforts, they lighted fires against it, and after it was
                        burnt away they slew all inside including the commander. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Cn. Scipio was killed after he had been eight years in
                        Spain, and twenty-nine days after his brother's death. The grief felt at
                        their death was as great throughout Spain as it was in Rome. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> The City had to mourn not only for them, but for
                        the loss of its armies, the defection of the province, and the blow
                        inflicted on the republic; in Spain it was the generals themselves whose
                        loss was so bitterly felt, more so in the case of Cnaeus, because he had
                        held his command there for a longer time; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        he too was the first to win popularity amongst the people, the first to show
                        what Roman justice and Roman self-control and moderation really meant. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the destruction of the armies it
                        seemed as though Spain must be lost. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But
                        one man restored the fallen fortunes of the State. There was in the army a
                        Lucius Marcius, the son of Septimius, a Roman knight, an active and
                        energetic youth whose character and abilities were somewhat superior to the
                        position in which he had been born. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His
                        many natural gifts had been developed by Scipio's training, under whom he
                        had learnt all the arts of war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Out of the
                        fugitive soldiers whom he had rallied, and some whom he had drawn from the
                        garrisons in Spain, he had formed quite a respectable army, and with it had
                        joined Ti. Fonteius, Scipio's lieutenant. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        After they had entrenched themselves in a camp on this side of the Ebrot his
                        soldiers decided to hold a regular election for the purpose of choosing a
                        general to command the united armies, and they relieved each other on
                        sentinel and outpost duty so that every man might give his vote. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> So far did the Roman knight surpass all others in
                        the authority and respect which he possessed with the soldiers that the
                        whole army unanimously conferred the supreme command on L. Marcius.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After this he spent the whole of the
                        time-and short enough it was-in strengthening the defences of the camp and
                        storing supplies in it, and the soldiers carried out all his commands with
                        alacrity and in anything but a despondent mood. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But when the news arrived that Hasdrubal-Gisgo's
                        son-had crossed the Ebro and was coming to stamp out the remains of the war
                        and the soldiers saw the signal for battle put out by their new general they
                        gave way completely. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The recollection of
                        the men who had so lately commanded them, the proud confidence which they
                        had always felt in their generals and their armies when they went into
                        battle quite unnerved them; they all burst into tears and smote their heads;
                        some raised their hands to heaven and reproached the gods; others lay on the
                        ground and invoked the names of their old commanders. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Nothing could check these wild outbursts of grief,
                        though the centurions tried to rouse their men, and Marcius himself went
                        about calming them and at the same time reproaching them for their unmanly
                        conduct. "Why," he asked them, "have you given way to womanish and idle
                        tears instead of bracing yourselves up to defend yourselves and the republic
                        and not allowing your commanders' death to go unavenged?" </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Suddenly a shout was heard and the sound
                        of trumpets, for the enemy was now close up to the rampart. In an instant
                        their grief changed to fury, they rushed to arms, and racing to the gates
                        like madmen they dashed upon the enemy who were coming on carelessly and in
                        disorder. The sudden and unlooked for movement created a panic among the
                        Carthaginians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They wondered whence all
                        these enemies had arisen, after their army had been all but annihilated,
                        what gave such daring and self-confidence to men who had been vanquished and
                        put to flight, who had come forward as their commander now that the two
                        Scipios were killed, who was over the camp, who had given the signal for
                        battle. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Bewildered and astounded at all
                        these utterly unlooked-for surprises they at first slowly retired, then as
                        the attack became heavier and more insistent they turned and fled.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> There would have been either a
                        frightful slaughter amongst the fugitives or a rash and dangerous attack on
                        the part of the pursuers if Marcius had not hurriedly given the signal to
                        retire and kept back the excited troops by throwing himself in front of the
                        foremost and even holding some back with his hands. Then he marched them
                        back to camp still thirsting for blood. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        When the Carthaginians saw that none were pursuing them after the first
                        repulse from the rampart they imagined that they had been afraid to go any
                        further, their feelings of contempt returned, and they marched at a
                        leisurely pace back to their camp. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> They
                        showed as much carelessness in guarding their own camp as they had shown in
                        attacking the Roman, for although their enemy was near them they regarded
                        them as only the wreckage of two armies which had been destroyed a few days
                        before. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Whilst they were, in consequence
                        of this, neglectful of everything, Marcius, who had become thoroughly aware
                        of it, thought out a plan, at first glance hazardous rather than bold, which
                        was to assume the aggressive and attack the enemy's camp. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> He thought it would be easier to storm Hasdrubal's camp
                        whilst he was alone than to defend his own, in case the three commanders
                        united their forces once more. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Besides,
                        if he succeeded he would have gone far to retrieve their late disasters; if
                        he failed the enemy could no longer despise him, since he would have been
                        the first to attack. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> His plan seemed a desperate one,
                        considering the position he was in, and might easily be upset by some
                        unforeseen incident creating a panic in the night. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> To guard against these dangers as far as possible, he
                        thought it well to address some words of encouragement to his men. He called
                        them together and made the following speech to them: "My loyalty and
                        affection for my old commanders whether living or dead, as well as the
                        situation in which we now find ourselves, ought to convince every one of
                        you, soldiers, that this command, honourable as you rightly deem it to be,
                        is, as a matter of fact, a position of very grave anxiety. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> For at a moment when I was hardly sufficient master of
                        myself-did not fear dull the sense of pain-to find any comfort in my
                        distress, I saw myself compelled to take thought alone for you all, the
                        hardest thing in the world in a time of grief. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Even when I have to consider how I can possibly
                        preserve for my country you who are all <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                        that remain out of two armies, it is still a grief to have to divert my
                        thoughts from a sorrow that is ever with me. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> Bitter memories vex me; the two Scipios haunt me in anxious thoughts by
                        day and in dreams at night; they rouse me from my slumbers and forbid me to
                        suffer them or their soldiers-your own comrades who never for eight years
                        knew defeat in these lands-or the republic, to remain unavenged. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> They call upon me to follow their example and act
                        on the principles they laid down; as no man obeyed them more faithfully
                        while they lived, so now that they are gone they would have me think that
                        what they would have done on any occasion that arose is the best thing for
                        me also to do. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And I would have you, my
                        soldiers, not follow them with tears and laments as though they had ceased
                        to be, for they live and are strong in the glory of all that they have
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> done, but go into battle thinking of
                        them as if they were here to encourage you and give you the signal.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Surely it was nothing else than their
                        image before your eyes which brought about that memorable battle yesterday,
                        in which you showed your enemy that the Roman name did not perish with the
                        Scipios, and that a people whose strength and courage even Cannae could not
                        crush will rise superior to the hardest blows of fortune. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "Well, as you showed such daring
                        yesterday on your own account, I want now to see if you will show as much
                        daring at the bidding of your commander. When I gave the signal yesterday to
                        recall you from your hot pursuit of your disordered foe it was from no wish
                        to damp your courage but to reserve it for a greater and more glorious
                        occasion, when you will shortly <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> be
                        able, prepared and armed, to fall upon the enemy when he is off his guard,
                        without his arms and even wrapped in slumbers. And in thus hoping, I am not
                        trusting simply to chance, but have good grounds for what I say. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> If any one were to ask you how, few as you are,
                        you managed to defend your camp against a mighty host, how after your defeat
                        you were able to repel those who had defeated you from your rampart, you
                        would, I am sure, reply that this was the very danger you feared, and
                        therefore you strengthened your defences in every possible way and held
                        yourselves at your posts in readiness. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        And such is generally the case; men are least safe when their circumstances
                        give them no cause for fear; what you think of no importance you leave open
                        and unguarded. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There is nothing which the
                        enemy are less afraid of than that we who were lately surrounded and
                        attacked should of our own motion attack their camp. Let us venture where no
                        one can believe we will venture. The fact that it is thought too difficult
                        will make it all the easier. I will lead you out in a silent march at the
                        third watch of the night. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> I have
                        ascertained that they have no proper arrangement of sentinels and pickets.
                        When once our shout is heard in their gates the camp will be carried at the
                        first rush. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Then, whilst they are heavy
                        with sleep, panic-struck at the unlooked-for tumult, and surprised
                        defenceless in their beds, that slaughter will take place amongst them from
                        which you were, to your intense disappointment, recalled yesterday. </p>
                    <p> "I know that the plan seems a daring one, but in difficult circumstances
                        which leave little to hope for the boldest measures are always the safest.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> If, when the critical moment comes,
                        you hang back ever so little and do not catch the opportunity as it flies
                        past, you will look for it in vain when once you have let it go. There is
                        one army near us, two more are not very far away. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> If we attack them now, there is some hope for us; you
                        have already tried your strength against theirs. <milestone n="20"
                            unit="section"/> If we put off the day, and after yesterday's sortie are
                        no longer regarded with contempt, there is the danger of all the generals
                        and their armies uniting. In that case, shall we withstand the three
                        generals, the three armies, which Cn. Scipio did not withstand when his army
                        was in its full strength? <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> As our generals
                        perished owing to their forces being divided, so the enemy can be crushed in
                        detail while they are divided. There is no other way of carrying on war; let
                        us, then, wait for nothing beyond the opportunity of the coming night.
                            <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Now go, trusting to the help of the
                        gods and get food and rest so that, fresh and vigorous, you may break into
                        the enemies' camp in the same courageous spirit in which you defended your
                        own." <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> They were delighted to hear this
                        new plan from their new general, and the more daring it was the more it
                        pleased them. The rest of the day was spent in getting their arms ready and
                        in looking after themselves. At the fourth watch they began to move. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The other Carthaginian forces were about
                        six miles beyond the camp nearest to the Romans. Between them lay a valley
                        thickly wooded, and on some ground about half-way through the wood a Roman
                        cohort, adopting Punic tactics, concealed themselves with some cavalry.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the road was thus occupied
                        midway, the rest of the force marched in silence to the enemy nearest to
                        them, and as there were no outposts in front of the gates and no guard
                        mounted they penetrated without any opposition into the camp just as if they
                        were entering their own. Then the signals were sounded and the battle shout
                        raised. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some slew the enemy while half
                        asleep, others threw firebrands on to their huts, which were thatched with
                        dry straw, others held the gates to intercept the fugitives. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The fire, the shouting, and the slaughter, all
                        combined, bereft the enemy almost of their senses and prevented them from
                        either hearing one another on taking any measures for their safety.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Without arms themselves they fell
                        amongst troops of armed men; some rushed to the gates, others, finding the
                        ways blocked, sprang over the rampart, and all who escaped in this way fled
                        at once to <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the other camp, where they
                        were met by the cohort and the cavalry running out from their concealment
                        and all cut down to a man. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Even if any one
                        had escaped from the carnage the Romans, after taking that camp, ran on so
                        swiftly to the other one that no one could get there before them to announce
                        the disaster. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they got to the second camp they
                        found neglect and disorder everywhere, partly owing to its greater distance
                        from them and partly because some of the defenders had dispersed in quest of
                        fodder and wood and plunder. At the outposts the arms were actually piled,
                        the soldiers, all unarmed, were sitting and lying about on the ground or
                        walking up and down in front of the gates and rampart. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> In this state of careless disorder they were assailed
                        by the Romans who were tired by their recent fighting and flushed with
                        victory. It was impossible to hold the gates against them, and once within
                        the gates a desperate battle began. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At
                        the first alarm there was a rush from all parts of the camp, and there would
                        have been a long and obstinate struggle if the Carthaginians had not seen in
                        the blood-stained shields of the Romans plain traces of the former contest,
                        which filled them with dismay and terror. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        They all turned and fled wherever they could find the way open to escape,
                        and all but those who had been already killed were driven out of the camp.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> So in a night and a day two of the
                        enemies' camps had been carried under the leadership of L. Marcius.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> According to Claudius, who translated
                        the annals of Acilius from Greek into Latin, as many as 37,000 of the enemy
                        were slain, 1830 being prisoners, besides an immense amount of plunder. The
                        latter included a silver shield one hundred and thirty-seven pounds in
                        weight, together with a statuette of Hasdrubal. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Valerius Antias relates that only Mago's camp was
                        taken, when the enemy lost 7000 killed; in the other battle when the Romans
                        made the sortie and fought with Hasdrubal 10,000 were killed and 4380 made
                        prisoners. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Piso says that 5000 men were
                        killed when Mago was ambushed while recklessly pursuing our men. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> All these authors dwell upon the greatness of
                        Marcius, and they exaggerate the glory he really won by describing a
                        supernatural incident. Whilst he was addressing his troops they say that a
                        flame shot from his head, without his being aware of it, to the great terror
                        of the soldiers standing round. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> It is
                        also stated that there was in the temple on the Capitol before it was burnt
                        a shield called "the Marcian" with a statuette of Hasdrubal, as memorials of
                        his victory. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> For some time after this,
                        matters were quiet in Spain, neither side after the defeats they had
                        suffered being anxious to risk a decisive action. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were occurring in
                        Spain, Marcellus, after the capture of Syracuse, settled the affairs of
                        Sicily with so much justice and integrity as to enhance not merely his own
                        reputation but the greatness and dignity of Rome as well. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He removed to Rome the ornaments of the city, the
                        statues and pictures in which Syracuse abounded; they were, it is true,
                        spoils taken from the enemy and acquired by the laws of war, but that was
                        the beginning of our admiration for Greek works of art, which has led to the
                        present reckless spoliation of every kind of treasure, sacred and profane
                        alike. This has at last recoiled upon the gods of Rome, upon that temple
                        especially which Marcellus so splendidly adorned. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> For the shrines near the Capena Gate, which Marcellus
                        dedicated, used to be visited by strangers on account of the very beautiful
                        specimens of that class of ornament; but very few are to be seen today.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whilst Marcellus was settling the
                        affairs of Sicily, deputations from nearly all the communities in the island
                        visited him. The treatment they received varied with their circumstances.
                        Those who had not revolted or had returned to our friendship prior to the
                        capture of Syracuse were welcomed and honoured as loyal allies; those who
                        after its capture had surrendered through fear, had to accept the terms
                        which the victor imposes on the vanquished. The Romans, however, had
                        considerable remnants of the war still on their hands round Agrigentum.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There were still left in the field the
                        generals Epicydes and Hanno who had commanded in the late war, and a fresh
                        general who had been sent in place of Hippocrates by Hannibal, a man of
                        Libyphoeniclan nationality, called Hippacritanus-his fellow-countrymen
                        called him Muttines-a man of energy and enterprise, who had had a thorough
                        military training under that master of war, Hannibal. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He was furnished by Epicydes and Hanno with a force of
                        Numidians, and with these troopers he committed such extensive depredations
                        on the lands of those who were hostile and was so active in keeping his
                        friends loyal by always bringing them help at the right moment, <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> that in a short time all Sicily had heard of
                        him and there was no one from whom the supporters of Carthage expected
                        greater things. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Up to that time Epicydes and Hanno had
                        been compelled to keep within the fortifications of Agrigentum; now,
                        however, in a spirit of self-confidence quite as much as in compliance with
                        the advice of Muttines, they ventured outside and fixed their camp by the
                        Himera. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> No sooner was this reported to
                        Marcellus than he promptly moved up and encamped about four miles from the
                        enemy with the intention of waiting for any action he might take. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> But no time was allowed him for either delay or
                        deliberation; Muttines crossed the river and charged his enemy's outposts,
                        creating the greatest terror and confusion. The next day there was almost a
                        regular battle and he drove the Romans within their lines. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Then he was recalled by tidings of a mutiny which had
                        broken out amongst the Numidians in Hanno's camp. Nearly three hundred of
                        them had gone off to Heraclea Minoa. When he left the camp to reason with
                        them and recall them, he is said to have most earnestly advised the generals
                        not to engage the enemy in his absence. They both resented this; more
                        especially Hanno who had long been jealous of Muttines' reputation.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> "Is Muttines," he exclaimed, "to
                        dictate to me; a low-born African to give orders to a Carthaginian general
                        bearing the commission of the senate and people? <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> "Epicydes wished to wait, but he brought him over to
                        his view, that they should cross the river and offer battle, for, he argued,
                        if they waited for Muttines, and then fought a successful action, he would
                        undoubtedly get all the credit for it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus was of course intensely
                        indignant at the idea of the man who had turned Hannibal, flushed with his
                        victory at Cannae, aside from Nola now giving way before enemies whom he had
                        defeated by sea and land, and he ordered his men to seize their arms at once
                        and march out in order of battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whilst
                        he was forming his lines, ten Numidians from the opposing army galloped up
                        to him at full speed with the announcement that their countrymen would take
                        no part in the fighting, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> first because
                        they sympathised with the three hundred mutineers who had gone to Heraclea,
                        and secondly because they saw that their leader had been got rid of on the
                        very day of battle by generals who wanted to cast a cloud on his reputation.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Deceitful as that nation usually is,
                        they kept their promise on that occasion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The news flew quickly through the ranks that the cavalry of whom they stood
                        in greatest fear had left the enemy in the lurch, and their courage rose
                        accordingly. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The enemy, on the other hand,
                        were in a great state of alarm because, not only were they losing the
                        support of their strongest arm, but there was a chance of their being
                        attacked by their own cavalry. So there was not much of a conflict, the
                        action was decided by the first battle shout and charge. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> When the opposing lines met, the Numidians were
                        standing quietly on the wings; when they saw their own side turn tail they
                        joined them in their flight for a short distance, but when they saw them
                        making in all haste for Agrigentum they dispersed to all the neighbouring
                        cities for fear of having to stand a siege. Several thousand men were killed
                        and eight elephants captured. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This was the
                        last battle Marcellus fought in Sicily. After his victory he returned to
                        Syracuse. As the year was now almost at an end, the senate decreed
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> that the praetor P. Cornelius should
                        send instructions to the consuls at Capua for one of them, if they approved,
                        to come to Rome to appoint new magistrates while Hannibal was at a distance
                        and no very critical operations were going on at Capua. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> After receiving the despatch the consuls came to a
                        mutual arrangement that Claudius should conduct the elections and Fulvius
                        remain at Capua. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The new consuls were Cn.
                        Fulvius Centimalus and P. Sulpicius Galba, the son of Servius, a man who had
                        never before filled a curule office. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        election of praetors followed; those elected were L. Cornelius Lentulus, M.
                        Cornelius Cethegus, C. Sulpicius, and C. Calpurnius Piso. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Piso took over the urban jurisdiction, Sicily was
                        allotted to Sulpicius, Apulia to Cethegus, Sardinia to Lentulus. The consuls
                        had their commands extended for another year. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
