<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 21</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="book">
                <head>From Saguntum to the Trebia</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> I consider myself at liberty to commence
                        what is only a section of my history with a prefatory remark such as most
                        writers have placed at the very beginning of their works, namely, that the
                        war I am about to describe is the most memorable of any that have ever been
                        waged, I mean the war which the Carthaginians, under Hannibal's leadership,
                        waged with Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> No states, no nations
                        ever met in arms greater in strength or richer in resources; these Powers
                        themselves had never before been in so high a state of efficiency or better
                        prepared to stand the strain of a long war; they were no strangers to each
                        other's tactics after their experience in the first Punic War; and so
                        variable were the fortunes and so doubtful the issue of the war that those
                        who were ultimately victorious were in the earlier stages brought nearest to
                        ruin. And yet, great as was their strength, the hatred they felt towards
                        each other was almost greater. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans
                        were furious with indignation because the vanquished had dared to take the
                        offensive against their conquerors; the Carthaginians bitterly resented what
                        they regarded as the tyrannical and rapacious conduct of Rome. The prime
                        author of the war was Hamilcar. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There was
                        a story widely current that when, after bringing the African War to a close,
                        he was offering sacrifices before transporting his army to Spain, the boy
                        Hannibal, nine years old, was coaxing his father to take him with him, and
                        his father led him up to the altar and made him swear with his hand laid on
                        the victim that as soon as he possibly could he would show himself the enemy
                        of Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The loss of Sicily and Sardinia
                        vexed the proud spirit of the man, for he felt that the cession of Sicily
                        had been made hastily in a spirit of despair, and that Sardinia had been
                        filched by the Romans during the troubles in Africa, who, not content with
                        seizing it, had imposed an indemnity as well. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Smarting under these wrongs, he made it
                        quite clear from his conduct of the African War which followed immediately
                        upon the conclusion of peace with Rome, and from the way in which he
                        strengthened and extended the rule of Carthage during the nine years' war
                        with Spain, that he was meditating a far greater war than any he was
                        actually engaged in, and that had he lived <milestone n="2??" unit="section"
                        /> longer it would have been under his command that the Carthaginians
                        effected the invasion of Italy, which they actually carried out under
                        Hannibal. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The death of Hamilcar, occurring
                        as it did most opportunely, and the tender years of Hannibal delayed the
                        war. Hasdrubal, coming between father and son, held the supreme power for
                        eight years. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He is said to have become a
                        favourite of Hamilcar's owing to his personal beauty as a boy; afterwards he
                        displayed talents of a very different order, and became his son-in-law.
                        Through this connection he was placed in power by the influence of the
                        Barcine party, which was unduly preponderant with the soldiers and the
                        common people, but his elevation was utterly against the wishes of the
                        nobles. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Trusting to policy rather than to
                        arms, he did more to extend the empire of Carthage by forming connections
                        with the petty chieftains and winning over new tribes by making friends of
                        their leading men than by force of arms or by war. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> But peace brought him no security. A barbarian whose
                        master he had put to death murdered him in broad daylight, and when seized
                        by the bystanders he looked as happy as though he had escaped. Even when put
                        to the torture, his delight at the success of his attempt mastered his pain
                        and his face wore a smiling expression. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Owing to the marvellous tact he had shown in winning over the tribes and
                        incorporating them into his dominions, the Romans had renewed the treaty
                        with Hasdrubal. Under its terms, the River Ebro was to form the boundary
                        between the two empires, and Saguntum, occupying an intermediate position
                        between them, was to be a free city. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was no hesitation shown in filling
                        his place. The soldiers led the way by bringing the young Hannibal forthwith
                        to the palace and proclaiming him their commander-in-chief amidst universal
                        applause. Their action was followed by the plebs. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst little more than a boy, Hasdrubal had written to
                        invite Hannibal to come to him in Spain, and the matter had actually been
                        discussed in the senate. The Barcines wanted Hannibal to become familiar
                        with military service; Hanno, the leader of the opposite party, resisted
                        this. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> "Hasdrubal's request," he said,
                        "appears a reasonable one, and yet I do not think we ought to grant it" This
                        paradoxical utterance aroused the attention of the whole senate. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> He continued: "The youthful beauty which
                        Hasdrubal surrendered to Hannibal's father he considers he has a fair claim
                        to ask for in return from the son. It ill becomes us, however, to habituate
                        our youths to the lust of our commanders, by way of military training.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Are we afraid that it will be too long
                        before Hamilcar's son surveys the extravagant power and the pageant of
                        royalty which his father assumed, and that there will be undue delay in our
                        becoming the slaves of the despot to whose son-in-law our armies have been
                        bequeathed as though they were his patrimony? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> I, for my part, consider that this youth ought to be
                        kept at home and taught to live in obedience to the laws and the magistrates
                        on an equality with his fellow-citizens; if not, this small fire will some
                        day or other kindle a vast conflagration." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hanno's proposal received but slight
                        support, though almost all the best men in the council were with him, but as
                        usual, numbers carried the day against reason. No sooner had Hannibal landed
                        in Spain than he became a favourite with the whole army. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The veterans thought they saw Hamilcar restored to them
                        as he was in his youth; they saw the same determined expression the same
                        piercing eyes, the same cast of features. He soon showed, however, that it
                        was not his father's memory that helped him most to win the affections of
                        the army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Never was there a character more
                        capable of the two tasks so opposed to each other of commanding and obeying;
                        you could not easily make out whether the army or its general were more
                        attached to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whenever courage and
                        resolution were needed Hasdrubal never cared to entrust the command to any
                        one else; and there was no leader in whom the soldiers placed more
                        confidence or under whom they showed more daring. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He was fearless in exposing himself to danger and
                        perfectly self-possessed in the presence of danger. No amount of exertion
                        could cause him either bodily or mental fatigue; he was equally indifferent
                        to heat and cold; his eating and drinking were measured by the needs of
                        nature, not by appetite; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> his hours of
                        sleep were not determined by day or night, whatever time was not taken up
                        with active duties <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> was given to sleep
                        and rest, but that rest was not wooed on a soft couch or in silence, men
                        often saw him lying on the ground amongst the sentinels and outposts,
                        wrapped in his military cloak. His dress was in no way superior to that of
                        his comrades; what did make him conspicuous were his arms and horses.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was by far the foremost both of the
                        cavalry and the infantry, the first to enter the fight and the last to leave
                        the field. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But these great merits were
                        matched by great vices-inhuman cruelty, a perfidy worse than Punic, an utter
                        absence of truthfulness, reverence, fear of the gods, respect for oaths,
                        sense of religion. Such was his character, a compound of virtues and vices.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For three years he served under
                        Hasdrubal, and during the whole time he never lost an opportunity of gaining
                        by practice or observation the experience necessary for one who was to be a
                        great leader of men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From the day when he was proclaimed
                        commander-in-chief, he seemed to regard Italy as his assigned field of
                        action, and war with Rome as a duty imposed upon him. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Feeling that he ought not to delay operations, lest
                        some accident should overtake him as in the case of his father and
                        afterwards of Hasdrubal, he decided to attack the Saguntines. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> As an attack on them would inevitably set the
                        arms of Rome in motion, he began by invading the Olcades, a tribe who were
                        within the boundaries but not under the dominion of Carthage. He wished to
                        make it appear that Saguntum was not his immediate object, but that he was
                        drawn into a war with her by the force of circumstances, by the conquest,
                        that is, of all her neighbours and the annexation of their territory.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Cartala, a wealthy city and the
                        capital of the tribe, was taken by storm and sacked; the smaller cities,
                        fearing a similar fate, capitulated and agreed to pay an indemnity. His
                        victorious army enriched with plunder was marched into winter quarters in
                        New Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here, by a lavish
                        distribution of the spoils and the punctual discharge of all arrears of pay,
                        he secured the allegiance of his own people and of the allied contingents. </p>
                    <p> At the beginning of spring he extended his operations to the Vaccaei, and
                        two of their cities, Arbocala and Hermandica, were taken by assault.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Arbocala held out for a considerable
                        time, owing to the courage and numbers of its defenders; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> the fugitives from Hermandica joined hands with those
                        of the Olcades who had abandoned their country-this tribe had been
                        subjugated the previous year-and together they stirred up the Carpetani to
                        war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Not far from the Tagus an attack was
                        made upon Hannibal as he was returning from his expedition against the
                        Vaccaei, and his army, laden as it was with plunder, was thrown into some
                        confusion. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Hannibal declined battle and
                        fixed his camp by the side of the river; as soon as there was quiet and
                        silence amongst the enemy, he forded the stream. His entrenchments had been
                        carried just far enough to allow room for the enemy to cross over, and he
                        decided to attack them during their passage of the river. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He instructed his cavalry to wait until they had
                        actually entered the water and then to attack them; his forty elephants he
                        stationed on the bank. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Carpetani
                        together with the contingents of the Olcades and Vaccaei numbered altogether
                        100,000 men, an irresistible force had they been fighting on level ground.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their innate fearlessness, the
                        confidence inspired by their numbers, their belief that the enemy's retreat
                        was due to fear, all made them look on victory as certain, and the river as
                        the only obstacle to it. Without any word of command having been given, they
                        raised a universal shout and plunged, each man straight in front of him,
                        into the river. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A huge force of cavalry
                        descended from the opposite bank, and the two bodies met in mid-stream. The
                        struggle was anything but an equal one. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        The infantry, feeling their footing insecure, even where the river was
                        fordable, could have been ridden down even by unarmed horsemen, whereas the
                        cavalry, with their bodies and weapons free and their horses steady even in
                        the midst of the current, could fight at close quarters or not, as they
                        chose. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A large proportion were swept down
                        the river, some were carried by cross currents to the other side where the
                        enemy were, and were trampled to death by the elephants. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Those in the rear thought it safest to return to their
                        own side, and began to collect together as well as their fears allowed them,
                        but before they had time to recover themselves Hannibal entered the river
                        with his infantry in battle order and drove them in flight from the bank.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> He followed up his victory by laying
                        waste their fields, and in a few days was able to receive the submission of
                        the Carpetani There was no part of the country beyond the Ebro which did not
                        now belong to the Carthaginians, with the exception of Saguntum. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> War had not been formally declared against
                        this city, but there were already grounds for war. The seeds of quarrel were
                        being sown amongst her neighbours, especially amongst the Turdetani.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the man who had sown the seed
                        showed himself ready to aid and abet the quarrel, and his object plainly was
                        not to refer the question to arbitration, but to appeal to force, the
                        Saguntines sent a deputation to Rome to beg for help in a war which was
                        inevitably approaching. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls for
                        the time being were P. Cornelius Scipio and Tiberius Sempronius Longus.
                        After introducing the envoys they invited the senate to declare its opinion
                        as to what policy should be adopted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It
                        was decided that commissioners should be sent to Spain to investigate the
                        circumstances, and if they considered it necessary they were to warn
                        Hannibal not to interfere with the Saguntines, who were allies of Rome; then
                        they were to cross over to Africa and lay before the Carthaginian council
                        the complaints which they had made. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But
                        before the commission was despatched news came that the siege of Saguntum
                        had, to every one's surprise, actually commenced. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The whole position of affairs required to be
                        reconsidered by the senate; some were for assigning Spain and Africa as
                        separate fields of action for the two consuls, and thought that the war
                        ought to be prosecuted by land and sea; others were for confining the war
                        solely to Hannibal in Spain; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> others again
                        were of opinion that such an immense task ought not to be entered upon
                        hastily, and that they ought to await the return of the commission from
                        Spain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This latter view seemed the safest
                        and was adopted, and the commissioners, P. Valerius Flaccus and Q. Baebius
                        Tamphilus, were despatched without further delay to Hannibal. If he refused
                        to abandon hostilities they were to proceed to Carthage to demand the
                        surrender of the general to answer for his breach of treaty. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these proceedings in Rome the siege
                        of Saguntum was being pressed with the utmost vigour. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> That city was by far the most wealthy of all beyond the
                        Ebro; it was situated about a mile from the sea. It is said to have been
                        founded by settlers from the island of Zacynthus, with an admixture of
                        Rutulians from Ardea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In a short time,
                        however, it had attained to great prosperity, partly through its land and
                        sea-borne commerce, partly through the rapid increase of its population, and
                        also through the maintenance of a high standard of political integrity which
                        led it to act with a loyalty towards its allies that brought about its ruin.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After carrying his ravages everywhere
                        throughout the territory, Hannibal attacked the city from three separate
                        points. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was an angle of the
                        fortifications which looked down on a more open and level descent than the
                        rest of the ground surrounding the city, and here he decided to bring up his
                        vineae to allow the battering rams to be placed against the walls.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But although the ground to a
                        considerable distance from the walls was sufficiently level to admit of the
                        vineae being brought up, they found when they had succeeded in doing this
                        that they made no progress. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A huge tower
                        overlooked the place, and the wall, being here more open to attack, had been
                        carried to a greater height than the rest of the fortifications. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> As the position was one of especial danger, so
                        the resistance offered by a picked body of defenders was of the most
                        resolute character. At first they confined themselves to keeping the enemy
                        back by the discharge of missiles and making it impossible for them to
                        continue their operations in safety. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As
                        time went on, however, their weapons no longer flashed on the walls or from
                        the tower, they ventured on a sortie and attacked the outposts and siege
                        works of the enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In these irregular
                        encounters the Carthaginians lost nearly as many men as the Saguntines.
                        Hannibal himself, approaching the wall somewhat incautiously, fell with a
                        severe wound in his thigh from a javelin, and such was the confusion and
                        dismay that ensued that the vineae and siege works were all but abandoned.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For a few days, until the general's wound
                        was healed, there was a blockade rather than an active siege, and during
                        this interval, though there was a respite from fighting, the construction of
                        siege works and approaches went on uninterruptedly. When the fighting was
                        resumed it was fiercer than ever. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In spite
                        of the difficulties of the ground the vineae were advanced and the battering
                        rams placed against the walls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        Carthaginians had the superiority in numbers-there were said to have been
                        150,000 fighting men-whilst the defenders, obliged to keep watch and ward
                        everywhere, were dissipating their strength and finding their numbers
                        unequal to the task. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The walls were now
                        being pounded by the rams, and in many places had been shaken down.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> One part where a continuous fall had
                        taken place laid the city open; three towers in succession, and the whole of
                        the wall between them fell with a tremendous crash. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The Carthaginians looked upon the town as already
                        captured after that fall, and both sides rushed through the breach as though
                        the wall had only served to protect them from each other. There was nothing
                        of the desultory fighting which goes on when cities are stormed, as each
                        side gets an opportunity of attacking the other. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The two bodies of combatants confronted one another in
                        the space between the ruined wall and the houses of the city in as regular
                        formation as though they had been in an open field. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> On the one side there was the courage of hope, on the
                        other the courage of despair. The Carthaginians believed that with a little
                        effort on their part the city would be theirs; the Saguntines opposed their
                        bodies as a shield for their fatherland now stripped of its walls; not a man
                        relaxed his foothold for fear of letting an enemy in through the spot which
                        he had left open. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So the hotter and closer
                        the fighting became the greater grew the number of wounded, for no missile
                        fell ineffectively amongst the crowded ranks. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The missile used by the Saguntines was the phalarica, a
                        javelin with a shaft smooth and round up to the head, which, as in the
                        pilum, was an iron point of square section. The shaft was wrapped in tow and
                        then smeared with pitch; the iron head was three feet long and capable of
                        penetrating armour and body alike. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Even
                        if it only stuck in the shield and did not reach the body it was a most
                        formidable weapon, for when it was discharged <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> with the tow set on fire the flame was fanned to a
                        fiercer heat by its passage through the air, and it forced the soldier to
                        throw away his shield and left him defenceless against the sword thrusts
                        which followed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The conflict had now gone on for a
                        considerable time without any advantage to either side; the courage of the
                        Saguntines was rising as they found themselves keeping up an unhoped-for
                        resistance, whilst the Carthaginians, unable to conquer, were beginning to
                        look upon themselves as defeated. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Suddenly
                        the defenders, raising their battle-shout, forced the enemy back to the
                        debris of the ruined wall; there, stumbling and in disorder, they were
                        forced still further back and finally driven in rout and flight to their
                        camp. Meantime it was announced that envoys had arrived from Rome.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal sent messengers down to the
                        harbour to meet them and inform them that it would be unsafe for them to
                        advance any further through so many wild tribes now in arms, and also that
                        Hannibal in the present critical position of affairs had no time to receive
                        embassies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was quite certain that if
                        they were not admitted they would go to Carthage. He therefore forestalled
                        them by sending messengers with a letter addressed to the heads of the
                        Barcine party, to warn his supporters and prevent the other side from making
                        any concessions to Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The result was that, beyond being received
                        and heard by the Carthaginian senate, the embassy found its mission a
                        failure. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hanno alone, against the whole
                        senate, spoke in favour of observing the treaty, and his speech was listened
                        to in silence out of respect to his personal authority, not because his
                        hearers approved of his sentiments. He appealed to them in the name of the
                        gods, who are the witnesses and arbiters of treaties, not to provoke a war
                        with Rome in addition to the one with Saguntum. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> "I urged you," he said, "and warned you not to send
                        Hamilcar's son to the army. That man's spirit, that man's offspring cannot
                        rest; as long as any single representative of the blood and name of Barca
                        survives our treaty with Rome will never remain unimperilled. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> You have sent to the army, as though supplying
                        fuel to the fire, a young man who is consumed with a passion for sovereign
                        power, and who recognises that the only way to it lies in passing his life
                        surrounded by armed legions and perpetually stirring up fresh wars. It is
                        you, therefore, who have fed this fire which is now scorching you.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Your armies are investing Saguntum,
                        which by the terms of the treaty they are forbidden to approach; before long
                        the legions of Rome will invest Carthage, led by the same generals under the
                        same divine guidance under which they avenged our breach of treaty
                        obligations in the late war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Are you
                        strangers to the enemy, to yourselves, to the fortunes of each nation? That
                        worthy commander of yours refused to allow ambassadors who came from allies,
                        on behalf of allies, to enter his camp, and set at naught the law of
                        nations. Those men, repulsed from a place to which even an enemy's envoys
                        are not refused access, have come to us; they ask for the satisfaction which
                        the treaty prescribes; they demand the surrender of the guilty party in
                        order that the State may clear itself from all taint of guilt. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The slower they are to take action, the longer
                        they are in commencing war, so much the more persistence and determination,
                        I fear, will they show when war has begun. Remember the Aegates and Eryx,
                        and all you had to go through for four-and-twenty years. This boy was not
                        commanding then, but his father, Hamilcar-a second Mars as his friends would
                        have us believe. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But we broke the treaty
                        then as we are breaking it now; we did not keep our hands off Tarentum or,
                        which is the same thing, off Italy then any more than we are keeping our
                        hands off Saguntum now, and so gods and men combined to defeat us, and
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the question in dispute, namely,
                        which nation had broken the treaty, was settled by the issue of the war,
                        which, like an impartial judge, left the victory on the side which was in
                        the right. It is against Carthage that Hannibal is now bringing up his
                        vineae and towers, it is Carthage whose walls he is shaking with his
                        battering rams. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The ruins of
                        Saguntum-would that I might prove a false prophet-will fall on our heads,
                        and the war which was begun with Saguntum will have to be carried on with
                        Rome. </p>
                    <p> "'Shall we then surrender Hannibal?' some one will say. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> I am quite aware that as regards him my advice will
                        have little weight, owing to my differences with his father, but whilst I
                        was glad to hear of Hamilcar's death, for if he were alive we should already
                        be involved in war with Rome, I feel nothing but loathing and detestation
                        for this youth, the mad firebrand who is kindling this war. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Not only do I hold that he ought to be
                        surrendered as an atonement for the broken treaty, but even if no demand for
                        his surrender were made I consider that he ought to be deported to the
                        farthest corner of the earth, exiled to some spot from which no tidings of
                        him, no mention of his name, could reach us, and where it would be
                        impossible for him to disturb the welfare and tranquillity of our State.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This then is what I propose: 'That a
                        commission be at once despatched to Rome to inform the senate of our
                        compliance with their demands, and a second to Hannibal ordering him to
                        withdraw his army from Saguntum and then surrendering him to the Romans in
                        accordance with the terms of the treaty, and I also propose that a third
                        body of commissioners be sent to make reparation to the Saguntines.'" </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hanno sat down no one deemed it
                        necessary to make any reply, so completely was the senate, as a body, on the
                        side of Hannibal. They accused Hanno of speaking in a tone of more
                        uncompromising hostility than Flaccus Valerius, the Roman envoy, had
                        assumed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The reply which it was decided to
                        make to the Roman demands was that the war was started by the Saguntines not
                        by Hannibal, and that the Roman people would commit an act of injustice if
                        they took the part of the Saguntines against their ancient allies, the
                        Carthaginians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans were
                        wasting time in despatching commissioners, things were quiet round Saguntum.
                        Hannibal's men were worn out with the fighting and the labours of the siege,
                        and after placing detachments on guard over the vineae and other military
                        engines, he gave his army a few days' rest. He employed this interval in
                        stimulating the courage of his men by exasperating them against the enemy,
                        and firing them by the prospect of rewards. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> After he had given out in the presence of his assembled troops that the
                        plunder of the city would go to them, they were all in such a state of
                        excitement that had the signal been given then and there it seemed
                        impossible for anything to withstand them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        As for the Saguntines, though they had a respite from fighting for some
                        days, neither meeting attacks nor making any, they worked at their defences
                        so continuously by day and night that they completed a fresh wall at the
                        place where the fall of the former wall had laid the town open. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The assault was recommenced with greater
                        vigour than ever. In every direction confused shouts and clamour resounded,
                        so that it was difficult to ascertain where to render assistance most
                        promptly or where it was most needed. Hannibal was present in person to
                        encourage his men, who were bringing up a tower on rollers which overtopped
                        all the fortifications of the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Catapults and ballistae had been put in position on each of the stories, and
                        after it had been brought up to the walls it swept them clear of the
                        defenders. Seizing his opportunity, Hannibal told off about 500 African
                        troops to undermine the wall with pick-axes, an easy task, as the stones
                        were not fixed with cement but with layers of mud between the courses in the
                        ancient fashion of construction. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> More of
                        it consequently fell than had been dug away, and through the gaping ruin the
                        columns of armed warriors marched into the city. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> They seized some high ground, and after massing their
                        catapults and ballistae there they enclosed it with a wall so as to have a
                        fortified position actually within the city which could dominate it like a
                        citadel. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Saguntines on their side
                        carried an inside wall round the portion of the city not yet captured. Both
                        sides kept up their fortifying and fighting with the utmost energy, but by
                        having to defend the interior portion of the city the Saguntines were
                        continually reducing its dimensions. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In
                        addition to this there was a growing scarcity of everything as the siege was
                        prolonged, and the anticipations of outside help were becoming fainter; the
                        Romans, their one hope, were so far away, whilst all immediately round them
                        was in the hands of the enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For a few
                        days their drooping spirits were revived by the sudden departure of Hannibal
                        on an expedition against the Oretani and the Carpetani. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The rigorous way in which troops were being levied in
                        these two tribes had created great excitement, and they had kept the
                        officers who were superintending the levy practically prisoners. A general
                        revolt was feared, but the unexpected swiftness of Hannibal's movements took
                        them by surprise and they abandoned their hostile attitude. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The attack on Saguntum was not slackened;
                        Maharbal, the son of Himilco, whom Hannibal had left in command, carried on
                        operations with such energy that the general's absence was not felt by
                        either friends or foes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He fought several
                        successful actions, and with the aid of three battering rams brought down a
                        considerable portion of the wall, and on Hannibal's return showed him the
                        place all strewn with the newly-fallen wall. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> The army was at once led to an assault on the citadel; a desperate fight
                        began, with heavy losses on both sides, and a part of the citadel was
                        captured. Attempts were now made in the direction of peace, though with but
                        faint hopes of success. Two men undertook the task, Alco, a Saguntine, and
                        Alorcus, a Spaniard. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Alco, thinking that
                        his prayers might have some effect, crossed over without the knowledge of
                        the Saguntines to Hannibal at night. When he found that he gained nothing by
                        his tears, and that the conditions offered were such as a victor exasperated
                        by resistance would insist upon, harsh and severe, he laid aside the
                        character of a pleader and remained with the enemy as a deserter, alleging
                        that any one who advocated peace on such terms would be put to death.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The conditions were that restitution
                        should be made to the Turdetani, all the gold and silver should be delivered
                        up, and the inhabitants should depart with one garment each and take up
                        their abode wherever the Carthaginians should order them. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As Alco insisted that the Saguntines would not accept
                        peace on these terms, Alorcus, convinced, as he said, that when everything
                        else has gone courage also goes, undertook to mediate a peace on those
                        conditions. At that time he was one of Hannibal's soldiers, but he was
                        recognised as a guest friend by the city of Saguntum. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He started on his mission, gave up his weapon openly to
                        the guard, crossed the lines, and was at his request conducted to the
                        praetor of Saguntum. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A crowd, drawn from
                        all classes of society, soon gathered, and after a way had been cleared
                        through the press, Alorcus was admitted to an audience of the senate. He
                        addressed them in the following terms: </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "If your fellow-townsman, Alco, had shown
                        the same courage in bringing back to you the terms on which Hannibal will
                        grant peace that he showed in going to Hannibal to beg for peace, this
                        journey of mine would have been unnecessary. I have not come to you either
                        as an advocate for Hannibal or as a deserter. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> But as he has remained with the enemy either through
                        your fault or his own-his own if his fears were only feigned, yours if those
                        who report what is true have to answer for their lives-I have come to you
                        out of regard to the old ties of hospitality which have so long subsisted
                        between us, that you may not be left in ignorance of the fact that there do
                        exist terms on which you can secure peace and the safety of your lives.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Now, that it is for your sake alone
                        and not on behalf of any one else that I say what I am saying before you is
                        proved by the fact that as long as you had the strength to maintain a
                        successful resistance, and as long as you had any hopes of help from Rome, I
                        never breathed a word about making peace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        But now that you have no longer anything to hope for from Rome, now that
                        neither your arms nor your walls suffice to protect you, I bring you a peace
                        forced upon you by necessity rather than recommended by the fairness of its
                        conditions. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the hopes, faint as they
                        are, of peace rest upon your accepting as conquered men the terms which
                        Hannibal as conqueror imposes and not looking upon what is taken from you as
                        a positive loss, since everything is at the victor's mercy, but regarding
                        what is left to you as a free gift from him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> The city, most of which he has laid in ruins, the whole of which he has
                        all but captured, he takes from you; your fields and lands he leaves you;
                        and he will assign you a site where you can build a new town. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> He orders all the gold and silver, both that
                        belonging to the State and that owned by private individuals, to be brought
                        to him; your persons and those of your wives and children he preserves
                        inviolate on condition that you consent to leave Saguntum with only two
                        garments apiece and without arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These
                        are the demands of your victorious enemy, and heavy and bitter as they are,
                        your miserable plight urges you to accept them. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> I am not without hope that when everything has passed
                        into his power he will relax some of these conditions, but I consider that
                        even as they are you ought to submit to them rather than permit yourselves
                        to be butchered and your wives and children seized and carried off before
                        your eyes." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A large crowd had gradually collected to
                        listen to the speaker, and the popular Assembly had become mingled with the
                        senate, when without a moment's warning the leading citizens withdrew before
                        any reply was given. They collected all the gold and silver from public and
                        private sources and brought it into the forum, where a fire had already been
                        kindled, and flung it into the flames, and most of them thereupon leaped
                        into the fire themselves. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The terror and
                        confusion which this occasioned throughout the city was heightened by the
                        noise of a tumult in the direction of the citadel. A tower after much
                        battering had fallen, and through the breach created by its fall a
                        Carthaginian cohort advanced to the attack and signalled to their commander
                        that the customary outposts and guards had disappeared and the city was
                        unprotected. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal thought that he
                        ought to seize the opportunity and act promptly. Attacking it with his full
                        strength, he took the place in a moment. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Orders had been given that all the adult males were to be put to death; a
                        cruel order, but under the circumstances inevitable, for whom would it have
                        been possible to spare when they either shut themselves up with their wives
                        and children and burnt their houses over their heads, or if they fought,
                        would not cease fighting till they were killed? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An enormous amount of booty was found in
                        the captured city. Although most of it had been deliberately destroyed by
                        the owners, and the enraged soldiers had observed hardly any distinctions of
                        age in the universal slaughter, whilst all the prisoners that were
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> taken were assigned to them, still,
                        it is certain that a considerable sum was realised by the sale of the goods
                        that were seized, and much valuable furniture and apparel was sent to
                        Carthage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some writers assert that
                        Saguntum was taken in the eighth month of the siege, and that Hannibal led
                        his force from there to New Carthage for the winter, his arrival in Italy
                        occurring five months later. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In this case
                        it is impossible for P. Cornelius and Ti. Sempronius to have been the
                        consuls to whom the Saguntine envoys were sent at the beginning of the siege
                        and who afterwards, whilst still in office, fought with Hannibal, one of
                        them at the Ticinus, both shortly afterwards at the Trebia. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Either all the incidents occurred within a much shorter
                        period or else it was the capture of Saguntum, not the beginning of the
                        siege, which occurred when those two entered upon office. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> For the battle of the Trebia cannot have fallen so late
                        as the year when Cn. Servilius and C. Flaminius were in office, because C.
                        Flaminius entered upon his consulship at Ariminum, his election taking place
                        under the consul Tiberius Sempronius, who came to Rome after the battle of
                        the Trebia to hold the consular elections, and, after they were over,
                        returned to his army in winter quarters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commissioners who had been sent to
                        Carthage, on their return to Rome, reported that everything breathed a
                        hostile spirit. Almost on the very day they returned the news arrived of the
                        fall of Saguntum, and such was the distress <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> of the senate at the cruel fate of their allies, such
                        was their feeling of shame at not having sent help to them, such their
                        exasperation against the Carthaginians and their alarm for the safety of the
                        State-for it seemed as though the enemy were already at their gates-that
                        they were in no mood for deliberating, shaken as they were by so many
                        conflicting emotions. There were sufficient grounds for alarm. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Never had they met a more active or a more
                        warlike enemy, and never had the Roman republic been so lacking in energy or
                        so unprepared for war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The operations
                        against the Sardinians, Corsicans, and Histrians, as well as those against
                        the Illyrians, had been more of an annoyance than a training for the
                        soldiers of Rome; whilst with the Gauls there had been desultory fighting
                        rather than regular warfare. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the
                        Carthaginians, a veteran enemy which for three-and-twenty years had seen
                        hard and rough service amongst the Spanish tribes, and had always been
                        victorious, trained under a general of exceptional ability, were now
                        crossing the Ebro fresh from the sack of a most wealthy city, and were
                        bringing with them all those Spanish tribes, eager for the fray. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> They would rouse the various Gaulish tribes, who
                        were always ready to take up arms; there would be the whole world to fight
                        against; the battleground would be Italy; the struggle would take place
                        before the walls of Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The seat of the campaigns had already been
                        decided; the consuls were now ordered to draw lots. Spain fell to Cornelius,
                        Africa to Sempronius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was resolved that
                        six legions should be raised for that year, the allies were to furnish such
                        contingents as the consuls should deem necessary, and as large a fleet as
                        possible was to be fitted out; 24,000 Roman infantry were called up and 1800
                        cavalry; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the allies contributed 40,000
                        infantry and 4400 cavalry, and a fleet of 220 ships of war and 20 light
                        galleys was launched. The question was then formally submitted to the
                        Assembly, Was it their will and pleasure that war should be declared against
                        the people of Carthage? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When this was
                        decided, a special service of intercession was conducted; the procession
                        marched through the streets of the city offering prayers at the various
                        temples that the gods would grant a happy and prosperous issue to the war
                        which the people of Rome had now ordered. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The forces were divided between the consuls in the following way: To
                        Sempronius two legions were assigned, each consisting of 4000 infantry and
                        300 cavalry, and 16,000 infantry and 1800 cavalry from the allied
                        contingents. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He was also provided with 160
                        warships and 12 light galleys. With this combined land and sea force he was
                        sent to Sicily, with instructions to cross over to Africa if the other
                        consul succeeded in preventing the Carthaginian from invading Italy.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cornelius, on the other hand, was
                        provided with a smaller force, as L. Manlius, the praetor, was himself being
                        despatched to Gaul with a fairly strong detachment. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Cornelius was weakest in his ships; he had only 60
                        warships, for it was never supposed that the enemy would come by sea or use
                        his navy for offensive purposes. His land force was made up of two Roman
                        legions, with their complement of cavalry, and 14,000 infantry from the
                        allies with 1600 cavalry. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The province of
                        Gaul1 was held by two Roman legions and 10,000 allied infantry with 600
                        Roman and 1000 allied cavalry. This force was ultimately employed in the
                        Punic War. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these preparations were completed,
                        the formalities necessary before entering upon war required that a
                        commission should be despatched to Carthage. Those selected were men of age
                        and experience-Q. Fabius, M. Livius, L. Aemilius, C. Licinius, and Q.
                        Baebius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were instructed to inquire
                        whether it was with the sanction of the government that Hannibal had
                        attacked Saguntum, and if, as seemed most probable, the Carthaginians should
                        admit that it was so and proceed to defend their action, then the Roman
                        envoys were to formally declare war upon Carthage. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as they had arrived in Carthage they appeared
                        before the senate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Q. Fabius had, in
                        accordance with his instructions, simply put the question as to the
                        responsibility of the government, when one of the members present said: "The
                        language of your previous deputation was peremptory enough when you demanded
                        the surrender of Hannibal on the assumption that he was attacking Saguntum
                        on his own authority, but your language now, so far at least, is less
                        provocative, though in effect more overbearing. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> For on that occasion it was Hannibal whose action you
                        denounced and whose surrender you demanded, now you are seeking to extort
                        from us a confession of <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> guilt and insist
                        upon obtaining instant satisfaction, as from men who admit they are in the
                        wrong. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I do not, however, consider that
                        the question is whether the attack on Saguntum was an act of public policy
                        or only that of a private citizen, but whether it was justified by
                        circumstances or not. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is for us to
                        inquire and take proceedings against a citizen when he has done anything on
                        his own authority; the only point for you to discuss is whether his action
                        was compatible with the terms of the treaty. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> Now, as you wish us to draw a distinction between what our generals do
                        with the sanction of the State and what they do on their own initiative, you
                        must remember that the treaty with us was made by your consul, C. Lutatius,
                        and whilst it contained provisions guarding the interests of the allies of
                        both nations, there was no such provision for the Saguntines, for they were
                        not your allies at the time. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But, you
                        will say, by the treaty concluded with Hasdrubal, the Saguntines are
                        exempted from attack. I shall meet that with your own arguments. You told us
                        that you refused to be bound by the treaty which your consul, C. Lutatius,
                        concluded with us, because it did not receive the authorisation of either
                        the senate or the Assembly. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A fresh
                        treaty was accordingly made by your government. Now, if no treaties have any
                        binding force for you unless they have been made with the authority of your
                        senate or by order of your Assembly, <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                        we, on our side, cannot possibly be bound by Hasdrubal's treaty, which he
                        made without our knowledge. Drop all allusions to Saguntum and the Ebro, and
                        speak out plainly what has long been secretly hatching in your minds."
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then the Roman, gathering up his
                        toga, said, "Here we bring you war and peace, take which you please."
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He was met by a defiant shout bidding
                        him give whichever he preferred, and when, letting the folds of his toga
                        fall, he said that he gave them war, they replied that they accepted war and
                        would carry it on in the same spirit in which they accepted it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This straightforward question and threat
                        of war seemed to be more consonant with the dignity of Rome than a wordy
                        argument about treaties; it seemed so previous to the destruction of
                        Saguntum, and still more so afterwards. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        For had it been a matter for argument, what ground was there for comparing
                        Hasdrubal's treaty with the earlier one of Lutatius? In the latter it was
                        expressly stated that it would only be of force if the people approved it,
                        whereas in Hasdrubal's treaty there was no such saving clause. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Besides, his treaty had been silently observed
                        for many years during his lifetime, and was so generally approved that, even
                        after its author's death, none of its articles were altered. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> But even if they took their stand upon the
                        earlier treaty-that of Lutatius-the Saguntines were sufficiently safeguarded
                        by the allies of both parties being exempted from hostile treatment, for
                        nothing was said about "the allies for the time being" or anything to
                        exclude "any who should be hereafter taken into alliance." <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> And since it was open to both parties to form fresh
                        alliances, who would think it a fair arrangement that none should be
                        received into alliance whatever their merits, or that when they had been
                        received they should not be loyally protected, on the understanding that the
                        allies of the Carthaginians should not be induced to revolt, or if they
                        deserted their allies on their own accord were not to be received into
                        alliance by the others? </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman envoys in accordance with their
                        instructions went on to Spain for the purpose of visiting the different
                        tribes and drawing them into alliance with Rome, or at least detaching them
                        from the Carthaginians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The first they
                        came to were the Borgusii, who were tired of Punic domination and gave them
                        a favourable reception, and their success here excited a desire for change
                        amongst many of the tribes beyond the Ebro. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> They came next to the Volciani, and the response they met with became
                        widely known throughout Spain and determined the rest of the tribes against
                        an alliance with Rome. This answer was given by the senior member of their
                        national council in the following terms: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        "Are you not ashamed, Romans, to ask us to form friendship with you in
                        preference to the Carthaginians, seeing how those who have done so have
                        suffered more through you, their allies, cruelly deserting them than through
                        any injury inflicted on them by the Carthaginians? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> I advise you to look for allies where the fall of
                        Saguntum has never been heard of; the nations of Spain see in the ruins of
                        Saguntum a sad and emphatic warning against putting any trust in alliances
                        with Rome." <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They were then peremptorily
                        ordered to quit the territory of the Volciani, and from that time none of
                        the councils throughout Spain gave them a more favourable reply. After this
                        fruitless mission in Spain they crossed over into Gaul. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Here a strange and appalling sight met
                        their eyes; the men attended the council fully armed, such was the custom of
                        the country. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the Romans, after
                        extolling the renown and courage of the Roman people and the greatness of
                        their dominion, asked the Gauls not to allow the Carthaginian invaders a
                        passage through their fields and cities, such <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> interruption and laughter broke out that the younger
                        men were with difficulty kept quiet by the magistrates and senior members of
                        the council. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They thought it a most stupid
                        and impudent demand to make, that the Gauls, in order to prevent the war
                        from spreading into Italy, should turn it against themselves and expose
                        their own lands to be ravaged instead of other people's. After quiet was
                        restored the envoys were informed that the Romans had rendered them no
                        service, nor had the Carthaginians done them any injury to make them take up
                        arms either on behalf of the Romans or against the <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> Carthaginians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the
                        other hand, they heard that men of their race were being expelled from
                        Italy, and made to pay tribute to Rome, and subjected to every other
                        indignity. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Their experience was the same
                        in all the other councils of Gaul, nowhere did they hear a kindly or even a
                        tolerably peaceable word till they reached Massilia. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> There all the facts which their allies had carefully
                        and honestly collected were laid before them; they were informed that the
                        interest of the Gauls had already been secured by Hannibal, but even he
                        would not find them very tractable, with their wild and untamable nature,
                        unless the chiefs were also won over with gold, a thing which as a nation
                        they were most eager to procure. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After
                        thus traversing Spain and the tribes of Gaul the envoys returned to Rome not
                        long after the consuls had left for their respective commands. They found
                        the whole City in a state of excitement; definite news had been received
                        that the Carthaginians had crossed the Ebro, and every one was looking
                        forward to war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the capture of Saguntum, Hannibal
                        withdrew into winter quarters at New Carthage. Information reached him there
                        of the proceedings at Rome and Carthage, and he learnt that he was not only
                        the general who was to conduct the war, but <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> also the sole person who was responsible for its
                        outbreak. As further delay would be most inexpedient, he sold and <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> distributed the rest of the plunder, and
                        calling together those of his soldiers who were of Spanish blood, he
                        addressed them as follows: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "I think,
                        soldiers, that you yourselves recognise that now that we have reduced all
                        the tribes in Spain we shall either have to bring our campaigns to an end
                        and disband our armies or else we must transfer our wars to other lands.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If we seek to win plunder and glory
                        from other nations, then these tribes will enjoy not only the blessings of
                        peace, but also the fruits of victory. Since, therefore, there await us
                        campaigns far from home, and it is uncertain when you will again see your
                        homes and all that is dear to you, I grant a furlough to every one who
                        wishes to visit his friends. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You must
                        reassemble at the commencement of spring, so that we may, <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> with the kindly help of the gods, enter upon a war
                        which will bring us immense plunder and cover us with glory." <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> They all welcomed the opportunity, so
                        spontaneously offered, of visiting their homes after so long an absence, and
                        in view of a still longer absence in the future. The winter's rest, coming
                        after their past exertions, and soon to be followed by greater ones,
                        restored their faculties of mind and body and strengthened them for fresh
                        trials of endurance. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the early days of spring they
                        reassembled according to orders. After reviewing the whole of the native
                        contingents, Hannibal left for Gades, where he discharged his vows to
                        Hercules, and bound himself by fresh obligations to that deity in case his
                        enterprise should succeed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As Africa
                        would be open to attack from the side of Sicily during his land march
                        through Spain and the two Gauls into Italy, he decided to secure that
                        country with a strong garrison. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To supply
                        their place he requisitioned troops from Africa, a light-armed force
                        consisting mainly of slingers. By thus transferring Africans to Spain and
                        Spaniards to Africa, the soldiers of each nationality would be expected to
                        render more efficient service, as being practically under reciprocal
                        obligations. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The force he despatched to
                        Africa consisted of 13,850 Spanish infantry furnished with ox-hide bucklers,
                        and 870 Balearic slingers, with a composite body of 1200 cavalry drawn from
                        numerous tribes. This force was destined partly for the defence of Carthage,
                        partly to hold the African territory. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At
                        the same time recruiting officers were sent to various communities; some
                        4000 men of good family were called up who were under orders to be conveyed
                        to Carthage to strengthen its defence, and also to serve as hostages for the
                        loyalty of their people. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Spain also had to be provided for, all the
                        more so as Hannibal was fully aware that Roman commissioners had been going
                        all about the country to win over the leading men of the various tribes.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He placed it in charge of his
                        energetic and able brother, Hasdrubal, and assigned him an army mainly
                        composed of African troops-11,850 native infantry, 300 Ligurians, and 500
                        Balearics. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In addition to this body of
                        infantry there were 450 Libyphoenician cavalry-these are a mixed race of
                        Punic and aboriginal African descent-some 1800 Numidians and Moors, dwellers
                        on the shore of the Mediterranean, and a small mounted contingent of 300
                        Ilergetes raised in Spain. Finally, that his land force might be complete in
                        all its parts, there were twenty-one elephants. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The protection of the coast required a fleet, and as it
                        was natural to suppose that the Romans would again make use of that arm in
                        which they had been victorious before, Hasdrubal had assigned to him a fleet
                        of 57 warships, including 50 quinqueremes, 2 quadriremes, and 5 triremes,
                        but only 32 quinqueremes and the 5 triremes were ready for sea. From Gades
                        he returned to the winter quarters of his army at New Carthage, and from New
                        Carthage he commenced his march on Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Passing by the city of Onusa, he marched along the coast to the Ebro.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The story runs that whilst halting
                        there he saw in a dream a youth of god-like appearance who said that he had
                        been sent by Jupiter to act as guide to Hannibal on his march to Italy. He
                        was accordingly to follow him and not to lose sight of him or let his eyes
                        wander. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first, filled with awe, he
                        followed him without glancing round him or looking back, but as instinctive
                        curiosity impelled him to wonder what it was that he was forbidden to gaze
                        at behind him, he could no longer command his eyes. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He saw behind him a serpent of vast and marvellous
                        bulk, and as it moved along trees and bushes crashed down everywhere before
                        it, whilst in its wake there rolled a thunder-storm. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He asked what the monstrous portent meant, and was told
                        that it was the devastation of Italy; he was to go forward without further
                        question and allow his destiny to remain hidden. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Gladdened by this vision he proceeded to
                        cross the Ebro, with his army in three divisions, after sending men on in
                        advance to secure by bribes the good-will of the Gauls dwelling about his
                        crossing-place, and also to reconnoitre the passes of the Alps. He brought
                        90,000 infantry and 12,000 cavalry over the Ebro. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> His next step was to reduce to submission the
                        Ilergetes, the Bargusii, and the Ausetani, and also the district of
                        Lacetania, which lies at the foot of the Pyrenees. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He placed Hanno in charge of the whole coast-line to
                        secure the passes which connect Spain with Gaul, and furnished him with an
                        army of 10,000 infantry to hold the district, and 1000 cavalry. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> When his army commenced the passage of the
                        Pyrenees and the barbarians found that there was truth in the rumour that
                        they were being led against Rome, 3000 of the Carpetani deserted. It was
                        understood that they were induced to desert not so much by the prospect of
                        the war as by the length of the march and the impossibility of crossing the
                        Alps. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As it would have been hazardous to
                        recall them, or to attempt to detain them by force, in case the quick
                        passions of the rest of the army should be roused, Hannibal sent back to
                        their homes more than <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> 7000 men who, he
                        had personally discovered, were getting tired of the campaign, and at the
                        same time he gave out that the Carpetani had also been sent back by him.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then, to prevent his men from being
                        demoralised by further delay and inactivity, he crossed the Pyrenees with
                        the remainder of his force and fixed his camp at the town of Iliberri.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Gauls were told that it was
                        against Italy that war was being made, but as they had heard that the
                        Spaniards beyond the Pyrenees had been subjugated by force of arms, and
                        strong garrisons placed in their towns, several tribes, fearing for their
                        liberty, were roused to arms and mustered at Ruscino. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> On receiving the announcement of this movement,
                        Hannibal, fearing delay more than hostilities, sent spokesmen to their
                        chiefs to say that he was anxious for a conference with them, and either
                        they might come nearer to Iliberri, or he would approach Ruscino to
                        facilitate their meeting, for he would gladly receive them in his camp or
                        would himself go to them without loss of time. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He had come into Gaul as a friend not a foe, and unless
                        the Gauls compelled him he would not draw his sword till he reached Italy.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This was the proposal made through the
                        envoys, but when the Gauls had, without any hesitation, moved their camp up
                        to Iliberri, they were effectually secured by bribes and allowed the army a
                        free and unmolested passage through their territory under the very walls of
                        Ruscino. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No intelligence, meanwhile, had reached
                        Rome beyond the fact reported by the Massilian envoys, namely that Hannibal
                        had crossed the Ebro. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> No sooner was this
                        known than the Boii, who had been tampering with the Insubres, rose in
                        revolt, just as though he had already crossed the Alps, not so much in
                        consequence of their old standing enmity against Rome as of her recent
                        aggressions. Bodies of colonists were being settled on Gaulish territory in
                        the valley of the Po, at Placentia and Cremona, and intense irritation was
                        produced. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Seizing their arms they made an
                        attack on the land, which was being actually surveyed at the time, and
                        created such terror and confusion that not only the agricultural population,
                        but even the three Roman commissioners who were engaged in marking out the
                        holdings, fled to Mutina, not feeling themselves safe behind the walls of
                        Placentia. The commissioners were C. Lutatius, C. Servilius, and M. Annius.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There is no doubt as to the name
                        Lutatius, but instead of Annius and Servilius some annalists have Manlius
                        Acilius and C. Herennius, whilst others give P. Cornelius Asina and C.
                        Papirius Maso. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There is also doubt as to
                        whether it was the envoys who had been sent to the Boii to remonstrate with
                        them that were maltreated, or the commissioners upon whom an attack was made
                        whilst surveying the ground. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Gauls
                        invested Mutina, but as they were strangers to the art of conducting sieges,
                        and far too indolent to set about the construction of military works, they
                        contented themselves with blockading the town without inflicting any injury
                        on the walls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At last they pretended that
                        they were ready to discuss terms of peace, and the envoys were invited by
                        the Gaulish chieftains to a conference. Here they were arrested, in direct
                        violation not only of international law but of the safe-conduct which had
                        been granted for the occasion. Having made them prisoners the Gauls declared
                        that they would not release them until their hostages were restored to them. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When news came that the envoys were
                        prisoners and Mutina and its garrison in jeopardy, L. Manlius, the praetor,
                        burning with anger, led his army in separate divisions to Mutina. Most of
                        the country was uncultivated at that time and the road went through a
                        forest. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He advanced without throwing out
                        scouting parties and fell into an ambush, out of which, after sustaining
                        considerable loss, he made his way with difficulty on to more open ground.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here he entrenched himself, and as
                        the Gauls felt it would be hopeless to attack him there, the courage of his
                        men revived, though it was tolerably certain that as many as 500 had fallen.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They recommenced their march, and as
                        long as they were going through open country there was no enemy in view;
                        when they re-entered the forest their rear was attacked and great confusion
                        and panic created. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They lost 700 men and
                        six standards. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> When they at last got out
                        of the trackless and entangled forest there was an end to the terrifying
                        tactics of the Gauls and the wild alarm of the Romans. There was no
                        difficulty in repelling attacks when they reached the open country and made
                        their way to Tannetum, a place near the Po. Here they hastily entrenched
                            <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> themselves, and, helped by the
                        windings of the river and assisted by the Brixian Gauls, they held their
                        ground against an enemy whose numbers were daily increasing. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the intelligence of this sudden
                        outbreak reached Rome and the senate became aware that they had a Gaulish
                        war to face in addition to the war with <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                        Carthage, they ordered C. Atilius, the praetor, to go to the relief of
                        Manlius with a Roman legion and 5000 men who had been recently enlisted by
                        the consul from among the allies. As the enemy, afraid to meet these
                        reinforcements, had retired, Atilius reached Tannetum without any fighting.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After raising a fresh legion in place
                        of the one which had been sent away with the praetor, P. Cornelius Scipio
                        set sail with sixty warships and coasted along by the shores of Etruria and
                        Liguria, and from there past the mountains of the Salyes until he reached
                        Marseilles. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here he disembarked his troops
                        at the first mouth of the Rhone to which he came-the river flows into the
                        sea through several mouths-and formed his entrenched camp, hardly able yet
                        to believe that Hannibal had surmounted the obstacle of the Pyrenees.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When, however, he understood that he
                        was already contemplating crossing the Rhone, feeling uncertain as to where
                        he would meet him and anxious to give his men time to recover from the
                        effects of the voyage, he sent forward a picked force of 300 cavalry
                        accompanied by Massilian guides and friendly Gauls to explore the country in
                        all directions and if possible to discover the enemy. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hannibal had overcome the opposition of
                        the native tribes by either fear or bribes and had now reached the territory
                        of the Volcae. They were a powerful tribe, inhabiting the country on both
                        sides of the Rhone, but distrusting their ability to stop Hannibal on the
                        side of the river nearest to him, they determined to make the river a
                        barrier and transported nearly all the population to the other side, on
                        which they prepared to offer armed resistance. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The rest of the river population and those of the
                        Volcae even, who still remained in their homes, were induced by presents to
                        collect boats from all sides and to help in constructing others, and their
                        efforts were stimulated by the desire to get rid as soon as possible of the
                        burdensome presence of such a vast host of men. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> So an enormous number of boats and vessels of every
                        kind, such as they used in their journeys up and down the river, was got
                        together; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> new ones were made by the Gauls
                        by hollowing out the trunks of trees, then the soldiers themselves, seeing
                        the abundance of timber and how easily they were made, took to fashioning
                        uncouth canoes, quite content if only they would float and carry burdens and
                        serve to transport themselves and their belongings. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Everything was now ready for the crossing,
                        but the whole of the opposite bank was held by mounted and unmounted men
                        prepared to dispute the passage. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In order
                        to dislodge them Hannibal sent Hanno, the son of Bomilcar, with a division,
                        consisting mainly of Spaniards, a day's march up the river. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He was to seize the first chance of crossing without
                        being observed, and then lead his men by a circuitous route behind the enemy
                        and at the right moment attack them in the rear. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The Gauls who were taken as guides informed Hanno that
                        about 25 miles up-stream a small island divided the river in two, and the
                        channel was of less depth in consequence. When they reached the spot they
                        hastily cut down the timber and constructed rafts on which men and horses
                        and other burdens could be ferried across. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The Spaniards had no trouble; they threw their clothes on to skins and
                        placing their leather shields on the top they rested on these and so swam
                        across. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The rest of the army was ferried
                        over on rafts, and after making a camp near the river they took a day's rest
                        after their labours of boat-making and the nocturnal passage, their general
                        in the meantime waiting anxiously for an opportunity of putting his plan
                        into execution. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The next day they set out
                        on their march, and lighting a fire on some rising ground they signalled by
                        the column of smoke that they had crossed the river and were not very far
                        away. As soon as Hannibal received the signal he seized the occasion and at
                        once gave the order to cross the river. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        The infantry had prepared rafts and boats, the cavalry mostly barges on
                        account of the horses. A line of large boats was moored across the river a
                        short distance up-stream to break the force of the current, and consequently
                        the men in the smaller boats crossed over in smooth water. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Most of the horses were towed astern and swam over,
                        others were carried in barges, ready saddled and bridled so as to be
                        available for the cavalry the moment they landed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls flocked together on the bank
                        with their customary whoops and war songs, waving their shields over their
                        heads and brandishing their javelins. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                        were somewhat dismayed when they saw what was going on in front of them; the
                        enormous number of large and small boats, the roar of the river, the
                        confused shouts of the soldiers and boatmen, some of whom were trying to
                        force their way against the current, whilst others on the bank were cheering
                        their comrades who were crossing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whilst
                        they were watching all this movement with sinking hearts, still more
                        alarming shouts were heard behind them; Hanno had captured their camp. Soon
                        he appeared on the scene, and they were now confronted by danger from
                        opposite quarters-the host of armed men landing from the boats and the
                        sudden attack which was being made on their rear. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> For a time the Gauls endeavoured to maintain the
                        conflict in both directions, but finding themselves losing ground they
                        forced their way through where there seemed to be least resistance and
                        dispersed to their various villages. Hannibal brought over the rest of his
                        force undisturbed, and, without troubling himself any further about the
                        Gauls, formed his camp. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the transport of the elephants I
                        believe different plans were adopted; at all events, the accounts of what
                        took place vary considerably. Some say that after they had all been
                        collected on the bank the worst-tempered beast amongst them was teased by
                        his driver, and when he ran away from it into the water the elephant
                        followed him and drew the whole herd after it, and as they got out of their
                        depth they were carried by the current to the opposite bank. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The more general account, however, is that they
                        were transported on rafts; as this method would have appeared the safest
                        beforehand so it is most probable that it was the one adopted. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> They pushed out into the river a raft 200 feet
                        long and 50 feet broad, and to prevent it from being carried down-stream,
                        one end was secured by several stout hawsers to the bank. It was covered
                        with earth like a bridge in order that the animals, taking it for solid
                        ground, would not be afraid to venture on it. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> A second raft, of the same breadth but only 100 feet
                        long and capable of crossing the river, was made fast to the former. The
                        elephants led by the females were driven along the fixed raft, as if along a
                        road, until they came on to the smaller one. As soon as they were safely on
                        this it was cast off and towed by light boats to the other side of the
                        river. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the first lot were landed
                        others were brought over in the same way. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        They showed no fear whilst they were being driven along the fixed raft;
                        their fright began when they were being carried into mid-channel on the
                        other raft which had been cast loose. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        They crowded together, those on the outside backing away from the water, and
                        showed considerable alarm until their very fears at the sight of the water
                        made them quiet. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some in their excitement
                        fell overboard and threw their drivers, but their mere weight kept them
                        steady, and as they felt their way into shallow water they succeeded in
                        getting safely to land. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the elephants were being ferried
                        across, Hannibal sent 500 Numidian horse towards the Romans to ascertain
                        their numbers and their intentions. This troop of horse encountered the 300
                        Roman cavalry who, as I have already stated, had been sent forward from the
                        mouth of the Rhone. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was a much more
                        severe fight than might have been expected from the number of combatants.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Not only were there many wounded but
                        each side lost about the same number of killed, and the Romans, who were at
                        last completely exhausted, owed their victory to a panic among the Numidians
                        and their consequent flight. Of the victors as many as 160 fell, not all
                        Romans, some were Gauls; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> whilst the
                        vanquished lost more than 200. This action with which the war commenced was
                        an omen of its final result, but though it portended the final victory of
                        Rome it showed that the victory would not be attained without much bloodshed
                        and repeated defeats. The forces drew off from the field and returned to
                        their respective commanders. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Scipio found
                        himself unable to form any definite plans beyond what were suggested to him
                        by the movements of the enemy. Hannibal was undecided whether to resume his
                        march to Italy or to engage the Romans, the first army to oppose him.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He was dissuaded from the latter
                        course by the arrival of envoys from the Boii and their chief, Magalus. They
                        came to assure Hannibal of their readiness to act as guides and take their
                        share in the dangers of the expedition, and they gave it as their opinion
                        that he ought to reserve all his strength for the invasion of Italy and not
                        fritter any of it away beforehand. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        bulk of his army had not forgotten the previous war and looked forward with
                        dismay to meeting their old enemy, but what appalled them much more was the
                        prospect of an endless journey over the Alps, which rumour said was, to
                        those at all events who had never tried it, a thing to be dreaded. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hannibal had made up his mind to go
                        forward and lose no time in reaching Italy, his goal, he ordered a muster of
                        his troops and addressed them in tones of mingled rebuke and encouragement.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "I am astonished," he said, "to see
                        how hearts that have been always dauntless have now suddenly become a prey
                        to fear. Think of the many victorious campaigns you have gone through, and
                        remember that you did not leave Spain before you had added to the
                        Carthaginian empire all the tribes in the country washed by two widely
                        remote seas. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman people made a
                        demand for all who had taken part in the siege of Saguntum to be given up to
                        them, and you, to avenge the insult, have crossed the Ebro to wipe out the
                        name of Rome and bring freedom to the world. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> When you commenced your march, from the setting to the rising sun, none
                        of you thought it too much for you, but now when you see that by far the
                        greater part of the way has been accomplished; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> the passes of the Pyrenees, which were held by most
                        warlike tribes, surmounted; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the Rhone,
                        that mighty stream, crossed in the face of so many thousand Gauls, and the
                        rush of its waters checked-now that you are within sight of the Alps, on the
                        other side of which lies Italy, you have become weary and are arresting your
                        march in the very gates of the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What
                        do you imagine the Alps to be other than lofty mountains? Suppose them to be
                        higher than the peaks of the Pyrenees, surely no region in the world can
                        touch the sky or be impassable to man. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Even the Alps are inhabited and cultivated, animals are bred and reared
                        there, their gorges and ravines can be traversed by armies. Why, even the
                        envoys whom you see here did not cross the Alps by flying through the air,
                        nor were their ancestors native to the soil. They came into Italy as
                        emigrants looking for a land to settle in, and they crossed the Alps often
                        in immense bodies with their wives and children and all their belongings.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What can be inaccessible or
                        insuperable to the soldier who carries nothing with him but his weapons of
                        war? What toils and perils you went through for eight months to effect the
                        capture of Saguntum! <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And now that Rome,
                        the capital of the world, is your goal, can you deem anything so difficult
                        or so arduous that it should prevent you from reaching it? <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Many years ago the Gauls captured the place which
                        Carthaginians despair of approaching; either you must confess yourselves
                        inferior in courage and enterprise to a people whom you have conquered again
                        and again, or else you must look forward to finishing your march on the
                        ground between the Tiber and the walls of Rome." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this rousing appeal he dismissed
                        them with orders to prepare themselves by food and rest for the march.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The next day they advanced up the left
                        bank of the Rhone towards the central districts of Gaul, not because this
                        was the most direct route to the Alps, but because he thought that there
                        would be less likelihood of the Romans meeting him, for <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> he had no desire to engage them before he arrived in
                        Italy. Four days' marching brought him to the "Island." <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Here the Isere and the Rhone, flowing down from
                        different points in the Alps, enclose a considerable extent of land and then
                        unite their channels; the district thus enclosed is called the "Island."
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The adjacent country was inhabited by
                        the Allobroges, a tribe who even in those days were second to none in Gaul
                        in power and reputation. At the time of Hannibal's visit a quarrel had
                        broken out between two brothers who were each aspiring to the sovereignty.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The elder brother, whose name was
                        Brancus, had hitherto been the chief, but was now expelled by a party of the
                        younger men, headed by his brother, who found an appeal to violence more
                        successful than an appeal to right. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Hannibal's timely appearance on the scene led to the question being referred
                        to him; he was to decide who was the legitimate claimant to the kingship.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He pronounced in favour of the elder
                        brother, who had the support of the senate and the leading men. In return
                        for this service he received assistance in provisions and supplies of all
                        kinds, especially of clothing, a pressing necessity in view of the notorious
                        cold of the Alps. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After settling the feud
                        amongst the Allobroges, Hannibal resumed his march. He did not take the
                        direct course to the Alps, but turned to the left towards the Tricastini;
                        then, skirting the territory of the Vocontii, he marched in the direction of
                        the Tricorii. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nowhere did he meet with
                        any difficulty until he arrived at the Durance. This river, which also takes
                        its rise in the Alps, is of all the rivers of Gaul the most difficult to
                        cross. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Though carrying down a great
                        volume of water, it does not lend itself to navigation, for it is not kept
                        in by banks, but flows in many separate channels. As it is constantly
                        shifting its bottom and the direction of its currents, the task of fording
                        it is a most hazardous one, whilst the shingle and boulders carried down
                        make the foothold insecure and treacherous. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> It happened to be swollen by rain at the time, and the men were thrown
                        into much disorder whilst crossing it, whilst their fears and confused
                        shouting added considerably to their difficulties. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Three days after Hannibal had left the
                        banks of the Rhone, P. Cornelius Scipio arrived at the deserted camp with
                        his army in battle order, ready to engage at once. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When, however, he saw the abandoned lines and realised
                        that it would be no easy matter to overtake his opponent after he had got
                        such a long start, he returned to his ships. He considered that the easier
                        and safer course would be to meet Hannibal as he came down from the Alps.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Spain was the province allotted to
                        him, and to prevent its being entirely denuded of Roman troops he sent his
                        brother Cneius Scipio with the greater part of his army to act against
                        Hasdrubal, not only to keep the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> old
                        allies and win new ones, but to drive Hasdrubal out of Spain. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He himself sailed for Genoa with a very small
                        force, intending to defend Italy with the army lying in the valley of the
                        Po. From the Durance Hannibal's route lay mostly through open level country,
                        and he reached the Alps without meeting with any opposition from the Gauls
                        who inhabited the district. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the sight
                        of the Alps revived the terrors in the minds of his men. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Although rumour, which generally magnifies untried
                        dangers, had filled them with gloomy forebodings, the nearer view proved
                        much more fearful. The height of the mountains now so close, the snow which
                        was almost lost in the sky, the wretched huts perched on the rocks, the
                        flocks and herds shrivelled and stunted with the cold, the men wild and
                        unkempt, everything animate and inanimate stiff with frost, together with
                        other sights dreadful beyond description-all helped to increase their alarm. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As the head of the column began to climb
                        the nearest slopes, the natives appeared on the heights above; had they
                        concealed themselves in the ravines and then rushed down they would have
                        caused frightful panic and bloodshed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Hannibal called a halt and sent on some Gauls to examine the ground, and
                        when he learnt that advance was impossible in that direction he formed his
                        camp in the widest part of the valley that he could find; everywhere around
                        the ground was broken and precipitous. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The Gauls who had been sent to reconnoitre got into conversation with the
                        natives, as there was little difference between their speech or their
                        manners, and they brought back word to Hannibal that the pass was only
                        occupied in the daytime, at nightfall the natives all dispersed to their
                        homes. Accordingly, at early dawn he began the ascent as though determined
                        to force the pass in broad daylight, and spent the day in movements designed
                        to conceal his real intentions and in fortifying the camp on the spot where
                        they had halted. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as he observed
                        that the natives had left the heights and were no longer watching his
                        movements, he gave orders, with the <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                        view of deceiving the enemy, for a large number of fires to be lighted,
                        larger in fact than would be required by those remaining in camp. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Then, leaving the baggage with the cavalry and
                        the greater part of the infantry in camp, he himself with a specially
                        selected body of troops in light marching order rapidly moved out of the
                        defile and occupied the heights which the enemy had held. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following day the rest of the army
                        broke camp in the grey dawn and commenced its march. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The natives were beginning to assemble at their
                        customary post of observation when they suddenly became aware that some of
                        the enemy were in possession of their stronghold right over their heads,
                        whilst others were advancing on the path beneath. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The double impression made on their eyes and
                        imagination kept them for a few moments motionless, but when they saw the
                        column falling into disorder mainly through the horses becoming frightened,
                        they thought that if they increased the confusion and panic it would be
                        sufficient to destroy it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So they charged
                        down from rock to rock, careless as to whether there were paths or not, for
                        they were familiar with the ground. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        Carthaginians had to meet this attack at the same time that they were
                        struggling with the difficulties of the way, and as each man was doing his
                        best for himself to get out of the reach of danger, they were fighting more
                        amongst themselves than against the natives. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> The horses did the most mischief; they were terrified at the wild shouts,
                        which the echoing woods and valleys made all the louder, and when they
                        happened to be struck or wounded they created terrible havoc amongst the men
                        and the different baggage animals. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        road was flanked by sheer precipices on each side, and in the crowding
                        together many were pushed over the edge and fell an immense depth. Amongst
                        these were some of the soldiers; the heavily-laden baggage animals rolled
                        over like falling houses. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Horrible as the
                        sight was, Hannibal remained quiet and kept his men back for some time, for
                        fear of increasing the alarm and confusion, but when he saw that the column
                        was broken and that the army was in <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                        danger of losing all its baggage, in which case he would have brought them
                        safely through to no purpose, he ran down from his higher ground and at once
                        scattered the enemy. At the same time, however, he threw his own men into
                        still greater disorder for the moment, but it was very quickly allayed now
                        that the passage was cleared by the flight of the natives. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> In a short time the whole army had traversed the pass,
                        not only without any further disturbance, but almost in silence. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> He then seized a fortified village, the head
                        place of the district, together with some adjacent hamlets, and from the
                        food and cattle thus secured he provided his army with rations for three
                        days. As the natives, after their first defeat, no longer impeded their
                        march, whilst the road presented little difficulty, they made considerable
                        progress during those three days. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They now came to another canton which,
                        considering that it was a mountain district, had a considerable population.
                        Here he narrowly escaped destruction, not in fair and open fighting, but by
                        the practices which he himself employed-falsehood and treachery. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The head men from the fortified villages, men of
                        advanced age, came as a deputation to the Carthaginian and told him that
                        they had been taught by the salutary example of other people's misfortunes
                        to seek the friendship of the Carthaginians rather than to feel their
                        strength. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were accordingly prepared
                        to carry out his orders; he would receive provisions and guides, and
                        hostages as a guarantee of good faith. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Hannibal felt that he ought not to trust them blindly nor to meet their
                        offer with a flat refusal, in case they should become hostile. So he replied
                        in friendly terms, accepted the hostages whom they placed in his hands, made
                        use of the provisions with which they supplied him on the march, but
                        followed their guides with his army prepared for action, not at all as
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> though he were going through a
                        peaceable or friendly country. The elephants and cavalry were in front, he
                        himself followed with the main body of the infantry, keeping a sharp and
                        anxious look-out in all directions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Just
                        as they reached a part of the pass where it narrowed and was overhung on one
                        side by a wall of rock, the barbarians sprang up from ambush on all sides
                        and assailed the column in front and rear, at close quarters, and at a
                        distance by rolling huge stones down on it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The heaviest attack was made in the rear, and as the infantry faced round
                        to meet it, it became quite obvious that if the rear of the column had not
                        been made exceptionally strong, a terrible disaster must have occurred in
                        that pass. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As it was, they were in the
                        greatest danger, and within an ace of total destruction. For whilst Hannibal
                        was hesitating whether to send his infantry on into the narrow part of the
                        pass-for whilst protecting the rear of the cavalry they had no reserves to
                        protect their own rear-the mountaineers, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                        making a flank charge, burst through the middle of the column and held the
                        pass so that Hannibal had to spend that one night without his cavalry or his
                        baggage. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day, as the savages attacked with
                        less vigour, the column closed up, and the pass was surmounted, not without
                        loss, more, however, of baggage animals than of men. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> From that time the natives made their appearance in
                        smaller numbers and behaved more like banditti than regular soldiers; they
                        attacked either front or rear just as the ground gave them opportunity, or
                        as the advance or halt of the column presented a chance of surprise.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The elephants caused considerable
                        delay, owing to the difficulty of getting them through narrow or precipitous
                        places; on the other hand, they rendered that part of the column safe from
                        attack where they were, for the natives were unaccustomed to the sight of
                        them and had a great dread of going too near them. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Nine days from their commencing the ascent they arrived
                        at the highest point of the Alps, after traversing a region mostly without
                        roads and frequently losing their way either through the treachery of their
                        guides or through their own mistakes in trying to find the way for
                        themselves. For two days they remained in camp on the summit, whilst the
                        troops enjoyed a respite from fatigue and fighting. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Some of the baggage animals which had fallen amongst
                        the rocks and had afterwards followed the track of the column came into
                        camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To add to the misfortunes of the
                        worn-out troops, there was a heavy fall of snow-the Pleiads were near their
                        setting-and this new experience created considerable alarm. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> In the early morning of the third day the army
                        recommenced its heavy march over ground everywhere deep in snow. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Hannibal saw in all faces an expression of
                        listlessness and despondency. He rode on in front to a height from which
                        there was a wide and extensive view, and halting his men, he pointed out to
                        them the land of Italy and the rich valley of the Po lying at the foot of
                        the Alps. "You are now," he said, "crossing the barriers not only of Italy,
                        but of Rome itself. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Henceforth all will be
                        smooth and easy for you; in one or, at the most, two battles, you will be
                        masters of the capital and stronghold of Italy." <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Then the army resumed its advance with no annoyance
                        from the enemy beyond occasional attempts at plunder. The remainder of the
                        march, however, was attended with much greater difficulty than they had
                        experienced in the ascent, for the distance to <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> the plains on the Italian side is shorter, and
                        therefore the descent is necessarily steeper. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Almost the whole of the way was precipitous, narrow,
                        and slippery, so that they were unable to keep their footing, and if they
                        slipped they could not recover themselves; they kept falling over each
                        other, and the baggage animals rolled over on their drivers. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At length they came to a much narrower
                        pass which descended over such sheer cliffs that a light-armed soldier could
                        hardly get down it even by hanging on to projecting roots and branches.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The place had always been precipitous,
                        and a landslip had recently carried away the road for 1000 feet. The cavalry
                        came to a halt here as though they had arrived <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> at their journey's end, and whilst Hannibal was
                        wondering what could be causing the delay he was informed that there was no
                        passage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then he went forward to examine
                        the place and saw that there was nothing for it but to lead the army by a
                        long circuitous route over pathless and untrodden snow. But this, too, soon
                        proved to be impracticable. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The old snow
                        had been covered to a moderate depth by a fresh fall, and the first comers
                        planted their feet firmly on the new snow, but when it had become melted
                        under the tread of so <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> many men and
                        beasts there was nothing to walk on but ice covered with slush. Their
                        progress now became one incessant and miserable struggle. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The smooth ice allowed no foothold, and as they were
                        going down a steep incline they were still less able to keep on their legs,
                        whilst, once down, they tried in vain to rise, as their hands and knees were
                        continually slipping. There were no stumps or roots about for them to get
                        hold of and support themselves by, so they rolled about helplessly on the
                        glassy ice and slushy snow. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The baggage
                        animals as they toiled along cut through occasionally into the lowest layer
                        of snow, and when they stumbled they struck out their hoofs in their
                        struggles to recover themselves and broke through into the hard and
                        congealed ice below, where most of them stuck as though caught in a gin.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At last, when men and beasts alike were
                        worn out by their fruitless exertions, a camp was formed on the summit,
                        after the place had been cleared with immense difficulty owing to the
                        quantity of snow that had to be removed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The next thing was to level the rock through which alone a road was
                        practicable. The soldiers were told off to cut through it. They built up
                        against it an enormous pile of tall trees which they had felled and lopped,
                        and when the wind was strong enough to blow up the fire they set light to
                        the pile. When the rock was red hot they poured vinegar upon it to
                        disintegrate it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After thus treating it by
                        fire they opened a way through it with their tools, and eased the steep
                        slope by winding tracks of moderate gradient, so that not only the baggage
                        animals but even the elephants could be led down. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Four days were spent over the rock, and the animals
                        were almost starved to death, for the heights are mostly bare of vegetation
                        and what herbage there is is buried beneath the snow. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> In the lower levels there were sunny valleys and
                        streams flowing through woods, and spots more deserving of human
                        inhabitants. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here the beasts were turned
                        loose to graze, and the troops, worn out with their engineering, were
                        allowed to rest. In three days more they reached the open plains and found a
                        pleasanter country and pleasanter people living in it </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such, in the main, was the way in which
                        they reached Italy, five months, according to some authorities, after
                        leaving New Carthage, fifteen days of which were spent in overcoming the
                        difficulties of the Alps. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The authorities
                        are hopelessly at variance as to the number of the troops with which
                        Hannibal entered Italy. The highest estimate assigns him 100,000 infantry
                        and 20,000 cavalry; the lowest puts his strength at 20,000 infantry and 6000
                        cavalry. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> L. Cincius Alimentus tells us
                        that he was taken prisoner by Hannibal, and I should be most inclined to
                        accept his authority if he had not confused the numbers by adding in the
                        Gauls and Ligurians; if these are included there were 80,000 infantry and
                        10,000 cavalry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is, however, more
                        probable that these joined Hannibal in Italy, and some authorities actually
                        assert this. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Cincius also states that he
                        had heard Hannibal say that subsequently to his passage of the Rhone he lost
                        36,000 men, besides an immense number of horses and other animals. The first
                        people he came to were the Taurini, a semi-Garlic tribe. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As tradition is unanimous on this point I am the more
                        surprised that a question should be raised as to what route Hannibal took
                        over the Alps, and that it should be generally supposed that he crossed over
                        the Poenine range, which is said to have derived its name from that
                        circumstance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Coelius asserts that he
                        crossed by the Cremonian range. These two passes, however, would not have
                        brought him to the Taurini but through the Salassi, a mountain tribe, to the
                        Libuan Gauls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is highly improbable that
                        those routes to Gaul were available at that time, and in any case the
                        Poenine route would have been closed by the semi-German tribes who inhabited
                        the district. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And it is perfectly certain,
                        if we accept their authority, that the Seduni and Veragri, who inhabit that
                        range, say that the name of Poenine was not given to it from any passage of
                        the Carthaginians over it but from the deity Poeninus, whose shrine stands
                        on the highest point of the range. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was a very fortunate circumstance for
                        Hannibal at the outset of his campaign that the Taurini, the first people he
                        came to, were at war with the Insubres. But he was unable to bring his army
                        into the field to assist either side, for it was whilst they were recovering
                        from the ills and misfortunes which had gathered upon them that they felt
                        them most. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Rest and idleness instead of
                        toil, plenty following upon starvation, cleanliness and comfort after
                        squalor and emaciation, affected their filthy and well-nigh bestialised
                        bodies in various ways. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was this state
                        of things which induced P. Cornelius Scipio, the consul, after he had
                        arrived with his ships at Pisa and taken over from Manlius and Atilius an
                        army of raw levies disheartened by their recent humiliating defeats, to push
                        on with all speed to the Po that he might engage the enemy before he had
                        recovered his strength. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when he
                        reached Placentia Hannibal had already left his encampment and taken by
                        storm one of the cities of the Taurini, their capital, in fact, because they
                        would not voluntarily maintain friendly relations with him. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He would have secured the adhesion of the Gauls in the
                        valley of the Po, not by fear but by their own choice, if the sudden arrival
                        of the consul had not taken them by surprise whilst they were waiting for a
                        favourable moment to revolt. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Just at the
                        time of Scipio's arrival, Hannibal moved out of the country of the Taurini,
                        for, seeing how undecided the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Gauls were
                        as to whose side they should take, he thought that if he were on the spot
                        they would follow him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The two armies were
                        now almost within sight of one another, and the commanders who were
                        confronting each other, though not sufficiently acquainted with each other's
                        military skill, were even then imbued with mutual respect and admiration.
                        Even before the fall of Saguntum the name of Hannibal was on all men's lips
                        in Rome, and in Scipio Hannibal recognised a great leader, seeing that he
                        had been chosen beyond all others to oppose him. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> This mutual esteem was enhanced by their recent
                        achievements; Scipio, after Hannibal had left him in Gaul, was in time to
                        meet him on his descent from the Alps; Hannibal had not only dared to
                        attempt but had actually accomplished the passage of the Alps. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Scipio, however, made the first move by crossing
                        the Po and shifting his camp to the Ticinus. Before leading his men into
                        battle he addressed them in a speech full of encouragement, in the following
                        terms: </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "If, soldiers, I were leading into battle
                        the army which I had with me in Gaul, there would have been no need for me
                        to address you. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For what encouragement
                        would those cavalry need who had won such a brilliant victory over the
                        enemy's cavalry at the Rhone or those legions of infantry with whom I
                        pursued this same enemy, who by his running away and shirking an engagement
                        acknowledged that I was his conqueror? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        That army, raised for service in Spain, is campaigning under my brother, Cn.
                        Scipio, who is acting as my deputy in the country which the senate and
                        people of Rome have assigned to it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                        order, therefore, that you might have a consul to lead you against Hannibal
                        and the Carthaginians, I have volunteered to command in this battle, and as
                        I am new to you and you to me I must say a few words to you. "Now as to the
                        character of the enemy and the kind of warfare which awaits you. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> You have to fight, soldiers, with the men whom
                        you defeated in the former war by land and sea, from whom you have exacted a
                        war indemnity for the last twenty years, and from whom you wrested Sicily
                        and Sardinia as the prizes of war. You, therefore, will go into this battle
                        with the exultation of victors, they with the despondency of the vanquished.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They are not going to fight now
                        because they are impelled by courage but through sheer necessity; unless
                        indeed you suppose that, after shirking a contest when their army was at its
                        full strength, they have gained more confidence now that they have lost
                        two-thirds of their infantry and <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> cavalry
                        in their passage over the Alps, now that those who survive are fewer than
                        those who have perished. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "'Yes,' it may be
                        said, 'they are few in number, but they are strong in courage and physique,
                        and possess a power of endurance and vigour in attack which very few can
                        withstand.' <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> No, they are only semblances
                        or rather ghosts of men, worn out with starvation, cold, filth, and squalor,
                        bruised and enfeebled amongst the rocks and precipices, and, what is more,
                        their limbs are frostbitten, their thews and sinews cramped with cold, their
                        frames shrunk and shrivelled with frost, their weapons battered and
                        shivered, their horses lame and out of condition. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> This is the cavalry, this the infantry with whom you
                        are going to fight; you will not have an enemy but only the last vestiges of
                        an enemy to meet. My only fear is that when you have fought it will appear
                        to be the Alps that have conquered Hannibal. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But perhaps it was right that it should be so, and that
                        the gods, without any human aid, should begin and all but finish this war
                        with a people and their general who have broken treaties, and that to us,
                        who next to the gods have been sinned against, it should be left to complete
                        what they began. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "I am not afraid of any one thinking that
                        I am saying this in a spirit of bravado for the sake of putting you in good
                        heart, whilst my real feelings and convictions are far otherwise. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> I was at perfect liberty to go with my army to
                        Spain, for which country I had actually started, and which was my assigned
                        province. There I should have had my brother to share my plans and dangers;
                        I should have had Hasdrubal rather than Hannibal as my foe, and undoubtedly
                        a less serious war on my hands. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But as I
                        was sailing along the coast of Gaul I heard tidings of this enemy, and at
                        once landed, and after sending on cavalry in advance moved up to the Rhone.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A cavalry action was fought-that was
                        the only arm I had the opportunity of employing-and I defeated the enemy.
                        His infantry were hurrying away like an army in flight, and as I could not
                        come up with them overland, I returned to my ships with all possible speed,
                        and after making a wide circuit by sea and land have met this dreaded foe
                        almost at the foot of the Alps. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Does it
                        seem to you that I have unexpectedly fallen in with him whilst I was anxious
                        to decline a contest and not rather that I am meeting him actually on his
                        track and challenging and dragging him into action? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> I shall be glad to learn whether the earth has suddenly
                        within the last twenty years produced a different breed of Carthaginans, or
                        whether they are the same as those who fought at the Aegates, and <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> whom you allowed to depart from Eryx on payment
                        of eighteen denarii a head, and whether this Hannibal is, as he gives out,
                        the rival of Hercules in his journeys, or whether he has been left by his
                        father to pay tax and tribute and to be the slave of the Roman people.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If his crime at Saguntum were not
                        driving him on, he would surely have some regard, if not <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> for his conquered country, at all events for his house
                        and his father, and the treaties signed by that Hamilcar who at the order of
                        our consul withdrew his garrison from Eryx, who with sighs and groans
                        accepted the hard conditions imposed on the conquered Carthaginians, and who
                        agreed to evacuate Sicily and pay a war indemnity to Rome. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> And so I would have you, soldiers, fight not merely in
                        the spirit which you are wont to show against other foes, but with feelings
                        of indignant anger as though you saw your own slaves bearing arms against
                        you. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When they were shut up in Eryx we
                        might have inflicted the most terrible of human punishments and starved them
                        to death; we might have taken our victorious fleet across to Africa, and in
                        a few days destroyed Carthage without a battle. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> We granted pardon to their prayers, we allowed them to
                        escape from the blockade, we agreed to terms of peace with those whom we had
                        conquered, and afterwards when they were in <milestone n="13??"
                            unit="section"/> dire straits through the African war we took them under
                        our protection, To requite us for these acts of kindness they are following
                        the lead of a young madman and coming to attack our fatherland. I only wish
                        this struggle were for honour alone and not for safety. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> It is not about the possession of Sicily and Sardinia,
                        the old subjects of dispute, but for Italy that you have to fight.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There is no second army at our back
                        to oppose the enemy if we fall to win, there are no more Alps to delay his
                        advance while a fresh army can be raised for defence. Here it is, soldiers,
                        that we have to resist, just as though we were fighting before the walls of
                        Rome. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Every one of you must remember that
                        he is using his arms to protect not himself only but also his wife and
                        little children; nor must his anxiety be confined to his home, he must
                        realise, too, that the senate and people of Rome are watching our exploits
                        today. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> What our strength and courage are
                        now here, such will be the fortune of our City yonder and of the empire of
                        Rome." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the language which the consul
                        used towards the Romans. Hannibal thought that the courage of his men ought
                        to be roused by deeds first rather than by words. After forming his army
                        into a circle to view the spectacle, he placed in the centre some Alpine
                        prisoners in chains, and when some Gaulish arms had been thrown down at
                        their feet he ordered an interpreter to ask if any one of them was willing
                        to fight if he were freed from his chains and received arms and a horse as
                        the reward of victory. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> All to a man
                        demanded arms and battle, and when the lot was cast to decide who should
                        fight, each wished that he might be the one whom Fortune should select for
                        the combat. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As each man's lot fell, he
                        hastily seized his arms full of eagerness and exultant delight, amidst the
                        congratulations of his comrades and danced after the custom of his country.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when they began to fight, such was
                        the state of feeling not only amongst the men who had accepted this
                        condition, but amongst the spectators generally that the good fortune of
                        those who died bravely was lauded quite as much as that of those who were
                        victorious. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After his men had been impressed by
                        watching several pairs of combatants Hannibal dismissed them, and afterwards
                        summoned them round him, when he is reported to have made the following
                        speech: "Soldiers, you have seen in the fate of others an example how to
                        conquer or to die. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If the feelings with
                        which you watched them lead you to form a similar estimate of your own
                        fortunes we are victors. That was no idle spectacle but a picture, as it
                        were, of your own condition. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fortune, I am
                        inclined to think has bound you in heavier chains and imposed upon you a
                        sterner necessity than on your captives. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        You are shut in on the right hand and on the left by two seas, and you have
                        not a single ship in which to make your escape; around you flows the Po, a
                        greater river than the Rhone and a more rapid one; the barrier of the Alps
                        frowns upon you behind, those Alps which you could hardly cross when your
                        strength and vigour were unimpaired. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here,
                        soldiers, on this spot where you have for the first time encountered the
                        enemy you must either conquer or die. The same Fortune which has imposed
                        upon you the necessity of fighting also holds out rewards of victory,
                        rewards as great as any which men are wont to solicit from the immortal
                        gods. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Even if we were only going to
                        recover Sicily and Sardinia, possessions which were wrested from our
                        fathers, they would be prizes ample enough to satisfy us. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Everything that the Romans now possess, which they have
                        won through so many triumphs, all that they have amassed, will become yours,
                        together with those who own it. Come then, seize your arms and with the help
                        of heaven win this splendid reward. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> You
                        have spent time enough in hunting cattle on the barren mountains of
                        Lusitania and Celtiberia, and finding no recompense for all your toils and
                        dangers; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> now the hour has come for you to
                        enter upon rich and lucrative campaigns and to earn rewards which are worth
                        the earning, after your long march over all those mountains and rivers, and
                        through all those nations in arms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here
                        Fortune has vouchsafed an end to your toils, here she will vouchsafe a
                        reward worthy of all your past services. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "Do not think because the war, being
                        against Rome, bears a great name, that therefore victory will be
                        correspondingly difficult. Many a despised enemy has fought a long and
                        costly fight; nations and kings of high renown have been beaten with a very
                        slight effort. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For, setting aside the
                        glory which surrounds the name of Rome, what point is there in which they
                        can be compared to you? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> To say nothing of
                        your twenty years' campaigning earned on with all your courage, all your
                        good fortune, from the pillars of Hercules, from the shores of the ocean,
                        from the furthest corners of the earth, through the midst of all the most
                        warlike peoples of Spain and Gaul, you have arrived here as victors.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The army with which you will fight is
                        made up of raw levies who were beaten, conquered, and hemmed in by the Gauls
                        this very summer, who are strangers to their general, and he a stranger to
                        them. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I, reared as I was, almost born, in
                        the headquarters tent of my father, a most distinguished general, I, who
                        have subjugated Spain and Gaul, who have conquered not only the Alpine
                        tribes, but, what is a much greater task, the Alps themselves-am I to
                        compare myself with this six months' general who has deserted his own
                            <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> army, who, if any one were to point
                        out to him the Romans and the Carthaginians after their standards were
                        removed, would, I am quite certain, not know which army he was in command of
                        as consul? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> I do not count it a small
                        matter, soldiers, that there is not a man amongst you before whose eyes I
                        have not done many a soldierly deed, or to whom I, who have witnessed and
                        attested his courage, could not recount his own gallant exploits and the
                        time and place where they were performed. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        I was your pupil before I was your commander, and I shall go into battle
                        surrounded by men whom I have commended and rewarded thousands of times
                        against those who know nothing of each other, who are mutual strangers. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Wherever I turn my eyes I see nothing but
                        courage and strength, a veteran infantry, a cavalry, regular and irregular
                        alike, drawn from the noblest tribes, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                        you, our most faithful and brave allies, you, Carthaginians, who are going
                        to fight for your country, inspired by a most righteous indignation.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> We are taking the aggressive, we are
                        descending in hostile array into Italy, prepared to fight more bravely and
                        more fearlessly than our foe because he who attacks is animated by stronger
                        hopes and greater courage than he who meets the attack. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Besides, we are smarting from a sense of injustice and
                        humiliation. First they demanded me, your general, as their victim, then
                        they insisted that all of you who had taken part in the siege of Saguntum
                        should be surrendered; had you been given up they would have inflicted upon
                        you the most exquisite tortures. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That
                        outrageously cruel and tyrannical nation claims everything for itself, makes
                        everything dependent on its will and pleasure; they think it right to
                        dictate with whom we are to make war or peace. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They confine and enclose us within mountains and rivers
                        as boundaries, but they do not observe the limits which they themselves have
                        fixed. 'Do not cross the Ebro, see that you have nothing to do with the
                        Saguntines.' <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> 'But Saguntum is not on the
                        Ebro.' 'You must not move a step anywhere.' 'Is it a small matter, your
                        taking from me my oldest provinces, Sicily and Sardinia? Will you cross over
                        into Spain as well, and if I withdraw from there, will you cross over into
                        Africa? Do I say, will cross over? You have crossed over.' They have sent
                        the two consuls for this year, one to Africa, the other to Spain. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> There is nothing left to us anywhere except what
                        we claim by force of arms. Those may be allowed to be cowards and dastards
                        who have something to fall back upon, whom their own land, their own
                        territory will receive as they flee through its safe and peaceful roads; you
                        must of necessity be brave men, every alternative between victory and death
                        has been broken off by the resolve of despair, and you are compelled either
                        to conquer, or if Fortune wavers, to meet death in battle rather than in
                        flight. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If you have all made up your minds
                        to this, I say again you are victors, no keener weapon has been put into
                        men's hands by the immortal gods than a contempt for death." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the fighting spirit of both armies
                        had been roused by these harangues, the Romans threw a bridge over the
                        Ticinus and constructed a blockhouse for its defence. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst they were thus occupied, the Carthaginian sent
                        Maharbal with a troop of 500 Numidian horse to ravage the lands of the
                        allies of Rome, but with orders to spare those of the Gauls as far as
                        possible, and to win over their chiefs to his side. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When the bridge was completed the Roman army crossed
                        over in the territory of the Insubres and took up a position five miles from
                        Ictumuli, where Hannibal had his camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As
                        soon as he saw that a battle was imminent, he hastily recalled Maharbal and
                        his troopers. Feeling that he could never say enough by way of admonition
                        and encouragement to his soldiers, he ordered an assembly, and before the
                        whole army offered definite rewards in the hope of which they were to fight.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He said that he would give them land
                        wherever they wished, in Italy, Africa, or Spain, which would be free from
                        all taxation for the recipient and for his children; if any preferred money
                        to land, he would satisfy his desires; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> if
                        any of the allies wished to become Carthaginian citizens he would give them
                        the opportunity; if any preferred to return to their homes he would take
                        care that their circumstances should be such that they would never wish to
                        exchange them with any of their countrymen. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> He even promised freedom to the slaves who followed their masters, and to
                        the masters, for every slave freed, two more as compensation. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> To convince them of his determination to carry
                        out these promises, he held a lamb with his left hand and a flint knife in
                        his right and prayed to Jupiter and the other gods, that, if he broke his
                        word and forswore himself they would slay him as he had slain the lamb. He
                        then crushed the animal's head with the flint. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> They all felt then that the gods themselves would
                        guarantee the fulfilment of their hopes, and looked upon the delay in
                        bringing on an action as delay in gaining their desires; with one mind and
                        one voice they clamoured to be led into battle. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans were far from showing this
                        alacrity. Amongst other causes of alarm they had been unnerved by some
                        portents which had happened lately. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A wolf
                        had entered the camp and after worrying all it met had got away unhurt. A
                        swarm of bees, too, had settled on a tree which overhung the headquarters
                        tent. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After the necessary propitiation had
                        been made Scipio moved out with a force of cavalry and light-armed javelin
                        men towards the enemy's camp to get a nearer view and to ascertain the
                        number and nature of his force. He fell in with Hannibal who was also
                        advancing with his cavalry to explore the neighbourhood. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Neither body at first saw the other; the first
                        indication of a hostile approach was given by the unusually dense cloud of
                        dust which was raised by the tramp of so many men and horses. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Each party halted and made ready for battle.
                        Scipio placed the javelin men and the Gaulish cavalry in the front, the
                        Roman horse and the heavy cavalry of the allies as reserves. Hannibal formed
                        his centre with his regular cavalry, and posted the Numidians on the flanks.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Scarcely had the battle shout been
                        raised before the javelin men retired to the second line amongst the
                        reserves. For some time the cavalry kept up an equal fight, but as the
                        foot-soldiers became mixed up with the mounted men they made their horses
                        unmanageable, many were thrown or else dismounted where they saw their
                        comrades in difficulty, until the battle was mainly fought on foot.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then the Numidians on the flanks
                        wheeled round and appeared on the rear of the Romans, creating dismay and
                        panic amongst them. To make matters worse the consul was wounded and in
                        danger; he was rescued by the intervention of his son who was just
                        approaching manhood. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This was the youth
                        who afterwards won the glory of bringing this war to a close, and gained the
                        soubriquet of Africanus for his splendid victory over Hannibal and the
                        Carthaginians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The javelin men were the
                        first to be attacked by the Numidians and they fled in disorder, the rest of
                        the force, the cavalry, closed round the consul, shielding him as much by
                        their persons as by their arms, and returned to camp in orderly retirement.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Caelius assigns the honour of saving
                        the consul to a Ligurian slave, but I would rather believe that it was his
                        son; the majority of authors assert this and the tradition is generally
                        accepted. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was the first battle with Hannibal,
                        and the result made it quite clear that the Carthaginian was superior in his
                        cavalry, and consequently that the open plains which stretch from the Po to
                        the Alps were not a suitable battlefield for the Romans. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The next night accordingly, the soldiers were ordered
                        to collect their baggage in silence, the army moved away from the Ticinus
                        and marched rapidly to the Po, which they crossed by the pontoon bridge
                        which was still intact, in perfect order and without any molestation by the
                        enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They reached Placentia before
                        Hannibal knew for certain that they had left the Ticinus; however, he
                        succeeded in capturing some 600, who were loitering on his side of the Po,
                        and were slowly unfastening the end of the bridge. He was unable to use the
                        bridge for crossing, as the ends had been unfastened and the whole was
                        floating down-stream. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> According to
                        Caelius, Mago with the cavalry and Spanish infantry at once swam across,
                        whilst Hannibal himself took his army across higher up the river where it
                        was fordable, the elephants being stationed in a row from bank to bank to
                        break the force of the current. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those who
                        know the river will hardly believe this for it is highly improbable that the
                        cavalry could have stood against so violent a river without damage to their
                        horses and arms, even supposing that the Spaniards had been carried across
                        by their inflated skins, and it would have required a march of many days to
                        find a ford in the Po where an army loaded with baggage could be taken
                        across. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I attach greater weight to those
                        authorities who state that it took them at least two days to find a spot
                        where they could throw a bridge over the river, and that it was there that
                        Mago's cavalry and the Spanish light infantry crossed. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst Hannibal was waiting near the river to give
                        audience to deputations from the Gauls, he sent his heavy infantry across,
                        and during this interval Mago and his cavalry advanced a day's march from
                        the river in the direction of the enemy at Placentia. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> A few days later Hannibal entrenched himself in a
                        position six miles from Placentia, and the next day he drew out his army in
                        battle order in full view of the enemy and gave him the opportunity of
                        fighting. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following night a murderous outbreak
                        took place amongst the Gaulish auxiliaries in the Roman camp; there was,
                        however, more excitement and confusion than actual loss of life. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> About 2000 infantry and 200 horsemen massacred
                        the sentinels and deserted to Hannibal. The Carthaginian gave them a kind
                        reception and sent them to their homes with the promise of great rewards if
                        they would enlist the sympathies of their countrymen on his behalf.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio saw in this outrage a signal of
                        revolt for all the Gauls, who, infected by the madness of this crime, would
                        at once fly to arms, and though still suffering severely from his wound, he
                        left his position in the fourth watch of the following night, <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> his army marching in perfect silence, and
                        shifted his camp close to the Trebia on to higher ground where the hills
                        were impracticable for cavalry. He was less successful in escaping the
                        notice of the enemy than he had been at the Ticinus, Hannibal sent first the
                        Numidians, then afterwards the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> whole of
                        his cavalry in pursuit and would have inflicted disaster upon the rear of
                        the column at all events, had not the Numidians been tempted by their desire
                        for plunder to turn aside to the deserted Roman camp. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst they were wasting their time in prying into
                        every corner of the camp, without finding anything worth waiting for, the
                        enemy slipped out of their hands, and when they caught sight of the Romans
                        they had already crossed the Trebia and were measuring out the site for
                        their camp. A few stragglers whom they caught on their side the river were
                        killed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Unable any longer to endure the
                        irritation of his wound, which had been aggravated during the march, and
                        also thinking that he ought to wait for his colleague-he had already heard
                        that he had been recalled from Sicily-Scipio selected what seemed the safest
                        position near the river, and formed a standing camp which was strongly
                        entrenched. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hannibal had encamped not far
                        from there, and in spite of his elation at his successful cavalry action he
                        felt considerable anxiety at the shortness of supplies which, owing to his
                        marching through hostile territory where no stores were provided, became
                        more serious day by day. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He sent a
                        detachment to the town of Clastidium where the Romans had accumulated large
                        quantities of corn. Whilst they were preparing to attack the place they were
                        led to hope that it would be betrayed to them. Dasius, a Brundisian, was
                        commandant of the garrison, and he was induced by a moderate bribe of 400
                        gold pieces to betray Clastidium to Hannibal. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The place was the granary of the Carthaginians while
                        they were at the Trebia. No cruelty was practiced on the garrison, as
                        Hannibal was anxious to win a reputation for clemency at the outset. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .The war on the Trebia had for the time
                        being come to a standstill, but military and naval actions were taking place
                        around Sicily and the islands fringing Italy, both under the conduct of
                        Sempronius and also before his arrival. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Twenty quinqueremes with a thousand soldiers on board had been despatched by
                        the Carthaginians to Italy, nine of them to Liparae, eight to the island of
                        Vulcanus, and three had been carried by the currents into the Straits of
                        Messana. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These were sighted from Messana,
                        and Hiero, the King of Syracuse, who happened to be there at the time
                        waiting for the consul, despatched twelve ships against them, and they were
                        taken without any opposition and brought into the harbour of Messana.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was ascertained from the prisoners,
                        that besides the fleet of twenty ships to which they belonged which had
                        sailed for Italy thirty-five quinqueremes were also on the way to Sicily
                        with the object of stirring up the old allies of Carthage. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Their main anxiety was to secure Lilybaeum, and the
                        prisoners were of opinion that the storm which had separated them from the
                        rest had also driven that fleet up to the Aegates. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The king communicated this information just as he had
                        received it to M. Aemilius, the praetor, whose province Sicily was, and
                        advised him to throw a strong garrison into Lilybaeum. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The praetor at once sent envoys and military tribunes
                        to the neighbouring states to urge them to take measures for self-defence.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Lilybaeum especially was engrossed in
                        preparations for war; orders were issued for the seamen to carry ten days'
                        rations on board that there might be no delay in setting sail when the
                        signal was given; and men were despatched along the coast to look out for
                        the approach of the hostile fleet. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So it
                        came to pass that although the Carthaginians had purposely lessened the
                        speed of their vessels, so that they might approach Lilybaeum before
                        daylight, they were descried in the offing owing to there being a moon all
                        night, and also because they were coming with their sails set. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Instantly the signal was given by the look-out
                        men; in the town there was the cry, "To arms," and the ships were manned.
                        Some of the soldiers were on the walls and guarding the gates, others were
                        on board the ships. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As the Carthaginians
                        saw that they would have to deal with people who were anything but
                        unprepared, they stood out from the harbour till daylight, and spent the
                        time in lowering their masts and preparing for action. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> When it grew light they put out to sea that they might
                        have sufficient room for fighting, and that the enemy's ships might be free
                        to issue from the harbour. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Romans did
                        not decline battle, encouraged as they were by the recollection of their
                        former conflicts in this very place, and full of confidence in the numbers
                        and courage of their men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they had sailed out to sea the Romans
                        were eager to come to close quarters and make a hand-to-hand fight of it;
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the Carthaginians, on the other hand,
                        sought to avoid this and to succeed by maneuvering and not by direct attack;
                        they preferred to make it a battle of ships rather than of soldiers.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For their fleet was amply provided
                        with seamen, but only scantily manned by soldiers, and whenever a ship was
                        laid alongside one of the enemy's they were very unequally matched in
                        fighting men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When this became generally
                        known, the spirits of the Romans rose as they realised how many of their
                        military were on board, whilst the Carthaginians lost heart when they
                        remembered how few they had. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Seven of
                        their ships were captured in a very short time, the rest took to flight.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the seven ships there were 1700
                        soldiers and sailors, amongst them three members of the Carthaginian
                        nobility. The Roman fleet returned undamaged into port, with the exception
                        of one which had been rammed, but even that was brought in. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Immediately after this battle Tiberius Sempronius, the
                        consul, arrived at Messana before those in the town had heard of it.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> King Hiero went to meet him at the
                        entrance of the Straits with his fleet fully equipped and manned, and went
                        on board the consul's vessel to congratulate him on having safely arrived
                        with his fleet and his army, and to wish him a prosperous and successful
                        passage to Sicily. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then described the
                        condition of the island and the movements of the Carthaginians, and promised
                        to assist the Romans now in his old age with the same readiness which he had
                        shown as a young man in the former war; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        he should supply the seamen and soldiers with corn and clothing gratis.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He also told the consul that
                        Lilybaeum and the cities on the coast were in great danger, some were
                        anxious to effect a revolution. The consul saw that there must be no delay
                        in his sailing for Lilybaeum; he started at once and the king accompanied
                        him with his fleet. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Lilybaeum Hiero and his fleet bade him
                        farewell, and the consul, after leaving the praetor to see to the defence of
                        the coast of Sicily, crossed over to Malta which was held by the
                        Carthaginians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hamilcar, the son of Gisgo,
                        who was in command of the garrison, surrendered the island and his men, a
                        little under 2000 in number. A few days later he returned to Lilybaeum, and
                        the prisoners, with the exception of the three nobles, were sold by auction.
                        After satisfying himself as to the security of that part of Sicily, the
                        consul sailed to the Insulae Vulcani, as he heard that the Carthaginian
                        fleet was anchored there. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> No enemy,
                        however, was found in the neighbourhood, for they had left for Italy to
                        ravage the coastal districts, and after laying waste the territory of Vibo
                        they were threatening the city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whilst he
                        was returning to Sicily the news of these depredations reached the consul,
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and at the same time a despatch was
                        handed to him from the senate informing him of Hannibal's presence in Italy
                        and ordering him to come to his colleague's assistance as soon as possible.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With all these causes for anxiety
                        weighing upon him, the consul at once embarked his army and despatched it up
                        the Adriatic to Ariminum. He furnished Sex. Pomponius, his legate, with
                        twenty-five ships of war, and entrusted to him the protection of the Italian
                        coast and the territory of Vibo, and made up the fleet of M. Aemilius, the
                        praetor, to fifty vessels. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After making
                        these arrangements for Sicily, he started for Italy with ten ships, and
                        cruising along the coast reached Ariminum. From there he marched to the
                        Trebia and effected a junction with his colleague. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="52" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The fact that both consuls and all the
                        available strength that Rome possessed were now brought up to oppose
                        Hannibal, was a pretty clear proof that either that force was adequate for
                        the defence of Rome or that all hope of its defence must be abandoned.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, one consul, depressed
                        after his cavalry defeat, and also by his wound, would rather that battle
                        should be deferred. The other, whose courage had suffered no check and was
                        therefore all the more eager to fight, was impatient of any delay.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The country between the Trebia and the
                        Po was inhabited by Gauls who in this struggle between two mighty peoples
                        showed impartial goodwill to either side, with the view, undoubtedly, of
                        winning the victor's gratitude. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans
                        were quite satisfied with this neutrality if only it was maintained and the
                        Gauls kept quiet, but Hannibal was extremely indignant, as he was constantly
                        giving out that he had been invited by the Gauls to win their freedom.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Feelings of resentment and, at the
                        same time, a desire to enrich his soldiers with plunder prompted him to send
                        2000 infantry and 1000 cavalry, made up of Gauls and Numidians, mostly the
                        latter, with orders to ravage the whole country, district after district,
                        right up to the banks of the Po. Though the Gauls had hitherto <milestone
                            n="6??" unit="section"/> maintained an impartial attitude, they were
                        compelled in their need of help to turn from those who had inflicted these
                        outrages to those who they hoped would avenge them. They sent envoys to the
                        consuls to beg the Romans to come to the rescue of a land which was
                        suffering because its people had been too loyal to Rome. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Cornelius Scipio did not consider that either the
                        grounds alleged or the circumstances justified his taking action. He
                        regarded that nation with suspicion on account of their many acts of
                        treachery, and even if their past faithlessness could have been forgotten
                        through lapse of time, he could not forget the recent treachery of the Boii.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Sempronius, on the other hand, was of
                        opinion that the most effective means of preserving the fidelity of their
                        allies was to defend those who first asked for their help. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> As his colleague still hesitated, he sent his own
                        cavalry supported by about a thousand javelin men to protect the territory
                        of the Gauls on the other side of the Trebia. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> They attacked the enemy suddenly whilst they were
                        scattered and in disorder, most of them loaded with plunder, and after
                        creating a great panic amongst them, and inflicting severe losses upon them,
                        they drove them in flight to their camp. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        The fugitives were driven back by their comrades who poured in great numbers
                        out of the camp, and thus reinforced they renewed the fighting. The battle
                        wavered as each side retired or pursued, and up to the last the action was
                        undecided. The enemy lost more men; the Romans claimed the victory. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="53" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To no one in the whole army did the
                        victory appear more important or more decisive than to the consul himself.
                        What gave him especial pleasure was that he had proved superior in that arm
                        in which his colleague had been worsted. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        He saw that the spirits of his men were restored, and that there was no one
                        but his colleague who wished to delay battle; he believed that Scipio was
                        more sick in mind than in body, and that the thought of his wound made him
                        shrink from the dangers of the battlefield. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> "But we must not be infected by a sick man's lethargy. What will be
                        gained by further delay, or rather, by wasting time? Whom are we expecting
                        as our third consul; what fresh army are we looking for? <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The camp of the Carthaginians is in Italy, almost in
                        sight of the City. They are not aiming at Sicily and Sardinia, which they
                        lost after their defeats, nor the Spain which lies on this side the Ebro;
                        their sole object is to drive the Romans away from their ancestral soil,
                        from the land on which they were born. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        What groans our fathers would utter, accustomed as they were to warring
                        round the walls of Carthage, if they could see us, their descendants, with
                        two consuls and two consular armies, cowering in our camp in the very heart
                        of Italy, whilst the Carthaginian is annexing to his empire all between the
                        Alps and the Apennines." This was the way he spoke when sitting by his
                        incapacitated colleague, this the language he used before his soldiers as
                        though he were haranguing the Assembly. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        was urged on, too, by the near approach of the time for the elections, and
                        the fear that the war, if delayed, might pass into the hands of the new
                        consuls, as well as by the chance he had of monopolising all the glory of it
                        while his colleague was on the sick list. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        In spite, therefore, of the opposition of Cornelius he ordered the soldiers
                        to get ready for the coming battle. </p>
                    <p> Hannibal saw clearly what was the best course for the enemy to adopt, and
                        had very little hope that the consuls would do anything rash or ill-advised.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When, however, he found that what he
                        had previously learnt by hearsay was actually the case, namely, that one of
                        the consuls was a man of impetuous and headstrong character, and that he had
                        become still more so since the recent cavalry action, he had very little
                        doubt in his own mind that he would have a favourable opportunity of giving
                        battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was anxious not to lose a
                        moment, in order that he might fight whilst the hostile army was still raw
                        and the better of the two generals was incapacitated by his wound, and also
                        whilst the Gauls were still in a <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                        warlike mood, for he knew that most of them would follow him with less
                        alacrity the further they were dragged from their homes. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> These and similar considerations led him to hope that a
                        battle was imminent, and made him desirous of forcing an engagement if there
                        was any holding back on the other side. He sent out some Gauls to
                        reconnoitre-as Gauls were serving in both armies they could be most safely
                        trusted to find out what he wanted-and when they reported that the Romans
                        had prepared for battle, the Carthaginian began to look out for ground which
                        would admit of an ambuscade. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="54" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Between the two armies there was a stream
                        with very high banks which were overgrown with marshy grass and the brambles
                        and brushwood which are generally found on waste ground. After riding round
                        the place and satisfying himself from personal observation that it was
                        capable of concealing even cavalry, Hannibal, turning to his brother Mago,
                        said, "This will be the place for you to occupy. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Pick out of our whole force of cavalry and infantry a
                        hundred men from each arm, and bring them to me at the first watch, now it
                        is time for food and rest." He then dismissed his staff. Presently Mago
                        appeared with his 200 picked men. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> "I see
                        here," said Hannibal, "the very flower of my army, but you must be strong in
                        numbers as well as in courage. Each of you therefore go and choose nine
                        others like himself, from the squadrons and the maniples. Mago will show you
                        the place where you are to lie in ambuscade, you have an enemy who are
                        blindly ignorant of these practices in war." <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> After sending Mago with his 1000 infantry and 1000 cavalry to take up his
                        position, Hannibal gave orders for the Numidian cavalry to cross the Trebia
                        in the early dawn and ride up to the gates of the Roman camp; then they were
                        to discharge their missiles on the outposts and so goad the enemy on to
                        battle. When the fighting had once started they were gradually to give
                        ground and draw their pursuers to their own side of the river. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> These were the instructions to the Numidians; the
                        other commanders, both infantry and cavalry, were ordered to see that all
                        their men had breakfast, after which they were to wait for the signal, the
                        men fully armed, the horses saddled and ready. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Eager for battle, and having already made up his mind
                        to fight, Sempronius led out the whole of his cavalry to meet the Numidian
                        attack, for it was in his cavalry that he placed most confidence; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> these were followed by 6000 infantry and at last
                        the whole of his force marched on to the field. It happened to be the season
                        of winter, a snowstorm was raging, and the district, situated between the
                        Alps and the Apennines, was rendered especially cold by the vicinity of
                        rivers and marshes. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To make matters worse,
                        men and horses alike had been hurriedly sent forward, without any food,
                        without any protection against the cold, so they had no heat in them and the
                        chilling blasts from the river made the cold still more severe as they
                        approached it in their pursuit of the Numidians. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> But when they entered the water which had been swollen
                        by the night's rain and was then breast high, their limbs became stiff with
                        cold, and when they emerged on the other side they had hardly strength to
                        hold their weapons; they began to grow faint from fatigue and as the day
                        wore on, from hunger. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="55" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal's men, meanwhile, had made fires
                        in front of their tents, oil had been distributed amongst the maniples for
                        them to make their joints and limbs supple and they had time for an ample
                        repast. When it was announced that the enemy had crossed the river they took
                        their arms, feeling alert and active in mind and body, and marched to
                        battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Balearic and light-armed
                        infantry were posted in front of the standards; they numbered about 8000;
                        behind them the heavy-armed infantry, the mainstay and backbone of the army;
                        on the flanks Hannibal distributed the cavalry, and outside them, again, the
                        elephants. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the consul saw his
                        cavalry, who had lost their order in the pursuit, suddenly meeting with an
                        unsuspected resistance from the Numidians, he recalled them by signal and
                        received them within his infantry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There
                        were 18,000 Romans, 20,000 Latin allies, and an auxiliary force of Cenomani,
                        the only Gallic tribe which had remained faithful. These were the forces
                        engaged. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Balearics and light infantry
                        opened the battle, but on being met by the heavier legions they were rapidly
                        withdrawn to the wings, an evolution which at once threw the Roman horse
                        into difficulties, for the 4000 wearied troopers had been unable to offer an
                        effective resistance to 10,000 who <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> were
                        fresh and vigorous, and now in addition they were overwhelmed by what seemed
                        a cloud of missiles from the light infantry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Moreover, the elephants, towering aloft at the ends of the line,
                        terrified the horses not only by their appearance but by their unaccustomed
                        smell, and created widespread panic. The infantry battle, as far as the
                        Romans were concerned, was maintained more by courage than by physical
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> strength, for the Carthaginians, who
                        had shortly before been getting themselves into trim, brought their powers
                        fresh and unimpaired into action, whilst the Romans were fatigued and hungry
                        and stiff with cold. Still, their courage would have kept them up had it
                        been only infantry that they were fighting against. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> But the light infantry, after repulsing the cavalry,
                        were hurling their missiles on the flanks of the legions; the elephants had
                        now come up against the centre of the Roman line, and Mago and his
                        Numidians, as soon as it had passed their ambuscade, rose up in the rear and
                        created a terrible disorder and panic. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Yet in spite of all the dangers which surrounded them, the ranks stood firm
                        and immovable for some time, even, contrary to all expectation, against the
                        elephants. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Some skirmishers who had been
                        placed where they could attack these animals flung darts at them and drove
                        them off, and rushed after them, stabbing them under their tails, where the
                        skin is soft and easily penetrated. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="56" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Maddened with pain and terror, they were
                        beginning to rush wildly on their own men, when Hannibal ordered them to be
                        driven away to the left wing against the auxiliary Gauls on the Roman right.
                        There they instantly produced unmistakable panic and flight, and the Romans
                        had fresh cause for .alarm when they saw their auxiliaries routed.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They now stood fighting in a square,
                        and about 10,000 of them, unable to escape in any other direction, forced
                        their way through the centre of the African troops and the auxiliary Gauls
                        who supported them and inflicted an immense loss on the enemy. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> They were prevented by the river from returning
                        to their camp, and the rain made it impossible for them to judge where they
                        could best go to the assistance of their comrades, so they marched away
                        straight to Placentia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then desperate
                        attempts to escape were made on all sides; some who made for the river were
                        swept away by the current or caught by the enemy while hesitating to cross;
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> others, scattered over the fields in
                        flight, followed the track of the main retreat and sought Placentia; others,
                        fearing the enemy more than the river, crossed it and reached their camp.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The driving sleet and the intolerable
                        cold caused the death of many men and baggage animals, and nearly all the
                        elephants perished. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians
                        stopped their pursuit at the banks of the Trebia and returned to their camp
                        so benumbed with cold that they hardly felt any joy in their victory.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the night the men who had guarded
                        the camp, and the rest of the soldiers, mostly wounded, crossed the Trebia
                        on rafts without any interference from the Carthaginians, either because the
                        roaring of the storm prevented them from hearing or because they were unable
                        to move through weariness and wounds and pretended that they heard nothing.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Whilst the Carthaginians were keeping
                        quiet, Scipio led his army to Placentia and thence across the Po to Cremona,
                        in order that one colony might not be burdened with providing winter
                        quarters for the two armies. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="57" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This defeat so unnerved people in Rome
                        that they believed the enemy was already advancing to attack the City, and
                        that there was no help to be looked for, no hope of repelling him from their
                        walls and gates. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After one consul had been
                        beaten at the Ticinus the other was recalled from Sicily, and now both
                        consuls and both consular armies had been worsted. What fresh generals, men
                        asked, what fresh legions could be brought to the rescue? Amidst this
                        universal panic Sempronius arrived. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He had
                        slipped through the enemy's cavalry at immense risk while they were
                        dispersed in quest of plunder, and owed his escape rather to sheer audacity
                        than to cleverness, for he had little hope of eluding them or of successful
                        resistance if he failed to do so. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After
                        conducting the elections, which was the pressing need for the moment, he
                        returned to winter quarters. The consuls elected were Cneius Servilius and
                        C. Flaminius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even in their winter
                        quarters the Romans were not allowed much quiet; the Numidian horse were
                        roaming in all directions, or where the ground was too rough for them, the
                        Celtiberians and Lusitanians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were,
                        therefore, cut off from supplies on every side, except what were brought in
                        ships on the Po. Near Placentia there was a place called Emporium, which had
                        been carefully fortified and occupied by a strong garrison. In the hope of
                        capturing the place, Hannibal approached with cavalry and light-armed
                        troops, and as he trusted mainly to secrecy for success, he marched thither
                        by night. But he did not escape the observation of the sentinels, and such a
                        shouting suddenly arose that it was actually heard at Placentia. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> By daybreak the consul was on the spot with his
                        cavalry, having given orders for the legions of infantry to follow in battle
                        formation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A cavalry action followed in
                        which Hannibal was wounded, and his retirement from the field discomfited
                        the enemy; the position was admirably defended. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After taking only a few days' rest, before
                        his wound was thoroughly healed Hannibal proceeded to attack Victumviae.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During the Gaulish war this place had
                        served as an emporium for the Romans; subsequently, as it was a fortified
                        place, a mixed population from the surrounding country had settled there in
                        considerable numbers, and now the terror created by the constant
                        depredations had driven most of the people from the fields into the town.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This motley population, excited by
                        the news of the energetic defence of Placentia, flew to arms and went out to
                        meet Hannibal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> More like a crowd than an
                        army they met him on his march, and as on the one side there was nothing but
                        an undisciplined mob, and on the other a general and soldiers who had
                        perfect confidence in each other, a small body routed as many as 35,000 men.
                        The next day they surrendered and admitted a Carthaginian garrison within
                        their walls. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They had just completed the
                        surrender of their arms in obedience to orders, when instructions were
                        suddenly given to the victors to treat the city as though it had been
                        carried by storm, and no deed of blood, which on such occasions historians
                        are wont to mention, was left undone, <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/>
                        so awful was the example set of every form of licentiousness and cruelty and
                        brutal tyranny towards the wretched inhabitants. Such were the winter
                        operations of Hannibal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="58" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The soldiers rested whilst the intolerable
                        cold lasted; it did not, however, last long, and at the first doubtful
                        indications of <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> spring Hannibal left his
                        winter quarters for Etruria with the intention of inducing that nation to
                        join forces with him, either voluntarily or under compulsion. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> During his passage of the Apennines he was
                        overtaken by a storm of such severity as almost to surpass the horrors of
                        the Alps. The rain was driven by the wind straight into the men's faces, and
                        either they had to drop their weapons or if they tried to struggle against
                        the hurricane it caught them and dashed them to the ground, so they came to
                        a halt. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then they found that it was
                        stopping their respiration so that they could not breathe, and they sat down
                        for a short time with their backs to the wind. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The heavens began to reverberate with terrific roar,
                        and amidst the awful din lightning flashed and quivered. Sight and sound
                        alike paralysed them with terror. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At last,
                        as the force of the gale increased owing to the rain having ceased, they saw
                        that there was nothing for it but to pitch their camp on the ground where
                        they had been caught by the storm. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Now all
                        their labour had to begin over again, for they could neither unroll anything
                        nor fix anything, whatever was fixed did not stand, the wind tore everything
                        into shreds and carried it off. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Soon the
                        moisture in the upper air above the cold mountain peaks froze and discharged
                        such a shower of snow and hail that the men, giving up all further attempts,
                        lay down as best they could, buried beneath their coverings rather than
                        protected by them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This was followed by
                        such intense cold that when any one attempted to rise out of that pitiable
                        crowd of prostrate men and beasts it was a long time before he could get up,
                        for his muscles being cramped and stiff with cold, he could hardly bend his
                        limbs. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At length, by exercising their
                        arms and legs, they were able to move about, and began to recover their
                        spirits; here and there fires were lighted, and those who were most helpless
                        turned to their colleagues for help. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They
                        remained on that spot for two days like a force blockaded; many men and
                        animals perished; of the elephants which survived the battle of the Trebia
                        they lost seven. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="59" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After descending from the Apennines
                        Hannibal advanced towards Placentia, and after a ten miles' march formed
                        camp. The following day he marched against the enemy with 12,000 infantry
                        and 5000 cavalry. Sempronius had by this time returned from Rome, and he did
                        not decline battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That day the two camps
                        were three miles distant from each other; the following day they fought, and
                        both sides exhibited the most determined courage, but the action was
                        indecisive. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the first encounter the
                        Romans were so far superior that they not only conquered in the field, but
                        followed the routed enemy to his camp and soon made an attack upon it.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal stationed a few men to defend
                        the rampart and the gates, the rest he massed in the middle of the camp, and
                        ordered them to be on the alert and wait for the signal to make a sortie.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was now about three o'clock; the
                        Romans were worn out with their fruitless efforts as there was no hope of
                        carrying the camp, and the consul gave the signal to retire. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as Hannibal heard it and saw that the
                        fighting had slackened and that the enemy were retiring from the camp, he
                        immediately launched his cavalry against them right and left, and sallied in
                        person with the main strength of his infantry from the middle of the camp.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Seldom has there been a more equal
                        fight, and few would have been rendered more memorable by the mutual
                        destruction of both armies had the daylight allowed it to be sufficiently
                        prolonged; as it was, night put an end to a conflict which had been
                        maintained with such determined courage. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        There was greater fury than bloodshed, and as the fighting had been almost
                        equal on both sides, they separated with equal loss. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Not more than 600 infantry and half that number of
                        cavalry fell on either side, but the Roman loss was out of proportion to
                        their numbers; several members of the equestrian order and five military
                        tribunes as well as three prefects of the allies were killed. Immediately
                        after the battle Hannibal withdrew into Liguria, and Sempronius to Luca.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Whilst Hannibal was entering Liguria,
                        two Roman quaestors who had been ambushed and captured, C. Fulvius and L.
                        Lucretius, together with three military tribunes and five members of the
                        equestrian order, most of them sons of senators, were given up to him by the
                        Gauls in order that he might feel more confidence in their maintenance of
                        peaceful relations, and their determination to give him active support. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="60" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were in progress in
                        Italy, Cn. Cornelius Scipio, who had been sent with a fleet and an army to
                        Spain, commenced operations in that country. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Starting from the mouth of the Rhone, he sailed round the eastward end of
                        the Pyrenees and brought up at Emporiae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Here he disembarked his army, and beginning with the Laeetani, he brought
                        the whole of the maritime populations as far as the Ebro within the sphere
                        of Roman influence by renewing old alliances and forming new ones.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He gained in this way a reputation for
                        clemency which extended not only to the maritime populations but to the more
                        warlike tribes in the interior and the mountain districts. He established
                        peaceable relations with these, and more than that, he secured their support
                        in arms and several strong cohorts were enrolled from amongst them.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The country on this side the Ebro was
                        Hanno's province, Hannibal had left him to hold it for Carthage. Considering
                        that he ought to oppose Scipio's further progress before the whole province
                        was under Roman sway, he fixed his camp in full view of the enemy and
                        offered battle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman general, too,
                        thought that battle ought not to be delayed; he knew he would have to fight
                        both Hanno and Hasdrubal, and preferred dealing with each singly rather than
                        meeting them both at once.. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The battle was
                        not a hard-fought one. The enemy lost 6000; 2000, including those who were
                        guarding the camp, were made prisoners; the camp itself was carried and the
                        general with some of his chiefs was taken; Cissis, a town near the camp, was
                        successfully attacked. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The plunder,
                        however, as it was a small place, was of little value, consisting mainly of
                        the barbarians' household goods and some worthless slaves. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The camp, however, enriched the soldiers with the
                        property belonging not only to the army they had defeated but also to the
                        one serving with Hannibal in Italy. They had left almost all their valuable
                        possessions on the other side of the Pyrenees, that they might not have
                        heavy loads to carry. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="61" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before he had received definite tidings of
                        this defeat, Hasdrubal had crossed the Ebro with 8000 infantry and 1000
                        cavalry, hoping to encounter the Romans as soon as they landed, but after
                        hearing of the disaster at Cissis and the capture of the camp, he turned his
                        route to the sea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not far from Tarracona
                        he found our marines and seamen wandering at will through the fields,
                        success as usual producing carelessness. Sending his cavalry in all
                        directions amongst them, he made a great slaughter and drove them pell-mell
                        to their ships. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Afraid to remain any
                        longer in the neighbourhood lest he should be surprised by Scipio, he
                        retreated across the Ebro. On hearing of this fresh enemy Scipio came down
                        by forced <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> marches, and after dealing
                        summary punishment to some of the naval captains, returned by sea to
                        Emporiae, leaving a small garrison in Tarracona. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He had scarcely left when Hasdrubal appeared on the
                        scene, and instigated the Ilergetes, who had given hostages to Scipio, to
                        revolt, and in conjunction with the warriors of that tribe ravaged the
                        territories of those tribes who remained loyal to Rome. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> This roused Scipio from his winter quarters, on which
                        Hasdrubal again disappeared beyond the Ebro, and Scipio invaded in force the
                        territory of the Ilergetes, after the author of the revolt had left them to
                        their fate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He drove them all into
                        Antanagrum, their capital, which he proceeded to invest, and a few days
                        later he received them into the protection and jurisdiction of Rome, after
                        demanding an increase in the number of hostages and inflicting a heavy fine
                        upon them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From there he advanced against
                        the Ausetani, who lived near the Ebro and were also in alliance with the
                        Carthaginians, and invested their city. The Laeetani whilst bringing
                        assistance to their neighbours by night were ambushed not far from the city
                        which they intended to enter. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As many as
                        12,000 were killed, almost all the survivors threw away their arms and fled
                        to their homes in scattered groups all over the country. The only thing
                        which saved the invested city from assault and storm was the severity of the
                        weather. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For the thirty days during which
                        the siege lasted the snow was seldom less than four feet deep, and it
                        covered up the mantlets and vineae so completely that it even served as a
                        sufficient protection against the firebrands which the enemy discharged from
                        time to time. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At last, after their chief,
                        Amusicus, had escaped to Hasdrubal's quarters, they surrendered and agreed
                        to pay an indemnity of twenty talents. The army returned to its winter
                        quarters at Tarracona. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="62" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this winter many portents occurred
                        in Rome and the neighbourhood, or at all events, many were reported and
                        easily gained credence, for when once men's minds have been excited by
                        superstitious fears they easily believe these things. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> A six-months-old child, of freeborn parents, is said to
                        have shouted "Io Triumphe" in the vegetable market, whilst in the Forum
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> Boarium an ox is reported to have
                        climbed up of its own accord to the third story of a house, and then,
                        frightened by the noisy crowd which gathered, it threw itself down.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A phantom navy was seen shining in the
                        sky; the temple of Hope in the vegetable market was struck by lightning; at
                        Lanuvium Juno's spear had moved of itself, and a crow had flown down to her
                        temple and settled upon her couch; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> in the
                        territory of Amiternum beings in human shape and clothed in white were seen
                        at a distance, but no one came close to them; in the neighbourhood of
                        Picenum there was a shower of stones; at Caere the oracular tablets had
                        shrunk in size; in Gaul a wolf had snatched a sentinel's sword from its
                        scabbard and run off with it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With regard
                        to the other portents, the decemvirs were ordered to consult the Sacred
                        Books, but in the case of the shower of stones at Picenum a nine days'
                        sacred feast was proclaimed, at the close of which almost the whole
                        community busied itself with the expiation of the others. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> First of all the City was purified, and full-grown
                        victims were sacrificed to the deities named in the Sacred Books; an
                        offering of forty pounds' weight of gold was conveyed to Juno at Lanuvium,
                        and the matrons dedicated a bronze statue of that goddess on the Aventine.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At Caere, where the tablets had
                        shrunk, a lectisternium was enjoined, and a service of intercession was to
                        be rendered to Fortuna on Algidus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In Rome
                        also a lectisternium was ordered for Juventas and a special service of
                        intercession at the temple of Hercules, and afterwards one in which the
                        whole population were to take part at all the shrines. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Five full-grown victims were sacrificed to the Genius
                        of Rome, and C. Atilius Serranus, the praetor, received instructions to
                        undertake certain vows which were to be discharged should the commonwealth
                        remain in the same condition for ten years. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> These ceremonial observances and vows, ordered in obedience to the Sacred
                        Books, did much to allay the religious fears of the people. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="63" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One of the consuls elect was C. Flaminius,
                        and to him was assigned by lot the command of the legions at Placentia. He
                        wrote to the consul giving orders for the army to be in camp at Ariminum by
                        the 15th of March. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The reason was that he
                        might enter upon his office there, for he had not forgotten his old quarrels
                        with the senate, first as tribune of the people, then afterwards about his
                        consulship, the election to which had been declared illegal, and finally
                        about his triumph. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He further embittered
                        the senate against him by his support of C. Claudius; he alone of all the
                        members was in favour of the measure which that tribune introduced. Under
                        its provisions no senator, no one whose father had been a senator, was
                        allowed to possess a vessel of more than 300 amphorae burden. This was
                        considered quite large enough for the conveyance of produce from their
                        estates, all profit made by trading was regarded as dishonourable for the
                        patricians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The question excited the
                        keenest opposition and brought Flaminius into the worst possible odium with
                        the nobility through his support of it, but on the other hand made him a
                        popular favourite and procured for him his second consulship. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Suspecting, therefore, that they would endeavour
                        to detain him in the City by various devices, such as falsifying the
                        auspices or the delay necessitated by the Latin Festival, or other
                        hindrances to which as consul he was liable, he gave out that he had to take
                        a journey, and then left the City secretly as a private individual and so
                        reached his province. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When this got abroad
                        there was a fresh outburst of indignation on the part of the incensed
                        senate; they declared that he was carrying on war not only with the senate
                        but even with the immortal gods. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "On the
                        former occasion," they said, "when he was elected consul against the
                        auspices and we recalled him from the very field of battle, he was
                        disobedient to gods and men. Now he is conscious that he has despised them
                        and has fled from the Capitol and the customary recital of solemn vows.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He refuses to approach the temple of
                        Jupiter Optimus Maximus on the day of his entrance upon office, to see and
                        consult the senate, to whom he is so odious and whom he alone of all men
                        detests, to proclaim the Latin Festival and offer sacrifice to Jupiter
                        Latiaris on the <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> Alban Mount, to proceed
                        to the Capitol and after duly taking the auspices recite the prescribed
                        vows, and from thence, vested in the paludamentum and escorted by lictors,
                        go in state to his province. He has stolen away furtively without his
                        insignia of office, without his lictors, just as though he were some menial
                        employed in the camp and had quitted his native soil to go into exile.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He thinks it, forsooth, more
                        consonant with the greatness of his office to enter upon it at Ariminum
                        rather than in Rome, and <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> to put on his
                        official dress in some wayside inn rather than at his own hearth and in the
                        presence of his own household gods." <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It
                        was unanimously decided that he should be recalled, brought back if need be
                        by force, and compelled to discharge, on the spot, all the duties he owed to
                        God and man before he went to the army and to his province. Q. Terentius and
                        M. Antistius were delegated for this task, but they had no more influence
                        with him than the despatch of the senate in his former consulship.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A few days afterwards he entered upon
                        office, and whilst offering his sacrifice, the calf, after it was struck,
                        bounded away out of the hands of the sacrificing priests and bespattered
                        many of the bystanders with its blood. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Amongst those at a distance from the altar who did not know what the
                        commotion was about there was great excitement; most people regarded it as a
                        most alarming omen. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Flaminius took over
                        the two legions from Sempronius, the late consul, and the two from C.
                        Atilius, the praetor, and commenced his march to Etruria through the passes
                        of the Apennines. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
