<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab urbe condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 21-22 - 21</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Boooks XXI-XXII With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1929: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.3"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="book">
                <head>Book XXI</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> IN this preface to a part of my history I may
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218-201</note>
                    properly assert what many an historian has declared at the outset of his entire
                    work, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Thucydides began his history as
                        follows: <quote> Thucydides, an Athenian, wrote the history of the war which
                            the Peloponnesians and Athenians waged against one another, beginning at
                            its very outset, in the expectation that it would be a great war and
                            more worthy of relation than any that had preceded it. </quote>
                    </note> to wit, that the war which I am going to describe was the most memorable
                    of all wars ever waged —the war, that is, which, under the leadership of
                    Hannibal, the Carthaginians waged with the Roman People. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For neither have states or nations met in arms possessed of
                    ampler resources, nor was their own might and power ever so great. Nor yet were
                    they strangers to one another's modes of fighting, which the First Punic War had
                    made them understand. And so variable were the fortunes of the war and so
                    uncertain was its outcome that those who ultimately conquered had been nearer
                    ruin. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The animosity, too, with which they
                    fought was almost greater than their strength: the Romans were enraged that the
                    conquered should be actually drawing sword upon their conquerors; the
                    Phoenicians, because they believed that the conquered had been treated with
                    domineering arrogance and greed. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.5"/>
                <p> It is said moreover that when Hannibal, then <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218-201</note> about nine years old,
                    was childishly teasing his father Hamilcar to take him with him into Spain, his
                    father, who had finished the African war and was sacrificing, before crossing
                    over with his army, led the boy up to the altar and made him touch the offerings
                    and bind himself with an oath that so soon as he should be able he would be the
                    declared enemy of the Roman People. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The loss
                    of Sicily and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        241</note> Sardinia was a continual torture to the proud spirit of Hamilcar.
                    For he maintained that they had surrendered Sicily <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the western part of the island, which had been
                        in the possession of the Carthaginians at the beginning of the First Punic
                        War. </note> in premature despair, and that the Romans had wrongfully
                    appropriated Sardinia — and even imposed an indemnity on them besides —in the
                    midst of their African disturbances. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tormented by these thoughts, he so bore <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 237-229</note>
                    himself in the African War, which followed hard upon the Roman peace and lasted
                    for five years, and likewise afterwards, during the nine years he spent in Spain
                    in extending the Punic empire, that it was plain to see that he meditated a more
                    important war than the one he was engaged in, and that if his life had been
                    prolonged, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the Phoenicians would have
                    invaded Italy under the leadership of Hamilcar, as they did in fact under that
                    of Hannibal. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hamilcar's very timely death and the boyhood
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 229-222</note>
                    of Hannibal delayed the war. In the interval betwixt father and son, the supreme
                    command devolved, for about eight years, on Hasdrubal. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It was his youthful beauty, they say, that won for him in
                    the first instance the favour of Hamilcar, who subsequently selected him, no
                    doubt for other, that is mental, qualifications, to be his son-in-law. As such
                    —through the influence of the Barcine <pb n="p.7"/> faction <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was the war-party in Carthage,
                        named for its leader Hamilcar Barca, which opposed the peace-at-any-price
                        policy of the merchant-aristocracy. </note> which was very strong with the
                    soldiers <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        229-222</note> and the common people —he was given the command, though the
                    leading citizens had no liking for this step. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Relying more often on policy than force, Hasdrubal enlarged the sway of Carthage
                    rather by setting up friendly relations with the petty kings and winning over
                    new tribes through the goodwill of their leaders than by war and arms.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But he was not a whit more safe for being
                    at peace. A certain barbarian slew him openly, to avenge his master, whom
                    Hasdrubal had put to death. On being seized by the bystanders he expressed in
                    his countenance the cheerfulness of one who had escaped, and even as he was
                    being tortured, joy so got the upper hand of agony that he seemed actually to
                    smile. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With this Hasdrubal, because of the
                    marvellous skill which he had shown in tempting the native tribes to join his
                    empire, the Roman People had renewed their covenant, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the treaty of <date when="-0241">241
                            B.C.</date> ( <hi rend="italics">Per.</hi> XX. and Chap. xix. §§ 1-5).
                    </note> with <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        226</note> the stipulation that neither side should extend its dominion
                    beyond the Ebro, while the Saguntines, situated between the empires of the two
                    peoples, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Saguntum (Murviedro) lay
                        about midway between the Ebro and New Carthage (Cartagena). Livy does not
                        mean that it lay between the two <quote>spheres of influence</quote> —for it
                        must, in that case, have occupied an island in the Ebro —but, vaguely, that
                        the Carthaginians were still far to the south of it and the Romans had not
                        yet approached it from the north. </note> should be preserved in
                    independence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For Hasdrubal's successor there could be no
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 221</note>
                    question but that the choice originating with the soldiers —who immediately bore
                    young Hannibal into the praetorium and with loud and universal acclamation
                    hailed him general —would obtain the ratification of the senate. The approval of
                    the <pb n="p.9"/> commons followed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The new
                    commander had been <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        221</note> summoned to Spain by Hasdrubal when a mere lad, and the matter
                    had even been debated in the senate. The Barcine party were urging that Hannibal
                    should become inured to warfare and succeed to the resources of his father, when
                    Hanno, the leader of the other faction, addressed the House. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>There is reason,</quote> said he, <quote>in Hasdrubal's request,
                        nevertheless I am opposed to granting it.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When astonishment at a speech so inconsistent
                    had attracted everybody's attention, he continued: <quote> The youthful charms
                        which Hasdrubal himself permitted Hannibal's father to enjoy he considers
                        that he has the right to require again at the hands of the son. But that we
                        should accustom our young men, by way of military training, to gratify the
                        concupiscence of our generals is most unseemly. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Or do we fear lest Hamilcar's son may too late behold
                        the inordinate powers and the regal pomp which his father has set up? that
                        the son of the king who left our armies as a legacy to his son-in-law may
                        find us too slow in accepting him for our master? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> For my part, I think that the young man should be kept
                        at home and taught to live in submission to the laws and the magistrates,
                        upon an equal footing with the others, lest one day this small fire kindle a
                        great conflagration. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few, and these included nearly all the best
                    men, supported Hanno, but, as often happens, the larger party prevailed over the
                    better. Hannibal was sent to Spain, where he was no sooner come than he won the
                    favour of the entire army. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The old soldiers
                    thought that Hamilcar was restored to them as he had been in his youth; they
                    beheld <pb n="p.11"/> the same lively expression and piercing eye, tile <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 221</note> same cast
                    of countenance and features. But he soon brought it to pass that his likeness to
                    his father was the least consideration in gaining him support. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Never was the same nature more adaptable to things the most
                    diverse —obedience and command. And so one could not readily have told whether
                    he were dearer to the general or the army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    When any bold or difficult deed was to be done, there was no one whom Hasdrubal
                    liked better to entrust with it, nor did any other leader inspire his men with
                    greater confidence or daring. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To reckless
                    courage in incurring dangers he united the greatest judgment when in the midst
                    of them. No toil could exhaust his body or overcome his spirit. Of heat and cold
                    he was equally tolerant. His consumption of meat and drink was determined by
                    natural desire, not by pleasure. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His times of
                    waking and sleeping were not marked off by day or night: <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> what time remained when his work was done he gave to sleep,
                    which he did not court with a soft bed or stillness, but was seen repeatedly by
                    many lying on the ground wrapped in a common soldier's cloak amongst the
                    sentinels and outguards. His dress was in no way superior to that of his
                    fellows, but his arms and horses were conspicuous. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Both of horsemen and of foot-soldiers he was undoubtedly
                    the first —foremost to enter battle, and last to leave it when the fighting had
                    begun. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These admirable qualities of the man
                    were equalled by his monstrous vices: his cruelty was inhuman, his perfidy worse
                    than Punic; he had no regard for truth, and none for sanctity, no fear of the
                    gods, no reverence for an oath, no religious scruple. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> With this endowment of <pb n="p.13"/> good and evil traits
                    he served for the space of three <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 221</note> years under Hasdrubal, omitting nothing that
                    should be done or seen by one who was to become a great commander. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For the rest, from the day on which he was
                    proclaimed commander-in-chief, as though Italy had been assigned to him for his
                    field of operations and he <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> had been
                    instructed to make war on Rome, he felt that no postponement was permissible,
                    lest he too, like his father Hamilcar, and afterwards Hasdrubal, should be
                    overtaken, while delaying, by some accident, and resolved upon attacking the
                    Saguntines. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Up to this point it is
                        probable that Livy has been drawing his material chiefly from Coelius
                        Antipater. He now turns to Polybius (or an account based on Polybius), and
                        somewhat awkwardly effects the transition by means of the sentence
                        following, in which he tries to smooth over the contradiction between <hi
                            rend="italics">nihil prolatandum ratus</hi> and the two years that
                        Hannibal now spent in wars that had nothing to do with the Saguntines. ( <hi
                            rend="italics">De Sanctis,</hi> p. 182.) </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But since an attack on them must certainly
                    provoke the Romans to hostile action, he marched first into the territory of the
                    Olcades —a tribe living south of the Ebro, within the limits of the
                    Carthaginians but not under their dominion —that he might appear not to have
                    aimed at the Saguntines but to have been drawn into that war by a chain of
                    events, as he conquered the neighbouring nations and annexed their territories.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Cartala, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This place —unknown except for its mention in this
                        connexion —is called Althaea by Polybius (III. xiii. 5) The name is perhaps
                        preserved in the modern Melkart. </note> a wealthy town, the capital of that
                    tribe, he stormed and sacked; and this so terrified the lesser towns that they
                    submitted and agreed to an indemnity. The victorious army, enriched with spoil,
                    was led back to New Carthage for <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the winter.
                    There, by a generous partition of the booty and the faithful discharge of all
                    arrears of pay, he confirmed them all, both citizens and allies, in their
                    allegiance to himself; and early in the spring pushed forward into the land of
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the Vaccaei. Their cities, Hermandica
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Supposed to have stood on the site
                        of Salamanca.</note> and <pb n="p.15"/> Arbocala, were taken by assault.
                    Arbocala, thanks to the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 221</note> bravery and numbers of its inhabitants, held out for a
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> long time. The fugitives from Hermandica,
                    uniting with the exiles of the <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Olcades —the
                    tribe which had been subdued in the previous summer —roused up the Carpetani,
                    and falling upon Hannibal as he was returning from the Vaccaei, not far from the
                    river Tagus, threw his column, encumbered as it was with booty, into <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> some disorder. Hannibal refrained from battle and
                    encamped on the bank of the river. As soon as the enemy were settled for the
                    night and silent, he crossed the river by a ford, and so laid out his rampart as
                    to allow them room for crossing, resolving to attack them as they were
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> passing over. He ordered his cavalry to
                    charge their column of foot when they saw that it had <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> entered the stream, and posted the elephants, of which he
                    had forty, along the bank. The Carpetani, together with the contingents of the
                    Olcades and Vaccaei, numbered a hundred thousand —an invincible array, had they
                    been going to fight in a <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> fair field. And so,
                    inspired by a native intrepidity, confiding in their multitude, and believing
                    —since they supposed that their enemies had retreated out of fear —that victory
                    was delayed but till they should have passed the river, they broke into a cheer,
                    and, staying for no man's orders, rushed into the stream wherever it happened to
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> be nearest. From the other side a great
                    body of cavalry was sent in <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> against them. The
                    meeting in mid-channel was no equal conflict, for there the footmen were
                    unsteady, and, scarce trusting to the ford, might even have been overthrown by
                    unarmed riders, urging their horses forward at haphazard; while the horsemen,
                    having <pb n="p.17"/> their bodies and weapons free and horses that were <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 221</note> steady
                    even in the deep pools, could fight either at close quarters or <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> long range. A great part of them perished in the
                    stream; some the eddying current carried over to their enemies, where they were
                    trampled down by <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> the elephants. The rearmost,
                    who could retreat to their own bank more safely, were gathering from the various
                    directions in which they had fled, when, before they could recover from so great
                    a panic, Hannibal entered the stream in a fighting column, and driving them in
                    confusion from the bank, laid waste their fields, and in a few days' time
                    received the surrender of the <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Carpetani also.
                    And now everything south of the Ebro, except Saguntum, was in the hands of the
                    Carthaginians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the Saguntines there was as yet no war,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> but
                    quarrels that might be a pretext for it were already being sown betwixt them and
                    their neighbours, especially the Turdetani. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Not the important tribe in the S.W. part of the
                        peninsula, but a lesser one, again mentioned as neighbour to the Saguntines
                        at XXIV. lii. 11, and <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> —there called
                        Turduli —at XXVIII. xxxix. 8. </note> Now when the side of the Turdetani was
                    espoused by the same man who had sowed the quarrel, and it was clearly seen that
                    he was aiming not at arbitration but force, the Saguntines sent ambassadors to
                    Rome, imploring help for a war that was now <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    indubitably imminent. The Roman consuls at that time were Publius Cornelius
                    Scipio and Tiberius Sempronius Longus. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > These were the consuls of <date when="-0218">218 B.C.</date> , but the
                        siege of Saguntum took place in 219. Livy now returns to —and follows until
                        he has finished the story of the siege in chap. xv. § 1 —the source he had
                        used for the opening chapters of this hook. Coelius —if he it was —so
                        telescoped events as to make the attack on Saguntum follow immediately on
                        the appointment of Hannibal, and the war with Rome begin in that same year.
                        In chap. xv. Livy becomes aware of the discrepancy and endeavours to dispose
                        of it. </note> After introducing the ambassadors into the senate, they had
                    brought up the question of public policy, and the senators had voted to dispatch
                    envoys to Spain, <pb n="p.19"/> to examine into the affairs of their <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> allies, to the end <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> that, if there appeared to
                    be just cause, they might formally warn Hannibal to keep aloof from the
                    Saguntines, the allies of the Roman People; after which they were to cross over
                    into Africa, to Carthage, and <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> present the
                    complaint of Rome's allies. This embassy had been voted but not yet sent off,
                    when, sooner than all expectation, came the news that Saguntum was besieged. The
                    case was <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> then referred anew to the senate.
                    Some were for sending the consuls into Spain and Africa respectively and waging
                    war by land and sea; others wanted to direct their <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> whole force against Spain and Hannibal; some there were who
                    argued that so grave a quarrel should not be lightly entered on, and proposed to
                    await the return <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> of the envoys out of Spain.
                    This last opinion, which seemed the safest, carried the day, and the envoys,
                    Publius Valerius Flaccus and Quintus Baebius Tamphilus, were sent off with the
                    more dispatch. They were to go to Saguntum first, to Hannibal, and thence, if he
                    would not cease hostilities, to Carthage, to demand the surrender of the general
                    himself in satisfaction of the broken treaty. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the Romans were thus planning and
                    deliberating, the siege of Saguntum was already being pressed with the greatest
                    vigour. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This city was much the wealthiest of
                    those beyond the Ebro and was situated about a mile from the sea. Its
                    inhabitants are said to have come originally from the island of Zacynthus, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Saguntum is only a Latinized form of
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">,</foreign> the name of a small island (now
                        Zante) off the coast of Elis. </note> and to have included also a strain
                    from the Ardeate Rutulians. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Ardea
                        (the seat of King Turnus, according to Virgil, <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi>
                        VII. 409 ff.) was the chief city of the Rutuli and had been a Roman colony
                        since <date when="-0442">442 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Be this as it may, they had attained quickly
                    to their great prosperity, whether owing to the produce of the sea or the <pb
                        n="p.21"/> land, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius, III.
                        xviii. 3, speaks of the great fertility of their territory, and under the
                        empire Saguntum was famous for its export of earthenware. </note> to the
                    growth of their population, or to the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 219</note> integrity of their discipline, which caused
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> them to keep faith with their allies
                    even to their own undoing. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Crossing their
                    borders with a hostile army Hannibal laid waste their country far and wide and
                    advanced in three divisions against their city. There was an angle of the wall
                    that gave on a valley more open and more level than the other ground about the
                    town. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Against this he determined to bring up
                    pent-houses, that under their cover the battering-rams might be brought into
                    contact with the walls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But though the ground
                    at some distance from the wall was smooth enough for moving the pent-houses, the
                    attempt succeeded very ill when it came to the final execution of it. There was
                    a great overhanging tower, and the wall —as was natural in a suspected place
                    —had been carried up to a greater height than elsewhere, and the pick of the
                    fighting men having been stationed there, where the greatest danger threatened,
                    offered a more strenuous resistance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At first
                    they drove the assailants off with missiles and left no spot safe for their
                    pioneers; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> afterwards not only did their
                    javelins dart from wall and tower, but they even had the hardihood to sally out
                    against the pickets and earthworks of their enemies, and in these
                    rough-and-tumble fights hardly more Saguntines fell than Phoenicians. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> But when Hannibal himself, who had somewhat
                    incautiously ventured up under the wall, was severely wounded in the front of
                    his thigh with a heavy javelin and sank to the ground, those about him fell into
                    such confusion and dismay as almost to abandon their works and pent-houses. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For the next few days, while the general's <pb
                        n="p.23"/> hurt was healing, there was rather a blockade than <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> an
                    assault; but though during this interval there was rest from combat, yet was
                    there no slackening in the preparation of engines and defences. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the fighting broke out afresh more fiercely
                    than before, and pent-houses began to be pushed forward and rams brought up at
                    many points, though in some places the ground would hardly admit of them.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Phoenician was lavishly equipped with
                    men —he is credibly supposed to have had a hundred and fifty thousand under arms
                    —but <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the townsmen, who, in order to guard and
                    defend every quarter, had been divided into numerous companies, found their
                    strength inadequate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And so now the walls were
                    being battered with rams and in many places had been severely shaken. One
                    section, giving way continuously for some distance, had exposed the town: three
                    towers in a row, together with the wall connecting them, had come down with a
                    loud crash. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Phoenicians believed that the
                    town was taken with that breach, through which from either side men rushed to
                    attack, as though the wall had protected both parties alike. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> It was not at all like the mellays that commonly occur in
                    sieges, where one side gets an opportunity, but regular battle lines had formed,
                    as in an open field, between the ruins of the wall and the buildings of the
                    city, which stood at some distance off. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On
                    this side hope, on that despair inspired courage. The Phoenicians believed the
                    city to be theirs, if they put forth a little effort. The Saguntines opposed
                    their bodies to defend their city, denuded of its walls, nor would one of them
                    draw back his foot lest he admit an enemy to the spot which he had vacated.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And the harder both sides fought and <pb
                        n="p.25"/> the more they crowded in together, the greater was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> the number
                    of those wounded, for no missile fell without taking effect on shield or body.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Saguntines had a javelin, called a
                        <hi rend="italics">phalarica,</hi> with a shaft of fir, which was round
                    except at the end whence the iron projected; this part, four-sided as in the <hi
                        rend="italics">pilum,</hi> they wrapped with tow and smeared with pitch.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Now the iron was three feet long, that it
                    might be able to go through both shield and body. But what chiefly made it
                    terrible, even if it stuck fast in the shield and did not penetrate the body,
                    was this, that when it <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> had been lighted at
                    the middle and so hurled, the flames were fanned to a fiercer heat by its very
                    motion, and it forced the soldier to let go his shield, and left him unprotected
                    against the blows that followed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the outcome of the struggle had long been
                    doubtful, and the Saguntines, because they were holding out beyond their hopes,
                    had gained new courage, while the Phoenician, because he had not conquered, was
                    as good as beaten; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> suddenly the townspeople
                    set up a shout and thrust forth their enemies amongst the ruins of the wall, and
                    routing them out from thence, confused and frightened, drove them back at last
                    in full flight to their camp. </p>
                <p> In the meantime it was announced that ambassadors had come from Rome. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal sent men to the shore to meet them and say
                    that it would not be safe for them to come to him through the armed bands of so
                    many unruly tribes, and that he had no time for listening to embassies at so
                    critical a juncture. It was clear that, if they were denied a hearing, they
                    would at once proceed to <pb n="p.27"/> Carthage. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore dispatched couriers before <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> them, with
                    a letter for the leaders of the Barcine faction, so that they might prepare the
                    minds of their adherents to prevent the opposing party from affording any
                    satisfaction to the Roman People. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accordingly, save for being admitted and
                    allowed a hearing, this mission also was idle and of no effect. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Hanno stood alone in pleading for the treaty against the
                    views of the senate. There was a deep hush while he spoke, by reason of his
                    personal authority, but he was listened to without approval. He adjured the
                    senators in the name of the gods, vouchers for treaties and their witnesses, to
                    provoke not a Roman along with the Saguntine war. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He had advised them and forewarned them not to send the
                    offspring of Hamilcar to the army; neither the man's ghost nor his progeny was
                    at rest, nor ever, so long as any of the lineage and name of Barca should
                    survive, would the treaty with the Romans rest untroubled. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>You have sent to your armies,</quote> he went on, <quote> as though
                        heaping fuel on a fire, a youth who burns with lust for sovereign power and
                        sees but one way to obtain it —if, by sowing seeds of war, he can raise up
                        other wars and live girt round with arms and legions. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> You have therefore fed these flames with which you are
                        now ablaze. Your armies now invest Saguntum, which the treaty forbids them
                        to approach: ere long the Roman legions will be investing Carthage, led by
                        those very gods who helped them in the former war to avenge the broken
                        treaty. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Is it your enemy you know not, or
                        yourselves, or the fortunes of both peoples? When <pb n="p.29"/> ambassadors
                        came from allies on behalf of allies, <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> your worthy general
                        would not admit them to his camp, but thrust aside the law of nations;
                        nevertheless these men, being driven from a place where even an enemy's
                        envoys are admitted, have come to you. They seek amends in accordance with a
                        treaty. That the state may be void of offence, they demand the author of the
                        wrong, the man on whom they charge the guilt. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The more mildly they proceed, the more slowly they
                        begin, the more obstinate, I fear, when they <hi rend="italics">have</hi>
                        begun, will be their rage. Set Eryx and the Aegatian islands <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Off these islands C. Lutatius
                            Catulus won in <date when="-0241">241 B.C.</date> the naval victory
                            which decided the First Punic War ( <hi rend="italics">Per.</hi> XIX.).
                        </note> before your eyes, and all that you suffered by land and sea for four
                        and twenty years. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor was this boy your
                        leader, but Hamilcar himself, the father, a second Mars, as his partisans
                        will have it. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Hanno knows that
                            most of his hearers are against him, and <hi rend="italics">isti</hi>
                            (literally <quote>those men of yours</quote> ) means <quote>those who
                                guide your opinion,</quote>
                            <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the friends of Hannibal. </note> But we
                        could not keep our hands from Tarentum, that is, from Italy, as by treaty
                        bound, even as now we cannot keep them from Saguntum. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Gods therefore vanquished men, and that which had been
                        verbally disputed —which people of the twain had broken the treaty — the
                        outcome of the war, like an impartial judge, decided, and to those who had
                        the right granted the victory. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It is
                        Carthage against which Hannibal is now bringing up his pent-houses and
                        towers; it is the walls of Carthage he is battering with his rams.
                        Saguntum's walls —may my prophecy prove false! — will fall upon <hi
                            rend="italics">our</hi> heads, and the war we have entered upon with the
                        Saguntines we must carry on against the Romans. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> 'Shall we then surrender Hannibal?' someone will ask. I
                        know that my <pb n="p.31"/> influence is slight, because of my quarrel with
                        his <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note>
                        father; but I rejoiced when Hamilcar perished, for this reason, that were he
                        living, we should now be at war with Rome; <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> and this young man, who, like a fury, now brandishes the torch of war, I
                        loathe and abominate, and I hold, not only that he ought to be surrendered
                        in expiation of the broken treaty, but that, if none demanded him, he ought
                        to be deported to the farthest limits of land and sea —to be banished to a
                        place whence neither name nor fame of his could reach us, nor he be able to
                        vex the quiet of our state. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> My opinion is
                        this: we should send ambassadors at once to Rome, to give satisfaction to
                        the senate; and others to announce to Hannibal that he must withdraw his
                        army from Saguntum, and to hand over Hannibal himself to the Romans as the
                        treaty requires; a third embassy I would send to make restitution to the
                        Saguntines. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hanno had concluded, not a single person
                    found it necessary to oppose his arguments, so nearly unanimous was the senate
                    in supporting Hannibal. They declared that Hanno had spoken more bitterly than
                    Valerius Flaccus, the Roman envoy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They then
                    gave their answer to the envoys, to the effect that the war had been begun by
                    the Saguntines, not by Hannibal, and that the Roman People would be doing wrong
                    if they preferred the Saguntines to their very ancient alliance with the
                    Carthaginians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While the Romans were wasting time in
                    dispatching embassies, Hannibal had allowed his soldiers, exhausted as they were
                    with fighting and constructing works, to rest for a few days, after posting
                    outguards to look to the pent-houses and other engines. <pb n="p.33"/> Meanwhile
                    he kindled their ardour, now by inciting <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> them to rage against their
                    enemies, again by holding out hopes of rewards. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> But when he made a speech proclaiming that the spoils of the captured city
                    should go to the soldiers, they were so excited, one and all, that if the signal
                    had been given instantly, it seemed as if no force could have withstood them.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Saguntines, though they had had a rest
                    from fighting, neither attacking nor being attacked for several days, had
                    laboured incessantly, both day and night, to replace the wall where its collapse
                    had exposed the town. </p>
                <p> The assault was now resumed, with far greater fury than before, and it was hard
                    for the inhabitants to know, when shouts and cries were resounding on every
                    hand, to what point they should first, or preferably, bring up supports.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hannibal was present in person to urge on
                    his men, where they were pushing up a movable tower that surpassed in height all
                    the defences of the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as it had
                    been brought up, and the catapults and <hi rend="italics">ballistae</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Engines for hurling darts and
                        stones.</note> distributed through all its platforms had stripped the
                    ramparts of defenders, Hannibal, believing that he now had his opportunity, sent
                    about five hundred Africans with pickaxes to undermine the wall. This was no
                    hard task, for the rubble had not been solidified with mortar, but filled in
                    with mud, after an ancient mode of building. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It therefore fell for wider stretches than were actually hacked away, and
                    through the breaches bands of armed men passed into the city. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> They even seized an elevation, and setting up catapults and
                        <hi rend="italics">ballistae</hi> there, built a wall around it, so as to
                    have within the town itself a stronghold that commanded it like a citadel.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The <pb n="p.35"/> Saguntines too built a
                    wall within the old one, to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 219</note> protect that part of the city that was not yet
                    taken. On both sides the soldiers worked and fought with the utmost energy; but
                    the Saguntines, contracting their defences, were bringing their city day by day
                    within a smaller compass. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At the same time
                    there was an increasing scarcity of everything, on account of the long blockade;
                    and the prospect of help from without was growing less, <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> since the Romans, their only hope, were so far away, and
                    all the country round about was in the possession of their enemies. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Yet their drooping spirits were revived for a little
                    while by the sudden departure of Hannibal for the territories of the Oretani and
                    the Carpetani. These two nations, exasperated by a rigorous conscription, had
                    seized the recruiting officers and thereby given rise to fears of a revolt, but
                    were caught unprepared by Hannibal's celerity, and laid down the arms they had
                    taken up. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the siege of Saguntum did not flag.
                    Maharbal, the son of Himilco, whom Hannibal had left in charge, so bestirred
                    himself that the absence of the general was felt neither by his countrymen nor
                    by the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He fought a number of successful
                    skirmishes, and with three battering-rams laid low a considerable portion of the
                    wall, and on Hannibal's return, showed him the place all covered with the newly
                    fallen ruins. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And so the troops were led at
                    once against the citadel itself, and a fierce battle began, in which many on
                    both sides were killed and a part of the citadel was taken. </p>
                <p> An all but hopeless attempt to arrange a peace was then made by two men, Alco, a
                    Saguntine, and a Spaniard named Alorcus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Alco,
                    thinking that <pb n="p.37"/> something might be effected by entreaties, went
                    over to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note>
                    Hannibal in the night, without the knowledge of the Sanguntines. But finding
                    that tears were of no avail and that the terms obtainable were such as a
                    wrathful conqueror would impose, he changed from pleader to deserter, and
                    remained with the enemy, declaring that anybody who should treat for peace on
                    those conditions would be put to death. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    conditions were as follows: they must make restitution to the Turdetani, and,
                    delivering up all their gold and silver, quit their city with a single garment
                    each and take up their abode where the Phoenician should direct them. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> When Alco asserted that the Saguntines would not
                    accept such terms, Alorcus, affirming that where all else is conquered the heart
                    is conquered too, undertook the negotiation of a peace. He was at that time a
                    soldier in the service of Hannibal, but was officially recognized by the
                    Saguntines as their friend and guest. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The stranger in an ancient city had no commercial or legal status but had to
                        depend on the good offices of some citizen. Guest-friendship ( <hi
                            rend="italics">hospitium</hi> ) was a species of permanent (and even
                        hereditary) alliance entered into by two citizens of different states for
                        purposes of mutual comfort and protection in commercial and other
                        intercourse. When a city honoured a member of another state by formally
                        conferring upon him the title of <hi rend="italics">hospes publicus,</hi> it
                        gave him the right to entertainment at the public cost, and to buy and sell
                        and bring actions in the courts. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Openly surrendering his weapon to the
                    sentries, he passed the enemy's lines, and was conducted —by his own command
                    —before the Saguntine general. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A crowd of all
                    descriptions immediately flocked together there; but all save the senators were
                    sent away, and Alorcus, being permitted to address them, spoke as follows: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> If Alco, your own fellow citizen, after going to Hannibal to sue for
                        peace, had brought back to you the terms of peace which Hannibal offers,
                        this journey of mine would have been superfluous, <pb n="p.39"/> for I
                        should have come to you neither as Hannibal's <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> spokesman nor yet as a
                        deserter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But seeing that, whether through
                        your fault or his own, he has stopped behind with your enemy —his own if his
                        fears were feigned, yours if it is unsafe to bring you a true report —that
                        you might not be ignorant that terms there are upon which you may enjoy both
                        life and peace, I have come to you myself, having regard to the
                        long-standing friendship which subsists between us. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Moreover, that I say what I say for your sake and no
                        other's, you may take this as proof: so long as you held your ground with
                        your own forces, and expected to receive help from the Romans, I never
                        mentioned peace to you; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but now that you
                        have no longer any hope from Rome, and neither your arms nor your
                        fortifications are adequate to defend you, I bring you a peace more
                        necessary than equitable. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That this peace
                        may be realized there is some ground for hoping only if, even as Hannibal
                        proposes it in the spirit of a conqueror, so you shall hearken to it in the
                        spirit of the conquered, and shall not consider as lost what is taken from
                        you, since all things are the victor's, but consider whatever is left you as
                        a gift. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Your city, which he has in great
                        part overthrown, and almost wholly captured, he takes from you: your lands
                        he leaves you, and intends to designate a site whereon you may erect a new
                        town. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All your gold and silver, both
                        public and private, he orders to be brought to him: your persons, with those
                        of your wives and children, he preserves inviolate, if you are willing to go
                        forth unarmed from Saguntum with two garments each. <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> Livy is not implying that Alorcus was in this
                            detail exaggerating Hannibal's offer. The <quote>single garment</quote>
                            of chap. xii. § 5 was loosely put for <quote>a single suit of
                                clothes,</quote>
                            <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the inner and outer tunic which everybody
                            wore. </note>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These <pb n="p.41"/> terms a victorious
                        enemy imposes on you; these <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 219</note> terms, albeit harsh and cruel, your
                        fortune counsels you to accept. Indeed I am not without hope that when full
                        control of everything shall have been granted him, he may remit somewhat of
                        this severity; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but even this you ought, I
                        think, rather to endure than to suffer yourselves to be massacred and your
                        wives and children to be forcibly dragged away into captivity before your
                        eyes, in accordance with the laws of war. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To hear this speech the populace had little by
                    little crowded round, and the people's council had mingled with the senate, when
                    on a sudden the leading men, withdrawing from the throng before an answer could
                    be given, fetched all the gold and silver, both of state and private ownership,
                    into the market-place, and casting it into a fire which they had hurriedly made
                    up for this purpose, many threw themselves headlong into the same flames.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The resulting panic and dismay had no
                    sooner spread to all the city, than another loud noise and outcry were heard
                    from the citadel. A tower that had long been battered had collapsed, and through
                    the breach a cohort of Phoenicians had rushed in and signalled to the general
                    that the city was denuded of its customary guards and sentinels. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal, deeming it no time to hesitate, when such
                    an opportunity offered, attacked with all his strength and captured the city out
                    of hand. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had given orders that all the
                    grown inhabitants be put to the sword —a cruel command, but found in the upshot
                    to have been well-nigh inevitable; for who could be spared of those who either
                    shut themselves up with their wives and children and burned the houses over <pb
                        n="p.43"/> their own heads, or took arms and never gave over <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note> fighting
                    till they died? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The captured town yielded enormous spoils. For
                    although much property had been destroyed on purpose by its owners, and in the
                    carnage rage had scarce made any distinction of years, and the captives had been
                    given as booty to the soldiers, nevertheless <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    it is agreed that a large sum was realized from the sale of goods, and much
                    valuable furniture and apparel sent to Carthage. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some have recorded that Saguntum was taken in
                    the eighth month from the beginning of the siege; that Hannibal then retired to
                    New Carthage, into winter quarters; and then, after leaving New Carthage,
                    arrived in the fifth month in Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If this
                    is so, it cannot have been the case that Publius Cornelius and Tiberius
                    Sempronius were the consuls to whom the Saguntine envoys were dispatched in the
                    beginning of the siege, and who, in their own year of office, fought with
                    Hannibal, the one at the river Ticinus, and both —a little later —at the Trebia.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Either all these things took up somewhat
                    less time, or Saguntum was not first besieged but finally captured in the outset
                    of the year which had Cornelius and Sempronius as consuls. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> For the battle at the Trebia cannot have been fought as
                    late as the consulship of Gnaeus Servilius and Gaius Flaminius; for Gaius
                    Flaminius began his consulship at Ariminum, having been elected under the
                    presidency of Tiberius Sempronius who was then consul, and had, after the battle
                    at the Trebia, come to <pb n="p.45"/> Rome to hold the consular elections, and
                    then <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note>
                    returned to the winter quarters of the army. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This paragraph is a footnote, in which Livy attempts to
                        clear up the chronological muddle which he has got himself into by
                        disregarding the clear statements of Polybius and following an inferior
                        authority. According to Polybius, Hannibal was made general and attacked the
                        Olcades in <date when="-0221">221 B.C.</date> In 220 came the war with the
                        Vaccaei and Carpetani. In 219 (consulship of M. Livius Salinator and L.
                        Aemilius Paulus) came the siege of Saguntum, after which Hannibal put his
                        army in winter quarters in New Carthage, and in 218 set forth on the march
                        to Italy (Polybius, III. xiii, xvii, xxxiii). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At almost the same time the ambassadors who
                    had returned from Carthage brought back word to Rome that all was hostile in
                    that quarter, and the fall of Saguntum was announced. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And so great was the grief of the senators, and their pity
                    at the unmerited doom of their allies, and their shame at having failed to help
                    them, and their wrath against the Carthaginians and fear for the safety of the
                    commonwealth —as though the enemy were already at their gates —that, confounded
                    with so many simultaneous emotions, they rather trembled than deliberated.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For they felt that they had never
                    encountered a fiercer or more warlike foe, and that Rome had never been so
                    torpid and unwarlike. The Sardinians and Corsicans, the Histrians and Illyrians,
                    had provoked but had hardly exercised the Roman arms; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> while against the Gauls there had been desultory fighting
                    rather than real war. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The wars
                        mentioned (and also a war with the Ligurians) occurred in the interval
                        between the First and Second Punic Wars and were described in Book xx (see
                        Summary). </note> But the Phoenician was an old and experienced enemy, who
                    in the hardest kind of service amongst the Spanish tribes had for three and
                    twenty years <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the interval between the First and Second Punic
                        Wars, though the Carthaginian conquest of Spain had not actually begun so
                        early as <date when="-0241">241 B.C.</date>
                    </note> invariably got the victory; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> he was
                    accustomed to the keenest of commanders, was flushed with the conquest of a very
                    wealthy city, and crossing the Ebro and drawing after him the many Spanish
                    peoples which he <pb n="p.47"/> had enlisted, would be rousing up the Gallic
                    tribes — <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> always eager to unsheathe the sword —and the
                    Romans would have to contend in war with all the world, in Italy and under the
                    walls of Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The fields of operation of the consuls had
                    already been named: they were now commanded to draw lots for them. Cornelius
                    obtained Spain, Sempronius Africa with Sicily. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Six legions were voted for that year, with such allied contingents as the
                    consuls themselves should approve and as large a fleet as could be got ready.
                    There were enrolled four and twenty thousand Roman foot-soldiers and eighteen
                    hundred horsemen, and of the allies forty thousand foot-soldiers and four
                    thousand four hundred horsemen. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of ships there
                    were launched two hundred and twenty quinqueremes, and twenty swift cruisers.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The question was then laid before the
                    people whether it were their will and pleasure that war be declared against the
                    people of Carthage; and on their voting in the affirmative a supplication was
                    held throughout the City and the gods were besought to grant a fair and
                    prosperous outcome to the war which the Roman People had decreed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The forces were divided between the consuls as
                    follows: Sempronius received two legions —each numbering four thousand foot and
                    three hundred horse —sixteen thousand foot of the allies, and eighteen hundred
                    horse, together with a hundred and sixty warships and twelve swift cruisers.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With these forces for land and sea
                    Tiberius Sempronius was dispatched to Sicily, that he might cross by that way
                    into Africa, if the other consul were able to keep the Phoenicians out of Italy.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cornelius was given fewer troops, since
                    Lucius Manlius, the praetor, <pb n="p.49"/> was also being sent into Gaul with a
                    not <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219</note>
                    inconsiderable army; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and of ships, in
                    particular, he received a smaller number, namely, sixty quinqueremes, for they
                    did not suppose that the enemy would come by sea or use that kind of warfare. He
                    had two Roman legions with their proper complement of horse, and fourteen
                    thousand infantry of the allies, with sixteen hundred horse. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The province of Gaul received two Roman legions and ten
                    thousand foot of the allies, with a thousand allied and six hundred Roman horse.
                    These troops were designed for the same service —the Punic War. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these arrangements had been made, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> in order
                    that, before going to war, they might observe all the formalities, they
                    dispatched into Africa an embassy consisting of certain older men, to wit,
                    Quintus Fabius, Marcus Livius, Lucius Aemilius, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> M. Livius and L. Aemilius were consuls in <date
                            when="-0219">219 B.C.</date> , and since they were now available to
                        serve on an embassy, it is a fair inference that the embassy had not set out
                        before the middle of March —then the beginning of the consular year —of 218
                        ( <hi rend="italics">De Sanctis,</hi> p. 1.1). </note> Gaius Licinius, and
                    Quintus Baebius, to demand of the Carthaginians whether Hannibal had attacked
                    Saguntum with the sanction of <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the state; and
                    if, as seemed likely to be the case, they should avow the act and stand to it as
                    their public policy, to declare war on the <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Carthaginian People. As soon as the Romans had come to Carthage and the senate
                    had granted them an audience, Quintus Fabius asked only the one question
                    contained in <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> his instructions. Then one of the
                    Carthaginians replied: <quote> There was something headlong, Romans, even in
                        your former embassy, when you demanded that we surrender Hannibal on the
                        ground that he was laying siege to Saguntum on his own responsibility; <pb
                            n="p.51"/> but your present embassy, though expressed thus far <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> more
                        mildly, is in reality <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> more harsh. For on
                        that occasion Hannibal was both accused and his surrender called for; at
                        present you are trying to wring a confession from us, and, as though we had
                        pleaded guilty, demand <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> instant
                        satisfaction. But to me it would seem that you ought to ask, not whether
                        Saguntum was besieged as the result of private or of public policy, but
                        whether justly <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> or unjustly. For it belongs
                        to us to enquire what our fellow citizen has done on our authority or his
                        own, and to punish him; with you the only question we have to discuss is
                        this, whether what he did was permissible under <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> the treaty. Well then, since you wish that a
                        distinction should be drawn between the things that generals do by direction
                        of the state and the acts for which they are themselves responsible, let me
                        remind you that we have a <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> treaty with
                        you, which Gaius Lutatius, your consul, made, wherein, although the allies
                        of both sides were protected, there was no provision made regarding the
                        Saguntines, for as yet they were not <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> your
                        allies. 'But,' you will say, 'in that treaty which was made with Hasdrubal,
                        the Saguntines are expressly cared for.' To this I shall make no other
                        answer than the one that I have learnt from you. For you denied that you
                        were bound by the treaty which Gaius Lutatius, the consul, originally
                        entered into with us, because it had been made without the senate's sanction
                        or the people's command; accordingly a new treaty, having the approval of
                        the state, was <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> entered into. Now, if you
                        are not bound by your treaties, unless they are concluded at your own
                        instance or command, no more could the <pb n="p.53"/> treaty of Hasdrubal,
                        which he made without our <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 218</note> knowledge, be binding <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> upon us. Cease then to prate of Saguntum and the Ebro,
                        and bring forth at last the thought with which your mind has long been
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> in travail! </quote> Then the Roman,
                    gathering up his toga into a fold, said, <quote>We bring you here both war and
                        peace; choose which you will!</quote> When he had said these words, they
                    cried out with no less truculence that he might give them whichever <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> he liked; and on his shaking out the fold again, and
                    announcing that he gave them war, they all replied that they accepted it, and in
                    that same spirit in which they accepted it were resolved to wage it. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This straightforward demand and declaration of
                    war seemed more in keeping with the dignity of the Roman People than to bandy
                    words regarding the rights involved in treaties, especially at that moment, when
                    Saguntum had been destroyed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Though for that
                    matter, had it been proper to debate the question, what comparison could there
                    be between Hasdrubal's treaty and the earlier treaty of Lutatius, which was
                    altered? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For in the treaty of Lutatius it had
                    been expressly added that it should be valid only if the people ratified it; but
                    in Hasdrubal's treaty no such proviso had been made, and by the silence of so
                    many years the treaty had during his lifetime been so sanctioned that even on
                    its author's death no slightest change was made in it. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And yet, even if the earlier treaty were adhered to, the
                    Saguntines had been sufficiently protected by the provision made concerning the
                    allies of both the parties; for there had been no specification of <quote>those
                        who were then allies,</quote> nor exception of <quote> such as might <pb
                            n="p.55"/> afterwards be received. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And since they were permitted <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> to take
                    new allies, who would think it fair either that they should admit no one,
                    however deserving, to their friendship, or that, having once taken people under
                    their protection, they should not defend them —provided only that allies of the
                    Carthaginians should not be tempted to desert them nor be made welcome if they
                    left them voluntarily? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The ambassadors, conformably to the
                    instructions given them in Rome, crossed over from Carthage into Spain for the
                    purpose of approaching the different states and winning them to an alliance, or
                    at least detaching them from the Phoenicians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Bargusii were the first they visited, and being warmly welcomed by them, for
                    men were wearying of the Punic sway, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The Bargusii, N. of the Ebro, were not as yet in the power of the
                        Carthaginians, but were growing uneasy at the prospect of annexation (cf.
                        chap. xxiii. § 2). </note> they aroused in many nations south of the Ebro a
                    desire to revolt. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From there they came to the
                    Volciani, who gave them an answer that was carried all over Spain and turned all
                    the other states against an alliance with the Romans. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> For the eldest of them replied as follows in their council:
                        <quote> With what face, Romans, can you ask us to prefer your friendship to
                        the Carthaginian, when those who did so have been more cruelly betrayed by
                        you, their allies, than destroyed by their enemy, the Phoenician? You must
                        seek allies, in my opinion, only where the disaster of Saguntum is unknown.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To the Spanish peoples the ruins of
                        Saguntum will constitute a warning, no less emphatic than deplorable, that
                        none should trust to the honour or alliance of the Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Being then bidden straightway to depart out
                    of the borders of the Volciani, they received from that day forth <pb n="p.57"/>
                    no kinder response from any Spanish council. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> Accordingly, having
                    traversed that country to no purpose, they passed over into Gaul. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There they beheld a strange and terrifying
                    spectacle, for the Gauls, as was customary with the race, came armed to their
                    assembly. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At an earlier date the
                        Romans, too, had come armed to their assembly <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> —the centuriate comitia (I. xliv. 1). </note> When the
                    envoys, boasting of the renown and valour of the Roman People and the extent of
                    their dominion, requested the Gauls to deny the Phoenician a passage through
                    their lands and cities, if he should attempt to carry the war into Italy,
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> it is said that they burst out into such
                    peals of laughter that the magistrates and elders could scarce reduce the
                    younger men to order <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> —so stupid and impudent a
                    thing it seemed, to propose that the Gauls should not suffer the invaders to
                    pass into Italy, but bring down the war on their own heads, and offer their own
                    fields to be pillaged in place of other men's. When at last the uproar had been
                    quelled, the Gauls made answer to the envoys that they owed the Romans no
                    kindness nor the Carthaginians any grudge, to induce them to draw the sword in
                    behalf of the former or against the <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> latter; on
                    the contrary, <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> they heard that men of their
                    own race were being driven from the land and even out of the borders of Italy by
                    the Roman People, and were paying tribute and suffering every other <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> humiliation. In the rest of the Gallic councils their
                    proposals and the replies they got were to substantially the same effect, nor
                    did they hear a single word of a truly friendly or peaceable tenor until they
                    reached <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Massilia. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Massilia (Marseilles), founded by Phocaeans about <date
                            when="-0600">600 B.C.</date> , had been, from the period of the Kings, a
                        faithful ally of Rome. </note> Here they learned of all that had happened
                    from their allies, who had made enquiries with faithful diligence. They reported
                    that <pb n="p.59"/> Hannibal had been beforehand with the Romans <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> in gaining
                    the good-will of the Gauls, but that even he would find them hardly tractable
                    —so fierce and untamed was their nature —unless from time to time he should make
                    use of gold, of which the race is very covetous, to secure the favour of their
                    principal <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> men. So the envoys, having travelled
                    through the nations of Spain and Gaul, returned to Rome, not long after the
                    consuls had set out for their respective commands. They found the citizens all
                    on tip-toe with expectation of the war, for the rumour persisted that the
                    Phoenicians had already crossed the Ebro. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, after the capture of Saguntum, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219-218</note> had
                    withdrawn his army into winter quarters at New Carthage. There he learned what
                    had been done in Rome and Carthage and what had been decreed, and that he was
                    not only commander in the war, but the cause of it as well. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> So, having divided or sold off what was left of the
                    plunder, he thought best to defer his plans no longer, and, calling together the
                    soldiers of Spanish blood, thus addressed them: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> My allies, I doubt not that you yourselves perceive how, having
                        conquered every tribe in Spain, we must either bring our campaigning to a
                        close and disband our armies, or shift the seat of war to other countries.
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy makes Hannibal speak
                            with rhetorical exaggeration. The Spanish troops whom he is addressing
                            have not conquered 'every tribe in Spain,' for they came themselves from
                            tribes which had been for some years friendly and subject to the
                            Carthaginians. He had not indeed conquered all the <hi rend="italics"
                                >hostile</hi> tribes, but only those lying south of the Ebro. </note>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For these nations here will enjoy the
                        blessings not merely of peace, but also of victory, only if we look to other
                        nations for spoils and glory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Since,
                        therefore, you are on the eve of an expedition that will carry <pb n="p.61"
                        /> you far afield, and it is uncertain when you will <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 219-218</note> see again your
                        homes and what there is dear to each of you, if any of you desires to visit
                        his friends, I grant him furlough. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Be at
                        hand, I charge you, with the first signs of spring, that with Heaven's good
                        help we may begin a war that shall bring us vast renown and booty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were very few who did not welcome the
                    opportunity thus freely proffered of visiting their homes, for they were already
                    homesick and looked forward to an even longer separation from their friends.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The full winter's rest between the labours
                    already undergone and those that were presently to come gave them new strength
                    and courage for a fresh encounter with every hardship. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Early in the spring they assembled in obedience to their
                    orders. </p>
                <p> When Hannibal had reviewed the contingents <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> sent in by all the
                    nations, he went to Gades <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Gades
                        (Cadiz) was a Tyrian colony and possessed a famous temple of Melkarth (whom
                        the Romans identified with Hercules), the tutelary god of the mother city.
                    </note> and discharged his vows to Hercules, binding himself with fresh ones, in
                    case he should be successful in the remainder of his undertaking. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Then, with equal concern for attack and defence,
                    lest while he should be himself advancing upon Italy by an overland march
                    through Spain and Gaul, Africa might lie exposed and open to a Roman invasion on
                    the side of Sicily, he resolved to garrison that country with a powerful force.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To supply its place he requisitioned
                    troops for himself from Africa —lightarmed slingers chiefly —so that Africans
                    might serve in Spain and Spaniards in Africa, and both be the better soldiers
                    for being far from home, as though mutually pledged to loyalty. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Thirteen thousand eight hundred and fifty targeteers
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Like the Greek <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">,</foreign> these were light infantry whose defensive
                        armour consisted of a small round shield covered with oxhide. </note> and
                    eight <pb n="p.63"/> hundred and seventy Baliaric slingers, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Baliares (Majorca and Minorca)
                        furnished the most skilful slingers in the world. Livy says (XXVIII. xxxvii.
                        6) that no single individual of any other people was so superior in this art
                        to his fellows as were all the Baliares to the rest of mankind. The ancients
                        derived Baliares from <foreign xml:lang="greek">,</foreign>
                        <quote>throw.</quote>
                    </note> with twelve <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        218</note> hundred horsemen drawn from many nations, he sent to Africa.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A part of these troops were to be a
                    garrison for Carthage, a part to be distributed through the country. At the same
                    time he directed that recruiting officers be sent out into the states, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi> of Africa. </note> and that four thousand picked
                    men be brought to Carthage, to serve at once as defenders and as hostages. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And considering that neither must Spain be
                    neglected, and so much the less since he was not unaware that Roman ambassadors
                    had journeyed through it to seek the support of its leading men, he appointed it
                    to be the charge of his brother Hasdrubal —an <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    active, energetic man —and secured it with troops, for the most part African. Of
                    infantry there were eleven thousand eight hundred and fifty Africans, three
                    hundred Ligurians, and five hundred Baliares. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    To these infantry forces he added the following units of cavalry: four hundred
                    and fifty Libyphoenicians —a race of mixed Punic and African blood —and some
                    eight hundred Numidians and Moors, who dwell near the ocean, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Mauretania corresponded to the present
                        Fez and Morocco.</note> and a little company of three hundred Spanish
                    Ilergetes. Finally, that no sort of land force might be lacking, there were
                    twenty-one elephants. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He also assigned a fleet
                    to Spain, for the protection of its seaboard, since it might be expected that
                    the Romans would <pb n="p.65"/> again on this occasion employ that mode of
                    warfare <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    in which they had been victorious. There were fifty quinqueremes, two
                    quadriremes, and five triremes. But only thirty-two quinqueremes and the five
                    triremes were equipped and manned with rowers. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In this enumeration of forces Livy follows Polybius
                        (III. xxxiii. 9), who says that he found the numbers recorded by Hannibal
                        himself on a bronze tablet which was set up on the Lacinian Promontory (near
                        Crotona). </note>
                </p>
                <p> From Gades Hannibal returned to New Carthage, to the winter quarters of his
                    army. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Setting out from thence, he marched
                    along the coast, past the city of Onusa, to the Ebro. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> It was there, as they tell, that he saw in his sleep a
                    youth of godlike aspect, who declared that he was sent by Jupiter to lead him
                    into Italy: let him follow, therefore, nor anywhere turn his eyes away from his
                    guide. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first he was afraid and followed,
                    neither looking to the right nor to the left, nor yet behind him; but presently
                    wondering, with that curiosity to which all of us are prone, what it could be
                    that he had been forbidden to look back upon, he was unable to command his eyes;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> then he saw behind him a serpent of
                    monstrous size, that moved along with vast destruction of trees and underbrush,
                    and a storm-cloud coming after, with loud claps of thunder; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and, on his asking what this prodigious portent was, he was
                    told that it was the devastation of Italy: he was therefore to go on, nor
                    enquire further, but suffer destiny to be wrapped in darkness. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Rejoicing at this vision, he led his troops
                    across the Ebro in three columns, after sending agents ahead, to win over with
                    presents the Gauls who dwelt in the region which the army had to cross, and to
                    explore the passes of the Alps. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had ninety
                    thousand foot and twelve thousand horse <pb n="p.67"/> when he crossed the Ebro.
                    He now subdued the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        218</note> Ilergetes, and the Bargusii and Ausetani, and also Lacetania,
                    which lies at the foot of the Pyrenees. All this coast he put in charge of
                    Hanno, that the passes connecting Spain and Gaul might be under his control.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To garrison this district, he gave Hanno
                    ten thousand foot and a thousand horse. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the army had entered the defiles which
                    lead over the Pyrenees, and more definite rumours had spread amongst the
                    barbarians that the war was to be with Rome, three thousand of the Carpetanian
                    foot turned back. It was understood that they were influenced not so much by the
                    war as by the long march and the impossibility of crossing the Alps. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> To recall them or to detain them forcibly would have
                    been hazardous, for it might have roused resentment in the savage bosoms of the
                    others. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And so Hannibal sent back to their
                    homes above seven thousand more, whom he had perceived to be chafing at the
                    service, pretending that he had also dismissed the Carpetani. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then, in order that his troops might not
                    become demoralized by delay and inaction, he crossed the Pyrenees with the
                    remainder of his forces <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius
                        (III. xxxv. 7) says that Hannibal now had fifty thousand foot and about nine
                        thousand horse. </note> and pitched his camp by the town of Iliberri. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The modern Elne is near the site.</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Gauls, though they heard that the war was
                    aimed at Italy, nevertheless, because it was said that the Spaniards beyond the
                    Pyrenees had been forcibly subjugated and strong garrisons imposed upon them,
                    were driven by the fear of servitude to arm themselves, and several tribes
                    assembled at Ruscino. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The name is
                        reflected in the French Tour de Roussillon, near Perpignan. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When Hannibal was apprised of this, he was
                    more <pb n="p.69"/> afraid of delay than of fighting, and dispatched <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    ambassadors to their chieftains to inform them that he wished to confer with
                    them in person, and suggested that either they come nearer to Iliberri or that
                    he would go forward to Ruscino, so that being close to one another they might
                    meet more easily. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He would be glad, he said,
                    to receive them in his camp, nor would he hesitate to go to them. He had come
                    into Gaul as a friend, not as an enemy, and would keep his sword sheathed, if
                    the Gauls would let him, till he had entered Italy. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Thus far his emissaries. But when the Gallic chieftains,
                    moving up their camp at once near Iliberri, came, nothing loath, to the
                    Phoenician, they were captivated by his gifts, and permitted the army to march
                    unmolested through their borders and past the town of Ruscino. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Italy meanwhile nothing more was known than
                    that Hannibal had crossed the Ebro —which was the news that Massiliot envoys
                    brought to Rome —when, as though he had already crossed the Alps, the Boi, after
                    rousing up the Insubres, revolted. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Livy has said nothing of any negotiations between Hannibal and the Boi,
                        preferring, in his love of dramatic effect, to let us see this Gallic
                        outbreak as it appeared to the Romans <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        —like a bolt from the blue. See chap. xxix. § 6. </note> To this they were
                    incited not so much by their old animosity against the Roman People as by
                    vexation at the recent establishment of colonies in Gallic territory, near the
                    Po, at Placentia and <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Cremona. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These were of the type called Latin
                        colonies. To each of them six thousand colonists had been assigned. They had
                        hardly got settled when the Gauls broke out (Polybius, III. xl. 3-6).
                    </note> Flying to arms they made an incursion into that very district, and
                    spread such terror and confusion that not only the rural population, but the
                    Roman commissioners themselves, who had come for the purpose of assigning lands,
                    not trusting to the <pb n="p.71"/> walls of Placentia, fled to Mutina. (Their
                    names <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    were Gaius Lutatius, Gaius Servilius, and Marcus Annius. There is no question
                    about Lutatius: for Annius and Servilius, some annals have Manius Acilius and
                    Gaius Herennius, others Publius Cornelius Asina and Gaius Papirius <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Maso. This, too, is uncertain, whether envoys sent to
                    expostulate with the Boi were maltreated, or an attack was made upon the three
                    commissioners as they were measuring off the <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    land.) Whilst they lay shut up in Mutina, the Gauls —who know nothing of the art
                    of assaulting cities, and, besides, are very indolent in regard to siege-works,
                    and were now sitting idly down before the walls without attempting them
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> —feigned a readiness to treat for peace;
                    and their leaders having invited the Romans to send out spokesmen to confer with
                    them, they seized these envoys, in violation not only of the <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> law of nations, but also of a pledge which they had given
                    for this time, and declared that they would not let them go unless their own
                    hostages were restored to them. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Apparently the Gauls left hostages with the Romans when they arranged for
                        the Romans to send representatives to talk things over with them in the
                        Gallic camp. </note> When word arrived of this affair of the envoys, and
                    Mutina and its garrison were in danger, Lucius Manlius, the praetor, blazing
                    with resentment, set out for Mutina with his army in loose marching <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> order. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Neither Polybius nor Livy tells us where Manlius was when the news reached
                        him. Weissenborn-Mueller think he was at Placentia, engaged in strengthening
                        the new fortifications. </note> In those days the road led through a forest,
                    as the country was not, for the most part, under cultivation, and Manlius,
                    advancing without reconnaissance, plunged into an ambush, and after sustaining
                    heavy losses, managed with difficulty to get through into the open <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> fields. There he entrenched <pb n="p.73"/> a camp,
                    and since the Gauls lacked heart to assail it, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the soldiers recovered their spirits,
                    though it was no secret that as many as five hundred men had <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> fallen. Then they began their march again, nor, so long as
                    the column advanced through open country, was the enemy to be seen; but when
                    they had once more got into the woods, the Gauls attacked <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> their rear, and throwing the whole column into terror and
                    confusion, slew seven hundred soldiers and carried off six ensigns. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This second attack —Polybius records
                        but the one —is suspiciously like the first. Livy, or Livy's immediate
                        source, may unconsciously have made two episodes out of slightly different
                        accounts of the same affair. </note> The alarming onsets of the Gauls and
                    the panic of the Romans ended when they got clear of the trackless <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> woods and thickets. Thereafter, marching across open
                    ground, the Romans had no difficulty in protecting their column, and hastened to
                    Tannetum, a village lying near the Po, where by means of temporary
                    fortifications and <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> supplies got in by the
                    river, and with the help also of the Brixian Gauls, they defended themselves
                    against the enemy, whose numbers were increasing daily. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Tannetum (now Tanneto) was really about ten miles south
                        of the Po, on the Via Aemilia Lepida. If <hi rend="italics">commeatibus
                            fluminis</hi> is correctly translated, we may suppose (1) that Livy
                        thought Tannetum was much nearer the Po, or (2) that he has confused Brixia
                        (Brescia) with Brixellum (Bresciello), which is nearly north of Tanneto and
                        close to the Po, and might have served as an <hi rend="italics"
                            >entrepôt</hi> for supplies sent down from Placentia. The statement in
                        chap. lv. § 4 that the Cenomani (whose capital was Brixia) were the only
                        Gallic tribe that was loyal to Rome favours (1). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of this sudden insurrection was
                    brought to Rome, and the Fathers learnt that the Punic War was augmented by a
                    war with the Gauls, they commanded Gaius Atilius, the praetor, to take one Roman
                    legion and five thousand of the allies —a <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    force which the consul <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">P. Cornelius
                        Scipio.</note> had just levied —and proceed to the relief of Manlius.
                    Atilius reached Tannetum without any fighting, for the enemy had retired in
                    alarm. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.75"/>
                <p> Publius Cornelius, too, after enrolling a new legion <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> in place of that which had
                    been sent with the praetor, set out from the City with sixty ships of war, and
                    coasting Etruria and the mountainous country of Liguria and the Salui, arrived
                    at Massilia, and went into camp at the nearest mouth of the Rhone —for
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the river discharges itself into the sea
                    by several <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius (XXXIV. x. 5)
                        says two, Pliny ( <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> III. iv. 33) three, and
                        Strabo (IV. i. 8) cites Timaeus as authority for the number five. </note>
                    —hardly believing, even then, that Hannibal could have crossed the Pyrenees.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But when he found that Hannibal was
                    actually planning how to cross the Rhone, being uncertain where he should
                    encounter him, and his soldiers not having as yet fully recovered from the
                    tossing of the sea, he sent out a chosen band of three hundred cavalry, with
                    Massiliot guides and Gallic auxiliaries, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius says that Scipio <quote> sent out three
                            hundred of his bravest cavalry, giving them as guides and supports
                            certain Celts who were in the service of the Massiliots as mercenaries
                        </quote> (Paton's translation). </note> to make, while he was waiting, a
                    thorough reconnaissance, and have a look at the enemy from a safe distance. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hannibal, having pacified the others through
                    fear or bribery, had now reached the territory of a powerful nation called the
                    Volcae. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It is usually held —with
                        Napoleon —that Hannibal crossed the Rhone above the confluence with the
                        Durance. The arguments of those who think that the crossing was just above
                        the Delta have been recently restated by Spencer Wilkinson, <hi
                            rend="italics">Hannibal's March Through the Alps,</hi> pp. 14-17.
                    </note> They inhabit both banks of the Rhone, but doubting their ability to keep
                    the Phoenician from the western bank, they had brought nearly all their people
                    over the Rhone, so as to have the river for a bulwark, and were holding the
                    eastern bank <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> with arms. The rest of the
                    dwellers by the river, and such of the Volcae themselves as had clung to their
                    homes, were enticed by Hannibal's gifts to assemble large boats from every
                    quarter and to fashion new ones; and indeed <pb n="p.77"/> they themselves were
                    eager to have the army set <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 218</note> across as soon as possible and to relieve
                    their district of the burden of so huge a horde of men. So they brought together
                    a vast number of boats, and of canoes roughly fashioned for local traffic, and
                    made new ones by hollowing out <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> single trees.
                    The Gauls took the lead in this, but the soldiers presently fell to work
                    themselves, when they found the timber plentiful and the <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> labour light. They were unshapely troughs, but the men
                    could make them quickly, and their one concern was to get something that would
                    float and hold a cargo, in which they might ferry themselves and their
                    belongings over. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Everything was now in readiness for the
                    crossing, which, however, was menaced by the enemy on the other side, who
                    covered the whole bank with their horse and foot. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> In order to draw them off, Hannibal ordered Hanno, the son
                    of Bomilcar, to set out in the first watch of <milestone n="3??" unit="section"
                    /> the night with a part of the troops, chiefly Spaniards, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Spaniards were preferred for this duty because of
                        their skill in swimming rivers, as we see at § 5 ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >cf.</hi> chap. xlvii. § 5). The method here employed was still in vogue
                        amongst them in Caesar's time ( <hi rend="italics">Bell. Civ.</hi> I.
                        xlviii. 7). </note> and, making a march of one day up the stream, to take
                    the first opportunity of crossing it, with the greatest secrecy, and fetch a
                    compass with his column, so that, when the time came, he might assail the enemy
                    in the rear. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Gauls who had been appointed
                    to be his guides informed him that some five-and-twenty miles upstream the river
                    flowed round a little island, and being wider where it divided, and therefore
                    shallower, afforded a passage. There they quickly felled some trees and
                    constructed rafts to transport the men and horses and other burdens. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Spaniards without <pb n="p.79"/> more ado stuffed
                    their clothes into skins, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The skins
                        of sheep and goats, such as are still used to hold wine. They could either
                        be inflated and used merely as a kind of life-belt, or could be made to
                        serve at the same time as kit bags. </note> and placing <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> their
                    bucklers on top of these and supporting themselves by means of them, swam
                    across. The rest of the force, too, got over, by means of the rafts which they
                    had made, and went into camp near the river. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They were tired by the night march and their strenuous exertions, but their
                    commander allowed them but one day to rest, being intent on carrying out the
                    stratagem at the proper time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Resuming their
                    march on the following day they sent up a smoke-signal from an elevated place,
                    to show that they had got over the river and were not far off. When Hannibal saw
                    this, he gave the order to cross, so as not to miss the favourable moment.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The infantry had their skiffs all ready
                    and equipped, while the cavalry had large boats, for the most part, on account
                    of their horses. The large boats were sent across higher up the stream, to take
                    the force of the current, and provided smooth water for the skiffs that crossed
                    below them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A good part of the horses swam and
                    were towed by their halters from the sterns of the boats, except those which
                    they had saddled and bridled and put on board, that their riders might have them
                    ready for instant use on landing. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls rushed to meet them on the bank,
                    with all sorts of yells and their customary songs, clashing their shields
                    together above their heads and brandishing darts in their <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> right hands, despite the menace of so great a multitude of
                    vessels coming against them and the loud roaring of the river and the confused
                    hallooing of the boatmen and the sailors, as they strove to force their way
                    athwart the current or shouted encouragement to their fellows <pb n="p.81"/>
                    from the further bank. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But the tribesmen were
                    already <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    somewhat daunted by the tumult which confronted them, when a still more
                    appalling clamour arose in the rear, where Hanno had captured their camp. He was
                    soon on the scene himself, and a twofold terror hemmed them in, as that mighty
                    force of armed men came out upon the shore and the unlooked-for line of battle
                    closed in from behind. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the Gauls had
                    attempted charges in both directions and found themselves repulsed, they broke
                    through where the way seemed least beset, and fled in confusion to their several
                    villages. Hannibal brought over at leisure the rest of his forces, and giving
                    himself no more concern over Gallic outbreaks, pitched his camp. </p>
                <p> I believe that there were various plans for transporting the elephants; at all
                    events the tradition varies as to how it was accomplished. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Some say that the elephants were first assembled on the
                    bank, and then the keeper of the fiercest of them provoked the beast and fled
                    into the water; as he swam off, the elephant pursued him and drew the herd in
                    his train; and though they were afraid of the deep water, yet as soon as each of
                    them got out of his depth, the current itself swept him over to the other bank.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It is, however, more generally believed
                    that they were carried across on rafts; this method, as it would be the safer,
                    if the thing were to be done, so, in view of its accomplishment, is more
                    probably the one employed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A raft, two hundred
                    feet long and fifty feet wide, was thrust out from the shore into the stream,
                    and, after being moored to the bank above by a number of stout hawsers, so as
                    not to be carried down the current, was covered with earth, <pb n="p.83"/> like
                    a bridge, in order that the beasts might boldly <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> venture upon it, as on
                    solid ground. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A second raft, of equal width
                    and a hundred feet long, and fit for crossing the river, was coupled to the
                    first. Then the elephants, with the females leading, were driven out over the
                    stationary raft, as over a road; and after they had passed on to the smaller
                    raft adjoining it, the ropes by which this had been loosely attached were cast
                    off and it was towed across by some rowboats to the eastern bank. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> After landing the first contingent in this fashion,
                    they returned and fetched the others over. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The elephants exhibited no signs of fear so long as they were being driven along
                    as though on a connected bridge; they first became frightened when the raft was
                    cast loose from the other and was carried out into mid-channel. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The crowding together which resulted, as those on
                    the outside shrank back from the water, gave rise to a slight panic, till terror
                    itself, as they looked at the water all about them, made them quiet. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Some, in their frenzy, even fell overboard; but,
                    steadied by their very weight, threw off their riders, and feeling their way to
                    the shallow places, got out upon the land. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius, who perhaps believed, as did Pliny ( <hi
                            rend="italics">N. H.</hi> VIII. 28), that elephants could not swim, says
                        that those that went overboard were saved by the length of their trunks,
                        which they kept above the surface, and, breathing so, passed through the
                        water, for the most part on their feet (III. xlvii. 12). Livy seems to have
                        thought of them as swimming. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the elephants were being got across,
                    Hannibal had dispatched five hundred Numidian horsemen in the direction of the
                    Roman camp, to find out where the enemy were and in what force, and what they
                    meant to do. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This body fell in with the three
                    hundred Roman horsemen, sent out, as was mentioned before, from the mouth of the
                    Rhone. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The battle that followed was more hotly
                    fought than the size of the contending forces would suggest, for besides the
                    many who were <pb n="p.85"/> wounded, the numbers of the slain were about equal
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> on
                    both sides, and only the dismay and panic of the Numidians gave the victory to
                    the Romans, who were by that time fairly exhausted. The victors lost about a
                    hundred and forty, not all Romans but some of them Gauls; the vanquished about
                    two hundred. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This was at once the beginning of
                    the war and an omen that promised the Romans success in the final outcome,
                    though their victory would be by no means without bloodshed and would only come
                    after a doubtful struggle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the participants in this affair had
                    returned to their respective generals, it was impossible for Scipio to adopt any
                    settled plan, except to frame his own measures to meet the strategy and
                    movements of the enemy; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> while Hannibal,
                    uncertain whether to march on, as he had begun, to Italy, or give battle to the
                    first Roman army that had come in his way, was diverted from an immediate trial
                    of strength by the arrival of Boian envoys, with their chief Magalus. These
                    assured him that they would guide his march and share its perils, and urged him
                    to avoid a battle and to keep his forces whole and unimpaired for the invasion
                    of Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The rank and file were fearful of
                    the enemy —for their memory of the former war was not yet erased —but more
                    fearful of the interminable march over the Alps, an undertaking which rumour
                    made appalling, at any rate to the inexperienced. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accordingly Hannibal, having settled in his
                    own mind to go forward and advance on Italy, called the soldiers together and
                    worked on their feelings with alternate chiding and encouragement. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> He marvelled, he said, what sudden terror had <pb
                        n="p.87"/> invaded breasts that had ever been dauntless. For <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> these many
                    years they had been victorious in war, nor had they quitted Spain until all the
                    tribes and territories which lay between two distant seas were in the power of
                    the Carthaginians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then, indignant that the
                    Roman People should demand that whoever had laid siege to Saguntum be
                    surrendered up to them, as though to expiate a felony, they had crossed the
                    Ebro, in order to wipe out the Roman name and liberate the world. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The march had not then seemed long to any of them,
                    though they meant to advance from the setting to the rising sun; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> but now, when they could see that they had measured
                    off the greater part of it; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius
                        (III. xxxix) estimates the distance covered by Hannibal as follows: New
                        Carthage to the Ebro 2600 stades (the stade is roughly a furlong); the Ebro
                        to Emporium 1600; Emporium to Narbo 600; Narbo to the passage of the Rhone
                        1600; the passage of the Rhone to the foot of the pass over the Alps 1400;
                        the foot of the pass to the valley of the Po 1200. </note> when they had
                    made their way, through the fiercest tribes, over the Pyrenees; when they had
                    crossed the Rhone —that mighty river —in the teeth of so many thousand Gauls,
                    overcoming, too, the violence of the stream itself; when the Alps, the other
                    side of which was in Italy, were in full sight; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> —were they halting now, as though exhausted, at the very gates of their
                    enemies? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What else did they think that the
                    Alps were but high mountains? They might fancy them higher than the ranges of
                    the Pyrenees; but surely no lands touched the skies or were impassable to man.
                    The Alps indeed were inhabited, were tilled, produced and supported living
                    beings; their defiles were practicable for armies. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Those very ambassadors whom they beheld had not crossed the
                    Alps in the air on wings. Even the ancestors of these men had not been natives
                    of Italy, but had lived there as foreign settlers, and had often crossed these
                    very Alps in <pb n="p.89"/> great companies, with their children and their
                    wives, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    in the manner of emigrants. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See v.
                        xxxiv-xxxv. Livy places the earliest Gallic immigration in the reign of
                        Tarquinius Priscus. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For armed soldiers, taking nothing with them
                    but the instruments of war, what could be impassable or insurmountable? To
                    capture Saguntum, what dangers or what hardships had they not endured for eight
                    long months? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Now that Rome, the capital of
                    the world, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This expression is a
                        strange anachronism in the mouth of Hannibal; but Livy thinks of Hannibal as
                        realizing —and so perhaps he may have done —that the struggle now beginning
                        would determine whether Rome or Carthage should rule the world. </note> was
                    their objective, could anything seem so painful or so difficult as to delay
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> their enterprise? Had Gauls once captured
                    that which the Phoenician despaired of approaching? Then let them yield in
                    spirit and manhood to a race which they had so often vanquished in the course of
                    the last few days, or look to end their march in the field <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Campus Martius lay outside the Servian wall,
                        between the Capitoline, Quirinal, and Pincian Hills and the Tiber. </note>
                    that lay between the Tiber and the walls of Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After encouraging them with this exhortation,
                    he bade them refresh themselves and make ready for the march. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Setting out the following day he advanced up the Rhone
                    towards the interior of Gaul, not that it was the more direct way to the Alps,
                    but believing that the farther he retired from the sea, the less likely he was
                    to fall in with the Romans, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> with whom he had
                    no mind to fight a battle until he should arrive in Italy. The fourth day's
                    march brought him to the Island. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There the
                    rivers Isara and Rhone, rushing down from different Alps, unite their waters,
                    after enclosing a considerable territory, and the Island is the name which has
                    been given to the plains lying between them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Near by is the country of the Allobroges, a tribe, even at <pb n="p.91"/> that
                    early day, inferior to no Gallic tribe in wealth <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> or reputation. Just then
                    it was a prey to discord. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The tribe
                        in question was not the Allobroges, according to Polybius, III. xlix., but
                        afforded the Carthaginians protection against the Allobroges. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two brothers were disputing the sovereignty.
                    The elder, Braneus by name, who had held sway before, was being driven out by a
                    faction of juniors headed by the younger brother, whose right was less but his
                    might greater. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This quarrel having very
                    opportunely been referred to Hannibal for settlement, who thus became arbiter of
                    the kingdom, he espoused the sentiments of the senate and the leading men and
                    restored the sovereign power to the elder. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In
                    requital of this service he was assisted with provisions and supplies of every
                    sort, particularly clothing, which the notorious cold of the Alps made it
                    necessary to provide. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having settled the contentions of the
                    Allobroges, Hannibal was now ready for the Alps; but instead of marching
                    directly towards them, he turned to the left, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A turn to the left is unintelligible at this point in
                        the march, and must be explained as due to a duplication of the march up the
                        Rhone mentioned in § 2. </note> to the country of the Tricastini, and thence
                    proceeded through the outer borders of the territory of the Vocontii to the
                    Tricorii, by a road which nowhere presented any difficulties, until he came to
                    the Druentia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Neither the Durance nor
                        any of these tribes is mentioned by Polybius. But Polybius disliked to
                        encumber his narrative with outlandish geographical names that would mean
                        nothing to his readers, and they are less likely to be arbitrary
                        embellishments <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> —on the part either of
                        Livy or his source —than authentic details drawn from a source or sources
                        common to Livy and Polybius and omitted by Polybius for the reason given.
                        (The same may be said of the name of the Gallic prince in § 6.) If we assume
                        that Hannibal ascended the Isère-Drac to the Druentia and thence crossed the
                        Genèvre, he would have touched the territories of these tribes, and there
                        would be no great difficulty in reconciling the account in Livy with that in
                        Polybius (see <hi rend="italics">De Sanctis,</hi> p. 69). </note> This, too,
                    is an Alpine river and by far the most difficult of all the rivers of Gaul
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> to <pb n="p.93"/> cross; for, though it
                    brings down a vast volume of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 218</note> water, it does not admit of navigation, since,
                    not being confined within any banks, but flowing at once in several channels,
                    not always the same, it is ever forming new shallows and new pools —a fact which
                    makes it dangerous for foot-passengers as well —besides which it rolls down
                    jagged stones and affords no sure or stable footing to one who <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> enters it. And at that time, as it happened, it was swollen
                    with rains, and the crossing took place amidst the wildest tumult, for the men
                    —besides their other difficulties —were confused by their own excitement and
                    bewildered outcries. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Publius Cornelius the consul, some three days
                    after Hannibal had left the bank of the Rhone, marched in fighting order to the
                    enemy's camp, intending to offer battle without delay. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But finding the works deserted, and perceiving that he
                    could not readily overtake the enemy, who had got so long a start of him, he
                    returned to the sea, where he had left his ships, thinking that he would thus be
                    more safely and easily enabled to confront Hannibal as he descended from the
                    Alps. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Still, that he might not leave Spain
                    stripped of Roman defenders —for the lot had assigned it to him as his province
                    —he <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> sent Gnaeus Scipio, his brother, with the
                    chief part of his troops, to deal with Hasdrubal, with the object not merely of
                    protecting the allies and of winning over new ones, but also of driving
                    Hasdrubal out of Spain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He himself, with
                    extremely scanty forces, sailed back to Genoa, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> At chap. xxxix. § 3 Livy agrees with Polybius in naming
                        Pisa as Scipio's port of debarkation, forgetting that he has here named
                        Genoa. </note> proposing to safeguard Italy with the army which lay in the
                    valley of the Po. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hannibal, leaving the Druentia, and advancing
                    for the most part through a champaign country, <pb n="p.95"/> reached the Alps
                    without being molested by the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 218</note> Gauls who inhabited those regions. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Then, though report, which is wont to exaggerate
                    uncertain dangers, had already taught them what to expect, still, the near view
                    of the lofty mountains, with their snows almost merging in the sky; the
                    shapeless hovels perched on crags; the frost-bitten flocks and beasts of burden;
                    the shaggy, unkempt men; animals and inanimate objects alike stiff with cold,
                    and all more dreadful to look upon than words can tell, renewed their
                    consternation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As their column began to mount
                    the first slopes, mountaineers were discovered posted on the heights above, who,
                    had they lain concealed in hidden valleys, might have sprung out suddenly and
                    attacked them with great rout and slaughter. Hannibal gave the command to halt,
                    and sent forward some Gauls to reconnoitre. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    When informed by them that there was no getting by that way, he encamped in the
                    most extensive valley to be found in a wilderness of rocks and precipices.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He then employed these same Gauls, whose
                    speech and customs did not differ greatly from those of the mountaineers, to
                    mingle in their councils, and in this way learned that his enemies guarded the
                    pass only by day, and at night dispersed, every man to his own home. As soon as
                    it was light, he advanced up the hills, as though lie hoped to rush the defile
                    by an open attack in the daytime. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then having
                    spent the day in feigning a purpose other than his real one, he entrenched a
                    camp on the spot where he had halted. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But no
                    sooner did he perceive that the mountaineers had dispersed from the heights and
                    relaxed their vigilance, than, leaving for show more fires than the <pb n="p.97"
                    /> numbers of those who remained in camp demanded; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> leaving, too, the baggage
                    and the cavalry and a great part of the infantry, he put himself at the head of
                    some light-armed soldiers —all <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> his bravest
                    men —and, marching swiftly to the head of the defile, occupied those very
                    heights which the enemy had held. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the ensuing dawn the Carthaginians broke
                    camp and the remainder of their army began to move. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The natives, on a signal being given, were already coming
                    in from their fastnesses to occupy their customary post, when they suddenly
                    perceived that some of their enemies were in possession of the heights and
                    threatened them from above, and that others were marching through the pass.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both facts presenting themselves at the
                    same time to their eyes and minds kept them for a moment rooted to the spot.
                    Then, when they saw the helter-skelter in the pass and the column becoming
                    embarrassed by its own confusion, the horses especially being frightened
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> and unmanageable, they thought that
                    whatever they could add themselves to the consternation of the troops would be
                    sufficient to destroy them, and rushed down from the cliffs on either side, over
                    trails and trackless ground alike, with all the ease of habit. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Then indeed the Phoenicians had to contend at one and the
                    same time against their foes and the difficulties of the ground, and the
                    struggle amongst themselves, as each endeavoured to outstrip the rest in
                    escaping from the danger, was greater than the struggle with the enemy.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The horses occasioned the greatest peril
                    to the column. Terrified by the discordant yells, which the woods and ravines
                    redoubled with their echoes, they quaked <pb n="p.99"/> with fear; and if they
                    happened to be hit or <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 218</note> wounded, were so maddened that they made enormous havoc not
                    only of men but of every sort of baggage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed the crowding in the pass, which was steep and precipitous on both sides,
                    caused many —some of them armed men —to be flung down to a great depth; but when
                    beasts of burden with their packs went hurtling down, it was just like the crash
                    of falling walls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Dreadful as these sights
                    were, still Hannibal halted for a little while and held back his men, so as not
                    to augment the terror and confusion. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then,
                    when he saw that the column was being broken in two, and there was danger lest
                    he might have got his army over to no avail, if it were stripped of its baggage,
                    he charged down from the higher ground and routed the enemy by the very impetus
                    of the attack, though he added to the disorder amongst his own troops.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But the flurry thus occasioned quickly
                    subsided, as soon as the roads were cleared by the flight of the mountaineers;
                    and the whole army was presently brought over the pass, not only without
                    molestation but almost in silence. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hannibal
                    then seized a stronghold which was the chief place in that region, together with
                    the outlying hamlets, and with the captured food and flocks supported his troops
                    for three days. And in those three days, being hindered neither by the natives,
                    who had been utterly cowed at the outset, nor very greatly by the nature of the
                    country, he covered a good deal of ground. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They came next to another canton, thickly
                    settled for a mountain district. There, not by open fighting, but by his own
                    devices, trickery and deception, Hannibal was all but circumvented. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.101"/> The elder headmen of the strongholds waited on <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.218</note> him, as a
                    deputation, and said that, taught by other men's misfortunes —a useful warning
                    —they preferred to experience the friendship of the Phoenicians rather than
                    their might; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> they were ready, therefore, to
                    carry out his orders, and they requested him to accept provisions and guides and
                    also hostages as a guarantee of good faith. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Hannibal, neither blindly trusting nor yet repulsing them, lest, being spurned,
                    they might become openly hostile, returned a friendly answer, accepted the
                    proffered hostages, and used the supplies, which they had brought down,
                    themselves, to the road. But he drew up his column, before following their
                    guides, by no means as though for a march through a friendly country. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The van was made up of elephants and cavalry; he
                    himself, with the main strength of the infantry, came next, looking warily about
                    him and watching everything. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they had got
                    to a narrow place, which was overhung on one side by a ridge, the tribesmen rose
                    up on every quarter from their ambush and assailed them, front and rear,
                    fighting hand to hand and at long range, and rolling down huge boulders on the
                    marching troops. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The rear-guard bore the brunt
                    of the attack, and as the infantry faced about to meet it, it was very evident
                    that if the column had not been strengthened at that point, it must have
                    suffered a great disaster in this pass. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Even
                    so, they were in the utmost peril and came near destruction. For while Hannibal
                    was hesitating to send his division <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        By <hi rend="italics">agmen</hi> Livy here means the second (and larger)
                        part of the column, under Hannibal's immediate command. </note> down into
                    the defile, since he had no troops left to secure the rear of the infantry, as
                    he himself <pb n="p.103"/> secured that of the horse, the <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> mountaineers rushed <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 21</note> in on his flank, and
                    breaking through the column, established themselves in the road, so that
                    Hannibal spent one night without cavalry or baggage. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following day, since by now the
                    barbarians were attacking with less vigour, his forces were re-united and
                    surmounted the pass; and though they suffered some casualties, still they lost
                    more baggage animals than men. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From this point
                    on the mountaineers appeared in smaller numbers, and, more in the manner of
                    brigandage than warfare, attacked sometimes the van, sometimes the rear,
                    whenever the ground afforded an advantage, or the invaders, pushing on too far
                    ahead or lagging behind, gave opportunity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    elephants could be induced to move but very slowly along the steep and narrow
                    trails; but wherever they went they made the column safe from its enemies, who
                    were unaccustomed to the beasts and afraid of venturing too near them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the ninth day they arrived at the summit of
                    the Alps, having come for the most part over trackless wastes and by roundabout
                    routes, owing either to the dishonesty of their guides, or —when they would not
                    trust the guides —to their blindly entering some valley, guessing at the way.
                    For two days they lay encamped on the summit. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The soldiers, worn with toil and fighting, were permitted to rest; and a number
                    of baggage animals which had fallen among the rocks made their way to the camp
                    by following the tracks of the army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Exhausted
                    and discouraged as the soldiers were by many hardships, a snow-storm —for the
                    constellation of the Pleiades was now setting <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The morning setting of the Pleiades occurred on October
                        26. </note> —threw them into a great fear. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.105"/> The ground was everywhere covered deep with snow <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> when at
                    dawn they began to march, and as the column moved slowly on, dejection and
                    despair were to be read in every countenance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Then Hannibal, who had gone on before the standards, made the army halt on a
                    certain promontory which commanded an extensive prospect, and pointing out Italy
                    to them, and just under the Alps the plains about the Po, he told them that they
                    were now scaling the ramparts not only of Italy, but of Rome itself; the rest of
                    the way would be level or downhill; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and after
                    one, or, at the most, two battles, they would have in their hands and in their
                    power the citadel and capital of Italy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The column now began to make some progress,
                    and even the enemy had ceased to annoy them, except to make a stealthy raid, as
                    occasion offered. But the way was much more difficult than the ascent had been,
                    as indeed the slope of the Alps on the Italian <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> side is in general more precipitous in proportion as it is
                    shorter. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For practically every road was
                    steep, narrow, and treacherous, so that neither could they keep from slipping,
                    nor could those who had been thrown a little off their balance retain their
                    footing, but came down, one on top of the other, and the beasts on top of the
                    men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They then came to a much narrower cliff, and
                    with rocks so perpendicular that it was difficult for an unencumbered soldier to
                    manage the descent, though he felt his way and clung with his hands to the
                    bushes and roots that projected here and there. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The place had been precipitous before, and a recent landslip had carried it
                    away to the depth of a good thousand feet. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In Polybius (III. liv. 7) the landslip carries away a
                        stretch of road more than a stade and a half (about a thousand feet) <hi
                            rend="italics">long.</hi> Livy got the idea that the thousand feet
                        represented the distance from the top to the bottom of the slip. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There the cavalry <pb n="p.107"/> came to a
                    halt, as though they had reached the end <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> of the road, and as
                    Hannibal was wondering what it could be that held the column back, word was
                    brought to him that the cliff was impassable. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Going then to inspect the place himself, he thought that there was nothing for
                    it but to lead the army round, over trackless and untrodden steeps, however
                    circuitous the detour might be. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But that way
                    proved to be insuperable; for above the old, untouched snow lay a fresh deposit
                    of moderate depth, through which, as it was soft and not very deep, the men in
                    front found it easy to advance; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but when it
                    had been trampled down by the feet of so many men and beasts, the rest had to
                    make their way over the bare ice beneath and the slush of the melting snow.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then came a terrible struggle on the
                    slippery surface, for it afforded them no foothold, while the downward slope
                    made their feet the more quickly slide from under them; so that whether they
                    tried to pull themselves up with their hands, or used their knees, these
                    supports themselves would slip, and down they would come again! Neither were
                    there any stems or roots about, by which a man could pull himself up with foot
                    or hand —only smooth ice and thawing snow, on which they were continually
                    rolling. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the baggage animals, as they went
                    over the snow, would sometimes even cut into the lowest crust, and pitching
                    forward and striking out with their hoofs, as they struggled to rise, would
                    break clean through it, so that numbers of them were caught fast, as if
                    entrapped, in the hard, deep-frozen snow. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At last, when men and beasts had been worn out
                    to no avail, they encamped upon the ridge, <pb n="p.109"/> after having, with
                    the utmost difficulty, cleared <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 218</note> enough ground even for this purpose, so much
                    snow were they obliged to dig out and remove. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The soldiers were then set to work to construct a road across the cliff-their
                    only possible way. Since they had to cut through the rock, they felled some huge
                    trees that grew near at hand, and lopping off their branches, made an enormous
                    pile of logs. This they set on fire, as soon as the wind blew fresh enough to
                    make it burn, and pouring vinegar over the glowing rocks, caused them to
                    crumble. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After thus heating the crag with
                    fire, they opened a way in it with iron tools, and relieved the steepness of the
                    slope with zigzags of an easy gradient, so that not only the baggage animals but
                    even the elephants could be led down. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This famous story has provoked much ridicule, but in Livy's defence may be
                        noted, (1) the well-known disintegrating effect on certain kinds of stone of
                        heat followed by a douche of cold water; (2) the belief entertained in
                        ancient times, and as late as the sixteenth century, that vinegar helped to
                        make stones friable; (3) the likelihood that Hannibal had at least a few
                        skins of sour wine in his baggage-train (some have held that a vast quantity
                        would have been required, but it must be remembered that Livy may have
                        conceived of the <hi rend="italics">width</hi> of the landslip as only a few
                        rods; see last note). In any case those who regard the vinegar story as
                        fiction must not fasten the fiction on Livy, if, as I think, we may discern
                        an allusion to it in Varro's Menippean Satires ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >Sesculixes,</hi> frag. 25, p. 237, of the Buecheler-Heraeus edition:
                        alteram viam deformasse Carneaden virtutis e cupis acris aceti), and it was
                        probably an old and popular tradition long before the time of Varro, who
                        died in <date when="-0027">27 B.C.</date> For recent discussion of the story
                        see the article by Evan T. Sage in <hi rend="italics">C. W.</hi> 16
                        (1922-1923) 73-76, and notes of modern instances by other contributors to
                        the same volume. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Four days were consumed at the cliff, and the
                    animals nearly perished of starvation; for the mountain tops are all practically
                    bare, and such grass as does grow is buried under snow. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius (III. Iv. 7) says that the pack-animals and
                        horses were sent over the road after one day's work had been done, and
                        turned out to pasture, but that three days were employed in making it
                        sufficiently wide for the elephants. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Lower down one comes to valleys and sunny
                    slopes and rivulets, and near them woods, and places that begin to be fitter for
                    man's habitation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There the beasts were turned
                    out to graze, and the men, exhausted with toiling at the road, were allowed to
                    rest. Thence they descended in three days' time <pb n="p.111"/> into the plain,
                    through a region now that was less <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 218</note> forbidding, as was the character of its
                    inhabitants. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the chief features of the march to
                    Italy, which they accomplished five months after leaving New Carthage —as
                    certain authorities state —having crossed the Alps in fifteen days. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The strength of Hannibal's forces on his entering
                    Italy is a point on which historians are by no means agreed. Those who put the
                    figures highest give him a hundred thousand foot and twenty thousand horse; the
                    lowest estimate is twenty thousand foot and six thousand horse. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So Polybius (III. lvi. 4), who says
                        that these numbers were given by Hannibal himself in an inscription at
                        Lacinium. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Lucius Cincius Alimentus, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Praetor in Sicily, <date when="-0210"
                            >210 B.C.</date> He and Fabius Pictor were contemporaries and were
                        Livy's oldest sources. </note> who says that he was taken prisoner by
                    Hannibal, would be our weightiest authority, did he not confuse the reckoning by
                    adding in Gauls and Ligurians: including these, he says that Hannibal brought
                    eighty thousand foot and ten thousand horse —but <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> it is more probable, and certain historians so hold, that these people joined
                    his standard in Italy; he says, moreover, that he had learned from Hannibal's
                    own lips that after crossing the Rhone he lost thirty-six thousand men and a
                    vast number of horses and other animals. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius (iii. Iv. 5) says that Hannibal left the Rhone
                        with thirty-eight thousand infantry and eight thousand cavalry, and lost
                        more than half his troops crossing the passes. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Taurine Gauls were the first people he
                    encountered on descending into Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Since
                    all are agreed on this point, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">It is a
                        moot question whether Polybius shared this view.</note> I am the more
                    astonished at the difference of opinion in regard to his route over the Alps,
                    and that it should be commonly held that he crossed by the Poenine Pass <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The Great St. Bernard.</note> and that
                    from this circumstance that ridge of the Alps derived its name —and <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> that Coelius should state that he crossed by the
                    ridge of Cremo; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Perhaps the Little St.
                        Bernard.</note> for <pb n="p.113"/> both these passes would have brought him
                    down, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    not amongst the Taurini but through the Salassi Montani to the Libuan Gauls.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Neither is it probable that these routes
                    to Gaul <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy means Cisalpine Gaul; he
                        is writing from Hannibal's standpoint. </note> were open at that time; those
                    leading to the Poenine Pass, at any rate, would have been blocked by tribes of
                    half-German stock. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor for that matter —if
                    anyone happens to consider this point of consequence —do the Seduni Veragri, who
                    inhabit those mountains, know of their having been named from any passage of the
                    Phoenicians (or Poeni) but from that deity whose sanctuary is established on
                    their very summit and whom the mountaineers call Poeninus. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Coins and votive offerings have been discovered there,
                        and the remains of the little temple of the god, who was apparently the
                        Juppiter Poeninus of certain extant inscriptions. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quite opportunely for the opening of the
                    campaign, the Taurini, the nearest tribe, had begun a war against the Insubres.
                    But Hannibal was unable to put an army in the field to aid the Insubres, as the
                    soldiers while convalescing felt more keenly than ever the distress arising from
                    the hardships they had undergone; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for rest
                    coming after toil, plenty after want, comfort after filth and wet, produced all
                    manner of disorders in their squalid and well-nigh brutalized bodies. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> This was the reason why the consul Publius Cornelius,
                    who had come by sea to Pisa, though the army which he received from Manlius and
                    Atilius was made up of raw recruits, still quaking from their recent defeats,
                    yet marched in all haste towards the Po, that he might join battle with an enemy
                    not yet restored to vigour. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when the
                    consul reached Placentia, Hannibal <pb n="p.115"/> had already broken camp and
                    taken the capital city <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 218</note> of the Taurini by assault, because they would not freely
                    come into his friendship. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the other hand,
                    he would have brought the Gauls who dwell along the Po to join him, not alone
                    from fear but even of their own free choice, had not the consul taken them by
                    surprise, appearing unexpectedly whilst they were looking about them for a
                    pretext to revolt. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hannibal, too, moved
                    forward from the Taurini, being persuaded that the Gauls, uncertain which side
                    they had best adhere to, would attach themselves to those who were on the spot. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The armies were now almost within sight of
                    each other, and the opposing generals, though as yet they did not know one
                    another well, had yet each been imbued with a kind of admiration for his
                    antagonist. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For Hannibal's name had been very
                    renowned amongst the Romans, even before the destruction of Saguntum, and Scipio
                    was a man of mark in the eyes of Hannibal, from the mere fact of his having been
                    selected, in preference to any other, to command against himself. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Each had increased the other's good opinion —Scipio,
                    because, though left behind in Gaul, he had confronted Hannibal at his crossing
                    over into Italy; Hannibal by the audacity with which he had conceived and
                    executed his passage of the Alps. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Scipio, however, was the first to cross the
                    Po. He brought his army up to the river Ticinus, and in order to put heart into
                    the men before leading them out to fight, harangued them after the following
                    fashion: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Soldiers, if I were leading into battle the
                    army that I had under me in Gaul, I should have <pb n="p.117"/> deemed it
                    unnecessary to address you. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For what <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> point
                    would there have been in exhorting either those horsemen who at the river Rhone
                    had signally defeated the horsemen of the enemy, or those legions with which I
                    pursued this very enemy in his flight, and by the confession implied in his
                    withdrawal and avoidance of a battle, gained a virtual victory? <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> As it is, since that army, enrolled for service in Spain,
                    is campaigning there under my auspices with my brother Gnaeus Scipio, where the
                    senate and the Roman People desired that it should serve, and I myself, that you
                    might <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> have a consul for your leader against
                    Hannibal and the Phoenicians, have of my own choice undertaken the present
                    conflict, it is right that your new commander should say a word or two to his
                    new soldiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "That you may not be ignorant what manner of
                    war it is, or what your enemies are, you are to fight, my men, with those whom
                    you defeated in the former war, on land and sea; with those from whom you
                    exacted tribute for twenty years; with those from whom you wrested Sicily and
                    Sardinia, which you now hold as the spoils of war. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> You and they will therefore enter the present struggle with
                    such spirits as usually attend the victors and the vanquished. Nor are they now
                    going to fight because they dare, but because they must; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> unless you think that those who avoided battle when their
                    strength was unimpaired would, now that they have lost two-thirds of their
                    infantry and cavalry in the passage of the Alps, have become more hopeful!
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But, you will say, their numbers indeed
                    are small, but their courage and vigour are so great that scarce any force could
                    withstand their might and power. Nay, not so! <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    They <pb n="p.119"/> are but the semblance, the shadows of men, wasted <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> away with
                    hunger and cold, with filth and squalor; bruised and crippled amongst the rocks
                    and cliffs; moreover, their limbs are frost-bitten, their muscles stiffened by
                    the snow, their bodies numb with cold, their arms shattered and broken, their
                    horses lame and feeble. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That is the cavalry,
                    that the infantry with which you are to fight; you have no enemy —only the last
                    relics of an enemy! And I fear nothing more than this, that when you have
                    fought, it may seem to have been the Alps that conquered Hannibal. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> But perhaps it was right that the gods themselves,
                    without any human aid, should begin and decide a war with a general and a people
                    who break their treaties; and that we, whose injury was second to that of the
                    gods, should add the finishing stroke to a war already so begun and so decided. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> I am not afraid that anyone may suppose that I am using these brave
                        words to encourage you, but that in my heart I think otherwise. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> It was open to me to proceed with my army to my
                        own province, Spain, for which I had already started; I might there have had
                        a brother to share my counsels and my dangers, and Hasdrubal instead of
                        Hannibal for my enemy, and a war undoubtedly less difficult to conduct;
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> nevertheless, when rumours of this
                        enemy reached me, as I sailed along by the coast of Gaul, I landed, and
                        sending my cavalry ahead, moved my camp up to the Rhone. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In a cavalry engagement —for this was the arm with
                        which I was given the opportunity of fighting —I put the enemy to rout: his
                        infantry column, marching hastily off as if in flight, I could not overtake
                        by land; returning therefore to my ships I accomplished with all <pb
                            n="p.121"/> possible expedition so circuitous a voyage and march, <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> and am
                        come to confront this redoubtable enemy almost at the very foot of the Alps.
                        Does it look as though I were avoiding battle and had blundered upon him
                        unawares? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> or, rather, as though I were in
                        hot haste to encounter him and to provoke and bait him into fighting?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I would willingly make trial whether
                        the earth has suddenly produced in the last twenty years <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The First Punic War had ended in
                                <date when="-0241">241 B.C.</date>
                        </note> another breed of Carthaginians, or whether they are the same who
                        fought at the Aegatian islands and whom you suffered to depart from Eryx at
                        a rating of eighteen denarii a head; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and
                        whether our friend Hannibal is a rival, as he himself would have it, of the
                        wandering Hercules, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Hercules was
                            fabled to have crossed the Alps on his return from the island Erythea
                            with the cattle of Geryon. Livy has alluded to this story before (I.
                            vii. 3 and v, xxxiv. 6). </note> or has been left to the Roman People by
                        his father to be their tributary, tax-payer, and slave. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Were he not maddened by the crime he committed at
                        Saguntum, he would surely have regard, if not for his conquered country, yet
                        at least for his house and his father and the treaties written by the hand
                        of Hamilcar, who, under the orders of our consul, withdrew his garrison from
                        Eryx; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> who submitted with rage and anguish
                        to the heavy terms imposed upon the beaten Carthaginians; who agreed, on
                        withdrawing from Sicily, to pay tribute to the Roman People. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> And so I could wish you, soldiers, to fight not
                        only with that courage with which you are wont to fight against other
                        enemies, but with a kind of resentful rage, as if you saw your slaves all at
                        once take up arms against you. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When we
                        had shut them up at Eryx, we might have killed them by starvation, the worst
                        torment that man can know; we might have dispatched our victorious fleet to
                        Africa, and in a few days' time, without <pb n="p.123"/> the slightest
                        struggle, have annihilated Carthage. <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But we gave them the quarter they
                        besought of us; we lifted the siege and let them go; we made peace with them
                        when we had conquered them; and thereafter, when they were hard pressed by
                        the war in Africa, we regarded them as under our protection. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> In requital of these benefits they are coming in
                        the train of a crazy youth to assail our country! <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> And I would that your honour only and not your very
                        existence were in jeopardy: you have got to fight not for the ownership of
                        Sicily and Sardinia, which were formerly in dispute, but for Italy.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There is no second army at our back
                        to stop the enemy, in case we fail to beat him, nor are there other Alps to
                        obstruct his advance while we make ready new defences. Here, soldiers, is
                        the spot where we must make our stand, as though we were fighting before the
                        walls of Rome. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Let each and every one of
                        you consider that his arms protect, not his own person, but his wife and
                        little children; nor let him be concerned for his family alone, but remember
                        that ours are the hands to which the senate and the Roman People are now
                        looking, and that even as our might and valour shall prove to be, <milestone
                            n="17??" unit="section"/> such henceforward will be the fortune of that
                        City and the Roman empire. </quote> So spoke the consul to the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal thought it well to encourage his
                    soldiers by an object lesson before haranguing them. He therefore caused the
                    army to gather in a circle for the spectacle, and setting in the midst some
                    captive mountaineers with fetters on them, gave the order to throw some Gallic
                    weapons down at their feet, and bade an interpreter enquire if any were willing
                    to fight for life or death, on condition of <pb n="p.125"/> being granted
                    freedom, if victorious, and presented <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C.218</note> with a horse and arms. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When the captives, to the last man, called for sword and
                    combat, and lots were being cast to decide amongst them, each hoped that he
                    should be the one whom fortune selected for that contest; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and he who had drawn the lot would leap for joy, and
                    dancing about —as their custom is —while the others showered congratulations on
                    him, would eagerly snatch up his weapons. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But
                    when they fought, the feeling, not only in the bosoms of the other captives but
                    even amongst the onlookers in general, was such that the fortune of those who
                    conquered was not more praised than that of those who met an honourable death.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius gives substantially the
                        same account of the episode (II. Iv. 2), except that he speaks of only one
                        pair of combatants. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having thus, by the exhibition of several
                    pairs, worked on the passions of his troops, he dismissed them. Then, convening
                    an assembly, he addressed them —so it is said —in the following strain: "If that
                    spirit which but now was roused in you by the example of the plight of others
                    shall presently be yours, when you consider your own prospects, then, soldiers,
                    the victory is ours. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For that was no mere
                    spectacle, but a kind of picture, as it were, of your own condition. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> And I incline to think that Fortune has laid you
                    under stronger bonds and heavier necessities than your captives. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> On the right and on the left two seas encompass you,
                    and you have not a single ship, even to flee in; round you is the river Po —the
                    Po, a greater and more turbulent river than the Rhone; behind you tower the
                    Alps, which you hardly scaled when you were fresh and vigorous. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Here, soldiers, you must conquer or die, where for the
                    first time you have faced the enemy. And the same Fortune which has laid upon
                    you the <pb n="p.127"/> necessity of fighting holds forth the promise of such
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    prizes, in the event of victory, that men are wont to ask not even the immortal
                    gods for greater. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If it were only Sicily and
                    Sardinia, wrested from our fathers, that we were going to recover by our valour,
                    these would still be great enough rewards. As it is, whatever the Romans have
                    won and heaped up in the course of all their triumphs, whatever they possess, is
                    all destined —and its owners with it —to be yours. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Come then! Arm yourselves, with Heaven helping you, to earn
                    this splendid wage! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Long enough have you been
                    chasing flocks on the barren mountains of Lusitania and Celtiberia, without
                    seeing any recompense for all your toil and dangers. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> It is now time for you to make rich and lucrative
                    campaigns, and reap the large rewards of so long a march over so many mountains
                    and rivers and through so many warlike tribes. Here Fortune has fixed the final
                    goal of your labours; here, when your wars are ended, she will worthily requite
                    you. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "Nor must you think that in proportion to the
                    great name of the war will be the difficulty you will have in winning it.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It has often happened that even an enemy
                    held cheap has caused a bloody battle, and that nations and princes of renown
                    have been very lightly overcome. Take from your enemies this one glory of the
                    Roman name, and in what particular can they bear comparison with you? <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> To say nothing of your twenty years of service and
                    your far-famed courage and good fortune, you <milestone n="13??" unit="section"
                    /> have come from the Pillars of Hercules, from the Ocean and the uttermost
                    limits of the world, and through so many of the fiercest tribes of Spain and
                    Gaul have fought your way victoriously to this field. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> You will be <pb n="p.129"/> pitted against an army of
                    recruits, who have been <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C.218</note> this very summer cut to pieces, routed, and besieged by
                    Gauls —an army as yet unknown to its general and one that knows not him.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Or am I, who if not actually born in the
                    headquarters of my father-most illustrious of commanders —was at least brought
                    up there, am I, the subjugator of Spain and Gaul and conqueror not only of the
                    Alpine tribes, but —what is much more —of the Alps themselves, am I, I ask you,
                    to compare myself to this six-months general, who has deserted his own army?
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Why, if one were to show him to-day the
                    Phoenicians and Romans without their standards, I am certain he would not know
                    which army he was consul of. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> For my part,
                    soldiers, I regard it as no slight advantage that there is not one of you in
                    whose sight I have not often myself performed some soldierly feat; not one of
                    whose courage I have not in my turn been a spectator and eye-witness —whose
                    deeds of prowess, noted, together with their times and circumstances, I am not
                    able to rehearse. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> I shall enter the battle in
                    company with men whom I have praised and decorated a thousand times, and to all
                    of whom I was a foster-son before I was their general. Opposed to me will be men
                    who do not even know each other. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Wherever I turn my eyes I see nothing but eagerness and strength, a
                        veteran infantry, cavalry from the noblest tribes, riding with bridles or
                        without, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Numidians used no
                            bridles: the cavalry using them were Spaniards. </note> here <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> the trustiest and most valiant of allies, there
                        Carthaginians, prepared to fight not only in defence of their native land,
                        but in satisfaction of a most righteous indignation. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> We are the assailants, and are descending with hostile
                        standards into Italy, <pb n="p.131"/> where we shall fight with more
                        boldness and courage <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                            >B.C. 218</note> than our foes in proportion as our hopes are higher and
                        the gallantry of the assailant greater than his who but defends himself.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Moreover, our hearts are kindled and
                        pricked by rancour, wrongs, and insults. They called for the punishment of
                        myself first, as your leader, then of all of you who had borne a part in the
                        assault upon Saguntum; had we been given up, they meant to have inflicted
                        upon us the worst of tortures. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Most
                        inhuman and most arrogant of nations, they reckon the world as theirs and
                        subject to their pleasure. With whom we are to be at war, with whom at
                        peace, they think it right that they should determine. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They circumscribe and hem us in with boundaries of
                        mountains and rivers which we may not cross; yet they do not observe those
                        boundaries which they have set. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> ' Do not
                        cross the Ebro! Have naught to do with the Saguntines!' But Saguntum is
                        free. ' Do not budge from where you are in any direction!' Is it not enough
                        that you have taken away my ancient provinces of Sicily and Sardinia? Are
                        you taking away Spain as well? If I withdraw from these, shall you cross
                        over into Africa? <hi rend="italics">Shall,</hi> do I say? They <hi
                            rend="italics">have</hi> dispatched the two consuls of this year, the
                        one into Africa, and the other into Spain! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Nothing is left us anywhere, except what we shall defend by force of arms.
                        They can afford to be timid and unenterprising who have something to fall
                        back upon; whom their own country and their own fields will receive as they
                        flee over safe and peaceful roads. As for you, you must be stout-hearted
                        men, and discarding, without vain regrets, all hopes of anything but <pb
                            n="p.133"/> victory or death, either conquer or, if Fortune falters,
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                        sooner perish in battle than in flight. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If
                        this idea has been firmly fixed and implanted in your hearts, let me say
                        once more: the victory is already yours. The immortal gods have bestowed on
                        man no sharper weapon for winning victories than contempt of death. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the spirits of the soldiers on both sides
                    had been whetted for the struggle by these speeches, the Romans threw a bridge
                    over the Ticinus and erected a fort besides for its protection; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and the Phoenician, whilst his enemies were engaged in
                    fortification, sent Maharbal with a squadron of Numidians, numbering five
                    hundred horse, to ravage the fields belonging to the allies of the Roman People,
                    with orders to spare the Gauls as much as possible and tempt their leaders to
                    desert. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the completion of the bridge, the
                    Roman army marched over into the country of the Insubres, and took up a position
                    five miles from Victumulae. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was there that
                    Hannibal had his camp, who, quickly recalling Maharbal and his cavalry, when he
                    saw that a battle was imminent, called his troops together —for he never felt
                    that he had done enough in the way of preparing and cheering the men —and held
                    out definite rewards to them to fight for; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> he
                    would give them land, he said, in Italy, Africa, or Spain, as each might choose,
                    tax-free to the recipient and to his children; those who had rather have money
                    than land he would content with silver; if any of the allies desired to become
                    citizens of Carthage, he would give them the opportunity; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> as for such as preferred to go back to their homes, he
                    would see to it that they should feel no inclination to change <pb n="p.135"/>
                    places with any of their countrymen; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> besides
                    this he <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    promised freedom to the slaves who had come with their masters, and declared
                    that he would make restitution to the latter, at the rate of two for one.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And that they might know that these
                    promises would be kept, he held a lamb with his left hand, and with his right a
                    flint, and praying that if he should deceive them, then Jupiter and the other
                    gods might slay him, even as he had slain the lamb, he thereupon smote the
                    lamb's head with the stone. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In this
                        ceremony the flint symbolizes the thunderbolt of Jupiter. The rite was
                        characteristic of the Roman fetials (I. xxiv. 9), and Livy here ascribes it
                        to Hannibal, to add to the dramatic effect of the scene. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then indeed they all, as though each had
                    received the blessing of the gods on his own particular hopes, and thought that
                    their fulfilment was being delayed only because they were not yet fighting,
                    cried out with one accord and one voice for battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the Roman side there was far less alacrity,
                    for, besides other things, they were also frightened by some recent portents:
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> a wolf had entered the camp and after
                    rending those whom it met, had itself escaped unharmed; and a swarm of bees had
                    settled in a tree that hung over the consul's tent. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> After averting these omens, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> having by sacrifice to the gods averted the
                        evil portended by these omens. </note> Scipio set out with his cavalry and
                    light-armed darters to reconnoitre at close hand the enemy's camp and the size
                    and character of his forces, and encountered Hannibal, who had likewise come out
                    with his cavalry to explore the surrounding country. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Neither party descried the other at first; afterwards an
                    increasingly thick cloud of dust, that rose with the advance of so many men and
                    horses, gave them notice that their enemies were approaching. Both bodies halted
                    and began to make ready for battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.137"/> Scipio stationed his darters and Gallic horse in front, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> holding in
                    reserve the Romans and the best of the allies; Hannibal put the cavalry who rode
                    with bridles in the centre, and made his wings strong with Numidians. Hardly had
                    the battle-cry been raised, when the darters fled through their supports to the
                    second line. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then followed a cavalry fight of
                    which the issue was for a time in doubt; but by and by the horses became excited
                    by the presence of the foot-soldiers who were mingled with them, and many riders
                    lost their seats or dismounted on seeing their fellows in distress, and the
                    battle was now fought chiefly on foot; until the Numidians, who were posted on
                    the flanks, rode round in a little circuit and showed themselves on the rear.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So alarming a sight filled the Romans with
                    dismay, and, to add to their fear, the consul was wounded and was only saved
                    from danger by the intervention of his son, who was just reaching manhood.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This is the youth who will have the glory
                    of finishing this war, and be surnamed Africanus, from his famous victory over
                    Hannibal and the Phoenicians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> However, the
                    rout was chiefly amongst the darters, the first to be charged by the Numidians:
                    the cavalry rallied, and receiving the consul into their midst, and shielding
                    him not only with their arms but with their persons also, brought him back to
                    camp without panic or confusion at any point in their retreat. (The credit for
                    saving the consul's life is given by Coelius to a Ligurian slave. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> I should prefer, for my own part, that the story
                    about his son were the true one, and this is the version which most authorities
                    have handed down and tradition has established. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius, who had the story from Laelius, the bosom
                        friend of the younger Africanus, is among those who make Scipio the hero of
                        this anecdote (x. iii. 2). Coelius dedicated his work to L. Aelius (Peter,
                            <hi rend="italics">Rell.</hi> I. ccxv.), not, as formerly thought, to
                        Laelius, which would have made his rejection of the version honouring Scipio
                        strange. </note> ) </p>
                <pb n="p.139"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the first battle fought with <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> Hannibal,
                    in which it was clearly seen that the Phoenician was superior in cavalry and
                    that consequently open plains, like those between the Po and the Alps, were
                    ill-suited to the Romans for campaigning. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, the next night Scipio gave his men the order to pack up without
                    making any noise, and quitting his camp on the Ticinus, marched swiftly to the
                    Po, intending to use the bridge of boats which he had thrown across the river
                    and had not yet broken up, in order to set his army over without confusion or
                    interruption by the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were at
                    Placentia before Hannibal was well aware that they were gone from the Ticinus;
                    nevertheless some six hundred men, who were lingering on the northern bank and
                    taking their time about casting off the raft, fell into Hannibal's hands. He was
                    not able to cross the bridge, for when the end was cast off, the whole raft
                    swung down stream with the current. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Polybius (III. lxvi) makes Hannibal pursue Scipio only as far as the Ticinus
                        (where Polybius places the episode of the six hundred), then turn back and
                        march W. along the Po two days, till he found a place where he could bridge
                        it. See Map 2, <hi rend="italics">Operations on the Po.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Coelius states that Mago with the cavalry and
                    the Spanish foot immediately swam the river, and that Hannibal himself led his
                    army across the Po by an upper ford, after placing the elephants in a line to
                    break the current of the river. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those who are
                    acquainted with the Po will hardly credit this account; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> One of the very few places where Livy implies a
                        firsthand acquaintance with the scene of events described. </note> for, in
                    the first place, it is unlikely that the horsemen could have breasted so strong
                    a current without the loss of arms or horses, even if all the Spaniards had swum
                    over on inflated skins, and in the second place it would have needed a
                    circuitous march of many days to reach fords on the Po by which an army
                    encumbered with baggage could get across. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.141"/>
                <p> Those writers seem to me more worthy of belief <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> who relate that in two
                    days' search a pace was scarcely found where the river could be spanned by a
                    bridge of boats; by this the cavalry and light Spanish infantry were sent
                    forward under Mago. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While Hannibal, who had
                    lingered on the northern bank to give a hearing to some Gallic embassies, was
                    bringing over the heavy infantry, Mago and his horsemen advanced a day's march
                    from the crossing of the river towards Placentia and the enemy. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A few days later, Hannibal went into camp behind
                    entrenchments, six miles from the town, and on the following day drew up his
                    troops in sight of the enemy and offered battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next night there was a bloody affray in
                    the Roman camp, occasioned by some Gallic auxiliaries, though the confusion was
                    greater than the loss of life. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Some two
                    thousand foot-soldiers and two hundred horsemen cut down the guards doing duty
                    at the gates and fled to Hannibal, who received them with fair words, and after
                    encouraging them to hope for great rewards, sent them off to their several
                    states to solicit the support of their countrymen. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio apprehended that this bloodshed would prove to be a
                    signal for the defection of all the Gauls, and that they would fly to arms, as
                    if maddened by the contagion of this crime. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, though still troubled with his wound, he marched silently away in
                    the fourth watch of the next night to the river Trebia, and encamped on higher
                    ground, where hills made it more difficult for cavalry to operate. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> He was less successful than he had been on the
                    Ticinus in eluding the observation of Hannibal, who sent after him first the
                    Numidians and then all his <pb n="p.143"/> cavalry, and would have thrown the
                    rearguard at <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        218</note> least into disorder, had not the Numidians, in their greed for
                    booty, turned aside to plunder the camp which the Romans had abandoned.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whilst they frittered away the time there,
                    rummaging in every nook and cranny without finding anything that really repaid
                    them for the loss of time, they let their enemies slip through their fingers.
                    The Romans had already passed the Trebia and were marking out their camp, when
                    the Numidians caught sight of them and cut down a few loiterers whom they
                    intercepted on the hither side of the stream. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio could no longer bear the pain occasioned by the jolting of his wound in
                    travelling, and besides he judged it best to wait for the arrival of his
                    colleague, who was already recalled —so he had heard —from Sicily. He therefore
                    chose what seemed to be the safest place near the river for a permanent camp,
                    and proceeded to entrench it. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hannibal, too, went into camp not far away.
                    Elated as he was at the victory of his horse, he was no less worried by the
                    dearth of food, which increased from day to day, as he advanced through hostile
                    territory without having anywhere arranged beforehand for supplies. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> In the village of Clastidium the Romans had got
                    together a great quantity of corn. Thither Hannibal dispatched some soldiers,
                    who were making preparations to assault the place, when hopes were held out of
                    its betrayal. The price was not a large one: Dasius of Brundisium, who was in
                    command of the garrison, accepted a bribe of four hundred gold pieces, and
                    turned Clastidium over to Hannibal. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This
                    served the Phoenicians as a granary, while they lay encamped on <pb n="p.145"/>
                    the Trebia. The surrendered garrison were spared, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> as Hannibal wished to gain
                    at the very outset a reputation for clemency. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though the war on land had come to a
                    standstill at the Trebia, engagements had in the meantime been fought by land
                    and sea off Sicily and the islands near the Italian coast, not only by
                    Sempronius the consul, but even before his coming thither. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Twenty quinqueremes with a thousand men at arms had been
                    sent by the Carthaginians to lay waste the coast of Italy; nine of them reached
                    Liparae and eight the Isle of Vulcan; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This island, south of Lirara, and known also as Thermissa, <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">,</foreign> and Hiera, is now called Volcano. </note>
                    three the current diverted from their course into the Straits. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> These last were sighted by the people of Messana, and
                    Hiero, king of the Syracusans, who happened to be in Messana at the time,
                    waiting for the Roman consul, dispatched twelve ships, which captured the
                    enemy's ships without a struggle and brought them into the harbour of Messana.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was learned from the prisoners that,
                    besides the fleet of twenty galleys to which they themselves belonged —which had
                    sailed for Italy —five and thirty other quinqueremes were on the way to Sicily
                    to rouse up the old allies; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the seizure of
                    Lilybaeum was their prime object; but they supposed that the same storm by which
                    they had themselves been scattered had struck this fleet as well and had driven
                    it out of its course to the Aegatian Islands. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The king wrote a full account of these rumours, just as they had come to him, to
                    Marcus Aemilius, the praetor, <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> who was in
                    command in Sicily, and warned him to garrison Lilybaeum strongly. The praetor at
                    once sent out his lieutenants and tribunes to the cities round about, and urged
                    his people to be on their guard. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Above all,
                    Lilybaeum <pb n="p.147"/> was kept in a state of readiness for war, an edict
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    having been published directing the naval allies to bring to their ships cooked
                    rations for ten days, so that, on the signal being given, there might be nothing
                    to delay their embarkation. All along the coast men were sent to keep a look-out
                    from the watch-towers for the coming of the enemy's fleet. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> And so, notwithstanding that the Carthaginians had delayed
                    their sailing on purpose that they might come up to Lilybaeum in the dark, they
                    were nevertheless perceived, because there was a moon all night and they bore
                    down under a spread of canvas. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The signal was
                    at once displayed from the watchtowers, and in the town the call to arms was
                    sounded and the ships were manned; some of the troops were at once on the walls
                    or guarding the gates, some on the ships. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And
                    the Carthaginians, seeing that they should have to do with men who were not
                    unprepared, stood off from the harbour until dawn and employed the time in
                    taking down their masts and sails and putting the fleet in fighting trim.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the day broke, they withdrew into
                    the open sea, to give room for the battle and to allow their enemy's ships a
                    ready egress from the harbour. Nor did the Romans shun the encounter. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> They remembered the victories that had been won in
                    that same vicinity, and relied on the numbers and the bravery of their men.
                        <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/> Once at sea, the Romans wanted to join
                    battle and match their strength against the enemy's at close quarters.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Phoenicians, on the contrary,
                    preferred to manœuvre; to conduct the affair by strategy, not by force, and to
                    make it a contest <pb n="p.149"/> rather of ships than of men or arms.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For although <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> their fleet was well
                    equipped with rowers, they were short of fighting men; and when a ship was
                    grappled, the men-at-arms in her were greatly outnumbered by their enemies.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Perceiving this, the Romans derived a
                    fresh access of courage from their numbers, and the other side were
                    correspondingly disheartened by their fewness. Seven Punic ships were instantly
                    cut out and captured, and the rest took to flight. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> There were seventeen hundred soldiers and sailors on the
                    captured ships, including three Carthaginian nobles. The Roman fleet returned
                    intact into the harbour: one ship only had been rammed, and even this was
                    brought safely in. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After this engagement, but before the people
                    in Messana had got wind of it, the consul Tiberius Sempronius came to that city.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As he was entering the straits, King Hiero
                    put out to meet him, with his fleet in fighting order, and passing over from the
                    royal galley to the praetorian, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So
                        the flagship was called, from the old use of <hi rend="italics">praetor</hi>
                        in the sense of <quote>commander</quote> ; cf. praetorian camp, praetorian
                        guard. The consuls were at first called praetors (III. Iv. 12). </note>
                    congratulated Sempronius on having arrived in safety with his army and his
                    ships, and prayed that he might have a safe and successful passage to Sicily.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then described conditions in the island
                    and the attempts made by the Carthaginians, and promised that with the same
                    spirit with which, in <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> his youth, he had
                    helped the Roman People in the former war he would help them now, as an old man,
                    and would furnish corn and clothing gratis to the legions of the consul and the
                    naval allies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He added that Lilybaeum and the
                    cities of the coast were in great danger, and that some of them would welcome a
                    revolution. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In view of these things, the
                    consul saw fit to sail without delay for Lilybaeum, and the king attended him
                    with <pb n="p.151"/> the royal fleet. On the voyage they learned of the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> action
                    that had been fought near that city, and the defeat and capture of the enemy's
                    ships. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From Lilybaeum the consul dismissed King Hiero
                    and his fleet, and leaving the praetor to protect the coast of Sicily, set sail
                    for the island of Melita, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Malta.</note> which was held by the Carthaginians. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> On his arrival, Hamilcar, Gisgo's son, the commandant of
                    the garrison, surrendered himself and nearly two thousand soldiers, together
                    with the town and island. From Melita Sempronius returned in a few days to
                    Lilybaeum, and consul and praetor sold into slavery the prisoners they had made,
                    with the exception of those who were distinguished by noble birth. When the
                    consul judged that Sicily was in no danger from that quarter, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> Africa. Livy has omitted to mention the fact,
                        recorded by Coelius (quoted by the grammarian Charisius, II. p. 203 K), that
                        Sempronius even sent a swift galley to spy out a good landing-place for a
                        Roman army on the coast of Africa. </note> he crossed over to the Isles of
                    Vulcan, where it was rumoured that a Punic fleet was lying; but no single enemy
                    was discovered near those islands. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They had
                    already, as it happened, sailed across to ravage the Italian <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> coast, and after pillaging the country about Vibo, were
                    even threatening the town. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul was
                    returning again to Sicily when tidings reached him of the enemy's raid on the
                    lands of Vibo, and a letter was delivered to him from the senate, apprising him
                    of Hannibal's descent into Italy and bidding him go to the assistance of his
                    colleague at the earliest possible moment. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Beset with many cares at once, he immediately embarked his army and dispatched
                    it through the Adriatic to Ariminum; to Sextus Pomponius, his lieutenant, he
                    assigned five and twenty ships of war, with the task of defending the territory
                    of Vibo and the coast of Italy; the fleet under Marcus Aemilius the praetor he
                    increased to fifty sail. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He himself, <pb
                        n="p.153"/> after settling the affairs of Sicily, took ten ships, and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> skirting
                    the Italian coast, arrived at Ariminum. Thence he marched with his army to the
                    Trebia and effected a junction with his colleague. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This important sketch of affairs in Sicily (chapters
                        xlixli) is drawn from a source which cannot be identified. De Sanctis (p
                        186) thinks that the condensed and unrhetorical character of the style
                        excludes its attribution to Coelius; neither Fabius nor Cincius is likely to
                        have been so impartial in giving credit to the allies, like Hiero, and we
                        know of no Greek writer who would have treated minor incidents with such
                        particularity. He conjectures that the unknown writer may have been Eumachus
                        of Naples (who wrote in Greek of the war with Hannibal) or some other
                        Italian or Sicilian historian. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now that both the consuls and all the forces
                    which the Romans could muster were opposing Hannibal, it was obvious enough
                    either that the troops there under arms were able to defend Rome's empire or
                    that her case was hopeless. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nevertheless one
                    of the consuls, disheartened by a single cavalry engagement and weak from his
                    wound, preferred to postpone the decision. The other, unwearied and therefore
                    the more impetuous, would put up with no delay. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The country between the Trebia and the Po was
                    in those days inhabited by Gauls, who in this struggle of two mighty peoples
                    maintained a neutral attitude and plainly intended to court the good-will of the
                    victor. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This policy was agreeable enough to
                    the Romans, if only the Gauls made no disturbance, but was far from acceptable
                    to Hannibal, who declared repeatedly that he had come on the invitation of the
                    Gauls, to set them free. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In his resentment at
                    this state of affairs, and in order at the same time to sustain his troops with
                    plunder, he ordered two thousand foot and a thousand horse —chiefly Numidians
                    but with a sprinkling of Gauls —to <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> waste the
                    entire country-side, field after field, right up to the banks of the Po. The
                    helpless Gauls, who had been undecided until then, were compelled to turn from
                    the authors of their wrongs to those who might avenge them; and, sending envoys
                        <pb n="p.155"/> to the consuls, besought the Romans to come to the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> aid of a
                    land that was suffering for its inhabitants' too great loyalty to Rome.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cornelius liked neither the occasion nor
                    the time for fighting, and regarded the Gauls with suspicion, both because of
                    many acts of perfidy, and especially —even though time had obliterated those
                    ancient grievances —because of the recent treachery of the Boi. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Sempronius, on the contrary, held that the strongest bond
                    for keeping the allies to their obligations was the defence of those who should
                    first stand in need of help. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On the present
                    occasion, while his colleague hesitated, Sempronius sent his cavalry,
                    interspersed with about a thousand foot-soldiers, armed with darts, to protect
                    the Gallic lands beyond the Trebia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Falling
                    unexpectedly upon the enemy, who were scattered and disorganized —most of them
                    laden too with spoils —they drove them with great slaughter in a terror-stricken
                    rout to the very outposts of the Carthaginian camp. Thence the enemy poured out
                    in numbers and repulsed the Romans, in their turn; but reserves came up and
                    restored the day. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thereafter the fortune of
                    the battle shifted, as pursuit was followed by retreat; and though in the end
                    the opposing armies were on even terms, still the enemy had lost more men and
                    the Romans got the credit of a victory. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But to no one did the victory seem greater or
                    more unequivocal than to Sempronius the consul; he was beside himself with joy
                    that with that arm of the service with which the other consul had been beaten,
                    he himself had been successful. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He declared
                    that the spirits of the men were restored and renewed, and that no one but his
                    colleague desired <pb n="p.157"/> to put off the struggle; Cornelius, he said,
                    was sick <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    in spirit rather than in body, and the recollection of his wound made him dread
                    a battle and its missiles. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But they must not
                    droop and languish along with a sick man. Why indeed should they further
                    postpone the conflict, or waste time? What third consul, what other army were
                    they waiting for? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians were
                    encamped in Italy and almost within sight of Rome. Their object was, not to get
                    back Sicily and Sardinia, taken from them after their defeat, nor to cross the
                    Ebro and occupy northern Spain, but to expel the Romans from the land of their
                    fathers and from their native soil. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>How would our fathers groan,</quote> he cried, <quote> that were wont to
                        wage war about the walls of Carthage, could they see us, their offspring,
                        two consuls and two consular armies, cowering within our camp in the heart
                        of Italy; and the Phoenician in full sway over all the territory between the
                        Alps and the Apennines! </quote> Thus he ran on, as he sat by the bed of his
                    sick colleague; thus he argued in the praetorium, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">praetorium</hi> here means the open space in front of the
                        general's tent, not (as often) the tent itself Sempronius meant that the
                        soldiers should know his sentiments, but did not quite go the length of
                        declaring them in a formal harangue. </note> almost as if haranguing the
                    troops. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His impatience was increased, too, by
                    the near approach of the elections, lest the war go over to the term of the new
                    consuls and he lose the opportunity of gaining all the glory for himself, while
                    his colleague was laid up. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Accordingly,
                    despite the unavailing protests of Cornelius, he commanded the soldiers to make
                    ready for an early battle. </p>
                <p> Hannibal, since he saw what was best for the enemy, hardly dared to hope that
                    the consuls would take any rash or ill-considered step; but knowing, as he did
                    —by hearsay first and afterwards by experience —that <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> one of them was of a fiery and <pb n="p.159"/> reckless
                    disposition, and believing that the late successful <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> brush with the
                    Carthaginian raiders would have made him still more headstrong, he was fairly
                    confident that the good fortune of a general engagement was at hand. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> It was therefore his one concern to let slip no
                    opportunity for bringing this about, while the soldiers of the enemy still
                    lacked experience, while the abler of their generals was incapacitated by his
                    wound, while the courage of the Gauls was up —since <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> he knew that their vast multitude would follow the less
                    willingly, the farther they were drawn from home. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> For these and similar reasons he hoped that a battle would
                    soon be fought, and was eager, should there be any hesitation, to force it on.
                    And so, when his Gallic scouts —who were safer for gathering the information
                    that he wanted because there were men of that nation in both camps —had reported
                    that the Romans were prepared to fight, the Phoenician began to look about for a
                    place in which to lay an ambush. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Between the two camps was a water-course, shut
                    in by very high banks on either side and overgrown all round with marsh-grass
                    and the underbrush and brambles with which uncultivated land is usually clothed.
                    When Hannibal, riding over the ground himself, saw that this place afforded
                    sufficient cover even for cavalry, he said to his brother Mago, <quote> This
                        will be the place for you to hold. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Choose
                        out a hundred men from all the infantry and a hundred from the cavalry, and
                        come with them to my quarters at the first watch. It is time now to sup and
                        rest. </quote> With that he broke up the council. In a little while Mago
                    presented himself with his picked men. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>I see the stoutest of my men,</quote> said <pb n="p.161"/> Hannibal,
                        <quote> but that your numbers too may be strong to <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> match your bravery,
                        choose, each of you, from the squadrons and the maniples, nine others like
                        yourselves. Mago will point out to you the spot where you are to lie in
                        ambush; you have an enemy who is blind to these stratagems. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Mago and his thousand horse and thousand foot
                    being thus dispatched, Hannibal ordered the Numidian cavalry to cross the Trebia
                    at dawn, and riding up to the enemy's gates and discharging missiles against his
                    outposts, to lure him into battle; and then, when the fight was on, to give
                    ground insensibly and draw him across the river. Such were the orders of the
                    Numidians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The other officers, both of cavalry
                    and of infantry, were instructed to make their men have breakfast, and then,
                    armed and with horses saddled, to await the signal. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the flurry caused by the Numidians,
                    Sempronius, confident where cavalry was concerned, first led out all of this
                    part of his forces; then six thousand of the infantry; and finally all the rest
                    of his troops. He had fully made up his mind beforehand and was eager for the
                    battle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It chanced to be the time of year when
                    the days are shortest, and it was snowing in the region between the Alps and the
                    Apennines, and the proximity of rivers and marshes intensified the bitter cold.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Moreover, men and horses had been turned
                    out in haste, without stopping for food or doing anything to guard against
                    becoming chilled; there was no warmth in them, and the nearer they approached
                    the atmosphere of the river the sharper grew the cold wind in their faces.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But when, in pursuit of the fleeing
                    Numidians, they entered the water —swollen breast-high with the <pb n="p.163"/>
                    rain that had fallen in the night —or at any rate <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> when they got out upon the
                    further bank, then indeed their bodies were all so benumbed that they could
                    hardly hold their weapons; and at the same time they were fainting with fatigue,
                    and, as the day wore on, with hunger as well. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal's soldiers had in the meantime made
                    fires before their tents; in each company they had been served with oil to
                    supple their joints, and had breakfasted at leisure. When, therefore, they were
                    told that the enemy had crossed the river, they were eager both in mind and
                    body, as they armed and went out to battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In
                    front of the standards Hannibal placed the Baliares, light-armed troops
                    numbering about eight thousand, and behind these his heavy infantry, tile
                    strength and flower of his army; the wings he formed of ten thousand horse, and,
                    dividing the elephants, stationed them outside the wings. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The consul's troopers were scattered in pursuit of the
                    Numidians, when suddenly the latter made a stand and took them unawares;
                    whereupon he called them back and posted them on either flank of the infantry.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There were eighteen thousand Romans and
                    twenty thousand allies of the Latin name, besides the auxiliaries of the
                    Cenomani, the only Gallic tribe that continued loyal. These were the contending
                    forces. </p>
                <p> The Baliares began the battle, but those light-armed troops, finding the legions
                    too strong to cope with, were quickly withdrawn and sent to the wings.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This manœuvre at once caused the Roman
                    cavalry acute distress; for they numbered but four thousand, and, tired as they
                    were, would scarce have been able to hold out any longer against the enemy's ten
                        <pb n="p.165"/> thousand cavalry alone, who were most of them <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> fresh;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and now they were overwhelmed, as it were
                    with a cloud of missiles, by the Baliares. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Besides this, the elephants, looming large on the outer extremities of the
                    wings, gave rise to such a panic, particularly among the horses, not only by
                    their strange appearance, but also by their unfamiliar smell, as to bring about
                    a general flight. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As for the infantry, they
                    were fairly matched in courage, but not in strength, which was unimpaired in the
                    case of the Phoenicians, who had refreshed themselves shortly before entering
                    the battle, while the Romans were faint with fasting and fatigue, and were stiff
                    and numb with cold. Yet their courage would have enabled them to resist, had
                    they fought against infantry alone. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the
                    Baliares, having put the cavalry to flight, were raining missiles on their
                    flanks; the elephants had now charged the centre of the line; and Mago and his
                    Numidians, as soon as the Roman army had passed their ambuscade without
                    observing it, started up in their rear, and caused the wildest panic and
                    confusion. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, amidst all these
                    evils, the line held for a time unshaken, and even —what no one had dared to
                    hope for —against the elephants. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Skirmishers,
                    expressly posted to deal with the beasts, would throw darts at them and make
                    them turn away, and then pursuing them would strike them under the tail, where
                    the skin is softest and it is possible to wound them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In their terror they were now on the point of
                    charging their own people, when Hannibal gave orders to drive them from the
                    centre to the extreme left wing, against the Gallic auxiliaries. Here they
                    immediately caused a decided stampede, and the <pb n="p.167"/> Romans
                    experienced a fresh alarm when they saw B.C. 218 their auxiliaries routed.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And so, hemmed in as they now were on
                    every side, about ten thousand men, when they found it impossible to escape at
                    any other point, forced a passage, with great slaughter of their enemies,
                    through the Carthaginian centre, which was composed of Gallic auxiliaries, and
                    being cut off by the river <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> from returning to
                    their camp and so blinded by the rain that they could not well discern where to
                    help their comrades, took the shortest way to Placentia. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy appears to have thought of Placentia as west of
                        the Trebia, which the ten thousand were therefore not now obliged to cross,
                        though Scipio and the garrison were (§ 8). </note> After that sundry groups
                    broke out at various points. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Those who headed
                    for the river were either drowned in its eddies, or, while they hesitated to
                    enter it, were overtaken by the enemy; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but
                    those who scattered over the countryside in flight made their way by following
                    the tracks of the retreating column, to Placentia; others, venturing, in their
                    terror of the enemy, to attempt the river, got across, and reached the camp.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The mingled rain and snow and the
                    intolerable sharpness of the cold brought death to many men and beasts of burden
                    and to almost all the elephants. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At
                        chap. lviii. § 11 Livy speaks of the loss of <hi rend="italics">seven</hi>
                        of the elephants which survived the Trebia. According to </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Phoenicians pursued their enemies no
                    further than to the river Trebia, and got back to camp so benumbed and chilled
                    as hardly to feel the joy of victory. Consequently, when, in the night that
                    followed, the garrison of the camp, and such soldiers without arms <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> for the most part-as had survived the rout, were
                    crossing the Trebia on rafts, they either heard nothing, owing to the noise made
                    by the rain, or being unable, for weariness and wounds, to bestir themselves,
                    pretended not to hear; and unmolested Polybius (II. lxxiv, 11), all but <hi
                        rend="italics">one</hi> perished from the effects of the rain and snow that
                    followed the battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.169"/> by the enemy Scipio led his army in silence to B.C. 218
                    Placentia, and thence-after crossing the Po-to Cremona, so that that one town
                    might not be overburdened with furnishing winter quarters for two armies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To Rome the news of this disaster brought such
                    consternation that people looked for the immediate appearance of the hostile
                    army before their very City, and knew not which way to turn for any hope or help
                    in defending their gates and walls against its onset. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The descriptions of the terror occasioned in Rome by
                        news of the defeat and of the journey of Sempronius are not found in
                        Polybius and are very likely drawn from Coelius Antipater. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When one consul had been defeated on the
                    Ticinus, the other had been summoned back from Sicily; but now that two consuls
                    and two consular armies had been beaten, what other generals, what other legions
                    had they to call upon? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the midst of this
                    alarm the consul Sempronius arrived. He had made his way, taking tremendous
                    risks, through the enemy's cavalry —which was widely dispersed in quest of booty
                    —relying more on audacity than calculation or the prospect of eluding his
                    enemies, or of resisting, should he be unable to elude them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The election of consuls was the one crying need of the
                    hour. This Sempronius accomplished and returned forthwith to his winter
                    quarters. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The choice had fallen on Gnaeus
                    Servilius and —for the second time —on Gaius Flaminius. </p>
                <p> For the rest, the Romans were given no peace even in their winter quarters. The
                    Numidian cavalry ranged far and wide, and any ground that was too rough for them
                    was covered by the Celtiberians and Lusitani. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The result was the cutting off of all supplies from every quarter, save such as
                    were brought up the Po in ships. Their magazine, which was near Placentia, was
                    elaborately fortified <pb n="p.171"/> and strongly garrisoned. This place
                    Hannibal hoped <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        218</note> to capture by assault, and set out thither with his cavalry and
                    light infantry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He had counted mainly on the
                    concealment of his movements for their effectiveness; but his night attack
                    failed to catch the sentries off their guard, and the defenders at once set up
                    so loud an outcry that it was heard even in Placentia. And so at break of day
                    the consul was on the spot with his cavalry, having ordered the legions to
                    follow him in fighting column. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, a
                    cavalry engagement took place, in which Hannibal was wounded and withdrew from
                    the fight, and <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the enemy were so alarmed by
                    this that the post was successfully defended. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    After this Hannibal, when he had rested only a few days and his wound was scarce
                    healed over, set out to attack Victumulae. This had been a Roman magazine in the
                    Gallic war, and having then been fortified had since attracted numerous settlers
                    from the various peoples dwelling in the neighbourhood; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> and just then the fear of raids had caused large numbers to
                    flock in from the countryside. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Such was the
                    character of the population, which, fired by the story of the stout defence of
                    the fortress near Placentia, flew to arms and went out to meet Hannibal. More
                    like marching columns than embattled armies they encountered each other in the
                    road; and since on one side there was only an undisciplined rabble, and on the
                    other a general who relied upon his soldiers, and soldiers who confided in their
                    general, some thirty-five thousand men were routed by a very few. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> The next day they surrendered and received a
                    garrison within their walls. Being commanded to give up their weapons they
                    complied: whereupon a <pb n="p.173"/> signal was suddenly given to the victors
                    to sack the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        218</note> town, as if they had taken it by storm. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was any cruelty omitted which historians generally deem
                    worth noting on such an occasion; but every species of lust and outrage and
                    inhuman insolence was visited upon the wretched inhabitants. Such were
                    Hannibal's winter expeditions. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For no long time thereafter, while the cold
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 217</note> was
                    still unbearable, he allowed his men to rest, and on the first doubtful
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> signs of spring broke up his winter
                    quarters and marched towards Etruria, with the object of drawing that nation
                    also to his standards, either by force or with their own consent, as he had done
                    with the Gauls and the Ligurians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In
                    attempting to cross the Apennines he was assailed by a storm so terrible as
                    almost to surpass the horrors of the Alps. With the wind and rain blowing full
                    in their faces, at first —because they must either have dropped their arms or
                    else, if they struggled against it, be caught by the hurricane and hurled to the
                    ground —they <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> halted; then, when it actually
                    stopped their breath and would not allow them to respire, they turned their
                    backs on the gale and for a time huddled together on the ground. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> And now the heavens resounded with a frightful
                    tumult, and between the terrific crashes the lightning flashed. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Deafened and blinded, they were all stunned with fear. At
                    length the downpour ceased, but the wind only blew the more furiously, and there
                    seemed to be nothing to do but to pitch camp on the very spot where they had
                    been caught. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This, however, was but a fresh
                    beginning of their troubles, for they could neither spread nor set up a tent,
                    nor, once set up, would it stay in place, for the wind rent <pb n="p.175"/>
                    everything to shreds and swept it away; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and
                    when <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 217</note>
                    presently the moisture taken up by the wind had been congealed over the cold
                    mountain ridges, it descended in such a storm of sleet that the men let go of
                    everything and threw themselves on their faces on the ground, overwhelmed by
                    their shelters rather than protected by them; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    and the cold that ensued was so severe that when anyone sought to rise and lift
                    himself from out that pitiful heap of men and beasts, for a long time he would
                    be unable, because his sinews were so stiff and tense that he could hardly bend
                    his joints. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Afterwards, when at last by
                    exerting themselves they had recovered the power of motion and regained their
                    courage, and had begun here and there to kindle fires, each, in his
                    helplessness, applied to someone else for help. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> For two days they remained on that spot as if beleaguered. Many men and many
                    horses perished, and seven of the elephants that had survived the battle on the
                    Trebia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Descending from the Apennines, Hannibal turned
                    back once more towards Placentia, and after marching about ten miles went into
                    camp. The next day he advanced against the enemy with twelve thousand foot and
                    five thousand horse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nor did the consul
                    Sempronius, who had now returned from Rome, decline the combat. That day there
                    were only three miles between the two encampments. On the following day they
                    fought, with great spirit and with shifting fortunes. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> At the first encounter the Romans had so far the best of it
                    that not only were they victorious in the battle, but they pursued the beaten
                    enemy to his camp, and were soon attacking the camp itself. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal stationed <pb n="p.177"/> a few defenders on the
                    rampart and at the gates <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 217</note> and received the rest in a crowded throng within the
                    enclosure, where he bade them watch intently for the signal to sally forth.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was now about the ninth hour of the
                    day, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Approximately three o'clock in
                        the afternoon.</note> when the Roman general, who had worn out his men to no
                    avail and saw no prospect of capturing the camp, bade sound the recall.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When Hannibal heard this and perceived
                    that the fighting had grown lax and that the enemy had retired from his rampart,
                    he suddenly sent his cavalry against them from the right and left and rushed out
                    himself with the strength of his infantry from the centre of the camp.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Seldom has there been a fiercer battle or
                    one more notable for the losses on both sides than this would have been, had the
                    light permitted it to be prolonged; but darkness put an end to a conflict which
                    had been begun with the greatest ardour. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    fury of the combatants was consequently greater than the carnage, and as the
                    battle was practically a drawn one, so were the losses equal when the opposing
                    forces separated. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On neither side had more
                    than six hundred of the infantry fallen or half as many of the cavalry; but the
                    loss of the Romans was out of proportion to the number slain, for it included
                    several knights, five tribunes of the soldiers, and three praefects of the
                    allies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After this engagement Hannibal
                    retired into Liguria and Sempronius to Luca. The Ligurians had ambushed and made
                    prisoners of two Roman quaestors, Gaius Fulvius and Lucius Lucretius, with two
                    tribunes of the soldiers and five members of the equestrian order —mostly sons
                    of senators. These men they handed over to Hannibal on his coming among them, as
                    a <pb n="p.179"/> further earnest of their peaceful and friendly <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 217</note>
                    disposition towards him. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the
                        events recorded in this chapter Livy is thought to have drawn upon some late
                        and worthless annalist. That the Romans should have been able, so soon after
                        their discomfiture on the Trebia, to hold their own in open battle — and a
                        battle too where cavalry cut so large a figure —is improbable, to say the
                        least. Polybius says nothing of any such operations, nor of the march to
                        Luca, which contradicts Livy's own statement, at chap. lxiii. § 1, that the
                        army of Sempronius wintered at Placentia (see also chap. lxiii. § 15). The
                        whole question is discussed by De Sanctis, pp. 186 f. Cf. too the notes in
                        Weissenborn-Mueller- Rossbach. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these things were going on in Italy,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    Gnaeus Cornelius Scipio, who had been sent out to Spain with a fleet and an
                    army, had <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> set sail from the mouth of the
                    Rhone and passing the Pyrenees had put into Emporiae. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Landing his army there and beginning with the Laeetani, he
                    had brought all that coast, as far as the river Ebro, under Roman sway, partly
                    by renewing old alliances and partly by forming new ones. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The reputation which he there acquired for clemency and
                    justice availed not only with the maritime tribes, but also with the more
                    warlike clans inhabiting the interior and the mountainous parts; so that he was
                    able not only to establish peaceful relations but even to conclude a military
                    alliance with them, and several strong cohorts of auxiliaries were raised there. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> North of the Ebro Hanno was the Carthaginian
                    commander, for Hannibal had left him there to defend that region. Feeling,
                    therefore, that something ought to be done, before everything was lost to
                    Carthage, he pitched his camp in sight of the enemy and offered battle.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman general saw no reason to put off
                    the engagement; he knew that he must fight with Hanno and Hasdrubal, and chose
                    rather to deal with them separately than both at once. Neither was the battle
                    very difficult to win. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Six thousand of the
                    enemy were killed and <pb n="p.181"/> two thousand captured, together with the
                    garrison <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    of the camp —for this too was attacked and taken. The general himself and
                    several chieftains were made prisoners, and Cissis, a town which stood near the
                    camp, was carried by assault. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The plunder of
                    the town yielded objects of little worth —household belongings of barbarians and
                    slaves of no great price —but the camp made the soldiers rich; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> for in it they found not only the valuables of the army
                    that they had just defeated, but also those of the army that was now serving
                    under Hannibal in Italy, for the men had left nearly all their treasures behind
                    when they crossed the Pyrenees, so as not to burden themselves with heavy
                    baggage on the march. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal had not yet received definite
                    tidings of this disaster when he crossed the Ebro with eight thousand infantry
                    and a thousand cavalry, as though to confront the Romans at their first arrival;
                    but on learning of the catastrophe at Cissis and the loss of the camp, he turned
                    and marched in the direction of the sea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not
                    far from Tarraco <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Later (under
                        Augustus) made the capital of the Roman province of Tarraconensis. There are
                        still in existence remains of Iberian walls and of the Roman citadel,
                        circus, amphitheatre, and water-system. </note> he came upon the soldiers of
                    the fleet and the naval allies, who were dispersed and wandering over the
                    country-side, with the carelessness which usually attends success; and sending
                    out his cavalry in all directions he drove them, with much slaughter and more
                    confusion, to their ships. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But not venturing
                    to tarry longer in that region, lest Scipio should be down upon him, he
                    retreated across the Ebro. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Scipio, hearing of
                    these new enemies, did indeed march thither with all speed; but after punishing
                    a few of the ships' captains, he left a garrison of moderate size in Tarraco and
                    returned with the <pb n="p.183"/> fleet to Emporiae. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> No sooner was he gone than <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note> Hasdrubal appeared, and
                    inciting the Ilergetes, who had given Scipio hostages, to revolt, he used the
                    young men of this very tribe to lay waste the fields of the allies who were
                    faithful to the Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But this having roused
                    Scipio from his winter quarters, he retreated again and abandoned all the
                    territory north of the Ebro. Scipio invaded the country of the Ilergetes —left
                    thus in the lurch by the instigator of their revolt —with fire and sword, and
                    driving them all into the city of Atanagrus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Site unknown: perhaps not far from Ilerda (Lerida) on
                        the Sicoris. </note> the capital of that nation, laid siege to them.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Within a few days he had exacted more
                    hostages of them than before, and mulcting them also in a sum of money, had
                    received them under his authority and rule. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Thence he marched against the Ausetani, near the Ebro, who were likewise allies
                    of the Phoenicians; and besieging their city, laid an ambush for the Lacetani,
                    as they were bringing assistance to their neighbours, and fell upon them in the
                    night, not far from the city, when they would have entered it. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The slain amounted to about twelve thousand; almost all the
                    others lost their arms, and scattering over the fields in all directions, fled
                    to their homes. As for the besieged, nothing could have saved them but a winter
                    that was most unfavourable to the besiegers. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The blockade lasted thirty days, during which time the snow rarely lay less than
                    four feet deep, and so completely had it covered the mantlets and pent-houses of
                    the Romans that this alone was sufficient to protect them from the firebrands
                    that were several times discharged upon them by the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Finally, when their chief Amusicus had fled and taken
                    refuge with Hasdrubal, <pb n="p.185"/> they made terms and surrendered, agreeing
                    to pay <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 218</note>
                    twenty talents of silver. The Romans returned to Tarraco and went into winter
                    quarters. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius knows nothing of
                        the events recounted in §§ 5-11, but makes Scipio retire for the winter to
                        Emporiae and Hasdrubal to Tarraco, at the conclusion of the campaign
                        described by Livy in §§ 1-4. The source which Livy used for the latter part
                        of the chapter was perhaps a Greek writer whose account of Hasdrubal's
                        offensive was so different from that of Polybius that Livy thought that they
                        related to two distinct campaigns. It is possible that Livy's immediate
                        source in §§ 5-11 was Coelius and that the discomfiture of the Lacetani is
                        an embellishment of the story due to the latter's patriotic inventiveness.
                        See De Sanctis, pp. 184, 185. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="62" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Rome or near it many prodigies occurred
                    that winter, or —as often happens when men's thoughts are once turned upon
                    religion —many were reported and too easily credited. Some of these portents
                    were: that a free-born infant of six months had cried <quote>Triumph!</quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> in the provision market; that in the cattle
                    market an ox had climbed, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> of its own accord,
                    to the third storey of a house and then, alarmed by the outcry of the occupants,
                    had thrown itself down; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that phantom ships had
                    been seen gleaming in the sky; that the temple of Hope, in the provision market,
                    had been struck by lightning; that in Lanuvium a slain victim had stirred, and a
                    raven had flown down into Juno's temple and alighted on her very couch; that in
                    the district of Amiternum, in many places, apparitions of men in shining raiment
                    had appeared in the distance, but had not drawn near to anyone; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> that in the Picentian country there had been a shower of
                    pebbles; that at Caere the lots had shrunk; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The lots were inscribed on little wooden or bronze
                        tablets; they are also associated with Praeneste, Falerii, and Patavium.
                    </note> that in Gaul a wolf had snatched a sentry's sword from its scabbard and
                    run off with it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the other prodigies the
                    decemviri were commanded to consult the Books, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Sibylline Books were wont to be consulted (but only
                        on the express command of the senate) as to the meaning and proper expiation
                        of portents. </note> but for <pb n="p.187"/> the shower of pebbles in the
                    Picentian country a <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        218</note> nine days' sacrifice was proclaimed. They then set about the
                    expiation of the other portents, and in this virtually all the citizens bore a
                    part. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> First of all, the city was purified, and
                    major victims were offered up to the designated gods; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> a gift of gold weighing forty pounds was carried to
                    Lanuvium for Juno, and a bronze statue was dedicated to Juno, by the matrons, on
                    the Aventine; a <hi rend="italics">lectisternium</hi> was ordered at Caere,
                    where the lots had shrunk; and a supplication was ordered to be made to Fortune
                    on Mount Algidus; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> in Rome, too, a <hi
                        rend="italics">lectisternium</hi> was specially appointed for Juventas, and
                    a supplication at the temple of Hercules, and later the entire people was
                    commanded to observe this rite at all the <hi rend="italics">pulvinaria;</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A <hi rend="italics"
                            >lectisternium</hi> (for the first one in <date when="-0399">399
                            B.C.</date> see I. xiii. 6) was a banquet tendered to the gods, at which
                        their images were placed on couches ( <hi rend="italics">pulvinaria</hi> ).
                        Juventas is here associated with Hercules, as was Hebe in Greece. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> also five major victims were slain in honour
                    of the Genius of the Roman People; and Gaius Atilius Serranus the praetor was
                    ordered to make a vow, <quote>if the commonwealth should abide for ten years in
                        its present state.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The making of these vows and expiations, as
                    prescribed by the Sibylline Books, went far to alleviate men's anxiety
                    concerning their relations with the gods. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="63" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Of the consuls designate, Flaminius, to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 217</note> whom the
                    legions wintering at Placentia had been assigned by lot, dispatched an edict and
                    a letter to the consul, commanding that these troops should be ready in the camp
                    at Ariminum on the Ides of March. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was here,
                    in his province, that he designed to enter on the consulship, for he remembered
                    his former controversies with the senators, which he had waged when a tribune of
                    the plebs, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the year <date
                            when="-0232">232 B.C.</date> he had carried a law in the Comitia Tributa
                        providing that certain Picentine and Gallic lands should be divided among
                        the poorer citizens. </note> and later as consul —in the first place about
                    his <pb n="p.189"/> consulship, which they tried to annul, and again <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 217</note> concerning
                    his triumph. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In <date when="-0223"
                            >223 B.C.</date> the senate commanded the consuls Furius and Flaminius,
                        who had marched against the Insubrian Gauls, to return to Rome and resign
                        their magistracies on the ground that unfavourable auguries had been
                        reported. But Flaminius refused to return, fought and won a battle, and
                        triumphed in the face of senatorial opposition <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> —by virtue of a decree of the people. </note> He was
                    also hated by the senators on account of an unprecedented law which Quintus
                    Claudius the tribune of the plebs had introduced, despite the opposition of the
                    senate, with the backing of Gaius Flaminius alone of all that body, providing
                    that no senator or senator's son should own a sea-going ship of more than three
                    hundred amphoras burden <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The amphora
                        —a wine-jar with two handles —was standardized as a liquid measure roughly
                        equal to six gallons. In our terminology such a vessel would be described as
                        of about seven tons burden. </note> —this was reckoned to be sufficient to
                    transport the crops from one's fields, and all money-making was held unseemly
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> in a senator. The measure, which was
                    vehemently opposed, had been productive of great resentment on the part of the
                    nobles against Flaminius, who had advocated its enactment; but had procured for
                    him the favour of the plebs and afterwards <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> a
                    second consulship. Believing, therefore, that his enemies would falsify the
                    auspices and make use of the Latin Festival <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The new consuls were required to fix the date of the
                        Feriae Latinae, at the first session of the senate after their entering upon
                        office, and they might not take the field for the summer's campaign before
                        they had duly presided over the sacrifice to Jupiter Latiaris, which was the
                        essential feature of the celebration. </note> and other means of hindering a
                    consul, to detain him in the City, he pretended that he had to take a journey,
                    and departing, as a private citizen, slipped away secretly <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> to his province. This behaviour, when the truth came out,
                    aroused fresh indignation in the breasts of the already hostile senators: Gaius
                    Flaminius, they said, was waging war not only with the senate, but this time
                    with <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the immortal gods. He had formerly been
                    made consul without the confirmation of the auspices, and, though both gods and
                    men had sought to recall him from the very battle-line, he <pb n="p.191"/> had
                    not obeyed; now, conscious of having spurned <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 217</note> them, he had fled the
                    Capitol and the vows that were regularly undertaken, that he might not, on the
                    day of entering upon his office, approach the temple of <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Jupiter Optimus Maximus; that he might not see and consult
                    the senate, which hated him and which he alone of all men hated; that he might
                    not proclaim the Latin Festival and offer the accustomed sacrifice to Jupiter
                    Latiaris on <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the Alban Mount; that he might
                    not, after receiving auspices, go up to the Capitol to make his vows, and thence
                    proceed, in the general's cloak <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                            <hi rend="italics">paludamentum,</hi> typifying military imperium, might
                        be assumed by the consul on leaving the City, the <hi rend="italics"
                            >toga</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">praetexta,</hi> white with a purple border, was worn by
                        the consul while in Rome. </note> and accompanied by lictors, to his
                    province; like some camp-follower, without insignia and without lictors, he had
                    set out in secret and by stealth, precisely as though <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> going into exile; he thought, forsooth, that it was more in
                    keeping with the dignity of his high command to begin his magistracy in Ariminum
                    than in Rome —to assume the purple-bordered toga <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">paludamentum,</hi> typifying
                        military imperium, might be assumed by the consul on leaving the City, the
                            <hi rend="italics">toga</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">praetexta,</hi> white with a purple border, was worn by
                        the consul while in Rome. </note> in an inn than in the presence of
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> his household gods! With one accord they
                    voted to recall him and drag him back and compel him to discharge in person all
                    his obligations to gods and men, before he went to his army <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and his province. On this commission —for commissioners
                    they resolved to dispatch —Quintus Terentius and Marcus Antistius set forth, but
                    moved Flaminius no more than the letter sent him by the senate had moved him in
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> his former consulship. A few days later
                    he entered on his magistracy, and as he was offering up a calf, it escaped
                    —after being struck —out of the hands of those who would have sacrificed it, and
                    spattered many of the bystanders <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> with its
                    blood. The dismay and confusion <pb n="p.193"/> were even greater among those
                    who stood farther B..217 off and knew not what was occasioning the panic. By
                    most people it was regarded as an omen <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> of
                    great terror. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This dreadful omen is
                        not mentioned by Polybius and looks like an invention of the aristocratic
                        opponents of Flaminius. Livy perhaps found the story in Coelius. </note>
                    After this the army comprising the two legions received from Sempronius, the
                    consul of the year before, and the two taken over from Gaius Atilius the
                    praetor, began its march into Etruria through the passes of the Apennines. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
