<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Rape of Proserpine</title>
        <author>Claudian</author>
        <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Bridget Almas</name>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>Claudian, with an English translation, in Two Volumes, Vol. II</title>
            <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
            <editor role="editor">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
              <date type="printing">1922</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
          </monogr>
          <ref target="https://archive.org/details/claudian02clau#page/292/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
      <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
        <state unit="book" delim="."/>
        <state unit="poem"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language id="la">Latin</language>
	<language id="greek">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text id="stoa0089.stoa005.perseus-eng1"><body>
<pb id="v.2.p.293"/>
    <div1 type="book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
      <div2 type="poem" id="poem.32" n="praef" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<head>PREFACE</head><p>

He who first made a ship and clave therewith
the deep, troubling the waters with roughly hewn
oars, who first dared trust his alder-bark to the
uncertain winds and who by his skill devised a
way forbidden of nature, fearfully at the first essayed
smooth seas, hugging the shore in an unadventurous
course. But soon he began to attempt the crossing
of broad bays, to leave the land and spread his
canvas to the gentle south wind ; and, as little
by little his growing courage led him on, and as
his heart forgot numbing fear, sailing now at large,
he burst upon the open sea and, with the signs of
heaven to guide him, passed triumphant through
the storms of the Aegean and the Ionian main.

</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="poem" n="2" id="poem.33"><p>

My full heart bids me boldly sing the horses
of the ravisher from the underworld and the stars
darkened by the shadow of his infernal chariot
<pb id="v.2.p.295"/>
and the gloomy chambers of the queen of Hell.
Come not nigh, ye uninitiate. Now has divine
madness driven all mortal thoughts from my breast,
and my heart is filled with Phoebus' inspiration ;
now see I the shrine reel and its foundations totter
while the threshold glows with radiant light telling
that the god is at hand. And now I hear a loud
din from the depths of the earth, the temple of
Cecrops re-echoes and Eleusis waves its holy torches.
The hissing snakes of Triptolemus raise their scaly
necks chafed by the curving collar, and, uptowering
as they glide smoothly along, stretch forth their
rosy crests towards the chant. See from afar rises
Hecate with her three various heads and with her
comes forth Iacchus smooth of skin, his temples
crowned with ivy. There clothes him the pelt of
a Parthian tiger, its gilded claws knotted together,
and the Lydian thyrsus guides his drunken footsteps.
Ye gods, whom the numberless host of the dead
serves in ghostly Avernus, into whose greedy
treasury is paid all that perishes upon earth, ye
whose fields the pale streams of intertwining Styx
surround, while Phlegethon, his rapids tossed in
spray, flows through them with steaming eddies—do
you unfold for me the mysteries of your sacred
story and the secrets of your world. Say with
what torch the god of love overcame Dis, and tell
how Proserpine was stolen away in her maiden
pride to win Chaos as a dower ; and how through
many lands Ceres, sore troubled, pursued her
anxious search ; whence corn was given to man
whereby he laid aside his acorn food, and the newfound
ear made useless Dodona's oaks.
Once on a time the lord of Erebus blazed forth
<pb id="v.2.p.297"/>
in swelling anger, threatening war upon the gods,
because he alone was unwed and had long wasted
the years in childless state, brooking no longer to
lack the joys of wedlock and a husband's happiness
nor ever to know the dear name of father. Now
all the monsters that lurk in Hell's abyss rush
together in warlike bands, and the Furies bind themselves
with an oath against the Thunderer. Tisi-phone,
the bloody snakes clustering on her head,
shakes the lurid pine-torch and summons to the
ghostly camp the armed shades. Almost had the
elements, once more at war with reluctant nature,
broken their bond ; the Titan brood, their deep
prison-house thrown open and their fetters cast
off, had again seen heaven's light ; and once more
bloody Aegaeon, bursting the knotted ropes that
bound his huge form, had warred against the
thunderbolts of Jove with hundred-handed blows
But the dread Fates brought these threats to
naught, and, fearing for the world, gravely laid
their hoary locks before the feet and throne of
the lord of Hell, and with suppliant tears touched
his knees with their hands — those hands beneath
whose rule are all things set, whose thumbs twist
the thread of fate and spin the long ages with their
iron spindles. First Lachesis, her hair unkempt and
disordered, thus called out upon the cruel king :
<q> Great lord of night, ruler over the shades, thou
at whose command our threads are spun, who
appointest the end and origin of all things and
ordainest the alternation of birth and destruction ;
arbiter thou of life and death — for whatsoever thing
comes anywhere into being it is by thy gift that it
is created and owes its life to thee, and after a fixed
<pb id="v.2.p.299"/>
cycle of years thou sendest souls once more into
mortal bodies — seek not to break the stablished
treaty of peace which our distaffs have spun and
given thee, and overturn not in civil war the compact
fixed 'twixt thee and thy two brothers. Why
raisest thou unrighteous standards of war ? Why
freest the foul band of Titans to the open air ? Ask
of Jove ; he will give thee a wife.</q>
Scarce had she spoken when Pluto stopped, shamed
by her prayer, and his grim spirit grew mild though
little wont to be curbed : even so great Boreas,
armed with strident blasts and tempestuous with
congealed snow, his wings all frozen with Getic hail
as he seeks battle, threatens to overwhelm the
sea, the woods, and the fields with sounding storm ;
but should Aeolus chance to bar against him the
brazen doors idly his fury dies away and his storms
retire baulked to their prison-house.
Then he bids summon Mercury, the son of Maia,
that he may carry these flaming words to Jove.
Straightway the winged god of Cyllene stands at
his side shaking his sleepy wand, his herald cap
upon his head. Pluto himself sits propped on his
rugged throne, awful in funereal majesty ; foul with
age-long dust is his mighty sceptre ; boding clouds
make grim his lofty head ; unpitying is the stiffness
of his dread shape ; rage heightened the terror of
his aspect. Then with uplifted head he thunders
forth these words, while, as the tyrant speaks, his
halls tremble and are still ; the massy hound,
guardian of the gate, restrains the barking of his
triple head, and Cocytus sinks back repressing his
fount of tears ; Acheron is dumb with silent wave,
and the banks of Phlegethon cease their murmuring.
<pb id="v.2.p.301"/>
<q> Grandchild of Atlas, Arcadian-born, deity that
sharest hell and heaven, thou who alone hast the
right to cross either threshold, and art the intermediary
between the two worlds, go swiftly, cleave
the winds, and bear these my behests to proud Jove.
' Hast thou, cruel brother, such complete authority
over me ? Did injurious fortune rob me at once
of power and light ? Because day was reft from me,
lost I therefore strength and weapons ? Thinkest
thou me humble and cowed because I hurl not
bolts forged by the Cyclops and fool not the empty
air with thunder ? Is it not enough that deprived
of the pleasant light of day I submit to the ill-fortune
of the third and final choice and these hideous
realms, whilst thee the starry heavens adorn and
the Wain surrounds with twinkling brilliance — must
thou also forbid our marriage ? Amphitrite,
daughter of Nereus, holds Neptune in her sea-grey
embrace ; Juno, thy sister and thy wife, takes thee
to her bosom when wearied thou layest aside thy
thunderbolts. What need to tell of thy secret love
for Lato or Ceres or great Themis ? How manifold
a hope of offspring was thine ! Now a crowd of
happy children surrounds thee. And shall I in
this empty palace, sans joy, sans fame, know no
child's love to still instant care ? I will not
brook so dull a life. I swear by elemental night
and the unexplored shallows of the Stygian lake,
if thou refuse to hearken to my word I will
throw open Hell and call forth her monsters, will
break Saturn's old chains, and shroud the sun in
darkness. The framework of the world shall be
loosened and the shining heavens mingle with
Avernus' shades.'</q>
<pb id="v.2.p.303"/>
Scarce had he spoken when his messenger trod
the stars. The Father heard the message and,
communing with himself, debated long who would
dare such a marriage, who would wish to exchange
the sun for the caves of Styx. He would fain decide
and at length his fixed purpose grew.
Ceres, whose temple is at Henna, had but one
youthful daughter, a child long prayed for ; for the
goddess of birth granted no second offspring, and
her womb, exhausted by that first labour, became
unfruitful. Yet prouder is the mother above all
mothers, and Proserpine such as to take the place
of many. Her mother's care and darling is she ;
not more lovingly does the fierce mother cow tend
her calf that cannot as yet scamper over the fields
and whose growing horns curve not yet moonwise
over her forehead. As the years were fulfilled she
had grown a maiden ripe for marriage, and thoughts
of the torch of wedlock stir her girlish modesty, but
while she longs for a husband she yet fears to plight
troth. The voice of suitors is heard throughout the
palace ; two gods woo the maiden. Mars, more skilled
with the shield, and Phoebus, the mightier bowman.
Mars offers Rhodope, Phoebus would give Amyclae,
and Delos and his temple at Claros ; in rivalry
Juno and Latona claim her for a son's wife. But
golden-haired Ceres disdains both, and fearing lest
her daughter should be stolen away (how blind to
the future !) secretly entrusts her jewel to the land
of Sicily, confident in the safe nature of this hiding-place.
Trinacria was once a part of Italy but sea and tide
changed the face of the land. Victorious Nereus
brake his bounds and interflowed the cleft mountains
<pb id="v.2.p.305"/>
with his waves whereby a narrow channel now
separates these kindred lands. Nature now thrusts
out into the sea the three-cornered island, cut off
from the mainland to which it once belonged. At
one extremity the promontory of Pachynum hurls
back with jutting crags the furious waves of the
Ionian main, round another roars the African sea
that rises and beats upon the curving harbour of
Lilybaeum, at the third the raging Tyrrhenian
flood, impatient of restraint, shakes the obstacle
of Cape Pelorus. In the midst of the island rise
the charred cliffs of Aetna, eloquent monument
of Jove's victory over the Giants, the tomb of
Enceladus, whose bound and bruised body breathes
forth endless sulphur clouds from its burning wounds.
Whene'er his rebellious shoulders shift their burden
to the right or left, the island is shaken from its
foundations and the walls of tottering cities sway
this way and that.
The peaks of Aetna thou must know by sight
alone ; to them no foot may approach. The rest
is clothed with foliage but the summit no husbandman
tills. Now it sends forth native smoke and
with pitch-black cloud darkens and oppresses the
day, now with awful stirrings it threatens the stars
and feeds its flame with the dread fruit of its own
body. But though it boils and bursts forth with
such great heat yet it knows how to observe a
truce with the snow, and together with glowing
ashes the ice grows hard, protected from the great
heat and secured by indwelling cold, so that the
harmless flame licks the neighbouring frost with
breath that keeps its compact. What huge engine
hurls those rocks ; what vast force piles rock on
<pb id="v.2.p.307"/>
rock ? Whence flows forth that fiery stream ?
Whether it be that the wind, forcing its way past
hidden barriers, rages amid the fissured rocks that
seek to bar its passage and, seeking a way of escape,
sweeps the crumbling caverns with its wandering
blasts in its bid for freedom, or that the sea, flowing
in through the bowels of the sulphurous mountain,
bursts into flame when its waters are compressed
and casts up great rocks, I know not.
When the loving mother had entrusted her charge
to the secret keeping of Henna she went freed from
care to visit tower-crowned Cybele in her Phrygian
home, driving a car drawn by twining serpents
which cleave the pervious clouds on their winged
course and fleck the bit with harmless poison.
Their heads are crested and spots of green mottle
their backs while sparkling gold glints amid their
scales. Now they swim circling through the air,
now they skim the fields with low-driven course.
The passing wheels sow the plough-land with golden
grain and their track grows yellow with corn.
Sprouting stalks cover their traces and attendant
crops clothe the path of the goddess.
Now is left behind Aetna, and all Sicily sinks lessening
into the distance. Ah, how often, foreknowing of
coming ill, did she mar her cheek with welling
tears ; how often look back upon her home with
words Uke these : <q> Be happy, dear land, dearer
than heaven to me, into thy safe keeping I commend
my daughter, my sole joy, loved fruit of my labour.
No despicable reward shall be thine, for thou shalt
suffer no hoe nor shall the cruel iron of the ploughshare
know thy soil. Untilled thy fields shall bear
fruit, and though thine oxen plough not, a richer
<pb id="v.2.p.309"/>
husbandman shall view with wonder the self-sown
harvest.</q> So spake she and reached Mount Ida,
drawn by her yellow serpents.
Here is the queenly seat of the goddess and in
her holy temple the sacred statue, o'ershadowed by
the thick leaves of the pine wood which, though no
storm wind shakes the grove, gives forth creakings
with its cone-bearing branches. Within are the
dread bands of the initiate with whose wild chantings
the shrine rings ; Ida is loud with howlings and
Gargarus bends his woods in fear. As soon as Ceres
appears the drums restrain their rattle ; the choirs
are silent and the Corybantes stay the flourish of
their knives. Pipes and cymbals are still, and the
hons sink their manes in greeting. Cybele 1 rejoicing
runs forth from the shrine and bends her towered
head to kiss her guest.
Long had Jove seen this, watching from his lofty
seat, and to Venus he thus enfolded the secrets of
his heart : <q> Goddess of Cythera, I will impart to
thee my hidden troubles ; long ago I decided that
fair Proserpine should be given in marriage to the
lord of Hell ; such is Atropos' bidding, such old
Themis' prophecy. Now that her mother has left
her is the time for action. Do thou visit the confines
of Sicily, and armed with thy wiles, lead Ceres'
daughter to sport in the level meads what time
to-morrow's light has unfolded the rosy dawn ;
employ those arts with which thou art wont to
inflame all things, often even myself. Why should
the nether kingdoms know not love ? Let no
land be free and no breast even amid the shades
unfired by Venus. At last let the gloomy Fury
<pb id="v.2.p.311"/>
feel the sting of passion and Acheron and the steely
heart of stern Dis grow tender with love's arrows.</q>
Venus hastes to do his bidding ; and at their sire's
behest there join her Pallas and Diana whose bent
bow affrights all Maenalus' slopes. Neath her
divine feet the path shone bright, even as a comet,
fraught with augury of ill, falls headlong, a glowing
portent of blood-red fire ; no sailor may look on it
and live, no people view it but to their destruction ;
the message of its threatening tail is storm to ships
and an enemy's attack to cities. They reached the
place where shone Ceres' palace, firm-built by the
Cyclopes' hands ; up tower the iron walls, iron stand
the gates, and steel bars secure the massy doors.
Neither Pyragmon nor Steropes e'er builded a
work with toil so great as that, nor ever did bellows
breathe forth such blasts nor the molten mass of
metal flow in a stream so deep that the very furnaces
were weary of heating it. The hall was walled with
ivory ; the roof strengthened with beams of bronze
and supported by lofty columns of electron.
Proserpine herself, soothing the house with sweet
song, was sewing all in vain a gift against her mother's
return. In this cloth she embroidered with her
needle the concourse of atoms and the dwelling of
the Father of the gods and pictured how mother
Nature ordered elemental chaos, and how the
first principles of things sprang apart, each to
his proper place — those that were light being born
aloft, the heavier ones falling to a centre. The air
grew bright and fire chose the pole as its seat.
Here flowed the sea ; there hung the earth suspended.
Many were the colours she employed,
tricking the stars with gold and flooding the sea
<pb id="v.2.p.313"/>
with purple. The shore she embossed with precious
stones and cunningly employed raised threadwork
to imitate the swelling billows. You might have
thought you saw the seaweed dashed against the
rocks and heard the murmur of the hissing waves
flooding up the thirsty sands. Five zones she added ;
indicating that the centre was the torrid zone by
embroidering it with red yarn : its desert confines
are parched and the thread she used was dried by
the sun's unfailing heat. On either side lay the two
habitable zones, blessed with a mild climate fit for
the life of man. At the top and bottom she set the
two frozen zones, portraying eternal winter's horror
in her weaving and the gloom of never-ceasing cold.
Further she embroidered the accursed seat of her
uncle, Dis, and the nether gods, her destined
fellows. Nor did the omen pass unmarked, for
prophetic of the future her cheeks grew wet with
sudden tears.
Next she began to trace Ocean's glassy shallows
at the tapestry's farthest edge, but at that moment
the doors opened, she saw the goddesses enter, and
left her work unfinished. A glowing blush that
mantled to her clear cheeks suffused her fair countenance
and lit the torches of stainless purity.
Not so beautiful even the glow of ivory which a
Lydian maid has stained with Sidon's scarlet dye.
Now the sun was dipped in Ocean, and misty night
scattering sleep had brought for mortals ease and
leisure in her black two-horsed chariot ; when Pluto,
warned by his brother, made his way to the upper
air. The dread fury Allecto yokes to the chariotpole
the two fierce pairs of steeds that graze Cocytus'
banks and roam the dark meads of Erebus, and,
<pb id="v.2.p.315"/>
drinking the rotting pools of sluggish Lethe, let
dark oblivion drip from their slumbrous lips — Orphnaeus,
savage and fleet, Aethon, swifter than
an arrow, great Nycteus, proud glory of Hell's
steeds, and Alastor, branded with the mark of Dis.
These stood harnessed before the door and savagely
champed the bit all eager for the morrow's enjoyment
of their destined booty.

</p>
    </div2></div1>
    <div1 type="book" n="2" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
      <div2 type="poem" n="praef" id="poem.34" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<head>PREFACE</head><p>

When Orpheus sought repose and, lulling his song
to sleep, had long laid aside his neglected task,
the Nymphs complained that their joy had been
reft from them and the sad rivers mourned the
loss of his tuneful lays. Nature's savagery returned
and the heifer in terror of the lion looked
in vain for help from the now voiceless lyre. The
rugged mountains lamented his silence and the woods
that had so often followed his Thracian lute.
But after that Hercules, setting forth from
Inachian Argos, reached the plains of Thrace on
his mission of salvation, and destroying the stables
of Diomede, fed the horses of the bloody tyrant on
grass, then it was that the poet, o'erjoyed at his
country's happy fate, took up once more the tuneful
strings of his lute long laid aside, and touching its
<pb id="v.2.p.317"/>
idle chords with the smooth quill, plied the famed
ivory with festal fingers. Scarce had they heard
him when the winds and waves were stilled ; Hebrus
flowed more sluggishly with reluctant stream,
Rhodope stretched out her rocks all eager for the
song, and Ossa, his summit less exalted, shook off
his coat of snow. The tall poplar and the pine,
accompanied by the oak, left the slopes of treeless
Haemus, and even the laurel came, allured by the
voice of Orpheus, though erstwhile it had despised
Apollo's art. Molossian dogs fawned playfully on
fearless hares, and the lamb made room for the wolf
by her side. Does sported in amity with the striped
tiger and hinds had no fear of the lion's mane.
He sang the stings of a step-dame's ire 1 and the
deeds of Hercules, the monsters overcome by his
strong right arm ; how while yet a child he had
shown the strangled snakes to his terrified mother,
and had laughed, fearlessly scorning such dangers.
<q> Thee nor the bull that shook with his bellowing
the cities of Crete alarmed, nor the savagery of
the hound of Hell ; thee not the lion, soon to become
a constellation in the heavens, nor the wild boar
that brought renown to Erymanthus height. Thou
hast stripped the Amazons of their girdles, shot with
thy bow the birds of Stymphalus, and driven home
the cattle of the western clime. Thou hast o'erthrown
the many limbs of the triple-headed monster
and returned thrice victorious from a single foe.
Vain the falls of Antaeus, vain the sprouting of the
Hydra's new heads. Its winged feet availed not
to save Diana's deer from thy hand. Cacus' flames
were quenched and Nile ran rich with Busiris' blood.
Pholoë's slopes reeked with the slaughter of the
<pb id="v.2.p.319"/>
cloud-born Centaurs. Thee the curving shore of
Libya held in awe ; thee the mighty Ocean gazed
at in amaze when thou laidst the world's bulk on
thy back ; on the neck of Hercules the heaven was
poised more surely ; the sun and stars coursed over
thy shoulders.</q>
So sang the Thracian bard. But thou, Florentinus, 1
art a second Hercules to me. 'Tis thou causest my
quill to stir, 'tis thou disturbest the Muses' cavern
long plunged in sleep and leadest their gentle bands
in the dance.

</p></div2>
      <div2 type="poem" id="poem.35" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N" n="1">
<p>

Not yet had bright day with herald beams struck
the waves of the Ionian main ; the light of dawn
shimmered on the waters and the straying brilliance
flickered over the deep blue sea. And now bold
Proserpine, forgetful of her mother's jealous care
and tempted by the wiles of Venus, seeks the streamfed
vale. Such was the Fates' decree. Thrice did
the doors sound a warning note as the hinges turned ;
thrice did prophetic Aetna rumble mournfully with
awful thunders. But her can no portent, no omen
detain. The sister goddesses bore her company.
First goes Venus exulting in her trickery and
inspired by her great mission. In her heart she
takes account of the coming rape ; soon she will
rule dread Chaos, soon, Dis once subdued, she will
lead the subject ghosts. Her hair, parted into many
<pb id="v.2.p.321"/>
locks, is braided round her head and secured by a
Cyprian pin, and a brooch cunningly fabricated by
her spouse Vulcan supports her cloak thick studded
with purple jewels.
Behind her hasten Diana, fair queen of Arcadian
Lycaeus, and Pallas who, with her spear, protects
the citadel of Athens — virgins both ; Pallas, cruel
goddess of war, Diana bane of wild creatures. On
her burnished helmet the Triton-born goddess wore
a carved figure of Typhon, the upper part of his
body lifeless, the lower limbs yet writhing, part
dead, part quick. Her terrible spear, piercing the
clouds as she brandished it, resembled a tree ; only
the Gorgon's hissing neck she hid in the spread of
her glittering cloak. But mild was Diana's gaze
and very like her brother looked she ; Phoebus'
own one had thought her cheeks and eyes, her sex
alone disclosed the difference. Her shining arms
were bare, her straying locks fluttered in the gentle
breeze, and the chord of her unstrung bow hung idle,
her arrows slung behind her back. Her Cretan tunic,
gathered with girdles twain, flows down to her knees,
and on her waving dress Delos wanders and stretches
surrounded by a golden sea.
Between the two Ceres' child, now her mother's
pride, so soon to be her sorrow, treads the grass with
equal pace, their equal, too, in stature and beauty ;
Pallas you might have thought her, had she carried
a shield, Diana, if a javelin. A brooch of polished
jasper secured her girded dress. Never did art
give happier issue to the shuttle's skill ; never was
cloth so beautifully made nor embroidery so lifelike.
In it she had worked the birth of the sun
from the seed of Hyperion, the birth, too, of the moon,
<pb id="v.2.p.323"/>
though diverse was her shape — of sun and moon that
bring the dawning and the night. Tethys affords
them a cradle and soothes in her bosom their infant
sobs ; the rosy light of her foster-children irradiates
her dark blue plains. On her right shoulder she
carried the infant Titan, too young as yet to vex with
his light, and his encircling beams not grown ; he
is pictured as more gentle in those tender years, and
from his mouth issues a soft flame that accompanies
his infant cries. The moon, his sister, carried on
Tethys' left shoulder, sucks the milk of that bright
breast, her forehead marked with a little horn.
Such is the wonder of Proserpine's dress. The
Naiads bear her company and on either side crowd
around her, those who haunt thy streams, Crinisus,
and Pantagia's rocky torrent and Gela's who gives
his name to the city ; those whom Camerina, the
unmoved, nurtures in her shallow marshes, whose
home is Arethusa's flood or the stream of Alpheus,
her foreign lover ; tallest of their company is Cyane.
So move they as the beauteous band of Amazons,
brandishing their moon-shaped shields what time the
maiden warrior Hippolyte, after laying waste the
regions of the north, leads home her fair army after
battle, whether they have o'erthrown the yellow-haired
Getae or cloven frozen Tanais with the axe
of their native Thermodon ; or as the Lydian Nymphs
celebrate the festivals of Bacchus — the Nymphs
whose sire was Hermus along whose banks they
course, splashed with his golden waters : the river-god
rejoices in his cavern home and pours forth the
flooding urn with generous hand.
Henna, mother of blossoms, had espied the goddess'
company from her grassy summit and thus addressed
<pb id="v.2.p.325"/>
Zephyrus, lurking in the winding vale : <q>Gracious
father of the spring, thou who ever rulest over my
meads with errant breeze and bringest rain upon the
summer lands with thine unceasing breath, behold
this company of Nymphs and Jove's tall daughters
who deign to sport them in my meadows. Be present
to bless, I pray. Grant that now all the trees be
thick with newly -grown fruit, that fertile Hybla
may be jealous and admit her paradise surpassed.
All the sweet airs of Panchaea's incense - bearing
woods, all the honied odours of Hydaspes' distant
stream, all the spices which from furthest fields the
long-lived Phoenix gathers, seeking new birth from
wished for death — spread thou all these through my
veins and with generous breath refresh my country.
May I be worthy to be plundered by divine fingers
and goddesses seek to be decked with my garlands.</q>
So spake she, and Zephyrus shook his wings adrip
with fresh nectar and drenches the ground with their
life-giving dew. Wheresoe'er he flies spring's brilliance
follows. The fields grow lush with verdure and
heaven's dome shines cloudless above them. He
paints the bright roses red, the hyacinths blue and the
sweet violets purple. What girdles of Babylon, meet
cincture of a royal breast, are adorned with such
varied jewels ? What fleece so dyed in the rich
juice of the murex where stand the brazen towers of
Tyre ? Not the wings of Juno's own bird display such
colouring. Not thus do the many-changing hues of the
rainbow span young winter's sky when in curved arch
its rainy path glows green amid the parting clouds.
Even more lovely than the flowers is the country.
The plain, with gentle swell and gradual slopes, rose
into a hill ; issuing from the living rock gushing
<pb id="v.2.p.327"/>
streams bedewed their grassy banks. With the
shade of its branches a wood tempers the sun's fierce
heat and at summer's height makes for itself the cold
of winter. There grows the pine, useful for seafaring,
the cornel-tree for weapons of war, the oak, friendly
to Jove, the cypress, sentinel of graves, the holm
filled with honeycombs, and the laurel foreknowing
of the future ; here the box-tree waves its thick
crown of leaves, here creeps the ivy, here the vine
clothes the elm. Not far from here lies a lake called
by the Sicani Pergus, girt with a cincture of leafy
woods close around its pallid waters. Deep down
therein the eye of whoso would can see, and the
everywhere transparent water invites an untrammelled
gaze into its oozy depths and betrays the
uttermost secrets of its pellucid gulfs. [Hither came
their company well pleased with the flowery climb.]
Venus bids them gather flowers. <q> Come, sisters,
while yet the morning sun shines through the moist
air, and while Lucifer, my harbinger of dawn, yet
drives his dewy steeds and waters the flower-bright
field.</q> So spake she and gathered the flower that
testifies to her own woe. 1 Her companions ranged
the various vales. You could have believed a swarm
of bees was on the wing, eager to gather its sweetness
from Hyblaean thyme, where the king bees lead out
their wax-housed armies and the honey-bearing host,
issuing from the beech-tree's hollow bole, buzzes
around its favourite flowers. The meadows are
despoiled of their glory ; this goddess weaves lilies
with dark violets, another decks herself with pliant
marjoram, a third steps forth rose-crowned, another
wreathed with white privet. Thee also, Hyacinthus,
<pb id="v.2.p.329"/>
they gather, thy flower inscribed with woe, and Narcissus
too — once lovely boys, now the pride of flowering
spring. Thou, Hyacinthus, wert born at Amyclae,
Narcissus was Helicon's child ; thee the errant discus
slew ; him love of his stream-reflected face beguiled ;
for thee weeps Delos' god with sorrow-weighted
brow ; for him Cephisus with his broken reeds.
But beyond her fellows she, the one hope of the
corn-bearing goddess, burned with a fierce desire to
gather flowers. Now she fills with the spoil of the
fields her laughing baskets, osier-woven ; now she
twines a wreath of flowers and crowns herself therewith,
little seeing in this a foreshadowing of the
marriage fate holds in store for her. E'en Pallas
herself, goddess of the trumpets and of the weapons of
war, devotes to gentler pursuits the hand wherewith
she o'erwhelms the host of battle and throws down
stout gates and city walls. She lays aside her spear
and wreaths her helmet with soft flowers — strange
aureole ! The iron peak is gay, o'ershadowed the
fierce martial glint, and the plumes, erstwhile levin
bolts, now nod with blossoms. Nor does Diana,
who scours Mount Parthenius with her keen-scented
hounds, disdain this company but would fain bind
her free-flowing tresses with a flowery crown.
But while the maidens so disport themselves, wandering
through the fields, a sudden roar is heard,
towers crash and towns, shaken to their foundations,
totter and fall. None knows whence comes the
tumult ; Paphus' goddess alone recognized the sound
that set her companions in amaze, and fear mixed
with joy fills her heart. For now the king of souls
was pricking his way through the dim labyrinth of
the underworld and crushing Enceladus, groaning
<pb id="v.2.p.331"/>

beneath the weight of his massy steeds. His chariot-wheels
severed the monstrous limbs, and the giant
struggles, bearing Sicily along with Pluto on his
burdened neck, and feebly essays to move and
entangle the wheels with his weary serpents ; still
o'er his blazing back passes the smoking chariot.
And as sappers seek to issue forth upon their unsuspecting
enemy and, following a mined path
beneath the foundations of the tunnelled field, pass
unmarked beyond the foe-invested walls of the city to
break out, a victorious party, into the citadel of the
outwitted enemy, seeming sprung from earth, even so
Saturn's third son scours the devious darkness whither-soever
his team hurries him, all eager to come forth
beneath his brother's sky. No door lies open for
him ; rocks bar his egress on every side and detain
the god in their escapeless prison. He brooked not
the delay but wrathfully smote the crags with his
beam-like staff. Sicily's caverns thundered, Lipare's
isle was confounded, Vulcan left his forge in amaze
and the Cyclops let drop their thunderbolts in fear.
The pent-up denizens of the frozen Alps heard the
uproar and he who then swam thy wave, father Tiber,
thy brows not as yet graced with the crown of Italy's
triumphs ; there heard it he who rows his bark
down Padus' stream.
So when the rock-encircled lake, ere Peneus' wave
rolled seaward, covered all Thessaly and allowed not
its submerged fields to be tilled, Neptune smote the
imprisoning mountain with his trident. Then did
the peak of Ossa, riven with the mighty blow, spring
apart from snowy Olympus ; a passage was made and
the waters were released, whereby the sea won back
her feeding streams and the husbandman his fields.
<pb id="v.2.p.333"/>
When Trinacria beneath Pluto's stroke loosed her
rocky bonds and yawned wide with cavernous cleft,
sudden fear seized upon the sky. The stars deserted
their accustomed courses ; the Bear bathed him in
forbidden Ocean ; terror hurried sluggish Boötes to
his setting ; Orion trembled. Atlas paled as he
heard the neighing coursers ; their smoky breath
obscures the bright heavens and the sun's orb
affrighted them, so long fed on darkness. They stood
biting the curb astonied at the brighter air, and
struggle to turn the chariot and hurry back to dread
Chaos. But soon, when they felt the lash on their
backs and learned to bear the sun's brightness, they
gallop on more rapidly than a winter torrent and
more fleet than the hurtling spear ; swifter than the
Parthian 's dart, the south wind's fury or nimble
thought of anxious mind. Their bits are warm with
blood, their death-bringing breath infects the air,
the polluted dust is poisoned with their foam.
The Nymphs fly in all directions ; Proserpine is
hurried away in the chariot, imploring aid of the
goddesses. Now Pallas unveils the Gorgon's head,
Diana strings her bow and hastes to help. Neither
yields to her uncle's violence ; a common virginity
compels them to fight and enrages them at the crime
of the fierce ravisher. Pluto is like a lion when he
has seized upon a heifer, the pride of the stall and
the herd, and has torn with his claws the defenceless
flesh and has sated his fury on all its limbs, and so
stands all befouled with clotted blood and shakes his
tangled mane and scorns the shepherds' feeble rage.
<q>Lord of the strengthless dead,</q> cries Pallas,
<pb id="v.2.p.335"/>
<q>wickedest of thy brothers, what Furies have stirred
thee with their goads and accursed torches ? Why
hast thou left thy seat and how darest thou pollute
the upper world with thy hellish team ? Thou hast
the hideous Curses, the other deities of Hell, the
dread Furies — any of them would be a worthy spouse
for thee. Quit thy brother's realm, begone from the
kingdom allotted to another. Get thee hence ; let
thine own night suffice thee. Why mix the quick
with the dead ? Why treadest thou our world, an
unwelcome visitant?</q>
So exclaiming she smote with her threatening
shield the horses who sought to advance and barred
their way with the bulk of her targe, thrusting them
back with the hissing snake-hair of Medusa's head
and o'ershadowing them with its outstretched
plumes. She poised for throwing her shaft of ash
whose radiance met and illumed Pluto's black chariot.
Almost had she cast it had not Jove from heaven's
height hurled his red thunderbolt on peaceful wings,
acknowledging his new son ; mid the riven clouds
thunders the marriage-paean and attesting fires
confirm the union.
All unwilling the goddesses yielded, and weeping
Diana laid aside her weapons and thus spake : <q> Fare
well, a long farewell ; forget us not. Reverence for
our sire forbade our help, and against his will we
cannot defend thee. We acknowledge defeat by a
power greater than our own. The Father hath conspired
against thee and betrayed thee to the realms
of silence, no more, alas ! to behold the sisters and
companions who crave sight of thee. What fate
hath reft thee from the upper air and condemned
the heavens to so deep mourning. ? Now no more
<pb id="v.2.p.337"/>
can we rejoice to set Parthenius' steep with nets nor
wear the quiver ; at large as he lists let the wild boar
raven and the lion roar savagely with none to say
him nay. Thee, Taygetus' crest, thee Maenalus'
height shall weep, their hunting laid aside. Long
shalt thou be food for weeping on sorrowing Cynthus'
slopes. E'en my brother's shrine at Delphi shall
speak no more.</q>
Meanwhile Proserpine is borne away in the
winged car, her hair streaming before the wind,
beating her arms in lamentation and calling in
vain remonstrance to the clouds : <q> Why hast thou
not hurled at me, father, bolts forged by the Cyclopes'
hands ? Was this thy will to deliver thy
daughter to the cruel shades and drive her for ever
from this world ? Does love move thee not at all ?
Hast thou nothing of a father's feeling ? What
ill deed of mine has stirred such anger in thee ?
When Phlegra raged with war's madness I bore
no standard against the gods ; 'twas through no
strength of mine that ice-bound Ossa supported
frozen Olympus. For attempt of what crime, for
complicity with what guilt, am I thrust down in
banishment to the bottomless pit of Hell ? Happy
girls whom other ravishers have stolen ; they at
least enjoy the general light of day, while I, together
with my virginity, lose the air of heaven ; stolen from
me alike is innocence and daylight. Needs must I
quit this world and be led a captive bride to serve
Hell's tyrant. Ye flowers that I loved in so evil an
hour, oh, why did I scorn my mother's warning ?
Too late did I detect the wiles of Venus. Mother,
my mother, whether in the vales of Phrygian Ida
the dread pipe sounds about thine ears with Lydian
<pb id="v.2.p.339"/>
strains, or thou hauntest mount Dindymus, ahowl
with self-mutilated Galli, and beholdest the naked
swords of the Curetes, aid me in my bitter need ;
frustrate Pluto's mad lust and stay the funereal reins
of my fierce ravisher.</q>
Her words and those becoming tears mastered
e'en that rude heart as Pluto first learned to feel
love's longings. The tears he wiped away with his
murky cloak, quieting her sad grief with these
soothing words : <q> Cease, Proserpine, to vex thy
heart with gloomy cares and causeless fear. A
prouder sceptre shall be thine, nor shalt thou face
marriage 'with a husband unworthy of thee. I am
that scion of Saturn whose will the framework of
the world obeys, whose power stretches through the
limitless void. Think not thou hast lost the light
of day ; other stars are mine and other courses ;
a purer light shalt thou see and wonder rather at
Elysium's sun and blessed habitants. There a richer
age, a golden race has its home, and we possess for
ever what men win but once. Soft meads shall fail
thee not, and ever-blooming flowers, such as thy
Henna ne'er produced, breathe to gentler zephyrs.
There is, moreover, a precious tree in the leafy
groves whose curving branches gleam with living
ore — a tree consecrate to thee. Thou shalt be queen
of blessed autumn and ever enriched with golden
fruit. Nay more ; whatsoe'er the limpid air embraces,
whatever earth nourishes, the salt seas
sweep, the rivers roll, or the marsh-lands feed, all
living things alike shall yield them to thy sway,
all, I say, that dwell beneath the orb of the moon
that is the seventh of the planets and in its ethereal
journey separates things mortal from the deathless
<pb id="v.2.p.341"/>
stars. To thy feet shall come purple-clothed kings,
stripped of their pomp, and mingling with the
unmoneyed throng ; for death renders all equal.
Thou shalt give doom to the guilty and rest to the
virtuous. Before thy judgement-throne the wicked
must confess the crimes of their evil lives. Lethe's
stream shall obey thee and the Fates be thy handmaidens.
 Be thy will done.</q>
So speaking he urges on his triumphant steeds
and enters Tartarus in gentler wise. The shades
assemble, thick as the leaves the stormy south
wind shakes down from the trees, dense as the rainclouds
it masses, countless as the billows it curls or the
sand it scatters. The dead of every age throng with
hastening foot to see so illustrious a bride. Soon
Pluto himself enters with joyful mien submitting
him to the softening influence of pleasant laughter,
all unlike his former self. At the incoming of his
lord and mistress huge Phlegethon rises ; his bristly
beard is wet with burning streams and flames dart
o'er all his countenance.
There hasten to greet the pair slaves chosen from
out the number. Some put away the lofty chariot,
take the bits from the mouths of the toil-freed
horses and turn them out to graze in their accustomed
pastures. Some hold back the curtains,
others decorate the doorway with branches and
fasten broidered hangings in the bridal chamber.
In chaste bands the matrons of Elysium throng
their queen, and with sweet converse banish her fear ;
they gather and braid her dishevelled hair and place
the wedding-veil upon her head to hide her troubled
blushes.
Joy fills that grey land, the buried throng holds
<pb id="v.2.p.343"/>
high festival, and the ghosts sport them at the
nuptial feast. The flower-crowned Manes sit at a
joyous banquet and unwonted song breaks the
gloomy silence ; wailing is hushed. Hell's murk
gladly disperses and suffers the darkness of age-long
night to grow less impenetrable. Minos'
urn of judgement throws no ambiguous lots ; the
sound of blows is stilled, and Tartarus, the prison
of the wicked, is hushed and still, for punishments
are intermitted. No longer is Ixion tortured by
the ever-turning wheel to which he is bound ; from
Tantalus' lips no more is the flying water withdrawn.
Ixion is freed, Tantalus reaches the stream, and
Tityus at length straightens out his huge limbs
and uncovers nine acres of foul ground (such was
his size), and the vulture, that burrows lazily into
the dark side, is dragged off from his wearied breast
sore against its will, lamenting that no longer is
the devoured flesh renewed for it.
The Furies, forgetful of crimes and dread wrath,
make ready the wine-bowl and drink therefrom
for all their snaky hair. Nay, with gentle song,
their threatenings laid aside, they stretch out their
snakes to the full cups and kindle the festal
torches with unusual flame. Then, too, the birds
flew unhurt over the now appeased stream of
poisonous Avernus, and Lake Amsanctus checked
his deadly exhalations ; the stream was stayed and
the whirlpool grew still. They say that then the
springs of Acheron were changed and welled up
with new milk, while Cocytus, enwreathed with ivy,
flowed along in streams of sweet wine. Lachesis
slit not the thread of life nor did funeral dirge sound
in challenge to the holy chant. Death walked not
<pb id="v.2.p.345"/>
RAPE OF PROSERPINE, II, III

on earth and no parents wept beside the funeral
pyre. The wave brought not destruction to the
sailor nor the spear to the warrior. Cities flourished
and knew not death, the destroyer. Charon crowned
his uncombed locks with sedge and singing plied
his weightless oars.
And now its own evening-star had shone upon the
underworld. The maiden is led into the bridal
chamber. Night, clad in starry raiment, stands by
her as her brideswoman ; she touches the couch
and blesses the union of marriage with a bond that
cannot be broken. The blessed shades raise their
voices and beneath the palace roof of Dis thus begin
their song with sleepless acclaim : <q> Proserpine,
queen of our realm, and thou, Pluto, at once the
brother and the son-in-law of Jove, the Thunderer,
be it yours to know the alliance of conjoined sleep ;
pledge mutual troth as ye hold each other in intertwining
arms. Happy offspring shall be yours ;
joyous Nature awaits gods yet to be born. Give
the world a new divinity and Ceres the grandchildren
she longs for.</q>

</p></div2>
    </div1>
<div1 type="book" n="3" id="poem.36" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<p>

Meanwhile Jove bids cloud-girt Iris go gather
the gods from the whole universe. She, outstripping
the breezes in her rainbow flight, calls to the seadeities,
chides the Nymphs for their delay, and
summons forth the river - gods from their moist
<pb id="v.2.p.347"/>
caverns. Out they haste in doubt and fear what
this disturbance of their peace may signify or what
has caused so great an upheaval. The starry heaven
is thrown open and the gods are bidden take their
seats as merit, not chance, dictates. The first places
are accorded to the heavenly powers, next come the
ocean-deities, calm Nereus and grey-haired Phorcus,
last twiform Glaucus and Proteus, for once of
unvarying shape. The agèd river-gods, too, are
privileged to take their seats ; the other rivers, a
thousand strong, stand as stands the youth of an
earthly assembly. Dripping water-nymphs lean
on their moist sires and Fauns in silence marvel
at the stars.
Then the grave Father from his seat on high
Olympus thus began : <q><p>Once more the affairs of
men have won care from me, affairs long neglected
since I looked upon the repose of Saturn's
reign and knew the torpor of that stagnant age,
when I had fain urged the race of man, long sunk
in lethargy by reason of my sire's sluggish rule,
with the goads of anxious life, whereby their crops
should no more grow to maturity of their own
accord in the untilled fields nor yet the forest trees
drip with honey nor wine flow from springs nor
every stream course sounding into cups. 'Twas not
that I grudged their blessings — gods may not envy
nor hurt — but because luxury is a foe to a godly life,
and plenty dulls the mind of men ; therefore I bade
necessity, invention's mother, provoke their sluggish
spirits and little by little search out the hidden
tracks of things ; bade industry give birth to civilization
and practice nourish it.
</p><p>Nature now with ceaseless complaint bids me
<pb id="v.2.p.349"/>
succour the race of man, calls me cruel and implacable
tyrant, calls to mind the centuries of my sire's
empery and dubs me miser of her riches, for that I
would have the world a wilderness and the land
covered with scrub and would beautify the year
with no fruits. She complained that she, who was
erstwhile the mother of all living things, had suddenly
taken upon her the hated guise of a stepmother.
' Of what avail that man derived his intelligence
from above, that he has held up his head to heaven,
if he wander like the beasts through trackless places,
if with them he crushes acorns for food ? Can
such a life as this bring him happiness, hid in the
forest glades, indistinguishable from the life of
animals ? ' Since I bore so often such complaints
from the lips of mother Nature, at length I took
pity on the world and decided to make man to
cease from his oak-tree food ; wherefore I have
decreed that Ceres, who now, ignorant of her loss,
lashes the lions of Mount Ida, accompanying her
dread mother, should wander over sea and land in
anxious grief, until, in her joy at finding the traces
of her lost daughter, she grant man the gift of corn
and her chariot is borne aloft through the clouds to
scatter among the people ears before unknown and
the steel-blue serpents submit them to the Attic
yoke.1 But if any of the gods dare inform Ceres who
is the ravisher, I swear by the immensity of mine
empire, by the firm-stablished peace of the world, be
he son or sister, spouse or one of my band of daughters,
vaunting her birth as from mine own head, that one
shall feel afar the wrath of mine arms, the thunderbolt's
blow, and be sorry he was born a god and pray
for death. Then, sore wounded, he shall be handed
<pb id="v.2.p.351"/>
over to my son-in-law, Pluto himself, for punishment
in those regions he had fain betray. There he shall
learn whether Hell is true to her own monarch's
cause. Such is my will ; thus let the unchangeable
fates fulfil my decree.</p></q> 
</p><p>He spake and shook the
stars with his dread nod.
But, far from Sicily, no uncertain suspicions of the
loss she had suffered alarmed Ceres, where long
she had dwelt peaceful and secure beneath the rocky
roof of the cave resounding with arms. Dreams
doubled her dread and a vision of Proserpine lost
troubled her every sleep. Now she dreams that
an enemy's spear is piercing her body, now (oh
horror !) that her raiment is changed and is become
black, now that the infecund ash is budding in the
midst of her house. Moreover, there stood a laurel,
loved above all the grove, that used with maiden
leaf to o'ershadow the virgin bower of Proserpine.
This she saw hewn down to the roots, its straggling
branches fouled with dust, and when she asked the
cause of this disaster weeping dryads told her that
the Furies had destroyed it with an axe of Hell.
Next her very image appeared in the mother's
dreams, announcing her fate in no uncertain manner.
She saw Proserpine shut in the dark confines of a
prison-house and bound with cruel chains. Yet not
so had she entrusted her to the fields of Sicily, not
so had the wondering goddesses beheld her in
Etna's flowery meadows. Foul was now that hair,
more beauteous erstwhile than gold ; night had
dimmed the fire of her eyes and frost banished the
roses from her pale cheeks. The gracious flush of
her skin and those limbs whose whiteness matched
the hoar-frost are alike turned to hell - tinctured
<pb id="v.2.p.353"/>
grain. When, therefore, she was at last able to
recognize her daughter, albeit with doubtful gaze,
she cried : <q> What crime hath merited these many
punishments ? Whence comes this dreadful wasting
away ? Who hath power to wreak such cruelty upon
me ? How have thy soft arms deserved fetters of
stubborn iron, scarce fitted for beasts ? Art thou
my daughter or does a vain shadow deceive me?</q>
Thus she answered : <q> Cruel mother, forgetful of
thy daughter's fate, more hard of heart than the
tawny lioness ! Could'st thou be so heedless of
me ? Didst thou hold me cheap for that I am thy
sole daughter ? Dear indeed to thee must be the
name of Proserpine who now, shut in this vast
cavern, as thou seest, am plagued with torment !
Hast thou heart to dance, cruel mother ? Canst
thou revel through the cities of Phrygia ? If thou
hast not banished the mother from thy breast, if
thou, Ceres, art really my mother and 'twas no
Hyrcanian tiger gave me birth, save me, I pray thee,
from this prison and restore me to the upper world.
If the fates forbid my return come thou down at
least and visit me.</q>
So spake she and strove to hold out her trembling
hands. The iron's ruthless strength forbade it, and
the clangour of the chains awoke her sleeping mother.
Ceres lay stiff with terror at the vision, rejoices that
it was not true, but grieves that she cannot embrace
her daughter. Maddened with fear she rushes out
of the cavern and thus addresses Cybele : <q> No longer
now will I tarry in the land of Phrygia, holy mother ;
the duty of protecting my dear daughter calls
me back after so long an absence, for she is of an
age that is exposed to many dangers. I put not
<pb id="v.2.p.355"/>
complete trust in my palace, though built with iron
from the Cyclopes' furnace. I fear lest rumour
disclose her hiding-place and Sicily too lightly guard
my trust. The fame of that place too widely bruited
abroad alarms me ; needs must I find elsewhere
some obscurer abode. Our retreat must be on all
men's tongues by reason of the groanings of Enceladus
and the neighbour flames. Ill-omened dreams,
too, with diverse visions often give me pause, and no
day passes but brings some inauspicious hap. How
often has my crown of golden ears fallen of itself !
How often blood flowed from my breast ! In mine
own despite streams of tears course down my cheeks
and unbidden my hands beat my astonished breast.
Would I blow up the flute, funereal is the note ; do I
shake the cymbals, the cymbals echo a sound of mourning.
Alas ! I fear there is some trouble in these
portents. This long sojourn has wrought me woe.</q>
<q> May the wind carry far away thy vain words,</q> replies
Cybele ; <q> not such the Thunderer's want of care
that he would not hurl his bolt in his daughter's defence.
Yet go and return, dismayed by no evil hap.</q>
This said, Ceres left the temple ; but no speed is
enough for her haste ; she complains that her sluggish
dragons scarce move, and, lashing the wings now of
this one and now of that (though little they deserved
it), she hopes to reach Sicily e'er yet out of sight
of Ida. She fears everything and hopes nothing,
anxious as the bird that has entrusted its unfledged
brood to a low-growing ash and while absent gathering
food has many fears lest perchance the wind
has blown the fragile nest from the tree, lest her
young ones be exposed to the theft of man or the
greed of snakes.
<pb id="v.2.p.357"/>
When she saw the gate-keepers fled, the house
unguarded, the rusted hinges, the overthrown door-posts,
and the miserable state of the silent halls,
pausing not to look again at the disaster, she rent
her garment and tore away the shattered corn-ears
along with her hair. She could not weep nor
speak nor breathe and a trembling shook the very-marrow
of her bones ; her faltering steps tottered.
She flung open the doors and wandering through
the empty rooms and deserted halls, recognized the
half-ruined warp with its disordered threads and
the work of the loom broken off. The goddess'
labours had come to naught, and what remained to
be done, that the bold spider was finishing with her
sacrilegious web.
She weeps not nor bewails the ill ; only kisses
the loom and stifles her dumb complaints amid the
threads, clasping to her bosom, as though it had been
her child, the spindles her child's hand had touched,
the wool she had cast aside, and all the toys scattered
in maiden sport. She scans the virgin bed, the
deserted couch, and the chair where Proserpine had
sat : even as a herd, whose drove the unexpected
fury of an African lion or bands of marauding beasts
have attacked, gazes in amaze at the vacant stall,
and, too late returned, wanders through the emptied
pastures, sadly calling to the unreplying steers.
And there, lying in the innermost parts of the
house, she saw Electra, loving nurse of Proserpine,
best known among the old Nymphs of Ocean ; she
who loved Proserpine as did Ceres. 'Twas she who,
when Proserpine had left her cradle, would bear
her in her loving bosom and bring the little girl to
mighty Jove and set her to play on her father's
<pb id="v.2.p.359"/>
knee. She was her companion, her guardian, and
could be deemed her second mother. There, with
torn and dishevelled hair, all foul with grey dust,
she was lamenting the rape of her divine foster-child.
Ceres approached her, and when at length her
grief allowed her sighs free rein : <q> What ruin is
here?</q> she said. <q> Of what enemy am I become
the victim ? Does my husband yet rule or do the
Titans hold heaven ? What hand hath dared this,
if the Thunderer be still alive ? Have Typhon's
shoulders forced up Inarime or does Alcyoneus
course on foot through the Etruscan Sea, having
burst the bonds of imprisoning Vesuvius ? Or has
the neighbouring mountain of Etna oped her jaws
and expelled Enceladus ? Perchance Briareus with
his hundred arms has attacked my house ? Ah,
my daughter, where art thou now ? Whither are
fled my thousand servants, whither Cyane ? What
violence has driven away the winged Sirens ? Is
this your faith ? Is this the way to guard another's
treasure?</q>
The nurse trembled and her sorrow gave place to
shame ; fain would she have died could she so escape
the gaze of that unhappy mother, and long stayed
she motionless, hesitating to disclose the suspected
criminal and the all too certain death. Scarce could
she thus speak : <q><p>Would that the raging band of
Giants had wrought this ruin ! Easier to bear is
a common lot. 'Tis the goddesses, and, though
thou wilt scarce credit it, her own sisters, who have
conspired to our undoing. Thou seest the devices
of gods and wounds inflicted by sisters' jealousy.
Heaven is a more cruel enemy than Hell.
</p><p>All quiet was the house, the maiden dared not
<pb id="v.2.p.361"/>
o'erstep the threshold nor visit the grassy pastures,
close bound by thy commands. The loom gave her
work, the Sirens with their song relaxation — with
me she held pleasant converse, with me she slept ;
safe delights were hers within the halls. Then
suddenly Cytherea came (who showed her the way
to our hid abode I know not), and, that she might not
rouse our suspicions, she brought with her Diana
and Minerva, attending her on either side. Straightway
with beaming smiles she put on a pretence of
joy, kissed Proserpine many a time, and repeated
the name of sister, complaining of that hard-hearted
mother who chose to condemn such beauty to imprisonment
and complaining that by forbidding her
intercourse with the goddesses she had removed her
far from her father's heaven. My unwitting charge
rejoiced in these evil words and bade a feast be
spread with plentiful nectar. Now she dons Diana's
aims and dress and tries her bow with her soft
fingers. Now crowned with horse-hair plumes she
puts on the helmet, Minerva commending her, and
strives to carry her huge shield.
</p><p>Venus was the first with guileful suggestion to
mention fields and the vale of Henna. Cunningly
she harps upon the nearness of the flowery mead,
and as though she knew it not, asks what merits
the place boasts, pretending not to believe that a
harmless winter allows the roses to bloom, that the
cold months are bright with flowers not rightly
theirs, and that the spring thickets fear not there
Boötes' wrath. So with her wonderment, her passion
to see the spot, she persuades Proserpine. Alas !
how easily does youth err with its weak ways !
What tears did I not shed to no purpose, what vain
<pb id="v.2.p.363"/>
entreaties did my lips not utter ! Away she flew,
trusting to the sisters' protection ; the scattered
company of attendant nymphs followed after her.
</p><p>They went to the hills clothed with undying
grass and gather flowers 'neath the twilight of dawn,
when the quiet meads are white with dew and violets
drink the scattered moisture. But when the sun
had mounted to higher air at noon, behold ! murky
night hid the sky and the island trembled and shook
beneath the beat of horses' hoofs and the rumble
of wheels. Who the charioteer was none might tell
— whether he was the harbinger of death or it was
Death himself. Gloom spread through the meadows,
the rivers stayed their courses, the fields were blighted,
nor did aught live, once touched with those horses'
breath. I saw the bryony pale, the roses fade, the
lilies wither. When in his roaring course the driver
turned back his steeds the night it brought accompanied
the chariot and light was restored to the
world. Proserpine was nowhere to be seen. Their
vows fulfilled, the goddesses had returned and tarried
not. We found Cyane half dead amid the fields ;
there she lay, a garland round her neck and the
blackened wreaths faded upon her forehead. At
once we approached her and inquired after her
mistress's fortune, for she had been a witness of the
disaster. What, we asked, was the aspect of the
horses ; who their driver ? Naught said she, but
corrupted with some hidden venom, dissolved into
water. Water crept amid her hair ; legs and arms
melted and flowed away, and soon a clear stream
washed our feet. The rest are gone ; the Sirens,
Achelous' daughters, rising on rapid wing, have
occupied the coast of Sicilian Pelorus, and in wrath
<pb id="v.2.p.365"/>
at this crime now turned their lyres to man's destruction,
tuneful now for ill. Their sweet voices
stay ships, but once that song is heard the oars can
move no more. I alone am left in the house to
drag out an old age of mourning.</p></q>
</p><p>
Ceres is still a prey to anxiety ; half distraught
she fears everything as though all were not yet
accomplished. Anon she turns her head and eyes
to heaven and with raging breast inveighs against
its denizens ; even as lofty Niphates shakes to the
roaring of the Hyrcan tigress whose cubs the terrified
horseman has carried off to be the playthings of
Persia's king. Speedier than the west wind that
is her paramour 1 rushes the tigress, anger blazing
from her stripes, but just as she is about to engulf
the terrified hunter in her capacious maw, she is
checked by the mirrored image of her own form 2 :
so the motlier of Proserpine rages over all Olympus
crying :</p><p><q><p>Give her back ; no wandering stream gave
me birth ; I spring not from the Dryad rabble.
Towered Cybele bare me also to Saturn. Where
are the ordinances of the gods, where the laws of
heaven ? What boots it to live a good life ? See,
Cytherea dares show her face (modest goddess !)
even after her Lemnian 3 bondage ! 'Tis that
chaste sleep and a loverless couch have given her
this courage ! This is, I suppose, the reward
of those maidenly embraces ! Small wonder that
after such infamy she account nothing disgraceful.
Ye goddesses that have known not marriage, is it
thus that ye neglect the honour due to virginity ?
<pb id="v.2.p.367"/>


Have ye so changed your counsel ? Do ye now
go allied with Venus and her accomplice ravishers ?
Worthy each of you to be worshipped in Scythian
temples and at altars that lust after human blood.
What hath caused such great anger ? Which of you
has my Proserpine wronged even in her slightest
word ? Doubtless she drove thee, Delian goddess,
from thy loved woods, or deprived thee, Triton-born,
of some battle thou hadst joined. Did she plague
you with talk ? Break rudely upon your dances ?
Nay, that she might be no burden to you, she dwelt
far away in the solitudes of Sicily. What good hath
her retirement done her ? No peace can still the
madness of bitter jealousy.</p></q></p><p>
Thus she upbraids them all. But they, obedient
to the Father's word, keep silence or say they know
nothing, and make tears their answer to the mother's
questionings. What can she do ? She ceases,
beaten, and in turn descends to humble entreaty.
<q> If a mother's love swelled too high or if I have
done aught more boldly than befitted misery, oh
forgive ! A suppliant and wretched I fling me at
your feet ; grant me to learn my doom ; grant me
at least this much — sure knowledge of my woes.
Fain would I know the manner of this ill ; whatsoever
fortune ye have visited upon me that will
I bear and account it fate, not injustice. Grant a
parent the sight of her child ; I ask her not back.
Whosoever thou art, possess in peace what thine
hand has taken. The prey is thine, fear not. But
if the ravisher has thwarted me, binding you by
some oath, yet do thou, at least, Latona, tell me his
name ; to thee mayhap Diana hath confessed her
knowledge. Thou hast known childbirth, the anxiety
<pb id="v.2.p.369"/>
and love for children ; to offspring twain hast thou
given birth ; this was mine only child. So may est
thou ever enjoy Apollo's locks, so mayest thou live
a happier mother than I.</q>
Plenteous tears then bedewed her cheeks. She
continued : <q> Why these tears ? why this silence ?
Woe is me ; all desert me. Why tarriest thou yet
to no purpose ? Seest thou not 'tis open war with
heaven ? were it not better to seek again thy daughter
by sea and land ? I will gird myself and scour the
world, unwearied I will penetrate its every corner,
nor ever stay my search, nor rest nor sleep till I find
my reft treasure, though she lie whelmed in the
Spanish Ocean bed or hedged around in the depths
of the Red Sea. Neither ice-bound Rhine nor
Alpine frosts shall stay me ; the treacherous tides
of Syrtes shall not give me pause. My purpose holds
to penetrate the fastnesses of the South and to tread
the snowy home of Boreas. I will climb Atlas on the
brink of the sunset and illumine Hydaspes' stream
with my torches. Let wicked Jove behold me wandering
through towns and country, and Juno's jealousy
be sated with her rival's ruin. Have your sport with
me, triumph in heaven, proud gods, celebrate your
illustrious victory o'er Ceres' conquered daughter.</q>
So spake she and glides down upon Etna's familiar
slopes, there to fashion torches to aid her nightwandering
labours.
There was a wood, hard by the stream of Acis,
which fair Galatea oft chooses in preference to
Ocean and cleaves in swimming with her snowy
breast — a wood dense 'with foliage that closed in
Etna's summit on all sides with interwoven branches.
'Tis there that Jove is said to have laid down his
<pb id="v.2.p.371"/>
bloody shield and set his captured spoil after the
battle. The grove glories in trophies from the plain
of Phlegra and signs of victory clothe its every tree.
Here hang the gaping jaws and monstrous skins of
the Giants ; affixed to trees their faces still threaten
horribly, and heaped up on all sides bleach the
huge bones of slaughtered serpents. Their stiffening
sloughs smoke with the blow of many a thunderbolt,
and every tree boasts some illustrious name.
This one scarce supports on its down-bended
branches the naked swords of hundred-handed
Aegaeon ; that glories in the murky trophies of
Coeus ; this bears up the arms of Mimas ; spoiled
Ophion weighs down those branches. But higher
than all the other trees towers a pine, its shady
branches spread wide, and bears the reeking arms of
Enceladus himself, all powerful king of the Earth-born
giants ; it would have fallen beneath the heavy
burden did not a neighbouring oak-tree support its
wearied weight. Therefore the spot wins awe and
sanctity ; none touches the aged grove, and 'tis
accounted a crime to violate the trophies of the
gods. No Cyclops dares pasture there his flock
nor hew down the trees, Polyphemus himself flies
from the hallowed shade.
Not for that did Ceres stay her steps ; the very
sanctity of the place inflames her wrath ; with angry
hand she brandishes her axe, ready to strike Jove
himself. She hesitates whether to cut down pines or
lay low knotless cedars, scans likely trunks and lofty
trees and shakes their branches with vigorous hand.
Even so when a man, fain to carry merchandise
over distant seas, builds a ship on dry land and makes
ready to expose his life to the tempest, he hews down
<pb id="v.2.p.373"/>
beech and alder and marks the diverse utility of the
yet growing forest ; the lofty tree he selects as yardarms
for the swelling sail ; the strong he prefers as a
helm ; the pliant will make good oars ; the waterproof
is suitable for the keel.
Two cypresses in the grass hard by raised their
inviolate heads to heaven ; Simois looks not on such
in amaze amid the crags of Ida, nor does Orontes
water their like, Orontes that feeds Apollo's grove
and harbours rich cities on his banks. You would
know them for sisters for they tower equal in height
and look down upon the wood with twin tops. These
she would have as torches ; she attacks each with
vigorous blows, her gown girt back, her arms bared
and armed with the axe. First one she strikes, then
the other, and rains blows upon their trembling
trunks with might and main. Together they crash
to the ground, lay their foliage in the dust and lie
upon the plain, wept of Fauns and wood-nymphs.
She seizes both just as they are, uplifts them and, with
hair out-streaming behind her, climbs panting the
slopes of the mountain, passes beyond the flames and
inaccessible precipices, and treads the lava that brooks
no mortal footstep : even as the grim Megaera hastens
to kindle yew-trees to light her to crime, speeding
her journey to the w alls of Cadmus' city or meaning
to work her devilment in Thyestean Mycenae ; darkness
and the shades give her passage, and Hell rings
to her iron tread, till she halts beside Phlegethon's
wave and fires her torch from its brimming waves.
When she had climbed to the mouth of the burning
rock, straightway, turning aside her head, she thrust
the kindling cypresses into its inmost depths, thus
closing in the cavern on all sides and stopping up the
<pb id="v.2.p.375"/>
blazing exit of the flames. The mountain thunders
with repressed fire and Vulcan is shut in a grievous
prison ; the enclosed smoke cannot escape. The
cone-bearing tops of the cypresses blaze and Etna
grows with new ashes ; the branches crackle, kindled
with the sulphur. Then, lest their long journey
should cause them to fail, she bids the flames never
die nor sleep and drenches the wood with that secret
drug 1 wherewith Phaethon bedews his steeds and the
Moon her bulls.
Silent night had now in her turn visited upon the
world her gift of sleep. Ceres, with her wounded
breast, starts on her long journey and, as she sets
out, speaks as follows : <q><p>Little thought I, Proserpine,
to carry for thee such torches as these. I had hoped
what every mother hopes ; marriage and festal torches
and a wedding-song to be sung in heaven — such was
my expectation. Are we divinities thus the sport of
fate ? does Lachesis vent her spleen on us as on mankind ?
How lofty was but now mine estate, surrounded
with suitors innumerable for my daughter's
hand ! What mother of many children but would
have owned her my inferior by reason of my only
daughter ! Thou wast my first joy and my last ; I
was called prolific for that I bare thee. Thou wert
my glory, my comfort, dear object of a mother's
pride ; with thee alive I was goddess indeed, with
thee safe I was Juno's equal. Now am I outcast,
beggared. 'Tis the Father's will. Yet why make
Jove answerable for my tears ? 'Twas I who so
cruelly undid thee, I confess it, for I deserted thee
and heedlessly exposed thee to threatening foes.
Too deeply was I enmeshed in careless enjoyment of
shrill-voiced revel, and, happy amid the din of arms,
<pb id="v.2.p.377"/>
I was yoking Phrygian lions whilst thou wast being
carried off. Yet see the punishment visited upon
me. My face is seared with wounds and long gashes
furrow my bloody breast. My womb, forgetful that
it gave thee birth, is beaten with continual blows.
</p><p>Where under heaven shall I find thee ? Beneath
what quarter of the sky ? Who shall point the way,
what path shall lead me ? What chariot was it ? Who
was that cruel ravisher ? A denizen of earth or sea ?
What traces of his wingèd wheels can I discover ?
Whithersoever my steps lead me or chance direct,
thither will I go. Even so may Dione be deserted
and seek for Venus !
</p><p>Will my labours be successful ? Shall I ever again
be blest with thine embrace, my daughter ? Art
thou still fair ; still glows the brightness of thy
cheeks ? Or shall I perchance see thee as thou
cam'st in my nightly vision ; as I saw thee in my
dreams ?</p></q></p><p>
So spake she and from Etna first she drags her
steps, and, cursing its guilty flowers and the spot
whence Proserpine was ravaged, she follows the
straying tracks of the chariot-wheels and examines
the fields in the full light of her lowered torch. Every
rut is wet -with her tears ; she weeps at each trace
she espies in her wanderings over the plain. She
glides a shadow o'er the sea and the farthest ray of
her torches' gleam strikes the coasts of Italy and
Libya. The Tuscan shore grows bright and the
Syrtes gleam with kindled wave. The light reaches
the distant cave of Scylla. of whose dogs some shrink
back and are still in dumb amaze, others, not yet
horrified into silence, continue to bark. 1
</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
