<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On Behalf of Marcus Claudius Marcellus </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <pb n="457"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN BEHALF OF MARCUS CLAUDIUS MARCELLUS.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>Marcus Claudius Marcellus was descended from the most illustrious families at
                    Rome, and had been consul with Servius Sulpicius Rufus; in which office he had
                    given great offence to Caesar by making a motion in the senate to deprive him of
                    his command; and in the civil war he espoused the side of Pompeius, and had been
                    present at the battle of Pharsalia, after which be retired to Lesbos. But after
                    some time the whole senate interceded with Caesar to pardon him, and to allow
                    him to return to his country. And when he yielded to their entreaties, Cicero
                    made the following speech, thanking Caesar for his magnanimity; though he had,
                    as he says himself, (<bibl n="Cic. Fam. 4.4.1">Ep. Fam. 4.4</bibl>,) determined
                    to say nothing; but he was afraid that if he continued silent Caesar would
                    interpret it as a proof that he despaired of the republic. Caesar, though he saw
                    the senate unanimous in their petition for Marcellus, yet had the motion for his
                    pardon put to the vote, and called for the opinion of every individual senator
                    on it. Cicero appears at this time to have believed that Caesar intended to
                    restore the republic, as he mentions in his letters, (<bibl
                        n="Cic. Fam. 13.68.1">Ep. Fam. 13.68</bibl>.)</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>This day, O conscript fathers, has brought with it an end to the long silence in
                which I have of late indulged; not out of any fear, but partly from sorrow, partly
                from modesty; and at the same time it has revived in me my ancient habit of saying
                what my wishes and opinions are. For I cannot by any means pass over in silence such
                great humanity, such unprecedented and unheard-of clemency, such moderation in the
                exercise of supreme and universal power, such incredible and almost godlike wisdom.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For now that Marcus Marcellus, O conscript
                fathers, has been restored to you and the republic, I think that not only his voice
                and authority are preserved and restored to you and to the republic, but my own
                also. </p>
            <p>For I was concerned, O conscript fathers, and most exceedingly grieved, when I saw
                such a man as he is, who had espoused the same cause which I myself had, not
                enjoying the same good fortune as myself; nor was I able to persuade myself <pb
                    n="458"/> self to think it right or fair that I should be going on in my usual
                routine, while that rival and imitator of my zeal and labours, who had been a
                companion and comrade of mine throughout, was separated from me. Therefore, you, O
                Caius Caesar, have reopened to me my former habits of life, which were closed up,
                and you have raised, as it were, a standard to all these men, as a sort of token to
                lead them to entertain hopes of the general welfare of the republic. <milestone
                    n="3" unit="section"/> For it was seen by me before in many instances, and
                especially in my own, and now it is clearly understood by everybody, since you have
                granted Marcus Marcellus to the senate and people of Rome, in spite of your
                recollection of all the injuries you have received at his hands, that you prefer the
                authority of this order and the dignity of the republic to the indulgence of your
                own resentment or your own suspicions. </p>
            <p>He, indeed, has this day reaped the greatest possible reward for the virtuous tenor
                of his previous life; in the great unanimity of the senate in his favour, and also
                in your own most dignified and important opinion of him. And from this you, in
                truth, must perceive what great credit there is in conferring a kindness, when there
                is such glory to be got even by receiving one. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And
                he too, is fortunate whose safety is now the cause of scarcely less joy to all other
                men than it will be to himself when he is informed of it. And this honour has
                deservedly and most rightfully fallen to his lot. For who is superior to him either
                in nobleness of birth, or in honesty, or in zeal for virtuous studies, or in purity
                of life, or in any description whatever of excellence. <milestone n="2"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>No one is blessed with such a stream of genius, no one is endowed with such vigour
                and richness of eloquence, either as a speaker or as a writer, as to be able, I will
                not say to extol, but even, O Caius Caesar, plainly to relate all your achievements.
                Nevertheless, I assert, and with your leave I maintain, that in all of them you
                never gained greater and truer glory than you have acquired this day. <milestone
                    n="5" unit="section"/> I am accustomed often to keep this idea before my eyes,
                and often to affirm in frequent conversations, that all the exploits of our own
                generals, all those of foreign nations and of most powerful states, all the mighty
                deeds of the most illustrious monarchs, can be compared with yours neither in the
                magnitude of your wars, nor in the number of your battles, nor in the variety of <pb
                    n="459"/> countries which you have conquered, nor in the rapidity of your
                conquests, nor in the great difference of character with which your wars have been
                marked; and that those countries the most remote from each other could not be
                traveled over more rapidly by any one in a journey, than they have been visited by
                your, I will not say journeys, but victories. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And if I were not to admit, that those actions are so great that scarcely any man's
                mind or comprehension is capable of doing justice to them, I should be very
                senseless. But there are other actions greater than those. For some people are in
                the habit of disparaging military glory, and of denying the whole of it to the
                generals, and of giving the multitude a share of it also, so that it may not be the
                peculiar property of the commanders. And, no doubt in the affairs of war, the valour
                of the troops, the advantages of situation, the assistance of allies, fleets, and
                supplies, have great influence; and a most important share in all such transactions,
                Fortune claims for herself, as of her right; and whatever has been done successfully
                she considers almost entirely as her own work. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But in this glory, O Caius Caesar, which you have just earned, you have no partner.
                The whole of this, however great it may be,—and surely it is as great as
                possible,—the whole of it, I say, is your own. The centurion can claim for himself
                no share of that praise, neither can the prefect, nor the battalion, nor the
                squadron. Nay, even that very mistress of all human affairs, Fortune herself, cannot
                thrust herself into any participation in that glory; she yields to you; she
                confesses that it is all your own, your peculiar private desert. For rashness is
                never united with wisdom, nor is chance ever admitted to regulate affairs conducted
                with prudence. <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="8" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>You have subdued nations, savage in their barbarism, countless in their numbers,
                boundless, if we regard the extent of country peopled by them, and rich in every
                kind of resource; but still you were only conquering things, the nature and
                condition of which was such that they could be overcome by force. For there is no
                strength so great that it cannot be weakened and broken by arms and violence. But to
                subdue one's inclinations, to master one's angry feelings, to be moderate in the
                hour of victory, to not merely raise from the ground a prostrate adversary, eminent
                for noble birth, for genius, and for virtue, but even to increase his previous
                dignity, —they are <pb n="460"/> actions of such a nature, that the man who does
                them, I do not compare to the most illustrious man, but I consider equal to God.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, O Caius Caesar, those military glories of yours will be celebrated not
                only in our own literature and language, but in those of almost all nations; nor is
                there any age which will ever be silent about your praises. But still, deeds of that
                sort somehow or other, even when they are read, appear to be overwhelmed with the
                cries of the soldiers and the sound of the trumpets. But when we hear or read of
                anything which has been done with clemency, with humanity, with justice, with
                moderation, and with wisdom, especially in a time of anger, which is very adverse to
                prudence, and in the hour of victory, which is naturally insolent and haughty, with
                what ardour are we then inflamed, (even if the actions are not such as have really
                been performed, but are only fabulous,) so as often to love those whom we have never
                seen! <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But as for you whom we behold present among
                us, whose mind, and feelings, and countenance, we at this moment see to be such,
                that you wish to preserve everything which the fortune of war has left to the
                republic, oh with what praises must we extol you? with what zeal must we follow you?
                with what affection must we devote ourselves to you! The very walls, I declare, the
                very walls of this senate-house appear to me eager to return you thanks; because, in
                a short time, you will have restored their ancient authority to this venerable abode
                of themselves and of their ancestors. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>In truth, O conscript fathers, when I just now, in common with you, beheld the tears
                of Caius Marcellus, a most virtuous man, endowed with a never-to-be-forgotten
                affection for his brother, the recollection of all the Marcelli presented itself to
                my heart. For you, O Caesar, have, by preserving Marcellus, restored their dignity
                even to those Marcelli who are dead, and you have saved that most noble family, now
                reduced to a small number, from perishing. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> You,
                therefore, justly prefer this day to all the splendid and innumerable
                congratulations which at different times have been addressed to you. For this
                exploit is your own alone; the other achievements which have been performed by you
                as general, were great indeed, but still they were performed by the agency of a
                great and numerous band of comrades. But in this exploit <pb n="461"/> you are the
                general, and you are your own sole comrade: and the act itself is such that no lapse
                of time will ever put an end to your monuments and trophies; for there is nothing
                which is wrought by manual labour which time will not sometime or other impair or
                destroy; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but this justice and lenity of yours
                will every day grow brighter and brighter, so that, in proportion as time takes away
                from the effect of your deed, in the same degree it will add to your glory. And you
                had already surpassed all other conquerors in civil wars, in equity, and clemency,
                but this day you have surpassed even yourself. I fear that this which I am saying
                cannot, when it is only heard, be understood as fully as I myself think and feel it;
                you appear to have surpassed victory itself, since you have remitted in favour of
                the conquered those things which victory had put in your power. For though, by the
                conditions of the victory itself, we who were conquered were all ruined, we still
                have been preserved by the deliberate decision of your clemency. You, therefore,
                deserve to be the only man who is never conquered, since you conquer the conditions
                and the violent privileges of victory itself. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="13" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And, O conscript fathers, remark how widely this decision of Caius Caesar extends.
                For by it, all of us who, under the compulsion of some miserable and fatal destiny
                of the republic, were driven to take up arms as we did, though we are still not free
                from the fault of having erred as men may, are at all events released from all
                imputation of wickedness. For when, at your entreaty, he preserved Marcus Marcellus
                to the republic, he, at the same time, restored me to myself and to the republic
                though no one entreated him in my favour, and he restored all the other most
                honourable men who were in the same case to ourselves and to their country; whom you
                now behold in numbers and dignity present in this very assembly. He has not brought
                his enemies into the senate-house; but he has decided that the war was undertaken by
                most of them rather out of ignorance, and because of some ungrounded and empty fear,
                than out of either any depraved desires or cruelty. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                />
            </p>
            <p>And in that war, I always thought it right to listen to all proposals that gave any
                hope of peace, and I always grieved that not only peace, but that even the language
                of those citizens who asked for peace, should be rejected. For I never approved of
                either that or of any civil war whatever; and my <pb n="462"/> counsels were always
                allied to peace and peaceful measures, not to war and arms. I followed the man from
                my own private feelings, not because of my judgment of his public conduct; and the
                faithful recollection of the grateful disposition which I cherish had so much
                influence with me, that though I had not only no desire for victory, but no hope
                even of it, I rushed on, knowingly, and with my eyes open, as it were to a voluntary
                death. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> And, indeed, my sentiments in the matter
                were not at all concealed; for in this assembly, before any decisive steps were
                taken either way, I said many things in favour of peace, and even while the war was
                going on I retained the same opinions, even at the risk of my life.<note
                    anchored="true">Cicero was not present at the battle of Pharsalia, but remained
                    at Dyrrachium, vexed at his advice being totally disregarded. Cato also remained
                    at Dyrrachium. When Labienus brought them the news of Pompey's defeat, Cato
                    offered Cicero the command, as the superior in dignity, and Plutarch relates,
                    that on his refusal of it, young Pompey was so enraged, that he could have
                    killed him on the spot if Cato had not prevented him. And this is what Middleton
                    (who quotes the sentence in the text) thinks that Cicero is alluding to
                    here.</note> And from this fact, no one will form so unjust an opinion as to
                doubt what Caesar's own inclination respecting the war was, when, the moment that it
                was in his power, he declared his opinion in favour of saving the advisers of peace,
                but showed his anger against the others. And, perhaps, that was not very strange at
                a time when the event of the war was still uncertain, and its fortune still
                undecided. But he who, when victorious, attaches himself to the advisers of peace,
                plainly declares that he would have preferred having no war at all even to
                conquering. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="16" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And in this matter I myself am a witness in favour of Marcus Marcellus. For as our
                opinions have at all times agreed in time of peace, so did they then in respect of
                that man. How often have I seen him affected with the deepest grief at the insolence
                of certain men, and dreading also the ferocity of victory! On which account your
                liberality, O Caius Caesar, ought to he more acceptable to us who have seen those
                things. For now we may compare, not the causes of the two parties together, but the
                use which each would have made of victory. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> We
                have seen your victory terminated at once by the result of your battles; we have
                seen no sword unsheathed in the city. The citizens whom we have lost were stricken
                down by the force of Mars, not by evil feelings let loose by <pb n="463"/> victory;
                so that no man can doubt that Caius Caesar would even raise many from the dead if
                that were possible, since he does preserve all those of that army that he can. </p>
            <p>But of the other party I will say no more than what we were all afraid of at the
                time, namely, that theirs would have been too angry a victory. <milestone n="18"
                    unit="section"/> For some of them were in the habit of indulging in threats not
                only against those of their enemies who were in arms, but even against those who
                remained quiet; and they used to say that the matter to he considered was not what
                each man had thought, but where he had been. So that it appears to me that the
                immortal gods, even if they were inflicting punishment on the Roman people for some
                offence, when they stirred up so serious and melancholy a civil war, are at length
                appeased, or at all events satiated and have now made all our hopes of safety depend
                on the clemency and wisdom of the conqueror. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Rejoice, then, in that admirable and virtuous disposition of yours; and enjoy not
                only your fortune and glory, but also your own natural good qualities, and amiable
                inclinations and manners; for those are the things which produce the greatest fruit
                and pleasure to a wise man. When you call to mind your other achievements, although
                you will often congratulate yourself on your valour, still you will often have
                reason to thank your good fortune also. But as often as you think of us whom you
                have chosen to live safely in the republic as well as yourself you will be thinking
                at the same time of your own exceeding kindness, of your own incredible liberality,
                of your own unexampled wisdom; qualities which I will venture to call not only the
                greatest, but the only real blessings. For there is so much splendour in genuine
                glory, so much dignity in magnanimity and real practical wisdom, that these
                qualities appear to be given to a man by virtue, while all other advantages seem
                only lent to them by fortune. </p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Be not wearied then in the preservation of
                virtuous men, especially of those who have fallen, not from any evil desires, or
                depravity of disposition, but merely from an opinion of their duty,—a foolish and
                erroneous one perhaps, but certainly not a wicked one,—and because they were misled
                by imaginary claims which they fancied the republic had on them. For it is no fault
                of yours if some people were afraid of you; and, on the other hand, it is your
                greatest praise that they have now felt that they had no reason to fear you. <pb
                    n="464"/>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="21" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But now I come to those severe complaints, and to those most terrible suspicions that
                you have given utterance to; of dangers which should be guarded against not more by
                you yourself than by all the citizens and most especially by us who have been
                preserved by you. And although I trust that the suspicion is an ungrounded one,
                still I will not speak so as to make light of it. For caution for you is caution for
                ourselves. So that, if we must err on one side or the other, I would rather appear
                too fearful, than not sufficiently prudent. But still, who is there so frantic? Any
                one of your own friends? And yet who are more your friends than those to whom you
                have restored safety which they did not venture to hope for? Any one of that number
                who were with you? It is not credible that any man should be so insane as not to
                prefer the life of that man who was his general when he obtained the greatest
                advantages of all sorts, to his own. But if your friends have no thoughts of
                wickedness, need you take precautions lest your enemies may be entertaining such?
                Who are they? For all those men who were your enemies have either already lost their
                lives through their obstinacy, or else have preserved them through your mercy; so
                that either none of your enemies survive, or those who do survive are your most
                devoted friends. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But still, as there are so many hiding places and so many dark corners in men's
                minds, let us increase your suspicions, for by so doing we shall at the same time
                increase your diligence. For who is there so ignorant of everything, so very new to
                the affairs of the republic, so entirely destitute of thought either for his own or
                for the general safety, as not to understand that his own safety is bound up with
                yours? that the lives of all men depend on your single existence? I myself, in
                truth, while I think of you day and night,—as I ought to do,—fear only the chances
                to which all men are liable, and the uncertain events of health and the frail tenure
                of our common nature, and I grieve that, while the republic ought to he immortal, it
                depends wholly on the life of one mortal man <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> But
                if to the chances of human life and the uncertain condition of man's health there
                were to be added also any conspiracy of wickedness and treachery, then what god
                should we think able to assist the republic, even if he were to desire to do so?
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>All things, O Caius Caesar, which you now see lying <pb n="465"/> stricken and
                prostrate—as it is inevitable that they should be—through the violence of war, must
                now be raised up again by you alone. The courts of justice must be reestablished,
                confidence must be restored, licentiousness must be repressed, the increase of
                population must be encouraged, everything which has become lax and disordered must
                be braced up and strengthened by strict laws. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> In
                so vast a civil war, when there was such ardour of feeling and of warlike
                preparation on both sides, it was impossible but that—whatever the ultimate result
                of the war might he—the republic which had been violently shaken by it should lose
                my ornaments of its dignity and many bulwarks of its security, and that each general
                should do many things while in arms, which he would have forbidden to have been done
                while clad in the garb of Peace. And all those wounds of war thus inflicted now
                require your attention, and there is no one except you who is able to heal them.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> Therefore, I was concerned when I heard that
                celebrated and wise saying of yours, “I have lived long enough to satisfy either
                nature or glory.” Sufficiently long, if you please: for nature, and I will add, if
                you like, for glory; but, which is of the greatest consequence of all, certainly not
                long enough for your country. Give up then, I entreat you, that wisdom of learned
                men shown in their contempt of death; do not be wise at our expense. For it has
                often come to my ears that you are in the habit of using that expression much too
                frequently—that you have lived long enough for yourself. I dare say you have; but I
                could only be willing to hear you say so if you lived for yourself alone, or if you
                had been born for yourself alone. But as it is—as your exploits have brought the
                safety of all the citizens and the entire republic to a dependence on you,—you are
                so far from having completed your greatest labours, that you have not even laid the
                foundations which you design to lay. And will you then limit your life, not by the
                welfare of the republic, but by the tranquillity of your own mind? What will you do,
                if that is not even sufficient for your glory, of which—wise man though you be—you
                will not deny that you are exceedingly desirous? <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                “Is it then,” you will say, “but small glory that we shall leave behind us?” It may,
                indeed, be sufficient for others, however many they may be, and insufficient for you
                alone. For whatever it is, however ample it may be, it certainly is insufficient, as
                long as <pb n="466"/> there is anything greater still. And if, O Caius Caesar, this
                was to be the result of your immortal achievements, that after conquering all your
                enemies, you were to leave the republic in the state in which it now is; then
                beware, I beg of you, lest your virtue should earn admiration rather than solid
                glory; since the glory which is illustrious and which is celebrated abroad, is the
                fame of many and great services done either to one's own friends, or to one's
                country, or to the whole race of mankind. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="27" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>This, then, is the part which remains to you—this is the cause which you have before
                you; this is what you must now labour at,—to settle the republic, and to enjoy it
                yourself as the first of its citizens, in the greatest tranquillity and
                peacefulness. And then, if you please when you have discharged the obligations which
                you owe to your country, and when you have satisfied nature herself with the
                devotion of your life, then you may say that you have lived long enough. For what is
                the meaning of this very word “long” when applied to what has an end? And when the
                end comes, then all past pleasure is to be accounted as nothing, because there is
                none to come after it. Although that spirit of yours has never been content with
                this narrow space which nature has afforded us to live in; but has always been
                inflamed with a desire of immortality. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/> Nor is
                this to be considered your life which is contained in your body and in your breath.
                That,—that, I say, is your life, which will flourish in the memory of all ages;
                which posterity will cherish; which eternity itself will always preserve. This is
                what you must be subservient to; it is to this that you ought to display yourself;
                which indeed has long ago had many actions of yours to admire, and which now is
                expecting some which it may also praise. Unquestionably, posterity will stand amazed
                when they hear and read of your military commands,—of the provinces which you have
                added to the empire,—of the Rhine, of the ocean, of the Nile, all made subject to
                us,—of your countless battles, of your incredible victories, of your innumerable
                monuments and triumphs. <milestone n="29" unit="section"/> But unless this city is
                now securely settled by your counsels and by your institutions, your name will
                indeed be talked about very extensively, but your glory will have no secure abode,
                no sure home in which to repose. There will he also among those who shall be born
                hereafter, as there has been among us, great disputes, when some with <pb n="467"/>
                their praises will extol your exploits to the skies, and others, perhaps, will miss
                something in them,—and that, too, the most important thing of all,—unless you
                extinguish the conflagration of civil war by the safety of the country, so that the
                one shall appear to have been the effect of destiny and the other the work of your
                own practical wisdom. Have regard, then, to those judges who will judge you many
                ages afterwards, and who will very likely judge you more honestly than we can. For
                their judgment will be unbiased by affection or by ambition, and at the same time it
                will be untainted by hatred or by envy. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/> And even
                if it will be incapable of affecting you at that time, (which is the false opinion
                held by some men,) at all events, it concerns you now to conduct yourself in such a
                manner that no oblivion shall ever be able to obscure your praises. <milestone
                    n="10" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>The inclinations of the citizens have been very diverse, and their opinions much
                distracted; for we showed our variance, not only by our counsels and desires, but by
                arms and warlike operations. And there was obscurity in the designs of, and
                contention between, the most illustrious generals: many doubted which was the best
                side; many, what was expedient for themselves; many, what was becoming; some even
                felt uncertain as to what it was in their power to do. <milestone n="31"
                    unit="section"/> The republic has at last come to the end of this miserable and
                fatal war; that man has been victorious who has not allowed his animosities to be
                inflamed by good fortune, but who has mitigated them by the goodness of his
                disposition; and who did not consider all those with whom he was displeased
                deserving on that account of exile or of death. Arms were laid aside by some, were
                wrested from the hands of others. He is an ungrateful and an unjust citizen, who,
                when released from the danger of arms, still retains, as it were, an armed spirit,
                so that that man is better who fell in battle, who spent his life in the cause. For
                that which seems obstinacy to some people may appear constancy in others. But now
                all dissension is crushed by the arms and extinguished by the justice of the
                conqueror; <milestone n="32" unit="section"/> it only remains for all men for the
                future to be animated by one wish, all at least who have not only any wisdom at all,
                but who are at all in their senses. Unless you, O Caius Caesar, continue safe, and
                also in the same sentiments as you have displayed on previous occasions, and on this
                day most eminently, we cannot be safe either. <pb n="468"/> Wherefore we all—we who
                wish this constitution and these things around us to be safe—exhort and entreat you
                to take care of your own life, to consult your own safety; and we all promise to
                you, (that I may say also on behalf of others what I feel respecting myself,) since
                you think that there is still something concealed, against which it is necessary to
                guard,—we promise you, I say, not only our vigilance and our wariness also to assist
                in those precautions, but we promise to oppose our sides and our bodies as a shield
                against every danger which can threaten you. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="33" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But let my speech end with the same sentiment as it began. We all, O Caius Caesar,
                render you the greatest thanks, and we feel even deeper gratitude than we express;
                for all feel the same thing, as you might have perceived from the entreaties and
                tears of all. But because it is not necessary for all of them to stand up and say
                so, they wish it at all events that by me, who am forced in some degree to rise and
                speak, should he expressed both all that they feel, and all that is becoming, and
                all that I myself consider due to Marcus Marcellus, who is thus by you restored to
                this order, and to the Roman people, and to the republic. For I feel that all men
                are exulting, not in the safety of one individual alone, but in the general safety
                of all. <milestone n="34" unit="section"/> And as it becomes the greatest possible
                affection, such as I was always well known by all men to have towards him, so that I
                scarcely yielded to Caius Marcellus, his most excellent and affectionate brother and
                certainly to no one except him,—that love for him which I displayed by my
                solicitude, by my anxiety, and my exertions, as long as there was a doubt of his
                safety, I certainly ought to display at this present time, now that I am relieved
                from my great care and distress and misery on his account. </p>
            <p>Therefore, O Caius Caesar, I thank you, as if,—though I have not only been preserved
                in every sort of manner, but also loaded with distinctions by you,—still, by this
                action of yours, a crowning kindness of the greatest importance was added to the
                already innumerable benefits which you have reaped upon me, which I did not before
                believe were capable of any augmentation. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
