<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six - 28</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change> </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXVIII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p>
                        Successful operations against the Carthaginians in Spain, under Silanus,
Scipio's lieutenant, and L. Scipio, his brother; of Sulpicius and
Attalus, against Philip, king of Macedonia. Scipio finally vanquishes
the Carthaginians in Spain, and reduces that whole country; passes
over into Africa, forms an alliance with Syphax, king of Numidia;
represses and punishes a mutiny of a part of his army; concludes a
treaty of friendship with Masinissa; returns to Rome, and is elected
consul; solicits Africa for his province, which is opposed by Quintus
Fabius Maximus; is appointed governor of Sicily, with permission to
pass over into Africa.
                    </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    AT the time when Spain appeared to be relieved in proportion to the degree in which the weight of the war was removed into Italy, by the passage of Hasdrubal, another war sprang up there equal in magnitude to the former.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    At this juncture, the Romans and Carthaginians thus occupied Spain: Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, had retired quite to the ocean and Gades;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    the coast of our sea, and almost the whole of that part of Spain which lies eastward, was subject to Scipio and the Romans.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The new general, Hanno, who had passed over from Africa, to supply the place of the Barcine Hasdrubal, with a new army, and formed a junction with Mago, having in a short time armed a large number of men in Celtiberia, which lies in the midway between
                    <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    the two seas, Scipio sent Marcus Silanus against him, with no more than ten thousand infantry and five hundred horse.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Silanus, by marching with all the haste he could, (though the ruggedness of the roads, and narrow defiles obstructed with thick woods, which are
                    <pb n="1162" xml:id="p.1162"/>
                    very frequent in Spain, impeded him,) yet being guided by deserters from Celtiberia, natives of that place, reached the enemy, anticipating not only messengers but even all rumour of his coming.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    From the same source he ascertained, when they were about ten thousand paces from the enemy, that they had two camps, one on each side of the road in which they were marching; that the Celtiberians, a newly-raised army, in number above nine thousand, were on the left, and that the Carthaginian camp was stationed on the right.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The latter was secured and protected by outposts, watches, and every kind of regular military guard, while the former was disorderly and neglected, as belonging to barbarians, who were raw soldiers, and were under the less apprehension, because they were in their own country.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Silanus, concluding that this was the camp to be attacked first, ordered the troops to march as much as possible towards the left, lest he should be observed from any point by the Carthaginian outposts, and sending scouts in advance, pushed on towards the enemy at a rapid pace.
                </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    He was now about three thousand paces from the enemy, when as yet none of them had perceived him. The ground was covered with craggy places, and hills overgrown with bushes.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Here in a hollow valley, and on that account unexposed to the view, he ordered his men to sit down and take refreshment.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    In the mean time the scouts returned, confirming the statements of the deserters. Then the Romans, collecting their baggage in the centre, took arms, and marched to battle in regular array. They were a thousand paces off when they were descried by the enemy, when suddenly all began to be in a state of hurry and confusion. At the first shout and tumult, Mago quitted the camp and rode up at full speed.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    As there were in the Celtiberian army four thousand targeteers and two hundred horsemen, this regular legion, as it formed the flower of his troops, he stationed in the first line; the rest, composed of light-armed, he posted in reserve.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    While he was leading them out of the camp thus marshalled, the Romans discharged their javelins at them before they had scarcely cleared the rampart.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Spaniards stooped down to avoid the javelins thrown at them by the enemy, and then rose up to discharge their own in turn; which the Romans
                    <pb n="1163" xml:id="p.1163"/>
                    having received according to their custom in close array, with their shields firmly united, they then engaged foot to foot, and began to fight with their swords.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But the ruggedness of the ground, while it rendered ineffectual the agility of the Celtiberians, who were accustomed to a skirmishing kind of battle, was at the same time not unfavourable to the Romans, who were accustomed to a steady kind of
                    <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    fight, except that the narrow passes and the bushes, which grew here and there, broke their ranks, and they were compelled to engage one against one, and two against two, as if matched together.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The same circumstance which obstructed the enemy's flight, delivered them up, as it were, bound for slaughter.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And now when almost all the targeteers had been slain, the light-armed and the Carthaginians, who had come up to their assistance from the other camp, having been thrown into confusion, were put to the sword.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Not more than two thousand of the infantry, and all the cavalry, fled from the field with Mago before the battle was well begun. The other general, Hanno, was taken alive, together with those who came up when the battle was now decided.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Almost the whole of the cavalry and the veteran infantry, following Mago in his flight, came to Hasdrubal on the tenth day in the province of Gades. The newly-raised Celtiberian troops, stealing off to the neighbouring woods, fled thence to their homes.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    By this very seasonable victory, a stop was put to a war which was not by any means so considerable as that to which it would have grown, had the enemy been allowed, after having prevailed upon the Celtiberians to join them, to solicit other nations also to take up arms.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, therefore, having liberally bestowed the highest commendations on Silanus, and entertaining a hope that he might bring the war to a termination, if he did not impede it by a want of activity on his own part, proceeded into the remotest part of Spain against Hasdrubal.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The Carthaginian, who then happened to be encamped in Baetica, in order to prevent his allies from wavering in their allegiance, retired quite to the ocean and Gades, in a manner much more resembling a flight than a march.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    He was afraid, however, that while he kept his forces together, he should form the principal object of attack. Before he crossed the strait to Gades he sent them into different cities, that they might both
                    <pb n="1164" xml:id="p.1164"/>
                    provide for their own safety by the help of walls, and for that of the town by their arms.
                </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, seeing the enemy's forces thus distributed, and that to carry about his forces to each of the several cities would be rather tedious than important, marched his army back.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Not to leave all that country, however, to the Carthaginians, he sent his brother, Lucius Scipio, at the head of ten thousand foot and one thousand horse, to besiege the most important city of that quarter, called by the barbarians Orinx, and situated on the borders of the Milesians, a nation of Spain so called.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The soil is fertile, and even silver is dug out of it by the inhabitants.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This place served as a fort to Hasdrubal, from which he might make incursions on the inland states. Scipio encamped near the city. Before he formed his lines round it, he sent to the gates to sound the inclinations of the inhabitants, by a direct interview, and persuade them to make trial of the friendship of the Romans rather than of their power.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    As they answered nothing of a friendly nature, he threw a double trench and rampart round the place, dividing his army into three parts, in order that one division might assault it while the other two rested.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The first of these beginning the attack, a furious and doubtful contest ensued.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    It was by no means easy to approach and bring the ladders to the walls, on account of the weapons which fell upon them; and even of those persons who had raised them, some were thrown down with forks made for the purpose, others were in danger of being laid hold of by iron grapples, and dragged up hanging to the wall.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, seeing that the contest was equalized owing to the fewness of his party, and that the enemy, fighting from the wall, were superior to him, called off the first division and attacked them with the two others together.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    This so terrified the besieged, who were already fatigued with fighting with the former, that not only the townsmen forsook the walls in sudden flight, but the Carthaginian garrison, fearing that the town had been betrayed, also quitted their posts and collected themselves into a body.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Upon this the inhabitants began to be alarmed, lest if the enemy broke into the town they should kill all they met indiscriminately, Carthaginian or Spaniard.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    They therefore suddenly threw open the gates and rushed out of the
                    <pb n="1165" xml:id="p.1165"/>
                    town, holding their shields before them, lest any weapons should be cast at them from a distance, and stretching out to view their bare right hands, that it might be seen they had thrown away their swords.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Whether this was not observed, in consequence of the distance, or whether some deception was suspected, is not known; but an attack was made on the deserters, and they were put to death as a hostile force.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Through this gate the enemy marched into the city in battle-array. The other gates were cut through and broken down with axes and sledges; and as each horseman entered, he galloped off to seize the forum, as had been ordered. A body of veteran troops were also added to the horse to support them.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    The legionary troops spread themselves in every part of the city, but neither killed nor plundered any, except such as defended themselves with arms.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    All the Carthaginians were put under guard, with more than three hundred of the inhabitants, who had shut the gates.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    The rest had the town put into their hands, and their property restored. About two thousand of the enemy fell in the assault on this city, and not more than ninety of the Romans.
                </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    As the taking of this town was a source of great joy to those who effected it, as well as to the general and the rest of the army, so their approach to their camp also presented a splendid spectacle, on account of the immense crowd of captives they drove before them.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, having bestowed high commendations upon his brother, representing the capture of Orinx as equal in importance to the capture of Carthage by himself, led his forces back into hither Spain.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    He could not make an attempt on Gades, or pursue the army of Hasdrubal, now dispersed through all parts of the province, in consequence of the approach of winter.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore dismissed the legions into winter quarters, and sent his brother Lucius Scipio with Hanno, the enemy's general, and other distinguished prisoners, to Rome, while he retired himself to Tarraco.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    During the same year, the Roman fleet under Marcus Valerius Laevinus, the proconsul, sailing over from Sicily into Africa, devastated to a wide extent the fields about Utica and Carthage. They carried off plunder from the remotest borders of the Carthaginian territory around the very walls of Utica.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    On their return to Sicily they were met by
                    <pb n="1166" xml:id="p.1166"/>
                    a Carthaginian fleet of seventy ships of war, of which seventeen were taken and four sunk; the rest were dispersed and compelled to fly.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans, victorious both by land and sea, returned to Lilybaeum with immense booty of every kind. The ships of the enemy having thus been driven from the whole sea, large supplies of corn were conveyed to Rome.
                </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    In the beginning of the summer in which these events occurred, Publius Sulpicius, proconsul, and king Attalus, having passed the winter at Aegina, as before observed, united their fleets, consisting of twenty-three Roman quinqueremes and thirty-five belonging to the king, and proceeded to Lemnos.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Philip also, that he might be prepared for every kind of measure, whether it should be necessary to meet the enemy on land or sea, came down to the coast of Demetrias and appointed to his army a day on which to meet him at Larissa.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    On the news of the king's arrival, ambassadors from his allies came to Demetrias from all sides. For the Aetolians, inspirited both by their
                    <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    alliance with the Romans and the approach of king Attalus, were ravaging the neighbouring states;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    not only the Acarnanians, Bœotians, and Eubœans were very much alarmed, but the Achaeans also were kept in a state of terror, both by the hostile proceedings of the Aetolians, and also by Machanidas, tyrant of Lacedaemon, who had encamped at a short distance from the borders of the Argives.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    All of these stating the dangers which threatened their possessions, both by land and sea, entreated succour from the king.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Philip received accounts even from his own kingdom, that things were not in a state of tranquillity; that both Scerdiledus and Pleuratus were in motion, and that some of the Thracians, and particularly the Maedians, would certainly make incursions on the contiguous provinces of Macedonia, should the king be occupied with a distant war.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The Bœotians, indeed, and the people inhabiting the inland parts of Greece, told him that the Aetolians had obstructed by a ditch and rampart the straits of Thermopylae, where the road is very narrow and confined, in order to prevent their passing to the assistance of the allied states.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    So many disturbances arising on all hands were sufficient to awaken an inactive general. He dismissed the ambassadors, promising to assist them all according as opportunity and circum-
                    <pb n="1167" xml:id="p.1167"/>
                    stances allowed.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    For the present, he sent to Peparethus a body of troops to garrison the city, for this was the most urgent business, as information had been received thence that Attalus, crossing over to Lemnos, was devastating all the neighbouring country.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    He sent Polyphantas with a small detachment to Bœotia, and also Menippus, one of his guards, with one thousand targeteers (the target is not unlike the ordinary buckler) to Chalcis.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Five hundred Agrianians were added, that every part of the island might be secured. He went himself to Scotussa, and ordered the Macedonian soldiers to be removed thither from Larissa.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Here he heard that the Aetolians had been summoned to an assembly at Heraclea, and that king
                    <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/>
                    Attalus was to come and advise with them as to the conduct of the war.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Determining to interrupt this meeting by his sudden approach, he led his troops by forced marches to Heraclea, where he arrived just after the assembly had broken up. However, he destroyed the crops, which were nearly ripe, particularly those round the Aenian bay.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    He then marched back to Scotussa, and leaving there the main army, retired to Demetrias with the royal guards. In order to be prepared against every attempt of the enemy, he sent persons hence to Phocis, Eubœa, and Peparethus, to select elevated situations, from which fires lighted upon them might be seen from a distance.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    He fixed a watchtower on Tisaeum, a mountain whose summit is prodigiously high, in order that when the enemy made any attempt he might instantly receive intimation of it by means of fires lighted up at a distance.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman general and king Attalus then passed over from Peparethus to Nicaea, and thence sailed to Orcus, the first city of Eubœa, on the left as you proceed to Chalcis and the Euripus from the bay of Demetrias.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    It was agreed upon between Attalus and Sulpicius, that the Romans should attack the town on the side neat the sea, and the king's forces on the land side.
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Four days after the fleet arrived, they attacked the city. That time had been employed in private conferences with Plator, whom Philip had put in command of the place.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The city has two citadels, one overhanging the coasts, the other in the middle of the town, from which there is a subterraneous passage to the ocean, whose entrance next the sea is defended
                    <pb n="1168" xml:id="p.1168"/>
                    by a strong fortification, a tower five stories high.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Here the affair commenced with a most furious contest, the tower being furnished with all kinds of weapons, and engines and machines of every kind for the purpose of the assault having been landed from the ships.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    While the eyes and attention of all were turned to that quarter, Plator opened one of the gates and received the Romans into the citadel next the sea, which they instantly became masters of.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The inhabitants, driven thence, fled to the other citadel in the middle of the city; but there had been troops posted there to shut the gates against them; so that, being thus excluded, they were surrounded and either slain or made prisoners.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Meanwhile the Macedonian garrison stood under the wall of the citadel, formed into a compact body, neither confusedly attempting a retreat, nor obstinately engaging in a contest.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    These men Plator, after obtaining permission from Sulpicius, put on board ships and landed them at Demetrias in Phthiotis; he himself withdrew to Attalus.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Sulpicius, elated with the success at Oreum, gained with so much ease, proceeded to Chalcis with his victorious fleet, where the issue by no means answered his expectations.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The sea, which is wide on both sides, being here contracted into a narrow strait, might perhaps, at first view, exhibit the appearance of two harbours facing the two entrances of the Euripus.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It would be difficult to find a station more dangerous for shipping; for not only do the winds come down with great violence from the high mountains on each side, but the strait itself of the Euripus does not ebb and flow seven times a day at stated times, as is reported, but the current changing irregularly, like the wind, now this way now that, is hurried along like a torrent rolling headlong down a steep mountain, so that no quiet is given to vessels there day or night.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But not only did so perilous a station receive his ships, but the town was strong and impregnable, covered on one side by the sea, and very well fortified on the other towards the land, secured by a strong garrison, and above all, by the fidelity of the prefects and principal men, which was wavering and unsettled at Oreum.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Though the business had been rashly undertaken, the Roman still acted with prudence, in so far as he speedily gave up the attempt, after he had seen all the difficulties which sur-
                    <pb n="1169" xml:id="p.1169"/>
                    rounded him, that he might not waste time, and passed his fleet over from thence to Cynus in Locris, the port of the town of Opus, which is one mile distant from the sea.
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Philip had received notice of this from Oreum, by the signal fires; but through the treachery of Plator they were raised from the watch-tower at a later period.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    As he was not a match for the enemy's forces at sea, it was difficult for him to approach the island; and thus, by delay, the opportunity was lost. He moved with promptness to the assistance of Chalcis as soon as he received the signal. For although Chalcis is a city of the same island, yet it is separated from the continent by so narrow a strait, that they communicate by means of a bridge, and the approach to it is easier by land than by water.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Philip therefore, going from Demetrias to Scotussa, and setting out thence at the third watch, dislodged the guard, put to flight the Aetolians who kept the pass of Thermopylae, and drove the enemy in confusion to Heraclea, marching in one day to Elatia in Phocis, a distance of above sixty miles.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Almost on the same day the town of Opus was taken and plundered by Attalus. Sulpicius had given it up to the king because Oreum had been plundered a few days before by the Roman soldiers, the royal soldiers not having shared the booty.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman fleet having retired thither, Attalus, who was not aware of Philip's approach, wasted time in levying contributions from the principal inhabitants, and so sudden was
                    <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    his coming, that had he not been descried by some Cretans, who happened to go farther from the town than usual in quest of forage, he might have been surprised.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    He fled hastily to the sea and his ships, without arms, and in the greatest disorder. Just as they were putting off from the land Philip arrived, and even from the shore created much alarm among the mariners.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He returned thence to Opus, accusing both gods and men, because he had lost an opportunity of so great importance, almost snatched from his hands.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    He also reproached the Opuntians with the like anger, because they had, immediately on sight of the enemy, made almost a voluntary surrender, though they might have prolonged the siege till his arrival. Having settled affairs at Opus, he proceeded thence to Thronium. Attalus, too, at first retired from Oreum; but there receiving intelligence that Prusias, king of Bithynia, had invaded his
                    <pb n="1170" xml:id="p.1170"/>
                    kingdom, he withdrew his attention from the Romans and the Aetolian war, and passed over into Asia.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Sulpicius also withdrew his fleet to Aegina, from whence he had set out in the beginning of spring. Philip took Thronium with as little difficulty as Attalus had at Opus.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    It was inhabited by foreigners, fugitives from Thebes in Phthiotis, who, on the capture of their own town by Philip, had fled to the protection of the Aetolians, and received from them a city as a settlement which had been laid waste and desolated in a former war by the same Philip.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Having recovered Thronium, as has been a little before mentioned, he set out thence; and having taken Tritonos and Drymae, inconsiderable towns of Doris, he came thence to Elatia, where he had ordered the ambassadors of Ptolemy and the Rhodians to wait for him.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    While consulting there as to the best method of bringing the Aetolian war to a conclusion, (for these ambassadors attended the late council of the Romans and Aetolians at Heraclea,) intelligence is brought that Machanidas intended to attack the Elians while busied in preparing for the celebration of the Olympic games.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Thinking it his duty to prevent such an attempt, he dismissed the ambassadors with a gracious answer to the effect, that he had neither caused the war, nor would he
                    <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/>
                    be any obstacle to the restoration of peace, if it should be possible on equitable and honourable terms;
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    then marching quickly through Bœotia he came down from Megara, and thence to Corinth, where receiving supplies of provisions, he went to Phlius and Pheneus. And now, when he had proceeded as far as Heraea, having received intelligence that Machanidas, terrified at the news of
                    <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/>
                    his approach, had retreated to Lacedaemon, he betook himself to Aegium, where the Achaeans were assembled in council, expecting at the same time to meet there a Carthaginian fleet, which he had sent for, in order that he might accomplish something by sea.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    But the Carthaginians had left a few days before, and were gone to the Oxean islands; and thence, hearing that the Romans and Attalus had left Oreum, to the harbours of the Acarnanians, for they feared that it was intended to attack them, and that they would be overpowered while within the straits of Rhium, which is the name of the entrance of the Corinthian bay.
                </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Philip was grieved and vexed when he reflected, that
                    <pb n="1171" xml:id="p.1171"/>
                    though he proceeded with the utmost speed on all occasions, yet he had not come up in time to accomplish any one object, and that fortune had frustrated his activity by snatching away every advantage from before his eyes.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    In the assembly, however, concealing his chagrin, he discoursed with elated spirits, calling gods and men to witness, that
                    <quote>
                        he had never been wanting at any time or place, so as not to repair instantly wherever the enemy's arms resounded, but that it was difficult to calculate whether the war was carried on more boldly by him or more pusillanimously by the enemy.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Such was the manner in which Attalus had slipped out of his hands from Opus; Sulpicius from Chalcis; and so, within these few days, Machanidas.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        That flight, however, was not always successful; and that that should not be esteemed a difficult war in which victory would be certain if the enemy could be brought to a regular engagement.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        He had already obtained one very great advantage, which was a confession on the part of the enemy themselves, that they were not a match for him; and in a short time,
                    </quote>
                    he said,
                    <quote>
                        he would be in possession of undoubted victory;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        for that he would engage with him with a result no better than their expectations.
                    </quote>
                    The allies listened to the king with great satisfaction.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    He then gave up to the Achaeans Heraera and Triphylia. Aliphera he restored to the Megalopolitans, they having brought satisfactory proof that it belonged to their territories.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Then having received some ships from the Achaeans, three quadriremes and three biremes, he sailed to Anticyra, whence with seven quinqueremes and more than twenty barks, which he had sent to the bay of Corinth
                    <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    to join the Carthaginian fleet, he proceeded to Erythrae, a town of the Aetolians near Eupalium, where he made a descent.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    He was not unobserved by the Aetolians; for all who were either in the fields or in the neighbouring forts of Potidania and Apollonia, fled to the woods and mountains. The cattle which they could not drive off in their haste they seized and put on board.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    He sent Nicias, praetor of the Achaeans, to Aegium with these and the other boot; and then going to Corinth, ordered his army to march by land through Bœotia, while he himself, sailing from Cenchrea along the coast of Attica, round the promontory of Sunium, reached Chalcis, having passed almost through the midst of the enemy's fleet.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    After commending in the highest terms their fidelity
                    <pb n="1172" xml:id="p.1172"/>
                    and bravery, as neither fear nor hope had influenced their minds, and after exhorting them to show the same fidelity in maintaining the alliance, he sailed to Oreum;
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    and having placed such of the chief inhabitants as chose to fly, rather than surrender to the Romans, in the command of the city and the direction of affairs, he sailed over from Eubœa to Demetrias, from which place he at first set out to succour his allies.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    After this, having laid the keels of one hundred ships of war at Cassandria, and collected a large number of ship carpenters for the completion of that business, and as both the departure of Attalus and the seasonable assistance he had brought to his allies had tranquillized affairs in Greece, he retired into his own dominions, in order to make war upon the Dardanians.
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Just at the close of the summer during which these operations were carried on in Greece, when Quintus Fabius, son of Maximus, ambassador from Marcus Livius the consul, brought a message to Rome to the senate, to the effect, that the consul considered that Lucius Portius with his legions formed a sufficient protection for the province, that he
                    <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    might himself retire thence, and that the consular army might be withdrawn, the fathers directed that not only Livius should return to the city, but also his colleague, Caius Claudius.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The only difference made between them in the decree was, that they ordered the army of Marcus Livius to be led back, and the legions of Nero to remain in their province opposed to Hannibal.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The consuls agreed between themselves by letter, that as they had conducted the affairs of the commonwealth with unanimity, they should arrive at the city at the same time, though they came from different quarters. He who arrived first at Praeneste was enjoined to wait there for his colleague.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    It so happened that they both came to Praeneste on the same day, and thence, sending a proclamation before them, directing that there should be a full attendance of the senate at the temple of Bellona, three days after, they came up to the city, when they were met by the whole body of the inhabitants.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Not only did the whole body pour around them and salute them, but each person individually, desiring to touch the victorious right hands of the consuls, some congratulated them, while others thanked them because by their services the state had been preserved.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    In the senate, when,
                    <pb n="1173" xml:id="p.1173"/>
                    having made a recital of their services according to the custom observed by all generals, they had requested, that
                    <quote>
                        in consideration of the brave and successful conduct of the affairs of the commonwealth, honours should be paid to the immortal gods, and they themselves enter the city in triumph;
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    the fathers replied, that
                    <quote>
                        they most willingly decreed those things which they requested in gratitude to the gods in the first instance, and, next to them, to the consuls.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    A supplication in the name of both, and a triumph to both of them, having been decreed, lest after having carried on the war with entire unanimity they should have a separate triumph, they made the following agreement;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    that
                    <quote>
                        since both the service had been performed in the province of Marcus Livius, and he was in possession of the command on the day on which the battle was fought, and further, that as the army of Livius had been withdrawn and had come to Rome, while Nero's could not be withdrawn from the province, Marcus Livius should enter the city in a four-horse chariot and followed by the soldiers; Caius Claudius on horseback without soldiers.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    This plan of associating the generals in the triumph increased the glory of both, but particularly of him who had yielded to his colleague in the honours he received, as much as he surpassed him in merit.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The people said, that
                    <quote>
                        the general on horseback had traversed the whole length of Italy in the space of six days, and had fought a pitched battle with Hasdrubal in Gaul, on the very day on which Hannibal supposed that he was occupying a camp pitched in Apulia to oppose him.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        That thus one consul, acting in defence of either extremity of Italy against two leaders, had opposed against one his skill, against the other his person.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        That the name of Nero had been sufficient to confine Hannibal within his camp, while with regard to Hasdrubal, by what, but his arrival, had he been overwhelmed and annihilated?
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        The other consul might move along raised aloft in a chariot, drawn if he pleased by a number of horses, but that the real triumph was his who was conveyed by one horse;
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        and that Nero, though he should go on foot, would be immortalized, whether on account of the glory he had acquired in the war, or the contempt he had shown for it in the triumph.
                    </quote>
                    Such continual expressions of the spectators attended Nero all the way to the Capitol.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The money they brought into the treasury was three hundred
                    <pb n="1174" xml:id="p.1174"/>
                    thousand sesterces, with eighty thousand asses of brass. Marcus Livius distributed among the soldiers fifty-six asses each.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Caius Claudius promised the same sum to his absent troops when he returned to the army. It was observed that more verses were written by the soldiery upon Caius Claudius in their jocular style, than upon their own consul;
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    that the horsemen highly extolled Lucius Veturius and Quintus Caecilius, lieutenant-generals, and exhorted the commons to create them consuls for the ensuing year;
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    that the consuls added their authority to the recommendation of the knights, relating in the public assembly the following day with what courage and fidelity their two lieutenant-generals in particular had served them.
                </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    When the time for the elections approached, and it was resolved that it should be held by a dictator, the consul Caius Claudius nominated as dictator his colleague Marcus Livius, who appointed Quintus Caecilius his master of the horse.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Veturius and Quintus Caecilius were created consuls by Marcus Livius the dictator, the latter being then master of the horse.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    After this the election of praetors was held. The persons appointed were, Caius Servilius, Marcus Caecilius Metellus, Titus Claudius Asellus, and Quintus Mamilius Turinus, who was at that time plebeian aedile.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    When the elections were finished, the dictator, having abdicated his office and dismissed his army, set out for his province of Etruria, according to a
                    <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    decree of the senate, to make inquiry what states of the Tuscans and Umbrians had formed schemes of revolt from the Romans to Hasdrudal at the time of his approach, and what states had assisted him with auxiliaries, provisions, or succours of any kind. Such were the transactions this year at home and abroad.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman games were thrice repeated in full by the curule aediles, Cneius Servilius Caepio and Servius Cornelius Lentulus.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    In the same manner the plebeian games also were once repeated entire by the plebeian aediles, Manius Pomponius Matho and Quintus Mamilius Thurinus.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    In the thirteenth year of the Punic war, when Lucius Veturius Philo and Quintus Caecilius Metellus were consuls, Bruttium was assigned to both of them, as their province, to carry on the war with Hannibal.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The praetors then cast lots for their provinces: Marcus Caecilius Metellus had the city
                    <pb n="1175" xml:id="p.1175"/>
                    jurisdiction; Quintus Mamilius, the foreign; Caius Servilius, Sicily; Tiberius Claudius, Sardinia. The armies were distributed thus:
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    to one of the consuls was given the army which Caius Claudius the consul of the former year, to the other that which Quintus Claudius the proprietor, had commanded, consisting of two legions each.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    It was decreed that Marcus Livius, proconsul, who was continued in command for the year, should take the two legions of volunteer slaves from Caius Terentius
                    <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                    the propraetor, and that Quintus Mamilius, transferring his judicial business to his colleague, should occupy Gaul with the army which Lucius Porcius, the praetor, had commanded, with orders to lay waste the lands of those Gauls who had revolted to the Carthaginians on the approach of Hasdrubal.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The protection of Sicily was assigned to Caius Servilius with the two legions which fought at Cannae, in the same manner as Caius Mamilius had held it.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    The old army which Aulus Hostilius had commanded was conveyed out of Sardinia, and the consuls enlisted a new legion, which Tiberius Claudius might take over with him.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Quintus Claudius and Caius Hostilius Tubulus were continued in command for a year, that the former might hold Tarentum as his province, the latter, Capua.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Marcus Valerius, the proconsul, to whom had been committed the protection of the sea-coast round Sicily, was ordered to deliver thirty ships to Caius Servilius, and return to the city with all the rest of the fleet.
                </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    In a state where the greatest anxiety prevailed, in consequence of the very critical situation in which the war stood, and where all events, prosperous or adverse, were attributed to the interposition of the gods, accounts of many prodigies were received;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    that the temple of Jupiter at Tarracina, and that of Mater Matuta at Satricum, had been struck by lightning. The people of Satricum were no less terrified by two snakes gliding into the temple of Jupiter by the very doors.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    A report was brought from Antium, that bloody ears of corn had been seen by the reapers. At Caere a pig with two heads had been littered, and a lamb yeaned which was both male and female.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Intelligence was brought that two suns ha been seen at Alba, and that light had suddenly appeared luring night at Fregellae. An ox was reported to have spoken in the Roman territory.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    A copious perspiration was said to
                    <pb n="1176" xml:id="p.1176"/>
                    have exuded from the altar of Neptune, in the Flaminian circus; and the temples of Ceres, Safety, and Quirinus were said to have been struck by lightning.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The consuls were directed to expiate these prodigies with victims of the larger sort, and to make a supplication for one day. These things were executed according to a decree of the senate. The extinction of the fire in the temple of Vesta struck more terror upon the minds of men than all the prodigies which were reported from abroad, or seen at home; and the vestal, who had the guarding of it for that night, was scourged by the command of Publius Licinius the pontiff.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Although this event was not appointed by the gods as a portent, but had happened through human neglect, yet it was thought proper that it should be expiated with victims of the larger sort, and that a supplication should be made at the temple of Vesta.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Before the consuls set out for the campaign, they were cautioned by the senate to take care that the common people should be brought back into the country; for since, through the goodness of the gods, the war was removed from the city of Rome and Latium, the country might be inhabited without fear. That it was most inconsistent that greater care should be taken in cultivating Sicily than Italy.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But it was a matter by no means easy for the people, the free labourers having been cut off by war, and there being a scarcity of slaves, their cattle having been carried off as booty, and the farmhouses pulled down or burnt.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    A large number, however, compelled by the authority of the consuls, returned into the country. The mention of this affair had been occasioned by ambassadors of Placentia and Cremona, who complained that their lands were being invaded and laid waste by the neighbouring Gauls; that a large portion of their settlers had dispersed; that their cities were thinly inhabited, and their lands devastated and deserted.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Mamilius the praetor was charged with the protection of the colonies from the enemy. The consuls, in conformity with a decree of the senate, issued an edict that all who were citizens of Cremona and Placentia should return to those colonies before a certain day; after which, in the beginning of spring, they set out for the campaign.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Quintus Caecilius, the consul, received the army from Caius Nero; Lucius Veturius received his from Quintus Claudius the proprietor, filling it up with new-
                    <pb n="1177" xml:id="p.1177"/>
                    raised soldiers, whom he had himself enlisted.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The consuls marched their army into the territory of Consentia, and devastating the country on all hands, when the troops were loaded with plunder, they were thrown into such confusion by some Bruttians and Numidian spearmen, who attacked them in a narrow defile, that not only the booty but the troops were in danger.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    There was more of confusion, however, than fighting; and sending the booty in advance, the legions themselves also escaped into a place free from danger.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Proceeding thence into Lucania, the whole of that people returned, without a contest, into subjection to the Roman people.
                </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    No action with Hannibal took place this year; for neither did he present himself after the public and personal calamity so recently inflicted, and the Romans did not provoke him while he remained quiet, such power did they consider that single general possessed, though every thing else around him was falling into ruin.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed I know not whether he was not more deserving of admiration in adversity than in prosperity;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    inasmuch as though he carried on a war in the territory of enemies through a period of thirteen years, at so great a distance from home, with varying success, and with an army not composed of his own countrymen, but made up of the offscouring of all nations, without communion of laws, customs, or language, different in their appearance, their dress, their arms, their religious ceremonies and observances, and I had almost said, their gods;
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    yet he so effectually united them by some one bond, that no disturbance ever arose either among the soldiers themselves, or between them and their general, though he often wanted money to pay them, and provisions, as being in
                    <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    a hostile country, through want of which, in the former Punic war, many dreadful transactions had occurred between the generals and their soldiers.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But after the destruction of Hasdrubal and his army, in which all hopes of victory had been treasured up; and after retiring from the possession of every other part of Italy by withdrawing into Bruttium, one corner of it; to whom does it not appear wonderful that no disturbance arose in the camp?
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For to other circumstances this also was added, that he had no hope of subsisting his army, except from the lands of Bruttium, which, though they were all cultivated, would be very
                    <pb n="1178" xml:id="p.1178"/>
                    insufficient for the maintenance of so large an army.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, many of the youth were drawn off from the cultivation of the fields, and engaged in the war; and a custom also prevailed among the people of that nation, grafted on a naturally depraved inclination, of carrying on a predatory kind of warfare.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Nor did he receive any supplies from home, where they were anxious about the retention of Spain, as if every thing was going on prosperously in Italy. In Spain the state of affairs was in one respect similar, but in another widely different;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    similar in that the Carthaginians, having been defeated with the loss of their general, had been driven to the remotest coast of that country, even to the ocean;
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    but different, because Spain, both from the nature of the country and the genius of its inhabitants, was better adapted not only than Italy, but than any other part of the world, for renewing a war.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    And accordingly, therefore, though this was the first of the provinces on the continent which the Romans entered, it was the last which was at length reduced, in the present age, under the conduct and auspices of Augustus Caesar.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Here Hasdrubal, son of Gisco, the greatest and most renowned general concerned in the war, next to the Barcine family, returning from Gades, and encouraged in his hopes of reviving the war by Mago, son of Hamilcar, by means of levies made throughout the Farther Spain, armed as many as fifty thousand foot and four thousand five hundred horse.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    With regard to his mounted force, authors are pretty much agreed, but some state that seventy thousand infantry were led to the city Silpia.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Here the two Carthaginian generals sat down on open plains, with a determination not to avoid a battle.
                </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    When Scipio received an account of the collection of so large an army, he felt convinced that he would not be a match for so great a multitude with the Roman legions only, without making a show at least of the auxiliary troops of the barbarians;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    at the same time that he did not think it right that they should form so large a portion of his force as to occasion important consequences if they should change sides, which had brought ruin upon his father and his uncle.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, sending forward Silanus to Colca, who was sovereign of twenty-eight towns, to receive from him the infantry and cavalry, which he promised to enlist during the
                    <pb n="1179" xml:id="p.1179"/>
                    winter, he himself set out from Tarraco;
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    and collecting small bodies of auxiliaries from his allies, who lay near his road as he proceeded, he came to Castulo.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    To this place Silanus led the auxiliaries, consisting of three thousand infantry and five hundred horse. Thence he advanced to the city of Baecula, with his entire army of countrymen and allies, foot and horse, amounting to forty-five thousand.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Mago and Masinissa attacked them with the whole body of their cavalry while forming their camp, and would have dispersed those engaged in the works, had not a party of horse, concealed by Scipio behind an eminence conveniently situated for the purpose, unexpectedly charged them when rushing on to
                    <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    the attack, and, ere the battle was well begun, routed all the most forward, both those who had advanced nearest the rampart, and those who were foremost in charging the very workmen. With the rest of the troops who came up with their standards, and in order of march, the contest lasted longer, and was for a considerable time doubtful.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But when first the light cohorts from the outposts, and then the troops withdrawn from the works and ordered to take arms, came up, being more numerous than those which had been engaged, and fresh while they were fatigued, and now a large body of armed troops rushed from the camp to the battle, the Carthaginians and Numidians at once turned their backs.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    At first they moved off in troops without breaking their ranks, through fear or precipitation; but afterwards, when the Romans pressed furiously upon their rear, and they were unable to bear the violence of their attack, then at length, utterly regardless of order, they fled precipitately in every direction, as suited each man's convenience.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And although, in consequence of this battle, the spirits of the Romans were considerably raised, and those of the enemy depressed, yet, for several days following, the horsemen and light-armed troops never ceased from skirmishes.
                </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    After having made sufficient trial of their strength in these slight engagements, Hasdrubal first led out his forces for battle, and then the Romans also advanced.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But both the armies stood drawn up before their ramparts; and as neither party began the attack, and the sun was now going down, the Carthaginian first, and then the Roman, led back his troops into the camp. The same occurred for several days. The
                    <pb n="1180" xml:id="p.1180"/>
                    Carthaginian was always the first to lead out his troops into the field, and the first to give the signal for retiring, when they were weary with standing.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Neither party sallied from their posts, nor was a weapon discharged, or a word uttered.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    On one side the Romans occupied the centre, on the other, the Carthaginians and Africans together; the allies occupied the wings, which were composed of Spaniards on both sides. The elephants which stood before the Carthaginian line, appeared at a distance like castles.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    It was now commonly talked of in both camps, that they would fight in the order in which they had stood when drawn up, and that their centres, composed of Romans and Carthaginians, who were the principals in the war, would engage with equal courage and strength.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    When Scipio perceived that this was firmly believed, he studiously altered all his arrangements against the day on which he intended to fight.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    He issued orders through the camp at evening, that the men and horses should be refreshed and fed before daylight, and that the horsemen, armed themselves, should keep their horses bridled and saddled. When it was scarcely yet daylight, he sent all his cavalry, with the light troops, against the Carthaginian outposts, and then without delay advanced himself, at
                    <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    the head of the heavy body of the legions, having strengthened his wings with Roman
                    <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    soldiers, and placed the allies in the centre, contrary to the full anticipations of his own men and of the enemy.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Hasdrubal, alarmed by the shout of the cavalry, sprang out of his tent, and, perceiving a tumult before the rampart, and his own troops in a state of hurry and confusion, the standards of the legions gleaming at a distance, and the plain filled with the enemy, immediately sent out the whole body of his cavalry against the horsemen of the enemy;
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    marching himself out of the camp, at the head of the infantry, without departing at all from the usual arrangement in forming his line.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The battle between the cavalry had continued for a long time doubtful; nor could they decide it themselves, because, when repulsed, which was the case in a manner alternately, they had a safe retreat upon the line of infantry.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    But when the armies were not more than five hundred paces distant from each other, Scipio, sounding a retreat and opening his files, received into the midst of them the whole body of his cavalry and light-armed troops;
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    and dividing them into
                    <pb n="1181" xml:id="p.1181"/>
                    two parts, placed them in reserve behind the wings. After this, when it was now time to commence the battle, he ordered the Spaniards, who formed the centre, to advance at a slow pace;
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    he himself sent a messenger from the right wing, for that he commanded, to Silanus and Marcius to extend the wing on the left in the same manner as they should see him extend
                    <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/>
                    that on the right, and engage the enemy with the light-armed of the horse and foot, before the two centres could meet.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The wings being thus extended, they advanced against the enemy at a rapid pace, with three cohorts of infantry, and three troops of horse, each with the addition of skirmishers, the rest following them in an oblique line.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    There was a depression in the centre of the line, because the battalions of the Spaniards advanced slower than the rest, and the wings had already encountered the enemy, when the veteran Carthaginians and Africans had not yet come within distance to discharge their darts;
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    nor dared they run in different directions to the wings to assist them when fighting, lest they should expose their centre to the enemy approaching over against them.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    The wings were hard pressed, by a twofold attack; the cavalry, the light-armed, and the skirmishers, wheeling round, charged their flanks, while the cohorts pressed them hard in front, in order to separate the wings from the rest of the line.
                </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The battle was now extremely unequal in every part, both because an irregular band of Balearians and raw Spaniards were opposed to Roman and Latin soldiers, and further, because, as
                    <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    the day was now getting on, Hasdrubal's troops began to grow languid, having been dispirited by the alarm in the morning, and compelled to go out hastily into the field, without refreshing themselves with food.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio had designedly spun out the day, in order that the battle might take place at a late hour; for it was not until the seventh hour that the battalions of infantry charged the wings.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    It was considerably later before the battle reached the centres, so that the heat from the meridian sun, and the fatigue of standing under arms, together with hunger and thirst, enfeebled their bodies before they engaged the enemy. Thus they stood still, supporting themselves upon their shields.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In addition to their other misfortunes, the elephants too, ter-
                    <pb n="1182" xml:id="p.1182"/>
                    rified at the tumultuous kind of attack of the cavalry, the skirmishers, and the light-armed, had transferred themselves from the wings to the centre.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Fatigued therefore in mind and body, they gave ground, preserving their ranks, however, just as though the army were retreating entire at the command of their general. But when the victors, perceiving that the enemy had given way, charged them on all sides
                    <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    with increased vehemence on that very account, so that the shock could hardly be sustained, though Hasdrubal endeavoured to stop them and hinder them from retiring, vociferating,
                    <quote>
                        that there were hills on their rear, and a safe refuge if they would retreat without precipitation;
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    yet, fear getting the better of their sense of shame, and all those who
                    <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    were nearest the enemy giving way, they immediately turned their backs, and all gave themselves up to disorderly flight.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The first place they halted at was the foot of the hills, where they endeavoured to recall the soldiers to their ranks, the Romans hesitating to advance their line up the opposite steep; but afterwards, when they saw them push on briskly, renewing their flight, they were driven into their camp in extreme alarm.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Nor were the Romans far from the rampart; and such was their impetuosity, that they would have taken their camp had not so violent a shower of rain suddenly poured down, while, as is usually the case, the solar rays darted with the greatest intensity between the clouds surcharged with water, that the victors with difficulty returned to their camp. Some were even deterred, by superstition, from making any further attempts that day.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Though night and the rain invited the Carthaginians to take necessary rest, yet, as their fears and the danger would not allow them to
                    <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    delay, as it was expected that the enemy would assault their camp as soon as it was light, they raised their rampart by stones collected from the neighbouring valleys around them on all sides, with the determination to defend themselves by works, since there was but little protection in their arms.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    But the desertion of their allies made it appear safer to fly than stay. Attanes, prince of the Turdetani, began this revolt; he deserted at the head of a numerous band of his countrymen.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Then two fortified towns, together with their garrisons, were delivered up by their praefects to the Romans.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    And, lest the evil should
                    <pb n="1183" xml:id="p.1183"/>
                    spread more widely, now that the disposition to revolt from the Carthaginians had evinced itself in one instance, Hasdrubal decamped during the silence of the ensuing night.
                </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The troops in the outposts having brought word, as soon as it was light, that the enemy had departed, Scipio, despatching his cavalry in advance, ordered the army to move forward;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and so rapidly were they led, that had they directly followed the track of the fugitives, they would certainly have overtaken them; but they trusted to the report of their guides, that there was a shorter cut to the river Baetis, where they might attack them while crossing it.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Hasdrubal, being precluded from passing the river, turned his course to the ocean; and they now advanced in disorder and in the manner of fugitives, so that the Roman legions were left considerably behind.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The cavalry and light-armed, attacking sometimes their rear, and sometimes their flank, harassed and delayed them;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    and as they were obliged to halt, in consequence of these frequent annoyances, and engaged sometimes the cavalry, at other times the skirmishers and the auxiliary infantry, the legions came up.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    After this it was no longer a fight, but a butchering as of cattle, till the general himself, who was the first to run away, made his escape to the neighbouring hills with about six thousand men half armed; the rest were slain or made prisoners.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Carthaginians hastily fortified an irregular camp on the highest eminence, and from thence they defended themselves without difficulty, the enemy failing in his attempt to get at them, from the difficulty of the ascent. But a siege in a place bare and affording no means of subsistence, was hardly to be supported, even for a few days; the troops therefore deserted to the enemy.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    At last the general himself, having procured some ships, for the sea was not at a great distance, left his army by night and effected his escape to Gades.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, having heard of the flight of the general of the enemy, left ten thousand foot and one thousand cavalry for Silanus to carry on the siege of the camp, and returned to Tarraco with the rest of the troops,
                    <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                    after a march of seventy days, during which he took cognizance of the causes of the petty princes and states, in order that rewards might be conferred according to a just estimate of their merits.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    After his departure, Masinissa, having held a private conference with Silanus, passed over into Africa with a few of his countrymen, in order
                    <pb n="1184" xml:id="p.1184"/>
                    that he might induce his nation also to acquiesce in his new designs.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The cause of this sudden change was not so evident at the time, as the proof was convincing which was afforded by his subsequent fidelity, preserved to extreme old age, that he did not on this occasion act without reasonable grounds. Mago went to Gades in the ships which had been sent back by Hasdrubal.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Of the rest of the troops thus abandoned by their generals, some deserted and others betook themselves to flight, and in this manner were dispersed through the neighbouring states. There was no body of them considerable either for numbers or strength.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Such were, as near as possible, the circumstances under which the Carthaginians were driven out of Spain, under the conduct and auspices of Publius Scipio, in the thirteenth year from the commencement of the war, and the fifth from the time that Publius Scipio received the province and the army.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Not long after, Silanus returned to Tarraco to Scipio, with information that the war was at an end.
                </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Scipio was sent to Rome to convey the news of the reduction of Spain, and with him a number of distinguished captives.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    While everybody else extolled this achievement as an event in the highest degree joyful and glorious, yet the author of it alone, whose valour was such that he never thought he had achieved enough, and whose search for true glory was insatiable, considered the reduction of Spain as affording
                    <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    but a faint idea of the hopes which his aspiring mind had conceived.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He now directed his view to Africa and Great Carthage, and the glorious termination of the war, as redounding to his honour, and giving lustre to his name.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Judging it therefore to be now necessary to pave the way to his object, and to conciliate the friendship of kings and nations, he resolved first to sound the disposition of Syphax, king of the Masaesylians, a nation bordering on the Moors, and lying for the most part over-against that quarter of Spain in which New Carthage is situated.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The king was at the present juncture in league with the Carthaginians;
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    and Scipio, concluding that he would not hold it as more binding and sacred than was customary with barbarians, sent Caius Laelius as envoy to him with presents.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The barbarian, delighted with these, and seeing that the Roman cause was then successful in every quarter, but that the Carthaginians were unfortunate
                    <pb n="1185" xml:id="p.1185"/>
                    in Italy, and no longer existed in Spain, consented to accept the friendship of the Romans, but refused to give or receive a solemn ratification of it except the Roman general himself were present in person.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    This being the case, Laelius returned to Scipio, having received from the king merely an assurance of a safe journey.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    To one desirous of getting a footing in Africa, Syphax was of great importance, as he was the most powerful king in that country, had already had experience of the Carthaginians themselves in war, and the boundaries of his dominions lay very conveniently with respect to Spain, from which they are separated by a narrow strait.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, therefore, considering it an object of sufficient importance to warrant his attempting it, notwithstanding the greatness of the danger which attended it, since he could not effect it otherwise, left for the protection of Spain Lucius Marcius at Tarraco, and Marcus Silanus at New Carthage, to which place he had gone on foot by long marches;
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    and setting out himself in company with Caius Laelius, with two quinqueremes from Carthage, passed over into Africa, working the vessels with oars for the greatest part of the voyage, in consequence of the calmness of the sea, though sometimes they were assisted by a gentle breeze.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    It so happened, that just at that time Hasdrubal, having been driven out of Spain, had entered the harbour with seven triremes, and having cast anchor was mooring his ships.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    The sight of two quinqueremes, which it was the firm opinion of everybody belonged to the enemy, and might be overpowered by superior numbers before they entered the harbour, produced no other effect than a tumult and confusion among the soldiers and sailors, who endeavoured to no purpose to get their arms and ships ready;
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    for their sails, impelled by a somewhat brisker gale from the sea, brought the quinqueremes into the harbour before the Carthaginians weighed their anchors, and no one dared make any further stir now that they were in the king's harbour.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Thus Hasdrubal, who landed first, and Scipio and Laelius, who landed soon after, proceeded to the king.
                </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Syphax considered it highly honourable to him, as it really was, that generals of the two most powerful people of the age should come to him on the same day to solicit peace and friendship with him.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    He invited them both to become his guests; and, as it was the will of fortune that they should be
                    <pb n="1186" xml:id="p.1186"/>
                    under one roof, and under the protection of the same household gods, he endeavoured to bring them together to a conference, in order to put an end to the difference between them;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    when Scipio declared, that there was no personal enmity between the Carthaginian and himself which he might do away with by a conference, and that he could not transact any business relating to the republic with an enemy without the command of the senate.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But the king being earnest in his endeavours to persuade him to come to the same entertainment, lest one of his guests should appear to be excluded, he did not withhold his assent.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    They supped together at the king's table, and Scipio and Hasdrubal even sat at meat on the same couch, because it was the king's pleasure.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    So courteous was the manner of Scipio, so naturally happy and universal was his genius, that by his conversation he gained the esteem not only of Syphax, a barbarian, and unused to Roman manners, but even of a most inveterate enemy, who openly avowed, that
                    <quote>
                        he
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                        appeared to him more to be admired for the qualities he displayed on a personal interview with him, than for his exploits in war, and that he had no doubt that Syphax and his kingdom were already at the disposal of the
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        Romans, such were the abilities that man possessed for gaining the esteem of others.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        That it, therefore, was incumbent upon the Carthaginians not more to inquire by what means they had lost Spain, than to consider how they might retain possession of Africa.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        That it was not from a desire to visit foreign countries, or to roam about delightful coasts, that so great a Roman captain, leaving a recently subdued province, and his armies, had crossed over into Africa with only two ships, entering an enemy's territory, and committing himself to the untried honour of the king, but in pursuance of a hope he had conceived of subduing Africa.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        That it had been long the object of his anxious solicitude, and had drawn from him open expressions of his indignation, that Scipio was not carrying on war in Africa in the same way as Hannibal was in Italy.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, having formed a league with Syphax, set out from Africa, and, after having been tossed about during his voyage by variable and generally tempestuous winds, made the port of New Carthage on the fourth day.
                </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    As Spain was undisturbed by a Carthaginian war, so it was evident that some of the states remained quiet more
                    <pb n="1187" xml:id="p.1187"/>
                    from fear, arising from a consciousness of demerit, than from sincere attachment. The most remarkable of them, both for their greatness and guilt, were Illiturgi and Castulo.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Castulo had been in alliance with the Romans when in prosperity, but had revolted to the Carthaginians after the destruction of the Scipios and their armies. The Illiturgians, by betraying and putting to death those who fled thither after that calamity, had added villany to revolt.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    It would have been more deserved than expedient to have executed severe vengeance upon these people on his first arrival, while the affairs of Spain were in an uncertain state;
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    but now, when all was tranquil, as the time for visiting them with punishment appeared to have arrived, he summoned Lucius Marcius from Tarraco, and sent him with a third of his forces to attack Castulo, and with the rest of the army he himself reached Illiturgi, after about five days' march.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The gates were closed, and every arrangement and preparation made for repelling an attack; so completely had the consciousness of what they deserved produced the same effect as a declaration of war against them. From this circumstance Scipio commenced his exhortation to his soldiers:
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    he said, that
                    <quote>
                        by closing their gates the Spaniards had themselves shown what their deserts were by what they feared, and that therefore they ought to prosecute the war against them with much greater animosity than against the Carthaginians. For with the latter the contest was carried on for empire and glory almost without any exasperated feeling, while they had to punish the former for perfidy, cruelty, and villany.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        That the time had now arrived when they should take vengeance for the horrid massacre of their fellow soldiers, and for the treachery which was prepared for themselves, had they been carried in their flight to the same place;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        and by the severity of the punishment inflicted in the present instance, establish it as a law for ever, that no one should consider a Roman citizen and soldier, whatever his situation, a fit object for injurious treatment.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Animated by this exhortation of their general, they distributed the scaling-ladders to men selected from each of the companies; and the army being divided into two parts, so that Laelius, as lieutenant-general, might command one, they attacked the city in two places at once; thus creating an alarm in two quarters at the same time.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It was not by the
                    <pb n="1188" xml:id="p.1188"/>
                    exhortations of one general, nor of the several nobles who were present, that the townsmen were stimulated to a vigorous defence of the city, but by the fear which they themselves entertained; they bore in mind, and admonished each other, that the object aimed at was punishment, and not victory.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    That the only question for them was, where they should meet death, whether in the battle and in the field, where the indiscriminate chance of war frequently raised up the vanquished and dashed the victor to the ground; or whether, after a short interval, when the city was burnt and plundered, after suffering every horror and indignity, they should expire amid stripes and bonds before the eyes of their captive wives and children.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, not only those who were of an age to bear arms, or men only, but women and children,
                    <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    beyond the powers of their minds and bodies, were there, supplying with weapons those who were fighting in defence of the place, and carrying stones to the walls for those who were strengthening the works; for not only was their liberty at stake, which excites the energies of the brave only, but they had before their eyes the utmost extremity of punishment, to be inflicted on all indiscriminately, and an ignominious death.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Their minds were worked up to the highest pitch, both by emulation in toil and danger, and also by the mere sight of each other.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly the contest was entered upon with such ardour, that the army which had subdued the whole of Spain was frequently driven back from the walls of one town, and exhibited such a want of resolution in the contest as was not very honourable to it.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    When Scipio perceived this, he was afraid lest, by the failure of his attempts, the courage of the enemy should be raised and his own troops be dispirited; and thinking it incumbent upon him to exert himself in person and share the danger, reproved his soldiers for their cowardice, and ordered the scaling-ladders to be brought, threatening to mount the wall himself, since the rest hesitated.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    He had now advanced near the walls with no small danger, when a shout was raised from all sides by the soldiers, who were alarmed at the danger their general was exposed to, and the scaling-ladders began to be reared in several places at once. Laelius too, in another quarter, pressed on vigorously.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    It was then that the energy of the townsmen was subdued, and those who defended the
                    <pb n="1189" xml:id="p.1189"/>
                    walls being beaten off, the Romans took possession of them. The citadel also was captured during the confusion on a side where it was thought impregnable.
                </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Some African deserters, who were at that time among the Roman auxiliaries, while the townsmen were occupied in defending those quarters whence danger was apprehended, and the Romans were making approaches where they could gain access, observed that the
                    <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    most elevated part of the town, which was protected by a very high rock, was neither fortified by any work nor furnished with defenders.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Being men of light make and nimble from being well exercised, they climbed up wherever they could gain access over the irregular projections of the rock, carrying with them iron spikes.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    If in any part they met with a cliff too steep and smooth, they fixed spikes at moderate intervals, and having thus formed a sort of steps, and those who were foremost pulling up those who followed, and those who were behind lifting up those before them, they succeeded in gaining the summit, whence they
                    <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    ran down with a shout into the city, which had already been taken by the Romans.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Then it became manifest indeed that it was resentment and hatred which prompted the assault upon the city. No one thought of taking any alive, nor of booty, though every thing lay exposed to plunder. They butchered all indiscriminately, armed and unarmed, male and female. Their cruel resentment extended to the slaughter of infants.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They then set fire to the houses, and pulled down those which could not be consumed by fire, so bent were they upon erasing even every vestige of the city, and blotting out the memory of their enemies.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio marched his army thence to Castulo, which was defended, not only by Spaniards who had assembled there, but also by the remains of the Carthaginian army, which had gone there from the various places to which they had been dispersed in their flight.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But the news of the calamity of the Illiturgians had reached them before the arrival of Scipio; and in consequence of this, dismay and desperation had seized them;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    and as their cases were differently circumstanced, and each party was desirous of consulting its own safety independent of the other, at first secret jealousy, and then an open rupture, created a separation between the Carthaginians and Spaniards.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Cerdubellus without disguise advised the latter to surrender. Himilco commanded the
                    <pb n="1190" xml:id="p.1190"/>
                    Carthaginian auxiliaries, which, together with the city, Cerdubellus delivered up to the Romans, having secretly obtained terms.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    This victory was attended with less cruelty; for not only was the guilt of this people less than the others, but their voluntary surrender had considerably mitigated resentment.
                </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Marcius was then sent against the barbarians, to reduce under the authority and dominion of the Romans such of them as had not yet been subdued. Scipio returned to Carthage, to pay his vows to the gods, and to exhibit a gladiatorial show, which he had prepared on account of the death of his father and uncle. This exhibition of gladiators was not formed from that description of men which the lanistae are accustomed to procure, such as slaves, or those who sell their blood.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    All the service of the combatants was voluntary and gratuitous; for some were sent by the petty princes,
                    <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    to show an example of the natural courage of their people; others came forward to fight, in compliment to their general;
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    others were induced to give and accept challenges, by a spirit of emulation and a desire of victory.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Some decided by the sword disputes which they either could not or were unwilling to determine by argument, with an agreement that the matter in question should be given up to the victor.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Nor was it confined to men of obscure rank, but comprehended persons of distinction and celebrity; such were Corbis and Orsua, cousins-german, who, having a dispute about the sovereignty of a city called Ibis, declared that they would contest it with the sword. Corbis was the elder of the two.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The father of Orsua was the last sovereign, having succeeded to that dignity on the death of his elder brother.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    When Scipio was desirous of settling the dispute by argument and allaying their irritation, they both declared that they had refused that to their mutual kinsmen, and that they would appeal to no other judge, whether god or man, than Mars.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The elder presuming upon his strength, the younger on the prime of youth, each wished to die in the combat rather than become the subject of the other; and every effort failing to prevent their prosecuting their mad design, they exhibited to the army a most interesting spectacle, and a proof how great mischief is occasioned among men by a thirst for power.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The elder, in consequence of his experience in arms and his address, easily mastered the unscientific efforts of the younger. To this show
                    <pb n="1191" xml:id="p.1191"/>
                    of gladiators were added funeral games, proportioned to the means possessed, and with such magnificence as the provinces and the camp afforded.
                </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Meanwhile the operations of the war were carried on with unabated activity by the lieutenant-generals. Marcius, crossing the river Baetis, which the natives call Certis, received the submission of two powerful cities without a contest.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    There was a city called Astapa, which had always sided with the Carthaginians; nor was it that which drew upon it the resentment of the Romans so much as the fact, that its inhabitants harboured an extraordinary animosity against them, which was not called for by the necessities of the war.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Their city was not so secured by nature or art as to make their dispositions so fierce, but the natural disposition of the inhabitants, which took delight in plunder, had induced them to make excursions into the neighboring lands belonging to the allies of the Romans, and to intercept such Roman soldiers, suttlers, and merchants as they found ranging about.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    They had also surrounded, by means of an ambuscade, and put to the sword on disadvantageous ground, a large company which was crossing their borders, for it had proved hardly safe to go in small parties.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    When the troops were marched up to assault this city, the inhabitants, conscious of their guilt, and seeing that it would be dangerous to surrender to an enemy so highly incensed, and that they could not hope to keep themselves in safety by means of their walls or their arms, resolved to execute upon themselves and those belonging to them a horrid and inhuman deed.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They fixed upon a place in their forum, in which they collected the most valuable of their property, and having directed their wives and children to seat themselves upon this heap, they raised a pile of wood around it and threw on it bundles of twigs.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They then ordered fifty armed youths to stand there and guard their fortunes, and the persons dearer to them than their fortunes, as long as the issue of the battle continued doubtful.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    If they should perceive that the battle went against them, and that it came to the point that the city must be captured, they might be assured that those whom they saw going out to engage the enemy would perish in the battle itself;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    but implored them by all the gods, celestial and infernal, that, mindful of their liberty, which must be terminated on that day either by
                    <pb n="1192" xml:id="p.1192"/>
                    an honourable death or ignominious servitude, they would leave nothing on which an exasperated enemy could wreak his fury;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    that they had fire and sword at their command, and it was better that friendly and faithful hands should destroy what must necessarily perish, than that enemies should insult it with haughty wantonness.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    To these exhortations a dreadful execration was added against any one who should be diverted from this purpose by hope or faintheartedness. Then throwing open the gates, they rushed out at a rapid pace and with the utmost impetuosity.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Nor was there any guard sufficiently strong opposed to them; for there could be nothing that was less apprehended than that they would have the courage to sally from their walls. A very few troops of horse, and the light-armed, hastily sent out of the camp for that purpose, opposed them.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The battle was furious and spirited, rather than steady and regular in any degree. The horse, therefore, which had first encountered the enemy, being repulsed, created an alarm among the light-armed; and the battle would have been fought under the very rampart, had not the legions, which were their main strength, drawn out their line, though they had a very short time to form in.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    These too, for a short time, wavered around their standards, when the Astapans, blind with rage, rushed upon wounds and the sword with reckless daring; but afterwards the veteran soldiers, standing firm against their furious assaults, checked the violence of those that followed by the slaughter of the foremost.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Soon after, the veteran troops themselves made an attempt to charge them, but seeing that not a man gave ground, and that they were inflexibly determined on dying each in his place, they extended their line, which the number of their troops enabled them to do with ease, and, surrounding their flanks, slew them all to a man while fighting in a circle.
                </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    But these, however, were acts committed by exasperated enemies in the heat of battle, and executed, in conformity with the laws of war, upon men armed and most fiercely resisting;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    there was another more horrible carnage in the city, where a harmless and defenceless crowd of women and children were butchered by their own countrymen, who threw their bodies, most of them still alive, upon the burning pile, while streams of blood damped the rising flame; and lastly,
                    <pb n="1193" xml:id="p.1193"/>
                    wearied with the piteous slaughter of their friends, they threw themselves, arms and all, into the midst of the flames.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When the carnage was now completed the victorious Romans came up, and at the first sight of so revolting a transaction they stood for some time wrapt in wonder and amazement;
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    but afterwards, from a rapacity natural to humanity, wishing to snatch out of the fire the gold and silver which glittered amid the heap of other materials, some were caught by the flames, others scorched by the hot blasts, as the foremost were unable to retreat, in consequence of the immense crowd which pressed upon them.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In this manner was Astapa destroyed by the sword and fire, without affording any booty to the soldiers. After the rest of the people in that quarter, influenced by fear, had made submission to him, Marcius led his victorious troops to Scipio, at Carthage.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Just at this same time deserters arrived from Gades, who promised to betray the town and Carthaginian garrison which occupied it, together with the commander and the fleet.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Mago had halted there after his flight, and having collected some ships on the ocean, had got together a considerable number of auxiliaries from the coast of Africa, on the other side the strait, and also by means of Hanno the praefect from the neighbouring parts of Spain.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    After pledges had been exchanged with the deserters, Marcius and Laelius were sent thither, the former with the light cohorts, the latter with seven triremes and one quinquereme, in order that they might act in concert by land and sea.
                </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    In consequence of Scipio's being afflicted with a severe fit of illness, which rumour represented as more serious than it really was; for every one made some addition to the account he had received, from a desire inherent in mankind of intentionally exaggerating reports, the whole province, and more especially the distant parts of it, were thrown into a state of ferment;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and it was evident what a serious disturbance would have been excited had he really died, when an unfounded report created such violent commotions.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Neither the allies kept their allegiance, nor the army their duty. Mandonius and Indibilis, who were not at all satisfied with what had occurred, for they had anticipated with certainty that they would
                    <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    have the dominion of Spain on the expulsion of the Carthaginians, called together their countrymen the Lacetani,
                    <pb n="1194" xml:id="p.1194"/>
                    and summoning the Celtiberian youth to arms, devastated in a hostile manner the territories of the Suessetanians and Sedetanians, allies of the Romans.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, a mutiny arose in the camp at Sucro. Here were eight thousand men, stationed as a guard over the nations dwelling on this side the Iberus.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    It was not on hearing uncertain rumours respecting the life of the general that their minds were first excited, but previously, owing to the licentiousness which naturally results from long-continued idleness, and in some degree also owing to the restraint felt in time of peace by men who had been accustomed to live freely on what they gained by plunder in an enemy's country.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    At first they only discoursed in private, asking what they were doing among people who were at peace with them, if there was a war in the province? if the war was terminated and the province completely subdued, why were they not conveyed back into Italy?
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The pay also was demanded with more insolence than was customary or consistent with military subordination, and the guards cast reproaches upon the tribunes while going round to the watches. Some too had gone out by night into the neighbouring lands, belonging to persons at peace with the Romans, to plunder; but at last they quitted their standards in the day-time and openly without furloughs.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Every thing was done according to the caprice and unrestrained will of the soldiers, and nothing according to rule and military discipline, or the orders of those who were in command.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The form, however, of a Roman camp was preserved solely in consequence of the hopes they entertained that the tribunes, catching the spirit of insubordination, would not be averse from taking part in the mutiny and defection, on which account they suffered them to dispense justice in their courts, went to them for the watch-word, and served in their turn on the outposts and watches;
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    and as they had taken away the power of command, so they preserved the appearance of obedience to orders, by spontaneously executing their own.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Afterwards, when they perceived that the tribunes censured and reprobated their proceedings, endeavoured to counteract them, and publicly declared that they would not take any share in their disorderly conduct, the mutiny assumed a decided character;
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    when, after driving the tribunes from their courts, and shortly after from the camp, the command was conferred by universal con-
                    <pb n="1195" xml:id="p.1195"/>
                    sent upon Caius Albius of Cales and Caius Atrius of Umbria, common soldiers, who were the prime movers of the sedition.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    These men were so far from being satisfied with the ornaments used by tribunes, that they had the audacity to lay hold even of the insignia of the highest authority, the fasces and axes, without ever reflecting that their own backs and necks were in danger from those very rods and axes which they carried before them to intimidate others.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Their mistaken belief of the death of Scipio had blinded their minds, and they doubted not that, in a short time, when that event should be made generally known, all Spain would blaze with war;
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    that during this confusion money might be exacted from the allies and the neighbouring cities plundered; and that in this unsettled state of affairs, when there was nothing which any man would not dare, their own acts would be less conspicuous.
                </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    As they expected that other fresh accounts would follow those which they had received, not only of the death, but even of the burial, of Scipio, and yet none arrived;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and as the rumour which had been so idly originated began to die away, the first author of it began to be sought out; and each backing out in order that he might appear rather to have inconsiderately credited than to have fabricated such a report, the leaders were forsaken, and began now to dread their own ensigns of authority, and to apprehend that, instead of that empty show of command which they wore, a legitimate and rightful power would be turned against them.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The mutiny being thus paralysed, and credible persons bringing in accounts, first, that Scipio was alive, and, soon after, that he was even in good health, seven military tribunes were sent by Scipio himself.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    At the first arrival of these their minds were violently excited; but they were soon calmed by the mild and soothing language which they addressed to such of their acquaintance as they met with;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    for, going round first of all to the tents, and then entering the principia and the praetorium, wherever they observed circles of men conversing together, they addressed them, inquiring rather what it was that had occasioned their displeasure and sudden consternation, than taxing them with what had occurred.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>That they had not received their pay at the appointed time,</quote>
                    was generally complained; and
                    <quote>
                        that although at the time of the horrid
                        <pb n="1196" xml:id="p.1196"/>
                        transaction of the Illiturgians, and after the destruction of two generals and two armies, the Roman cause had been defended and the province retained by their valour; the Illiturgians had received the punishment due to their offence, but there was no one found to reward them for their meritorious services.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The tribunes replied,
                    <quote>
                        that, considering the nature of their complaints, what they requested was just, and that they would lay it before the general; that they were happy that there was nothing of a more gloomy and irremediable character; that both Publius Scipio, by the favour of the gods, and the commonwealth, were in a situation to requite them.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, who was accustomed to war but inexperienced in the storms of sedition, felt great anxiety on the occasion, lest the army should run into excess in transgressing, or himself in punishing.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For the present he resolved to persist in the lenient line of conduct with which he had begun, and sending collectors round to the tributary states, to give the soldiers hopes of soon receiving their pay.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Immediately after this a proclamation was issued that they should come to Carthage to receive their pay, whether they wished to do so in detached parties or all in a body.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The sudden suppression of the rebellion among the Spaniards had the effect of tranquillizing the mutiny, which was by this time beginning to subside of itself; for Mandonius and Indibilis, relinquishing their attempt, had returned within their borders when intelligence was brought that Scipio was alive; nor did there now remain any person, whether countryman or foreigner, whom they could make their companion in their desperate enterprise.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    On examining every method, they had no alternative except that which afforded a retreat from wicked designs, which was not of the safest kind, namely, to commit themselves either to the just anger of the general, or to his clemency, of which they need not despair.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For he had pardoned even enemies whom he had encountered with the sword;
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    while they reflected that their sedition had been unaccompanied with wounds or blood, and was neither in itself of an atrocious character nor merited severe punishment. So natural is it for men to be over-eloquent in extenuating their own demerit.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    They felt doubtful whether they should go to demand their pay in single cohorts or in one entire body; but the opinion that they should go in a body, which they regarded as the safer mode, prevailed.
                    <pb n="1197" xml:id="p.1197"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    At the same time, when they were employed in these deliberations, a council was held on their case at Carthage;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    when a warm debate took place as to whether they should visit with punishment the originators only of the mutiny, who were in number not more than thirty-five, or, whether atonement should be made for this defection, (for such it was rather than a mutiny,) of so dreadful a character as a precedent, by the punishment of a greater number.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The opinion recommending the more lenient course, that the punishment should fall where the guilt originated, was adopted. For the multitude a reprimand was considered sufficient.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    On the breaking up of the council, orders were given to the army, which was in Carthage, to prepare for an expedition against Mandonius and Indibilis, and to get ready provisions for several days, in order that they might appear to have been deliberating about this.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The seven tribunes who had before gone to Sucro to quell the mutiny, having been sent out to meet the army, gave in, each of them, five names of persons principally concerned in the
                    <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    affair, in order that proper persons might be employed to invite them to their homes, with smiles and kind words; and that, when overpowered with wine, they might be thrown into chains.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They were not far distant from Carthage when the intelligence, received from persons on the road, that the whole army was going the following day with Marcus Silanus against the Lacetanians, not only freed them from all the apprehensions which, though they did not give utterance to them, sat heavy upon their minds, but occasioned the greatest transport, because they would thus have the general alone, and in their power, instead of being themselves in his.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    They entered the city just at sun-set, and saw the other army making every preparation for a march. Immediately on their arrival they were greeted in terms feigned for the
                    <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    purpose, that their arrival was looked upon by the general as a happy and seasonable circumstance, for they had come when the other army was just on the point of setting out. After which they proceeded to refresh themselves.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The authors of the mutiny, having been conveyed to their lodgings by proper persons, were apprehended by the tribunes without any disturbance, and thrown into chains.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    At the fourth watch the baggage belonging to the army, which, as it was pretended, was about to march, began to set out. As soon as it was
                    <pb n="1198" xml:id="p.1198"/>
                    light the troops marched, but were stopped at the gate, and guards were sent round to all the gates to prevent any one going out of the city.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Then those who had arrived the day before, having been summoned to an assembly, ran in crowds into the forum to the tribunal of the general, with the presumptuous purpose of intimidating him by their shouts.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    At the same time that the general mounted the tribunal, the armed troops, which had been brought back from the gates, spread themselves around the rear of the unarmed assembly.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Then all their insolence subsided; and, as they afterwards confessed, nothing terrified them so much as the unexpected vigour and hue of the general, whom they had supposed they should see in a sickly state, and his countenance, which was such as they declared that they did not remember to have ever seen it even in battle.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    He sat silent for a short time, till he was informed that the instigators of the mutiny were brought into the forum, and that every thing was now in readiness.
                </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Then, a herald having obtained silence, he thus began: "I imagined that language would never fail me in which to address my army;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    not that I have ever accustomed myself to speaking rather than action, but because, having been kept in a camp almost from my boyhood, I had become familiar with the dispositions of soldiers.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But I am at a loss both for sentiments and expressions with which to address you, whom I know not even by what name I ought to call.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Can I call you countrymen, who have revolted from your country? or soldiers, who have rejected the command and authority of your general, and violated the solemn obligation of your oath? Can I call you enemies?
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    I recognise the persons, faces, dress, and mien of fellow countrymen; but I perceive the actions, expressions, intentions, and feelings of enemies. For what have you wished and hoped for, but what the Ilergetians and Lacetanians did. Yet they followed Mandonius and Indibilis, men of royal rank, who were the leaders of their mad project; you conferred the auspices and command upon the Umbrian, Atrius, and the Calenian, Albius.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Deny, soldiers, that you were all concerned in this measure, or that you approved of it when taken. I shall willingly believe, when you disclaim it, that it was the folly and madness of a few. For the acts which have been committed are of such a nature, that, if
                    <pb n="1199" xml:id="p.1199"/>
                    the whole army participated in them, they could not be expiated without atonements of tremendous magnitude.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Upon these points, like wounds, I touch with reluctance; but unless touched and handled, they cannot be cured.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part, I believed that, after the Carthaginians were expelled from Spain, there was not a place in the whole province where, or any persons to whom, my life was obnoxious; such was the manner in which I had conducted myself, not only towards my allies, but even towards my enemies.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But lo, even in my own camp, so much was I deceived in my opinion, the report of my death was not only readily believed, but anxiously waited for.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Not that I wish to implicate you all in this enormity; for, be assured, if I supposed that the whole of my army desired my death, I would here immediately expire before your eyes; nor could I take any pleasure in a life which was odious to my countrymen and my soldiers.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But every multitude is in its nature like the ocean; which, though in itself incapable of motion, is excited by storms and winds. So, also, in yourselves there is calm and there are storms; but the cause and origin of your fury is entirely attributable to those who led you on; you have caught your madness by contagion.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Nay, even this day you do not appear to me to be aware to what a pitch of phrensy you have proceeded; what a heinous crime you have dared to commit against myself, your country, your parents, your children; against the gods, the witnesses of your oath; against the auspices under which you serve; against the laws of war, the discipline of your ancestors, and the majesty of the highest authority.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    With regard to myself, I say nothing. You may have believed the report of my death rather inconsiderately than eagerly. Lastly, suppose me to be such a man that it could not at all be a matter of astonishment that my army should be weary of my command, yet what had your country deserved of you, which you betrayed by making common cause with Mandonius and Indibilis?
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    What the Roman people, when, taking the command from the tribunes appointed by their suffrages, you conferred it on private men? When, not content even with having them for tribunes, you, a Roman army, conferred the fasces of your general upon men who never had a slave under their command?
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Albius and Atrius had their tents in your general's pavilion. With them the trumpet sounded, from
                    <pb n="1200" xml:id="p.1200"/>
                    them the word was taken, they sat upon the tribunal of Scipio, upon whom the lictor attended, for them the crowd was cleared away as they moved along, before them the fasces with the axes were carried.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    When showers of stones descend, lightnings are darted from the heavens, and animals give birth to monsters, you consider these things as prodigies. This is a prodigy which can be expiated by no victims, by no supplications, without the blood of those men who have dared to commit so great a crime.
                </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    "Now, though villany is never guided by reason, yet so far as it could exist in so nefarious a transaction, I would fain know what was your design.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Formerly, a legion which was sent to garrison Rhegium, wickedly put to the sword the principal inhabitants and kept possession of that opulent city through a space of ten years;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    on account of which enormity the entire legion, consisting of four thousand men, were beheaded in the forum at Rome.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But they, in the first place, did not put themselves under the direction of Atrius the Umbrian, scarcely superior to a scullion, whose name even was ominous, but of Decius Jubellius, a military tribune; nor did they unite themselves with Pyrrhus, or with the Samnites or Lucanians, the enemies of the Roman people. But you made common cause with Mandonius and Indibilis, and intended also to have united your arms with them.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    They intended to have held Rhegium as a lasting settlement, as the Campanians held Capua, which they took from its ancient Tuscan inhabitants;
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    and as the Mamertines held Messana in Sicily, without any design of commencing without provocation a war upon the Roman people or their allies. Was it your purpose to hold Sucro as a place of abode?
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    where, had I, your general, left you on my departure after the reduction of the province, you would have been justified in imploring the interference of gods and men, because you could not return to your wives and children.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But suppose that you banished from your minds all recollection of these, as you did of your country and myself; I would wish to track the course of a wicked design, but not of one utterly insane.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    While I was alive, and the rest of the army safe, with which in one day I took Carthage, with which I routed, put to flight, and expelled from Spain four generals and four armies of the Carthaginians; did you, I say, who were only eight thousand men, all of course of less
                    <pb n="1201" xml:id="p.1201"/>
                    worth than Albius and Atrius, to whom you subjected yourselves, hope to wrest the province of Spain out of the hands of the Roman people? I lay no stress upon my own name, I put it out of the question.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Let it be supposed that I have not been injured by you in any respect beyond the ready credence of my death.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    What! if I were dead, was the state to expire with me? was the empire of the Roman people to fall with me? Jupiter, most good and great, would not have permitted that the existence of the city, built under the auspices and sanction of the gods to last for ever, should terminate with that of this frail and perishable body.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman people have survived those many and distinguished generals who were all cut off in one war; Flaminius, Paulus, Gracchus, Posthumius Albinus, Marcus Marcellus, Titus Quinctius Crispinus, Cneius Fulvius, my kinsmen the Scipios; and will survive a thousand others who may perish, some by the sword, others by disease; and would the Roman state have been buried with my single corpse?
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    You yourselves, here in Spain, when your two generals, my father and my uncle, fell, chose Septimus Marcius as your general to oppose the Carthaginians, exulting on account of their recent victory. And thus I speak, on the supposition that Spain would have been without a leader.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Would Marcus Silanus, who was sent into the province with the same power and the same command as myself, would Lucius Scipio my brother, and Caius Laelius, lieutenant-generals, have been wanting to avenge the majesty of the empire?
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Could the armies, the generals themselves, their dignity or their cause, be compared with one another? And even had you got the better of all these, would you bear arms in conjunction with the Carthaginians against your country, against your countrymen? Would you wish that Africa should rule Italy, and Carthage the city of Rome? If so, for what offence on the part of your country?
                </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        An unjust sentence of condemnation, and a miserable and undeserved banishment, formerly induced Coriolanus to go and fight against his country; he was restrained, however, by private duty from public parricide. What grief, what resentment instigated you?
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Was the delay of your pay for a few days, during the illness of your general, a reason of sufficient weight for you to declare war against your country? to revolt from the Roman people and join the Ilergetians? to
                        <pb n="1202" xml:id="p.1202"/>
                        leave no obligation, divine or human, unviolated? Without doubt, soldiers, you were mad; nor was the disease which seized my frame more violent than that with which your minds were affected.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        I shrink with horror from the relation of what men believed, what they hoped and wished.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Let oblivion cover all these things if possible; if not, however it be, let them be covered in silence. I must confess my speech must have appeared to you severe and harsh, but how much more harsh, think you, must your actions be than my words!
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Do you think it reasonable that I should suffer all the acts which you have committed, and that you should not bear with patience even to hear them mentioned? But you shall not be reproached even with these things any further. I could wish that you might as easily forget them as I shall.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Therefore, as far as relates to the general body of you, if you repent of the error you have committed, I shall have received sufficient and more than sufficient atonement for it.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Albius the Calenian, and Atrius the Umbrian, with the rest of the principal movers of this impious mutiny, shall expiate with their blood the crime they have perpetrated.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        To yourselves, if you have returned to a sound state of mind, the sight of their punishment ought not only to be not unpleasant, but even gratifying; for there are no persons to whom the measures they have taken are more hostile and injurious than to you.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    He had scarcely finished speaking, when, according to the plan preconcerted, every object of terror was at once presented to their eyes and ears.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The troops, which had formed a circle round the assembly, clashed their swords against their shields; the herald's voice was heard citing by name the persons who had been condemned in the council; the culprits were dragged naked into the midst of the assembly, and at the same time all the apparatus for punishment was brought forth.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    They were tied to the stake, scourged with rods, and decapitated; while those who were present were so benumbed with fear, that not only no expression of dissatisfaction at the severity of the punishment, but not even a groan was heard.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    They were then all dragged out, the place was cleared, and the men cited by name took the oath of allegiance to Scipio before the military tribunes, each receiving his full demand of pay as he answered to his name. Such was the termination and result which the
                    <pb n="1203" xml:id="p.1203"/>
                    insurrection of the soldiers, which began at Sucro, met with.
                </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    During the time of these transactions, Hanno, the lieutenant-general of Mago, having been sent from Gades to the river Baetis with a small body of Africans, by tempting the Spaniards with money, armed as many as four thousand men;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    but afterwards, being deprived of his camp by Lucius Marcius, and losing the principal part of his troops in the confusion occasioned by its capture, and some also in the flight, for the cavalry pursued them closely while they were dispersed, he made his escape with a few attendants.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    During these transactions on the river Baetis, Laelius in the mean time, sailing out of the straits into the ocean, came with his fleet before Carteia, a city situated on the coast of the ocean, where the sea begins to expand itself, after being confined in a narrow strait.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He had entertained hopes of having Gades betrayed to him without a contest, persons having come unsolicited into the Roman camp to make promises to that effect, as has been before mentioned. The plot was discovered before it was ripe, and all having been apprehended, were placed by Mago in the hands of Adherbal the praetor, to be conveyed to Carthage.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Adherbal, having put the conspirators on board a quinquereme, sent it in advance, because it sailed slower than a trireme, and followed himself at a moderate distance with eight triremes.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The quinquereme was just entering the strait, when Laelius, who had himself also sailed out of the harbour of Carteia in a quinquereme, followed by seven triremes, bore down upon Adherbal and his triremes, feeling assured that the trireme, when once caught in the rapid strait, would not be able to return against the opposing current. The Carthaginian, alarmed by the suddenness of the affair, hesitated for some little time whether he should follow the trireme, or turn his prows against the enemy.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This very delay put it out of his power to decline an action, for they were now within a weapon's cast, and the enemy were bearing down upon him on all sides.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The current also had rendered it impossible to manage the ships. Nor was the action like a naval engagement, inasmuch as it was in no respect subject to the control of the will, nor afforded any opportunity for the exercise of skill or method.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The nature of the strait and the tide, which solely and en-
                    <pb n="1204" xml:id="p.1204"/>
                    tirely governed the contest, carried the ships against those of their own and the enemy's party indiscriminately, though striving in a contrary direction; so that you might see one ship which was flying whirled back by an eddy and driven against the victors, and another which was engaged in pursuit, if it had fallen into an opposite current, turning itself away as if for flight.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And when actually engaged, one ship while bearing down upon another with its beak directed against it, assuming an oblique position itself, received a stroke from the beak of the other; while another which lay with its side exposed to the enemy, receiving a sudden impulse, was turned round so as to present its prow.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    While the triremes were thus engaged in a doubtful and uncertain contest, in which every thing was governed by chance, the Roman quinquereme, whether being more manageable in consequence of its weight, or by means of more banks of oars making its way through the eddies, sunk two triremes, and swept off the oars from one side of another, while sailing by it with great violence.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The rest too, had they come in its way, it would have disabled; but Adherbal, with his remaining four ships, sailed over into Africa.
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Laelius returned victorious into Carteia; and hearing there what had occurred at Gades, that the plot had been discovered, the conspirators sent to Carthage, and
                    <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    that the hopes which had brought them there had been completely frustrated, he sent a message to Lucius Marcius, to the effect that, unless they wished to waste time uselessly in lying before Gades, they should return to the general; and Marcius consenting to the proposal, they both returned to Carthage a few days after.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    In consequence of their departure, Mago not only obtained a temporary relief from the dangers which beset him on all sides, both by sea and land, but also on hearing of the rebellion of the Ilergetians, conceived hopes of recovering Spain, and sent messengers to Carthage to
                    <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    the senate, who, at the same time that they represented to them in exaggerated terms both the intestine dissension in the Roman camp and the defection of their allies, might exhort them to send succours by which the empire of Spain, which had been handed down to them by their ancestors, might be regained.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Mandonius and Indibilis, retiring within their borders, remained quiet for a little time, not knowing what course to take, till they knew what was determined upon respecting the mutiny; but not
                    <pb n="1205" xml:id="p.1205"/>
                    distrusting that if Scipio pardoned the error of his own countrymen, they also might obtain the same.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But when the severe punishment inflicted came to be generally known, concluding that their offence also would be considered as demanding a similar expiation, they again summoned their countrymen to arms;
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    and assembling the auxiliaries which had joined them before, they crossed over into the Sedetanian territory, where they had had a fixed camp at the beginning of the revolt, with twenty thousand foot and two thousand five hundred horse.
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio having without difficulty regained the affection of his soldiers, both by his punctuality in discharging the arrears of pay to all, as well the guilty as the innocent, and particularly by the looks and language of reconciliation towards all, before he quitted Carthage summoned an assembly;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and after inveighing at large against the perfidy of the petty princes who were
                    <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    in rebellion, declared
                    <quote>
                        that the feelings with which he set out to take revenge for their villany were widely different from those with which he lately corrected the error committed by his countrymen.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        That on the latter occasion, he had with groans and tears, as though he were cutting his own vitals, expiated either the imprudence or the guilt of eight thousand men with the heads of thirty; but now he was going to the destruction of the Ilergetians with joyful and animated feelings: for they were neither natives of the same soil, nor united with him by any bond of society.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The only connexion which did subsist between them, that of honour and friendship, they had themselves severed by their wicked conduct.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        When he looked at the troops which composed his army, besides that he saw that they were all either of his own country, or allies and of the Latin confederacy; he was also strongly affected by the circumstance, that there was scarcely a soldier in it who was not brought out of Italy into that country either by his uncle, Cneius Scipio, who was the first of the Roman name who had come into that province, or by his father when consul, or by himself.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        That they were all accustomed to the name and auspices of the Scipios; that it was his wish to take them home to their country to receive a well-earned triumph; and that he hoped that they would support him when he put up for the consulship, as if the honour sought were to be shared
                        <pb n="1206" xml:id="p.1206"/>
                        in common by them all.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        With regard to the expedition which they were just going to undertake, that the man who considered it as a war must be forgetful of his own achievements. That, by Hercules, Mago, who had fled for safety with a few ships beyond the limits of the world into an island surrounded by the ocean, was a source of greater concern to him than the Ilergetians;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        for in it there was both a Carthaginian general and a Carthaginian army, whatever might be its numbers; while here were only robbers and leaders of robbers, who, though they possessed sufficient energy for ravaging the lands of their neighbours, burning their houses, and carrying off their cattle, yet would have none at all in a regular and pitched battle; and who would come to the encounter relying more on the swiftness with which they can fly than on their arms.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Accordingly,
                    </quote>
                    he said,
                    <quote>
                        that he had thought it right to quell the Ilergetians before he quitted the province, not because he saw that any danger could arise from them, or that a war of greater importance could grow out of these proceedings;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        but in the first place, that a revolt of so heinous a character might not go unpunished, and in the next place, that not a single enemy might be said to be left in a province which had been subdued with such valour and success.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        He bid them, therefore, follow him, with the assistance of the gods, not so much to make war upon, for the contest was not with an enemy who was upon an equality with them, but to take vengeance on the basest of men.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    After this harangue he dismissed them, with orders to get themselves in readiness in every respect for marching the next day; when, setting out, he arrived at the river Iberus in ten days. Then crossing the river, he, on the fourth day, pitched his camp within sight of the enemy.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Before him was a plain enclosed on all sides by mountains. Into the valley thus formed Scipio ordered some cattle, taken chiefly from the lands of the enemy, to be driven, in order to excite the rapacity of the barbarians, and then
                    <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    sent some light-armed troops as a protection for them, directing Laelius to charge the enemy from a place of concealment when they were engaged in skirmishing.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    A mountain which projected conveniently concealed the ambuscade of the cavalry, and the battle began without delay. The Spaniards, as soon as they saw the cattle at a distance, rushed upon them, and the light-armed troops
                    <pb n="1207" xml:id="p.1207"/>
                    attacked the Spaniards while occupied with their booty.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    At first they annoyed each other with missiles; but afterwards, having discharged their light weapons, which were calculated to provoke rather than to decide the contest, they drew their swords, and began to engage foot to foot.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The fight between the infantry would have been doubtful, but that the cavalry then came up, and not only, charging them in front, trod down all before them, but some also, riding round by the foot of the hill, presented themselves on their rear, so that they might intercept the greater part of them; and consequently the carnage was greater than usually takes place in light and skirmishing engagements.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The resentment of the barbarians was rather inflamed by this adverse battle, than their spirits depressed. Accordingly, that they might not appear cast down, they marched out into the field the following day as soon as it was light.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The valley, which was confined, as has been before stated, would not contain all their forces. About two-thirds of their foot and all their cavalry came down to the engagement. The remainder of their infantry they stationed on the declivity of the hill.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, conceiving that the confined nature of the ground would be in his favour, both because the Roman troops were better adapted for fighting in a contracted space than the Spanish, and also because the enemy had come down and formed their line on ground which would not contain all their forces, applied his mind to a new expedient.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    For he considered that he could not himself cover his flanks with his cavalry, and that those of the enemy which they had led out, together with their infantry, would be unable to act.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly he ordered Laelius to lead the cavalry round by the hills as secretly as possible, and separate, as far as he could, the fight between the cavalry from that between the infantry.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    He himself drew up the whole body of his infantry against the enemy, placing four cohorts in front, because he could not extend his line further. He commenced the battle without delay, in order that the contest itself might divert the attention of the enemy, and prevent their observing the cavalry which were passing along the hills.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Nor were they aware that they had come round before they heard the noise occasioned by the engagement of the cavalry in their rear.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Thus there were two battles; two lines of infantry and two bodies of horse being engaged within the space occupied by the plain lengthwise; and that because
                    <pb n="1208" xml:id="p.1208"/>
                    it was too narrow to admit of both descriptions of force being engaged in the same lines.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    When the Spanish infantry could not assist their cavalry, nor their cavalry the infantry, and the infantry, which had rashly engaged in the plain, relying on the assistance of the cavalry, were being cut to pieces, the cavalry themselves also, being surrounded and unable to stand the shock of the enemy's infantry in front, (for by this time their own infantry were completely overthrown,) nor of the cavalry in their rear, after having formed themselves into a circle and defended themselves for a long time, their horses standing still, were all slain to a man.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Nor did one person, horse or foot, survive of those who were engaged in the valley. The third part, which stood upon the hill rather to view the contest in security than to take any part of it upon themselves, had both time and space to fly;
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    among whom the princes themselves also fled, having escaped during the confusion, before the army was entirely surrounded.
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The same day, besides other booty, the camp of the Spaniards was taken, together with about three thousand men.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Of the Romans and their allies as many as one thousand two hundred fell in that battle; more than three thousand were wounded. The victory would have been less bloody had the battle taken place in a plain more extended, and affording facilities for flight.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Indibilis, renouncing his purpose of carrying on war, and considering that his safest reliance in his present distress was on the tried honour and clemency of Scipio, sent his brother Mandonius to him; who, falling prostrate before his knees, ascribed his conduct to the fatal frenzy of those times, when, as it were
                    <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    from the effects of some pestilential contagion, not only the Ilergetians and Lacetanians, but even the Roman camp had been infected with madness.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    He said that his own condition, and that of his brother and the rest of his countrymen, was such, that either, if it seemed good, they would give back their lives to him from whom they had received them, or if preserved a second time, they would in return for that favour devote their lives for ever to the service of him to whom alone they were indebted for them.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They before placed their reliance on their cause, when they had not yet had experience of his clemency, but now, on the contrary, placing no reliance on their cause, all their hopes were centred in the mercy of the conqueror.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    It was a custom with the Romans, observed from ancient times, not to ex-
                    <pb n="1209" xml:id="p.1209"/>
                    ercise any authority over others, as subject to them, in cases where they did not enter into friendship with them by a league and on equal terms, until they had surrendered all they possessed, sacred and profane; until they had received hostages, taken their arms from them, and placed garrisons in their cities.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    In the present instance, however, Scipio, after inveighing at great length against Mandonius, who stood before him, and Indibilis, who was absent, said
                    <quote>
                        that they had justly forfeited their lives by their wicked conduct, but that they should be preserved by the kindness of himself and the Roman people.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Further, that he would neither take their arms from them, (which only served as pledges to those who feared rebellion,) but would leave them the free use of them, and their minds free from fear; nor would he take vengeance on their unoffending hostages, but upon themselves, should they revolt, not inflicting punishment upon a defenceless but an armed enemy.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        That he gave them the liberty of choosing whether they would have the Romans favourable to them or incensed against them, for they had experienced them under both circumstances.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Thus Mandonius was allowed to depart, having only a pecuniary fine imposed upon him to furnish the means of paying the troops. Scipio himself, having sent Marcius in advance into the Farther Spain, and sent Silanus back to Tarraco, waited a few days until the Ilergetians had paid the fine imposed upon them;
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    and then, setting out with some troops lightly equipped, overtook Marcius when he was now drawing near to the ocean.
                </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The negotiation which had some time before commenced respecting Masinissa, was delayed from one cause after another; for the Numidian was desirous by all means of conferring with Scipio in person, and of touching his right hand in confirmation of their compact. This was the cause of Scipio's undertaking at this time a journey of such a length, and into so remote a quarter.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa, when at Gades, received information from Marcius of the approach of Scipio, and by pretending that his horses were injured by being pent up in the island, and that they not only caused a scarcity of every thing to the rest, but also felt it themselves; moreover that his cavalry were beginning to lose their energy for want of employment;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    he prevailed upon Mago to allow him to cross over to the continent, to plunder the adjacent country of
                    <pb n="1210" xml:id="p.1210"/>
                    Spain.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Having passed over, he sent forward three chiefs of the Numidians, to fix a time and place for the conference, desiring that two might be detained by Scipio as hostages. The third being sent back to conduct Masinissa to the place to which he was directed to bring him, they came to the conference with a few attendants.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The Numidian had long before been possessed with admiration of Scipio from the fame of his exploits; and his imagination had pictured to him the idea of a grand and magnificent person; but his veneration for him was still greater when he appeared before him.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    For besides that his person, naturally majestic in the highest degree, was rendered still more so by his flowing hair, by his dress, which was not in a precise and ornamental style, but truly masculine and soldier-like, and also by his age, for he was then in full vigour of body, to which the bloom of youth,
                    <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    renewed as it were after his late illness, had given additional fulness and sleekness.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The Numidian, who was in a manner thunderstruck by the mere effect of the meeting, thanked him for having sent home his brother's son. He affirmed, that from that time he had sought for this opportunity, which being at length presented to him, by favour of the immortal gods, he had not allowed to pass without seizing it.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    That he desired to serve him and the Roman people in such a manner, as that no one foreigner should have aided the Roman interest with greater zeal than himself.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Although he had long since wished it, he had not been so able to effect it in Spain, a foreign and strange country; but that it would be easy for him to do so in that country in which he had been born and educated, under the hope of succeeding to his father's throne.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    If, indeed, the Romans should send the same commander, Scipio, into Africa, he entertained a well-grounded hope that Carthage would continue to exist but a short time.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio saw and heard him with the highest delight, both because he knew that he was the first man in all the cavalry of the enemy, and because the youth himself exhibited in his manner the strongest proof of a noble spirit. After mutual pledges of faith, he set out on his return to Tarraco.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa, having laid waste the adjacent lands, with the permission of the Romans, that he might not appear to have passed over into the continent to no purpose, returned to Gades.
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Mago, who despaired of success in Spain, of which he
                    <pb n="1211" xml:id="p.1211"/>
                    had entertained hopes, from the confidence inspired first by the mutiny of the soldiers, and afterwards by the defection of Indibilis, received a message from Carthage, while preparing to cross over into Africa, that the senate ordered him to carry over into Italy the fleet he had at Gades;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and hiring there as many as he could of the Gallic and Ligurian youth, to form a junction with Hannibal, and not to suffer the war to flag which had been begun with so much vigour and still more success.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For this object Mago not only received a supply of money from Carthage, but himself also exacted as much as he could from the inhabitants of Gades, plundering not only their treasury, but their temples, and compelling them individually to bring contributions of gold and silver, for the public service.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    As he sailed along the coast of Spain, he landed his troops not far from New Carthage, and after wasting the neighbouring lands, brought his fleet thence to the city. Here, keeping his troops in the ships by day, he landed them by night, and marched them to that part of the wall at which Carthage had been captured by the Romans;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    for he had supposed both that the garrison by which the city was occupied was not sufficiently strong for its protection, and that some of the townsmen would act on the hope of effecting a change. But messengers who came with the utmost haste and alarm from the country, brought intelligence at once of the devastation of the lands, the flight of the rustics, and the approach of the enemy.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, the fleet had been observed during the day, and it was evident that there was some object in choosing a station before the city. Accordingly, the troops were kept drawn up and armed within the gate which looks towards the lake and the sea.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    When the enemy, rushing forward in a disorderly manner, with a crowd of seamen mingled with soldiers, came up to the walls with more noise than strength;
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    the gate being suddenly thrown open, the Romans sallied forth with a shout, and pursued the enemy, routed and put to flight at the first onset and
                    <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    discharge of their weapons, all the way to the shore, killing a great number of them;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    nor would one of them have survived the battle and the flight, had not the ships, which had been brought to the shore, afforded them a refuge in their dismay.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Great alarm and confusion also prevailed in the ships, occasioned by their drawing up the ladders, lest the enemy should force their way in together with
                    <pb n="1212" xml:id="p.1212"/>
                    their own men, and by cutting away their halsers and anchors that they might not lose time in weighing them.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Many, too, met with a miserable death while endeavouring to swim to the ships, not knowing, in consequence of the darkness, which way to direct their course, or what to avoid.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    On the following day, after the fleet had fled back to the ocean, whence it had come, as many as eight hundred were slain between the wall and the shore, and two thousand stand of arms were found.
                </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Mago, on his return to Gades, not being allowed to enter the place, brought his fleet to shore at Cimbis, a place not far distant from Gades; whence he sent ambassadors with complaints of their having closed their gates upon a friend and ally.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    While they endeavoured to excuse themselves on the ground that it was done by a disorderly assembly of their people, who were exasperated against them on account of some acts of plunder which had been committed by the soldiers when they were embarking, he enticed their suffetes, which is the name of the chief magistracy among the Carthaginians, together with their quaestor, to come to a conference;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    when he ordered them to be lacerated with stripes and crucified.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He then passed over with his fleet to the island Pityusa, distant about a hundred miles from the continent, and inhabited at that time by Carthaginians; on which account the fleet was received in a friendly manner; and not only were provisions liberally furnished, but also young men and arms were given them to reinforce their fleet. Rendered confident by these supplies, the Carthaginians crossed over to the Balearian islands, fifty miles distant.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The Balearian islands are two in number; one larger than the other, and more powerful in men and arms; having also a harbour in which, as it was now the latter end of autumn, he believed he might winter conveniently.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But here his fleet was opposed with as much hostility as he would have met with had the Romans inhabited that island. The only weapons they used at that time, and which they now principally employ, were slings; nor is there an individual of any other nation who possesses such a degree of excellence in the skilful use of this weapon, as the Balearians universally possess over the rest of the world.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Such a quantity of stones, therefore, was poured like the thickest hail on the fleet, when approaching the shore, that, not daring to enter the harbour,
                    <pb n="1213" xml:id="p.1213"/>
                    they made off for the main.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    They then passed over to the lesser Balearian island, which is of a fertile soil, but not equally powerful in men and arms.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Here, therefore, they landed, and pitched a camp in a strong position above the harbour; and having made themselves masters of the city and country without a contest, they enlisted two thousand auxiliaries, which they sent to Carthage, and then hauled their ships on shore for the winter.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    After Mago had left the coast of the ocean, the people of Gades surrendered to the Romans.
                </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Such were the transactions in Spain under the conduct and auspices of Publius Scipio. Scipio himself, having put Lucius Lentulus and Lucius Manlius Acidinus in charge of the province, returned to Rome with ten ships.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Having obtained an audience of the senate without the city, in the temple of Bellona, he gave an account of the services he had performed in Spain; how often he had fought pitched battles, how many towns he had taken by force from the enemy, and what nations he had brought under the dominion of the Roman people.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    He stated that he had gone into Spain against four generals, and four victorious armies, but that he had not left a Carthaginian in that country.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    On account of these services he rather tried his prospect of a triumph, than pressed it pertinaciously; for it was quite clear, that no one had triumphed up to that time for services performed, when not invested with a magistracy.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    When the senate was dismissed he entered the city, and carried before him into the treasury fourteen thousand three hundred and forty-two pounds of silver, and a great quantity of coined silver.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Veturius Philo then held the assembly for the election of consuls, when all the centuries, with the strongest marks of attachment, named Publius Scipio as consul. Publius Licinius Crassus, chief pontiff, was joined with him as his colleague.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    It is recorded, that this election was attended by a greater number of persons than any other during the war.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    People had come together from all quarters, not only to give their votes, but also for the purpose of seeing Publius Scipio. They ran in crowds, not only to his house, but also to the Capitol;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    where he was engaged in offering a sacrifice of a hundred oxen to Jupiter, which he had vowed in Spain, impressed with a presentiment, that as Caius Lutatius had terminated the former Punic war,
                    <pb n="1214" xml:id="p.1214"/>
                    so Publius Scipio would terminate the present;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    and that as he had driven the Carthaginians out of every part of Spain, so he would drive them out of Italy; and dooming Africa to him as his province, as though the war in Italy were at an end.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The assembly was then held for the election of praetors. Two were elected who were then plebeian aediles, namely, Spurius Lucretius and Cneius Octavius; and of private persons, Cneius Servilius Caepio and Lucius Aemilius Papus.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In the fourteenth year of the Punic war, Publius Cornelius Scipio and Publius Licinius Crassus entered on the consulship, when the provinces assigned to the consuls were, to Scipio, Sicily, without drawing lots, his colleague not opposing it, because the care of the sacred affairs required the presence of the chief pontiff in Italy; to Crassus, Bruttium.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The provinces of the praetors were then put to the determination of lots, when the city jurisdiction fell to Servilius; Ariminum, for so they called Gaul, to Spurius Lucretius; Sicily to Lucius Aemilius; Sardinia to Cneius Octavius.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    A senate was held in the Capitol, when, on the motion of Publius Scipio, a decree was made, that he should exhibit the games which he had vowed in Spain during the mutiny of the soldiers, out of the money which he had himself brought into the treasury.
                </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    He then introduced into the senate the Saguntine ambassadors, the eldest of whom thus spoke:
                    <quote>
                        Although there remains no degree of suffering, conscript fathers, beyond what we have endured, in order that we might keep our faith towards you to the last; yet such are the benefits which we have received both from yourselves and your generals, that we do not repent of the calamities to which we have ourselves been exposed.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        On our account you undertook the war, and having undertaken it, you have continued to carry it on for now the fourteenth year with such inflexible perseverance, that frequently you have both yourselves been reduced, and have brought the Carthaginians to the last extremity.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        At a time when you had a war of such a desperate character in Italy, and Hannibal as your antagonist, you sent your consul with an army into Spain, to collect, as it were, the remains of our wreck.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Publius and Cneius Cornelius, from the time they entered the province, never ceased from adopting such measures as were favourable to us and detrimental to our enemies.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        First of all, they restored to us our
                        <pb n="1215" xml:id="p.1215"/>
                        town; and, sending persons to collect our countrymen, who were sold and dispersed throughout all Spain, restored them from a state of slavery to freedom.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        When our circumstances, from being wretched in the extreme, had nearly assumed a desirable state, your generals Publius and Cneius Cornelius fell, more to be lamented by ourselves even than by you.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Then truly we seemed to have been dragged back from distant places to our ancient abode, to perish again, and witness the second destruction of our country. Nor did it appear that there was any need forsooth of a Carthaginian army or general to effect our destruction;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        but that we might be annihilated by the Turdulans, our most inveterate enemies, who had also been the cause of our former overthrow. When suddenly, to our great surprise, you sent us this Publius Scipio, in seeing whom declared consul, and in having it in
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                        our power to carry word back to our countrymen that we have seen it, for on him our hopes and safety entirely rest, we consider ourselves the most fortunate of all the Saguntines.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        He, when he had taken a great number of the cities of your enemies in Spain, on all occasions separated the Saguntines out of the mass of captives, and sent them back to their country; and lastly, by his arms he reduced to so low a state Turdetania, which harboured such animosity against us, that if that
                        <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                        nation continued to flourish it was impossible that Saguntum could stand, that it not only was not an object of fear to us, but, and may I say it without incurring odium, not even to our posterity.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        We see the city of those persons demolished, to gratify whom Hannibal destroyed Saguntum. We receive tribute from their lands, which is not more acceptable to us from the advantage we derive from it than from revenge.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        In consideration of these benefits, than which we could not hope or wish for greater from the immortal gods, the senate and people of Saguntum have sent us ten ambassadors to you to return their thanks;
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        and at the same time to offer you their congratulations on your having carried on your operations in Spain and Italy so successfully of late years, that you have subdued by your arms, and have gotten possession of Spain, not only as far as the river Iberus, but also to where the ocean forms the limit of the remotest regions of the world; while in Italy you have left nothing to the Carthaginian except so much space as the rampart of his camp en-
                        <pb n="1216" xml:id="p.1216"/>
                        closes.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        We have been desired, not only to return thanks for these blessings to Jove most good and great, the guardian deity of the capitoline citadel, but also, if you should permit us, to carry into the Capitol this present of a golden crown in token of victory.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        We request that you would permit us so to do; and, if you think proper, that you would, by your authority, perpetuate and ratify the advantages which your generals have conferred upon us.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The senate replied to the Saguntines,
                    <quote>
                        that the destruction and restoration of Saguntum would form a monument to all the nations of the world of social faith preserved on both sides.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        That, in restoring Saguntum, and rescuing its citizens from slavery, their generals had acted properly, regularly, and according to the wishes of the senate; and that, whatever other acts of kindness they had done to them, were in conformity with the wishes of the senate. That they gave them permission to deposit their present in the Capitol.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Orders were then given to furnish the ambassadors with apartments and entertainment, and that not less than ten thousand
                    <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    should be given to each as a present. After this, the rest of the embassies were introduced and heard.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    On the request of the Saguntines that they
                    <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/>
                    might go and take a view of Italy as far as they could with safety, they were furnished with guides, and letters were sent to the several towns, requiring them to entertain the Spaniards kindly.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    The senate then took into consideration the state of public affairs, the levying troops, and the provinces.
                </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    It being generally reported that Africa, as a new province, was destined for Publius Scipio without casting lots; and he himself, not content with any moderate share of glory, asserting that he had been declared consul, not only for prosecuting, but for finishing the war;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    that that object could not be accomplished by any other means than by his transporting an army into Africa; and himself openly declaring that he would do it through the people if the senate opposed him; the design by no means pleased the principal senators; and when the rest, either through fear or a wish to ingratiate themselves with him, only murmured, Quintus Fabius Maximus, being asked his opinion, thus spoke:
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    "I know, conscript fathers, that by many of you the question which is this day agitated is considered as already determined; and that the man who shall deliver his sentiments on the subject of making
                    <pb n="1217" xml:id="p.1217"/>
                    Africa a province, as a new proposal, will speak to little purpose.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But, in the first place, I cannot see how it can be considered as determined, that Africa shall be the province of the consul, that brave and active officer, when neither the senate have voted nor the people ordered that it should be constituted a province this year.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In the next place, if it is determined, I think the consul is to blame, who, by pretending to consult the senate on a question already decided, insults that body, and not the senator only who delivers his sentiments in his place on the subject of deliberation.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Now I am well aware, that by disapproving of this excessive eagerness to pass over into Africa, I subject myself to two imputations: one grounded on the caution inherent in my disposition, which young men may if they please call cowardice and
                    <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    sloth, so long as we have the consolation to reflect, that though hitherto the measures of others have always appeared on the first view of them the more plausible, mine on experience have proved the sounder.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The other imputation is that of jealousy and envy towards the daily increasing glory of this most valiant consul.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But if neither my past life and character, nor a dictatorship, together with five consulships, and so much glory acquired, both in peace and war, that I am more likely to loathe it than desire more, exempt me from such a suspicion, let my age at least acquit me. For what rivalry can there exist between myself and a man who is not equal in years even to my son?
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    When I was dictator, when as yet in the possession of full vigour, and engaged in a series of affairs of the utmost magnitude, no one heard me, either in the senate or in the popular assembly, express any reluctance to have the command equally shared between myself and the master of the horse, at the time when he was maligning me; a proposition which no one ever heard mention of before.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    I chose to bring it about by actions rather than by words, that he who was placed on the same footing with me in the judgment of others, should soon by his own confession declare me his superior.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Much less, after having passed through these honours, would I propose to myself to enter the lists of competition and rivalry with a man in the very bloom of youth.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    And that, forsooth, in order that Africa, if it shall have been denied to him, may be assigned as a province to me, who am now weary of life, and not merely of active employments. I must live and die with that share
                    <pb n="1218" xml:id="p.1218"/>
                    of glory which I have already acquired.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    I prevented Hannibal from conquering, in order that he might even be conquered by you, whose powers are now in full vigour.
                </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    "It is but fair, Publius Cornelius, that you should pardon me, if I, who in my own case never preferred the honour of men to the interest of the state, do not place even your fame before the public good.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Although, if there were either no war in Italy, or an enemy of such a description that no glory could be acquired from conquering him, the man who would retain you in Italy, though actuated by a desire to promote the public good, might appear to wish to deprive you of an opportunity of acquiring renown when he objected to your removing the war.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But since Hannibal is our antagonist, who is besieging Italy for now the fourteenth year, with an army unimpaired, will you have reason to be dissatisfied, Publius Cornelius, with the glory you will acquire, if you in your consulate shall drive out of Italy an enemy who has been the cause of so many deaths and so many disasters to us, and if you should enjoy the distinction of having terminated this, as Caius Lutatius did the former Punic war?
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Unless either Hamilcar is a general more worthy of consideration than Hannibal, or a war in Africa of more importance, or a victory there greater and more glorious, (should it be our lot to be victorious while you are consul,) than one here. Would you rather have drawn away Hamilcar from Drepanum and Eryx than have expelled the Carthaginians and Hannibal from Italy?
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Although you naturally prize more highly the renown which you have acquired than that which
                    <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    you hope for, yet surely you would not boast more of having freed Spain from war than of having freed Italy.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Hannibal is not as yet in such a state as that the man who prefers another war would not appear to have feared rather than to have despised him. Why then do you not apply yourself to this, and carry the war in a straightforward manner to the place where Hannibal is, rather than pursue that circuitous course, according to which you expect that when you shall have crossed over into Africa Hannibal will follow you thither? Do you seek to obtain the distinguished honour of having finished the Punic war?
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    After you have defended your own possessions, for this is naturally the first object, then proceed to attack those of others.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Let there be peace in Italy before war in
                    <pb n="1219" xml:id="p.1219"/>
                    Africa; and let us be free from fear ourselves before we bring it upon others.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    If it is possible that both objects may be accomplished under your conduct and auspices, having first conquered Hannibal here, then go and lay siege to Carthage; but if one or other of these conquests must be left for the succeeding consuls, the former is both the greater and more glorious, and also the cause of the second.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    For now indeed, besides that the treasury is not able to maintain two different armies, one in Italy and one in Africa; besides that we have nothing left from which we may equip fleets or be able to furnish provisions, who knows not how great danger would be incurred? 'Publius Licinius will wage war in Italy, Publius Scipio in Africa.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    What if, (an omen which may all the gods avert, and which my mind shrinks back with alarm from mentioning, —but what has happened may happen again, —) what I say, if Hannibal, having gained a victory, should advance to the city?
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Shall we then at length send for you, our consul, out of Africa, as we formerly sent for Quintus Fulvius from Capua? What shall we say when we consider that in Africa also both parties will be liable to the chances of war?
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Let your own house, your father and your uncle, slain together with their armies within the space of thirty days, after that, having spent several years in the performance of the most important services, both by sea and land, they had
                    <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/>
                    inspired foreign nations with the highest reverence for the name of the Roman people and your family, be a warning to you.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    The day would fail me were I disposed to enumerate the kings and generals who have brought the most signal calamities upon themselves and their armies by rashly passing into the territories of their enemies.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The Athenians, a state distinguished for prudence, leaving a war at home, sent a great fleet into Sicily at the instance of a youth equally enterprising and illustrious; but by one naval battle they reduced their flourishing republic to a state of humiliation from which she could never recover.
                </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        But I am adducing foreign and too remote examples. That same Africa, and Marcus Atilius, who was a signal example of both extremes of fortune, may form a warning to us.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Without doubt, Publius Cornelius, when you shall have a view of Africa from the sea, the reduction of your province of Spain will appear to you to have been a mere matter of
                        <pb n="1220" xml:id="p.1220"/>
                        sport and pastime.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        For what similarity is there between them? After sailing along the coast of Italy and Gaul to Emporiae without any enemy to oppose you, you brought your fleet to land at a city of our allies.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        There landing your soldiers, you marched them through countries entirely secure from danger to Tarraco, to join the allies and friends of the Roman people. After that, from Tarraco you marched through places garrisoned by Roman troops.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        On the banks of the Iberus were the armies of your father and your uncle, rendered. still more furious after the loss of their generals, even by the very calamity they had suffered. The general, indeed, Lucius Marcius, had been irregularly constituted and chosen for the time by the suffrages of the soldiers; but had he been adorned with noble birth and the regular gradations of preferment, he would have been equal to the most distinguished generals, from his skill in every art of war.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        You then laid siege to Carthage, quite at your leisure, not one of the three Punic armies coming to the defence of their allies.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        The rest of your achievements, nor do I wish to disparage them, are by no means to be compared with what you will have to do in a war in Africa, where there is not a single harbour open to receive our fleet, no part of the country at peace with us, no state in alliance, no king in friendship with us, no room in any part either to take up a position or to advance.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Whichever way you turn your eyes, all is hostility and danger. Do you trust in the Numidians and Syphax? Let it suffice to have trusted in them once. Temerity is not always successful, and the fraudulent usually pave the way to confidence in small matters, that when an advantageous opportunity occurs, they may deceive with great gain.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Your father and uncle were not cut off by the arms of their enemies till they were duped by the treachery of their Celtiberian allies; nor were you yourself exposed to so much danger from Mago and Hasdrubal, the generals of your enemies, as from Indibilis and Mandonius, whom you had received into friendship.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Can you place any confidence in Numidians after having experienced a defection in your own soldiers? Syphax and Masinissa would rather that they themselves should have the rule in Africa than the Carthaginians, but that the Carthaginians should rather than any other state.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        At present, emulation and the various causes of dispute existing be-
                        <pb n="1221" xml:id="p.1221"/>
                        tween them incite them against each other, because the fear of any foreign enemy is remote. But show them the Roman arms and a body of troops, natives of another country, and they will run together as if to extinguish a common conflagration.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        These same Carthaginians defended Spain in a different manner from that in which they will defend the walls of their capital, the temples of their gods, their altars, and their hearths; when their terrified wives will attend them on the way to the battle, and their little children will run to them.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        What, moreover, if the Carthaginians, feeling sufficiently secure in the harmony subsisting in Africa, in the attachment of the sovereigns in alliance with them, and their own fortifications, should, when they see Italy
                        <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/>
                        deprived of the support of yourself and your army, themselves assuming an offensive attitude, either send a fresh army out of Africa into Italy, or order Mago, who, it is certain, having passed over from the Baleares, is now sailing along the coast of Liguria and the Alps, to form a junction with Hannibal.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Without doubt, we should be thrown into the same state of alarm as we were lately, when Hasdrubal passed over into Italy; that Hasdrubal, whom you, who are about to blockade, not Carthage only, but all Africa with your army, allowed to slip out of your hands into Italy. You will say that he was conquered by you. For that very reason I should be less willing, not on account of the commonwealth only, but of yourself, that, after having been defeated, he should be allowed to march into Italy.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        Suffer us to ascribe to your prudence all the successful events which have happened to you and the empire of the Roman people, and to impute all those of an adverse nature to the uncertain chances of war and to fortune. The more meritorious and brave you are, so much the more do your country and all Italy desire to retain you as their protector.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        You cannot even yourself pretend to deny, that where Hannibal is, there is the head and principal stress of the war, for you profess, that your motive in crossing over into Africa is to draw Hannibal thither. Whether, therefore, here or there, it is with Hannibal that you will have to contend. Will you then, I pray, have more power in Africa and alone, or here, with your own and your colleague's army united?
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        Is not the great difference which this makes proved to you even by the recent precedent of Claudius and Livius,
                        <pb n="1222" xml:id="p.1222"/>
                        the consuls? What! will Hannibal, who has now for a long time been unavailingly soliciting succours from home, be rendered more powerful in men and arms when occupying the remotest corner of the Bruttian territory, or when near to Carthage and supported by all Africa?
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        What sort of policy is that of yours, to prefer fighting where your own forces will be diminished by one half, and the enemy's greatly augmented, to encountering the enemy when you will have two armies against one, and that wearied with so many battles, and so protracted and laborious a service?
                        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                        Consider how far this policy of yours corresponds with that of your parent. He, setting out in his consulship for Spain, returned from his province into Italy, that he might meet Hannibal on his descent from the Alps; while you are going to leave Italy when Hannibal is there, not because you consider such a course beneficial to the state, but because you think it will redound to your own honour and glory;
                        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                        acting in the same manner as you did when leaving your province and your army without the sanction of a law, without a decree of the senate, you, a general of the Roman people, intrusted to two ships the fortune of the commonwealth and the majesty of the empire, which were then hazarded in your person.
                        <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                        In my estimation, conscript fathers, Publius Cornelius was elected consul for the service of the state and of us, and not to forward his own individual interest; and the armies were enlisted for the protection of the city and of Italy, and not for the consuls, like kings, to carry into whatever part of the world they please from motives of vanity.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Fabius having made a strong impression on a large portion of the senate, and especially those advanced in years, by this speech, which was adapted to the occasion, and also by his authority and his long-established reputation for prudence; and those who approved of the counsel of this old man being more numerous than those who commended the hot spirit of the young one;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio is reported thus to have spoken:
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    "Even Quintus Fabius himself has observed, conscript fathers, in the commencement of his speech, that in the opinion he gave a feeling of jealousy might be suspected.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And though I dare not myself charge so great a man with harbouring that feeling, yet, whether it is owing to a defect in his language, or to the fact, that suspicion has certainly not
                    <pb n="1223" xml:id="p.1223"/>
                    been removed. For he has so magnified his own honours and the fame of his exploits, in order to do away with the imputation of envy, that it would appear I am in danger of being rivalled by every obscure person, but not by himself, because, as he enjoys an eminence above every body else, an eminence to which I do not dissemble that I also aspire, he is unwilling that I should be placed upon a level with him.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    He has represented himself as an old man, and as one who has gone through every gradation of honour, and me as below the age even of his son;
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    as if he supposed that the desire of glory did not exceed the limits of human life, and as if its chief part had not respect to memory and future ages.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    I am confident, that it is usual with all the most exalted minds, to compare themselves, not only with the illustrious men of the present, but of every age.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part, I do not dissemble that I am desirous, not only to attain to the share of glory which you possess, Quintus Fabius, but, (and in saying it I mean no offence,) if I can, even to exceed it. Let not such a feeling exist in your mind towards me, nor in mine towards those who are my juniors, as that we should be unwilling that any of our countrymen should attain to the same celebrity with ourselves;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    for that would be a detriment, not to those only who may be the objects of our envy, but to the state, and almost to the whole human race.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    He mentioned what a great degree of danger I should incur, should I cross over into Africa, so that he appeared solicitous on my account, and not only for the state and the army. But whence has this concern for me so suddenly sprung?
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    When my father and uncle were slain; when their two armies were cut up almost to a man; when Spain was lost; when four armies of the Carthaginians and four generals kept possession of every thing by terror and by arms; when a general was sought for to take the command of that war, and no one came forward besides myself, no one had the courage to declare himself a candidate; when the Roman people had conferred the command upon me, though only twenty-four years of age;
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    why was it that no one at that time made any mention of my age, of the strength of the enemy, of the difficulty of the war, and of the recent destruction of my father and uncle?
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Has some greater disaster been suffered in Africa now than had at that time befallen us in Spain? Are there now larger armies in Africa, more and better generals, than were then in Spain?
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1224" xml:id="p.1224"/>
                    Was my age then more mature for conducting a war than now? Can a war with a Carthaginian enemy be carried on with greater convenience in Spain than in Africa?
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    After having routed and put to flight four Carthaginian armies; after having captured by force, or reduced to submission by fear, so many cities; after having entirely subdued every thing as far as the ocean, so many petty princes, so many savage nations; after having regained possession of the whole of Spain, so that no trace of war remains, it is an easy matter to make light of my services;
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    just as easy as it would be, should I return victorious from Africa, to make light of those very circumstances which are now magnified in order that they may appear formidable, for the purpose of detaining me here. He says that there is no possibility of entering Africa; that there are no ports open.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    He mentions that Marcus Atilius was taken prisoner in Africa, as if Marcus Atilius had miscarried on his first access to Africa. Nor does he recollect that the ports of Africa were open to that very commander, unfortunate as he was; that he performed some brilliant services during the first year, and continued undefeated to the last, so far as related to the Carthaginian generals. You will not, therefore, in the least deter me by that example of yours.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    If that disaster had been sustained in the present, and not in the former war, if lately, and not forty years ago, yet why would it be less advisable for me to cross over into Africa after Regulus had been made prisoner there, than into Spain after the Scipios had been slain there?
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    I should be reluctant to admit that the birth of Xanthippus the Lacedaemonian was more fortunate for Carthage than mine for my country. My confidence would be increased by the very circumstance, that such important consequences depended upon the valour of one man.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    But further, we must take warning by the Athenians, who inconsiderately crossed over into Sicily, leaving a war in their own country.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Why, therefore, since you have leisure to relate Grecian tales, do you not rather set before us the instance of Agathocles, king of Syracuse, who, when Sicily was for a long time wasted by a Punic war, by passing over into this same Africa, removed the war to the country from whence it came.
                </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        But what need is there of ancient and foreign examples to remind us what sort of thing it is boldly to carry terror against an enemy, and, removing the danger from oneself, to
                        <pb n="1225" xml:id="p.1225"/>
                        bring another into peril?
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Can there be a stronger instance than Hannibal himself, or one more to the point? It makes a great difference whether you devastate the territories of another, or see your own destroyed by fire and sword.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        He who brings danger upon another has more spirit than he who repels it. Add to this, that the terror excited by unknown circumstances is increased on that account.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        When you have entered the territory of an enemy, you may have a near view of his advantages and disadvantages. Hannibal did not expect that it would come to pass that so many of the states in Italy would come over to him as did so after the defeat at Cannae.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        How much less would any firmness or constancy be experienced in Africa by the Carthaginians, who are themselves faithless allies, oppressive and haughty masters! Besides, we, even when deserted by our allies, stood firm in our own strength, the Roman soldiery. The Carthaginians possess no native strength. The soldiers they have are obtained by hire; —Africans and Numidians —people remarkable above all others for the inconstancy of their attachments.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Provided no impediment arises here, you will hear at once that I have landed, and that Africa is blazing with war; that Hannibal is preparing for his departure from this country, and that Carthage is besieged.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Expect more frequent and more joyful despatches from Africa than you received from Spain. The considerations on which I ground my anticipations are the good fortune of the Roman people, the gods, the witnesses of the treaty violated by the enemy, the kings Syphax and Masinissa; on whose fidelity I will rely in such a manner as that I may be secure from danger should they prove perfidious.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Many things which are not now apparent, at this distance, the war will develope; and it is the part of a man, and a general, not to be wanting when fortune presents itself, and to bend its events to his designs.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        I shall, Quintus Fabius, have the opponent you assign me, Hannibal; but I shall rather draw him after me than be kept here by him. I will compel him to fight in his own country, and Carthage shall be the prize of victory rather than the half-ruined forts of the Bruttians.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        With regard to providing that the state sustain no injury in the mean time, while I am crossing over, while I am landing my troops in Africa, while I am advancing my camp to the walls of Carthage;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        be not too sure that it is not an insult to
                        <pb n="1226" xml:id="p.1226"/>
                        Publius Licinius, the consul, a man of consummate valour, who did not draw lots for so distant a province merely that, as he was chief pontiff, he might not be absent from religious affairs, to say that he is unable to do that, now that the power of Hannibal is shaken, and in a manner shattered, which you, Quintus Fabius, were able to effect when he was flying victorious throughout all Italy.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        By Hercules, even if the war would not be more speedily terminated by adopting the plan I propose, yet it were consistent with the dignity of the Roman people, and the high character they enjoy with foreign kings and nations, to appear to have had spirit not only to defend Italy, but also to carry hostilities into Africa; and that it should not be supposed and spread abroad that no Roman general dared what Hannibal had dared;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        that in the former Punic war, when the contest was about Sicily, Africa should have been so often attacked by our fleets and armies, and that now, when the contest is about Italy, Africa should be left undisturbed.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Let Italy, which has so long been harassed, at length enjoy some repose; let Africa, in her turn, be fired and devastated.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Let the Roman camp overhang the gates of Carthage rather than that we should again behold the rampart of the enemy from our walls. Let Africa be the seat of the remainder of the war. Let terror and flight, the devastation of lands, the defection of allies, and all the other calamities of war which have fallen upon us, through a period of fourteen years, be turned upon her.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        It is sufficient for me to have spoken on those matters which relate to the state, the war before us, and the provinces which form the subject of deliberation.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        My discourse would be tedious and uninteresting to you if, as Fabius has depreciated my services in Spain, I should also in like manner endeavour, on the other hand, to turn his glory into ridicule, and make the most of my own.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        I will do neither, conscript fathers; and if in nothing else, though a young man, I shall certainly have shown my superiority over this old man, in modesty and the government of my tongue. Such has been my life, and such the services I have performed, that I can gladly rest contented in silence with that opinion which you have spontaneously conceived of me.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio was heard less favourably, because a report had been spread that, if he did not prevail with the senate to have
                    <pb n="1227" xml:id="p.1227"/>
                    Africa decreed to him as his province, he would immediately lay the matter before the people.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, Quintus Fulvius, who had been consul four times, and censor, requested of the consul that he would openly declare in the senate whether
                    <quote>
                        he submitted to the fathers to decide respecting the provinces; and whether he intended to abide by their determination, or to put it to the people.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio having replied that he would act as he thought for the interest of the state, Fulvius then rejoined:
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        When I asked you the question I was not ignorant of what answer you would give, or how you would act; for you plainly show that you are rather sounding than consulting the senate;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        and, unless we immediately decree to you the province you wish, have a bill ready (to lay before the people). Therefore,
                    </quote>
                    said he,
                    <quote>
                        I require of you, tribunes of the people, to support me in refusing to give my opinion, because, though my recommendation should be adopted, the consul is not disposed to abide by it.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    An altercation then arose, the consul asserting that it was unfair for the tribunes to interpose so as to prevent any senator from giving his opinion in his place on being asked it.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The tribunes came to the determination,
                    <quote>
                        that if the consul submit to the senate the question relating to the provinces, whatever the senate decree we shall consider as final, nor will we allow a bill to be proposed to the people on the subject. If he does not submit it to them, we will support any one who shall refuse to deliver his sentiments upon the matter.
                    </quote>
                    The consul requested the delay of a day to confer with his colleague.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The next day the decision was submitted to the senate. The provinces were assigned in this manner: to one of the consuls Sicily and thirty ships of war, which Caius Servilius had commanded the former year; he was also permitted to cross over into Africa if he conceived it to be for the advantage of the state.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    To the other consul Bruttium and the war with Hannibal were assigned; with either that army which Lucius Veturius or that which Quintus Caecilius commanded.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The two latter were to draw lots, and settle between themselves which should act in Bruttium with the two legions which the consul gave up; and he to whose lot that province fell, was to be continued in command for a year. The other persons also, besides the consuls and praetors, who were to take the command of armies and provinces, were continued in command.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1228" xml:id="p.1228"/>
                    It fell to the lot of Quintus Caecilius to carry on the war against Hannibal in Bruttium, together with the consul.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The games of Scipio were then celebrated in the presence of a great number of persons, and with the approbation of the spectators. The deputies, Marcus Pomponius Matho and Quintus Catius, sent to Delphi to convey a present out of the spoils taken from Hasdrubal, carried with them a golden crown of two hundred pounds' weight, and representations of the spoils made out of a thousand pounds' weight of silver.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, though he could not obtain leave to levy troops, a point which he did not urge with great eagerness, obtained leave to take with him such as volunteered their services;
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    and also, as he declared that the fleet would not be the occasion of expense to the state, to receive what was furnished by the allies for building fresh ships.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    First, the states of Etruria engaged to assist the consuls to the utmost of their respective abilities. The people of Caere furnished corn, and provisions of every description, for the crews; the people of Populoni furnished iron; of Tarquinii, cloth for sails;
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    those of Volaterrae, planks for ships, and corn; those of Arretium, thirty thousand shields, as many helmets;
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    and of javelins, Gallic darts, and long spears, they undertook to make up to the amount of fifty thousand, an equal number of each description, together with as many axes, mattocks, bills, buckets, and mills, as should be sufficient for fifty men of war, with a hundred and twenty thousand pecks of wheat;
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    and to contribute to the support of the decurios and rowers on the voyage. The people of Perusia, Clusium, and Rusella furnished firs for building ships, and a great quantity of corn.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio had firs out of the public woods. The states of Umbria, and, besides them, the people of Nursia, Reate, and Amiternum, and all those of the Sabine territory, promised soldiers.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Many of the Marsians, Pelignians, and Marrucinians volunteered to serve in the fleet. The Cameritans, as they were joined with the Romans in a league on equal terms, sent an armed cohort of six hundred men.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Having laid the keels of thirty ships, twenty of which were quinqueremes, and ten quadriremes, he prosecuted the work with such diligence, that, on the forty-fifth day after the materials were taken from the woods, the ships, being fully equipped and armed, were launched.
                </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    He set out into Sicily with thirty ships of war, with
                    <pb n="1229" xml:id="p.1229"/>
                    about seven thousand volunteers on board.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Publius Licinius came into Bruttium to the two consular armies, of which he selected for himself that which Lucius Veturius, the consul, had commanded.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    He allowed Metellus to continue in the command of those legions which were before under him, concluding that he could act more easily with the troops accustomed to his command. The praetors also went to their different provinces.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    As there was a scarcity of money to carry on the war, the quaestors were ordered to sell a district of the Campanian territory extending from the Grecian trench to the sea, with permission to receive information as to what land belonged to a native Campanian, in order that it might be put into the possession of the Roman people.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The reward fixed upon for the informer was a tenth part of the value of the lands so discovered.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Cneius Servilius, the city praetor was also charged with seeing that the Campanians dwelt where they were allowed, according to the decree of the senate, and to punish such as dwelt anywhere else.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The same summer, Mago, son of Amilcar, setting out from the lesser of the Balearian islands, where he had wintered, having put on board his fleet a chosen body of young men, conveyed over into Italy twelve thousand foot, and about two thousand horse, with about thirty ships of war, and a great number of transports. By the suddenness of his arrival he took Genoa, as there were no troops employed in protecting the sea-coast.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Thence he brought his fleet to shore, on the coast of the Alpine Ligurians, to see if he could create any commotion there.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The Ingaunians, a tribe of the Ligurians, were at that juncture engaged in war with the Epanterians, a people inhabiting the mountains.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The Carthaginian, therefore, having deposited his plunder at Savo, an Alpine town, left ten ships of war for its protection. He sent the rest to Carthage to guard the seacoast, as it was reported that Scipio intended to pass over thither; formed an alliance with the Ingaunians, whose friendship he preferred; and commenced an attack upon the mountaineers.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    His army increased daily, the Gauls flocking to his standard from all sides, from the splendour of his fame.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    When the senate received information of these things, by a letter fron Spurius Lucretius, they were filled with the most intense anxiety, lest the joy they had experienced on the destruction of Hasdrubal and his army, two years before, should
                    <pb n="1230" xml:id="p.1230"/>
                    be rendered vain by another war's springing up in the same quarter, equal in magnitude, but under a new leader.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    They therefore ordered Marcus Livius, proconsul, to march his army of volunteer slaves out of Etruria to Ariminum, and gave in charge to Cneius Servilius to issue orders, if he thought it necessary for the safety of the state, that the city legions should be marched out under the command of any person he thought proper. Marcus Valerius Laevinus led those legions to Arretium.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    About the same time, as many as eighty transports of the Carthaginians were captured, near Sardinia, by Cneius Octavius, who had the government of that province. Caelius states that they were laden with corn and provisions, sent for Hannibal; Valerius, that they were conveying the plunder of Etruria, and the Ligurian mountaineers who had been captured, to Carthage. In Bruttium scarcely any thing was done this year worth recording.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    A pestilence had attacked both Romans and Carthaginians with equal violence; but the Carthaginian army, in addition to sickness, was distressed by famine.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Hannibal passed the summer near the temple of Juno Lacinia, where he erected and dedicated an altar with an inscription engraved in Punic and Greek characters, setting forth, in pompous terms, the achievements he had performed.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
