<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 28</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="book">
                <head>The Final Conquest in Spain</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though Hasdrubal's invasion had shifted
                        the burden of war to Italy and brought corresponding relief to Spain, war
                        was suddenly renewed in that country which was quite as formidable as the
                        previous one. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the time of Hasdrubal's
                        departure Spain was divided between Rome and Carthage as follows: <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal Gisgo had retreated to the ocean
                        littoral near Gades, the Mediterranean coast-line and almost the whole of
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> Eastern Spain was held by Scipio on
                        behalf of Rome. A new general took Hasdrubal's place, named Hanno, who
                        brought over <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> a fresh army, and marched
                        into Celtiberia, which lies between the Mediterranean and the ocean, and
                        here he soon raised a very considerable army. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio sent M. Silanus against him with a force of not
                        more than 10,000 infantry and 500 cavalry. Silanus marched with all the
                        speed he could, but his progress was impeded by the bad state of the roads
                        and <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> by the narrow mountain passes,
                        obstacles which are met with in most parts of Spain. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In spite of these difficulties he outstripped not only
                        any natives who might have carried tidings, but even any <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> floating rumours of his advance, and with the
                        assistance of some Celtiberian deserters who acted as guides he succeeded in
                        finding the enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When he was about ten
                        miles distant, he was informed by his guides that there were two camps near
                        the road on which he was marching; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> the
                        one on the left was occupied by the Celtiberians, a newly raised army about
                        9000 strong, the one on the right by the Carthaginians. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The latter was carefully guarded by outposts, pickets
                        and all the usual precautions against surprise; <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> the Celtiberian camp was without any discipline, and
                        all precautions were neglected as might be expected of barbarians and raw
                        levies who felt all the less fear because they were in their own country.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Silanus decided to attack that one
                        first, and kept his men as much to the left as possible, so as not to be
                        seen by the Carthaginian outposts. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After
                        sending on his scouts he advanced rapidly against the enemy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He was now about three miles away and none
                        of the enemy had yet noticed his advance, the rocks and thickets which
                        covered the whole of this hilly district concealed his movements. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Before making his final advance, he ordered his
                        men to halt in a valley where they were effectually hidden and take food.
                        The scouting parties resumed and confirmed the statements of the deserters,
                        on which the Romans, after placing the baggage in the centre and arming
                        themselves for the combat, advanced in order of battle. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The enemy caught sight of these when they were a mile
                        distant and hurriedly prepared to meet them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> As soon as Mago heard the shouting and confusion he galloped across from
                        his camp to take command. There were in the Celtiberian army 4000 men with
                        shields and 200 cavalry, making up a regular legion. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> These were his main strength and he stationed them in
                        the front; the rest who were lightly armed he posted in reserve. In this
                        formation he led them out of the camp, but they had hardly crossed the
                        rampart when the Romans hurled their javelins at them. The Spaniards stooped
                        to avoid them, and then sprang up to discharge their own, which the Romans
                        who were in their usual close order received on their overlapping shields;
                        then they closed up foot to foot and fought with their swords. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians, accustomed to rapid evolutions,
                        found their agility useless on the broken ground, but the Romans, who were
                        used to stationary fighting, found no inconvenience from it beyond the fact
                        that their ranks were sometimes broken when moving through narrow places or
                        patches of brushwood. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then they had to
                        fight singly or in pairs, as if they were fighting duels. </p>
                    <p> These very obstacles, however, by impeding the enemy's flight, gave them up,
                        as though bound hand and foot, to the sword. Almost all the heavy infantry
                        of the Celtiberians had fallen when the Carthaginian light infantry, who had
                        now come from the other camp, shared their fate. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Not more than 2000 infantry escaped; the cavalry, which
                        had hardly taken any part in the battle, together with Mago also got away.
                        The other general, Hanno, was taken prisoner, together with those who were
                        the last to appear in the field when the battle was already lost. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Mago, with almost the whole of his cavalry and
                        his veteran infantry, joined Hasdrubal at Gades ten days after the battle.
                        The Celtiberian levies dispersed amongst the neighbouring forests and so
                        reached their homes. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So far the war had
                        not been a serious one, but there was all the material for a much greater
                        conflagration had it been possible to induce the other tribes to join the
                        Celtiberians in arms; that possibility was by this most timely victory
                        destroyed. Scipio therefore eulogised Silanus in generous terms, and felt
                        hopeful of bringing the war to a termination if he on his part acted with
                        sufficient promptitude. He advanced, accordingly, into the remote corner of
                        Spain where all the remaining strength of Carthage was concentrated under
                        Hasdrubal. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He happened at the time to be
                        encamped in the district of Baetica for the purpose of securing the fidelity
                        of his allies, but on Scipio's advance he suddenly moved away and in a march
                        which closely resembled a flight retreated to Gades on the coast. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Feeling, however, quite certain that as long as
                        he kept his army together he would be the object of attack, he arranged,
                        before he crossed over to Gades, for the whole of his force to be
                        distributed amongst the various cities, so that they could defend the walls
                        whilst the walls protected them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Scipio became aware of this breaking
                        up of the hostile forces, he saw that to carry his arms from city to city
                        would involve a loss of time far greater than the results gained, and
                        consequently marched back again. Not wishing, however, to leave that
                        district in the enemy's hands, he sent his brother Lucius with 10,000
                        infantry and 1000 cavalry to attack the richest city in that part of the
                        country; the natives call it Orongi. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It is
                        situated in the country of the Maessesses, one of the tribes of Southern
                        Spain; the soil is fertile, and there are also silver mines. Hasdrubal had
                        used it as his base from which to make his incursions on the inland tribes.
                        Lucius Scipio encamped in the neighbourhood of the city, but before
                        investing it, he sent men up to the gates to hold a parley with the townsmen
                        and endeavour to persuade them to put the friendship rather than the
                        strength of the Romans to the proof. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As
                        nothing in the shape of a peaceable answer was resumed, he surrounded the
                        place with a double line of circumvallation and formed his army into three
                        divisions, so that one division at a time could be in action while the other
                        two were resting, and thus a continuous attack might be kept up. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> When the first division advanced to the storm
                        there was a desperate fight; they had the utmost difficulty in approaching
                        the walls and bringing up the scaling-ladders owing to the rain of missiles
                        showered down upon them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even when they
                        had planted the ladders against the walls and began to mount them, they were
                        thrust down by forks made for the purpose, iron hooks were let down upon
                        others so that they were in danger of being dragged off the ladders and
                        suspended in mid-air. Scipio saw that what made the struggle indecisive was
                        simply the insufficient number of his men and that the defenders had the
                        advantage because they were fighting from their walls. He withdrew the
                        division which was engaged, and brought up the two others. In face of this
                        fresh attack the defenders, worn out with meeting the former assault,
                        retreated hastily from the walls, and the Carthaginian garrison, fearing
                        that the city had been betrayed, left their various posts and formed into
                        one body. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This alarmed the townsmen, who
                        dreaded lest the enemy when once inside the city should massacre every one,
                        whether Carthaginian or Spaniard. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They
                        flung open one of the gates and burst out of the town, holding their shields
                        in front of them in case missiles should be hurled on them from a distance,
                        and showing their empty right hands to make it plain that they had thrown
                        away their swords. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Their action was
                        misinterpreted either owing to the distance at which they were seen, or
                        because treachery was suspected, and a fierce attack was made upon the
                        flying crowd, who were cut down as though they were a hostile army. The
                        Romans marched in through the open gate whilst other gates were demolished
                        with axes and mallets, and as each cavalry man entered he galloped in
                        accordance with instructions to the forum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        The cavalry were supported by a detachment of triarii; the legionaries
                        occupied the rest of the city. There was no plundering and, except in the
                        case of armed resistance, no bloodshed. All the Carthaginians and about a
                        thousand of the townsmen who had closed the gates were placed under guard,
                        the town was handed over to the rest of the population and their property
                        restored to them. About 2000 of the enemy fell in the assault upon the city;
                        not more than 90 of the Romans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The capture of this city was a source of
                        great gratification to those who had effected it, as it was also <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> to the commander-in-chief and the rest of the
                        army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The entry of the troops was a
                        noteworthy sight owing to the immense number of prisoners who preceded them.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Scipio bestowed the highest
                        commendation on his brother, and declared that the capture of Orongis was as
                        great an <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> achievement as his own capture
                        of New Carthage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The winter was now coming
                        on, and as the season would not admit of his making an attempt on Gades or
                        pursuing Hasdrubal's army, dispersed as it was throughout the province,
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Scipio brought his entire force back
                        into Hither Spain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After dismissing the
                        legions to their winter quarters, he sent his brother to Rome with Hanno and
                        the other <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> prisoners of high rank, and
                        then retired to Tarraco. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Roman fleet
                        under the command of the proconsul M. Valerius Laevinus sailed during the
                        year to Africa, and committed widespread devastation round Utica and
                        Carthage; plunder was carried off under the very walls of Utica and on the
                        frontiers of Carthage. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On their return to
                        Sicily they fell in with a Carthaginian fleet of seventy vessels. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Out of these seventeen were captured, four were
                        sunk, the rest scattered in flight. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                        Roman army, victorious alike on land and sea, returned to <milestone
                            n="14??" unit="section"/> Lilybaeum with an enormous amount of plunder
                        of every kind. Now that the enemy's ships had been driven off and the
                            <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> sea rendered safe, large supplies
                        of corn were conveyed to Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was in the beginning of this summer
                        that the proconsul P. Sulpicius and King Attalus who, as already stated, had
                        wintered at Aegina, sailed for Lemnos with their combined fleets, the Roman
                        vessels numbering twenty-five and the king's ships, thirty-five. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> In order to be in readiness to meet his enemies
                        by land or sea, Philip went down to Demetrias on the coast and <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> issued orders for his army to assemble at
                        Larissa by a given day. When they heard of the king's arrival at Demetrias,
                        deputations from all his allies visited him there. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The Aetolians, emboldened by their alliance with Rome
                        and the arrival of Attalus, were ravaging their neighbours' lands.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Great alarm was created amongst the
                        Acarnanians, the Boeotians and the inhabitants of Euboea, and the Achaeans
                        had further cause for apprehension, for, in addition to their war with
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the Aetolians, they were threatened
                        by Machanidas the tyrant of Lacedaemon, who had encamped not far from the
                        Argive frontiers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The deputations informed
                        the king of the state of things, and one and all begged him to render them
                        assistance against the dangers which were threatening by land and sea.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The condition of his own kingdom was
                        far from tranquil; reports were brought to him announcing that Scerdilaedus
                        and Pleuratus were again active and that Thracian tribes, especially the
                        Maedi, were prepared to invade Macedonia as soon as the king was involved in
                        a distant war. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Boeotians and the
                        States in the interior of Greece reported that the Aetolians had closed the
                        pass of Thermopylae at its narrowest part with <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> a fosse and rampart to prevent him from carrying
                        succour to the cities of his allies. Even a lethargic leader would have been
                        roused to activity by all these disturbances round him. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He dismissed the deputations with a definite promise
                        that he would furnish assistance to them all as time and circumstances
                        allowed. For the moment the most pressing care was the city of Peparethos,
                        as King Attalus, who had sailed thither from Lemnos, was reported to be
                        plundering and destroying all the country round. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Philip sent a detachment to protect the place.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He also sent Polyphantas with a small
                        force into Boeotia, and Menippus, one of his generals, with 1000 peltasts to
                        Chalcis. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> This force was supplemented by
                        500 Agrianians, in order that the whole of the island might be protected.
                        Philip himself proceeded to Scotusa and ordered the Macedonian troops at
                        Larissa to march there. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Information was
                        brought to him here that the national council of the Aetolians had been
                        summoned to meet at Heraclea and that Attalus would be present to consult
                        with them as to the conduct of the war. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        Philip accordingly proceeded thither by forced marches, but did not reach
                        the place till the council was broken up. He destroyed the crops, however,
                        which were almost ripe, especially round the gulf of the Aenianes, and then
                        led his army back to Scotusa. Leaving the bulk of his forces there he
                        returned to Demetrias with his household troops. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> With the view of meeting any movement on the part of
                        the enemy, he sent men into Phocis, Euboea and Peparethos to select elevated
                        positions on which beacon fires might be lighted, and himself fixed an
                        observation post on Tisaeos, a peak of immense height. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> In this way he hoped to receive instant notice from the
                        distant fires of any movement on the part of the enemy. The Roman general
                        and Attalus sailed from Peparethos to Nicaea, and from there to the city of
                        Oreus in Euboea. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> This is the first city
                        in Euboea which you pass on your left hand as you leave the Gulf of
                        Demetrias for Chalcis and the Euripus. It was arranged between Attalus and
                        Sulpicius that the Romans should attack by sea and the king's troops by
                        land. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was not till the fourth day after their
                        arrival that they commenced the attack, the interval having been spent in
                        secret conferences with Plator, whom Philip had made commandant of the
                        garrison. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The city has two citadels, one
                        overlooking the sea, the other in the heart of the city. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> From the latter a subterranean passage leads down to
                        the sea, and at one time terminated in a tower five stories high, which
                        formed an imposing defence. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here a violent
                        contest took place, for the tower was plentifully stored with missiles of
                        every <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> kind, and the engines and
                        artillery had been brought up from the ships for use against the walls.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whilst every one's attention was
                        engrossed by the struggle going on here, Plator admitted the Romans through
                        the gate of the seaward citadel, and this was captured at once. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Then the defenders, finding themselves forced
                        back into the city, tried to gain the other citadel. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Men who were posted here for the purpose closed the
                        gates against them, and thus shut out from both citadels they were killed or
                        made prisoners. The Macedonian garrison stood in a close phalanx under the
                        wall of the citadel, neither attempting to flee nor taking an active part in
                        the fighting. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Plator persuaded Sulpicius
                        to let them go and they were placed on board and landed at Demetrium in
                        Phthiotis. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Plator himself joined Attalus.
                        Encouraged by his easy success at Oreus, Sulpicius sailed at once with his
                        victorious fleet to Chalcis, <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> but here
                        the result by no means answered his expectations. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The sea which is wide and open at each end of the
                        Euripus contracts here into a narrow channel, which at first sight presents
                            <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> the appearance of a double harbour
                        with two mouths opposite each other. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But
                        it would be difficult to find a more dangerous roadstead for a fleet. Sudden
                        tempestuous winds sweep down from the lofty mountains on both sides, and the
                        Euripus does not, as is commonly asserted, ebb and flow seven times a day
                            <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> at regular intervals, but its
                        waters, driven haphazard like the wind first in one direction and then in
                        another, <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> rush along like a torrent down
                        the side of a precipitous mountain, so that ships are never in quiet waters
                        day or night. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> After Sulpicius had
                        anchored his fleet in these treacherous waters, he found that the town was
                        protected on the one side by the sea, and on the other, the land side, by
                        very strong fortifications, whilst the strength of its garrison and the
                        loyalty of the officers, so different from the duplicity and treason at
                        Oreus, made it impregnable. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> After
                        surveying the difficulties of his position, the Roman commander acted
                            <milestone n="19??" unit="section"/> wisely in desisting from his rash
                        enterprise, and without any further loss of time sailed away to Cynos in
                        Locris, a place situated about a mile from the sea, which served as the
                        emporium of the Opuntians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The beacon fires at Oreus had given Philip
                        warning, but through the treachery of Plator they were lighted too late, and
                        in any case Philip's inferiority in naval strength would have made it
                        extremely difficult for him to reach the island. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> In consequence of this delay he made no effort for its
                        relief, but he hastened to the relief of Chalcis as soon as he got the
                        signal. Although this city is also situated on the island, it is separated
                        from the mainland by such a narrow strait as to allow of its being connected
                        by a bridge, and it is therefore more easy to approach it by land than by
                        sea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Philip marched from Demetrias to
                        Scotusa; he left that place at midnight, and after routing the Aetolians who
                        were holding the pass of Thermopylae drove them in confusion to Heraclea.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He finally reached Elatia in Phocis,
                        having covered more than sixty miles in one day. Almost on the very same day
                        the city of the Opuntians was taken and sacked by Attalus. Sulpicius had
                        left the spoils to him, because Oreus had been sacked by the Romans a few
                        days previously, when the king's troops were elsewhere. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst the Roman fleet was lying off Oreus, Attalus was
                        busily occupied in extorting contributions from the principal citizens of
                        Opus, utterly unaware of Philip's approach. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> So rapid was the Macedonian advance that had not some Cretans who had
                        gone foraging further than usual caught sight of the hostile column in the
                        distance, Attalus would have been completely surprised. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> As it was he fled, without stopping to arm, in wild
                        disorder to his ships, and the men were actually pushing their vessels off
                        when Philip appeared, and even from the water's edge created great alarm
                        amongst the crews. Then he returned to Opus, storming at gods and men
                        because the chance of a great success had been almost snatched out of his
                        hands. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was just as furious with the
                        Opuntians, for, though they might have held out till his arrival, no sooner
                        did they see the enemy than they voluntarily surrendered. </p>
                    <p> After settling matters at Opus, he went on to Thronium. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Attalus had sailed to Oreus, but on learning that
                        Prusias, the king of Bithynia, had violated the frontiers of his dominions
                        he dropped all his projects in Greece, including the Aetolian war, and
                        sailed to Asia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Sulpicius took his fleet
                        back to Aegina, whence he had started in the beginning of spring. Philip
                        captured Thronium with no more difficulty than Attalus had experienced at
                        Opus. The population of this city consisted of refugees from Thebes in
                        Phthiotis. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When the place was captured by
                        Philip, they escaped and put themselves under the protection of the
                        Aetolians, who assigned for their abode a city which had been ruined and
                        abandoned in the previous war with Philip. After his capture of Thronium he
                        advanced to the capture of Tithronon and Drymiae, small unimportant towns in
                        Doris. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Ultimately he reached Elatia,
                        where it was arranged that the embassies from Ptolemy and the Rhodians
                        should meet him. Here they were discussing the question of bringing the
                        Aetolian war to a close-the ambassadors had been present at the recent
                        council of the Romans and Aetolians at Heraclea-when news was brought that
                        Machanidas had decided to attack the Eleans in the midst of their
                        preparations for the Olympic Games. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Philip thought it his duty to prevent this, and accordingly dismissed the
                        ambassadors after assuring them that he was responsible for the war and
                        would place no obstacles in the way of peace, provided its terms were fair
                        and honourable. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He then set off with his
                        army in light marching order, and passed through Boeotia to Megara, and from
                        there he descended to Corinth. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Here he
                        collected supplies, and then advanced towards Phlius and Pheneos. When he
                        had reached Heraea he heard that Machanidas, alarmed at his rapid approach,
                        had made a hurried return to Lacedaemon. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        On receiving this intelligence he repaired to Aegium, in order to be present
                        at the meeting of the Achaean League; he also expected to find there the
                        Carthaginian fleet, which he had sent for in the hope of doing something by
                        sea. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians had left that
                        place a few days previously for Oxeae and then, when they heard that Attalus
                        and the Romans had left Oreus, they sought shelter in the harbours of
                        Acarnania, fearing lest if they were attacked within the strait of Rhium,
                        the neck of the Gulf of Corinth, they should be overpowered. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip was extremely disappointed and
                        vexed at finding that in spite of his rapid movements he was always
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> too late to do anything, and that
                        Fortune mocked his energy and activity by snatching away every opportunity
                        from before his eyes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, he
                        concealed his disappointment in the presence of the council, and spoke in a
                        very confident tone. Appealing to gods and men he declared that at no time
                        or place <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> had he ever failed to go with
                        all possible speed wherever the clash of hostile arms was heard. It would be
                        difficult, he continued, to estimate whether the enemy's anxiety to flee or
                        his own eagerness to fight played the greater part in the war. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> In this way Attalus got away from Opus, and
                        Sulpicius from Chalcis, and now Machanidas had slipped out of his hands. But
                        flight did not always mean victory, and it was impossible to regard as
                        serious a war in which when once you have come into touch with the enemy,
                        you have conquered. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The most important
                        thing was the enemy's own admission that they were no match for him, and in
                        a short <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> time he would win a decisive
                        victory, the enemy would find the result of the battle no better than they
                        had anticipated. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His allies were delighted
                        with his speech. He then made over Heraea and Triphylia to the Achaeans, and
                        on their bringing forward satisfactory evidence that Aliphera in Megalopolis
                        had formed part of their territory, he restored that place also to them.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Subsequently with some vessels
                        furnished by the Achaeans-three quadriremes and as many biremes-he sailed to
                        Anticyra. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He had previously sent into the
                        Gulf of Corinth seven quinqueremes and more than twenty light vessels,
                        intending to strengthen the Carthaginian fleet, and with these he proceeded
                        to Eruthrae in Aetolia near Eupalium, where he disembarked. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The Aetolians were aware of his landing, for all
                        the men who were in the fields or in the neighbouring forts of Potidania or
                        Apollonia fled to the woods and the mountains; their flocks and herds which
                        they were unable in their haste to drive away Philip secured and placed on
                        board. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The whole of the plunder was
                        despatched in charge of Nicias the praetor of the Achaeans to Aegium;
                        Philip, sending his army overland through Boeotia, went himself to Corinth,
                        and from there to Cenchreae. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Here he
                        re-embarked, and sailing past the coast of Attica, round the headland of
                        Sunium and almost through the hostile fleets, arrived at Chalcis. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> In his address to the citizens he spoke in the
                        highest terms of their loyalty and courage in refusing to be moved by either
                        threats or promises, and <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> he urged them,
                        in case they were attacked, to show the same determination to be true to
                        their ally if they thought their own position preferable to that of Opus or
                        Oreus. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> From Chalcis he sailed to Oreus,
                        where he entrusted the administration and defence of the city to those
                        magnates who had fled on the capture of the place rather than betray it to
                        the Romans. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Then he returned to
                        Demetrias, the place from which he had started to render assistance to his
                        allies. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> He now proceeded to lay down the
                        keels of 100 war-ships at Cassandrea, and a large number of shipwrights were
                        assembled for their construction. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> As
                        matters were now quiet in Greece, owing to the departure of Attalus and the
                        effective assistance which Philip had given to his allies in their
                        difficulties, he returned to Macedonia to commence operations against the
                        Maedi. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just at the close of this summer Quintus
                        Fabius, the son of Maximus, who was on the staff of the consul M. Livius,
                        came to Rome to inform the senate that the consul considered L. Porcius and
                        his legions sufficient for the defence of Gaul, in which case he, Livius,
                        and his consular army might be safely withdrawn. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The senate recalled not only Livius, but his colleague
                        as well, but the instructions given to each differed. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> M. Livius was ordered to bring his troops back, but
                        Nero's legions were to remain in their province, confronting Hannibal. The
                        consuls had been in correspondence with each other and had agreed that as
                        they had been of the same mind in their conduct of public affairs, so,
                        though coming from opposite directions, they should approach the City at the
                        same time. Whichever should be the first to reach Praeneste was to wait
                        there for his colleague, and, as it happened, they both arrived there on the
                        same day. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After despatching a summons for
                        the senate to meet at the temple of Bellona in three days' time they went on
                        together towards the City. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The whole
                        population turned out to meet them with shouts of welcome, and each tried to
                        grasp the consuls' hands; congratulations and thanks were showered upon them
                        for having, by their efforts, rendered the commonwealth safe. When the
                        senate was assembled they followed the precedent set by all victorious
                        generals and laid before the House a report of their military operations.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then they made request that in
                        recognition of their energetic and successful conduct of public affairs
                        special honours should be rendered to the gods and they, the consuls, should
                        be allowed to enter the City in triumph The senators passed a decree that
                        their request should be granted out of gratitude to the gods in the first
                        place, and then, next to the gods, out of gratitude to the consuls. A solemn
                        thanksgiving was decreed on their behalf, and each of them was allowed to
                        enjoy a triumph. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As they had been in perfect agreement as
                        to the management of their campaign, they decided that they would not have
                        separate triumphs, and the following arrangement was made: <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As the victory had been won in the province assigned to
                        Livius, and as it had fallen to him to take the auspices on the day of
                        battle, and further, as his army had been brought back to Rome, whilst
                        Nero's army was unable to leave its province, it was decided that Livius
                        should ride in the chariot at the head of his soldiers, and C. Claudius Nero
                        alone on horseback. The triumph thus shared between them enhanced the glory
                        of both, but especially of the one who allowed his comrade to surpass him in
                        honour as much as he himself surpassed him in merit. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> "That horseman," men said to one another, "traversed
                        Italy from end to end in six days, and at the very time when Hannibal
                        believed him to be confronting him in Apulia he was fighting a pitched
                        battle with Hasdrubal in Gaul. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So one
                        consul had checked the advance of two generals, two great captains from the
                        opposite corners of Italy, by opposing his strategy to the one and meeting
                        the other in person. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The mere name of
                        Nero had sufficed to keep Hannibal quiet in his camp, and as to Hasdrubal,
                        what brought about his defeat and destruction but Nero's arrival in the
                        field? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The one consul may ride in a
                        chariot with as many horses as he pleases, the real triumph belongs to the
                        other who is borne on horseback through the City; even if he went on foot
                        Nero's renown would never die, whether through the glory he acquired in war,
                        or the contempt he showed for it in his triumph." These and similar remarks
                        from the spectators followed Nero till he reached the Capitol. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The money they brought into the treasury
                        amounted to 300,000 sesterces and 80,000 of bronze coinage. M. Livius'
                        largesse to his soldiers amounted to fifty-six ases per man, and C. Nero
                        promised to give the same amount to his men as soon as he rejoined his army.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> It is remarked that in their jests
                        and songs the soldiers on that day celebrated the name of C. Claudius Nero
                        more frequently than that of their own consul; and that the members of the
                        equestrian order were full of praises for L. Veturius and Q. Caecilius, and
                        urged the plebs to make them consuls for the coming year. The consuls added
                        considerably to the weight of this recommendation when on the morrow they
                        informed the Assembly with what courage and fidelity the two officers had
                        served them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The time was approaching for the elections
                        and it was decided that they should be conducted by a Dictator. C. Claudius
                        Nero named his colleague M. Livius as Dictator, and he nominated Q.
                        Caecilius as his Master of the Horse. L. Veturius and Q. Caecilius were both
                        elected consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then came the election of
                        praetors; those appointed were C. Servilius, M. Caecilius Metellus, Tiberius
                        Claudius Asellus and Q. Mamilius Turrinus, who was a plebeian aedile at the
                        time. When the elections were over, the Dictator laid down his office and
                        after disbanding his army went on a mission to Etruria. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He had been commissioned by the senate to hold an
                        enquiry as to which cantons in Etruria had entertained the design of
                        deserting to Hasdrubal as soon as he appeared, and also which of them had
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> assisted him with supplies, or men,
                        or in any other way. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Such were the events
                        of the year at home and abroad. The Roman Games were celebrated in full on
                        three successive days by the curule aediles, Cnaeus Servilius Caepio and
                        Servilius Cornelius Lentulus; similarly the Plebeian Games were celebrated
                        by the plebeian aediles, M. Pomponius Matho and Q. Mamilius Turrinus.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was now the thirteenth year of the
                        Punic War. Both the consuls, L. Veturius Philo and Q. Caecilius Metellus,
                        had the same province-Bruttium-assigned to them, that they might jointly
                        carry on operations against Hannibal. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        praetors balloted for their provinces. M. Caecilius Metellus obtained the
                        City jurisdiction; Q. Mamilius, that over aliens. Sicily fell to C.
                        Servilius, and Sardinia to Ti. Claudius. </p>
                    <p> The armies were distributed as follows: One of the consuls took over Nero's
                        army; the other, that which Q. Claudius had commanded; each consisted of two
                        legions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> M. Livius, who was acting as
                        proconsul for the year, took over from C. Terentius the two legions of
                        volunteer slaves in Etruria. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was also
                        decreed that Q. Mamilius, to whom the jurisdiction over aliens had been
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> allotted, should transfer his
                        judicial business to his colleague, and hold Gaul with the army which L.
                        Porcius had commanded as propraetor; he was also instructed to ravage the
                        fields of those Gauls who had gone over to the Carthaginians on the arrival
                        of Hasdrubal. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> C. Servilius was to protect
                        Sicily, as C. Mamilius had done, with the two legions of the survivors of
                        Cannae. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The old army in Sardinia, under
                        A. Hostilius, was recalled, and the consuls enrolled a new legion which
                        Tiberius Claudius was to take with him to the island. A year's extension of
                        command was granted to Q. Claudius, that he might remain in charge at
                        Tarentum, and to C. Hostilius Tubero, that he might continue to act at
                        Capua. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> M. Valerius, who had been charged
                        with the defence of the Sicilian seaboard, was ordered to hand over thirty
                        ships to the praetor' C. Servilius, and return to Rome with the rest of his
                        fleet. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the anxiety caused by the strain of
                        such a serious war when men referred every occurrence, fortunate or the
                        reverse, to the direct action of the gods, numerous portents were announced.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At Tarracina the temple of Jupiter, at
                        Satricum that of Mater Matuta were struck by lightning. At the latter place
                        quite as much alarm was created by the appearance of two snakes which glided
                        straight through the doors into the temple of Jupiter. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> From Antium it was reported that the ears of corn
                        seemed to those who were reaping them to be covered with blood. At Caere a
                        pig had been farrowed with two heads, and a lamb yeaned which was both male
                        and female. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Two suns were said to have
                        been seen at Alba, and at Fregellae it had become light during the night. In
                        the precinct of Rome an ox was said to have spoken; the altar of Neptune in
                        the Circus Flaminius was asserted to have been bathed in perspiration, and
                        the temples of Ceres, Salus and Quirinus were all struck by lightning.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls received orders to expiate
                        the portents by sacrificing full-grown victims and to appoint a day of
                        solemn intercession. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These measures were
                        carried out in accordance with the senatorial resolution. What was a much
                        more terrifying experience than all the portents reported from the country
                        or seen in the City, was the extinction of the fire in the temple of Vesta.
                        The vestal who was in charge of the fire that night was severely flogged by
                        order of P. Licinius, the Pontifex Maximus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Though this was no portent sent by the gods, but merely the result of
                        human carelessness, it was decided to sacrifice full-grown victims and hold
                        a service of solemn supplication in the temple of Vestal. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Before the consuls left for the seat of
                        war, they were advised by the senate "to see to it that the plebeians were
                        reinstated on their holdings. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Through the
                        goodness of the gods the burden of war had now been shifted from the City of
                        Rome and from Latium, and men could dwell in the country parts without fear,
                        it was <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> by no means fitting that they
                        should be more concerned for the cultivation of Sicily than for that of
                        Italy." The people found it, however, anything but an easy matter.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The small holders had been carried
                        off by the war, there was hardly any servile labour available, the cattle
                        had been driven off as plunder, and the homesteads had been either stripped
                        or burnt. Still, at the authoritative behest of the consuls a considerable
                        number did return to their farms. What led to the senate taking up this
                        question was the presence of deputations from Placentia and Cremona, who
                        came to complain of the invasion and wasting of their country by their
                        neighbours, the Gauls. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A large proportion
                        of their settlers, they said, had disappeared, their cities were almost
                        without inhabitants, and the countryside was a deserted wilderness. The
                        praetor Mamilius was charged with the defence of these colonies; the
                        consuls, acting on a resolution of the senate, published an edict requiring
                        all those who were citizens of Cremona and Placentia to return to their
                        homes before a certain day. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At last,
                        towards the beginning of spring, they left for the seat of war. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> The consul Q. Caecilius took over the army from
                        C. Nero, and L. Veturius, the one which Q. Claudius had commanded, and this
                        he brought up to its full strength with the fresh levies which he had
                        raised. They led their armies into the district of Consentia, and ravaged it
                        in all directions. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> As they were returning
                        laden with plunder they were attacked in a narrow pass by a force of
                        Bruttians and Numidian javelin-men, and not only the plunder but the troops
                        themselves were in danger. There was, however, more alarm and confusion than
                        real fighting. The plunder was sent forward and the legions succeeded in
                        getting into a position free from danger. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        They advanced into Lucania, and the whole of the district returned to its
                        allegiance to Rome without offering any resistance. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No action was fought with Hannibal this
                        year, for after the blow <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> which had
                        fallen upon him and upon his country, he made no forward movement, nor did
                        the Romans care to disturb him, such was their impression of the powers
                        which that single general possessed, even while his cause was everywhere
                        round him crumbling into ruin. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I am
                        inclined to think that he deserves our admiration more in adversity than in
                        the time of his greatest successes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For
                        thirteen years he had been carrying on war with varying fortune in an
                        enemy's country far from home. His army was not made up of his own
                        fellow-countrymen, it was a mixed assemblage of various nationalities who
                        had nothing in common, neither laws nor customs, nor language, who differed
                        in appearance, dress <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and arms, who were
                        strangers to one another in their religious observances, who hardly
                        recognised the same gods. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And yet he had
                        united them so closely together that no disturbance ever broke out, either
                        amongst the soldiers themselves or against their commander, though very
                        often money and supplies were lacking and it was through want of these that
                        numerous incidents of a disgraceful character had occurred between the
                        generals and their soldiers in the First Punic War. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He had rested all his hopes of victory on Hasdrubal and
                        his army, and after that army had been wiped out he withdrew into Bruttium
                        and abandoned the rest of Italy to the Romans. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Is it not a matter of surprise that no mutiny broke out
                        in his camp? For in addition to all his other difficulties, there was no
                        prospect of feeding his army except <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> from
                        the resources of Bruttium, and even if the whole of that country had been in
                        cultivation it would have afforded but meager support for so large an army.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But as it was, a large part of the
                        population had been diverted from the tillage of the soil by the war and by
                        their traditional and innate love of brigandage. He received no assistance
                        from home, for the government was mainly concerned about keeping their hold
                        on Spain, just as though everything in Italy was going on successfully. </p>
                    <p> The situation in Spain was in some respects similar, in others completely
                        dissimilar to the state of affairs in Italy. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> It was similar in so far as the Carthaginians after
                        their defeat and the loss of their general had been driven into the most
                        distant parts of Spain to the shores of the ocean. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> It was dissimilar because the natural features of the
                        country and the character of the inhabitants made Spain more fitted than
                        Italy, more fitted, in fact, than any country in the world for the constant
                        renewal of hostilities. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Though it was the
                        first province, at all events on the continent, into which the Romans made
                        their way, it was, owing to this cause, the very last to be completely
                        subjugated, and this <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> only in our own
                        days under the conduct and auspices of Augustus Caesar. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Hasdrubal Gisgo, who, next to the Barcine family, was
                        the greatest and most brilliant general that held command in this war, was
                        encouraged by Mago to renew hostilities. He left Gades, and traversing
                        Further Spain, raised a force of 50,000 infantry and 4500 cavalry.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> As to the strength of his cavalry the
                        authorities are generally agreed, but some writers assert that the infantry
                        force which he led to Silpia amounted to 70,000 men. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Near this city the two Carthaginian commanders encamped
                        on a wide and open plain, determined to accept battle if offered. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When intelligence was brought to Scipio of
                        the muster of this large army, he did not consider that he could meet it
                        with his Roman legions unless he employed his native auxiliaries to give at
                        all events the appearance of greater strength. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> At the same time he felt that he ought not to depend
                        too much upon them, for if they changed sides it might lead to the same
                        disaster as that which had overtaken his father and his uncle. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Culchas, whose authority extended over
                        twenty-eight towns, had promised to raise a force of infantry and cavalry
                        during the winter, and Silanus was sent to bring them up. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Then breaking up his quarters at Tarraco, Scipio
                        marched down to Castulo, picking up small contingents furnished by the
                        friendly tribes which lay on his line of march. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> There Silanus joined him with 3000 infantry and 500
                        cavalry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His entire army, Romans and
                        allied contingents, infantry and cavalry, amounted now to 55,000 men. With
                        this force he advanced to meet the enemy and took up his position near
                        Baecula. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Whilst his men were entrenching
                        their camp they were attacked by Mago and Masinissa with the whole of their
                        cavalry and would have been thrown into great disorder had not Scipio made a
                        charge with a body of horse which he had placed in concealment behind a
                        hill. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These speedily routed those of the
                        assailants who had ridden close up to the lines and were actually attacking
                        the entrenching parties; with the others, however, who kept their ranks and
                        were advancing in steady order the conflict was more sustained, and for a
                        considerable time remained undecided. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But
                        when the cohorts of light infantry came in from the <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> outposts, and the men at work on the intrenchments had
                        seized their arms and, fresh for action, were in ever increasing numbers
                        relieving their wearied comrades until a considerable body of armed men were
                        hastening from the camp to do battle, the Carthaginians and Numidians
                        retreated. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At first they retired in order
                        though hurriedly and kept their ranks, but when the Romans pressed their
                            <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> attacks home and resistance was no
                        longer possible, they broke and fled as best they could. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Though this action did much to raise the spirits of the
                        Romans and depress those of the enemy, there were for several days incessant
                        skirmishes between the cavalry and light infantry on both sides. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the strength of each side had been
                        sufficiently tested in these encounters Hasdrubal led out his army to
                        battle, on which the Romans did the same. Each army remained standing in
                        front of its camp, neither caring to begin the fight. Towards sunset the two
                        armies, first the Carthaginian and then the Roman, marched back to camp.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This went on for some days; the
                        Carthaginians were always the first to get into line and the first to
                        receive the order to retire when they were tired out with standing. No
                        forward movement took place on either side, no missile was discharged, no
                        battle-shout raised. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans were
                        posted in the centre on the one side, the Carthaginians in the centre of the
                        other; the flanks on both armies were composed of Spanish troops. In front
                        of the Carthaginian line were the elephants which looked in the distance
                        like towers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was generally supposed in
                        both camps that they would fight in the order in which they had been
                        standing, and that the main battle would be between the Romans and
                        Carthaginians in the centre, the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                        principals in the war and fairly matched in courage and in arms. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> When Scipio found that this was assumed as a
                        matter of course, he carefully altered his dispositions for the day on which
                        he intended to fight. The previous evening he sent a tessera through the
                        camp ordering the men to take their breakfast and see that their horses were
                        fed before daybreak, <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the cavalry were at
                        the same time to be fully armed with their horses ready, bitted and saddled.
                        Day had scarcely broken when he sent the whole of his cavalry with the light
                        infantry against the Carthaginian outposts, and at once followed them up
                        with the heavy infantry of the legions under his personal command.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Contrary to universal expectation he
                        had made his wings the strongest part of his army by posting the Roman
                        troops there, the auxiliaries occupied the centre. </p>
                    <p> The shouts of the cavalry roused Hasdrubal and he rushed out of his tent.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When he saw the melee in front of the
                        rampart and the disordered state of his men, and in the distance the
                        glittering standards of the legions and the whole plain covered with the
                        enemy, he at once sent the whole of his mounted force against the hostile
                        cavalry. He then led his infantry out of the camp, and formed his battle
                        line without any change in the existing order. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The cavalry fight had now been going on for some time
                        without either side gaining the advantage. Nor could any decision be arrived
                        at, for as each side was in turn driven back they retreated into safety
                        amongst their infantry. But when the main bodies were within half a mile of
                        each other, Scipio recalled his cavalry and ordered them to pass to the rear
                        of the infantry, whose ranks opened out to give them passage, he then formed
                        them into two divisions, and posted one as a support behind each of the
                        wings. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then when the moment for executing
                        his maneuver arrived he ordered the Spaniards in the centre to make a slow
                        advance, and sent word to Silanus and <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                        Marcius that they were to extend to the left as they had seen him extend to
                        the right, and engage the enemy with their light cavalry and infantry before
                        the centers had time to close. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Each wing
                        was thus lengthened by three infantry cohorts and three troops of horse,
                        besides velites, and in this formation they advanced against the enemy at a
                        run, the others following en echelon. The line curved inwards towards the
                        centre because of the slower advance of the Spaniards. The wings were
                        already engaged whilst the Carthaginians and African veterans, the main
                        strength of their army, had not yet had the chance of discharging a single
                        missile. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> They did not dare to leave their
                        place in the line and help their comrades for fear of leaving the centre
                        open to the advance of the enemy. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The
                        wings were being pressed by a double attack, the cavalry and light infantry
                        had wheeled round and were making a flank charge, whilst the cohorts were
                        pressing their front in order to sever them from their centre. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The struggle had now become a very
                        one-sided one in all parts of the field. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Not only were untrained Balearics and raw Spanish levies face to face with
                        the Roman and Latin legionaries but as the day went on, the physical
                        strength of Hasdrubal's army began to give way. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Surprised by the sudden attack in the early morning
                        they had been compelled to go into battle before they could strengthen
                        themselves with food. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was with this
                        view that Scipio had deliberately delayed the fight till late in the day,
                        for it was not until the seventh hour that the attack began on the wings,
                        and it was some time after that before the battle reached the <milestone
                            n="5??" unit="section"/> centre, so that, what with the heat of the day,
                        the fatigue of standing under arms, and the hunger and thirst from which
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> they were suffering, they were worn
                        out before they closed with the enemy. Thus exhausted they leaned on their
                        shields as they stood. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To complete their
                        discomfiture the elephants, scared by the sudden onsets of the cavalry and
                        the rapid movements of the light infantry, rushed from the wings into the
                        centre of the line. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Wearied and depressed,
                        the enemy began to retreat, keeping their ranks however, just as if they had
                        been ordered to retire. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But when the
                        victors saw that matters were going in their favour they made still more
                        furious attacks in all parts of the field, which the enemy were almost
                        powerless to withstand, though Hasdrubal tried <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> to rally them and keep them from giving way by calling
                        out that the hill in their rear would afford them a safe retreat if they
                        would retire in good order. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Their fears,
                        however, got the better of their sense of shame, and when those nearest to
                        the enemy gave way, their example was suddenly followed by all and there was
                        a universal flight. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their first halt was
                        on the lower slope of the hill, and as the Romans hesitated about mounting
                        the hill, they began to re-form their ranks, but when they saw them steadily
                        advancing they again fled and were driven back in disorder to their camp.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Romans were not far from the
                        rampart and would have carried the camp in their onset had not the brilliant
                        sunshine which often glows between heavy showers been succeeded <milestone
                            n="14??" unit="section"/> by such a storm that the victors could hardly
                        get back to their camp, and some were even deterred by superstitious fears
                        from attempting anything further for the day. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Although the night and the storm invited the
                        Carthaginians, exhausted as they were by their toil and many of them by
                        their wounds, to take the rest they so sorely needed, yet their fears and
                        the danger they were in allowed them no respite. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Fully expecting an attack on their camp as soon as it
                        was light they strengthened their rampart with large stones collected from
                        all the valleys round, hoping to find in their intrenchments the defence
                        which their arms had failed to afford them. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                        /> The desertion of their allies, however, decided them to seek safety in
                        flight rather than risk another battle. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        The first to abandon them was Attenes, chief of the Turdetani; he went over
                        with a considerable body of his countrymen, and this was followed by the
                        surrender of two fortified towns with their garrisons to the Romans.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> For fear of the evil spreading and
                        the spirit of disaffection becoming general, Hasdrubal shifted his camp the
                        following night. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the outposts brought intelligence of
                        the enemy's departure Scipio sent on his cavalry and followed with his
                        entire army. Such was the rapidity of the pursuit that had they followed in
                        Hasdrubal's direct track they must have caught him up. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> But, acting on the advice of their guides, they took a
                        shorter route to the river Baetis, so that they might be able to attack him
                        if he attempted its passage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Finding the
                        river closed to him, Hasdrubal turned his course towards the ocean, and his
                        hurried march, which in its haste and confusion looked like a flight gave
                        him a considerable start on the Roman legions. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Their cavalry and light infantry harassed and retarded
                        him by attacking him <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> in flank and rear,
                        and whilst he was continually forced to halt to repel first the cavalry and
                        then infantry skirmishers, the legions came up. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Now it was no longer a battle but sheer butchery, until
                        the general himself set the example of flight and escaped to the nearest
                        hills with some 6000 men, many of them without arms. The rest were killed or
                        made prisoners. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians hastily
                        improvised an intrenched camp on the highest point of the hills, and as the
                        Romans found it useless to attempt the precipitous ascent, they had no
                        difficulty in making themselves safe. But a bare and sterile height was
                        hardly a place in which to stand even a few days' siege, and there were
                        numerous desertions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At last Hasdrubal
                        sent for ships-he was not far from the sea-and fled in the night, leaving
                        his army to its fate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As soon as Scipio
                        heard of his flight he left Silanus to keep up the investment of the
                        Carthaginian camp with 10,000 infantry and 1000 cavalry, whilst he himself
                        with the rest of his force returned to Tarraco. During his seventy days'
                        march to this place, he took steps to ascertain the attitude of the various
                        chiefs and tribes towards Rome, so that they might be recompensed as they
                        deserved. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After his departure Masinissa
                        came to <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> a secret understanding with
                        Silanus, and crossed over with a small following to Africa, to induce his
                        people to support him in his new policy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        The reasons which determined him on this sudden change were not evident at
                        the time, but the loyalty which he subsequently displayed throughout his
                        long life to its close proved beyond question that his motives at the
                        beginning were carefully weighed. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After
                        Mago had sailed to Gades in the ships which Hasdrubal had sent back for him,
                        the rest of the army abandoned by their generals broke up, some <milestone
                            n="14??" unit="section"/> deserting to the Romans, others dispersing
                        amongst the neighbouring tribes. No body of troops remained worth
                        consideration either for numbers or fighting strength. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Such, in the main, was the way in which under the
                        conduct and auspices of Publius Scipio the Carthaginians were expelled from
                        Spain, fourteen years from the commencement of the war, and five years after
                        Scipio assumed supreme command. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Not long
                        after Mago's departure Silanus joined Scipio at Tarraco, and reported that
                        the war was at an end. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Scipio was sent to Rome in charge
                        of numerous prisoners of high rank to announce the subjugation of Spain.
                        Everybody else welcomed this brilliant success with feelings of delight and
                        exultation, but the one man who had achieved it and <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> whose thirst for solid and lasting renown was
                        insatiable looked upon his conquest of Spain as only a small instalment of
                        what his lofty ambition led him to hope for. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Already he was looking to Africa and the great city of Carthage as
                        destined to crown his glory and immortalise his name. This was the goal
                        before him and he thought it best to prepare the way to it by gaining over
                        the kings and tribes in Africa. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He began
                        by approaching Syphax, king of the Masaesulians, a tribe of Moorish
                        nationality. They lived opposite that part of the Spanish coast where New
                        Carthage lies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At that time there existed
                        a treaty of alliance between their king and Carthage, but Scipio did not
                        imagine that Syphax would regard the sanctity of treaties more scrupulously
                        than they are generally regarded by barbarians whose fidelity depends upon
                        the caprices of fortune. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly he
                        sent C. Laelius to him with presents to win him over. The barbarian was
                        delighted with the presents, and, as he saw that the cause of Rome was
                        everywhere successful, whilst the Carthaginians had failed in Italy and
                        entirely disappeared from Spain, he consented to <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> become friendly to Rome, but insisted that the mutual
                        ratification of the treaty should take place in the presence of the Roman
                        general. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All that Laelius could obtain
                        from the king was a safe-conduct, and with that he returned to Scipio.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In furtherance of his designs on
                        Africa it was of supreme importance for him to secure Syphax; he was the
                        most powerful of the native princes, and had even attempted hostilities
                        against Carthage; moreover, his frontiers were only separated from Spain by
                        a narrow strait. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Scipio thought it worth while running
                        considerable risk in order to accomplish his end, and as it could not be
                        effected in any other way, he made arrangements for visiting Syphax.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Leaving the defence of Spain in the
                        hands of L. Marcius at Tarraco and M. Silanus at New Carthage, to which
                        latter place he had proceeded by forced marches from Tarraco, he sailed
                        across to Africa accompanied by C. Laelius. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> He only took two quinqueremes, and as the sea was calm most of the
                        passage was made by rowing, though a light breeze occasionally assisted
                        them. It so happened that Hasdrubal after his expulsion from Spain entered
                        the harbour at the same time. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He had
                        brought his seven triremes to anchor and was preparing to land when the two
                        quinqueremes were sighted. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> No one
                        entertained the smallest doubt that they belonged to the enemy and could
                        easily be overpowered by superior numbers before they gained the harbour.
                        The efforts of the soldiers and sailors, however, to get their arms ready
                        and the ships <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> into trim amidst much
                        noise and confusion were rendered futile by a freshening breeze from the
                        sea, which filled the sails of the quinqueremes and carried them into port
                        before the Carthaginians could get up their anchors. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> As they were now in the king's harbour, no one ventured
                        to make any further attempt to molest them. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                        /> So Hasdrubal, who was the first to land. and Scipio and Laelius, who
                        disembarked soon afterwards, all made their way to the king. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Syphax regarded it as an exceptional
                        honour-as indeed <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> it was-for the captains
                        of the two most powerful nations of their time to come to him seeking his
                        friendship and alliance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He invited them
                        both to be his guests, and as Fortune had <milestone n="4??" unit="section"
                        /> willed that they should be under the same roof and at <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> the same hearth he tried to induce them to confer
                        together with the view of removing all causes of quarrel. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio declined on the ground that he had no personal
                        quarrel <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> with the Carthaginian and he was
                        powerless to discuss affairs of State without the orders of the senate.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The king was anxious that it should
                        not seem as if one of his guests was excluded from his table, and he did his
                        utmost to persuade Scipio to be present. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        He raised no objection, and they both dined with the king, and at his
                        particular request occupied the same couch. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> Such was Scipio's charm of manner and innate tact in dealing with
                        everybody that he completely won over not only Syphax, who as a barbarian
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> was unaccustomed to Roman manners,
                        but even his deadly enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal
                        openly avowed that "he admired Scipio more now that he had made his personal
                        acquaintance than after his military successes, and he had no doubt that
                        Syphax <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> and his kingdom were already at
                        the disposal of Rome, such skill did the Roman possess in winning men.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The question for the Carthaginians
                        was not how Spain had been lost, but how Africa was to be retained.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> It was not from a love of travel or a
                        passion for sailing along pleasant shores that a great Roman commander had
                        quitted his newly subjugated province and his armies and crossed over with
                        two vessels to Africa, <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> the land of his
                        enemies, and trusted himself to the untried honour of a king. <milestone
                            n="17" unit="section"/> His real motive was the hope of becoming master
                        of Africa; <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> this project he had long been
                        pondering over; he openly complained that 'Scipio was not <milestone
                            n="19??" unit="section"/> conducting war in Africa as Hannibal was in
                        Italy."' <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> After the treaty with Syphax was
                        concluded Scipio set sail from Africa and, after a four days' passage in
                        which he was buffeted by changeable and mostly stormy winds, reached the
                        harbour of New Carthage. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Spain was now quiet as far as war with
                        Carthage was concerned, but it was quite evident that some communities
                        conscious of wrong-doing were kept quiet more by their fears than by any
                        feeling of loyalty to Rome. Amongst these Iliturgi and Castulo were foremost
                        in importance and foremost in guilt. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As
                        long as Roman arms were successful Castulo remained true to her alliance;
                        after the Scipios and their armies were destroyed they revolted to Carthage.
                        Iliturgi had gone further, for the inhabitants had betrayed and put to death
                        those who had sought refuge with them after those disasters, thus
                        aggravating their treason by crime. To take action against these cities
                        immediately on his arrival in Spain, whilst the issue was still undecided,
                        might have been justifiable but hardly wise. Now, however, that matters were
                        settled, it was felt that the hour of punishment had arrived. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio sent orders to L. Marcius to take a third
                        part of his force to Castulo and at once invest the place, and with the
                        remainder he himself marched to Iliturgi where he arrived after a five days'
                        march. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The gates were closed and every
                        preparation had been made to repel an assault; the townsmen were quite
                        conscious of the punishment they deserved, and any formal declaration of war
                        was, therefore, unnecessary. Scipio made this the subject of his address to
                        his soldiers. "The Spaniards," he said, "by closing their gates have shown
                        how well they deserve the punishment which they fear. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> We must treat them with much greater severity than we
                        treated the Carthaginians; with the latter we contend for glory and
                        dominion, with hardly any feeling of anger, but from the former we have to
                        exact the penalty for cruelty, treachery and murder. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The time has come for you to avenge the atrocious
                        massacre of your fellow-soldiers and the treachery meditated against
                        yourselves had you been carried there in your flight. You will make it clear
                        for all time by this awful example that no one must ever consider a Roman
                        citizen or a Roman soldier a fit subject for ill-treatment, whatever his
                        condition may be." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Roused by their general's words the men
                        began to prepare for the assault, storming parties were picked out of all
                        the maniples and supplied with ladders, and the army was formed into two
                        divisions, one being placed under the command of Laelius, so that the town
                        might be attacked from opposite sides and a twofold terror created.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The defenders were stimulated to a
                        determined and prolonged resistance not by their general or their chiefs but
                        by the fear which came from a consciousness of guilt. With their past crime
                        in mind they warned each other that the enemy was seeking not victory so
                        much as vengeance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The question was not
                        how to escape from death but where to meet it, whether, sword in hand, on
                        the battlefield where the fortune of war often raises up the vanquished and
                        flings the victor to the ground, or amidst the ashes of their city before
                        the eyes of their captive wives and children after being torn with the lash
                        and subjected to shameful and horrible tortures. With this prospect before
                        them every man who could carry arms took his part in the fighting, and even
                        the women and children working beyond their strength supplied missiles to
                        the combatants, and carried stones up to the walls for those who were
                        strengthening the defences. Not only was their liberty at stake-that motive
                        only inspires the brave-but they had before their eyes the very extremity of
                        torture and a shameful death. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As they
                        looked at each other and saw that each was trying to outdo all the rest in
                        toil and danger, their courage was fired, and they offered such a furious
                        resistance that the army which had conquered Spain was again and again
                        repulsed from the walls of one solitary city, and fell back in confusion
                        after a contest which brought it no honour. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> Scipio was afraid that the futile efforts of his troops might raise the
                        enemies' courage and depress his own men, and he decided to take his part in
                        the fighting and his share of the danger. Reproaching his soldiers for their
                        cowardice he ordered the ladders to be brought up and threatened to mount
                        himself if the rest hung back. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He had
                        already reached the foot of the wall and was in imminent danger when shouts
                        arose on all sides from the soldiers who were anxious for their commander's
                        safety, and the ladders were at once planted against the wall. Laelius now
                        delivered his attack from the other side of the town. This broke the back of
                        the resistance; the walls were cleared of their defenders and seized by the
                        Romans, and in the tumult the citadel also was captured on that side where
                        it was considered impregnable. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Its capture was effected by some African
                        deserters who were serving with the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Whilst the attention of the townsmen was directed to defending the
                        positions which appeared to be in danger and the assailants were mounting
                        their ladders wherever they could approach the walls, these men noticed that
                        the highest part of the city, which was protected by precipitous cliffs, was
                        left unfortified and undefended. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These
                        Africans, men of light make and through constant training extremely agile,
                        were furnished with iron hooks, and where the projections of the cliff gave
                        them a footing they <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> climbed it, when
                        they came to a place where it was too steep or too smooth they fixed the
                        hooks in at moderate intervals and used them as steps, those in front
                        pulling up those behind, and those below pushing up those above them.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In this way, they managed to reach the
                        top, and no sooner had they done so than they ran down with loud shouts into
                        the city which the Romans had already captured. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> And now the hatred and resentment which had prompted
                        the attack on the city showed itself. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> No
                        one thought of making prisoners or securing plunder though everything was at
                        the mercy of the spoilers; the scene was one of indiscriminate butchery,
                        non-combatants together with those in arms, women equally with men were all
                        alike massacred; the ruthless savagery extended even to the slaughter of
                        infants. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then they flung lighted brands on
                        the houses and what the fire could not consume was completely demolished. So
                        bent were they upon obliterating every vestige of the city, and blotting out
                        all record of their foes. From there Scipio marched to Castulo. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> This place was being defended by natives from the
                        surrounding towns and also by the remains of the Carthaginian army who had
                        gathered there after their flight. But Scipio's approach had been preceded
                        by the news of the fall of Iliturgi, and this spread dismay and despair
                        everywhere. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The interests of the
                        Carthaginians and of the Spaniards were quite distinct, each party consulted
                        for <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> its own safety without regard to
                        the other, and what was at first mutual suspicion soon led to an open
                        rupture between them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Cerdubelus openly
                        advised the Spaniards to surrender, Himilco, the Carthaginian commander,
                        counselled resistance. Cerdubelus came to a secret understanding with the
                        Roman general, and betrayed the city and the Carthaginians into his hands.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> More clemency was shown in this
                        victory; the town was not so deeply involved in guilt and the voluntary
                        surrender went far to soften any feelings of resentment. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this Marcius was sent to reduce to
                        submission any tribes that had not yet been subjugated. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio returned to New Carthage to discharge his vows
                        and to exhibit the gladiatorial spectacle which he had prepared in honour of
                        the memory of his father and his uncle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The gladiators on this occasion were not drawn from the class from which the
                        trainers usually take them-slaves and men who sell their blood-but were all
                        volunteers and gave their services gratuitously. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Some had been sent by their chiefs to give an
                        exhibition of the instinctive courage of their race, others professed their
                        willingness to fight out of compliment to their general, others again were
                        drawn by a spirit of rivalry to challenge one another to single combat.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There were several who had outstanding
                        quarrels with one another and who agreed to seize this opportunity of
                        deciding them by the sword on the agreed condition that the vanquished was
                        to be at the disposal of the victor. It was not only obscure individuals who
                        were doing this. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two distinguished members
                        of the native nobility, Corbis and Orsua, first cousins to each other, who
                        were disputing the primacy of a city called Ibes gave out that they intended
                        to settle their dispute with the sword. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Corbis was the elder of the two, but Orsua's father had been the last to
                        hold that dignity, having succeeded his brother. Scipio wanted them to
                        discuss the question calmly and peaceably, but as they had refused to do so
                        at the request of <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> their own relations,
                        they told him that they would not accept the arbitrament of any one, whether
                        god or man except Mars, and to him alone would they appeal. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The elder relied upon his strength, the younger on his
                        youth; they both preferred to fight to the death rather than that one should
                        be subject to the commands of the other. They presented a striking spectacle
                        to the army and an equally striking proof of the mischief which the passion
                        for power works amongst men. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The elder
                        cousin by his familiarity with arms and his dexterity easily prevailed over
                        the rough untrained strength of the younger. The gladiatorial contests were
                        followed by funeral games with all the pomp which the resources of the
                        province and the camp could furnish. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meantime Scipio's lieutenants were by no
                        means inactive. Marcius crossed the Baetis, called by the natives the
                        Certis, and received the surrender of two cities without striking a blow.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Astapa was a city which had always
                        been on the side of Carthage. But it was not this that created a strong
                        feeling of resentment so much as its extraordinary hatred against the
                        Romans, far more than was justified by the necessities of war. Neither the
                        situation nor the fortifications of the city were such as to inspire its
                        inhabitants with confidence, but their love of brigandage induced them to
                        make raids on the territories of their neighbours who were allies of Rome.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In these excursions they made a
                        practice of capturing any Roman soldiers or camp sutlers or traders whom
                        they came across. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As it was dangerous to
                        travel in small parties, large companies used to travel together and one of
                        these whilst crossing the frontier was surprised by the brigands who were
                        lying in ambush, and all were killed. When the Roman army advanced to attack
                        the place, the inhabitants, fully aware of the chastisement which their
                        crime merited, felt quite certain that the enemy were too much incensed to
                        allow of any hope of safety in surrender. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Despairing of protection either in their walls or their arms, they resolved
                        upon a deed equally cruel and horrible to themselves and to those who
                        belonged to them. Collecting the more valuable of their possessions they
                        piled them up into a heap in a selected place in their forum. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> On this pile they ordered their wives and
                        children to take their seats and then heaped round them a quantity of wood,
                        on the top of which they threw dead brushwood. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Fifty armed men were told off to guard their
                        possessions and the persons of those who were dearer than their possessions,
                        and the following instructions were given them: "Remain on guard as long as
                        the battle is doubtful, but if you see that is going against us, and the
                        city is on the point of being captured, you know that those whom you see
                        going into action will never return alive, and we implore you by all the
                        gods celestial and infernal in the name of liberty, liberty which will end
                        in either an honourable death or a dishonourable servitude, that you leave
                        nothing on which a savage enemy can vent his rage. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Fire and sword are in your hands. Better that faithful
                        and loving hands should make away with what is doomed to die than that the
                        enemy should add mockery and scorn to murder. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> "These admonitions were followed by a dire curse on any
                        one who was turned from his purpose by hope of life or by softheartedness. </p>
                    <p> Then they flung open the gates and burst out in a tumultuous charge. There
                        was no advanced post strong enough to check them, for the last thing to be
                        feared was that the besieged would venture outside their walls. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> One or two troops of horse and some light
                        infantry were sent against them from the camp, and a fierce irregular fight
                        ensued in which the troopers who had been first to come into collision with
                        the enemy were routed, and this created a panic amongst the light infantry.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The attack would have been pushed
                        even to the foot of the rampart if the pick of the legions had not made the
                        most of the few minutes allowed them for getting into line. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> As it was, there was at first some wavering
                        amongst the front ranks, for the enemy, blinded by rage, rushed with mad
                        recklessness upon wounds and death. Then the veterans who came up in
                        support, unshaken by the frantic onset, cut down the front ranks and stayed
                        the advance of those behind. When in their turn they tried to force the
                        enemy back they found that not a man would give ground, they were all
                        resolved to die where they stood. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On this
                        the Romans extended their lines, which their superiority in numbers enabled
                        them to do easily, until they outflanked the enemy, who fighting in a
                        compact body were killed to a man. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The wholesale slaughter was at any rate
                        the work of an exasperated soldiery who met their armed foes in the shock of
                        open battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But a much more horrible
                        butchery took place in the city, where a weak and defenceless crowd of women
                        and children were massacred by their own people, and their still writhing
                        bodies flung on to the lighted pile which was again almost extinguished by
                        the streams of blood. And last of all the men themselves, exhausted by the
                        pitiful slaughter of those dear to them, flung themselves arms and all into
                        the midst of the flames. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All had perished
                        by the time the Romans came on the scene. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        At first they stood horror-struck at such a fearful sight, then, seeing the
                        melted gold and silver flowing amongst the other articles which made up the
                        heap, the greediness common to human nature impelled them to try and snatch
                        what they could out of the fire. Some were caught by the flames, others were
                        scorched by the heated air, for those in front could not retreat owing to
                        the crowd pressing on behind. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thus Astapa
                        was destroyed without yielding any plunder to the soldiers. After accepting
                        the surrender of the remaining cities in that district Marcius led his
                        victorious army back to Scipio at New Carthage. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Just at this time some deserters came from Gades and
                        promised to deliver up the city with its Carthaginian garrison and the
                        commandant and also the ships in the harbour. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> After his flight Mago had taken up his quarters in that
                        city, and with the help of the ships which he had assembled he had got
                        together a considerable force, partly from the opposite coast of Africa and
                        partly through the agency of Hanno from the Spanish tribes round. After
                        guarantees of good faith had been given on both sides, Scipio sent Marcius
                        with the cohorts of light infantry and Laelius with seven triremes and one
                        quinquereme to conduct joint operations against the place by sea and land.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio was overtaken by a serious illness,
                        which rumour, however, made still more serious, as each man from the innate
                        love of exaggeration added some fresh detail to what he had already heard.
                        The whole of Spain, especially the remoter parts, was much agitated at the
                        news, and it was easy to judge what an amount of trouble would have been
                        caused by his actual death from seeing what storms arose from the groundless
                        rumour of it. Friendly states did not preserve their fidelity, the army did
                        not remain loyal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Mandonius and Indibilis
                        had made up their minds, that after the expulsion of the Carthaginians the
                        sovereignty of Spain would pass to them. When they found that their hopes
                        were frustrated they called out their countrymen, the Lacetani, and raised a
                        force amongst the Celtiberians with which they ravaged the country of the
                        Suessitanians and the Sedetanians, who were allies of Rome. A disturbance of
                        a different kind, an act of madness on the part of the Romans themselves,
                        occurred in the camp at Sucro. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was held
                        by a force of 8000 men who were stationed there to protect the tribes on
                        this side the Ebro. The vague rumours about their commander's life were not
                        however the primary cause of their movement. A long period of inactivity
                        had, as usual, demoralised them, and they chafed against the restraints of
                        peace after being accustomed to live on the plunder captured from the enemy.
                        At first their discontent was confined to murmurs amongst themselves. "If
                        there is war going on in the province," they said, "what are we doing here
                        amongst a peaceable population? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If the war
                        is at an end why are we not taken back to Rome? "Then they demanded their
                        arrears of pay with an insolence quite inconsistent with military discipline
                        or the respect which soldiers should show towards their officers. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The men at the outposts insulted the tribunes as
                        they went their rounds of inspection, and some went off during the night to
                        plunder the peaceable inhabitants in the neighbourhood, till at last they
                        used to quit their standards in broad daylight without leave. They did
                        everything just as their caprice and fancy dictated, no attention was paid
                        to rules or discipline or to the orders of their officers. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> One thing alone helped to keep up the outward aspect of
                        a Roman camp and that was the hope which the men entertained that the
                        tribunes would become infected with their madness and take part in their
                        mutiny. In this hope they allowed them to administer justice from their
                        tribunals, they went to them for the watchword and the orders of the day,
                        and relieved guard at the proper intervals. Thus after depriving them of any
                        real authority they kept up the appearance of obedience, whilst they were
                        actually their own commanders. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When they
                        found that the tribunes censured and reprobated their proceedings and
                        endeavoured to repress them, and openly declared that they would have
                        nothing to do with their insensate folly, they broke out into open mutiny.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They drove the tribunes from their
                        official seats, and then out of the camp, and amidst universal acclamation
                        placed the supreme command in the hands of the chief ringleaders of the
                        mutiny, two common soldiers whose names were C. Albius of Cales and C.
                        Atrius, an Umbrian. These men were by no means content to wear the insignia
                        of the military tribunes, they had the audacity to affect those of the chief
                        magistrates, the fasces and the axes. It never occurred to them that those
                        symbols which they had carried before them to strike fear into others were
                        impending over their own backs and necks. The false belief that Scipio was
                        dead blinded them; they felt certain that the spread of this report would
                        kindle the flames of war throughout the whole of Spain. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> In the general turmoil they imagined that they would be
                        able to levy contributions on the allies of Rome and plunder the cities
                        round them, and when crime and outrage were being committed everywhere, what
                        they had done would not be noticed in the universal confusion. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They were every hour expecting fresh
                        details of Scipio's death, and even news of his funeral. None came however
                        and the idle rumours by degrees died away. Then they began to look for those
                        who started the report, but each in turn kept out of the way, preferring to
                        be thought credulous rather than suspected of inventing such a story.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Abandoned by their followers, the
                        ringleaders looked with dread upon the insignia they had assumed, and fully
                        expected that in return for this idle show of power they would draw down
                        upon themselves the weight of the true and legitimate authority. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> While the mutiny was thus at a standstill,
                        definite information was brought that Scipio was alive and this was soon
                        followed by the further intelligence that his health was restored. This
                        intelligence was brought by a party of seven military tribunes, whom Scipio
                        had sent to Sucro. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At first their presence
                        was strongly resented, but the quiet talks they had with those they happened
                        to know had a calming effect; they visited the soldiers in their tents, and
                        chatted with the groups which gathered round the tribunals or in front of
                        the headquarters tent. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They made no
                        reference to the treason the soldiers had been guilty of, but only
                        questioned them as to the causes of the sudden outbreak. They were told in
                        reply that the men did not get their pay punctually, nor their due share of
                        credit for the part they had played in the campaign. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was by their courage, they asserted, that the Roman
                        name was preserved and the province saved for the republic after the
                        destruction of the two armies and their commanders, at the time when the
                        Iliturgans committed their foul crime. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And
                        though they had received the just recompense for their treason, no one had
                        been found to reward the Roman soldiers for their meritorious services. </p>
                    <p> In reply to these and similar complaints the tribunes told the men that
                        their requests were reasonable and they would lay them before the general.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were glad that these were nothing
                        worse or harder to set right, and the men might rest assured that P. Scipio,
                        after the favour the gods had shown him, and, indeed, the whole State, would
                        show their gratitude. Scipio was experienced in war, but unfamiliar with the
                        storms of internal disturbances. Two things made him anxious, the
                        possibility of the army exceeding all measure in its insubordination, or of
                        his inflicting punishments which would be excessive. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> For the present he decided to go on as he had begun,
                        and handle the matter gently. Collectors were sent among the tributary
                        states so that the soldiers might hope to receive their pay soon. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> An order was shortly after issued for them to
                        assemble at New Carthage for that purpose; they might go in a body or
                        successively in single detachments as they preferred. The unrest was already
                        dying down when the sudden cessation of hostilities on the part of the
                        revolted Spaniards completely stopped it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        When Mandonius and Indibilis heard that Scipio was still alive, they gave up
                        their enterprise and retired within their frontiers, and the mutineers could
                        no longer find any one either amongst their own countrymen or amongst the
                        natives who would associate himself with their mad scheme. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> After carefully considering every possible plan they
                        saw that the only way of escaping the consequences of their evil counsels,
                        and that not a very hopeful way, was to submit themselves either to the just
                        displeasure of their general or to his clemency, which they were not without
                        hopes of experiencing. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They argued that
                        he had ever pardoned the enemies of his country after armed conflict,
                        whereas during their mutiny not a wound had been received or a drop of blood
                        shed, it had been free from all cruelty and did not deserve a cruel
                        punishment. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So ready are men with reasons
                        when they wish to palliate their own misconduct. There was considerable
                        hesitation as to whether they should go to receive their pay separately
                        cohort by cohort. or all together. The latter course seemed the safer and
                        they decided upon it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst they were discussing these points a
                        council of war was being held over them in New Carthage. The members were
                        divided; some thought it sufficient to proceed only against the ringleaders,
                        who did not number more than five-and-thirty; <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> others regarded it as an act of high treason rather
                        than a mutiny and held that such a bad example could only be dealt with by
                        the punishment of the many who were implicated. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The more merciful view, that punishment should only
                        fall on those with whom the mischief originated, finally prevailed; for the
                        troops generally a severe reprimand was considered sufficient. On the
                        breaking up of the council the army stationed in Carthage was informed that
                        an expedition was to be made against Mandonius and Indibilis, and that
                        rations were to be prepared for several days in advance. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The object was to make it appear that this was the
                        business for which the council had been held. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The seven tribunes who had been sent to Sucro to quell
                        the mutiny now returned in advance of the troops, and each handed in the
                        names of five ringleaders. Suitable men had been told off to meet the
                        culprits with smiles and pleasant words, and invite them to their houses,
                        and when they had drunk themselves into a state of stupor place them in
                        fetters. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the men were now not far
                        from New Carthage they were informed by people who met them that the whole
                        of the army at Carthage were starting on the morrow with M. Silanus against
                        the Lacetanians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This news did not
                        completely dispel the secret fears which haunted their minds, still they
                        were greatly rejoiced to hear it, as they imagined that now that their
                        commander would be alone, they would have him in their power, instead of
                        their being in his. </p>
                    <p> The sun was setting when they entered the city, and they found the other
                        army making all preparations for their march. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> It had been arranged beforehand how they were to be
                        received, they were told that their commander was glad that they had arrived
                        when they did, just before the other army left. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> They then dispersed for food and rest, and the
                        ringleaders were conducted by the men selected for the purpose to their
                        houses, where they were entertained, and where the tribunes arrested and
                        manacled them without any disturbance. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At
                        the fourth watch the baggage train of the army began to move for its
                        pretended march; at daybreak the standards went forward, but the whole army
                        was halted as soon as it reached the gate, and guards were posted round all
                        the gates to prevent any one from leaving the city. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The newly arrived troops were then summoned to an
                        assembly, and they ran into the forum and crowded threateningly round their
                        general's tribunal, expecting to intimidate him by their shouts. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> At the moment when he ascended his tribunal the
                        troops who had marched back from the gate and were fully armed surrounded
                        the unarmed crowd. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Now their rebellious
                        spirit was completely cowed, and, as they afterwards admitted, the thing
                        that they were most afraid of was the colour and vigour of their chief whom
                        they expected to see looking weak and ill, and the expression in his face
                        such as they had never witnessed before, not even in the heat of battle.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> For some time he sat in silence,
                        until he received information that the ringleaders had been brought down to
                        the forum and everything was in readiness. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the usher had obtained silence he
                        made the following speech: "I never supposed that I should want words in
                        which to address my army, not that I ever trained myself to speak rather
                        than to act, but that having lived a camp life from boyhood I have learnt to
                        understand the soldier's character. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As to
                        what I am to say to you now, words and ideas alike fail me; I do not even
                        know by what title I am to address you. Am I to call you Roman citizens-you
                        who have revolted against your country? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Can I call you soldiers when you have renounced the authority and auspices
                        of your general, and broken the solemn obligations of your military oath?
                        Your appearance, your features, your dress, your demeanour I recognise as
                        those of my fellow-countrymen, but I see that your actions, your language,
                        your designs, your spirit and temper are those of your country's foes. What
                        difference is there between your hopes and aims and those of the Ilergetes
                        and the Lacetanians? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And yet they chose
                        men of kingly rank, Mandonius and Indibilis, to lead them in their madness,
                        whilst you delegated the auspices and the supreme command to Atrius, an
                        Umbrian, and Albius, a man from Cales. Do tell me, soldiers, that you did
                        not all join in that or approve of its being done. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> I will gladly believe that only a few were guilty of
                        such insensate folly, if you assure me that this is so. For the crime is of
                        such a nature that had it involved the whole army it could only have been
                        expiated by a frightful sacrifice. </p>
                    <p> "It is painful for me to speak thus, opening up, as it were, wounds, but
                        unless they are handled and probed they cannot be healed. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> After the expulsion of the Carthaginians from Spain I
                        did not believe that there were anywhere people who wished me dead, such had
                        been my conduct towards friends and enemies alike. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> And yet, alas so greatly was I mistaken that even in my
                        own army the report of my death was not only credited but eagerly looked
                        for. I would not for a moment wish to lay this to the charge of you all, for
                        if I thought that the whole of my army wished for my death, I would die here
                        before your eyes. My life would have no attraction for me if it were hateful
                        to my fellow-countrymen and my soldiers. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        But every multitude is like the sea which left to itself is naturally
                        motionless, till winds and gales excite it. So it is with calm and storms
                        amongst you, the cause and origin of your madness is to be found in your
                        ringleaders, who infected you with their frenzy. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> For you do not seem even now to be aware to what
                        lengths of folly you have gone or what criminal recklessness you have been
                        guilty of towards me, towards your country, your parents and your children,
                        towards the gods who were witnesses of <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                        your military oath, towards the auspices under which your served, towards
                        the traditions of the army and the discipline of our ancestors, towards the
                        majesty inherent in supreme authority. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        About myself I prefer to be silent; you may have lent a thoughtless rather
                        than a willing ear to the report of my death; I may be a man whose rule
                        might be naturally expected to prove irksome to his army. But your
                        country-what has it deserved of you that you should make common cause with
                        Mandonius and Indibilis for its betrayal? What have the Roman people done
                        that you should deprive the tribunes whom they elected of their authority,
                        and bestow it on private individuals? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And
                        not content with having such men for tribunes you, a Roman army, have
                        transferred the fasces of your commander to men who never possessed a single
                        slave to be at their command! <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                        headquarters tent was occupied by an Albius and an Atrius; at their doors
                        the trumpet sounded; to them you went for orders; they were seated on P.
                        Scipio's tribunal; the lictor was in attendance and cleared the way before
                        them; in front of them the axes and fasces were borne! <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> When there is a shower of stones, or buildings are
                        struck by lightning, or animals produce monstrous offspring, you consider
                        these things as portents. We have here a portent which no victims, no
                        intercessions can expiate but the blood of those who have dared such an
                        awful crime. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Though no crime is dictated by rational
                        motives, I should still like to know what was in your mind, what was your
                        intention, so far as such wickedness admitted of any. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Years ago a legion which was sent to garrison Regium
                        murdered the principal men of the place and kept possession of that wealthy
                        city for ten years. For this crime the entire legion of 4000 men were
                        beheaded at Rome in the Forum. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But they
                        did not choose for their leader an Umbrian who was little more than a
                        camp-follower, an Atrius whose very name is an evil omen. They followed D.
                        Vibellius, a military tribune. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor did
                        they join hands with Pyrrhus, or with the Samnites and Lucanians, the
                        enemies of Rome, but you communicated your plans to Mandonius and Indibilis
                        and prepared to join them in arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                        were content to do as the Campanians did when they wrested Capua from the
                        Tuscans, its old inhabitants, or as the Mamertines did when they seized
                        Messana in Sicily; they intended to make Regium their future home without
                        any idea of attacking Rome or the allies of Rome. Did you intend to make
                        Sucro your permanent abode? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If, after
                        subjugating Spain, I had gone away and left you here you would have rightly
                        complained to gods and men that you had not returned to your wives and
                        children. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But you may have banished from
                        your minds all thought of them, as you have in the case of your country and
                        in my own case. I want to trace the course which your criminal project would
                        have taken, though stopping short of the extreme of madness. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> As long as I was alive and retained intact the
                        army with which in one day I captured New Carthage and defeated and routed
                        four Carthaginian armies, would you really have wrested the province of
                        Spain from <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the hands of Rome, you, a
                        force of some 8000 men, every one of you of less account at all events than
                        the Albius and Atrius whom you made your masters? </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "I put aside and ignore my own honour and
                        reputation, and assume that I was in no way injured by your too easily
                        crediting the story of my death. But what then? Supposing I had died, would
                        the commonwealth have died with me, would the sovereignty of Rome have
                        shared my fate? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No, Jupiter Optimus
                        Maximus would never have allowed a City built for eternity, built under the
                        auspices and sanction of the gods, to be as short-lived as this fragile
                        mortal body of mine. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> C. Flaminius,
                        Aemilius Paulus, Sempronius Gracchus, Postumius Albinus, M. Marcellus, T.
                        Quinctius Crispinus, Cnaeus Fulvius, and my own relations, the two Scipios,
                        all of them distinguished generals, have been carried off in this single
                        war, and yet Rome lives on and will live on though a thousand more should
                        perish through sickness or the sword. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Would then the republic have been interred in my solitary grave? <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Why even you yourselves, after the defeat and
                        death of my father and my uncle, chose Septimus Marcius to lead you against
                        the Carthaginians, flushed as they were with their recent victory.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I am speaking as though Spain would
                        have been left without a general; but would not the sovereignty of the
                        empire have been amply vindicated by M. Silanus, who came into the province
                        invested with the same power and authority as I myself with my brother
                        Lucius and C. Laelius as his lieutenants? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        Can any comparison be made between their army and you, between their rank
                        and experience and those of the men you have chosen, between the cause for
                        which they are fighting and the one which you have taken up? <milestone
                            n="17" unit="section"/> And if you were superior to them all would you
                        bear arms in company with the Carthaginians against your country, against
                        your fellow-citizens? What injury have they done to you?" </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Coriolanus was once driven to make war on
                        his country by an iniquitous sentence which condemned him to dishonoured and
                        forlorn exile, but his affection as a son recalled him from the crime which
                        he was meditating as a citizen. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> What have
                        you suffered to call out this bitter hostility? Did you proclaim war against
                        your country, did you desert the people of Rome in favour of the Ilergetes,
                        did you trample underfoot all law, human and divine, simply because your pay
                        was a few days in arrear owing to your general's illness? <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> There is no doubt about it, soldiers, you were seized
                        with madness; the bodily illness from which I suffered was not one whit more
                        severe than the mental malady which overtook you. I shrink with horror from
                        dwelling upon the credit men gave to rumours, the hopes they entertained,
                        the ambitious schemes they formed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Let all
                        be forgotten, if possible, or if not that, let silence at least draw a veil
                        over all. I admit that my words have appeared stern and unfeeling to you,
                        but how much more unfeeling, think you, has your conduct been than anything
                        I have said? You imagine that it is right and proper for me to tolerate your
                        actions, and yet you have not patience to hear them mentioned. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Bad as they are however, I will not reproach you
                        with them any longer; I only wish you may forget them as easily as I shall.
                        As for the army as a body, if you sincerely repent of your wrongdoing you
                        give me satisfaction enough and more than enough. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Albius of Cales and Atrius of Umbria with the other
                        ringleaders in this detestable mutiny will expiate their crime with their
                        blood. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The sight of their punishment ought
                        to give you satisfaction rather than pain, if indeed you have recovered your
                        sanity, for their designs would have proved more mischievous and destructive
                        to you than to any one else." He had hardly finished speaking when, at a
                        preconcerted signal, the eyes and ears of his audience were assailed by
                        everything which could terrify and appal. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        The army which was on guard all round the assembly clashed their swords
                        against their shields, and the voice of the usher was heard calling over the
                        names of those who had been sentenced in the council or war. These were
                        stripped to the waist and conducted into the middle of the assembly; all the
                        apparatus of punishment was at once brought out; they were tied to the
                        stake, scourged and finally beheaded. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        spectators were so benumbed by terror that no voice was raised against the
                        severity of the punishment, not even a groan was heard. Then the bodies were
                        all dragged away, and after the place was cleansed, the soldiers were
                        summoned each by name to take the oath of obedience to P. Scipio before the
                        military tribunes. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then they each
                        received the pay due to them. Such was the end and issue of the mutiny which
                        started amongst the soldiers at Sucro. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hanno, Mago's lieutenant, had been
                        despatched during this time, with a small body of Africans to hire troops
                        among the Spanish tribes, and succeeded in raising 4000 men. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Soon afterwards, his camp was captured by L.
                        Marcius, most of his men were killed in the assault, some during their
                        flight by the pursuing cavalry; Hanno himself escaped with a handful of his
                        men. Whilst this was going on at the Baetis Laelius sailed westward and
                        brought up at Carteia, a city situated on that part of the coast where the
                        Straits begin to widen into the ocean. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Some men had come into the Roman camp with a voluntary offer to surrender
                        the city of Gades, but the plot was discovered before it was ripe.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All the conspirators were arrested and
                        Mago handed them over to the custody of Adherbal for conveyance to Carthage.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Adherbal placed them on board a
                        quinquereme which was sent on in advance as it was a slower vessel than the
                        eight triremes with which he followed shortly after The quinquereme was
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> just entering the Straits when
                        Laelius sailed out of the harbour of Carteia in another quinquereme followed
                        by seven triremes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He bore straight down
                        upon Adherbal, feeling quite sure that the quinquereme could not be brought
                        round, as it was caught by the current sweeping through the channel. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Surprised by this unsuspected attack, the
                        Carthaginian general hesitated for a few moments whether to follow his
                        quinquereme or turn his prows against the enemy. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> This hesitation put it out of his power to decline the
                        contest, for they were now within range of one another's missiles, and the
                        enemy were pressing on him on all sides. The strength of the tide prevented
                        them from steering their ships as they wished. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> There was no semblance of a naval battle, no freedom of
                        action, no room for tactics or maneuvers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        The tidal currents completely dominated the action and carried the ships
                        against their own side and against the enemy indiscriminately, in spite of
                        all the efforts of the rowers. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> You might
                        see a ship which was endeavouring to escape carried stem foremost against
                        the victors, whilst the one pursuing it, if it got <milestone n="13??"
                            unit="section"/> into an opposing current, was swept back as though it
                        were the one in flight. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And when they
                        were actually engaged and one ship was making for another in order to ram
                        it, it would swerve from its course and receive a side-blow from the other's
                        beak, whilst the one which was coming broadside on would suddenly be swung
                        round and present its prow. So the varying struggle of the triremes went on,
                        directed and controlled by Chance. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The
                        Roman quinquereme answered the helm better, either because its weight made
                        it steadier, or because it had more banks of oars to cut through the waves.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It sank two triremes, and sweeping
                        rapidly past a third sheared off all the oars on one side, and it would have
                        disabled the rest if Adherbal had <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> not
                        got clear away with the remaining five, and crowding all sail reached
                        Africa. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After his victory Laelius returned to
                        Carteia where he learnt what had been going on at Gades, how the plot had
                        been discovered and the conspirators sent to Carthage. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> As the purpose for which he had come was thus
                        frustrated he sent word to L. Marcius, saying that if they did not wish to
                        waste their time by sitting before Gades, they ought both to rejoin their
                        commander-in-chief. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Marcius quite agreed,
                        and they both returned in a few days to New Carthage. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> On their departure Mago breathed more freely after
                        having been threatened by the double danger from land and sea, and on
                        receiving intelligence of the renewal of hostilities by the Ilergetes, he
                        once more entertained hopes of reconquering Spain. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Messengers were despatched to Carthage, to lay before
                        the senate a highly coloured account of the mutiny in the Roman camp and the
                        defection of the allies of Rome, and at the same time strongly urge
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> that assistance should be sent to
                        him in order that he might win back the heritage left him by his ancestors,
                        the sovereignty of Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Mandonius and
                        Indibilis had retired for some time within their borders and were quietly
                        waiting till they knew what was decided with regard to the mutiny.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They felt no doubt that if Scipio
                        pardoned the offence of his own fellow-countrymen, he would exercise
                        clemency towards them also. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But when the
                        severity of the punishment became generally known they were convinced that
                        equal measure would be meted out to them, and so they decided to resume
                        hostilities. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They summoned their
                        tribesmen once more to arms, and called out the auxiliaries who had joined
                        them before, and with a force of 20,000 infantry and 2500 cavalry <milestone
                            n="11??" unit="section"/> they crossed their frontiers and marched to
                        their old camping ground in Sedetania. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By his punctual payment of arrears to all
                        alike, the guilty as well as the innocent, and by his affable tone and
                        bearing towards every one, Scipio soon regained the affection of his
                        soldiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Before he broke up his quarters
                        at New Carthage, he called his troops together and after denouncing at some
                        length the treachery of the two chiefs in recommencing war went on to say
                        that the temper in which he was going to avenge that crime was very
                        different from the spirit in which he had recently healed the fault of his
                        misled fellow-citizens. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then he felt as if
                        he were tearing his own vitals, when with groans and tears he expiated
                        either the thoughtlessness or the guilt of 8000 men at the cost of thirty
                        lives. Now it was in a cheerful and confident spirit that he was marching to
                        the destruction of the Ilergetes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They
                        were not natives of the same soil with him, nor was there any treaty bond
                        between them; the only bond was that of honour and friendship, and that they
                        had themselves broken by their crime. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When
                        he looked at his own army he saw that they were all either Roman citizens or
                        Latin allies, but what affected him most was the fact that there was hardly
                        a single soldier amongst them who had not been brought from Italy, either by
                        his uncle Cnaeus Scipio, who was the first Roman general to come into that
                        province, or by his father or else by himself. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They were all of them accustomed to the name and
                        auspices of the Scipios, and he wanted to take them back with him to their
                        country to enjoy a well-earned triumph. Should he become a candidate for the
                        consulship he hoped that they would support him, as the honour conferred on
                        him would belong to them all. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As to the
                        expedition in front of them the man who regarded it as a war must have
                        forgotten all that he had hitherto done. Mago, who had fled with a few ships
                        to an island surrounded by an ocean; beyond the limits of the world of men,
                        was, he assured them, more of a concern to him than the Ilergetes were, for
                        a Carthaginian general and a Carthaginian garrison, however small, were
                        still there, but here there were only brigands and brigand chiefs.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They may be strong enough to plunder
                        their neighbours' fields and burn their houses and carry off their flocks
                        and herds but they have no courage for a pitched battle and an open field;
                        when they have to fight they will trust more to their swiftness for flight
                        than to their weapons. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was not,
                        therefore, because he saw that there was any danger from them, or any
                        prospect of serious war that he was marching to crush the Ilergetes before
                        his departure from the province, but because <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> such a criminal revolt must not go unpunished, and also
                        because it must not be said that a single enemy has been left behind in a
                        province which by such courage and good fortune has been reduced to
                        submission. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "Follow me then," he said, in
                        conclusion, "with the kind help of heaven, not to make war-for you have to
                        do with an enemy who is no match for you-but to inflict punishment upon men
                        steeped in crime." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The men were then dismissed with orders to
                        make their preparations for the next day's departure. Ten days after leaving
                        New Carthage he reached the Ebro, and within four days of his passage of the
                        river he came within view of the enemy. In front of his camp there was a
                        level stretch of ground shut in on either side by mountains. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Scipio ordered some cattle taken mostly from the
                        enemy's fields to be driven towards the hostile camp in order to rouse the
                        savagery of the barbarians. Laelius was instructed to remain with his
                        cavalry in concealment behind a projecting mountain spur, and when the light
                        infantry who went to guard the cattle had drawn the enemy into a skirmish he
                        was to charge from his hiding-place. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        battle soon began, the Spaniards on catching sight of the cattle rushed out
                        to secure them, and the skirmishers attacked them while occupied with their
                        plunder. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At first the two sides harassed
                        one another with missiles, then they discharged light darts, which are more
                        likely to provoke than to decide a battle, and at last they drew their
                        swords. It would have been a steady hand-to-hand fight if the cavalry had
                        not come up. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They not only made a frontal
                        attack, riding down all in their way, but some galloped round the foot of
                        the mountain so as to cut off the retreat of the enemy. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> There was more slaughter than usually occurs in
                        skirmishes of this kind, and the barbarians were infuriated rather than
                        disheartened at their want of success. </p>
                    <p> In order, therefore, to show that they were not defeated, they marched out
                        to battle the next morning at daybreak. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        There was not room for them all in the narrow valley, described above; two
                        divisions of their infantry and the whole of their cavalry occupied the
                        plain and the rest of their infantry were posted on the slope of a hill.
                        Scipio saw that the confined space would give him an advantage. Fighting on
                        a narrow front was more adapted to Roman than to Spanish tactics, and as the
                        enemy had brought his line into a position where he could not employ all his
                        strength, Scipio adopted a novel stratagem. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> As there was no room for him to outflank the enemy with his own cavalry,
                        and as the enemy's cavalry which was massed with the infantry would be
                        useless where it was, he gave Laelius orders to make a detour along the
                        hills, escaping observation as far as possible, and keep the cavalry action
                        distinct from the infantry battle. Scipio led the whole of his infantry
                        against the enemy with a front of four cohorts, as it was impossible to
                        extend further. He did not lose a moment in beginning the fight, for he
                        hoped that in the heat of battle his cavalry might execute their maneuver
                        unnoticed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor were the enemy aware of
                        their movements till they heard the sounds of battle in their rear. So two
                        separate contests were going on through the whole length of the valley, one
                        between the infantry and the other between the cavalry, and the narrow width
                        of the valley prevented the two armies from assisting each other or acting
                        in concert. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Spanish infantry, who had
                        gone into action trusting to the support of their cavalry, were cut to
                        pieces and the cavalry, unable to stand the attack of the Roman infantry
                        after their own had all fallen, and taken in rear by Laelius and his
                        cavalry, closed up and for a time stood their ground and kept up their
                        resistance, but at last all were killed to a man. Not a single combatant out
                        of the cavalry and infantry which fought in the valley remained alive. The
                        third division which had been standing on the mountain side, looking on in
                        safety instead of participating in the fight, had room and time enough to
                        make good their retreat. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Amongst them
                        were the two chieftains, who escaped in the confusion before the entire army
                        was surrounded. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Spanish camp was captured the same day
                        and in addition to the rest of the booty 3000 prisoners were secured.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As many as 2000 Romans and allies fell
                        in the battle; the wounded amounted to more than 3000. The victory would not
                        have been so costly had the battle been fought in a wider plain where flight
                        would have been easier. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Indibilis laid
                        aside all idea of continuing the war, and thought that the safest course,
                        considering his hopeless position, would be to throw himself on Scipio's
                        well-known clemency and honour. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He sent
                        his brother Mandonius to him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Throwing
                        himself on his knees before the victor he put everything down to the fatal
                        frenzy of the time, which like some pestilential contagion had infected not
                        only the Ilergetes and Lacetanians but even a Roman army with madness. He
                        declared that he and his brother and the rest of their countrymen were in
                        such a condition that they would, if he thought it right, give back
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> their lives to the same P. Scipio
                        from whom they had received them, or, if they were spared a second time,
                        they would devote the whole of their lives to the one man to whom they owed
                        them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Previously they had trusted to the
                        strength of their cause and had not made trial of his clemency, now that
                        their cause was hopeless they put all their trust in their conqueror's
                        mercy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was the traditional practice of
                        the Romans, in the case of a conquered nation with whom no friendly
                        relations had previously existed either through treaty or community of
                        rights and laws, not to accept their submission or allow any terms of peace
                        until all their possessions sacred and profane had been surrendered,
                        hostages given, their arms taken away and garrisons placed in their cities.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the present instance however,
                        Scipio, after sternly reprimanding Mandonius and the absent Indibilis at
                        considerable length, said that <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> their
                        lives were justly forfeited by their crime, but that through his own
                        kindness and that of the Roman people, they would be spared. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> He would not, however, demand hostages, since
                        these were only a security for those who feared a fresh outbreak of
                        hostilities, nor would he take away their arms, he would leave their minds
                        at rest. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But if they revolted it was not
                        unoffending hostages but they themselves who would feel the weight of his
                        arm; he would inflict punishment not upon a defenceless but upon an armed
                        foe. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He would leave it to them whether
                        they preferred the favour or the wrath of Rome; they had experience of both.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So Mandonius was dismissed, the only
                        condition imposed upon him being a pecuniary indemnity sufficient to furnish
                        the pay which was owing to the troops. After sending Marcius on in advance
                        into Southern Spain, Scipio stayed where he was for a few days until the
                        Ilergetes paid over the indemnity and then, <milestone n="15??"
                            unit="section"/> setting out with a light-armed force, overtook Marcius
                        who was already nearing the ocean. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The negotiations which had been begun with
                        Masinissa were delayed for various reasons. He wanted in any case to meet
                        Scipio personally and to grasp his hand in confirmation of the league
                        between them, and this was the reason why Scipio undertook at that time such
                        a long and out-of-the-way journey. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Masinissa was at Gades, and on being informed by Marcius that Scipio was
                        coming, he represented to Mago that his horses were getting out of condition
                        through being confined in so small an island, and were causing a general
                        scarcity from which all alike suffered, whilst his cavalry were becoming
                        enervated through inaction. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He persuaded
                        the Carthaginian commander to allow him to cross to the mainland for the
                        purpose of plundering the adjacent country. When he had landed he sent three
                        Numidian chieftains to Scipio to fix the time and place of the interview.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Two were to be detained by Scipio as
                        hostages, the third was to be sent back to conduct Masinissa to the place
                        that had been decided upon. They came to the conference, each with a small
                        escort. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From what he had heard of his
                        achievements the Numidian had already conceived a great admiration for the
                        Roman commander and had pictured him in imagination as a man of grand and
                        imposing presence. But when he saw him he felt a deeper veneration for him.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The majesty, natural to Scipio, was
                        heightened by his flowing hair and the simplicity of his general appearance,
                        which was devoid of all adornment and decoration, and in the highest degree
                        manly and soldierly. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He was at the most
                        vigorous time of life, and his recovery from his recent illness had given
                        him a freshness and clearness of complexion which renewed the bloom of
                        youth. </p>
                    <p> Almost speechless with astonishment at this his first meeting with him, the
                        Numidian began by thanking him for having sent his nephew home. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> From that moment, he declared, he had looked for
                        such an opportunity as this of expressing his gratitude, and now that one
                        was offered him by the kindness of heaven he would not let it slip.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was desirous of rendering such
                        service to Scipio and to Rome that no one of foreign birth might ever be
                        found to have afforded more zealous assistance. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> This had long been his wish, but Spain was a strange
                        and unknown land to him, and he had been unable to carry out his purpose
                        there; it would, however, be easy to do it in the land of his birth, where
                        he had been brought up in the expectation of succeeding to his father's
                        throne. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If the Romans sent Scipio as
                        their general into Africa, he felt pretty certain that the time of Carthage
                        would be very short. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scipio watched him
                        and listened to him with great pleasure. He knew that Masinissa was the
                        master-spirit in all the enemy's cavalry, and the youth's whole bearing
                        showed high courage. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After they had
                        pledged their faith to each other, Scipio returned to Tarraco. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Masinissa was allowed by the Romans to carry off
                        plunder from the adjacent fields, in order that he might not be thought to
                        have sailed across to the mainland without sufficient cause. After this he
                        returned to Gades. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mago's hopes had been raised by the mutiny
                        in the Roman camp and the revolt of Indibilis. Now he despaired of effecting
                        anything in Spain and made preparations for his departure. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst he was so employed a despatch came from the
                        Carthaginian senate ordering him to take the fleet which he had at Gades
                        over to Italy, and after raising as large a force as possible <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> of Gauls and Ligurians in that country to form
                        a junction with Hannibal and not allow the war which had been begun with so
                        much energy and even more success to drag on lifelessly. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Money was brought to him from Carthage for the purpose,
                        and he also requisitioned as much as he could from the people in Gades. Not
                        only their public treasury but even their temples were plundered, and they
                        were all compelled to contribute their private stores of gold and silver.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Sailing along the Spanish coast, he
                        landed a force not far from New Carthage, and plundered the nearest fields,
                        after which he brought up his fleet at the city. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> During the day he kept his men on board, and did not
                        disembark them till night. He then took them to that part of the city wall
                        where the Romans had effected the capture of the place; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> thinking that the city was held by a weak garrison and
                        that there would be a movement amongst some of the townsmen who hoped for a
                        change of masters. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The country people,
                        however, who were fleeing from their fields had brought news of the
                        depredations and approach of the enemy. His fleet had also been seen during
                        the day, and it was obvious that they would not have taken their station
                        before the city without some special reason. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> An armed force was accordingly drawn up outside the gate which faced the
                        sea. The enemy approached the walls in disorder, soldiers and seamen were
                        mixed together, and there was much more noise and tumult than fighting
                        strength. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Suddenly the gate was thrown
                        open and the Romans burst out with a cheer; the enemy were thrown into
                        confusion, turned their backs at the very first discharge of missiles and
                        were pursued with heavy loss down to the shore. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> If the ships had not been brought up close to the beach
                        and so afforded a means of escape, not a single fugitive would have
                        survived. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On the ships, too, there was
                        hurry and confusion; the crews drew up the ladders, lest the enemy should
                        clamber on board with their comrades, and cut the cables and hawsers so as
                        not to lose time in weighing anchor. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Many
                        who tried to swim to the ships could not see in the darkness what direction
                        to take or what dangers to avoid, and perished miserably. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The next day, after the fleet had regained the ocean,
                        it was discovered that 800 men had been killed between the wall and the
                        shore and as many as 2000 arms of different kinds picked up. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On his return to Gades, Mago found the
                        gates closed against him, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> so he anchored
                        off Cimbii, a place not far from Gades, and sent envoys to lodge a complaint
                        against the gates being closed to him, an ally and a friend. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> They excused themselves by saying that it was
                        done by a gathering of the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> townsmen who
                        were incensed at some acts of pillage committed by the soldiers during the
                        embarkation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He invited their sufetes-the
                        title of their supreme magistrate-together with the city treasurer to a
                        conference, and when they were come he ordered them to be scourged and
                        crucified. From there he sailed to Pityusa, an island about a hundred miles
                        distant from the mainland, which had at the time a Phoenician population.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here the fleet naturally met with a
                        friendly reception, and not only were supplies furnished on a generous scale
                        but he received reinforcements for his fleet in the shape of arms and men.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thus encouraged, the Carthaginian
                        sailed on to the Balearic Isles, a voyage of about fifty miles. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> There are two islands so called; the larger one
                        was better supplied with arms and contained a more numerous population;
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> it also possessed a harbour where Mago
                        thought he could conveniently shelter his fleet for the winter, as the
                        autumn was now closing. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But his fleet met
                        with quite as hostile a reception as if the island had been inhabited by
                        Romans. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The sling which the Balearics
                        make most use of today was at that time their sole weapon, and no nation
                        comes near them in the skill with which they handle it. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> When the Carthaginians tried to approach the land such
                        a shower of stones fell upon them like a violent hailstorm that they did not
                        venture inside the harbour. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Putting out
                        once more to sea they approached the smaller island, which possessed a
                        fertile soil, but fewer resources in men and arms. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Here they landed and encamped in a strong position
                        commanding the harbour, from which they became masters of the island without
                        meeting any resistance. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> They raised a
                        force of 2000 auxiliaries which they sent to Carthage and then beached their
                        ships for the winter. After Mago's departure Gades surrendered to the
                        Romans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such is the record of Scipio's command in
                        Spain. After handing over the charge of the province to the proconsuls L.
                        Lentulus and L. Manlius Acidinus, he set sail with ten ships for Rome.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On his arrival a meeting of the senate
                        was held at the temple of Bellona, at which he gave a <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> report of all he had done in Spain, how many pitched
                        battles he had fought, how many towns he had captured, and what tribes he
                        had brought under the dominion of Rome. He asserted that when he arrived in
                        Spain he found four Carthaginian armies opposed to him; when he. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> left, there was not a single Carthaginian in the
                        country. He was not without hope that a triumph might be accorded to him for
                        his services; he did not, however, press his demand for one, as it was quite
                        understood that no one had up to that time enjoyed a triumph who was not
                        invested with a magistracy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the
                        senate had been dismissed, he made his entry into the City and had borne
                        before him 14,342 pounds of silver and a great quantity of silver coins, all
                        of which he, deposited in the treasury. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> L.
                        Veturius Philo now proceeded to hold the consular elections, and all the
                        centuries voted amidst much enthusiasm for Scipio. Publius Licinius Crassus,
                        the Pontifex Maximus, was elected as his colleague. It is recorded that a
                        larger number of voters took part in that election than at any other time
                        during the war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They had come from all
                        parts, not only to give their votes, but also to get sight of Scipio; they
                        flocked in crowds round his house, and at the Capitol when he sacrificed the
                        hecatomb which he had vowed to Jupiter in Spain. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> They assured themselves that as C. Lutatius had brought
                        the First Punic War to a close, so Scipio would terminate this one, and as
                        he had driven the Carthaginians out of Spain, so he would drive them out of
                        Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They were marking out Africa as his
                        province just as though the war in Italy was at an end. Then followed the
                        election of praetors. Two of those elected-Spurius Lucretius and Cnaeus
                        Octavius-were plebeian aediles at the time; the others-Cnaeus Servilius
                        Caepio and L. Aemilius Papus-were not holding any office. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> It was in the fourteenth year of the Second Punic War
                        (B.C. 205) that P. Cornelius Scipio and P. Licinius Crassus entered on their
                        consulship. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In the assignment of the
                        consular provinces Scipio with his colleague's consent took Sicily without
                        recourse to the ballot, because Crassus, as Pontifex Maximus, was prevented
                        by his sacred duties from leaving Italy; he therefore took Bruttium. The
                        praetors then balloted for their provinces. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> The City jurisdiction fell to Cnaeus Servilius; Spurius Lucretius
                        received Ariminum, as the province of Gaul was then called; Sicily fell to
                        L. Aemilius and Sardinia to Cnaeus Octavius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate held a session in the Capitol.
                        A resolution was passed on the motion of P. Scipio that he should celebrate
                        the Games which he had vowed during the mutiny and defray the cost out of
                        the money which he had brought into the treasury. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Then he introduced a deputation from Saguntum, the
                        senior member of which addressed the House in the following terms: "Although
                        there is no form of suffering, senators, which we have not endured in order
                        to keep our faith with you to the last, still the kindness which you and
                        your generals have shown to us has made us forget our misery. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> For us you have undertaken war and for fourteen
                        years have carried it on with such determination that often you have brought
                        yourselves and often reduced the Carthaginians to the last extremities.
                        Though you had in the heart of Italy such a terrible war and such an enemy
                        as Hannibal, you nevertheless sent a consul with his army to Spain to
                        collect, as it were, the remains of our wreckage. From the day that the two
                        Scipios, Publius and C. Cornelius, came into the province they never at any
                        moment failed to do good to us and injury to our enemies. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> First of all, they restored our city to us, and sent
                        men all over Spain to find out those of us who had been sold into slavery
                        and set them free. When our fortunes, from being utterly miserable, had
                        become almost enviable, your two generals Publius and C. Cornelius met with
                        their deaths, a loss which we felt even more bitterly than you. It seemed at
                        the time as though we had been brought back from distant exile to our old
                        home only to see for the second time our own ruin and our country's
                        destruction. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It did not require a
                        Carthaginian general or army to effect our annihilation, the Turduli, our
                        inveterate enemies who had been the cause of our former collapse, would have
                        been quite able to extinguish us. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And just
                        when we had lost all hope, you suddenly sent P. Scipio, whom we are more
                        fortunate than all our fellow-citizens in seeing here today. We shall carry
                        back to our people the news that we have seen, as your consul-elect, the one
                        man in whom we placed all our hopes of safety. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> City after city has been taken by him from your enemies
                        throughout Spain, and in every instance he picked out the Saguntines from
                        the mass of prisoners and sent them home. And lastly the Turdetani, such
                        deadly enemies to us that had their strength remained unimpaired Saguntum
                        must have fallen, even they have been brought so low by his arms that they
                        are no longer to be feared by us, nor, if I may dare to say so, by our
                        posterity. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The tribe in whose favour
                        Hannibal destroyed Saguntum have had their own city destroyed before our
                        eyes. We take tribute from their land, but it is not the profit, but the
                        revenge that we enjoy most. </p>
                    <p> "For these blessings, the greatest that we could hope for or ask heaven to
                        grant, the senate and people of Saguntum have sent this deputation to convey
                        their grateful thanks. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> We are at the same
                        time to convey their congratulations to you on having been so successful
                        these last years in Spain and Italy that you have subjugated the one country
                        by the might of your arms, not only as far as the Ebro, but even to its most
                        distant shores which the ocean bounds, whilst in the other you have left the
                        Carthaginian nothing outside the rampart of his camp. To the great Guardian
                        of your stronghold in the Capitol, Jupiter Optimus Maximus, we are bidden
                        not only to render thanks for these boons, but also, if you allow us, to
                        offer and carry to him in the Capitol this gift of a golden crown, as a
                        memorial of your victories. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> We pray that
                        you will sanction this and further, if <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                        it seem good to you, that you will ratify and confirm for all time the
                        advantages which your generals have conferred upon us." <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The senate replied to the effect that the destruction
                        and restoration of Saguntum would both alike be a proof to all the world of
                        the faith which each side had kept to the other. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Their generals had acted wisely and properly and in
                        accordance with the wishes of the senate in restoring Saguntum and rescuing
                        its citizens from slavery, and all other acts of kindness which they had
                        performed were such as the senate wished to have done. They accorded
                        permission to the envoys to place their gift in the Capitol. Free quarters
                        and hospitality were provided for them at the cost of the State, and orders
                        were given for each to be presented with a sum of not less than 10,000 ases.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The other deputations were then
                        admitted to an audience of the senate. The Saguntines also asked to be
                        allowed to make a tour through Italy as far as they could with safety, and
                        guides were furnished them and letters sent to the different towns
                        requesting them to give the Spaniards a hospitable reception </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next question before the senate
                        concerned the raising of troops and the distribution of the various
                        commands. There was a rumour that Africa was to form a new province and be
                        allotted to Scipio without having recourse to the ballot. Scipio himself, no
                        longer contented with a moderate share of glory, was telling people that he
                        had been returned as consul not simply to carry on the war but to bring it
                        to an end, and the only way of doing that was for him to take an army over
                        to Africa. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the event of the senate's
                        opposition he asserted openly that he would carry his proposal by the
                        authority of the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The project was
                        most distasteful to the leaders of the senate, and as the rest of the
                        senators, afraid of becoming unpopular, refused to speak out, Q. Fabius
                        Maximus was asked for his opinion. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This he
                        gave in the following speech: "I am quite aware, senators, that many of you
                        regard the question before us today as already decided, and consider that
                        any one who discusses the destination of Africa as though it were still an
                        open question is wasting words. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I do not
                        quite understand, however, how Africa can have been definitely assigned as
                        the province of our gallant and energetic consul, when neither the senate
                        nor the people have decided that it shall be included amongst the provinces
                        for the year. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If it has been so assigned
                        then I think the consul is quite wrong in inviting a sham discussion upon a
                        measure that has been decided upon; he is not only stultifying the senate as
                        a body, but each individual senator who is called upon in turn for his
                        opinion. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "In expressing my dissent from those who
                        think that we ought at once to invade Africa, I am quite conscious that I
                        expose myself to two imputations. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For one
                        thing my action will be set down to my cautious nature. Young men may call
                        it timidity and indolence if they please, as long as we have no cause to
                        regret that though the counsels of others have seemed at first sight more
                        attractive, experience shows that mine are better. The other charge against
                        me will be that I am actuated by motives of malevolence and envy against the
                        ever-growing glory of our most gallant consul. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> If my past life, my character, my dictatorship and five
                        consulships, the glory I have acquired as a citizen and as a soldier, a
                        glory so great as to produce surfeit rather than a desire for more-if these
                        do not shield me from this imputation at least let my age free me from it.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> What rivalry can exist between myself
                        and a man who is not even as old as my son? <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> When I was Dictator, in the full maturity of my powers and engaged in
                        most important operations my authority was by an unheard-of innovation
                        divided with the Master of the Horse. Yet no one ever heard a word of
                        protest from me either in the senate or in the Assembly, even when he was
                        pursuing me with abuse. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It was through my
                        actions rather than my words that I wished the man whom others considered my
                        equal to be compelled to admit his inferiority to me. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> And am I, who have received all the honours that the
                        State can confer, to enter into competition with one who is in the full
                        flower of his youth? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And simply that if
                        Africa is refused to him, it may be granted to me, tired as I am not only of
                        public business but of life itself? No, I must live and die with the glory
                        that I have won. I have prevented Hannibal from conquering in order that he
                        might be conquered by those of you who are in the full vigour of your
                        powers." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "It is but fair, Publius Cornelius, that
                        whilst in my own case I have never preferred my own reputation to the
                        interests of the State, you should pardon me for not regarding even your
                        glory as more important than the welfare of the commonwealth. I admit that
                        if there were no war in Italy or only an enemy from whose defeat no glory
                        was to be gained, then the man who would keep you in Italy though acting in
                        the public interest might appear to be depriving you of the chance of
                        winning glory in a foreign war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But as our
                        enemy Hannibal has been holding Italy for fourteen years with an undefeated
                        army, you will surely not despise the glory of expelling from Italy during
                        your consulship the enemy who has been the cause of so many <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> defeats, so many deaths, and of leaving it on
                        record that it is you who have terminated this war, as C. Lutatius has the
                        lasting glory of bringing the First Punic War to a close? <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Unless, indeed, Hasdrubal was a finer general than
                        Hannibal, or the last war a more serious one than this one, or the victory
                        which closed it a greater and more brilliant one than this will be, should
                        it fall to our lot to conquer whilst you are consul. Would you rather have
                        drawn Hamilcar away from Drepana and Eryx, than expel Hannibal and his
                        Carthaginians from Italy? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even though you
                        should cling to the glory you have acquired more than to what you hope for,
                        you will not pride yourself upon having delivered Spain from war rather than
                        Italy. Hannibal is not yet such an enemy that the man who prefers to fight
                        against another foe would not be thought to fear rather than to despise him.
                        Why do you not gird yourself to this task? Why do you not march straight
                        from here to where Hannibal is and carry the war thither instead of taking a
                        roundabout course in the hope that when you have crossed over into Africa he
                        will follow you? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You are anxious to win
                        the crowning glory of bringing the Punic War to an end; your natural course
                        will be to defend your own country before you go to attack the enemy's. Let
                        there be peace in Italy before there is war in Africa; let our own fears be
                        banished before we make others tremble. If both objects can be achieved
                        under your generalship and auspices, then when you have conquered Hannibal
                        here, go on and capture Carthage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If one
                        of the two victories must be left for your successors, the former is the
                        greater and more glorious one and will necessarily lead to the latter. As
                        matters now are, the public exchequer is unable to support two armies in
                        Italy and also in Africa, we have nothing left from which to equip a fleet
                        and furnish it with supplies, and over and above all this who can fail to
                        see what great dangers would be incurred? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        P. Licinius, let us suppose, is conducting the campaign in Italy and P.
                        Scipio one in Africa. Well, supposing-may all the gods avert the omen which
                        I shudder at the mention of! but what has happened may happen
                        again-supposing, I say, that Hannibal wins a victory and marches on Rome,
                        are we to wait till then before recalling you from Africa, as we recalled Q.
                        Fulvius from Capua? What, if even in Africa the fortunes of war prove
                        equally favourable for both sides? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Take
                        warning from the fate of your own house, your father and uncle destroyed
                        with their armies within a month of each other in the country where they had
                        raised the name of Rome and the glory of your family high among the nations
                        through their successful operations by land and sea. The daylight would fail
                        me if I attempted to enumerate the kings and captains who by their rash
                        invasion of their enemy's territory have brought the most crushing defeat on
                        themselves and their armies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Athens, a
                        city most sensible and wise, listened to the advice of a young man of high
                        birth and equally high ability, and sent a great fleet to Sicily before it
                        had disposed of the war at home, and in one naval battle the flourishing
                        republic was, for ever ruined." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "I will not take instances from distant
                        lands and remote times. This very Africa we are speaking about and the fate
                        of Atilius Regulus form a conspicuous example of the fickleness of fortune.
                        "When you, Scipio, have a view of Africa from the sea will not your conquest
                        of Spain seem mere child's play? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> What
                        resemblance is there between them? You began by coasting along the shores of
                        Italy and Gaul over a sea free from any hostile fleet, and you brought up at
                        Emporiae, a friendly city. After disembarking your troops you led them
                        through a perfectly safe country to Tarraco, to the friends and allies of
                        Rome, and from Tarraco your route led through the midst of Roman garrisons.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Round the Ebro lay the armies of your
                        father and your uncle, whose courage had been raised by defeat and who were
                        burning to avenge the loss of their commanders. Their leader was, it is
                        true, irregularly chosen by the vote of the soldiery to meet the emergency,
                        but had he belonged to an ennobled family and been duly appointed he would
                        have rivalled distinguished generals in his mastery of the art of war.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then you were able to attack New
                        Carthage without the slightest interruption; not one out of the three
                        Carthaginian armies attempted to defend their allies. The rest of your
                        operations, though I am far from depreciating them, are not to be compared
                        with a war in Africa. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There no harbour is
                        open to our fleet, no district which will receive us peaceably, no city in
                        alliance with us, no king friendly to us, no spot which we can use as a base
                        of operations. Wherever you turn your eyes, you see hostility and menace. </p>
                    <p> "Do you put your trust in Syphax and his Numidians? Be satisfied with having
                        trusted them once. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Rashness does not
                        always succeed and duplicity prepares the way for confidence through
                        trifles, so that when the occasion calls for it, it may succeed in securing
                        some great advantage. Your father and your uncle were not defeated until the
                        treachery of their Celtiberian auxiliaries left them victims to the enemy.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> You yourself were not exposed to
                        anything like the danger from the Carthaginian commanders, Mago and
                        Hasdrubal, that you were from Indibilis and Mandonius after you had accepted
                        their alliance. Can you trust the Numidians after the experience you have
                        had of the disloyalty of your own troops? Syphax and Masinissa would both
                        prefer that they rather than the Carthaginians should be the leading powers
                        in Africa, but failing that, they would rather have the Carthaginians than
                        any one else. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At this moment mutual
                        rivalry and numberless grounds of complaint are embittering them against one
                        another, because external dangers are far distant; but once let them see the
                        arms of Rome and a foreign army, and they will hasten side by side to
                        extinguish, as it were, a conflagration which threatens them both. Those
                        Carthaginians defended Spain in a very different way from that in which they
                        would defend their country's walls, the temples of their gods, their hearths
                        and homes, when their trembling wives will follow them and their little
                        children cling to them as they march out to battle. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> What, moreover, if, feeling quite assured of the united
                        support of Africa, the fidelity of their royal allies and the strength of
                        their walls, and seeing that you and your army are no longer here to protect
                        Italy, the Carthaginians should send over a fresh army from Africa, or order
                        Mago, who, we understand, has left the Balearic Isles and is sailing along
                        the Ligurian coast, to form a junction with Hannibal? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Surely we should be in the same state of alarm as we
                        were at the appearance in Italy of Hasdrubal, after you had allowed him to
                        slip through your hands-you, who are going to blockade not Carthage only but
                        the whole of Africa with your army! <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> You
                        will say that you defeated him. Then I regret all the more, both on your
                        account and on behalf of the republic, that you allowed him after his defeat
                        to invade Italy. </p>
                    <p> "Allow us to ascribe all that has gone happily for you and for the dominion
                        of Rome to your wise counsels, and all misfortunes to the uncertain chances
                        of war-the more talent and courage you claim for yourself the more will your
                        native country and all Italy desire to keep such a doughty defender at home.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Even you cannot disguise the fact
                        that where Hannibal is, there is the centre and mainstay of the war, for you
                        are giving out that the one reason for your going to Africa is to draw
                        Hannibal there. Whether there then or here, you still have Hannibal to deal
                        with. And will you, I should like to know, be in a stronger position in
                        Africa, single-handed, than here with your own army and your colleague's
                        acting together? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> What a difference that
                        makes is shown by the recent instance of the consuls Claudius and Livius.
                        Where, pray, is Hannibal more likely to be supplied with men and arms?
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> In the most remote corner of Bruttium
                        where he has so long been vainly asking for reinforcements from home, or in
                        the country round Carthage and on the soil of Africa which is entirely
                        occupied by his allies? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> What an
                        extraordinary idea that is of yours to fight where your forces are reduced
                        by one-half and those of the enemy largely augmented, rather than in a
                        country where with two armies you would engage only one, and that, too,
                        exhausted by so many battles, and such long and burdensome service.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Just think how different your plan is
                        from your father's. On his election as consul he proceeded to Spain, then
                        left his province and returned to Italy in order to meet Hannibal on his
                        descent from the Alps; you are preparing to leave Italy while Hannibal is
                        actually here, not in the interest of the republic but because you think it
                        a grand and glorious thing to do. Just in the same way you, a general of the
                        Roman people, left your province and your army without any legal authority,
                        without any instructions from the senate, and entrusted to a couple of ships
                        the fortunes of the State and the majesty of the empire which were for the
                        time bound up with your own safety. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> I
                        hold the view that P. Cornelius Scipio was elected consul not for his own
                        private ends, but for us and the commonwealth, and that armies are raised to
                        guard this city and the soil of Italy, and not for consuls to transport to
                        any part of the world they please in the arrogant style of kings and
                        despots." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This speech of Fabius, so appropriate to
                        the circumstances under which it was delivered, and backed up by the weight
                        of his character and his long-established reputation for prudence, produced
                        a great effect upon most of those present, especially upon the seniors.
                        Seeing that the majority approved of the sage counsels of age in preference
                        to the impetuous temper of youth, Scipio is reported to have made the
                        following reply: "Senators, at the beginning of his speech, Q. Fabius
                        admitted that what he had to say might lay him under a suspicion of
                        jealousy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Personally, I should not dare to
                        accuse so great a man of that weakness, but either through the inadequacy of
                        his defence or the impossibility of making a successful one, he has utterly
                        failed to clear himself of the charge. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For
                        in his anxiety to dispel the suspicion, he spoke about his distinctions and
                        his reputation in such exaggerated terms as to give the impression that I
                        was in danger of finding a rival in the lowest of the Romans, not in him
                        who, because he stands above all others-a position which I frankly confess I
                        am striving to attain, denies the possibility of any rivalry between us.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He has represented himself as an old
                        man full of honours, and me as a youth not even as old as his son, as if the
                        passion for glory did not extend beyond the span of human life and find its
                        chief satisfaction in the memory of future generations. I am quite certain
                        that it is the lot of all great men to compare themselves not with their
                        contemporaries alone, but also with the illustrious of all ages. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> I admit, Quintus Fabius, that I am desirous not
                        only of equalling your renown but-forgive my saying so-of surpassing it, if
                        I can. Let not your feeling towards me, or mine towards my juniors, be such
                        that we would prevent any of our fellow-citizens from reaching our level.
                        That would not only injure the victims of our envy, it would be a loss to
                        the State, and almost to the human race. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "The speaker dwelt upon the danger to
                        which I should be exposed if I landed in Africa, showing apparently
                        solicitude not only for the commonwealth and its army but even for me. What
                        has led to this sudden anxiety on my account? <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> When my father and my uncle were killed and their
                        armies all but annihilated; when Spain was lost; when four Carthaginian
                        armies and their generals were holding the whole country down by the terror
                        of their arms; when you were looking for a man to take the supreme command
                        in that war and no one appeared, no one came forward to offer himself but
                        me; when the Roman people conferred the supreme command on me before I had
                        reached my twenty-fifth year-why did no one then say anything about my age,
                        the strength of the enemy, the difficulties of the campaign or the recent
                        disaster which had overtaken my father and my uncle? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Has some calamity occurred recently in Africa greater
                        than the one which happened then in Spain? Are there larger armies and
                        better and more numerous commanders in Africa now than there were then in
                        Spain? Was I then at a riper age for undertaking a great war than I am
                        today? Is Spain a more convenient field for operations against the
                        Carthaginians than Africa? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Now that I have
                        scattered four Carthaginian armies in flight, reduced so many cities by
                        force or fear, and subjugated every part down to the shores of the ocean,
                        petty kings and savage tribes alike; now that I have reconquered the whole
                        of Spain so completely that no vestige of war anywhere remains, it is an
                        easy task to make light of my services, as easy, in fact, as it will be,
                        when I have returned victorious from Africa, to make light of those very
                        difficulties which are now painted in such dark colours in order to keep me
                        here. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "Fabius says that no part of Africa is
                        accessible, that there are no harbours open to us. He tells us that M.
                        Atilius Regulus was made prisoner in Africa, as though he had met with
                        misfortune as soon as he landed. He forgets that that very commander,
                        unfortunate as he was afterwards, did find some harbours in Africa open to
                        him, and for the first twelve months won some brilliant victories, and as
                        far as the Carthaginian generals were concerned, remained undefeated to the
                        last. You will not, therefore, deter me by quoting that instance. Even if
                        that disaster had occurred in this war instead of in the last one, quite
                        recently and not forty years ago-even then why should I be prevented from
                        invading Africa because Regulus was made prisoner any more than I was
                        prevented from going to Spain after the two Scipios were killed? <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> I should be sorry to believe that Xanthippus,
                        the Lacedaemonian, was born to be a greater blessing to Carthage than I am
                        to be to my country, and my confidence is strengthened by seeing what
                        tremendous issues depend upon one man's courage. We have had to listen even
                        to stories about the Athenians, how they neglected the war at their doors in
                        order to go to Sicily. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Well, since you
                        are at leisure to tell us tales about Greece why do you not mention
                        Agathocles, king of Syracuse, who after Sicily had long been wasted by the
                        flames of the Punic War sailed across to this same Africa and turned the
                        tide of war back to the country from which it had started?" </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Put what need is there of instances drawn
                        from other lands and other times to remind us how much depends upon taking
                        the aggressive and removing danger from ourselves by making it recoil upon
                        others? It makes all the difference in the world whether you are devastating
                        the territory of another nation or seeing your own destroyed by fire and
                        sword. It shows more courage to attack than to repel attacks. Then again,
                        the unknown always inspires terror, but when you have entered your enemy's
                        country you have a nearer view of his strength and weakness. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Hannibal never hoped that so many communities
                        would go over to him after Cannae; how much less could the Carthaginians,
                        faithless allies, harsh and tyrannical masters as they are, count upon the
                        firmness and stability of their African empire! So far, even when deserted
                        by our allies, we stood in our own strength, the soldiery of Rome. The
                        Carthaginians have no citizen army, their soldiers are all mercenaries,
                        ready to change sides on the smallest provocation. If only nothing stops me,
                        you will hear that I have landed, that Africa is wrapped in the flames of
                        war, that Hannibal is tearing himself away from Italy, that Carthage is
                        besieged-all at one stroke. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> You may look
                        for more cheerful and more frequent news from Africa than you received from
                        Spain. Everything inspires me with hope-the Fortune which waits on Rome, the
                        gods who witnessed the treaty which the enemy has broken, the two princes
                        Syphax and Masinissa, whose fidelity I shall so far trust as to protect
                        myself from any perfidy they may attempt. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Many advantages which at this distance are not apparent will be disclosed as
                        the war goes on. A man proves his capacity for leadership by seizing every
                        opportunity that presents itself, and making every contingency subserve his
                        plans. I shall have the adversary whom you, Q. Fabius assign to
                        me-Hannibal-but I would rather draw him away than that he should keep me
                        here; I would compel him to fight in his own country, and Carthage shall be
                        the prize of victory rather than the half-ruined strongholds of Bruttium. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "And now as to any injury that may befall
                        the republic during my voyage or whilst I am disembarking my men on the
                        shores of Africa or during my advance on Carthage. As the consul, P.
                        Licinius, is also Pontifex Maximus, and cannot be absent from his sacred
                        duties, it is impossible for him to ballot for so distant a province. Would
                        it not be almost an insult to say that he cannot accomplish the task, after
                        Hannibal's power has been shaken and almost shattered, which you, Q. Fabius,
                        were able to accomplish when Hannibal in the hour of victory was flying
                        about in every part of Italy? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And even if
                        the war should not be brought to a more speedy termination by the plan which
                        I suggest, the dignity of Rome and her prestige amongst foreign kings and
                        nations would surely require us to show that we possess sufficient courage
                        not only to defend Italy but to carry our arms even as far as Africa.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We must not let the idea get abroad
                        that no Roman general durst do what Hannibal has done, or that whilst in the
                        First Punic War, when the struggle was for Sicily, Africa was frequently
                        attacked by our fleets and armies, in this war, when the struggle is for
                        Italy, Africa is left in peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Let Italy,
                        which has been so long harassed, have some rest at last; let Africa take its
                        turn of fire and ruin; let a Roman camp threaten the gates of Carthage
                        rather than that we should see the enemy's lines from our walls. Let Africa
                        be the seat of war henceforth; let us roll back there all the terror and the
                        flight, all the wasting of our lands and the defection of our allies, all
                        the other miseries of war which have been assailing us for the last fourteen
                        years. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Enough has been said as to the
                        republic and the present war and the allocation of provinces. It would be a
                        long and uninteresting discussion if I were to follow the example of Q.
                        Fabius, and as he has depreciated my services in Spain, so I were to pour
                        ridicule on his glory and extol my own. I will do neither the one nor the
                        other, senators, and if, young as I am, I cannot have the advantage over an
                        old man in anything else, I will at least prove his superior in moderation
                        and restraint of language. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> My life and my
                        conduct of affairs have been such that I am quite content to accept in
                        silence the judgment which you have spontaneously formed." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio was listened to with impatience,
                        for it was generally believed that if he did not succeed in inducing the
                        senate to decree that Africa should be his province, he would at once bring
                        the question before the Assembly. So Q. Fabius, who had held four
                        consulships, challenged Scipio to say openly before the senate whether he
                        left the decision as to the provinces in their hands, and was prepared to
                        abide by it, or whether he was going to refer it to the people. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Scipio replied that he should act as he thought
                        best in the interests of the State. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On
                        this Fabius observed: "It was not because I did not know what you would say
                        or how you would act that I made my request, for you openly avow that you
                        are sounding the House rather than consulting it, and that if we do not at
                        once assign you the province which you want, you have a resolution ready to
                        put to the Assembly." (Then, turning to the tribunes) "I demand of you,
                        tribunes of the plebs, that you support me in my refusal to vote, for even
                        if the decision is in my favour the consul is not going to recognise it."
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then a discussion arose between the
                        consul and the tribunes, he asserting that there was no just ground for
                        their intervening and supporting a senator in his refusal to vote, when
                        called upon to do so. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The tribunes gave
                        their decision in the following terms: "If the consul submits to the senate
                        the allocation of the provinces their decision shall be binding and final,
                        and we will not allow any reference to the people. If he does not so submit
                        it, we shall support any senator in his refusal to vote when called upon to
                        do so." The consul asked for a day's grace in order to consult his
                        colleague. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The following day he submitted
                        the matter to the decision of the senate. The decree made respecting the
                        provinces was that one consul should take Sicily and the thirty warships
                        which C. Servilius had had the previous year, permission being granted him
                        to sail to Africa, if he thought such a course would be in the interests of
                        the State; the other consul was to take Bruttium and the operations against
                        Hannibal, with either the army which had served under L. Veturius, or the
                        one which Q. Caecilius had commanded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        These two were to ballot and arrange which of them was to act in Bruttium
                        with the two legions which the consul would not require, and the one to whom
                        that field should fall was to have his command extended for a year. With the
                        exception of the consuls and praetors, all who were to take charge of armies
                        and provinces had their commands extended for a year. It fell to Q.
                        Caecilius to act with the consul against Hannibal in Bruttium. </p>
                    <p> Scipio exhibited the Games amidst the applause of a large and enthusiastic
                        crowd of spectators. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> M. Pomponius Matho
                        and Q. Catius were sent on a mission to Delphi to carry thither the offering
                        made from the plunder of Hasdrubal's camp. It was a golden crown of 200
                        pounds' weight, and there were facsimiles of the pieces of spoil made in
                        silver weighing in the aggregate 1000 pounds. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio did not succeed in obtaining permission to levy
                        troops and indeed he did not press the point, but he was allowed to enlist
                        volunteers. As he had stated that his fleet would not be a charge on the
                        State he was given liberty to accept any materials contributed by the allies
                        for the construction of his ships. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        cantons of Etruria were the first to promise assistance, each according to
                        its means. Caere contributed corn and provisions of all kinds for the crews;
                        Populonia, iron; Tarquinii, cloth for the sails; Volaterrae, timber for the
                        hulls and corn; Arretium, 3000 shields and as many helmets, whilst they were
                        ready to supply as many as 50,000 darts, javelins and long spears.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They also offered to furnish all the
                        axes, spades, sickles, gabions and hand-mills required for forty warships as
                        well as 120,000 pecks of wheat and provision for the sailing-masters and the
                        rowers on the voyage. Perusia, Clusium and Russellae sent pine-wood for the
                        timbers of the ships and a large quantity of corn. The Umbrian communities
                        as well as the inhabitants of Nursia, Reate and Amiternum and the whole of
                        the Sabine country promised to furnish men. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> Numerous contingents from the Marsi, the Paeligni and the Marrucini
                        volunteered to serve on board the fleet. Camerinum, a city leagued on a
                        basis of equal rights with Rome, sent a cohort of six hundred men-at-arms.
                        The keels of thirty ships-twenty quinqueremes and ten quadriremes-were laid
                        down, and Scipio pressed on the work so rapidly that forty-five days after
                        the timber had been brought from the forests, the ships were launched with
                        their tackle and armament complete. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio sailed to Sicily with 7000
                        volunteers on board his thirty warships, and P. Licinius proceeded to
                        Bruttium. Of the two consular armies stationed there he selected the one
                        which the former consul L. Veturius had commanded. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He allowed Metellus to keep the legions he was in
                        command of, as he thought he would do better with men accustomed to his
                        leadership. The praetors also departed for their several provinces.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As money was needed for the war the
                        quaestors received instructions to sell that part of the Capuan territory
                        which extends from the Fossa Graeca to the coast, and evidence was asked for
                        of any cases where land had been appropriated by a citizen of Capua, that it
                        might be included in the Roman stateland. The informer was to receive a
                        gratuity of ten per cent. of the value of the land. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The City praetor, Cnaeus Servilius, was also to see
                        that the citizens of Capua were residing where the senate had given them
                        permission to reside, and any who were living elsewhere were to be punished.
                        During the summer Mago who had been wintering in Minorca embarked with a
                        force of 12,000 infantry and 2000 cavalry, and set sail for Italy with about
                        thirty warships and a large number of transports. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The coast was quite unguarded and he surprised and
                        captured Genua. From there he went on to the Ligurian coast on the chance of
                        rousing the Gauls. One of their tribes-the Ingauni-were at the time engaged
                        in a war with the Epanterii, an Alpine tribe. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> After storing his plunder in Savo and leaving ten
                        vessels as guardships, Mago sent the remainder of his ships to Carthage to
                        protect the coast, as it was rumoured that Scipio intended to invade Africa,
                        and then he formed an alliance with the Ingauni, from whom he expected more
                        support than from the mountaineers, and commenced to attack the latter. His
                        army grew in numbers every day; the Gauls, drawn by the spell of his name,
                        flocked to him from all parts. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        movement became known in Rome through a despatch from Spurius Lucretius, and
                        the senate were filled with the gravest apprehensions. It seemed as though
                        the joy with which they heard of the destruction of Hasdrubal and his army
                        two years before would be completely stultified <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> by the outbreak of a fresh war in the same quarter,
                        quite as serious as the former one, the only difference being in the
                        commander. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They sent orders to the
                        proconsul M. Livius to move the army of Etruria up to Ariminum, and the City
                        praetor, Cnaeus Servilius, was empowered, in case he thought it advisable,
                        to order the City legions to be employed elsewhere and give the command to
                        the man whom he thought most capable. M. Valerius Laevinus led these legions
                        to Arretium. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> About this time Cnaeus
                        Octavius who was commanding in Sardinia captured as many as eighty
                        Carthaginian transports in the neighbourhood. According to Coelius' account
                        they were loaded with corn and supplies for Hannibal; Valerius, however,
                        says that they were carrying the plunder from Etruria and the Ligurian and
                        Epanterian prisoners to Carthage. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hardly
                        anything worth recording took place in Bruttium this year. A pestilence
                        attacked the Romans and the Carthaginians and was equally fatal to both, but
                        in addition to the epidemic, the Carthaginians were suffering from scarcity
                        of food. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hannibal spent the summer near
                        the temple of Juno Lacinia, where he built and dedicated an altar with a
                        long inscription recording his exploits in Phoenician and also in Greek.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
