<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 28-30 - 28</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Moore" role="editor"> Frank Gardener Moore, Professor Emeritus in
                    Columbia University </editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XXVIII-XXX With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1949: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.3"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="book">
                <head>Book XXVIII</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> WHILE the passage of Hasdrubal, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Hasdrubal's attempt to aid his brother
                        Hannibal by a second invasion of Italy had ended in disaster at the
                        Metaurus; XXVII. xlvii. ff. The narrative now reverts to Spain, where a
                        third brother, Mago, was in command of an army. </note> by shifting <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> the war to
                    Italy, was felt to have lightened in proportion the burden for Spain, suddenly a
                    war as dangerous as the former broke out again in that country. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Spanish territory was at that time occupied by Romans and
                    Carthaginians as follows: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal son of
                    Gisgo had retired all the way to the Ocean and Gades; the coast of Our Sea and
                    nearly all of Spain facing eastward were under Scipio and Roman rule; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> a new commander, Hanno, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> When a second descent upon Italy was first planned nine
                        years earlier, Hasdrubal had urged the authorities at Carthage to send out
                        another army with a general to take his place in Spain; XXIII. xxvii. 12. A
                        new commander has now arrived, but this Hanno is soon captured and sent to
                        Rome; ii. 11; iv. 4. </note> as successor to Hasdrubal Barca had crossed
                    over from Africa with a new army, and uniting with Mago, had promptly armed men
                    in large numbers in Celtiberia, which lies directly between the two seas.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whereupon Scipio sent Marcus Silanus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXVI. xix. 10; XXVII. vii. 17; xxii.
                        7.</note> with not more than ten thousand infantry and five hundred cavalry
                    against Hanno. Silanus made his marches as long <pb n="p.5"/> as possible, being
                    hampered, however, both by rough <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 207</note> roads and narrow passes frequently hemmed in
                    by wooded mountains, as is usual in Spain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Nevertheless he outstripped not only messengers reporting his approach but even
                    rumours of it, and guided by deserters from the same Celtiberia he made his way
                    to the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From the same informants it was
                    learned, when they were about ten miles from the enemy, that there were two
                    camps, one on each side of the road along which they were moving; that, on the
                    left lay the Celtiberians, a new army, over nine thousand men, on the right the
                    Carthaginian camp; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that this was strongly
                    defended by outposts, sentries and all the protection usual in the field, while
                    the other camp was lax and carelessly guarded, as belonging to barbarians who
                    were raw recruits and less afraid because they were in their own country. </p>
                <p> Silanus, thinking this camp must be attacked first, ordered the standards to
                    move as far to the left as possible, for fear he might be seen from somewhere by
                    the Carthaginian outposts. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He sent scouts in
                    advance and himself proceeded towards the enemy with a swiftly moving column.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He was some three miles away when not one of
                    the enemy had yet noticed them; a rugged terrain and brush-covered hills kept
                    them concealed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There in a deep valley that
                    was consequently unseen he bade his soldiers sit down and take food. Meantime
                    came the scouts confirming the deserters' reports. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Then the Romans piled their light baggage in the centre,
                    took up their arms and advanced to fight in regular line of battle. They were a
                    mile away when they were seen by the enemy, who suddenly began to show alarm.
                    Mago too, leaving his <pb n="p.7"/> camp at the first shouting and uproar, rode
                    up at a <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note>
                    gallop. In the army of the Celtiberians there were four thousand men with long
                    shields and two hundred horsemen. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This
                    complete legion —and they were the best of his troops —was placed in the front
                    line. The rest, the light-armed, he posted as reserves. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> While he was leading the men in that order out of their
                    camp and they had scarcely got beyond the rampart, the Romans hurled their
                    javelins at them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Spaniards squatted down
                    to meet the enemy's volley; then they in turn rose to hurl their weapons. After
                    the Romans in dense array, as usual, had received these on their shields held
                    close together, men fought at close quarters and began to use swords. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> But the roughness of the ground made nimbleness of no
                    use to the Celtiberians, whose custom it is to be skirmishers in battle, and at
                    the same time it was not unfavourable for the Romans, accustomed to a static
                    order of battle, except that restricted spaces and intervening thickets broke up
                    their ranks, and they <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> were forced to engage
                    now singly, now in couples, as though with men paired against them. Whatever
                    hampered the flight of the enemy exposed them to slaughter, as if they were
                    fettered. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And now that nearly all the
                    Celtiberian heavy infantry had been slain, the <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> light-armed and the Carthaginians who had come to their aid
                    from the other camp were being routed and cut down. Not more than two thousand
                    infantry and all the cavalry escaped with Mago almost at the beginning of the
                    battle. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hanno, the second in command, was
                    captured alive with those who had been the last to arrive when the battle was
                    nearly over. Almost all the cavalry and such old soldiers as there were in the
                    infantry <pb n="p.9"/> followed Mago in flight and on the tenth day reached
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note>
                    Hasdrubal <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The son of Gisgo, mentioned
                        just above, i. 2; cf. iii. 3. </note> in the region of Gades. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> The newly recruited Celtiberians slipped away into
                    the neighbouring forests and thence scattered to their homes. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This very timely victory had made a sudden
                    end, not so much indeed of the war already in progress, as of the resources for
                    some subsequent war, had it been possible for the Carthaginians, after calling
                    out the Celtiberian nation, to entice other tribes also to take up arms.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Accordingly Scipio praised Silanus in
                    generous terms and cherished the hope of ending the war if only he should not
                    retard the fulfilment by his own delaying. Aiming to finish what remained of the
                    war he proceeded into the farthest part of Spain against Hasdrubal. The
                    Carthaginian, in order to ensure the loyalty of his allies, had his camp at that
                    time, as it happened, in Baetica. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Here not the later (Augustan) province of that name, but a vague term for
                        the southernmost part of Spain, including Gades and most of the valley of
                        the Baetis (Guadalquivir). </note>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Nevertheless he suddenly took up his
                    standards and with the appearance of a flight rather than of a march led his men
                    all the way to the Ocean and Gades. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But
                    before taking ship along the strait to Gades, thinking he would be the object of
                    attack so long as he kept his army together, he scattered his entire force among
                    the cities in every direction, that they might defend themselves by walls and at
                    the same time defend walled cities by their arms. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, observing that the field of operations
                    was widely extended, and that to attack the cities one after another would be a
                    protracted task, if not a great one, turned back. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Not to leave the region, however, to the enemy, he sent his
                    brother Lucius <pb n="p.11"/> Scipio with ten thousand infantry and a thousand
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note>
                    cavalry to besiege the wealthiest city in that country —Orongis <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably the same as Auringis (or
                        Aurinx) in Andalusia; XXIV. xlii. 5. </note> the barbarians called it. It is
                    situated in the territory of the Maesesses, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Mention of silver mining places this lesser tribe in
                        the mountains, while the Bastetani proper occupied the south coast. </note>
                    a Bastetanian tribe. Its land is fruitful; the inhabitants mine silver also.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That city had been a stronghold for
                    Hasdrubal in making-raids among the tribes of the interior. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio pitched his camp near the city and before investing
                    it sent men up to the gates to sound the inhabitants by speaking to them from a
                    short distance, urging them to test the friendship of the Romans rather than
                    their power. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When no peaceable replies were
                    forthcoming, he surrounded the city with a trench and a double earthwork and
                    divided his army into three parts, so that one third should always be attacking
                    while two thirds in the meantime were resting. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    When the first third essayed an attack there was, to be sure, a fierce battle
                    and indecisive. It was not easy to come near the walls for the shower of
                    missiles, nor to bring up ladders. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some who
                    had succeeded in raising their ladders against the walls were pushed down by
                    forks made for that very purpose, others had iron grappling-hooks lowered upon
                    them from above, so that they were in danger of being caught up and dragged to
                    the top of the wall. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When Scipio noted that
                    owing to the greatly inferior number of his men the struggle was evenly
                    balanced, and that the enemy had an advantage already in fighting from the wall,
                    he attacked the city with two thirds of his men at the same time, having
                    recalled the first third. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This <pb n="p.13"/>
                    inspired so much alarm among men already spent in <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> fighting with the first to
                    attack them that the townsmen in sudden flight abandoned the walls and for fear
                    the city had been betrayed the Carthaginian garrison also left their posts and
                    gathered in one place. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then the men of the town were possessed by
                    the fear that, if the enemy should enter the city, those whom they happened to
                    meet anywhere would be slain with no distinction between Carthaginian and
                    Spaniard. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly they suddenly opened a
                    gate and dashed out of the town in large numbers, holding their shields in front
                    of them for fear weapons might be hurled at long range, but displaying their
                    right hands empty, so that it should be clear that they had thrown away their
                    swords. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Whether this was not seen owing to
                    distance, or whether some ruse was suspected, has not been ascertained. The
                    Romans, making an attack upon the deserters, cut them down like an opposing
                    battle-line; and by the same gate hostile units entered the city. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Elsewhere also gates were being hewed to pieces and
                    broken open with hatchets and pickaxes, while a cavalryman on entering would
                    ride ahead at full speed to seize the forum; for such were their orders. A
                    detachment of <hi rend="italics">triarii</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The seasoned infantry, here on
                        special duty, not in the formal battle line with its <hi rend="italics"
                            >ordines</hi> (as in XXVI. xlvi. 7). Cf. VIII. viii. 9ff.; x. 5;
                        Polybius VI. xxi. 7ff. </note> also had been assigned to support the
                    cavalry. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The legionaries made their way
                    through the other quarters of the city. They refrained from plundering and from
                    slaying those they met, except when men defended themselves with arms.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians were all put under
                    guard, also about three hundred of the citizens who had closed the gates.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The town was handed over to the rest and
                    their property restored. About two thousand of the <pb n="p.15"/> enemy were
                    slain in the siege of the city, of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 207</note> Romans not more than ninety. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The storming of that city brought joy not only
                    to those who took part in the exploit but also to the commander-in-chief and the
                    rest of his army; and the troops made their approach an impressive sight, as
                    they drove before them a great crowd of captives. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio warmly praised his brother, with the highest
                    possible compliment placing his capture of Orongis on the same level as his own
                    capture of (New) Carthage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Thereupon, and
                    because winter was at hand, so that he was unable either to attack Gades or to
                    follow up Hasdrubal's army, widely scattered throughout the province, he led all
                    his forces back into Hither Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After
                    sending the legions away to their winter quarters and his brother Lucius Scipio
                    to Rome, and with him Hanno, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See p. 3,
                        n. 2.</note> a general of the enemy, and the rest of the noble captives, he
                    himself retired to Tarraco. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The same year a Roman fleet under Marcus
                    Valerius Laevinus, the proconsul, was sent over from Sicily to Africa, and in
                    the territory of Utica and Carthage they ravaged the country far and wide. Along
                    the edge of the Carthaginian territory, close to the very walls of Utica, booty
                    was carried off. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On their return voyage to
                    Sicily a Carthaginian fleet of seventy warships encountered them. Seventeen of
                    these were captured, four sunk at sea, the rest of the fleet routed and put to
                    flight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Victorious on land and sea, the Romans
                    returned with ample plunder of every kind to Lilybaeum. Thereafter, as the sea
                    was safe in consequence of the discomfiture of the enemy's ships, great supplies
                    of grain were brought to Rome. </p>
                <pb n="p.17"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the summer in which these
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note>
                    events took place <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Since Roman
                        progress in Greece had been slow Livy is summarizing events of 208 and <date
                            when="-0207">207 B.C.</date> in that theatre under the latter year. Cf.
                        XXVII. xxix. 9 ff. (Vol. VII. p. 330, n. 2). Polybius is the source (X. xli.
                        f.) for the events which follow. </note> Publius Sulpicius, the proconsul,
                    and King Attalus, after wintering at Aegina, as has been stated above, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> XXVII. xxxiii. 5. </note> sailed across to
                    Lemnus with their combined fleets, twenty-five Roman and thirty-five royal
                    quinqueremes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And Philip, to be prepared for
                    every effort of the enemy, whether he must be met on land or on sea, came down
                    himself to the sea at Demetrias <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At
                        the north end of the Sinus Pagasaeus (Demetriacus in §18), it was the chief
                        trade centre of Thessaly; cf. Vol. VII. p. 342, n. 2. </note> and appointed
                    a day for the army to assemble at Larisa. From his allies all around deputations
                    gathered at Demetrias on the first report of the king's coming. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> For the Aetolians in consequence of their alliance with the
                    Romans, and particularly after the arrival of Attalus, <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> had been emboldened and were laying waste their neighbours'
                    lands. And not only were the Acarnanians and Boeotians and the <milestone
                        n="5??" unit="section"/> inhabitants of Euboea greatly alarmed but also the
                    Achaeans, who in addition to the Aetolian war were further terrified by
                    Machanidas, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXVII. xxix. 9; below,
                        vii. 17.</note> tyrant of Sparta, who had pitched his camp not far from the
                    Argive frontier. All these delegations stated the dangers impending by land and
                    sea for their several cities and were imploring the aid of the king. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Even from his own kingdom the report was of no
                    peaceful conditions: that Scerdilaedus and Pleuratus had taken the field;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> also that of the Thracians the Maedi <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Between Thrace and Paeonia, in the
                        upper valley of the Strymon and eastward; XXVI. xxv. 6, 8. </note> in
                    particular were ready to invade the nearest part of Macedonia if some distant
                    war should <pb n="p.19"/> engage the king's attention. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> In fact the Boeotians <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> and inland Greek states
                    reported that the pass of Thermopylae, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Cf. vii. 3; Strabo IX. iv. 12 ff.</note> where a narrow entrance hems in
                    the road, was being closed with a ditch and an earthwork by the Aetolians, that
                    it might not allow Philip a passage in order to defend the cities of his allies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Even a general lacking in spirit might have
                    been aroused by so many alarms from all sides. Philip sent the deputations away
                    with a promise that he would lend aid to them all as time and circumstances
                    might permit. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As the urgency of the moment
                    required, he sent to Peparēthus a garrison for the city, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Of the same name as the island, and destroyed by
                        Philip; XXXI. xxviii. 6. </note> from which had come the news that Attalus,
                    sending his fleet over from Lemnus, had ravaged all the country round the city.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Philip sent Polyphantas with a force of
                    moderate size into Boeotia; also one of his own generals, Menippus, to Chalcis
                    with a thousand peltasts, whose shield is not unlike the <hi rend="italics"
                        >caetra.</hi>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Five hundred of the Agrianes <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Paeonian auxiliaries (archers) of the
                        Macedonians; XXXIII. xviii. 9; Thucydides II. 96; Polybius II. lxv; X. xlii.
                        3; Strabo VII. fr. 36 f. </note> were added, to enable Menippus to protect
                    all parts of the island. The king himself set out for Scotussa and ordered that
                    the Macedonian troops should march across from Larisa to the same place.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There the report reached him that a
                    council had been appointed for the Aetolians at Heraclēa, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Above Thermopylae, to the west of the pass and
                        commanding the road to it; XXXVI. xvi. 4 f.; xxii. 1, 4 f.; Thuc. III. 92;
                        Strabo IX. iv. 13; Polybius X. xlii. 4. From Scotussa, in eastern Thessaly,
                        to Thermopylae the distance was about 50 Roman miles; cf. vii. 3. </note>
                    and that <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> King Attalus would attend for a
                    consultation on the issues of the war. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> To
                    break up this gathering by his sudden arrival Philip led his men by forced
                    marches to Heraclēa. He arrived indeed after the <pb n="p.21"/> council had been
                    dismissed; but he destroyed crops <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 207</note> which were now almost ripe, especially along
                    the Gulf of the Aenianes, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the Sinus Maliacus (XXVII. xxx. 3), for the
                        Aenianes lay to the west of that gulf. </note> and led his troops back to
                    Scotussa. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> There he left the whole army and
                    with his cohort of guards returned to Demetrias. From there, in order that he
                    might meet every movement of his enemies, he sent men into Phocis and Euboea and
                    to Peparethus, to select heights from which signal fires might be visible.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> For himself he placed a watch-tower on
                    Mount Tisaeus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plainly visible from
                        Demetrias across the gulf. The height of the mountain is 2112 ft. Cf.
                        Polybius X. xlii. 7. </note> whose peak rises to a great height, so that by
                    fires <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For signalling by fires cf.
                        XXIX. vi. 8, 10. Polybius has an excursus of several pages on the subject,
                        including improvements he had himself made; <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi>
                        xliii-xlvii. The Romans seem to have made no use of so elaborate a system;
                        cf. Riepl, <hi rend="italics">Das Nachrichtenwesen des Altertums</hi> 61 f.,
                        74 ff., 91 ff. </note> on distant heights he might in an instant receive a
                    message as to where his enemies were active. </p>
                <p> The Roman commander and King Attalus crossed from Peparethus to Nicaea. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A stronghold of the Eastern Locrians
                        and a seaport 2 1/2 miles east of Thermopylae; XXXII. xxxii. 9; xxxv. 2;
                        Polybius X. xlii. 4; XVIII. vii. 8; Strabo IX. iv. 13. </note>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> From there they sailed over to Euboea in
                    their fleet and to the city of Oreum, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cf. XXXI. xlvi. 6 if.; Strabo X. i. 3 if. Earlier it had been called
                        Histiaea. </note> which is the first of the cities of Euboea situated on the
                    left as one coming from the Gulf of Demetrias steers towards Chalcis and the
                    Euripus. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Between Attalus and Sulpicius it was
                    agreed that the Romans should attack from the sea, the king's forces from the
                    land. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In four days after the fleet came in they
                    attacked the city. That time was spent in secret conversations with Plator, who
                    had been put in command of the city by Philip. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The place has two citadels, one overhanging the sea; the other is in the centre
                    of the city. From it a road leads down to the sea through a tunnel, and at <pb
                        n="p.23"/> the seaward end a tower having fie stories, a <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> remarkable
                    defensive work, used to close the road. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There
                    at first a very fierce engagement began, for the tower was provided with
                    missiles of every kind, while artillery also and engines had been landed from
                    the ships for an attack upon it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When that
                    conflict had diverted the attention and the eyes of all, Plator admitted the
                    Romans through a gate in the citadel by the sea, and in an instant the citadel
                    was seized. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The citizens being repulsed
                    hastened to the heart of the city and the other citadel; and men had been posted
                    there to close the gates. Being thus shut out they were surrounded and slain or
                    captured. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Macedonian garrison stood in a
                    mass under the wall of the citadel, having neither taken to flight in disorder
                    nor gone into battle with determination. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Plator, having gained permission from Sulpicius, embarked his men and landed
                    them at Demetrium <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Two and a half
                        miles from Thebae Phthiotides and named from a temple of Demeter. It was
                        known also as Pyrasus; Strabo IX. v. 14. </note> in Phthiotis, while he
                    himself joined Attalus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Sulpicius, inspired by a success so easily won
                    at Oreum, sailed thence with his victorious fleet directly to Chalcis, where the
                    result by no means matched his expectation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The sea, which from a wide expanse on both sides is narrowed into a strait,
                    might give one at first sight the appearance of a double harbour facing two
                    entrances. But hardly any other anchorage is more dangerous for a fleet.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For sudden, squally winds blow down from
                    very high mountains on either shore, and also the Euripus strait itself does not
                    reverse its direction seven times a day at <pb n="p.25"/> fixed times, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is the statement of Strabo <hi
                            rend="italics">l.c.</hi> ii. 8 and Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi>
                        II. 219. Regularity is stressed by Cicero <hi rend="italics">N.D.</hi> III.
                        24, without giving the number of times daily. But the irregularity was
                        proverbial; Plato <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi> 90 C. In actual fact the
                        real tides are perfectly regular, with four changes daily, while in a strait
                        so narrow very marked irregularities are due to secondary causes, chiefly
                        winds. </note> as report has it, but with a current that <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> like the
                    wind changes irregularly, now this way, now that, it races along as a torrent
                    dashes down from a steep mountain. Thus neither by night nor by day are ships
                    given rest. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Not only was the anchorage into
                    which the fleet came so dangerous, but in addition the town was strong and
                    impregnable, being protected on one side by the sea, on the other side, towards
                    the land, extraordinarily fortified and secured by a strong garrison and in
                    particular by the loyalty of its commanders and leading citizens, a quality
                    which at Oreum had been uncertain and delusive. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> It was wise on the part of the Roman, considering his rash undertaking, that
                    after surveying the difficulties, in order not to waste time for nothing, he
                    promptly gave up the attempt and with his fleet crossed over to Cynus in Locris,
                    the mart of the city of Opus, which is situated a mile from the sea. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Nearly two miles from the sea according
                        to Strabo IX. iv. 2, and less than eight east of its port, Cynus. Opus was
                        the chief city of the Eastern (Opuntian) Locrians. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip had been warned also by fire-signals
                    from Oreum, but through the treachery of Plator they were set too late on the
                    watch-tower. Also, since he was no match in naval strength, approach to the
                    island by a fleet was not easy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He let slip
                    that project by delaying, and, on receiving the signal accordingly, set out with
                    spirit to bring aid to Chalcis. For although Chalcis is likewise a city of the
                    same island, still it is separated by a strait so narrow that the city is linked
                    to the mainland by a bridge, and approach by land is easier than by sea.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly Philip <pb n="p.27"/> hastened
                    from Demetrias to Scotussa, whence he set <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> out in the third watch,
                    dislodged the garrison and routed the Aetolians occupying the pass of
                    Thermopylae. Then after driving the enemy in alarm into Heraclēa, he himself in
                    a single day covered a distance of more than sixty miles to Elatīa <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The largest city of Phocis, commanding
                        roads from the north coast and Thermopylae; Strabo IX. iii. 2, 15. </note>
                    in Phocis. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On about the same day the captured
                    city of Opus was being sacked by King Attalus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Its booty had been given up to the king by Sulpicius because Oreum <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The name is always masculine in our
                        Greek sources.</note> had been sacked by Roman soldiers a few days before,
                    while the king's troops had no share in it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    When the Roman fleet had returned to Oreum, Attalus, unaware of the coming of
                    Philip, was spending his time in exacting money from leading citizens.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And so unexpected was the attack that if
                    some of the Cretans, who happened to have gone a long distance from the city to
                    forage, had not caught sight of the enemy's column in the distance, the king
                    could have been overpowered. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Attalus' men,
                    being unarmed and in disorder, rushed pellmell to the sea and their ships; and
                    as they were struggling to cast off, Philip came upon them and from the shore
                    caused further confusion among the sailors. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Then he returned to Opus, accusing gods and men because he had lost so great an
                    opportunity, snatched away almost before his eyes. The men of Opus also were no
                    less angrily upbraided because, although they could have dragged out the siege
                    until his coming, at the first sight of the enemy they had almost willingly
                    surrendered. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.29"/>
                <p> Having settled matters in the neighbourhood of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> Opus, he went to Thronium.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> More than two miles from the sea
                        (Strabo IX. iv. 4), this ancient town was high-perched at the west end of
                        Mt. Cnemis. Hence the Locrians of this region were called Epicnemidian. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Attalus also retired at first to Oreum; and
                    then, when the report reached him that Prusias, King of Bithynia, had crossed
                    into territory belonging to his kingdom, he sailed over to Asia, forsaking the
                    Roman cause and the Aetolian war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And
                    Sulpicius withdrew with his fleet to Aegina, from which he had set out at the
                    beginning of the spring. Philip captured Thronium with no greater struggle than
                    Attalus had in capturing Opus. The inhabitants of the former were refugees from
                    Thebes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A very ancient and important
                        city of Achaia Phthiotis, on a ridge above its port, Pyrasus, two miles away
                        on the Sinus Pagasaeus; Strabo IX. v. 14. </note> in Phthiotis. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> When their city was taken by Philip they had sought
                    refuge in the protection of the Aetolians, whereupon the Aetolians had given
                    them an abiding-place in that city, desolated and abandoned in a previous war
                    with the same Philip. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then setting out from
                    Thronium, which he had recovered, as has just been said, he captured Tithronion
                    and Drumiae, small and unimportant towns in Doris. Then he came to Elatīa,
                    having bidden the envoys of Ptolemy and of the Rhodians <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXVII. xxx. 4.</note> to wait for him there.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> While they were there discussing how to
                    end the Aetolian war —for <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> the envoys had
                    recently been present at the council of the Romans and Aetolians at Heraclēa
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. v. 13 f.</note> —came the news
                    that Machanidas had decided to attack the Eleans, who were making ready to
                    celebrate the Olympic Games. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> those of the year <date when="-0208">208
                            B.C.</date> ; cf. XXVII. xxxv. 3. </note>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Thinking he must make that his first task,
                    the king <pb n="p.31"/> sent away the envoys with a friendly answer: that <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> he had not
                    been the cause of this war, and would not delay making peace, provided it was
                    possible to do so on fair and honourable terms. <milestone n="18" unit="section"
                    /> Setting out with a light column he came down through Boeotia to Megara and
                    then to Corinth, from which he took on supplies and marched to Phlīus and
                    Phenĕus. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Phlīus lay south-west of
                        Corinth; Phenĕus farther west, near a lake of the same name, at the foot of
                        Mt. Cyllene in north-eastern Arcadia. </note> And when he had already
                    reached Heraea, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In western Arcadia,
                        on the river Alphēus and the road to Olympia. It still belonged to the
                        Macedonian king. Cf. Pausanias <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> xxvi. </note> he heard that Machanidas,
                    alarmed by the report of his coming, had fled back to Sparta. Thereupon the king
                    went to Aegium for the council of the Achaeans, at the same time thinking that
                    there he would find the Carthaginian fleet which he had summoned that he might
                    be able to accomplish something by sea as well. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> A few days earlier the Carthaginians had crossed over to the Oxēae, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Oxēae were small western islands
                        off the mouth of the Achelōus and opposite Cephallenia. They formed the
                        southernmost group of the Echinades archipelago. Cf. Strabo VIII. iii. 26
                            <hi rend="italics">fin.;</hi> X. ii. 19. </note> and then had made for
                    the Acarnanian ports, on hearing that Attalus and the Romans had set sail from
                    Oreum. They were afraid they might be pursued and overpowered inside of Rhium,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Properly the Headland on the
                        south side of the strait, and its counterpart, Antirrhium, on the Aetolian
                        side, marking the entrance to the Gulf of Corinth; Thuc. II. 86; Strabo
                        VIII. ii. 3; Pausanias VII. xxii. 10 (Frazer). Also at times of the strait
                        itself; so Livy here and in XXVII. xxix. 9. </note> the narrows, that is, of
                    the Gulf of Corinth. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> VIII. Philip was sorry indeed and vexed that,
                    although he had himself made rapid marches in every direction, nevertheless he
                    had not met a single situation at the right moment, and that fortune had mocked
                    his speed by whisking everything out of his sight. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In the council, however, concealing his vexation, he made a
                    proud speech, calling gods and men <pb n="p.33"/> to witness that at no place or
                    time had he failed to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 207</note> hasten with all possible speed to any place where the din
                    of enemies' arms had been heard. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But it could
                    scarcely be made out, he said, whether his audacity in carrying on the war was
                    the greater, or his enemies' eagerness to run away. So from Opus Attalus had
                    slipped out of his hands, so had Sulpicius from Chalcis, so in those very days
                    had Machanidas. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But not always was flight
                    successful, nor must that be accounted a difficult war in which you are the
                    victor if you have merely made contact with the enemy. What was of most
                    significance, he said, he had the confession of his enemies that they were by no
                    means his equals. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Soon he would likewise have
                    no uncertain victory, and they would fight against him with a result no better
                    than they had hoped. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The allies rejoiced when they listened to the
                    king. Thereupon he delivered Heraea and Triphylia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Not actually given back to Achaia until <date
                            when="-0198">198 B.C.</date> ; XXXII. v. 4. Cf. Strabo VIII. iii. 3. For
                        Heraea cf. p. 30, n. 2. Triphylia lay south of the Alphēus, and reached the
                        sea on the west. </note> to the Achaeans, but restored Aliphēra <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In Arcadia, near the border of
                        Triphylia; XXXII. l.c.; Pausanias VIII. xxvi. 5-7. </note> to Megalopolis,
                    because the citizens of the latter gave sufficient proofs that it had belonged
                    to their territory. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then on receiving
                    ships-they were three quadriremes and as many biremes-from the Achaeans, he
                    sailed over to Anticyra. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Locrian
                        Anticyra, near the entrance to the Gulf; cf. Vol. VII. p. 100, n. </note>
                    From there he set sail with seven quinqueremes and more than twenty light
                    vessels previously sent by him into the Gulf of Corinth to be added to the
                    Carthaginian fleet, and made a landing at <pb n="p.35"/> Erythrae, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A seaport of the Ozolian Locrians, on
                        the north shore of the Gulf, but at this time belonging to the Aetolians.
                        Inland and to the north lay Eupalium. </note> in Aetolia and near Eupalium.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He did <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> not surprise the
                    Aetolians, for all the men who were either on the farms or in the nearest
                    strongholds, Potidania <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Mentioned by
                        Thucydides III. 96; along the upper course of the Daphnus river, north-west
                        of Anticyra and Erythrae. Not far away was a similar stronghold, Apollonia,
                        not to be confused with any of the better-known Apollonias. </note> and
                    Apollonia, fled into the forests and the mountains. Sheep and goats which in
                    their haste could not be driven away were seized and loaded on the ships.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> With these and the rest of the booty
                    Nicias, chief magistrate of the Achaeans, was sent to Aegium; and when the king
                    had reached Corinth, he ordered his land forces to march from there overland
                    across Boeotia. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He himself sailing from
                    Cenchreae along the coast of Attica round Sunium, almost through the midst of
                    enemy fleets, came to Chalcis. Then, after praising their loyalty and courage,
                    in that neither fear nor hope had swayed their spirit, and encouraging them to
                    remain his allies with the same steadfastness for the future, if they preferred
                    their own lot to that of the men of Oreum and Opus, he sailed from Chalcis to
                    Oreum. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then entrusting the government and
                    defence of the city to leading citizens who had preferred to flee after the
                    capture of the city rather than to surrender to the Romans, he himself crossed
                    over from Euboea to Demetrias, from which he had first set out to bring aid to
                    his allies. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> At Cassandrīa <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On the Chalcidic Peninsula; formerly
                        called Potidaea, but rebuilt by Cassander (founder of Thessalonica also) in
                            <date when="-0316">316 B.C.</date> Cf. XLIV. xi. 2. </note> he then laid
                    down the keels of a hundred war-ships and brought together a great number of
                    ship-carpenters to complete the task. Having done so, inasmuch as peaceful
                    conditions had been produced in Greece both by the departure of Attalus and by
                    the timely aid which he <pb n="p.37"/> had himself borne to his distressed
                    allies, he withdrew <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        207</note> into his own kingdom in order to wage war against the Dardanians.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For their threatened invasion cf.
                        XXVII. xxxii. 9; xxxiii. 1. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the end of the summer in which these events
                    took place in Greece, Quintus Fabius Maximus the son, as an emissary of Marcus
                    Livius, the consul, reported to the senate at Rome that the consul considered
                    Lucius Porcius with his legions a sufficient defence for Gaul, his own
                    assignment; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The undefined region
                        meant by Gallia was often called Ager Gallicus, or merely suggested by the
                        town-name Ariminum. There was no province then in the sense comparable to'
                        province of Sardinia.' Cf. Vol. VI. p. 315 and n. 2; below, x. 12; xxxviii.
                        13; XXIX, xiii. 2; XXX. i. 7. </note> that he himself could retire from it
                    and his consular army could be withdrawn. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Thereupon the senators ordered that not merely Marcus Livius but also his
                    colleague Gaius Claudius should return to the city. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The only difference in the decree was that they ordered the
                    return of the army of Marcus Livius, but that Nero's legions facing Hannibal
                    should remain in that province. Between the consuls an agreement was made by
                    letter that, just as they had carried on the war with one purpose only, so,
                    although coming from opposite directions, they should approach the city at one
                    and the same time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whichever should first
                    reach Praeneste was instructed to wait for his colleague there. It chanced that
                    both reached Praeneste on the same day. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From
                    there they sent in advance an edict that three days later the senate should meet
                    with full attendance in the Temple of Bellona; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This temple stood below the Citadel and near the east
                        end of the Flaminian Circus. Being outside the pomerium it was used by the
                        senate when returning generals were to present their claims to a triumph;
                        also when foreign ambassadors were to be received. Cf. xxxviii. 2; XXVI.
                        xxi. 1; XXX. xxi. 12; XLII. xxxvi. 2. </note> and with the whole populace
                    flocking out to meet them they drew near to the city. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Not only did everyone in the surrounding crowd greet them,
                        <pb n="p.39"/> but vying with one another in their desire to grasp <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note> the
                    victorious right hands of the consuls some were congratulating them, others were
                    offering thanks because by their services the state was safe. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> In the senate after the manner of all commanders-in-chief
                    they stated their achievements and demanded that for a brave and successful
                    conduct of the war honour should be paid to the immortal gods; likewise that
                    they themselves should be permitted to enter the city in triumph. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Whereupon the senators replied that they did indeed
                    decree the granting of their demands with due recognition first of the gods, and
                    then next to the gods, of the consuls. After a thanksgiving had been decreed in
                    honour of them both and <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> a triumph also to
                    each, in order that they should not have separate triumphs after conducting the
                    war with a common purpose, they came to an agreement as follows. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Inasmuch as the battle had been fought in the
                    province of Marcus Livius, and on the day of the battle the auspices also, as it
                    happened, had been his, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Since the
                        consuls had commanded on alternate days, only one of them had both <hi
                            rend="italics">imperium</hi> and auspices on the day of the battle
                    </note> and inasmuch as Livius' army had been brought back to Rome, while Nero's
                    could not be brought back from his province, they agreed between them that
                    Marcus Livius should enter the city in a four-horse chariot with his soldiers
                    following him, and that Gaius Claudius should ride on horseback without his
                    soldiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This sharing of the triumph added indeed to
                    the glory of both, but even more so for the one who had yielded to his colleague
                    in honour to the same degree that he surpassed him in his achievement.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That man now on horseback in the space of
                    six days had traversed the whole length of Italy, men kept saying, and had
                    fought, standards against standards, with <pb n="p.41"/> Hasdrubal in Gaul on a
                    day on which Hannibal had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 207</note> believed the consul had his camp established
                    facing his own in Apulia. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Thus a single
                    consul in defence of both regions of Italy had confronted two armies and two
                    generals, here with his strategy and there in person. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Nero's name had been enough, they said, to keep Hannibal
                    within his camp. As for Hasdrubal, what else than Nero's arrival had overwhelmed
                    and destroyed him? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Thus let the other consul
                    drive standing erect in a chariot drawn, if he wished, by many horses. The truly
                    triumphant progress through the city was on a single horse; and Nero, even if he
                    went on foot, would be memorable, be it for the glory won in that war, or for
                    his contempt of it in that triumph. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Such was
                    the talk of the spectators who accompanied Nero all the way to the Capitol. As
                    for money, the consuls carried into the Treasury three million sesterces and
                    eighty thousand <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> To his soldiers Marcus Livius apportioned
                    fifty-six <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> apiece. Gaius Claudius promised the same
                    amount to his absent soldiers when he should return to the army. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> It has been remarked that in the jesting of the
                    soldiers on that day more of their songs were levelled at Gaius Claudius than at
                    their own consul; <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> that the knights highly
                    extolled Lucius Veturius and Quintus Caecilius, the lieutenant-generals, and
                    urged the commons to elect them consuls for the following year; <milestone
                        n="20" unit="section"/> also that to the knights' preliminary choice the
                    consuls on the next day added their authority by an address to the people,
                    stating what brave and faithful service they had had in particular from their
                    two lieutenants. </p>
                <pb n="p.43"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Inasmuch as the time for elections was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 207</note>
                    approaching and it had been decided that the elections should be conducted by a
                    dictator, the consul Gaius Claudius named his colleague Marcus Livius dictator,
                    and Livius named Quintus Caecilius master of the horse. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls elected were announced by Marcus Livius as
                    dictator, namely, Lucius Veturius and Quintus Caecilius, the same being at the
                    time master of the horse. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then the elections
                    of praetors were held. Elected were Gaius Servilius, Marcus Caecilius Metellus,
                    Tiberius Claudius Asellus, Quintus Mamilius Turrinus, who was at the time a
                    plebeian aedile. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The elections being
                    completed, the dictator, abdicating his office and discharging his army, set out
                    in accordance with a decree of the senate for Etruria as <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> his province, to conduct an investigation as to what
                    communities among the Etruscans or Umbrians had discussed plans to revolt from
                    the Romans to Hasdrubal upon his arrival, and which states had aided him with
                    auxiliaries or supplies or any kind of assistance. Such were the events at home
                    and in the field that year. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman Games were repeated three times
                    completely by the curule aediles, Gnaeus Servilius Caepio and Servius Cornelius
                    Lentulus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Likewise the Plebeian Games were
                    completely repeated once by the plebeian aediles, Marcus Pomponius Matho and
                    Quintus Mamilius Turrinus. </p>
                <p> In the thirteenth year of the Punic war, the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> consulship of Lucius
                    Veturius Philo and Quintus Caecilius <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    Metellus, the land of the Bruttii was assigned by decree to them both as their
                    province, to carry on war with Hannibal. The praetors then received their
                    assignments by lot, Marcus Caecilius Metellus the <pb n="p.45"/> city
                    praetorship, Quintus Mamilius the duties of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> praetor peregrinus; Gaius
                    Servilius received Sicily and Tiberius Claudius Sardinia. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The armies were divided as follows: <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> to one of the consuls the army which Gaius Claudius had had
                    as consul in the preceding year, to the other consul that which Quintus Claudius
                    had had as propraetor; and these were of two legions each. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> In Etruria Marcus Livius as proconsul, with his command
                    continued for one year, was to take the two legions of slave-volunteers from
                    Gaius Terentius, the propraetor; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and it was
                    decreed that Quintus Mamilius, handing over his judicial duties to his
                    colleague, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the city praetor. It was a frequent practice
                        during this war to relieve the praetor peregrinus of his judicial duties so
                        that he might take a command; <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> XXV. iii. 2;
                        XXVII. xxxvi. 11; XXX. i. 9; xxvii. 9; xl. 5. </note> should have command of
                    Gaul with the army which Lucius Porcius, the praetor, had commanded; and he was
                    ordered to lay waste the lands of the Gauls who had revolted to the
                    Carthaginians upon the coming of Hasdrubal. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The defence of Sicily was given to Gaius Servilius with the two legions from
                    Cannae, just as Gaius Mamilius had held it. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    From Sardinia the old army which Aulus Hostilius had commanded was withdrawn. A
                    new legion which Tiberius Claudius should take across with him was enrolled by
                    the consuls. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Military authority was continued
                    for the year for Quintus Claudius, to have Tarentum as his assignment, and for
                    Gaius Hostilius Tubulus, who was to have Capua. <milestone n="16" unit="section"
                    /> Marcus Valerius, the proconsul, who had been in charge of the defence of the
                    entire seacoast of Sicily, was ordered to turn over thirty ships to Gaius
                    Servilius, the praetor, and to return to the city with all the rest of his
                    fleet. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the state perturbed by so critical a moment
                    in the war, since men attributed to the gods the causes of everything fortunate
                    and unfortunate, <pb n="p.47"/> many portents were reported: that at Tarracina
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note>
                    temple of Jupiter, at Satricum that of Mater Matuta, had been struck by
                    lightning. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The people of Satricum were no less
                    alarmed by two serpents that glided into the temple of Jupiter, actually through
                    the doorway. From Antium it was reported that ears of grain appeared to the
                    reapers to be blood-stained. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As in
                        XXII. i. 10, also at Antium</note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Caere a pig had been born with two heads
                    and a lamb that was at the same time male and female; and at Alba they said that
                    two suns were seen, and at Fregellae that light had appeared in the night; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Probably an aurora; cf. note on XXIX.
                        xiv. 3.</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and an ox was said to have spoken in the
                    country about Rome, and the altar of Neptune in the Flaminian Circus to have
                    been dripping with sweat; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and the temples of
                    Ceres and Salus and Quirinus to have been struck by lightning. The consuls were
                    bidden to expiate the prodigies with full-grown victims and to have a single day
                    of prayer observed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Both orders were carried
                    out in accordance with the decree of the senate. More terrifying to men than all
                    the prodigies, whether reported from outside or seen in the city, was the
                    extinction of the fire in the Temple of Vesta; and the Vestal who had been on
                    duty that night was scourged by order of Publius Licinius, the pontifex. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> pontifex maximus, elected in <date when="-0212"
                            >212 B.C.</date> ; XXV. v. 2-4. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Although the thing had happened without a
                    portent from the gods but by a mortal's negligence, it was nevertheless decided
                    that it should be expiated by full-grown victims and that a day of prayer at the
                    Temple of Vesta should be observed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Before the consuls should leave for the field
                    they were reminded by the senate that they should take care to restore the
                    common people to their farms. By the favour of the gods the war had been
                    removed, they said, from the city of Rome and from Latium, <pb n="p.49"/> and it
                    was possible to live on the farms without fear; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> it was illogical to give
                    more attention to the cultivation of Sicily than of Italy. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But it was no easy matter for the people, since free
                    farmers had been wiped out by the war, and there was a scarcity of slaves, while
                    cattle had been stolen and farm-houses demolished or burned. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> A large proportion of the rustics, however, were
                    constrained by the authority of the consuls to move back to their farms. The
                    occasion for bringing up the matter had been the complaints of representatives
                    of Placentia and Cremona that their territory was being raided and laid waste by
                    neighbouring Gauls, and that a large part of their colonists had scattered, and
                    that now they had sparsely peopled cities and land desolated and deserted.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Mamilius, the praetor, was ordered to
                    protect the colonies from the enemy. The consuls in accordance with a decree of
                    the senate proclaimed that all citizens of Cremona and Placentia should return
                    to their colonies before a fixed date. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then
                    at the beginning of spring they also set out for the field. </p>
                <p> Quintus Caecilius, the consul, received his army from Gaius Nero; Lucius
                    Veturius took his from Quintus Claudius, the propraetor, and recruited it with
                    fresh soldiers whom he had himself enrolled. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The consuls led their army into the territory of Consentia and ravaged it far
                    and wide. When the column was now laden with booty, they were so harried by
                    Bruttians and Numidian spearmen in a narrow pass that not only the booty but
                    also the troops were in danger. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> However,
                    there was more commotion than battle; and sending the booty in advance the
                    legions without loss made their way out into arable country. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Thence the consuls set out <pb n="p.51"/> for Lucania. That
                    entire nation returned without a <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> struggle to its allegiance to the Roman
                    people. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With Hannibal there was no campaigning that
                    year. For neither did he invite attack, owing to his very recent wound, a blow
                    national as well as personal, nor did the Romans provoke him so long as he
                    remained inactive; such power they believed to be present in that one commander,
                    even though everything else round him crashed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    And I am inclined to think he was more marvellous in adversity than in success.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For here he was, carrying on war in the
                    enemy's land for thirteen years, so far from home with varying fortune, having
                    an army not made up of his own citizens but a mixture of the offscourings of all
                    nations, men who had in common no law, no custom, no language, differing from
                    each other in bearing, in garb, in their arms, differing as to religious rites,
                    sacred observances, one might almost say as to their gods. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Yet he somehow bound them together by a single bond, so
                    that no outbreak ensued among the men themselves nor any mutiny against their
                    general. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This passage is obviously
                        reminiscent of Polybius' tribute to Hannibal in a fragment of Book XI (xix.
                        esp. 3-5). Cf. XXIII. v. 11; XXX. xxxiii. 8; XXIV. iii. 12. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Yet in the enemy's country both money to pay
                    them and supplies were often wanting —deficiencies which in the previous Punic
                    war had given rise to many unspeakable acts on the part of commanders and
                    soldiers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Certainly after the destruction of
                    Hasdrubal's army with its commander-and on them he had rested all his hope of
                    victory —, when by retiring into the remote land of the Bruttii he had given up
                    the rest of Italy, who would not find it a marvel that there was no outbreak in
                    his camp? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For added to everything else was
                    this also, that he had no hope even of feeding his army except from the Bruttian
                    region; and even supposing all of it to be under cultivation, it <pb n="p.53"/>
                    was nevertheless too small to feed so large an army. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Moreover a great part of the young men, drawn
                    off from the farming of the land, had been claimed instead by the war and by
                    their custom of training soldiers through brigandage, a practice viciously
                    inbred in their nation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Furthermore, nothing
                    was being sent from home, since they were concerned about their hold upon Spain,
                    as though everything was succeeding in Italy. </p>
                <p> In Spain the campaign was having an issue in part the same, in part very
                    different: the same in that the Carthaginians, vanquished in battle with the
                    loss of a general, had been forced to the farthest coast of Spain, even to the
                    Ocean; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> on the other hand different in that
                    Spain, owing to the nature of the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> country
                    and its people, was better adapted not merely than Italy but than any other part
                    of the world to preparing for another war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In
                    consequence, though the first of the provinces, at least of those on the
                    mainland, to be entered by the Romans, it has been the last of all to be
                    completely conquered, and not until our own times under the command and auspices
                    of Augustus Caesar. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Since Agrippa's
                        completion of the conquest of northwestern Spain is evidently meant here, we
                        have in this reference to a contemporary event evidence that Book XXVIII was
                        written (or published) after <date when="-0019">19 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There Hasdrubal son of Gisgo, being the
                    greatest and most distinguished general after the Barca family in that war, had
                    at that time returned from Gades in the hope of renewing the war. After
                    conducting levies in Farther Spain with the help of Mago the son of Hamilcar, he
                    armed about fifty thousand infantry and four thousand five hundred cavalry.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As to the cavalry forces there is
                    substantial agreement among the authorities, but some writers state that seventy
                    thousand foot-soldiers were <pb n="p.55"/> brought to the city of Silpia. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the MSS. of Polybius <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">)HLIGGA</foreign> (Elinga, unknown), probably an error
                        for <foreign xml:lang="greek">)ILIPPA,</foreign>
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> Ilipa (accepted by his editors, XI. xx. 1). It
                        lay 10 miles north of Hispalis (Seville), and on the right bank of the
                        Baetis. Cf. XXXV. i. 10; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> III. 11; Strabo
                        III. ii. 3; v. 9. For Livy's habit of substituting place-names familiar to
                        his readers for those used by Polybius cf. Ed. Meyer, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Kleine Schriften</hi> II, 406 ff.; Veith in Kromayer, <hi
                            rend="italics">Antike Schlachtfelder</hi> IV, 518; Scullard, <hi
                            rend="italics">Scipio Africanus in the Second Punic War</hi> 127 f. </note>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There in open plains <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> the two Carthaginian
                    generals established themselves, resolved not to refuse a battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, when the news reached him that they
                    had got together so large an army, thought that with Roman legions alone he
                    would be no match for such a multitude unless barbarian auxiliaries should
                    confront them, at least for appearance' sake. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Yet he felt that these must not compose so large a part of his forces that by
                    changing sides —which had been the cause of disaster to his father and uncle
                    —they might decide the outcome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly he
                    sent Silanus in advance to Culchas, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Kolichas in Polybius <hi rend="italics">l.c. §§</hi> 3, 5. </note> who ruled
                    over twenty-eight towns, in order to receive from him the cavalry and infantry
                    which he had promised to enlist during the winter. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then Scipio himself set out from Tarraco, and gathering up
                    as he went a moderate number of auxiliaries from the allies dwelling near the
                    road, he arrived at Castulo. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On a
                        tributary of the upper Baetis, giving its name to the Saltus Castulonensis
                        (Sierra Morena). The main road to Corduba and Gades passed through the city;
                        Strabo III, iv. 9. <hi rend="italics">fin.</hi> Cf. xix. 2, 4; xx. 8; XXIV.
                        xli. 7. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thither Silanus brought auxiliaries, three
                    thousand infantry and five hundred cavalry. From there Scipio advanced to the
                    city of Baecula <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. Vol. VII. p. 283
                        n. It was west of Castulo but on the same road. The site cannot be certainly
                        determined, although it has been identified with Bailén. Cf. Polybius XI.
                        xx. 5; Veith in Kromayer <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> IV. 503 if.;
                        Scullard <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> 300 ff. </note> with the entire
                    army, forty-five thousand legionaries and allies, infantry and cavalry.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As they were pitching camp Mago and
                    Masinissa with all their <pb n="p.57"/> cavalry attacked them <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The reader would naturally assume that
                        this attack and the important battle which follows took place very near
                        Baecula. But at xii. 14 the Carthaginian generals were encamped near Silpia
                        (Ilipa), <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> less than 60 miles from the Atlantic
                        at the nearest point, while Baecula is 130 miles farther in a straight line.
                        In Polybius it is Scipio who does the marching (XI. xx. 9). No long march of
                        the Carthaginians to meet him is mentioned, and near Baecula there is no
                        open plain suited to this battle. Hence this was near modern Seville and not
                        a <quote>second battle of Baecula,</quote> as Mommsen, Ihne and others have
                        it. </note> and would have thrown the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> men working on the
                    fortifications into confusion, had not cavalry concealed by Scipio behind a hill
                    favourably situated for the purpose unexpectedly charged them in their disorder.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These horsemen at the very beginning of
                    the battle put to flight the most active and those who had been the first to
                    ride up close to the earthwork and even among the men at work. With the rest,
                    who had advanced under their standards and in marching order, the battle was
                    more protracted and for a long time indecisive. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> But when light cohorts at first drawn off from the outposts, and then
                    soldiers withdrawn from work on the fortifications and ordered to take up arms,
                    came up in increasing number, and fresh to assist the weary, while by this time
                    a long column of men under arms was dashing out from camp into battle,
                    Carthaginians and Numidians thereupon faced about in unmistakable retreat.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And at first they were retiring by troops,
                    while their ranks were not at all broken on account of fear or haste. Then when
                    the Roman fell more fiercely upon their rear and the attack could not be
                    withstood, no longer mindful of their ranks, they scattered in flight hither and
                    thither, each taking the shortest way. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And
                    although the spirit of the Romans was notably higher in consequence of that
                    battle and that of the enemy notably lowered, still for some days following
                    there was never any respite from sudden attacks by cavalry and light-armed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When his forces had been sufficiently tested
                    by these skirmishes, Hasdrubal was the first to lead <pb n="p.59"/> his troops
                    out into battle-line; then the Roman also <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> went forward. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> But each of the two lines stood drawn up in front of
                    its earthwork, and when neither side had begun the battle and the day was now
                    nearing sunset, the troops were led back into camp, first by the Carthaginian
                    and then by the Roman. The same thing happened for a number of days. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Always the first to lead his troops out of camp, the
                    first to sound the recall for his men weary of standing still, would be the
                    Carthaginian. From neither side was there a charge, or a missile hurled, or any
                    raising of a shout. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The centre was held on one
                    side by the Romans, on the other by the Carthaginians combined with Africans,
                    the wings by their allies, and for both armies these were Spanish troops.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In front of the wings, in advance of the
                    Punic line of battle, the elephants presented from a distance the appearance of
                    forts. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Some of the elephants carried
                        on their backs a crenellated tower from which javelins were hurled by four
                        or more soldiers posted on the tower; hence the resemblance to forts;
                        XXXVII. xl. 4; cf. Curtius VIII. xii. 7; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi>
                        VIII. 22 and 27; Lucretius V. 1302. Such <hi rend="italics">elephant
                            turriti</hi> are represented in terracotta figures and on painted ware. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Already it was common talk in both camps that
                    they were to fight in the formation in which they had stood; that the centres,
                    the Roman and Carthaginian troops, between whom lay the cause of the war, would
                    clash, evenly matched in spirit and in arms. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    When Scipio observed that this was a persistent belief, he deliberately changed
                    everything for the day on which he was to give battle. At evening he passed a
                    written order through the camp that before daybreak the horses should be cared
                    for and the men have breakfast, that the horsemen <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> under arms should keep their mounts bridled and saddled.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not quite literal for this
                        period. Primarily the word has to do with a cloth kept in place by a girth
                        and straps. Evolution of cloth into saddle was slow. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was not yet quite daylight when he sent all
                    his <pb n="p.61"/> cavalry with the light-armed against the Punic <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> outposts.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For this battle of Ilipa see the
                        works already cited: Scullard, 126 ff. with plan; Veith, 517 ff. with map. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Immediately afterwards he himself with the
                    heavy column of the legions went forward, and contrary to the fixed idea of his
                    own men and of the enemy, he formed strong wings of his Roman soldiers, while
                    the allies were taken into the centre. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When
                    Hasdrubal, who was aroused by the shouts of the horsemen, sprang out of his tent
                    and saw the uproar outside his earthwork and the excitement among his men, and
                    in the distance the gleaming <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> standards of
                    the legions and the plain filled with the enemy, he forthwith sent out all his
                    cavalry against the horsemen. As for himself, he marched out of the camp with
                    the infantry column, and in drawing up his line made no change from the
                    customary order. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The cavalry engagement had
                    long been uncertain, and by itself it could not be decisive because when
                    repulsed —and this repeatedly happened almost by turns —they could safely retire
                    into the infantry line. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But when the lines of
                    battle were not more than half a mile apart, Scipio sounding the recall and
                    opening his ranks admitted all the cavalry and the light-armed into the centre;
                    and dividing them into two sections he posted them as a reserve behind the
                    wings. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then, when it was now time to begin
                    the battle, he ordered the Spaniards —they formed the centre of the line-to
                    advance at a slow pace. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> From the right wing
                    —for he was himself in command there —he sent a message to Silanus and Marcius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. Vol. VII. pp. 5 <hi
                            rend="italics">fin.,</hi> 65 (and notes), 77. Repeatedly mentioned in
                        this Book. </note> that they should prolong their wing towards the left,
                    just as they <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> had seen him pressing to the
                    right, and with the light infantry and cavalry should engage the enemy <pb
                        n="p.63"/> before the centres could come together. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Here Polybius XI. xxiii has a detailed account of
                        complicated movements executed by the Roman wings in order to outflank the
                        weaker Carthaginian wings before fighting could reach the centre of the
                        lines. Cf. Scullard <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> 132 ff.; Veith, 522 ff. </note>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Thus <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> extending the wings, with
                    three cohorts <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It has been held that
                        Livy here mistranslated Polybius, who meant maniples. Everything depends
                        upon the interpretation of <foreign xml:lang="greek">trei=s
                            spei/ras</foreign> and a following parenthesis, <quote> this infantry
                            unit is called a cohort ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">koo/rtis</foreign>
                            )by the Romans </quote> (XI. xxiii. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        1). It remains debatable whether <quote>this unit</quote> refers to the
                        single <foreign xml:lang="greek">spei/ra,</foreign> which must then be a
                        maniple, or to the three combined to make a cohort. For <hi rend="italics"
                            >manipulus</hi> the regular word was <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >shmei/a</foreign> Later on <foreign xml:lang="greek">spei/ra</foreign>
                        came to be cohort almost invariably. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> But
                        in Polybius' time one could use either <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >shmei/a</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="greek">spei/ra</foreign> in the
                        same meaning, as VI. xxiv. 5; so even in the same sentence, as <hi
                            rend="italics">l. c.</hi> § 8; III. cxiii. 3; <milestone n="15"
                            unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ix. 7. In this battle the larger number,
                        1800 men, seems absolutely required. Cf. Veith <hi rend="italics">l.
                            c.;</hi> F. G. Moore, <hi rend="italics">Classical</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">Weekly,</hi> XXXVII. 238f. </note> of infantry and three
                    troops of cavalry on each wing, and with skirmishers in addition, they led at a
                    rapid pace against the enemy, while the rest followed them obliquely. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> In the centre was a curve where the Spanish units
                    were more slowly advancing. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By this time the wings were already engaged,
                    while the main strength of the enemy's line, the veteran Carthaginians and
                    Africans, had not yet come within range, and did not dare to dash towards the
                    wings to help the combatants, for fear of exposing the centre to the enemy
                    directly advancing. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The wings were being hard
                    pressed by a double attack; cavalry and light-armed and skirmishers with
                    enclosing wings were charging into their flanks, while the cohorts were pressing
                    them in front, endeavouring to cut off the wings from the rest of the
                    battle-line. XV. And not only was the battle in general far from being evenly
                    matched, but especially because the horde of Baliares and Spanish recruits had
                    been made to face Roman and Latin soldiers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, as the day now wore on their strength also began to fail Hasdrubal's
                    soldiers, who had been surprised by an early morning onslaught and compelled to
                    go out into line in haste before they <pb n="p.65"/> could take food to sustain
                    them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And Scipio had <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> deliberately dragged out
                    the day, in order that the battle might be belated. For it was not until the
                    seventh hour that the infantry units <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> those of xiv. 17, three cohorts on each wing
                        (Veith), or one cohort as the passage has been commonly understood. </note>
                    charged the wings. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The battle reached the
                    centre of the lines considerably later, so that the heat of the midday sun and
                    the strain of standing under arms, and at the same time hunger and thirst,
                    weakened their bodies before they engaged the enemy. Accordingly they stood
                    resting on their shields. By this time, in addition to everything else, the
                    elephants also took fright at the skirmishing tactics of cavalry and skirmishers
                    and light-armed and had shifted from the wings into the centre. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Weakened therefore in body <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> and spirit the men retreated, keeping their ranks
                    nevertheless, just as if by order of the general the line was giving way intact. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But when the victors, on seeing that the tide
                    of battle had turned, for that reason charged with more spirit from all sides,
                    and it was not easy to withstand their attack, although Hasdrubal tried to hold
                    his men back and confronted them as they gave way, shouting to them again and
                    again that in the rear there were hills and a safe refuge if they retired
                    slowly. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, as fear overcame their
                    respect for him and those nearest to the enemy were falling, at once they faced
                    about and all took to flight. And at first the standard-bearers began to halt at
                    the foot of the hills and to call the soldiers back into their ranks, while the
                    Romans hesitated to advance their line up the hill. Then when the enemy saw the
                    standards coming bravely on, they resumed their flight and were <pb n="p.67"/>
                    driven panic-stricken into camp. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Not far from
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note>
                    earthwork were the Romans; and by such momentum they would have captured the
                    camp if, after a blazing sun, such as shines out in the midst of clouds heavy
                    with rain, there had not been so extraordinary a downpour that the victors with
                    difficulty retired to their camp, and had not some been beset by scruples also
                    against any further attempt that day. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginians, although night and pouring rain invited them to needed rest,
                    being weak from exertion and wounds, nevertheless, because fear and danger gave
                    them no time to be idle when the enemy would attack the camp at daybreak,
                        <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> raised their earthwork by gathering
                    stones from near-by valleys all round, intending to defend themselves by a
                    fortification, since in their arms they would have no sufficient protection. But
                    the desertion of their allies made flight seem safer than delay. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Defection began with Attenes, prince of the
                    Turdetani, who deserted with a large force of his tribesmen. Then two fortified
                    towns were handed over with their garrisons to the Roman by their commanders.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> And for fear the mischief might spread
                    farther, now that men were once disposed to change sides, Hasdrubal moved his
                    camp in the silence of the following night. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, when men on outpost duty reported at
                    daylight that the enemy had left, sent his cavalry ahead and ordered the
                    standards to advance. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The column also marched
                    at such a pace that, if they had directly followed the enemy's track, they would
                    undoubtedly have overtaken them. They believed the guides that there was another
                    shorter road to the river Baetis, by which they might attack the enemy while
                    crossing over. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, finding the passage
                        <pb n="p.69"/> of the river closed, turned aside towards the Ocean, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Hasdrubal had intended to cross the
                        Baetis and then retreat to Gades (total distance about 75 miles to the
                        harbour of that city). But now he is obliged to remain on the right bank,
                        thus increasing the distance considerably. </note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> and
                    henceforward, scattering like fugitives, away they went. Thus he put a
                    considerable distance between himself and the Roman <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> legions. Cavalry and light-armed, dashing upon them now
                    from the rear, now on the flanks, kept wearing them out and delaying <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> them. But when in view of the numerous clashes the
                    standards came to a halt and the men were engaged now with cavalry, now with
                    skirmishers and auxiliary infantry, the legions came <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> up. Thereafter it was no longer a battle but a slaughter as
                    of cattle, until the general, himself now approving their flight, escaped to the
                    nearest hills with some six thousand half-armed men. The rest were slain or
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> captured. The Carthaginians hastily
                    fortified an improvised camp on a very high hill and from it they defended
                    themselves without difficulty, since the enemy had tried in vain to come up the
                    steep <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> slope. But in an exposed situation which
                    furnished nothing a siege was scarcely endurable even for a few days.
                    Accordingly there were repeated desertions to the enemy. Finally the general
                    himself sent for ships <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">From Gades; cf.
                        § 13.</note> — the sea was not far away —and leaving his army by night he
                    escaped to <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Gades. Scipio, learning of the
                    flight of the enemy's general, left Silanus ten thousand infantry and a thousand
                    cavalry to besiege the <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> camp. With the rest of
                    the forces he himself returned to Tarraco in seventy days' marches, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The slow progress is explained by what
                        immediately follows. </note> hearing the cases of chiefs and states as he
                    proceeded, in order to bestow rewards according to the real worth of their
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> services. After his departure <pb
                        n="p.71"/> Masinissa conferred secretly with Silanus, then crossed <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> over to
                    Africa with a few of his countrymen, in order that in changing his policy he
                    might count upon the obedience of his nation <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    also. The reason for his sudden change was not so clear then as was later the
                    evidence furnished by a loyalty unswerving down to extreme age, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He lived on until <date when="-0148"
                            >148 B.C.</date> , upwards of 90 years old, and reigned 60 years; App.
                            <hi rend="italics">Pun.</hi> 106; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi>
                        VII. 156. </note> that even at that time he had not acted without a
                    reasonable <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> ground. Mago then reached Gades on
                    the ships sent back by Hasdrubal. The rest, abandoned by their generals, were
                    scattered, some by desertion, others by flight, among the neighbouring states;
                    no force remained which was notable for its numbers or its strength. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So much in general for the manner in which
                    under the command and auspices of Publius Scipio the Carthaginians were driven
                    out of Spain in the fourteenth year <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        An error corrected by x. 8 and xxxviii. 12, the 14th year of the war being
                            <date when="-0205">205 B.C.</date>
                    </note> from the beginning of the war, the fifth <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy had assigned Scipio's arrival in Spain to the year
                            <date when="-0211">211 B.C.</date> ; XXVI. xix, 11 ff. Consequently he
                        placed the capture of New Carthage in <date when="-0210">210 B.C.</date> See
                        Vol. VII. notes on pp. 68, 230, 296; Scullard, 304 ff. </note> after Publius
                    Scipio received his province and <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> army. Not
                    much later Silanus returned to Scipio at Tarraco, reporting the war at an end.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Although his readers would here
                        infer that a campaign has now been completed, the historian goes on to
                        include a seemingly impossible range of operations within what remained of
                        the same year, <date when="-0206">206 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Scipio with many noble captives was
                    sent to Rome to announce the conquest of Spain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> And while everyone else was publishing the fact abroad with great rejoicing
                    and high praise, the one man who had accomplished it was insatiable in his
                    craving for merit and well-earned distinction. He considered the conquest of
                    Spain insignificant compared with all that he had imagined in his high-minded
                    hopes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Already his eye was upon Africa and the
                    greater Carthage and the glory of such a war, as if <pb n="p.73"/> accumulated
                    to bring him honour and a name. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly, thinking that he must already
                    make preparations and gain the goodwill of kings and tribes, he decided first to
                    sound King Syphax. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He was the king of the
                    Masaesulians. A tribe bordering on the Mauri, the Masaesulians directly face the
                    region of Spain in which lies New Carthage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At
                    that time the king had a treaty with the Carthaginians; and Scipio, thinking it
                    would have for Syphax no more weight and sanctity than is usual for barbarians,
                    with whom loyalty depends upon success, sent Gaius Laelius as an envoy to him
                    with gifts. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Delighted with these, and since at
                    that time the situation <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> was everywhere
                    favourable for the Romans but for the Carthaginians unfavourable in Italy and
                    now quite hopeless in Spain, the barbarian indicated that he would accept the
                    friendship of the Romans; that for its confirmation he would neither give nor
                    receive a pledge except in the actual presence of the Roman commander.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So Laelius, having received from the king
                    a promise to this effect only, that for the visit safety would be assured,
                    returned to Scipio. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A factor of great importance in every respect
                    for a man planning an attack upon Africa was Syphax, the richest king in that
                    land and one who had already gained experience even of the Carthaginians in war,
                    while boundaries of his kingdom were also well situated with reference to Spain
                    in being separated from it by a narrow strait only. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Consequently Scipio thought the matter deserved to be
                    pursued even at a great risk, since it was otherwise impossible. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Leaving Lucius Marcius at Tarraco and Marcus Silanus
                    at New Carthage —to which he had come by land in long stages from Tarraco —that
                    they might defend Spain, <pb n="p.75"/> he himself sailed with Gaius Laelius and
                    two quinqueremes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        206</note> from (New) Carthage. Using oars for the most part over a calm
                    sea, while at times a gentle wind lent its help, he crossed over to Africa.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably to Siga, in Mauretania,
                        where Syphax at times resided; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> V. 19;
                        Strabo XVII; iii. 9; App. <hi rend="italics">Hisp.</hi> 29 f. </note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It so chanced that at the very same time
                    Hasdrubal, who had been forced out of Spain and had sailed into the harbour with
                    seven triremes and cast anchor, was bringing his ships to the shore when the two
                    quinqueremes were sighted. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> No one had any
                    doubt that they belonged to the enemy, and that they could be surprised by
                    superior numbers before they entered the harbour. But they caused nothing more
                    than uproar and excitement both among soldiers and sailors, as they made ready
                    their arms and ships all to no purpose. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For
                    the sails, catching a slightly stronger wind from the open sea, brought the
                    quinqueremes into the harbour before the Carthaginians could weigh anchor.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Nor did anyone dare to make further
                    disturbance in the king's harbour. So first Hasdrubal and then Scipio and
                    Laelius disembarked and went to the king. <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To Syphax it seemed a splendid thing —as
                    indeed it was —that the generals of the two richest peoples of that time had
                    come on the same day to ask for peace and friendship from him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He invited both of them to be his guests, and
                    inasmuch as chance had ordained that they should be under one roof and in the
                    same dwelling, he tried to draw them into a conference to put an end to their
                    quarrels. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio indeed stated that neither as
                    a private citizen had he any hatred toward <pb n="p.77"/> the Carthaginian which
                    might be ended by a conference, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> nor as regarded the state could he treat with
                    an enemy without an order from the senate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    When the king kept insisting that he consent to come to the same feast for fear
                    one of his guests should seem to have been excluded from his table, Scipio did
                    not decline, and they dined together in the king's house. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On the same couch even, since the king would have it so,
                    Scipio and Hasdrubal reclined. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Moreover, such
                    was the genial manner of Scipio, such his inborn cleverness in meeting every
                    situation, that by his eloquent mode of address he won not Syphax only, the
                    barbarian unacquainted with Roman ways, but his own bitterest enemy as well.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal plainly showed that when he met
                    him face to face, Scipio seemed even more marvellous than in his achievements in
                    war, and that he did not doubt Syphax and his kingdom would soon be in the power
                    of the Romans; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> such skill did the man possess
                    in winning men over. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A single
                        sentence remains from Polybius' account of this meeting of the three and
                        their conversation (XI. xxiva. 4), here reflected by Livy. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And so, he said, it was not so essential for
                    the Carthaginians to inquire how their Spanish provinces had been lost as to
                    consider how they were still to hold Africa. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It was not as a traveller, nor as one who idles along beautiful shores, that so
                    great a Roman general had left a newly subdued province, had left his armies,
                    and with only two ships had crossed over to Africa and entrusted himself to an
                    enemy's land, to a king's power, to a man's untested honour; on the contrary he
                    was cherishing a hope of conquering Africa. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    It had long <pb n="p.79"/> been Scipio's constant reflection, his open
                    complaint, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        206</note> he added, that he was not waging war in Africa, as Hannibal was
                    in Italy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scipio, after making a treaty with
                    Syphax, set sail from Africa, and tossed in open sea by unsteady winds, mostly
                    violent, he reached the harbour of New Carthage on the fourth day. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although the Spanish provinces were having a
                    respite from a Carthaginian war, still it was evident that on account of a
                    guilty conscience certain states were quiet out of fear rather than because of
                    loyalty. Most conspicuous both for size and guilt among these were Iliturgi
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The last previous mention of a
                        town of this name was XXVI. xvii. 4. That was about 175 miles in a straight
                        line from New Carthage, and in a quite unthinkable direction for retreating
                        Romans. Amtorgis, where the two brothers separated, cannot be identified
                        (XXV. xxxii. 5, 9). Iliturgi has taken the place here of a town less well
                        known, perhaps that of Pliny's Ilorci (the <hi rend="italics">rogus
                            Scipionis,</hi> i.e. of Gnaeus, <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> III. 9;
                        Ilurgia in App. <hi rend="italics">Hisp.</hi> 32, Ilourgeia in Polybius, XI.
                        xxiv. <hi rend="italics">sub.fin.,</hi> a fragment which seems to belong
                        here, Dindorf). This may be modern Lorca, on a tributary of the Tader, about
                        40 miles west of Cartagena; so Ed. Meyer, <hi rend="italics">Kl. Schr.</hi>
                        II. 445 f. and Schulten in <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi> LXIII. 288 ff. Or
                        possibly Lorqui on the Tader, 35 miles north-west of Cartagena; so Scullard,
                        143. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">Cambridge Ancient History</hi> VIII. 90. </note> and
                    Castulo. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. xiii. 4; XXIV. xli. 7.
                        Here App. <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi> has Castax, unknown and an improbable
                        form, but accepted by Scullard, 144 and Hallward in C.A.H. <hi
                            rend="italics">l.c.</hi> Any argument for rejecting Castulo is less
                        cogent than in the case of Iliturgi. We may have our doubts, however, about
                        an advance so far to the west unsupported except by the annalistic
                        tradition. Cf. Kahrstedt in Meltzer, <hi rend="italics">Geschichte der
                            Karthager</hi> III. 495 if. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Although in favourable times its citizens had
                    been allies, Castulo, after the Scipios had been slain with their armies, had
                    revolted to the Carthaginians. The men of Iliturgi, by betraying and slaying
                    those who from that disaster had fled to them for refuge, had added a crime also
                    to their revolt. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On Scipio's first coming,
                    when the Spanish provinces were wavering, vengeance upon those states would have
                    been deserved but not politic. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now, however,
                    since in a time of peace the moment for exacting the penalty seemed to have
                    arrived, he summoned Lucius Marcius from Tarraco and sent him with a third of
                    his forces to lay siege to Castulo. He himself with the rest of the army reached
                    Iliturgi in about five stages. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The gates had
                    been closed and <pb n="p.81"/> everything disposed and prepared to resist an
                    attack. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note>
                    So true was it that consciousness of what they knew they had deserved had meant
                    as much for them as a declaration of war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With
                    this point also Scipio opened his speech of encouragement to his soldiers,
                    saying that the Spaniards by closing their gates had themselves shown what they
                    had deserved to fear. Consequently, he said, they must wage war against them
                    with much more animosity than against the Carthaginians. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> With these it was a contest almost devoid of anger in
                    pursuit of power and glory; from the Iliturgians they must exact the penalty for
                    treachery and cruelty and crime. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The time had
                    come for them to avenge the atrocious slaughter of their comrades and the
                    perfidy which would have been brought to bear against themselves if in flight
                    they had reached the same city. It was time also for them by a severe example to
                    ordain that no one should ever account a Roman citizen or soldier in any
                    misfortune as fair game for ill treatment. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Immediately after this exhortation from their
                    general the officers, thoroughly aroused, issued ladders to men picked out of
                    one maniple after another, and dividing the army so that Laelius as lieutenant
                    should command one half, they attacked the city in two places at the same time,
                    causing a double alarm. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was not a single
                    commander or a number of leading men that urged the citizens gallantly to defend
                    the city, but their own fear due to consciousness of guilt. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They remembered and reminded one another also that the aim
                    was their punishment, not victory; that when every man perished what mattered
                    most was whether he did so in battle and in the line, where the fortune of the
                    fray, <pb n="p.83"/> making no distinctions, often lifted up the defeated <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> and dashed
                    down the victor, or whether later, when their city was in <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> ashes and ruins, there before the faces of their captured
                    wives and children, after enduring every outrage and indignity, they breathed
                    their last under the scourge and in chains. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly not merely those of military age or men alone, but women and
                    children also helped beyond their powers of mind and body, bringing up weapons
                    for the fighting men and carrying stones for the builders up to the wall.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The stake was not freedom only, which
                    whets the courage of brave men alone, but all had before their eyes extreme
                    penalties and a hideous death. Bravery was kindled by emulation in toil and
                    danger and by the mere sight of one another. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    And so the battle was begun with such heat that that famous army, the conqueror
                    of all Spain, was repeatedly beaten back from the walls by the young men of a
                    single town and thrown into disorder in an inglorious battle. When Scipio saw
                    this, he was afraid that, owing to so many vain attempts made by his men, the
                    enemy's spirits might be cheered and his own soldiers lose heart. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> Thinking that he must himself make the attempt and
                    claim a share in the danger, he berated the soldiers for their cowardice,
                    ordered ladders to be brought up, and threatened that if the rest hesitated he
                    would climb up himself. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Already at no small
                    risk <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> App. <hi rend="italics"
                            >Hisp.</hi> 32 has him wounded; Zonaras IX. x. 2. </note> he had come
                    close to the walls when from all sides an outcry was made by the soldiers, who
                    were concerned for their commander and began to set up ladders in many places at
                    the same time; and on the other side Laelius pressed the attack. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> Then the resistance of <pb n="p.85"/> the townsmen
                    was broken and, once the defenders <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> had been dislodged, the walls were occupied. </p>
                <p> The citadel also in the midst of the confusion was captured from the side on
                    which it appeared to be impregnable. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> African deserters, who were at that time in
                    the Roman auxiliaries, just when the townsmen had turned to the defence of
                    places where the danger was evident, while at the same time the Romans kept
                    coming up <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> ... by any possible approach,
                    caught sight of a very lofty part of the city lacking any kind of
                    fortifications, lacking defenders as well, because it was protected by a very
                    high cliff. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Men of light build and nimble,
                    thanks to much training, they carried iron spikes with them and climbed up
                    wherever they could over the irregular projections of the cliff. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Wherever they encountered rock too steep and smooth,
                    by driving in spikes at suitable intervals they made something like steps.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then while the first men with their hands
                    drew up those who followed and the last pushed up those ahead of them, they made
                    their way up to the summit. Thence they dashed down with a shout into the city
                    already captured by the Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was then in
                    truth evident that the city had been attacked out of anger and hatred. No one
                    thought of taking men alive, no one thought of booty, although every place was
                    open for plunder. They slaughtered the unarmed and the armed alike, women as
                    well as men; cruel anger went even so far as to slay infants. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Then they threw firebrands into houses and demolished what
                    could not be consumed by the flames. So delighted were they to destroy even the
                        <pb n="p.87"/> traces of the city and to blot out the memory of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> their
                    enemies' abode. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio then led his army to Castulo, a city
                    defended not only by Spaniards from other places but also by remnants of the
                    Carthaginian army after a scattering flight in every direction. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But Scipio's coming had been preceded by a report of the
                    disaster at Iliturgi, and in consequence alarm and despair had taken possession.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Also as their interests were different,
                    since everyone wished to be safeguarded himself without regard to any one else,
                    at first unexpressed suspicion, then open discord produced a separation between
                    Carthaginians and Spaniards. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The latter were
                    commanded by Cerdubelus, an open advocate of surrender, the Punic auxiliaries by
                    Himilco. After receiving a secret promise Cerdubelus betrayed garrison and city
                    to the Roman commander. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> More merciful was
                    this victory. Not so serious a crime had been committed and voluntary surrender
                    had greatly appeased their anger. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcius was thereupon sent to bring under
                    Roman sway and authority any barbarians who had not yet been thoroughly subdued.
                    Scipio returned to (New) Carthage to pay his vows to the gods and to conduct the
                    gladiatorial show which he had prepared in honour of his deceased father and
                    uncle. The exhibition of gladiators was not made up from the class of men which
                    managers are in the habit of pitting against each other, that is, slaves sold on
                    the platform and free men who are ready to sell their lives. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> In every case the service of the men who fought was
                    voluntary and without compensation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For some
                    were sent by their chieftains to display an example of the courage inbred in
                    their tribe; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> some declared on their <pb
                        n="p.89"/> own motion that they would fight to please the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> general;
                    in other cases rivalry and the desire to compete led them to challenge or, if
                    challenged, not to refuse. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some who had been
                    unable or unwilling to end their differences by a legal hearing, after agreeing
                    that the disputed property should fall to the victor, settled the matter with
                    the sword. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Men also of no obscure family but
                    conspicuous and distinguished, Corbis and Orsua, being cousins and competing for
                    the post of chief of a city called Ibes, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Only here, site unknown, unless it be Ibi, 12 miles
                        northnorth-west of Alicante (Castrum Album, XXIV. xli. 3). </note> declared
                    that they would contend with the sword. Corbis was the older in years.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Orsua's father had lately been chief,
                    having succeeded to an elder brother's rank upon his death. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When Scipio desired to settle the question by a hearing and
                    to calm their anger, they both said they had refused that request to their
                    common relatives, and that they were to have as their judge no other god or man
                    than Mars. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The older man was confident in his
                    strength, the younger in the bloom of his youth, each preferring death in the
                    combat rather than to be subject to the rule of the other. Since they could not
                    be made to give up such madness, they furnished the army a remarkable spectacle,
                    demonstrating how great an evil among mortals is the ambition to rule.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The older man by his skill with arms and
                    by his cunning easily mastered the brute strength of the younger. In addition to
                    this gladiatorial show there were funeral games so far as the resources of the
                    province and camp equipment permitted. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meantime operations were carried on no less
                    actively by the lieutenants. Marcius after crossing the river Baetis, which the
                    inhabitants call Certis, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Another local
                        name was Perces; Steph. Byz. 156. 9.</note> accepted the surrender of two
                    rich cities without an <pb n="p.91"/> engagement. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> There was the city of Astapa, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Ostippo in Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> III. 12
                        and inscriptions; now Estepa, 70 miles east-south-east of Seville. App. <hi
                            rend="italics">Hisp.</hi> 33 retells the tale. </note> always <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> on the
                    side of the Carthaginians; and this did not so much justify anger as that they
                    bore a particular hatred against the Romans over and above the exigencies of
                    war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor did they have a city secure either by
                    reason of its situation or fortifications to make them over-confident. But their
                    natural delight in brigandage had impelled the inhabitants to make raids into
                    adjoining territory of allies of the Roman people and to capture stray Roman
                    soldiers and sutlers and merchants. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Even a
                    caravan —large because there had been too little safety for small numbers
                    —crossing their territory had been entrapped in an unfavourable spot by an
                    ambuscade and cut to pieces. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the army had
                    been brought up to lay siege to this city, the men of the town, prompted by a
                    guilty conscience, because neither surrender to an enemy so incensed seemed safe
                    nor was there any hope of defending their lives by walls and arms, resolved to
                    carry out against themselves and their families a brutal and barbarous act.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXI. xiv, the similar conduct
                        of the Saguntines, and XXXI. xvii, Abydus; cf. Polybius XVI. xxxi. ff. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A spot in the marketplace was selected where
                    they were to bring together their most valuable possessions. Having ordered
                    their wives and children to sit down upon that heap they piled up wood all
                    around and threw on bundles of brush. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They
                    then instructed fifty armed young men to keep guard at that place, so long as
                    the issue of the battle was uncertain, over their treasures and over persons
                    that were dearer than treasures. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If they
                    should see that the battle had gone against them and the city was on the point
                    of being captured, they were to know that all those whom they now saw <pb
                        n="p.93"/> marching out to battle would meet death where they <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> were
                    fighting. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They implored them, they said, by
                    the gods above and below to remember the freedom which must be brought to an end
                    that day either by an honourable death or an infamous slavery, and leave nothing
                    upon which an angry enemy might vent his fury. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Sword and firebrand were in their hands; let friendly and loyal hands destroy
                    all that was doomed to perish, rather than have the enemy offer indignities with
                    insolent mockery. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To these exhortations they
                    added a dreadful curse, in case hope or weakness of character should turn any
                    one from their purpose. </p>
                <p> Then at the double they burst out of wide-open gates with a great uproar.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And no outpost in sufficient strength had
                    been stationed to face them, since nothing less could be feared than that the
                    besieged should venture to sally out from the walls. A very few troops of
                    cavalry and such light-armed infantry as were suddenly sent out of the camp for
                    that very purpose encountered them. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    battle was fierce in courageous onslaught rather than regular in any formation.
                    Accordingly the horsemen who had been the first to confront the enemy were
                    beaten back and brought panic to the light-armed. The fighting would also have
                    been directly outside the earthwork had not the heavy legionary infantry drawn
                    up their line of battle in spite of the very short time given them to form.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Even there for a short time there was
                    some alarm in the front line, while men blinded by frenzy dashed on to meet
                    wounds and steel with mad recklessness. Then the veteran soldiers, steadfast
                    against rash attacks, by slaying the first men checked those who followed.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.95"/> A little later, venturing to take the offensive, when <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> they saw
                    no one giving way and every man resolutely dying in his tracks, they extended
                    their line, as superior numbers of armed men made it possible for them to do,
                    outflanked the enemy, and as they fought in circular formation slew them to the
                    last man. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such slaughter, however, arose from the attack
                    of a furious enemy, fighting at that moment according to the law of war against
                    armed men resisting. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> More horrible was another
                    butchery within the city, when their own citizens were slaying an unarmed,
                    unresisting throng of women and children and throwing bodies, very often only
                    half-dead, upon a pyre they had lighted, and streams of blood were putting out
                    the rising flames. Finally the men, exhausted by the pitiful slaying of their
                    own kin, threw themselves and their arms into the midst of the fire. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The slaughter was already finished when the
                    victorious Romans arrived. And at the first sight of so terrible a scene they
                    stood for a little while stunned with amazement. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Then, when gold and silver glistened in the heap of other objects and with
                    the eagerness which is natural to man they were trying to snatch them from the
                    flames, some caught fire themselves, others were scorched by the hot blast,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Here Polybius' narrative survives
                        in a single sentence about frantic efforts to recover gold and silver, XI.
                        xxiv. 11. </note> since those in front had no way of escape, while the mass
                    of men pressed upon them from the rear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thus
                    was Astapa destroyed by sword and fire without booty for the soldiers. Marcius,
                    having received the <pb n="p.97"/> surrender of all the other tribes of that
                    region owing <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        206</note> to their fear, led his victorious army back to Scipio at (New)
                    Carthage. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About the same time came deserters from Gades
                    promising to betray the city and the Punic garrison in that city and the
                    commander of the garrison together with the fleet. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Mago after his flight had halted there, and having
                    assembled ships on the Ocean, he had gathered up a considerable force of
                    auxiliaries both from the African coast across the strait and from the nearest
                    places in Spain with the help of Hanno, the prefect. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Promises were received from the deserters and given them,
                    and Marcius with cohorts lightly equipped and Laelius also with seven triremes
                    and one quinquereme were sent thither, to carry on the campaign by land and sea
                    with a single plan. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio himself fell ill with an alarming
                    malady, but still more alarming as reported, since everyone added something to
                    what he had heard, with the inbred human passion for purposely magnifying
                    rumours. His illness agitated the whole province and especially the distant
                    parts of it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And how serious a situation would
                    have been created if the fatality had been real was evident, since an empty
                    report had stirred up such tempests. Allies did not remain loyal, nor the army
                    mindful of duty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Mandonius and Indibilis,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. Vol. VII. pp. 279, n. 4; 282,
                        n. 1; below, xxv. 11; XXIX. i. 19 and iii. 1 ff. </note> because they had
                    reckoned upon a kingdom of Spain for themselves when the Carthaginians should be
                    expelled from it, and yet nothing to match their hopes had come to them, stirred
                    up their countrymen —and <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> they were Lacetani
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably an error for Laeetani;
                        in the north-east corner of Spain around Barcĭno (Barcelona); xxxiv. 4; XXI.
                        xxiii. 2; XXXIV. xx. 2. </note> —called <pb n="p.99"/> out the young men of
                    the Celtiberians and ravaged <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> the territory of the Suessetani and Sedetani,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Also north of the Ebro and near
                        the coast; xxxi. 7; XXIX. i. 26. So were the Suessetani, enemies in XXV.
                        xxxiv. 6, but now allies, neighbours of the Edetani across the river.
                    </note> allies of the Roman people, in warlike fashion. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From citizens sprang a different outbreak in
                    the camp near Sucro. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The town of the
                        same name on the river (now the Júcar). Near it Pompey fought against
                        Sertorius; Plutarch <hi rend="italics">Sert.</hi> 19; <hi rend="italics"
                            >Pomp.</hi> 19; App. <hi rend="italics">B.C.</hi> I. 110. Livy's source
                        for the narrative of this mutiny was Polybius XI. xxv-xxx. Cf. App. <hi
                            rend="italics">Hisp.</hi> 34 ff. It remained a mutiny to the end (xxix.
                        12). The only citizens were (1) Romans in the army, and (2) Italian allies
                        serving with them (xxxii.6). There can be no hint of civil war in <hi
                            rend="italics">civilis furor,</hi> for the theme now to be developed was
                        announced in § 2, <hi rend="italics">non exercitus,</hi> etc. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Eight thousand soldiers were there, posted as
                    a garrison for the tribes dwelling on this side of the Ebro. Their disloyalty,
                    however, was not just beginning when unsubstantiated reports of the general's
                    imminent danger reached them, but existed even before, owing to the usual
                    licence resulting from long inaction. It was also to some extent because men
                    accustomed to live unrestrainedly on plunder in an enemy's territory felt the
                    pinch of peace-time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And at first they merely
                    engaged in secret conversations: If there was a war in the province, what were
                    they doing among people already pacified? If the war was over now and the
                    province set in order, why were they not transported back to Italy? <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> They made demands also for their pay with more
                    petulance than accorded with the customary self-control of the soldier; and
                    sentries heaped reproaches on tribunes making the rounds of the guard, and at
                    night some men had gone out for plunder into peaceful country all around.
                    Finally by day and openly without permission they would leave their standards.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Everything was being done in accordance
                    with the whim and fancy of the soldiers, nothing according to the traditions and
                    discipline of the service or the orders of superior officers. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The outward appearance, however, of a Roman camp was
                    maintained in this alone, that, believing the <pb n="p.101"/> tribunes, infected
                    with their madness, would not fail <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> to share their mutiny and revolt, they
                    permitted them to hear cases before the headquarters, went to them for the
                    password and did outpost and guard duty in succession. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Moreover, though they had robbed their command of power,
                    yet they kept up a show of obedience while actually giving orders themselves. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then the mutiny broke out after they observed
                    that the tribunes censured and disapproved of what was being done and were
                    endeavouring actively to oppose it, also openly declaring that they would not be
                    partners in their madness. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Accordingly,
                    chasing the tribunes out of the space before headquarters and soon after out of
                    the camp, they by common consent bestowed the command upon the leaders of the
                    mutiny, the privates Gaius Albius of Gales and Gaius Atrius, an Umbrian.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> These men, not at all satisfied with the
                    distinguishing marks of tribunes, ventured to pollute the insignia of the very
                    highest command, the fasces and axes. Nor did it occur to them that those rods
                    and axes, which they caused to be carried before them to frighten others, were
                    hanging over their own backs and their own necks. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> The unfounded belief in Scipio's death was the cause of
                    their blindness and, once rumour of it should presently be spread abroad, they
                    had no doubt that all Spain would be ablaze with war. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> In that uprising, they thought, money could be exacted from
                    allies, and also neighbouring cities plundered; and in the confusion, when any
                    man would dare anything, what they had themselves done would be less
                    conspicuous. <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While they waited from moment to moment for
                    fresh news, expecting to hear not only of his death but even of his funeral, and
                    yet none came and the groundless <pb n="p.103"/> report was losing hold, then
                    its first sponsors began <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 206</note> to be sought out. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And as
                    one after another drew back, that he might be thought to have rashly believed
                    such a thing rather than to have invented it, the deserted leaders were now
                    alarmed at their own insignia and, in place of the empty semblance of command
                    which was theirs, at the real, duly bestowed authority that would presently turn
                    against them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Thus when the mutiny was at a
                    standstill and credible informants brought the news, first that Scipio was
                    alive, and then that he was even well, seven tribunes of the soldiers arrived,
                    being sent by Scipio himself. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Upon their
                    arrival there was at first irritation; soon after, as the tribunes themselves by
                    mild words calmed acquaintances whom they had met, the men were less resentful.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For going round at first among the tents,
                    then in the headquarters square and before the general's tent, where they saw
                    groups talking together, they would speak to the men, asking them what was the
                    reason for their anger and their sudden mania, instead of finding fault with
                    them for what they had done. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A common
                    complaint was that their pay had not been given them on the proper date; also
                    that, whereas at the time when the men of Iliturgi <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. xix. i. and n.</note> had committed their crime,
                    after the slaughter of the two commanders-in-chief and the two armies, the Roman
                    name had been defended and the province retained by their own courage, yet,
                    while the Iliturgians now had a due punishment for their crime, there was no one
                    to reward their own good deeds. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In reply the
                    tribunes said that those who complained of such matters only were making just
                    pleas, and they would report them to the commander-in-chief. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> They were glad that there was nothing more serious <pb
                        n="p.105"/> nor more incurable; and by favour of the gods <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> Scipio and
                    the republic, they said, were in a position to show gratitude. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio, who was familiar with wars but
                    unacquainted with the gusts of mutinies, was kept in a state of concern lest
                    either the army should go to excess in wrong-doing or he himself in punishing
                    them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For the present he decided to use
                    gentle measures, as he had begun to do, and to bring the hope of pay nearer by
                    sending collectors round the tributary states. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> Next an edict was posted up that they should assemble at (New) Carthage to
                    get their pay, whether they preferred to do so as separate units or all
                    together. The mutiny, already of itself on the wane, was quelled by sudden peace
                    on the part of the rebellious Spaniards. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For
                    Mandonius and Indibilis had abandoned their project and retired to their borders
                    when they had news that Scipio was alive. Nor was there either a fellow-citizen
                    or foreigner any longer with whom the soldiers might share their madness.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On surveying all possible plans they had
                    nothing left except a not altogether safe retreat from criminal designs, namely,
                    to give themselves up either to the commander's well-grounded anger or to his
                    mercy, as not beyond their hopes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He had
                    pardoned even enemies, they said, with whom he had fought with the sword; their
                    mutiny had been free from wounds, free from bloodshed, and neither in itself
                    savage nor meriting a savage punishment. So unduly eloquent is human nature in
                    minimizing one's own guilt. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.107"/> The only question was whether to go in separate <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> cohorts to
                    get their pay, or all together. Their decision was that all should go together,
                    which they thought safer. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the days on which they were thus
                    deliberating there was a war-council in regard to them at (New) Carthage, and a
                    conflict of opinions as to whether the leaders only of the mutiny —and
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> they were not more than thirty-five in
                    number — should be punished, or whether punishment of a larger number was
                    required in penalizing, not a mutiny but rather a rebellion which set so
                    terrible an example. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The milder opinion
                    prevailed, that punishment should be limited to those with whom the breach of
                    discipline had begun, whereas for the mass a reprimand was enough. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> After the dismissal of the council, to give the
                    impression that this was the matter discussed, an expedition against Mandonius
                    and Indibilis was announced to the army which was at (New) Carthage, and they
                    were ordered to make ready their rations for several days. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The seven tribunes who had already gone to Sucro to repress
                    the mutiny and were now sent to meet the army had each of them the <milestone
                        n="6??" unit="section"/> names of five leaders of the mutiny assigned him,
                    to have them invited with kindly countenance and words by suitable men to be
                    their guests, lulled to sleep by wine and then bound. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The mutineers were now not far from (New) Carthage when the
                    news, heard from those they met, that on the next day the entire army would set
                    out under Marcus Silanus against the Lacetani, not only relieved them of all
                    fear which remained unexpressed in their minds, but caused great rejoicing that
                    they would have the commander alone, rather than be themselves in his <pb
                        n="p.109"/> power. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At sunset they entered
                    the city and saw the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 206</note> other army making every preparation for the march.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Received with studied words of welcome
                    —that their coming was a happy and timely thing for the general, in that they
                    had arrived at the very time the other army was leaving —they took refreshment
                    and rest. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The tribunes, without causing any
                    commotion, had the promoters of the mutiny brought by suitable persons to their
                    hospitable quarters, then seized and bound. At the fourth watch the baggage of
                    the army which, it was pretended, was to march away began to take the road.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> By daybreak the standards were in motion,
                    but at the gate the column was halted and guards were sent round to all the
                    gates, that no one should leave the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Then the men who had arrived the day before, on being summoned to an assembly,
                    rushed fiercely into the open space <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Polybius' <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >a)gora/</foreign> (VI. xxxi. 1 f.) to the right of the headquarters,
                        not the similar space (also called <hi rend="italics">forum</hi> ) in which
                        stood the <hi rend="italics">quaestorium;</hi> XLI. ii. 11. </note> and up
                    to the general's platform, intending actually to intimidate him by their
                    interruptions. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At the same moment that the
                    general mounted the platform the armed men brought back from the gates
                    surrounded the unarmed assembly from the rear. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> Then all their fierceness failed them and, as they afterwards admitted,
                    nothing alarmed them so much as the unexpected strength and healthy colour of
                    the general whom they had believed they would see as an invalid, also an
                    expression of his face such as, they said, they never remembered even in battle.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He sat in silence for a moment, until the
                    report reached him that the promoters of the mutiny had been <pb n="p.111"/>
                    brought into the open space and that everything was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> ready. <milestone n="27"
                        unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then, when the herald had enforced silence,
                    Scipio began as follows: <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        following speech has few direct borrowings from the briefer discourse in
                        Polybius XI. xxviii f., <hi rend="italics">e.g.,</hi> the comparison of a
                        crowd to the sea, § 11, more fully developed in the Greek peroration, xxix.
                        9-11. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "Never have I supposed that language with
                    which to address my army would fail me; not that I have ever occupied myself
                    with words rather than deeds, but because, having lived in camps almost from
                    boyhood, I was familiar with the minds of soldiers. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But how to speak to <hi rend="italics">you</hi> —for that
                    both thoughts and language fail me. I do not know even by what name I ought to
                    address you. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Citizens? when you have revolted
                    from your country? Or soldiers? when you have rejected the high command and the
                    auspices, have broken the sanctity of your oath? Enemies? <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> I recognize the bodies, faces, clothing, appearance of
                    citizens, but the deeds, the words, the plans, the spirit of enemies. For what
                    else did you either wish or hope for but the same as the Ilergetes and the
                    Lacetani? And yet they followed Mandonius and Indibilis, men of royal rank, as
                    leaders in their madness. You conferred the auspices and high command upon the
                    Umbrian Atrius and the Calenian Albius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Say
                    that not all of you did that, soldiers, or wished it done; that it was the
                    frenzy and folly of a few; I will gladly accept your denial. For the acts
                    committed were such that, if they were shared by the entire army, they cannot be
                    expiated without atonements on a great scale. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "Unwillingly do I handle such misdeeds, as if
                    they were wounds. But unless handled and treated they cannot be healed.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As for myself, after the Carthaginians
                    were driven out of Spain I did not believe <pb n="p.113"/> there was in the
                    entire province any place, any people, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> where my life was hated; so had I borne myself
                    not only towards allies, but also towards enemies. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Behold! here in my own camp —how mistaken I was! —a rumour
                    of my death was not only believed but even waited for. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Not that I should wish the crime to be shared by all. For
                    my part, if I believed that the whole of my army had desired my death I should
                    die here at once before your eyes, nor would a life hated by my fellow-citizens
                    and my soldiers give me pleasure. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But every
                    crowd is in itself motionless, as is the natural state of the sea; rather do
                    winds and breezes ruffle it. So among you there is either calm or sudden storms.
                    And the cause and source of every madness is chargeable to its promoters; your
                    insanity came by contagion. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Even today you do
                    not seem to me to know what a pitch of frenzy you have reached, what a crime you
                    have dared to commit against me, against your country and parents and children,
                    against the gods, witnesses of your oath, what a crime as regards the auspices
                    under which: you are serving, or the custom of the service and the discipline of
                    your ancestors, or the dignity of the supreme command! </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> "Of myself I say nothing, granting that you
                    were hasty rather than eager in believing, granting in short that I am a man
                    whose authority irks an army, and no wonder. But the country, what evil had she
                    done you, when you were betraying her by sharing your designs with Mandonius and
                    Indibilis? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> What harm had the Roman people
                    done you when you took away <pb n="p.115"/> the command from tribunes elected by
                    vote of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        206</note> people and conferred it upon private persons, when, not even
                    satisfied with having them as tribunes, you, a Roman army, bestowed the fasces
                    of your commander upon men who had never had a slave to whom they might give
                    orders? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In the headquarters were lodged
                    Albius and Atrius; at their tent sounded the trumpet, men came to them for the
                    watchword; they sat on Publius Scipio's tribunal. A lictor attended them; the
                    way was cleared before they proceeded; fasces with their axes were borne before
                    them. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Showers of stones and thunderbolts
                    hurled from the sky and animals bringing forth strange offspring you reckon
                    portents; here we have a portent which cannot be expiated by any victims, by any
                    set days of prayer, without the blood of those who have dared so great a crime. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "And although no crime has a reasonable
                    ground, nevertheless I should like to know what was your purpose, what your
                    plan, seeing that we are dealing with a flagrant offence. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> A legion formerly sent as a garrison to Regium, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. <hi rend="italics">Periocha</hi> 12
                        fin.; Polybius I. vii. 6 ff. This legion was made up of Campanians. As such
                        they were Roman citizens and did not serve as auxiliaries. </note> after
                    foully slaying the leading men of the state, held that wealthy city for ten
                    years. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For that crime the entire legion, four
                    thousand men, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. <hi rend="italics"
                            >Periocha</hi> 15. Livy overlooked serious losses the legion must have
                        suffered when the city was captured and in the course of ten years. This may
                        reduce the number executed to about Polybius' figure —more than 300; <hi
                            rend="italics">l.c.</hi> §§ 11 f. </note> were beheaded in the Forum at
                    Rome. But in the first place they did not follow the lead of Atrius the Umbrian,
                    half-soldier half-sutler, with an ominous name <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> from <hi rend="italics">ater,</hi> 'coal
                        black,' 'unlucky'; cf. the <hi rend="italics">dies atri</hi> of the
                        calendar. </note> also, but of Decimus Vibellius, a tribune of the
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> soldiers; neither did they ally themselves
                    with Pyrrhus, nor with the Samnites and Lucanians, enemies of the Roman people.
                    You <pb n="p.117"/> have shared your plans with Mandonius and Indibilis <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> and were
                    to have been their comrades in arms as <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> well.
                    The legion would have held Regium as its permanent abode, just as the Campanians
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It was in fact the Samnites who
                        captured Etruscan Capua; cf. IV. xxxvii. 1. ( <date when="-0424">424
                            B.C.</date> ); Strabo V. iv. 3. </note> held Capua, wrested away from
                    its former Etruscan inhabitants, just as the Mamertines held Messana in
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Sicily; and it would not have gone so far
                    as to attack the Roman people or allies of the Roman people. Was Sucro to have
                    been your <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> domicile? If I had left you there
                    when as general-in-command I was retiring from my province completely subdued,
                    it would have been right for you to implore the help of gods and men because you
                    were not returning to your wives and children. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "But granted that you have banished their
                    memory also from your minds, as you have that of your country and of myself, I
                    wish to follow up the outcome of your plan, a criminal one but not utterly
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> insane. If I lived and the rest of the
                    army was intact with which I captured (New) Carthage in a single day and with
                    which I routed, put to flight, drove out of Spain, four generals, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Both Hasdrubals, Hanno (ii. 11) and Mago
                        (xvi. 13).</note> four armies of the Carthaginians, would you —eight
                    thousand men, all of you certainly of less consequence than Albius and Atrius,
                    to whom you submitted yourselves —would you really have intended to wrest the
                    province of Spain from the Roman <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> people?
                    Suppose I take no account whatever of my name — granted that I have not been
                    wronged by you except in your readiness to believe me dead, <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> tell me, if I had been dying would the state have breathed
                    its last with me, would the empire of the Roman people have fallen with me? May
                    Jupiter the best and greatest forbid that the city, founded with due auspices
                    and <pb n="p.119"/> favour of the gods to endure forever, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Cf. IV. iv. 4; V. vii. 10. For <hi rend="italics">urbs
                            aeterna</hi> see <hi rend="italics">Trans. Amer. Philol. Assn.</hi> XXV.
                        (1894), 34 ff.; Franz Christ in <hi rend="italics">Tübinger Beiträge</hi>
                        XXXI. (1938), 59 ff. </note> should live no <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> longer than this frail,
                    mortal <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> body! Although Flaminius, Paulus,
                    Gracchus, Postumius Albinus, Marcus Marcellus, Titus Quinctius Crispinus, Gnaeus
                    Fulvius, my Scipios —so many generals and so distinguished —have perished in one
                    war, the Roman people survives and will survive, although a thousand others die,
                    now by the sword, now by disease. At <hi rend="italics">my</hi> funeral —one
                    man's —would the republic have been borne to its <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> tomb? You yourselves here in Spain, after the slaying of my
                    father and uncle, two generals, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Although Gnaeus Scipio was not legally an <hi rend="italics">imperator,</hi>
                        having been sent to Spain by Publius, while he himself returned to Italy
                        (XXI. xxxii. 3; xl. 3), it was unnecessary for the historian to be pedantic.
                        Cf. XXV. xxxii. 1; xxxvii. 9; XXVI. ii. 5. </note> appointed Septimus
                    Marcius as your commander against the Carthaginians, who were overjoyed by their
                    recent victory. And I am speaking just as if the Spanish provinces would have
                    been without a <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> commander. But would Marcus
                    Silanus, who was sent with me into the province with the same authority, the
                    same command, would my brother Lucius Scipio and Gaius Laelius, my lieutenants,
                    have failed to avenge the dignity of the high command? Could army have been
                    compared with army, or generals with <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    generals? Could rank or cause have been matched? If in all these respects you
                    had been superior, would you have borne arms against your country, against your
                    fellow-citizens? Would you have wished Africa to rule over Italy, Carthage over
                    the city of Rome? For what offence on the part of your country? <milestone
                        n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Coriolanus was once impelled by an unjust
                    condemnation, a wretched and undeserved banishment, to set out to besiege his
                    native city. Nevertheless family devotion recalled him from foul treason to the
                    state. In your case what <pb n="p.121"/> grievance, what anger spurred you on?
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Was delay of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> a few days in receiving
                    your pay owing to the illness of your general a sufficient reason why you should
                    declare war on your country, why you should revolt from the Roman people to the
                    Ilergetes, why not one thing divine or human should be to you inviolable? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Insane you surely were, soldiers, and no more critical ailment attacked
                        my body than your minds. I shrink from recalling what men believed, what
                        they hoped, what they desired. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Let
                        forgetfulness carry away and cancel everything if possible; if not, let
                        silence somehow cover it all. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I would not
                        deny that my speech has seemed to you severe and cruel; how much more cruel
                        do you believe your acts are than my words? And you think I ought patiently
                        to bear what you have done: on your side can you not bear patiently even the
                        telling of the whole story? But even those acts themselves will not be the
                        subject of further reproaches. May you forget them as easily as I shall
                        forget them! <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly, so far as the
                        mass of you are concerned, if you repent of your mistake, that is to me a
                        quite sufficient punishment. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Albius of
                        Cales and Atrius the Umbrian and the rest of those who brought about a
                        wicked mutiny will atone with their blood for what they have done.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To you the spectacle of their
                        punishment, if your minds have returned to health, ought not only to bring
                        no bitterness but even joy. For there are no men whom they have treated in a
                        more hostile and unfriendly spirit than yourselves. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scarcely had he made an end of speaking when,
                    in accordance with previous orders, their eyes and ears were assailed by
                    terrifying sights and sounds everywhere. The troops who had encircled the <pb
                        n="p.123"/> assembly crashed swords against shields. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The herald's <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> voice was heard, calling out the names of
                    those condemned in the war-council. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They were
                    being dragged out into the centre stripped, and at the same time everything
                    requisite for punishment was being brought out. Bound to a stake they were
                    scourged and beheaded, while the spectators were so paralysed by fear that not
                    only was no fierce protest against the severity of the punishment heard, but not
                    even a groan. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then all the bodies were
                    dragged away from the centre, and after the ground had been cleansed the
                    soldiers, summoned by name, in the presence of the military tribunes, swore
                    allegiance to Publius Scipio; and as each man was called his pay was counted out
                    to him. Such was the end and outcome of the mutiny of the soldiers which began
                    at Sucro. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time along the Baetis River
                    Hanno, Mago's prefect, who-had been sent from Gades with a small force of
                    Africans, enlisting Spaniards for pay, armed about four thousand young men.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then stripped of his camp by Lucius
                    Marcius, while the largest part of his troops were lost in the confusion of its
                    capture, some also lost in the flight, since the cavalry pursued the scattered
                    fugitives, Hanno himself with a small number only escaped. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While these things were going on along the
                    Baetis River, Laelius meantime sailed down the strait into the Ocean and came
                    with his fleet to Carteia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At the
                        north end of the Bay of Gibraltar, about half-way between the Rock, Calpe,
                        and Algeciras. Livy thinks of the Atlantic as beginning immediately beyond
                        the Pillars of Hercules, and thus including nearly the whole of the
                        Strait(Fretum Gaditanum). In <date when="-0171">171 B.C.</date> Carteia
                        became a Latin colony; XLIII. iii. 3 f. Cf. also Strabo III. i. 7; Mela II.
                        96. </note> This city is situated on the coast of the Ocean, where <pb
                        n="p.125"/> the sea begins to open out after the narrow entrance. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of Gades, as has been said above, he had hoped
                    without a battle to gain possession by betrayal, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. above, xxiii. 6.</note> since men actually came into
                    the Roman camp to make such a promise. But the betrayal was prematurely
                    revealed, and Mago arrested all the conspirators and turned them over to
                    Adherbal, the magistrate, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> one of the two <hi rend="italics">sufĕtes</hi>
                        and at the same time a general. Cf. xxxvii. 2 (at Gades); XXX. vii. 5.
                    </note> to be transported to Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Adherbal placed the conspirators on a quinquereme and after sending it in
                    advance, because it was slower than a trireme, himself followed with eight
                    triremes at no great distance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The quinquereme
                    was already entering the strait when Laelius, also on a quinquereme, sailed out
                    from the harbour of Carteia followed by seven triremes, and steered for Adherbal
                    and his triremes, feeling quite sure that the quinquereme, caught in the swift
                    current of the strait, could not reverse its course in the face of the tide. The
                    Carthaginian in the unexpected situation was troubled for the moment and
                    uncertain whether to follow his quinquereme or to turn his prows towards the
                    enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That hesitation in itself deprived him
                    of the power to refuse a battle; for they were already within range and the
                    enemy was pressing them from all sides. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    tide also had deprived them of control of their ships. Nor was the fight like a
                    naval battle; for here there was no initiative, no skill or strategy. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The nature of the strait and its tide alone
                    controlled the entire engagement, carrying men, vainly struggling to row in the
                    opposite direction, against their own ships or those of the enemy. And one might
                    have seen a fleeing ship swung about by a swirl <pb n="p.127"/> and borne
                    against the victors, and a pursuing ship, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> if it chanced upon an
                    opposite current, turning away as if in flight. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> In actual combat now one ship, aiming to ram a ship of the enemy with its
                    beak, turning aslant would itself receive the blow of the other's beak. Another
                    ship, exposing its beam to the enemy, would suddenly be swung and turned bow
                    foremost. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While- between the triremes an
                    indecisive battle controlled by chance was in progress, the Roman quinquereme,
                    whether because she was steadier by reason of her weight or more easily steered
                    as her more numerous banks of oars <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> If
                        a quinquereme had but one bank of oars, each oar pulled by five men, as many
                        now incline to believe, it remains unexplained how Livy in comparing a
                        quinquereme in battle with triremes could simply say that the former had
                        more <hi rend="italics">ordines remorum,</hi> unless he thought that to be
                        the case. In XXIV. xxxiv. 7 <hi rend="italics">exteriore ordine remorum</hi>
                        includes all the oars on one side of a ship but does not tell us whether in
                        a single bank or in five. Certainly the quinquereme, however rowed, was a
                        more impressive sight from the shore than a trireme even to a landlubber;
                        cf. XXIX. xi. 4. For the whole question see A. Köster, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Das antike Seewesen</hi> 143 ff.; and in Kromayer- Veith, <hi
                            rend="italics">Heerwesen,</hi> etc. 182 f.; 616 f.; W. W. Tarn, <hi
                            rend="italics">Hellenistic Military and Naval Developments</hi> 124 ff.;
                        and-in <hi rend="italics">Journal of Hellenic Studies,</hi> XXV. 137 ff.,
                        156, 204 ff.; Starr, C.G., <hi rend="italics">Class. Philol.</hi> XXXV. 353
                        ff.; 373. </note> cleft the whirling waters, sank two triremes and shooting
                    past another swept away the oars on one side. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In addition she would have seriously damaged the rest of the ships with which
                    she had closed, had not: Adherbal with five remaining ships crossed over to
                    Africa under sail. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laelius as victor sailed back to Carteia, and
                    on hearing of the occurrences at Gades —that the betrayal had been revealed and
                    the conspirators sent to Carthage; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that the
                    hope in which they had come to him had been frustrated —he sent messengers to
                    Lucius Marcius, saying that unless they wished to waste time to no purpose in
                    idling before Gades, they must return to the commander-in-chief. As Marcius
                    agreed, they both returned after a few days to (New) Carthage. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Upon their departure Mago was not only <pb n="p.129"/>
                    relieved, since he was beset by a two-fold source of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> alarm, by sea and by land,
                    but when he heard of the defection of the Ilergetes he conceived the hope also
                    of recovering Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly he sent
                    messengers to the senate at Carthage, to exaggerate at the same time both the
                    mutiny of citizens in the Roman camp and the rebellion of allies, and to urge
                    them to send auxiliaries, by whose help rule over Spain, which they had
                    inherited from their fathers, could be recovered. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Mandonius and Indibilis returned into their
                    own territory and for a time remained quietly on the alert, until they should
                    know what decision was reached in regard to the mutiny, not without confidence
                    that, if a misunderstanding on the part of Roman citizens should be pardoned,
                    they themselves also might possibly be pardoned. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> After the harsh punishment came to be generally known, they thought that
                    their guilt likewise was reckoned as deserving the same penalty. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Recalling the men of their tribe to arms and
                    assembling their previous auxiliaries, with twenty thousand infantry and two
                    thousand five hundred cavalry they crossed into the land of the Sedetani, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. xxiv. 4.</note> where they had
                    maintained a permanent camp at the beginning of the rebellion. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio by his conscientiousness in paying all
                    his men, guilty and innocent alike, and more by his countenance and speech
                    showing no resentment against any one, easily won the hearts of his soldiers.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Before moving his camp away from (New)
                    Carthage he summoned an assembly. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There after
                    inveighing at great length against the treachery of the chiefs in rebellion, he
                    declared that in order to punish their crime he was setting out in a very
                    different spirit <pb n="p.131"/> from that in which he recently cured a
                    misunderstanding <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        206</note> on the part of citizens. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At
                    that time, he said, with sighing and tears, just as though he were cutting into
                    his own vital organs, he had atoned by the lives of thirty men for the folly, or
                    it might be the guilt, of eight thousand. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But
                    now with joy and exaltation of spirit he was advancing to the slaughter of the
                    Ilergetes. For they had not been born in the same land, nor were they linked by
                    any alliance with himself. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The only bond which
                    once existed, that of loyalty and friendship, they had themselves broken by
                    their crime. As for his own army, he was stirred on seeing all the men in it
                    citizens or allies and Latins, and also because there was hardly a soldier who
                    had not been brought from Italy either by his uncle Gnaeus Scipio, who was the
                    first of the Romans to come into that province, or by his father as consul, or
                    by himself. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were all of them accustomed
                    to the name and auspices of the Scipios, being men whom he would like to bring
                    home to their country for a well-earned triumph, men who he hoped would support
                    his canvass for the consulship, just as if an honour shared by all alike were at
                    stake. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So far as concerned the enterprise now
                    impending, he said, any man who considered it a war was forgetting their own
                    achievements. Mago surely, who fled with a few ships beyond the known world to
                    an island surrounded by the Ocean, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf.
                        p. 141 and note.</note> was a greater concern to him than the Ilergetes.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For there it was a Carthaginian general
                    and also a Punic force however small; here there were brigands and brigand
                    chiefs, who might, to be sure, have considerable strength for ravaging the lands
                    of neighbouring tribes and for burning houses and stealing cattle, but none <pb
                        n="p.133"/> at all in battle-line and when standards faced standards. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> In battle
                    they would rely more upon swiftness in flight than upon arms. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly it was not because he saw any danger from them
                    or the seed of a greater war, that he had thought the Ilergetes must be
                    overpowered before he left his province. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It
                    was in the first place in order that so criminal a rebellion might not go
                    unpunished, and then that it might not possibly be said that any enemy had been
                    left in a province which had been thoroughly conquered by such courage combined
                    with such success. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Wherefore with the kind
                    aid of the gods let them follow him, not so much to carry on a war —for it was
                    no conflict with a well-matched enemy —as to exact punishment from criminals. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Dismissing them after this speech, he ordered
                    them to make ready for the march on the morrow; and setting out he came in ten
                    stages to the river Hiberus. Then crossing the river, he pitched camp on the
                    fourth day in sight of the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In front was
                    level ground hemmed in on this side and that by mountains. Into that valley
                    Scipio first ordered men to drive cattle —mostly booty from the enemy's own
                    farms-to tempt the barbarians' love of pillage, and then sent light —armed
                    troops to their assistance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When these had
                    begun the battle with a charge, he ordered Laelius to make an attack with
                    cavalry from an ambush. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A hill conveniently
                    projecting concealed the ambsucade of cavalry, and the battle began without
                    delay. The Spaniards, catching sight of cattle in the distance, dashed upon
                    them, the light-armed upon the Spaniards busy with their plunder. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> At first they inspired alarm by their missiles; then
                    abandoning their light weapons, which <pb n="p.135"/> could provoke rather than
                    decide the battle, they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 206</note> drew their swords and began fighting at close quarters. And
                    the infantry battle would have remained doubtful if the cavalry had not arrived.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Not only did they trample down those they
                    met by a frontal attack, but some also rode round along the lowest part of the
                    slope and made an attack in the rear, so that they cut off a good many; and the
                    slaughter was greater than unimportant skirmishes usually cause. </p>
                <p> This defeat kindled the anger of the barbarians, instead of diminishing their
                    courage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Consequently, not to appear daunted,
                    they went out into battle-line at daybreak the next day. The valley being
                    narrow, as stated above, had no room for all the forces. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> About two-thirds of the infantry and all the cavalry came
                    down into line. The remainder of their infantry they stationed on the slope of
                    the hill. Scipio, who thought the limited space was to his advantage, both
                    because a battle at close range seemed likely to be better <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> suited to the Roman than to the Spanish soldier, also
                    because the enemy's line had been enticed down into a position which did not
                    have room for all of their multitude, turned his attention to a further new
                    plan. He could not place his cavalry on the wings, he thought, in so limited a
                    space, and the enemy would have no use of the cavalry they had brought down with
                    their infantry. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Therefore he ordered Laelius
                    to lead his cavalry about over the hills, taking the road that was best hidden,
                    and <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> to separate the cavalry battle, so far
                    as he could, from that of the infantry. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As
                    for himself, he made all his infantry units face the enemy; four cohorts he
                    placed in the front line, since he was unable to extend his line to a greater
                    length. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He did not delay <pb n="p.137"/>
                    beginning the engagement, in order to divert <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> attention by the battle
                    itself from the sight of the cavalry crossing over the hills; and they were not
                    aware that the horsemen had outflanked them until they heard the din of a
                    cavalry battle in their rear. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Thus there were
                    two distinct battles; two infantry lines, two cavalry forces, were fighting down
                    the length of the level ground, since the narrow space did not permit a battle
                    that combined both arms. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> On the Spanish side
                    neither did infantry aid cavalry nor cavalry infantry; the foot-soldiers, who in
                    reliance upon the cavalry had been rashly posted on the level ground, were cut
                    to pieces; the cavalry, being outflanked, were neither withstanding Roman
                    infantry in front —for their own infantry were already overwhelmed —nor Roman
                    cavalry in the rear. Consequently the horsemen also, after they had formed a
                    circle and with their horses at a standstill had defended themselves for a long
                    time, were all slain to a man; and not one of their foot or horse that fought in
                    the valley survived. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Only a third of them,
                    having stood on the hill, to look on in safety rather than to take part in the
                    battle, had both a suitable position and time for flight. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> Among them the princes also fled, having slipped away in
                    the confusion before the entire line should be surrounded. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The camp of the Spaniards was captured the
                    same day, with about three thousand men in addition to other booty. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Of the Romans and allies about twelve hundred fell in
                    that battle; more than three thousand men were wounded. The victory would have
                    been less bloody if the battle had been fought on a more open ground affording
                    an easy escape. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.139"/>
                <p> Indibilis, having discarded his plans for war, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> thought no refuge safer in
                    his distress than Scipio's honesty and mercy, of which he had had experience,
                    and sent his brother Mandonius to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Mandonius, clasping Scipio's knees, laid the blame upon the fateful madness of a
                    time in which some pestilent epidemic had frenzied not merely the Ilergetes and
                    Lacetani but also a Roman camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As for
                    himself, -indeed, and his brother and the rest of their countrymen, such was
                    their situation that they should either give back to Publius Scipio, if he
                    approved, the life they had received also from him, or, if spared twice, they
                    should perpetually devote to him the lives they owed to him alone. Formerly,
                    when they had as yet no experience of his mercy, they had confidence in their
                    cause. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now, however, they had no hope, he
                    said, in their cause, but rested it all on the pity of the victor. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The old custom of the Romans in establishing
                    peaceful relations with a people neither on the basis of a treaty nor on equal
                    terms had been this: not to exert its authority over that people, as now
                    pacified, until it had surrendered everything divine and human, until hostages
                    had been received, arms taken away and garrisons posted in its cities.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio, however, after inveighing at
                    length against Mandonius, who was present, and the absent Indibilis, said that
                    in consequence of their own misdeeds they had surely deserved to die; that they
                    should live by his kindness and that of the Roman people. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But he would not take away their arms nor demand hostages;
                    for those were the pledges for men who feared a rebellion, whereas he was
                    leaving them their arms without restriction, their minds relieved of fear. And
                    if they <pb n="p.141"/> should revolt his wrath would be directed, not against
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note>
                    innocent hostages, but against themselves, and he would exact punishment, not
                    from an unarmed, but from an armed enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As
                    they had known both kinds of fortune, he gave them their choice, whether they
                    preferred to find the Romans kindly disposed or angry. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Thus Mandonius was dismissed with no other demand than
                    money, that the soldiers might receive their pay. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> After sending Marcius ahead into Farther Spain and Silanus
                    back to Tarraco, Scipio delayed a few days for the Ilergetes to pay the whole
                    amount demanded, and then with an unencumbered force overtook Marcius as he was
                    now approaching the Ocean. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Dealings which had to do with Masinissa, begun
                    even before this time, had been postponed on one pretext or another because the
                    Numidian desired in any case to meet Scipio in person and to ratify the
                    agreement by clasping his hand. That was Scipio's reason at this time for a
                    march so long and so circuitous. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Masinissa,
                    being at Gades and informed by Marcius of Scipio's approach, pretended that the
                    horses, being shut up on an island, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Gades, the oldest Phoenician city in the West (possibly 300 years older than
                        Carthage), was built at first on a very small island at the north-west end
                        of a long narrow island tapering away to the south-south-east. In later
                        times the harbour was closed in that direction by the slow action of
                        Atlantic tides, so that the long island became a peninsula. The city, now
                        Cadiz, is separated from the mainland to the east (at the Trocadero) by a
                        channel three-fourths of a mile wide. Cf. Strabo III. v. 3; Mela III. 46;
                        Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> IV. 119 f.; Schulten in <hi
                            rend="italics">Arch. Anzeiger</hi> 1927, pp. 203 ff. (maps). </note>
                    were deteriorating and not only causing a general scarcity for the rest but also
                    themselves suffering from it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Adding that the
                    horsemen were losing their vigour from inaction, he prevailed upon Mago to
                    permit him to cross over to the mainland in order to lay waste the nearest lands
                    in Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After crossing over he sent three
                    prominent Numidians in advance to fix a time and <pb n="p.143"/> place for a
                    conference. He gave instructions that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> two were to be kept by Scipio as hostages.
                    When the third had been sent back to conduct Masinissa to the place indicated in
                    the order, they came with a small escort to the conference. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Numidian had already been filled with admiration for
                    the man in consequence of his reported achievements, and had conjured up in mind
                    an ideal figure, tall and stately. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But greater
                    still was the reverence that possessed him for the man in his presence; and
                    while Scipio had great natural dignity, long hair added charm, as did a general
                    appearance not due to studied elegance, but truly masculine and soldierly;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and his age was exactly at the height of
                    physical strength, amplified and made more dazzling by the youthful bloom which
                    appeared to have been renewed after his illness. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Almost dazed by merely meeting him, the
                    Numidian thanked him for sending home his nephew. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Here a brother's son, while according to XXVII. xix. 9,
                        perhaps from a different source, Massiva would be a sister's son. </note>
                    From that time on, he said, he had sought the opportunity which he did not let
                    slip when at last it was. presented him by the favour of the immortal gods.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was eager to give such services to
                    Scipio and the Roman people that no individual foreigner would have aided the
                    Roman state with more ardour. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That aid,
                    although he had long wished to give it, he had been unable to furnish in Spain,
                    a foreign and unknown land. But in the land in which he had been born and
                    brought up in the hope of inheriting his father's kingdom, he would easily
                    furnish it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If indeed the Romans should send
                    Scipio as commander into Africa as well he was quite confident that Carthage
                    would be very short-lived. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scipio was glad to
                    see and hear him, since he knew that in the entire cavalry of the enemy
                    Masinissa had been the soul <pb n="p.145"/> of everything, and in himself the
                    young man showed <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        206</note> clear evidence of his spirit. After giving and receiving promises
                    Scipio set out on the return to Tarraco. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa by permission of the Romans, that he might not appear to have crossed
                    to the mainland without reason, devastated the nearest lands and returned to
                    Gades. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just as Mago, who had despaired of success in
                    Spain —a hope to which first the mutiny of the soldiers and then the rebellion
                    of Indibilis had raised his spirits —was preparing to cross over to Africa, word
                    reached him from Carthage that the senate commanded him to take the fleet which
                    he had at Gades over to Italy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There he was
                    ordered to hire the greatest possible number of young Gauls and Ligurians, to
                    join Hannibal and not permit a war that had been begun with the greatest vigour
                    and even greater good fortune to decline now. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For that purpose money was brought to Mago from Carthage, and in addition he
                    himself exacted all that he could from the citizens of Gades by plundering not
                    merely their treasury but also the temples, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Including the famous temple of Hercules, 12 miles south
                        of the city, on a very small peninsula, now an island (Santipetri). Cf. XXI.
                        xxi. 9; Strabo <hi rend="italics">l.c. sub fin.;</hi> Mela <hi
                            rend="italics">l.c.;</hi> Schulten <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi>
                        1922, pp. 38 ff.; 1927, p. 211. </note> and by compelling all private owners
                    to contribute gold and silver to the public funds. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As he was sailing along the coast of Spain he
                    landed soldiers not far from New Carthage and laid waste the nearest farms; then
                    he brought his fleet up to the city. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There
                    after keeping the soldiers on shipboard during the day, he landed them on the
                    shore by night and led them to that part of the wall where (New) Carthage had
                    been stormed by the Romans. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXVI.
                        xlv. 7 ff.; xlvi. 2.</note> For he thought the city was not held by a
                    garrison of sufficient strength, also that with the <pb n="p.147"/> prospect of
                    changing sides many of the townspeople <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> would take an active part. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But messengers coming in alarm from the country had brought
                    news at the same time of lands laid waste and farmers fleeing and the enemy
                    approaching. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By day the fleet also had been
                    seen, and it was evident that an anchorage before the city had not been chosen
                    without reason. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly the men were kept
                    drawn up under arms inside the gate which faced the lagoon and the sea. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Inexact, for the gate at the west end
                        of the city beneath the citadel of Hasdrubal faced neither lagoon nor sea.
                        It merely gave access to a bridge over the canal (outlet of the lagoon) and
                        so by diverging roads to the <hi rend="italics">stagnum</hi> or to the
                        harbour. See plan in Vol. VII; Scullard, 298 f. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the enemy pouring out of the ships —a mob
                    of sailors mingling with the soldiers —approached the walls with an uproar out
                    of proportion to their power the Romans suddenly opened the gate and burst out
                    with a shout, <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> threw the enemy into
                    confusion, routed them at the first charge and the first volley of their
                    missiles and pursued them down to the shore with great slaughter. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> And if the ships moored to the shore had not
                    received them in their alarm not a man would have survived the flight and the
                    battle. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Even on the ships also there was
                    confusion while, to prevent the enemy from dashing on board along with their own
                    men, they were drawing in the ladders <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Used in place of gang-planks. Cf. <hi rend="italics">Bell. Alex.</hi> 20. 4;
                        Theocr. 22. 30. </note> and cutting hawsers <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> From stern to shore; XXII. xix. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> 10; Quint. IV. ii. 41. Bows were headed seaward and
                        held by <hi rend="italics">ancoralia</hi> (here <hi rend="italics"
                            >ancorae</hi> by the same figure of speech as <quote>shores</quote> for
                            <quote>shore cables</quote> ). Cf. <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> xxx. 10. </note> and cables, to avoid
                    delay in getting away. And many perished miserably while swimming towards the
                    ships, as in the darkness it was not clear what they should make for and what
                    they should avoid. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the next day, when the
                    fleet had slipped away, returning towards the Ocean from which it had come,
                    about eight hundred bodies and some two thousand weapons were found between the
                    wall and the shore. </p>
                <pb n="p.149"/>
                <p> XXXVII. Mago, upon his return to Gades finding <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> himself shut out of the
                    city, put in with his fleet to Cimbii, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Mentioned here only.</note> a place not far from Gades. He sent emissaries
                    and complained because the gates had been closed against him, an ally and
                    friend. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Gaditani tried to excuse
                    themselves, saying it was done by a mob enraged on account of some looting
                    committed by the soldiers as they were embarking. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He thereupon enticed their <hi rend="italics">sufĕtes
                        —the</hi> highest magistrates among the Phoenicians —together with the
                    treasurer to a conference and ordered them to be scourged and crucified. Then he
                    crossed over on his ships to the island of Pityusa, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The larger (now Iviza) separated by a narrow strait
                        from a smaller island also called Ebusus. Cf. XXII. xx. 7; Pliny <hi
                            rend="italics">N.H.</hi> III. 76, 78; Strabo III. v. 1; Mela II. 125;
                        Diodorus Sic. V. 16. </note> about a hundred miles from the mainland.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Carthaginians at that time inhabited the
                    island; consequently the fleet was received on friendly terms, and not only were
                    supplies generously furnished but young men to recruit the fleet, and arms also
                    were given. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Relying upon these the
                    Carthaginian crossed over to the Balearic Islands, fifty miles away. </p>
                <p> There are two Balearic Islands, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Now
                        Mallorca and Menorca, 30 miles apart, the former with its towns, Palma and
                        Pollentia (Pollenzo); Mela II. 124 and the others just cited. </note> one
                    larger and richer in arms and men. It has a harbour also, where Mago —and it was
                    now the end of autumn —believed he could winter comfortably. But an attack was
                    made on the fleet, just as if the inhabitants of the island were Romans.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The sling, now their most used weapon, was
                    then their only one, and not a single man in any other tribe so excels in the
                    art of using it as do all the Balearic Islanders in comparison with other
                    peoples. Accordingly such a volley of stones, <pb n="p.151"/> like the densest
                    hail, was rained upon the fleet now <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 206</note> approaching land that, not venturing to enter
                    the harbour, they headed their ships out to sea. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Thereupon they crossed over to the smaller of the Balearic Islands, fertile
                    in its land, not so strong in men and arms. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Disembarking, therefore, they pitched camp in a strong position above the
                    harbour. And having gained possession of the city and its territory without a
                    battle they enlisted two thousand auxiliaries from there, sent them to Carthage
                    and beached their ships to spend the winter. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    After Mago's retirement from the coast of the Ocean Gades surrendered to the
                    Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the results in Spain under the
                    command and auspices of Publius Scipio. Turning over the province to Lucius
                    Lentulus and Lucius Manlius Acidinus, the propraetors, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Both had been praetors (in 211 and <date when="-0210"
                            >210 B.C.</date> respectively) but were not technically propraetors,
                        having been sent out as private citizens <hi rend="italics">cum
                            imperio,</hi> thus having the rank and authority of proconsuls. Such was
                        Scipio's own status. Cf. XXIX. xii. 2; xiii. 7; XXXI. xx. 4 (Vol. IX. p. 59
                        and note). </note> Scipio himself returned to Rome with ten ships.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And when a session of the senate was
                    granted him in the Temple of Bellona <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Cf. ix. 5 and note.</note> outside the city, he set forth his achievements
                    in Spain; how many times he had fought pitched battles; how many towns he had
                    taken by force from the enemy; what tribes he had subjected to the sway of the
                    Roman people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He had gone to Spain, he said,
                    against four generals-in-command, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf.
                        xxviii. 9, note.</note> against four victorious armies; he had left not a
                    Carthaginian in that country. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For these
                    achievements he sought the desired triumph but did not make an insistent demand,
                    because it was established that down to that time no one who had commanded
                    without being a magistrate had triumphed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    senate having <pb n="p.153"/> adjourned, he entered the city on foot, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As being a private citizen; of. Vol.
                        VII. p. 80, n. 1; XXXII. vii. 4. </note> and before <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 206</note> him he caused fourteen
                    thousand three hundred and forty-two pounds of silver to be carried to the
                    treasury, and a great number of silver coins. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Then an election for the choice of consuls was conducted by Lucius Veturius
                    Philo, and all the centuries with great enthusiasm named Publius Cornelius
                    Scipio consul. As his colleague he was given Publius Licinius Crassus, the
                    pontifex maximus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The election was thronged,
                    it is further related, by greater numbers than any other during that war.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From every side they had come together,
                    not only to vote but also to get a sight of Publius Scipio, and they flocked in
                    large numbers both to his house <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It
                        was south of the Forum, just behind the Tabernae Veteres; XLIV. xvi. 10.
                    </note> and to him on the Capitol as he was sacrificing, offering up to Jupiter
                    the hundred oxen he had vowed in Spain. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They
                    promised themselves also that, just as Gaius Lutatius had finished the former
                    Punic war, so Publius Cornelius would finish the war that was upon them;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that as he had driven the
                    Carthaginians entirely out of Spain, so he would drive them out of Italy;
                    further assuring themselves that Africa should be his province, just as if the
                    war in Italy were over. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then the election of
                    praetors was held. Two who at that time were plebeian aediles were elected,
                    Spurius Lucretius and Gnaeus Octavius, and from private life Gnaeus Servilius
                    Caepio and Lucius Aemilius Papus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In the fourteenth year of the Punic war, at
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> time
                    Publius Cornelius Scipio and Publius Licinius Crassus entered upon their
                    consulship, the consuls' provinces were designated, Sicily for Scipio — <pb
                        n="p.155"/> without casting lots, as his colleague gave way <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> because
                    the charge of religious rites kept a pontifex maximus in Italy —and the land of
                    the Bruttians for Crassus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then the
                    praetorian assignments were determined by lot. The city praetorship fell to
                    Gnaeus Servilius, Ariminum <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. ix. 1,
                        note.</note> —so they used to designate Gaul —to Spurius Lucretius, Sicily
                    to Lucius Aemilius, Sardinia to Gnaeus Octavius. </p>
                <p> The senate met on the Capitol. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf.
                        Vol. VII. p. 2, note; XXIV. x. 1; XXX. xxvii. 1.</note>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> There, the question being raised by Publius
                    Scipio, a decree of the senate was passed that the games which he had vowed
                    during the mutiny of the soldiers in Spain should be celebrated by him, drawing
                    upon the money which he had himself brought into the treasury. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thereupon he presented the ambassadors from
                    Saguntum. The eldest of these spoke as follows: "Although no calamity exists
                    which goes beyond what we have suffered, conscript fathers, in our desire to
                    keep our faith with you to the very end, nevertheless, such have been your
                    services and those of your generals towards us that we do not regret our
                    disasters. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> You undertook the war on our
                    account; having undertaken it you have carried it on with such persistence
                    through thirteen years that often you yourselves reached the extreme of danger
                    and brought the Carthaginian people often to the same pass. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Although in Italy you had so terrible a war and Hannibal as
                    your enemy, you sent a consul with his army into Spain, as if to gather up the
                    flotsam of our shipwreck. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Publius Cornelius
                    and Gnaeus Cornelius from the time when they came into the province never ceased
                    doing what was in our favour and against our enemies. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> First of all they restored our city to us; they sent men
                    all over Spain in search of <pb n="p.157"/> our citizens who had been sold and
                    out of slavery <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        205</note> restored them to freedom. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When
                    now we had almost attained an enviable lot after the utmost misery, Publius
                    Cornelius and Gnaeus Cornelius, your generals, brought almost more sorrow to us
                    than to you by their death. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> ."Then indeed we seemed to ourselves to have
                    been dragged back from distant places to our former abode merely to perish again
                    and to witness a second destruction of our native city. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> We were thinking also that there was no need whatever of a
                    Carthaginian general or army for our ruin, that we could be wiped out by the
                    Turduli, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The most that we know about
                        this tribe is that they were neighbours of the Turdetani in Baetica, fully
                        250 miles from Saguntum, which was in the land of the Edetani. Livy and his
                        source (probably Coelius) ignored the impossible distance and made the
                        Turdetani (§ 11), or here the Turduli, responsible. App. <hi rend="italics"
                            >Hisp.</hi> 10 has <foreign xml:lang="greek">Torbolh=tai,</foreign> and
                        if any Greek source had such a reading as <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >Tordolh=tai,</foreign> the confusion might perhaps be accounted for.
                        Cf. XXI. vi. 1; XXIV. xlii. 11; Strabo III. i. 6; ii. 11, 15; iii. 5; E.
                        Meyer, <hi rend="italics">Kl. Schr.</hi> II. 408. In Polybius' account no
                        tribe is mentioned (III. xiv. f., xvii). </note> our oldest enemies, who had
                    been responsible for our former destruction as well, when suddenly and
                    unexpectedly you sent us this Publius Scipio. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    In seeing him declared consul and in reporting, as we intend, to our citizens
                    that we have seen him, our hope, our help, our safety, so elected we deem
                    ourselves the most fortunate of all the Saguntines. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> On capturing many cities of your enemies in Spain he
                    everywhere separated Saguntines from the number of captives and sent them back
                    to their native city. Finally, as for Turdetania, which was so hostile to us
                    that Saguntum could not stand if that tribe was <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> preserved, he so crushed it in war that not only we, but
                    even our descendants do not need to fear it —without boasting be it said! We see
                    the ruined city of a people to favour whom Hannibal had destroyed Saguntum.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> We receive <pb n="p.159"/> from their
                    territory a revenue which is not more <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 205</note> welcome to us as income than as vengeance. For
                    these things —and we could not hope or pray for greater things from the immortal
                    gods —the <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> senate and people of Saguntum have
                    sent us, ten ambassadors, to you to express our thanks, at the same time to
                    congratulate you because for these years you have so conducted the war in Spain
                        <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> and in Italy that you hold Spain
                    subdued by arms, not merely so far as the river Hiberus, but even where Ocean
                    sets bounds to the most distant lands, and have left the Carthaginian only so
                    much of Italy as the fortification of his camp encircles. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> To Jupiter greatest and best, defender of the Capitoline
                    citadel, we have been bidden not merely to render thanks for all this but with
                    your permission to carry this gift of a golden wreath also to the Capitol on
                    account of your victory. We beg you to permit this, and if it seems best to you,
                    that you ratify and perpetuate by your authority those advantages which your
                    generals have bestowed upon us. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The senate replied to the Saguntine
                    ambassadors that the destruction and restoration of Saguntum would be to all
                    nations an example of a loyalty which both allies have maintained; <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> that its generals had been entirely right and had
                    complied with the wish of the senate in restoring Saguntum and rescuing the
                    citizens of Saguntum from slavery; <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> and that
                    where ever the generals had treated them with consideration the senate had
                    approved of such action; that they permitted them to deposit their gift on the
                    Capitol. It was then ordered that lodgings and <pb n="p.161"/> comforts <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The term <hi rend="italics">lautia</hi>
                        by its derivation from <hi rend="italics">lavare</hi> at first meant bathing
                        facilities, but came to include other comforts provided for guests of the
                        state. Cf. XXX. xvii. 14. </note> be provided for the ambassadors, and that
                    to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> each
                    of them be presented not less than ten thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> as
                    a gift. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXX. <hi rend="italics"
                            >l.c.,</hi> for a gift in money to ambassadors. </note>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Then the rest of the embassies were
                    introduced into the senate and had their hearing. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> And upon request of the Saguntines that they might make
                        <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/> a tour of Italy so far as they could
                    safely do so, guides were furnished them and letters sent to the different
                    towns, bidding them to receive the Spaniards hospitably. <milestone n="22"
                        unit="section"/> Thereupon the senate took up matters concerning the state,
                    the enrolment of armies, the assignment of posts. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This last had already been done (xxxviii. 12 f.).
                        Popular feeling, however, favoured at least giving Scipio power to cross
                        over from Sicily to Africa if he should deem it best (xlv. 8), or even
                        substituting Africa for Sicily as his assignment. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While it was commonly reported that without
                    casting lots Africa was to be assigned to Publius Scipio as a new province, he
                    himself, no longer satisfied with moderate fame, kept saying that he had been
                    named consul not only to carry on the war but also to finish it. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> This was impossible unless he should himself
                    transport his army to Africa, he said, openly declaring that he would accomplish
                    that result by popular vote if the senate should oppose. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This plan being by no means approved by the leading
                    senators, while because of fear or else to curry favour, all the rest failed to
                    speak out, Quintus Fabius Maximus, when asked his opinion, said: "I know that
                    many of you, conscript fathers, hold that we are today debating a closed
                    question, and that whoever expresses an opinion on Africa as a province, just as
                    if it were an open question, will be speaking to no purpose. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> For myself, however, in the first place I <pb n="p.163"/>
                    do not understand how Africa is already definitely <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> assigned to that brave and
                    energetic man, the consul, since neither has the senate voted nor the people
                    commanded <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The people in such a case
                        could act only on request of the senate; XXX. xxvii. 3; xl. 10. Scipio's
                        threat (§ 2) would first involve action by the senate. </note> that it be a
                    province for this year. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the second place,
                    if it is his, I think that the consul who mocks the senate by pretending to
                    bring before the house business upon which action has been taken is at fault,
                    not a senator who in his proper order states his opinion on the matter under
                    consideration. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And I am quite certain that in
                    opposing such haste to cross over into Africa I must expose myself to two
                    charges, first, of an inborn habit of delay, <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    which young men are free to call fear and lack of spirit, provided there are as
                    yet no regrets that other men's policies have always appeared at first sight
                    more attractive, mine the better in practice. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Secondly, they will accuse me of carping criticism and envy towards the daily
                    increasing fame of a very brave consul. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From
                    this suspicion if neither my past life and my character nor my dictatorship and
                    five consulships can defend me, together with so much glory won in the field and
                    at home that I tend to be sated rather than to crave it, may my years at least
                    bring exemption. For what rivalry can I have with a man who is not even my son's
                    contemporary? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In my dictatorship, although I
                    was still at the height of my powers and in the stream of great events, no one
                    heard me refuse either in the senate or before the people to have the command of
                    my master of the horse, who was inveighing against me, made equal to mine, a
                    thing which never had been heard of before. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXII. xxv f.</note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.165"/> By acts rather than words I preferred to gain this <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> result,
                    that one who by the verdict of other men had been made my colleague should
                    presently by his own admission place me above himself. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Much less would I, who have filled the high offices, set
                    before me competition and rivalry with a young man in the very flower of his
                    youth, with the intention, <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> of course, of
                    having Africa, if it be denied him, awarded as a province to me, who am now worn
                    out by mere living, not only by cares of state. With such glory as has been
                    already earned must I live and die. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> I have
                    prevented Hannibal from conquering, in order that you men whose powers are still
                    strong might even conquer him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "One thing it will be right, Publius
                    Cornelius, for you to pardon me —inasmuch as in my own case I have never rated
                    what men say more highly than the state —namely, if I do not prefer your glory,
                    either, to the welfare of the state. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If,
                    however, there were no war in Italy, or if the enemy were one from whose defeat
                    no glory was to be earned, only then could a man who kept you in Italy, even if
                    he did so with advantage to the state, be thought to have been bent on taking
                    away the war from you and with it your opportunity for fame. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But since Hannibal as an enemy with army intact is
                    occupying Italy for the fourteenth year, will <hi rend="italics">you</hi> be
                    dissatisfied with your fame, Publius Cornelius, if in your consulship you shall
                    have driven out of Italy the enemy who has caused us so many losses, so many
                    disasters, and if you shall have the distinction of finishing the present war,
                    just as Gaius Lutatius had that of ending the former Punic war? <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. <hi rend="italics">Periocha</hi> 19
                            <hi rend="italics">fin.;</hi> Polybius I. lix.-lxi for the naval victory
                        off the Aegates Islands, <date when="-0241">241 B.C.</date> ; XXII. xiv. 13;
                        XXIII. xiii. 4. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Unless Hamilcar is to be rated above Hannibal
                    as a general, or that war above this <pb n="p.167"/> one, or unless that victory
                    was greater and more <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 205</note> famous than this one is to be, if only it be our good
                    fortune to win in your consulship. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Would you
                    rather have dragged Hamilcar away from Drepana or down from Eryx <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Now Monte San Giuliano, 2465 ft. It had
                        a famous temple of Aphrodite, whose cult was presumably of Phoenician
                        origin. Cf. XXI. x. 7; xli. 6 ff.; Polybius I. lv. 7 ff.; Strabo VI. ii. 6.
                        Here Hamilcar held out until the Roman naval victory brought the First Punic
                        War to an end. Drepana (Trapani), the seaport, was 41 miles away. </note>
                    than have driven the Carthaginians and Hannibal out of Italy? <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Although you take more delight in glory already won than in
                    glory hoped for, even you would not boast of having rid Spain of the war rather
                    than Italy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "Not yet has Hannibal reached such a pass that
                    the man who preferred some other war would not seem to have feared rather than
                    despised him. Therefore gird yourself for this war, and not employing your
                    roundabout method —crossing first to Africa, and then hoping Hannibal will
                    follow you thither —but <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> rather by a direct
                    march from here aim your campaign at the region where Hannibal is, if you seek
                    your glorious palm for bringing the Punic war to an end. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> This is also the natural order: first to defend your own
                    possessions, then to proceed to attack those of others. First peace in Italy,
                    then be it war-in Africa! and let our fear abate before we use fear as an
                    offensive weapon against others. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If both can
                    be done under your lead and your auspices, after defeating Hannibal here, storm
                    Carthage over there. If one or the other of these two victories must be left to
                    new consuls, the earlier will prove not only greater and more celebrated but the
                    cause as well of the later victory. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For at
                    the present time, not to mention that the treasury cannot support two widely
                    separated armies, in Italy and in Africa, not to mention that no resources <pb
                        n="p.169"/> remain out of which we may maintain fleets, out of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> which we
                    may be able to furnish supplies, pray tell me, who does not see how great is the
                    danger involved? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Publius Licinius will carry
                    on the war in Italy, Publius Scipio in Africa. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> Tell me, if a victorious Hannibal —may all the gods avert the omen! and my
                    mind even shudders to mention it; but what has happened can happen —if he shall
                    advance towards the city, then and not before, are we to summon you as consul
                    out of Africa, as we summoned Quintus Fulvius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXVI. viii-xi.</note> from Capua? <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> What of it that in Africa also the fortune of war will make
                    no distinctions? Let your own house be a warning, your father and uncle, slain
                    with their armies within thirty days, and that in a land where for some years by
                        <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> very great achievements on land and sea
                    they won a most honourable name among foreign nations for the Roman people and
                    for your family. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Time would fail me if I
                    should attempt to enumerate the kings and generals who have rashly invaded the
                    land of their enemies with disastrous defeats for themselves and their armies.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The Athenians, although their state had
                    great foresight, leaving a war at home crossed over to Sicily with a great fleet
                    under the leadership of a young man <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Alcibiades . </note> as energetic as he was
                    noble, and in a single naval battle permanently ruined their prosperous state. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Foreign examples are these that I am
                    recalling and too ancient. Let that same Africa of yours and Marcus Atilius,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Regulus; <hi rend="italics"
                            >Periocha</hi> 17 f.; Polybius I. xxv. 7 —xxxv.; Diodorus Sic. XXIII.
                        12. 15. Cf. below XXX. xxx. 23. </note> a striking example of good fortune
                    and bad, be a lesson to <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> us. Verily, Publius
                    Cornelius, when you sight Africa from the sea your <pb n="p.171"/> Spanish
                    provinces will seem to you to have been mere <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> child's <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> play. For what is there that is comparable? Over an
                    unmolested sea you sailed along the coast of Italy and Gaul, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">For this voyage cf. XXVI. xix. 11
                        ff.</note> and put in with your fleet at Emporiae, a city of our <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> allies. Landing your troops you led them through
                    country everywhere perfectly safe and reached allies and friends of the Roman
                    people at Tarraco. From Tarraco it was then a march from one Roman post to
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> another. Along the Hiberus were the armies
                    of your father and uncle, which after losing their generals had gained more
                    spirit even from disaster. Their commander also was the well-known Lucius
                    Marcius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. on xiv. 15.</note>
                    irregularly appointed, to be sure, being chosen for an emergency by vote of the
                    soldiers, but if nobility and the normal magistracies added their distinction,
                    equal to famous generals in all the arts of <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    war. (New) Carthage was taken without any interference, since none of the three
                    Punic armies came to the defence of their allies. The rest of your campaign —and
                    I do not belittle it <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> —cannot, however, be
                    compared in any way with a war in Africa, where there is no harbour open to our
                    fleet, no subjugated territory, no allied city, no friendly king, no place
                    anywhere to hold your ground, no place to advance, while wherever you look, the
                    country all about you will be hostile and dangerous. </p>
                <p> "Can it be that you trust Syphax and the Numidians? Let it suffice to have
                    trusted them <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> once. Not always is rashness
                    successful, and treachery seeks in small matters to ensure trustfulness, so that
                    when it becomes worth while, it may deceive with great profit. The enemy did not
                    overpower your father and uncle by force of arms until the Celtiberian allies
                    had done so by <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> treachery. Nor in your own case
                    was <pb n="p.173"/> there as much danger from Mago and Hasdrubal, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> generals
                    of the enemy, as from Indibilis and Mandonius, who had come under your
                    protection. Can you trust the Numidians after experiencing a mutiny of your own
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> soldiers? Both Syphax and Masinissa
                    prefer that they themselves rather than the Carthaginians should be supreme in
                    Africa, and the Carthaginians rather than anyone else. At present rivalry
                    between them and all possible reasons for contention spur them on because the
                    foreigners whom they fear are far <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> away. Show
                    them Roman arms and a foreign-born army, and now they will rush, as it were, to
                    put out a fire that concerns them <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> all. In one
                    fashion those same Carthaginians have defended Spain; in quite another fashion
                    will they defend the walls of their native city, the temples of the gods, their
                    altars and hearths, when as they go out to battle a frightened wife will escort
                    them and little children will throw themselves in their way. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> "Furthermore, what if the Carthaginians,
                    confidently relying upon the united spirit of Africa, the loyalty of the allied
                    kings, and their own walls, shall take the initiative themselves when they have
                    seen Italy stripped of protection from yourself and your <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> army? What if they either send a new army into Italy from
                    Africa, or order Mago —and it is known that he has crossed from the Balearic
                    Islands on his fleet and is already sailing along the coast held by the Alpine
                    Ligurians —to unite with <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Hannibal? Surely we
                    shall be in the same panic as we were recently when Hasdrubal crossed into Italy
                    —the man whom you, who are about to invest not merely Carthage but all Africa by
                    your army, allowed to slip out of your hands into Italy. He had been defeated by
                    you, <pb n="p.175"/> you will say; all the more do I regret —and this for <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> your own
                    sake, not merely for that of the state — that a passage into. Italy was allowed
                    to the <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> defeated. Permit us to attribute to
                    your strategy all that resulted favourably for you and the empire of the Roman
                    people, to ascribe the unfavourable to the uncertainties of war and to fortune.
                    The better and braver man you are the more do your native city and all Italy
                    keep their hold upon so capable a <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> defender.
                    You are unable even yourself to conceal the fact that where Hannibal is, there
                    is the centre and stronghold of this war, since you declare that your reason for
                    crossing over to Africa is in order to draw Hannibal thither. Therefore, be it
                    here, be it there, you will have Hannibal to deal with. </p>
                <p>
                    <quote> Will you, therefore, be stronger, pray, -in Africa when alone, or here,
                        uniting your army with that of your colleague? Do not Claudius also and
                        Livius, the consuls, by a very recent instance prove how great a difference
                        that <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> makes? And tell me, pray, will the
                        remote and secluded Bruttian territory make Hannibal stronger in arms and
                        men, when he: has long been begging in vain for auxiliaries from home, or
                        rather Carthage near at hand and all Africa her <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> ally? What is that plan of yours, to prefer to decide
                        the issue just where your forces are reduced by one-half, the forces of the
                        enemy greatly increased, rather than where two armies have to fight against
                        one exhausted by so many battles and a service so long and so <milestone
                            n="20" unit="section"/> hard? Reflect how different is your plan from
                        that of your father. He as consul had set out for Spain, but he <pb
                            n="p.177"/> returned to Italy from his province in order to meet <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                        Hannibal as he came down from the <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Alps.
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf XXI. xxxii. 1 ff.</note>
                        You, although Hannibal is in Italy, are preparing to leave Italy, not
                        because you think it to the advantage of the state, but because you hold it
                        great and glorious for yourself. It was thus that leaving province and army,
                        unauthorized by any law or decree of the senate, you, a commanding general
                        of the Roman people, entrusted to two ships the fortune of the state and
                        majesty of the empire, which were at that time endangered in your <milestone
                            n="22" unit="section"/> person. My opinion is that Publius Cornelius was
                        elected consul for the republic and for us, not for himself and his personal
                        ends, and that armies were enlisted for the defence of the city and Italy,
                        not that consuls in the arrogant manner of tyrants may transport them to
                        whatever lands they choose. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Fabius by a speech adapted to the
                    situation, but especially by his prestige and long-established reputation for
                    foresight, had stirred a large part of the senate and in particular the older
                    members, and while more were praising the wisdom of the veteran than the
                    confident spirit of the young man, Scipio is said to have spoken as follows:
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "Even Quintus Fabius himself at the
                    beginning of his speech, conscript fathers, stated that in his expression of
                    opinion captious criticism might be suspected. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Far as I should be from venturing to bring that charge against so great a man,
                    nevertheless such suspicion has certainly not been cleared away, be it the
                    speech or the subject that is at fault. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For he
                    has highly extolled his offices and the fame of his achievements <pb n="p.179"/>
                    in order to refute the charge of envy, just as if it were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> from men of the lowest
                    rank that there is danger of rivalry for me, and not rather from one who because
                    he rises above all others —a distinction towards which I do not deny that I also
                    am striving —is unwilling to have me compared with himself. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He has represented himself as an old man and one who has
                    played his part, and me as younger even than his son, just as if the desire for
                    glory <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> did not reach farther than the span of
                    human life and project in fullest measure into the memory of posterity.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of the greatest minds it is true, I am
                    sure, that they compare themselves not only with the living but with eminent men
                    in every age. For my part I do not deny, Quintus Fabius, that I wish not only to
                    attain to your fame but also —by your good leave —if possible to surpass it.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Let us not have such a spirit —you towards
                    me, I towards younger men — that we should be unwilling to have any
                    fellowcitizen come to be like us. For that would be a loss affecting, not only
                    those whom we have envied, but the state also and almost the entire human race. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "He called to mind how great a danger I should
                    encounter if I were to cross over to Africa, so that he seemed concerned for me
                    also, not merely for the state and the army. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Whence has come this sudden solicitude about me? When my father and uncle had
                    been slain, when their two armies had been all but annihilated, when the Spanish
                    provinces had been lost, when four armies of Carthaginians and four <milestone
                        n="11??" unit="section"/> generals held the whole country in the grip of
                    fear and arms, when, though sought for, no commanding general presented himself
                    for that war except myself, no one had dared to put forward his name, when the
                        <pb n="p.181"/> Roman people had bestowed upon me at the age of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                    twenty-four years its high command, why in such circumstances did no one at that
                    time call to <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> mind my youth, the might of
                    the enemy, the difficulty of the war, the recent disaster to my father and my
                    uncle? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Has some greater catastrophe now
                    befallen us in Africa than had been suffered then in Spain? Or are there now
                    larger armies in Africa and more generals and better than there were then in
                    Spain? Or was my age then riper for the conduct of war than it is now?
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Or is it more suitable to wage war with a
                    Carthaginian enemy in Spain than in Africa? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    It is easy to disparage my achievements after the rout and flight of four Punic
                    armies, after the storming of so many cities or their subjugation through fear,
                    after a thorough and complete conquest all the way to the Ocean —so many
                    princes, so many warlike nations — after the recovery of all Spain so that no
                    trace of war remains. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It will indeed be just
                    as easy if I return as a victor from Africa to disparage precisely the same
                    things which now, in order to hold me back, are magnified by the speaker to make
                    them appear terrible. </p>
                <p> "He denies that we have any access to Africa, he denies that any harbours are
                    open to us. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> He states that Marcus Atilius was
                    captured in Africa, as if Marcus Atilius met disaster upon his first landing in
                    Africa. Also he does not recall that even that unfortunate general found the
                    harbours of Africa nevertheless open to him and conducted a remarkable campaign
                    in his first year, and so far as Carthaginian generals are concerned, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The implied exception was the Spartan
                        (mercenary) general presently to be mentioned. </note> remained undefeated
                    to the end. You shall not frighten me, therefore, by the example you give.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> If that disaster had been incurred in
                    this war, not in the former war, if recently and not <pb n="p.183"/> forty years
                    ago, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> An error for fifty years. In
                        XXIX. xxviii. 5 Livy has <hi rend="italics">prope quinquaginta</hi> for the
                        actual fify-two. </note> why after Regulus' capture should I <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> hesitate
                    to cross over to Africa any more than to Spain after the Scipios had fallen?
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> I should not admit that the Spartan
                    Xanthippus' <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. Polybius I. xxxii.
                        ff., xxxvi; <hi rend="italics">Periocha</hi> 18; Diodorus Sic. XXIII. 14 f.
                    </note> birth had been more fortunate for Carthage than mine for my native city;
                    and my confidence would be increased by the mere possibility of such weight in
                    the ability of a single man. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> But we must hear
                    likewise of the Athenians, how neglecting a war at home they crossed rashly to
                    Sicily. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Why then, since you have time to tell
                    Greek tales, do you not prefer to relate how Agathocles, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For the career of this tyrant of Syracuse (died <date
                            when="-0289">289 B.C.</date> ) and his wars with the Carthaginians both
                        in Sicily and Africa v. Diodorus Sic. XX. 3-18 <hi rend="italics">et
                            passim;</hi> Justin XXII f. </note> King of Syracuse, after Sicily had
                    long been ablaze with a Punic war, crossed over into this same Africa and
                    diverted the war to the country from which it had come? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "But what is the need of calling to mind by
                    old and foreign examples what it means to make fear an offensive weapon against
                    the enemy, and removing danger from yourself to bring another into peril?
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Can there be any greater and more
                    effective example than Hannibal? A great difference it makes whether you are
                    seeing the land of others ravaged or your own being burned over and devastated.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> More spirit has an aggressor than a
                    defender. Besides there is greater dread of things unknown; on entering the
                    territory of the enemy you have a near view of their advantages and
                    disadvantages. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal had not hoped that so
                    many states in Italy would come over to his side as did so after the <pb
                        n="p.185"/> disaster at Cannae. How much less is anything in <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> Africa to
                    be strong and steadfast for the Carthaginians, faithless as allies, oppressive
                    and arrogant as masters! <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Furthermore, even
                    when deserted by our allies, we kept our footing by our own forces, our Roman
                    soldiers. The Carthaginians have no forces of their own citizens. They have
                    mercenaries, Africans and Numidians, very inconstant by nature and ready to
                    change their allegiance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If only there is no
                    delay here, at the same moment you will hear that I have crossed and that Africa
                    is ablaze with war, and Hannibal casting off from here, and Carthage blockaded.
                    Look for more cheering news from Africa and more frequent than you used to
                    receive from Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Inspiring these hopes in
                    me are the fortune of the Roman people, the gods who witnessed the treaty
                    violated by the enemy, the kings, Syphax and Masinissa, on whose honour I shall
                    rely —but so as to be well protected against treachery. </p>
                <p> "Many things which, owing to distance, are not now evident the war will reveal.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is the part of a man and a general not
                    to prove wanting when fortune presents herself, and to fit what is offered by
                    chance into his plan. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I shall have Hannibal as
                    the antagonist you assign me, Quintus Fabius; but I shall draw him after me, not
                    let him hold me back. In his own land will I compel him to fight, and Carthage
                    is to be the reward of victory, not the half-ruined strongholds of the
                    Bruttians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Meantime, while I am crossing
                    over, while landing my army in Africa, while moving my camp up to Carthage, let
                    the republic suffer no harm here. That service you, Quintus Fabius, were able to
                    guarantee while everywhere in Italy the victorious <pb n="p.187"/> Hannibal
                    flitted about. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Would it not be insulting,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> with
                    Hannibal now shaken and almost broken, to claim that Publius Licinius, the
                    consul —a very brave man who took no part in the allotment of so distant a
                    province, solely that as pontifex maximus he might not be absent from religious
                    ceremonies —cannot do the same? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If in truth
                    the war were not completed any more promptly by the method which I propose, it
                    would nevertheless conduce to the dignity of the Roman people and its reputation
                    among kings and foreign nations to let it be seen that we have the spirit not
                    only to defend Italy but also to invade Africa. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> Likewise not to have it believed and published abroad that what Hannibal has
                    dared no Roman general dares, and that in the former Punic war, at a time when
                    the stake was Sicily, Africa was attacked so many times by our armies and
                    fleets, but that now, when Italy is the stake, Africa is at peace. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Let Italy, so long harried, at length have rest; let
                    Africa in turn be burned over and laid waste. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Let Roman camps threaten the gates of Carthage; better so than that we should
                    see the enemy's earthworks from our walls for the second time. Let Africa be the
                    theatre of the remainder of the war. In that direction may terror and flight be
                    diverted, the devastation also of farms, the desertion of allies, and the other
                    calamities of war which for fourteen years have assailed us. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> It is enough to have spoken of matters concerning the state and the war
                        now in progress and the provinces which are in question. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> A long speech it would be and one of no concern to you
                        senators if, after the manner in which Quintus Fabius has disparaged my
                        achievements in Spain, I on my part should be <pb n="p.189"/> minded to
                        scoff at his fame and to enlarge upon my <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> own. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> I will do neither, conscript fathers, and if in no
                        other respect, in modesty at least and in control of my tongue I, who am
                        young, will outstrip the older man. Such have been my life and achievements
                        that, although silent, I am quite content with the opinion which of your own
                        accord you have formed and retain. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio met with a less favourable hearing
                    because it had been generally reported that, if he should not carry his point in
                    the senate and have Africa decreed him as his province, he would at once bring a
                    bill before the people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And so Quintus
                    Fulvius, who had been consul four times and censor, demanded of the consul that
                    he should frankly state in the senate whether he would permit the senators to
                    make a decree in regard to the provinces and would stand by their vote, or was
                    intending to bring a bill before the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When Scipio replied that he would act for the best interests of the state,
                    Fulvius said: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> I was not unaware, when I asked my question, of the answer you would
                        give or of what you would do, since you make it plain that you are sounding
                        the senate rather than consulting it, and since, unless we at once decree
                        for you the province which you have desired, you have a bill ready.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly, tribunes of the people
                    </quote> he said <quote> I demand of you that you come to my defence if I
                        decline to express an opinion for the reason that, even in case our vote by
                        division should favour a motion of mine, the consul will not consider it
                        valid. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then arose a dispute, the consul maintaining
                    that it was not right for the tribunes to use their veto to excuse a senator
                    from stating his opinion when called upon in his regular <pb n="p.191"/> order.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The tribunes made this decree: <quote> If
                        the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                        consul permits the senate to assign the provinces, we decide that he must
                        stand by the vote of the senate, and we will not allow a bill touching that
                        matter to be brought before the people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If
                        he does not permit, we will come to the defence of a man who refuses to
                        express an opinion on that matter. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This decree so fortified the
                        opposition that Scipio was unable to risk a vote referring the question to
                        the people. </note>
                </p>
                <p> The consul begged for one day to confer with his colleague; on the next day he
                    gave the senate his permission. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The provinces
                    were assigned by decree as follows: to one of the consuls Sicily and the thirty
                    war-ships <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A small fleet in comparison
                        with the hundred ships assigned to Sicily in <date when="-0208">208
                            B.C.</date> ; XXVII. xxii. 9. For an invasion a much larger navy would
                        seem to be required. Add the 30 new ships presently to be built (§ 21). But
                        actually only 40 war-ships escorted 400 transports in <date when="-0204">204
                            B.C.</date> ; XXIX. xxvi. 3. </note> which Gius Servilius had commanded
                    in the previous year; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. x.
                        16.</note> and permission to cross over to Africa was given, if he should
                    consider that to be to the advantage of the state; to the other consul the land
                    of the Bruttians and the war with Hannibal, together with the army which he
                    preferred. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> of the two in that region; cf. x. 10; xi. 12;
                        xlvi. 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Lucius Veturius and Quintus Caecilius were to
                    decide between them by lot or by arrangement which of them was to wage war in
                    the Bruttian land with the two legions which the <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> consul should leave there, and whichever should have that
                    province assigned to him was to have his command continued for one year.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And for the rest who were to command
                    armies and provinces —apart from consuls and praetors —their commands were
                    continued. It fell to Quintus Caecilius by lot to wage war together with the
                    consul in the Bruttian land against Hannibal. </p>
                <pb n="p.193"/>
                <p> Scipio's games were then held with great crowds <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> and great approval on the
                    part of the spectators. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As ambassadors Marcus
                    Pomponius Matho and Quintus Catius were sent to Delphi to carry a gift from the
                    spoils of Hasdrubal. They took a golden wreath weighing two hundred pounds and
                    representations of spoils <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Doubtless
                        in the form of trophies, possibly a pair of them, to flank the golden
                        wreath, presumably to be set up in one of the treasure houses. At XXIII. xi.
                        3 Apollo had bidden them send a gift when they had preserved their state. So
                        Fabius Pictor, the Roman ambassador, had reported in <date when="-0216">216
                            B.C.</date>
                    </note> made of a thousand pounds of silver. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Although he had neither gained consent to
                    hold a levy, nor had been especially insistent, Scipio obtained permission to
                    take volunteers and to receive whatever should be given by the allies towards
                    the construction of new ships, —this because he had stated that the fleet would
                    not be an expense to the state. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> First the
                    Etruscan communities promised that they would aid the consul, each according to
                    its own resources. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The men of Caere promised
                    grain for the crews and supplies of every kind, the men of Populonium <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> f. XXX. xxxix. 2; now Piombino, the
                        nearest port to Elba. Usually Populonia, but Polybius and Strabo use the
                        neuter (P. at XXXIV. xi. 3; S. at V. ii. 5 f., 8). So also the <hi
                            rend="italics">Itin. Ant.</hi>
                    </note> iron, Tarquinii linen for sails, Volaterrae the interior fittings of
                    ships, also grain. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Arretium promised three
                    thousand shields, an equal number of helmets; and that they would furnish a
                    total of fifty thousand javelins, short spears and lances, with an equal
                    proportion of each type; also axes, shovels, sickles, baskets and hand-mills, as
                    many as were needed for forty war-ships; <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> a
                    hundred and twenty thousand pecks of wheat also; and that they would contribute
                    allowances <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In addition to their
                        pay.</note> for petty officers and oarsmen. Perusia, Clusium and Rusellae
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Beyond the Umbro and near
                        Vetulonia; X. iv. 5; xxxvii.</note> promised fir for shipbuilding and a
                    great quantity of grain. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> He <pb n="p.195"/>
                    used fir also from forests belonging to the state. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> The communities of Umbria
                    and in addition Nursia and Reate and Amiternum and the whole Sabine district
                    promised soldiers. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Marsians, Paelignians and
                    Marrucini in large numbers gave in their names as volunteers for the fleet.
                        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Camerinum, although it treated with the
                    Romans on an equal footing, sent an armed cohort of six hundred men. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> just as if they were allies and hence bound to
                        furnish troops. </note> After thirty keels had been laid down, twenty
                    quinqueremes and ten quadriremes, Scipio so pushed the work that on the
                    forty-fifth day after the timber had been brought from the forests the ships,
                    rigged and equipped, were launched. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He set out for Sicily on thirty war-ships
                    after embarking some seven thousand volunteers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> And Publius Licinius came to the two consular armies in the land of the
                    Bruttians. Of these he took the army which Lucius Veturius had commanded as
                    consul. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He allowed Metellus to command the
                    same legions which he had previously commanded, for he thought Metellus would
                    more easily carry on the war with men accustomed to his authority. The praetors
                    also set out in different directions to their provinces. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And because there was a lack of money for the war the
                    quaestors were ordered to sell a region of Campania extending from the Fossa
                    Graeca <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Near Cumae and probably dug by
                        that city long before to drain marshy lowlands near the sea; cf. XXII. xvi.
                        4, Not far away was Liternum, where Scipio Africanus later lived in
                        retirement at his villa, described by Seneca <hi rend="italics">Ep.</hi> 86,
                        1-12; cf. Val. Max. II. x. 2; and there was his tomb; Seneca <hi
                            rend="italics">l.c.</hi>
                    </note> to the sea, it being permitted also to give information as to any land
                    which had belonged to a Campanian citizen, so that it might become public land
                    of the Roman people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For the informant
                    one-tenth of the price of the land <pb n="p.197"/> reported was established as a
                    reward. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And to <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> Gnaeus Servilius, the city
                    praetor, was assigned the task of seeing to it that Campanian citizens should
                    dwell only where in accordance with a decree of the senate it was permitted them
                    severally to dwell, and of punishing those who were dwelling elsewhere. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the same summer Mago the son of Hamilcar
                    embarked upon his fleet picked young men from the smaller of the Balearic
                    Islands, where he had wintered, and brought across to Italy on some thirty
                    war-ships and many transports twelve thousand infantry and about two thousand
                    cavalry. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Upon his sudden arrival he also
                    captured Genua, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On the Ligurian
                        coast; cf. XXI. xxxii. 5, the first appearance of Genoa in history; XXIX. v.
                        2. Destroyed by Mago and rebuilt by Spurius Lucretius, XXX. i. 10. </note>
                    since no forces were guarding the sea-coast. Then he put in with his fleet to
                    the coast belonging to the Alpine <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Western; see note on Savo below. </note>
                    Ligurians, in the hope of causing some uprising there. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The Ingauni, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf.
                        XXIX. <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi> Their town was a seaport, Album Ingaunum
                        or Albingaunum, now Albenga; Strabo IV. vi. 1; Mela II. 72; Tacitus <hi
                            rend="italics">Hist.</hi> II. 15 <hi rend="italics">fin.</hi> The
                        Epanterii were above them on the slopes of the coast range (Alpes
                        Maritimae). </note> a Ligurian tribe, were at that time carrying on a war
                    with the Epanterii Montani. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly the
                    Carthaginian, depositing his plunder at Savo, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Now Savona, 27 miles west of Genoa. Though a seaport it
                        is an <hi rend="italics">oppidum Alpinum</hi> as lying at the foot of the
                        Maritime Alps. Eastward of Savona is another coast range; a part of the
                        Apennines. On the dividing line between the two, cf. Strabo <hi
                            rend="italics">l.c.</hi> and V. i. 3; also Decimus Brutus writing to
                        Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Ep.</hi> XI. xiii. 2. For Vada Sabat(i)a, now
                        Vado, west of Savo, of. XXIX. v. 2, note; Strabo <hi rend="italics">I.
                            e.;</hi> Mela l. c. j Pliny <hi rend="italics">N. H.</hi> III. 48; <hi
                            rend="italics">Itin. Ant.</hi> 295. </note> a town at the foot of the
                    Alps, and leaving ten war-ships at anchor to protect it, sent the rest to
                    Carthage to defend the sea-coast, because there was a report that Scipio would
                    cross over. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Mago himself made an alliance
                    with the Ingauni, whose friendship he preferred, and set about attacking the
                    Montani. And his army was daily increasing because the Gauls <pb n="p.199"/> on
                    hearing his name flocked together from all sides. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This fact, when it was made known to the
                    senators through a letter of Spurius Lucretius, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. xxxviii. 11, 13; XXX. i. 9 f.</note> kindled great
                    anxiety among them, for fear they had rejoiced in vain two years before over the
                    destruction of Hasdrubal and his army, if another equally serious war with only
                    a change of commander should break out from that quarter. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> So they ordered Marcus Livius, the proconsul, to bring his
                    army of slave-volunteers from Etruria to Ariminum. Also they assigned to Gnaeus
                    Servilius, the praetor, if he thought it to the advantage of the state, the duty
                    of appointing at his discretion a commander for the two city legions and
                    ordering them to be brought up from the city. Marcus Valerius Laevinus brought
                    these legions to Arretium. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Just at that time about eighty Carthaginian
                    transports were captured off Sardinia by Gnaeus Octavius, who was in command of
                    that province. Coelius states that they were laden with grain sent to Hannibal
                    and with provisions, Valerius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Antias;
                        cf. Vol. VI. p. 492, n. 2; VII. pp. 24, n. 1 and 187. For Coelius cf. VI. p.
                        183, n. 2; VII. pp. 41, 323. </note> that they were captured while carrying
                    Etruscan booty and captive Ligurians and Montani to Carthage. In the land of the
                    Bruttians virtually nothing notable was done that year. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> An epidemic, equally disastrous to both, had attacked
                    Romans and Carthaginians, with this difference that in addition to disease
                    hunger also weakened the Carthaginian army. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Hannibal spent the summer near the temple of Juno Lacinia, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Cf. Vol. VI. pp. 115, n., 182 f., notes (especially in
                        reference to the inscription); VII. p. 315. The promontory took its name
                        from <foreign xml:lang="greek">nao/s,</foreign> temple, and is still Capo
                        Nao (or delle Colonne). </note> and there he erected an altar and dedicated
                    it together with a great record of his achievements in a Punic and Greek
                    inscription. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
