<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six -
                    31</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to
                                thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXXI.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Renewal of the war with Philip, king of Macedon. Successes of Publius
                        Sulpicius, consul, who had the conduct of that war. The Abydenians, besieged
                        by Philip, put themselves to death, together with their wives and children.
                        Lucius Furius, praetor, defeats the Insubrian Gauls who had revolted; and
                        Hamilcar, who stirred up the insurrection, is slain, with thirty-five
                        thousand men. Further operations of Sulpicius, Attalus, and the Rhodians
                        against Philip. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> IT is delightful even to me to have come to
                    the end of the Punic war, as if I myself had borne a share of the toil and
                    danger. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For though it by no means becomes a
                    person, who has ventured to promise an entire history of all the Roman affairs,
                    to be fatigued by any particular parts of so extensive a <pb n="1342"
                        xml:id="p.1342"/> work; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> yet when I reflect
                    that sixty-three years (for so many there are from the first Punic war to the
                    end of the second) have occupied as many of my <milestone n="4??" unit="section"
                    /> volumes, as the four hundred and eighty-seven years, from the building of the
                    city to the consulate of Appius Claudius, who first made war on the
                    Carthaginians, I plainly perceive that, like those who, tempted by the shallows
                    near the shore, walk into the sea, the farther I advance, I am carried, as it
                    were, into a greater depth and abyss; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and that
                    my work almost increases on my hands, which seemed to be diminished by the
                    completion of each of its earlier portions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The peace with Carthage was quickly followed by a war with Macedonia: a war, not
                    to be compared to the former, indeed, either in danger, or in the abilities of
                    the commander, or the valour of the soldiers; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    but almost more remarkable with regard to the renown of their former kings, the
                    ancient fame of that nation, and the vast extent of their empire, in which they
                    had formerly comprehended a large part of Europe, and the greater part of Asia.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The contest with Philip, which had begun
                    about ten years before, had been intermitted for the three last years; the
                    Aetolians having been the occasion both of the war and the peace. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The entreaties of the Athenians whom, having ravaged
                    their lands, Philip had driven into their city, excited the Romans to a renewal
                    of the war, left, as they were, disengaged by the Carthaginian peace, and
                    incensed against him as well for his treacherous negotiation of peace <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> with the Aetolians and the other allies in that
                    region, as on account of the auxiliaries sent by him with money into Africa to
                    Hannibal and the Carthaginians. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time, ambassadors arrived both
                    from king Attalus, and from the Rhodians, with information that the Macedonian
                    was tampering with the states of Asia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To
                    these embassies an answer was given, that the senate would give attention to the
                    affairs of Asia. The determination with regard to the making war on him, was
                    left open to the consuls, who were then in their provinces. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In the mean time, three ambassadors were sent to Ptolemy,
                    king of Egypt, namely, Caius Claudius Nero, Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, and Publius
                    Sempronius Tuditanus, to announce their conquest of Hannibal and the
                    Carthaginians; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> to give thanks to the king for
                    his faithful adherence to his engagements in the time of <pb n="1343"
                        xml:id="p.1343"/> their distress, when even the nearest allies of the Romans
                    abandoned them; and to request that if, compelled by ill treatment, they should
                    undertake a war with Philip, he would preserve his former disposition towards
                    the Roman people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In Gaul, about this time,
                    the consul, Publius Aelius, having heard that, before his arrival, the Boians
                    had made inroads on the territories of the allies, levied two occasional legions
                    on account of this disturbance; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and adding to
                    them four cohorts from his own army, ordered Caius Oppius, the prefect, to march
                    with this tumultuary band through Umbria, (which is called the Sappinian
                    district,) and to invade the territories of the Boians. He himself led his own
                    troops thither openly, over the intervening mountains. Oppius, on entering the
                    same, for some time committed depredations with tolerable success and safety.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But afterwards, having pitched on a place
                    near a fort called Mutilum, convenient enough for cutting down the corn, (for
                    the crops were now ripe,) and setting out without having reconnoitred around,
                    and without establishing armed posts of sufficient strength to protect those who
                    were unarmed and intent on their work, he was suddenly surrounded, together with
                    his foragers, by an unexpected invasion of the Gauls. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> On this, panic and flight seized even on those who were
                    furnished with weapons. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Seven thousand men,
                    dispersed through the corn fields, were put to the sword, among whom was the
                    commander himself, Caius Oppius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The rest
                    were driven by terror into the camp; from whence, in consequence of a resolution
                    of the soldiers, they set out on the following night, without any particular
                    commander; and, leaving behind a great part of their baggage, made their way,
                    through woods almost impassable, to the consul, who returned <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> to Rome without having performed any thing in his province
                    worth notice, except that he ravaged the lands of the Boians, and made a treaty
                    with the Ingaunian Ligurians. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first time he assembled the senate, it was
                    unanimously ordered that he should propose no other business before that which
                    related to Philip and the complaints of the allies. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It was immediately taken into consideration, and a numerous
                    senate decreed, that Publius Aelius, consul, should send such person as he might
                    think proper, vested with command, to <pb n="1344" xml:id="p.1344"/> receive the
                    fleet which Cneius Octavius was bringing home from Sicily, and pass over to
                    Macedonia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, Marcus Valerius
                    Laevinus, propraetor, was sent; and, receiving thirty-eight ships from Cneius
                    Octavius, near Vibo, he sailed to Macedonia, where, when Marcus Aurelius, the
                    ambassador, had <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> come to him and informed him
                    what numerous forces and what large fleets the king had prepared, and how
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> he was arousing the inhabitants to arms,
                    partly by visiting them himself and partly by ambassadors, not only through all
                    the cities of the continent, but even in the islands, (Laevinus was convinced)
                    that the war ought to be undertaken by the Romans with greater vigour;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> lest, if they were dilatory, Philip might
                    attempt that which had been formerly undertaken by Pyrrhus, who possessed not
                    such large dominions. He therefore desired Aurelius to convey this intelligence
                    by letter to the consuls and to the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Towards the end of this year the senate,
                    taking into consideration the lands to be given to the veteran soldiers, who,
                    under the conduct and auspices of Publius Scipio, had finished the war in
                    Africa, decreed that <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Marcus Tunius, praetor
                    of the city, should, if he thought proper, appoint ten commissioners to survey,
                    and distribute among them, that part of the Samnite and Apulian lands which was
                    the property of the Roman people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For this
                    purpose were appointed, Publius Servilius, Quintus Caecilius Metellus, Caius and
                    Marcus Servilius, both surnamed Geminus, Lucius and Aulus Hostilius Cato,
                    Publius Villius Tappulus, Marcus Fulvius Flaccus, Publius Aelius Paetus, and
                    Quintus Flaminius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the same time, Publius
                    Aelius presiding at the election of consuls, Publius Sulpicius Galba and Caius
                    Aurelius Cotta were elected. Then were chosen praetors, Quintus Minucius Rufus,
                    Lucius Furius Purpureo, Quintus Fulvius Gillo, Cneius Sergius Plancus.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman stage-games were exhibited, in a
                    sumptuous and elegant manner, by the curule aediles, Lucius Valerius Flaccus,
                    and Lucius Quintius Flaminius, and repeated for two days; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and a vast quantity of corn, which Scipio had sent from
                    Africa, was distributed by them to the people, with strict impartiality and
                    general satisfaction, at the rate of four <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> a peck.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The plebeian games were thrice repeated
                    entire by the plebeian aediles, Lucius Apustius <pb n="1345" xml:id="p.1345"/>
                    Fullo, and Quintus Minucius Rufus; the latter of whom was, from the aedileship,
                    elected praetor. There was also a feast of Jove on occasion of the games. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the year five hundred and fifty-two from
                    the building of the city, Publius Sulpicius Galba and Caius Aurelius being
                    consuls, within a few months after the conclusion of the peace with the
                    Carthaginians, the war was entered upon against king Philip. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This was the first business introduced by the consul,
                    Publius Sulpicius, on the ides of March, the day on which, in those times, the
                    consulship commenced; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and the senate decreed,
                    that the consul should perform sacrifices with the greater victims, to such gods
                    as they should judge proper, with prayers to this purpose, —that <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> the business which the senate and people of Rome had then under
                        deliberation, concerning the state, and the entering on a new war, might
                        issue prosperously and happily to the Roman people, the allies, and the
                        Latin confederacy; </quote> and that, after the sacrifices and prayers, they
                    should consult the senate on the state of public affairs, and the provinces.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At this time, very opportunely for
                    exciting their minds to war, the letters were brought from Marcus Aurelius, the
                    ambassador, and Marcus Valerius Laevinus, proprietor. A fresh embassy, likewise,
                    arrived from the Athenians, to acquaint them that the king was approaching their
                    frontiers, and that in a short time, not only their lands, but their city also,
                    must fall into his hands, unless they received aid from the Romans. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> When the consuls had made their report, that the
                    sacrifices had been duly performed, and that the gods had accepted their
                    prayers; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that the aruspices had declared that
                    the entrails showed good omens, and that enlargement of territory, victory, and
                    triumph were portended; the letters of Valerius and Aurelius were read, and
                    audience given to the ambassadors of the Athenians. After which, a decree of the
                    senate was passed, that thanks should be given to their allies, because, though
                    long solicited, they had not, even when in fear of a siege, renounced their
                    fidelity. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With regard to sending assistance to
                    them, they resolved, that an answer should be given as soon as the consuls
                    should have cast lots for the provinces; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and
                    when the consul to whose lot Macedonia fell should have proposed to the people,
                    that war should be declared against Philip, king of the Macedonians <pb n="1346"
                        xml:id="p.1346"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The province of Macedonia fell by lot to
                    Publius Sulpicius; and he proposed to the people to declare, <quote> that they
                        chose and ordered, that on account of the injuries and hostilities committed
                        against the allies of the Roman people, war should be proclaimed against
                        king Philip, and the Macedonians under his government. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The province of Italy fell to the lot of the
                    other consul, Aurelius. The praetors then cast lots: to Cneius Sergius Plancus
                    fell the city jurisdiction; to Quintus Fulvius Gillo, Sicily; to Quintus
                    Minucius Rufus, Bruttium; and to Lucius Furius Purpureo, Gaul. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> At the first meeting of the people, the proposal concerning
                    the Macedonian war was rejected by almost all the tribes. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This was done partly spontaneously, as the people were
                    wearied by the length and severity of the late war, and disgusted with toils and
                    dangers; and partly by Quintus Baebius, tribune of the people, who, pursuing the
                    old practice of criminating the patricians, charged them with multiplying wars
                    one after another, so that the people could never enjoy peace. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This proceeding the patricians with difficulty brooked, and
                    the tribune was severely reprehended in the senate; where each severally urged
                    the consul to call a new assembly, for passing the proposal; to rebuke the
                    backwardness of the people; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and to prove to
                    them how much loss and disgrace the delay of this war would occasion. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, having assembled the people in the
                    field of Mars, before he dismissed the centuries to the vote, required their
                    attention, and addressed them thus: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Citizens, you seem to me not to understand that the question before you
                        is not whether you choose to have peace or war: for Philip, having already
                        commenced hostilities with a formidable force, both on land and sea, allows
                        you not that option. The question is, Whether you must transport your
                        legions to Macedonia, or admit the enemy into Italy? <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> How important the difference is, if you never
                        experienced it before, you certainly did in the late Punic war. For who
                        entertains a doubt, but if, when the Saguntines were besieged, and implored
                        our protection, we had assisted them with vigour, as our fathers did the
                        Mamertines, we should have averted the whole weight of the war upon Spain;
                        which, by our dilatory proceedings, we suffered to our extreme loss to fall
                        upon Italy? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor does it admit a doubt,
                        that we confined this same Philip in Mace- <pb n="1347" xml:id="p.1347"/>
                        donia, (after he had entered into an engagement with Hannibal, by
                        ambassadors and letters, to cross over into Italy,) by sending Laevinus with
                        a fleet to make war aggressively upon him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        And what we did at that time, when we had Hannibal to contend with in Italy,
                        do we hesitate to do now, after Hannibal has been expelled Italy, and the
                        Carthaginians subdued? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Suppose that we
                        allow the king to experience the same inactivity on our part, while he is
                        taking Athens, as we suffered Hannibal to experience while he was taking
                        Saguntum: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> it will not be in the fifth
                        month, as Hannibal came from Saguntum, but on the fifth day after he sets
                        sail from Corinth, that he will arrive in Italy. Perhaps you may not
                        consider Philip as equal to Hannibal; or the Macedonians to the
                        Carthaginians: certainly, however, you will allow him equal to Pyrrhus.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Equal, do I say? what a vast
                        superiority has the one man over the other, the one nation over the other!
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Epirus ever was, and is at this day,
                        deemed but an inconsiderable accession to the kingdom of Macedonia. Philip
                        has the entire Peloponnesus under his dominion; even Argos itself, not more
                        celebrated for its ancient glory than for the death of Pyrrhus. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Now compare our situation. How much more
                        flourishing was Italy, how much greater its strength, with so many
                        commanders, so many armies unimpaired, which the Punic war afterwards
                        consumed, when Pyrrhus attacked and shook it, and advanced victorious almost
                        to the Roman capital! <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and not the
                        Tarentines only, and the inhabitants of that tract of Italy which they call
                        the greater Greece, whom you may suppose to have been led by the similarity
                        of language and name, but the Lucanian, the Bruttian, and the Samnite
                        revolted from us. Do you believe that these would continue quiet and
                        faithful, if Philip should come over to Italy? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> They subsequently continued faithful, forsooth, during
                        the Punic war! Be assured those states will never fail to revolt from us,
                        except when there is no one to whom they can go over. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> If you had been annoyed at passing into Africa, you
                        would this day have had Hannibal and the Carthaginians to contend with in
                        Italy. Let Macedonia, rather than Italy, be the seat of war. Let the cities
                        and lands of the enemy be wasted with fire and sword. We have already found
                        by experience, that our arms are more powerful and more successful abroad
                        than at home. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Go to the vote with the
                        blessing <pb n="1348" xml:id="p.1348"/> of the gods; and what the senate
                        have voted, do you ratify by your order. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        This resolution is recommended to you, not only by your consul, but even by
                        the immortal gods themselves; who, when I offered sacrifice, and prayed that
                        the issue of this war might be happy and prosperous to me and to the senate,
                        to you and the allies and Latin confederates, to our fleets and armies,
                        portended all joyful and prosperous results. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this speech of Sulpicius, being sent to
                    give their votes, they declared for the war as he had proposed. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> On which, in pursuance of a decree of the senate, a
                    supplication for three days was proclaimed by the consuls; and prayers were
                    offered to the gods at all the shrines, that the war which the people had
                    ordered against Philip might turn out well and happily. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The consul Sulpicius inquiring of the heralds, whether they
                    would direct the declaration of the war against king Philip to be made to
                    himself in person, or whether it would be sufficient to publish it in the
                    nearest garrison, within the frontiers of his kingdom, they answered, that they
                    would do rightly whichever course they should adopt. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The consul received authority from the senate to send any
                    person whom he thought proper, not being a senator, as ambassador, to denounce
                    war against the king. They then arranged for the armies of the consuls and
                    praetors. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls were ordered to levy two
                    legions, and to disband the veteran troops. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Sulpicius, to whom the management of this new and highly important war had been
                    decreed, was allowed permission to carry with him as many volunteers as he could
                    procure out of the army which Publius Scipio had brought home from Africa; but
                    he was not empowered to take with him any veteran soldier against his will.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They ordered that the consul should give
                    to the praetors, Lucius Furius Purpureo and Quintus Minucius Rufus, five
                    thousand of the allies of the Latin confederacy; with which forces they should
                    hold, one, the province of Gaul, the other, Bruttium. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Gillo was ordered, in like manner, to
                    select out of the army which Publius Aelius, late consul, had commanded, such as
                    had been the shortest time in the service, until he also made up five thousand
                    of the allies and Latin confederates; that this was to be the protection of the
                    province of Sicily. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To Marcus Valerius Falto,
                    who, during the former year, had held the province of Campania, as praetor, the
                    command was continued <pb n="1349" xml:id="p.1349"/> for a year; <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> in order that he might go over, as propraetor, to
                    Sardinia, and choose out of the army there five thousand of the allies of the
                    Latin confederacy, who had served the fewest campaigns. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls were at the same time ordered to levy two
                    legions for the city, which might be sent wherever occasions should require; as
                    there were many states in Italy infected with an attachment to the
                    Carthaginians, which they had formed during the war, and, in consequence,
                    swelling with resentment. The state was to employ during that year six Roman
                    legions. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the midst of the preparations for war,
                    ambassadors came from king Ptolemy, who delivered a message; that <quote> the
                        Athenians had petitioned the king for aid against Philip; <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> but that although they were their common allies, yet
                        the king would not, except with the sanction of the Roman people, send
                        either fleet or army into Greece, for the purpose of defending or attacking
                        any person. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That he would either remain
                        quiet in his kingdom, if the Romans were at leisure to protect their allies;
                        or, if more agreeable to them to be at rest, would himself send such aid as
                        might easily secure Athens against Philip. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thanks were returned to the king by the
                    senate, and this answer: that <quote> it was the intention of the Roman people
                        to protect their allies; that if they should have occasion for any
                        assistance towards carrying on the war, they would acquaint the king; and
                        that they were fully sensible, that the resources of his kingdom were the
                        sure and faithful support of their own state. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Presents were then, by order of the senate,
                    sent to the ambassadors, of five thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 16 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 1 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to each. While the consuls were engaged in the levy, and preparing what
                    was necessary for the war, the people, prone to religious observances,
                    especially <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> at the beginning of new wars,
                    after supplications had been already performed, and prayers offered up at all
                    the shrines, lest any thing should be omitted that had ever been practised,
                    ordered, that the consul who was to have the province of Macedonia should vow
                    games and a present to Jove. Licinius, the chief pontiff, occasioned some delay
                    to this public vow, alleging, that <quote> it ought not to be fulfilled from
                        promiscuous funds. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For as the sum to be
                        named could not be applied to the uses of the war, it should be immediately
                        set apart, and not to be intermixed with other money; <pb n="1350"
                            xml:id="p.1350"/> and that, unless this were done, the vow could not be
                        properly performed. </quote> Although the objection and the author of it
                    were influential, yet the consul was ordered to consult the college of pontiffs,
                    whether a vow could be undertaken at an indeterminate expense? <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The pontiffs determined, that it could; and that it would
                    be even more in order to do it in that way. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, therefore, repeating after the chief pontiff, made the vow in the
                    same words in which those made for five years of safety used to be expressed;
                    only that he engaged to perform the games, and make the offerings, at such
                    expense as the senate should direct by their vote, at the time when the vow was
                    performed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Before this, the great games, so
                    often vowed, were constantly rated at a certain expense: these first at an
                    unspecified amount. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While every one's attention was turned to the
                    Macedonian war, and at a time when people apprehended nothing less, a sudden
                    account was brought of an inroad of the Gauls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The Insubrians, Canomanians, and Boians, having been joined by the Salyans,
                    Ilvatians, and other Ligurian states, and putting themselves under the command
                    of Hamilcar, a Carthaginian, who, having been in the army of Hasdrubal, had
                    remained in those parts, had fallen upon Placentia; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and, after plundering the city, and, in their rage, burning
                    a great part of it, leaving scarcely two thousand men among the flames and
                    ruins, passed the Po, and advanced to plunder Cremona. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The news of the calamity which had fallen on a city in
                    their neighbourhood, having reached thither, the inhabitants had time to shut
                    their gates, and place guards on the walls, that they might, at least, be
                    besieged before they were taken, and send messengers to the Roman praetor.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Lucius Furius Purpureo, who had then the
                    command of the province, had, in pursuance of the decree of the senate,
                    disbanded the army, excepting five thousand of the allies and Latin confederacy;
                    and had remained, with these troops, in the nearest district of the province
                    about Ariminum. He immediately informed the senate, by letter, in what confusion
                    the province was. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That, <quote> of the two
                        colonies which had escaped in the dreadful storm of the Punic war, one was
                        taken and sacked by the present enemy, and the other besieged. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Nor was his army capable of affording sufficient
                        protection to the distressed colonists, unless he chose to expose five
                        thousand allies to be slaughtered by forty thousand <pb n="1351"
                            xml:id="p.1351"/> invaders (for so many there were in arms); and by such
                        a loss, on his side, to augment the courage of the enemy, already elated on
                        having destroyed one Roman colony. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This letter having been read they decreed,
                    that the consul Aurelius should order the army which he had appointed to
                    assemble on a certain day in Etruria, to attend him on the same day at Ariminum;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and should either go in person, if the
                    public business would permit, to suppress the tumult of the Gauls, or write to
                    the praetor Lucius Furius, that, as soon as <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    the legions from Etruria came to him, he should send five thousand of the allies
                    to guard that place in the mean time, and should himself proceed to relieve the
                    colony from the siege. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They also determined,
                    that ambassadors should be sent to Carthage, and also into Numidia, to
                    Masinissa: to Carthage, to announce that <quote> their countryman, Hamilcar,
                        having been left in Gaul, (either with a part of the army formerly commanded
                        by Hasdrubal, or with that of Mago —they <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        did not with certainty know which,) was waging war, contrary to the treaty.
                        That he had excited the armies of the Gauls and Ligurians to arms against
                        the Roman people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That, if they wished for
                        peace, they must recall him, and give him up to the Roman people. </quote>
                    They were ordered at the same time to tell them, that <quote> all the deserters
                        had not been sent back; that a great part of them were said to appear openly
                        in Carthage, who ought to be sought after, and surrendered according to the
                        treaty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such was the message to the Carthaginians. To
                    Masinissa they were charged with congratulations, on his <quote> having not only
                        recovered the kingdom of his father, but enlarged it by the acquisition of
                        the most flourishing parts of Syphax's territories. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were ordered also to acquaint him, that
                        <quote> a war had been undertaken against Philip, because he had given aid
                        to <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the Carthaginians, while, by the
                        injuries which he offered to the allies of the Roman people, he had obliged
                        them to send fleets and armies into Greece, while Italy was blazing with
                        war; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that by thus making them
                        separate their forces, had been the principal cause of their being so late
                        passing over into Africa; and to request him to send to that war supplies of
                        Numidian horsemen. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Ample presents were given them to be carried
                    to the king; vases of gold and silver, a purple robe, and a tunic adorned with
                    palms of purple, an ivory sceptre, and a robe of state, with a curule <pb
                        n="1352" xml:id="p.1352"/> chair. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They
                    were also directed to assure him, that if he deemed any thing further requisite
                    to confirm and enlarge his kingdom, the Roman people, in return for his good
                    services, would exert their utmost zeal to effect it. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> At this time, too, ambassadors from Vermina, son of Syphax,
                    came to the senate apologizing for his mistaken conduct, on account of his youth
                    and want of judgment, and throwing all the blame on the deceitful policy of the
                    Carthaginians: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> adding, that as Masinissa had
                    from an enemy become a friend to the Romans, so Vermina would also use his best
                    endeavours that he should not be outdone in offices of friendship to the Roman
                    people, either by Masinissa, or by any other; and requesting that he might
                    receive from the senate the title of king, friend, and ally." <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> The answer given to these ambassadors was, that <quote> not
                        only his father Syphax, from a friend and ally, had on a sudden, without any
                        reason, become an enemy to the Roman people, but that he himself had made
                        his first essay of manhood in bearing arms against them. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> He must, therefore, sue to the Roman people for peace,
                        before he could expect to be acknowledged king, ally, and friend; that it
                        was the practice of that people to bestow the honour of such title, in
                        return for great services performed by kings towards them; <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> that the Roman ambassadors would soon be in Africa, to
                        whom the senate would give instructions to regulate conditions of peace with
                        Vermina, if he would leave the terms of it entirely to the will of the Roman
                        people; and that, if he wished that any thing should be added, left out, or
                        altered, he must make a second application to the senate. </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The ambassadors sent to Africa on those
                    affairs, were Caius Terentius Varro, Publius Lucretius, and Cneius Octavius,
                    each of whom had a quinquereme assigned him. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A letter was then read in the senate, from
                    Quintus Minucius, the praetor, who held the province of Bruttium, that <quote>
                        the money had been privately carried off by night out of the treasury of
                        Proserpine at Locri; and that there were no traces to those to whom the
                        charge applied. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate was highly incensed at finding that
                    the practice of sacrilege continued, and that even the fate of Pleminius, an
                    example so recent and so conspicuous both of the guilt and of the punishment,
                    did not deter men from it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They ordered the
                    consul, Cneius Aurelius, to signify to the praetor in Bruttium, <pb n="1353"
                        xml:id="p.1353"/> that <quote> it was the pleasure of the senate, that an
                        inquiry be made concerning the robbery of the treasury, according to the
                        method used by Marcus Pomponius, praetor, three years before; <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> that the money which could be discovered should
                        be restored, that what was not found should be made up, and that, if he
                        thought proper, atonements should be made for the purpose of expiating the
                        violation of the temple, in the manner formerly prescribed by the pontiffs. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At the same time, also, prodigies were
                    announced as having happened in many places. It was said, that in Lucania the
                    sky had been seen in a blaze; that at Privernum, in clear weather, the sun had
                    been of a red colour during a whole day; that at Lanuvium, in the temple of Juno
                    Sospita, a very loud noise had been heard in the night. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Besides, monstrous births of animals were related to have
                    occurred in many places: in the country of the Sabines, an infant was born whose
                    sex was doubtful; and another was found, sixteen years old, of doubtful sex.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At Frusino a lamb was born with a swine's
                    head; at Sinuessa, a pig with a human head; and in Lucania, in the land
                    belonging to the state, a foal with five feet. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    All these were considered as horrid and abominable, and as if nature were
                    straying to strange productions. Above all, the people were particularly shocked
                    at the hermaphrodites, which were ordered to be immediately thrown into the sea,
                    as had been lately done with a production of the same monstrous kind, in the
                    consulate of Caius Claudius and Marcus Livius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Notwithstanding they ordered the decemvirs to inspect the books in regard of
                    that prodigy; and the decemvirs, from the books, directed the same religious
                    ceremonies which had been performed on an occasion of the same kind. They
                    ordered, besides, a hymn to be sung through the city by thrice nine virgins, and
                    an offering to be made to imperial Juno. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    consul, Caius Aurelius, took care that all these matters were performed
                    according to the direction of the decemvirs. The hymn was composed by Publius
                    Licinius Tegula, as a similar one had been, in the memory of their fathers, by
                    Livius. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> All religious scruples were fully removed by
                    expiations; at Locri, too, the affair of the sacrilege had been thoroughly
                    investigated by Quintus Minucius, and the money replaced in the treasury out of
                    the effects of the guilty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the consuls
                    wished to set out to their provinces, a <pb n="1354" xml:id="p.1354"/> number of
                    private persons, to whom the third payment became due that year, of the money
                    which they had lent to the public in the consulate of Marcus Valerius and Marcus
                    Claudius, applied to the senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls,
                    however, declared that the treasury being scarcely sufficient for the exigencies
                    of a new war, in which a great fleet and great armies must be employed, there
                    were no means of paying them at present. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    senate could not stand against them when they complained, that <quote> if the
                        state intended to use, for the purpose of the Macedonian war, the money
                        which had been lent for the Punic war, as one war constantly arose after
                        another, what would be the issue, but that, in return for their generosity,
                        their property would be confiscated as for some crime? </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The demands of the private creditors being
                    equitable, and the state being in no capacity of discharging the debt, they
                    decreed a middle course between equity and convenience; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> resolving that <quote> whereas many of them mentioned that
                        lands were frequently exposed to sale, and that they themselves wished to
                        become purchasers, they should, therefore, have liberty to purchase any
                        belonging to the public, and which lay within fifty miles of the city.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the consuls should make a
                        valuation of these, and impose on each acre one <hi rend="italics">as,</hi>
                        as an acknowledgment that the land was the property of the public, in order
                        that, when the people should become able to <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> pay, if any one chose rather to have the money than the
                        land, he might restore it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The private creditors accepted the terms with
                    joy; and that land was called Trientius and Tabulius, because it was given in
                    lieu of the third part of their money. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Publius Sulpicius, after making his vows in
                    the Capitol, set out robed from the city with his lictors, and arrived at
                    Brundusium; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> where, having formed into legions
                    the veteran soldiers of the African army who were willing to follow him, and
                    chosen his ships out of the fleet of the late consul, Cornelius, he crossed and
                    arrived in Macedonia the day after he had set sail from Brundusium. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> There he was met by ambassadors from the Athenians,
                    entreating him to relieve them from the siege. Immediately, Caius Claudius
                    Centho was despatched to Athens, with twenty ships of war, and a thousand of
                    land forces. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For it was not the king himself
                    who carried on the siege of Athens; he was at that time besieging <pb n="1355"
                        xml:id="p.1355"/> Abydus, after having tried his strength in naval contests
                    against Attalus, and against the Rhodians, without success in either engagement.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But, besides the natural presumptuousness
                    of his temper, he acquired confidence from a treaty which he had formed with
                    Antiochus, king of Syria, in which they had divided the wealth of Egypt between
                    them; on which, on hearing of the death of Ptolemy, they were both intent.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Athenians now had entangled themselves
                    in a war with Philip on too trifling an occasion, and at a time when they
                    retained nothing of their former condition but their pride. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> During the celebration of the mysteries, two young men of
                    Acarnania, who were not initiated, unapprized of its being an offence against
                    religion, entered the temple of Ceres along with the rest of the crowd:
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> their discourse readily betrayed them, by
                    their asking some absurd questions; whereupon, being carried before the
                    presidents of the temple, although it was evident that they went in through
                    mistake, yet they were put to death, as if for a heinous crime. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The Acarnanian nation made complaint to Philip of this
                    barbarous and hostile act. and prevailed on him to grant them some aid of
                    Macedonian soldiers, and to allow them to make war on the Athenians. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> At first this army, after ravaging the lands of
                    Attica with fire and sword, retired to Acarnania with booty of all kinds. This
                    was the first provocation to hostilities. The Athenians afterwards, on their
                    side, entered into a regular war, and proclaimed it by order of the state.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For king Attalus and the Rhodians, having
                    come to Aegina in pursuit of Philip, who was retiring to Macedonia, the king
                    crossed over to Piraeus, for the purpose of renewing and confirming his alliance
                    with the Athenians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On entering the city, the
                    whole inhabitants received him, pouring forth with their wives and children to
                    meet him; the priests, with their emblems of religion; and in a manner the gods
                    themselves, called forth from their abodes. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately the people were summoned to an
                    assembly, that the king might treat with them in person on such subjects as he
                    chose; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> but afterwards it was judged more
                    suitable to his dignity to explain his sentiments in writing, than, being
                    present, to be forced to blush, either at the recital of his favours to the
                    state, or at the immoderate applause of the multitude, which would overwhelm his
                    modesty with acclam- <pb n="1356" xml:id="p.1356"/> ations, and other signs of
                    approbation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the letter which he sent, and
                    which was read to the assembly, was contained, first, a recapitulation of his
                    acts of kindness to the state, as his ally; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    then, of the actions which he had performed against Philip; and lastly, an
                    exhortation to <quote> enter immediately on the war; while they had himself, the
                        Rhodians, and the Romans also to assist them; </quote> not omitting to warn
                    them, that <quote> if they were backward now, they would hereafter wish in vain
                        for the opportunity which they neglected. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They then gave audience to the ambassadors of
                    the Rhodians, to whom they were under a recent obligation for having retaken,
                    and sent home, four of their ships of war, which had been lately seized by the
                    Macedonians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> War was determined upon against
                    Philip with universal consent. Unbounded honours were conferred on king Attalus,
                    and then on the Rhodians. At that time, mention was made of adding a tribe,
                    which they were to call Attalus, to the ten ancient tribes; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> the Rhodian state was presented with a golden crown, as an
                    acknowledgment of its bravery, and the freedom of the city was given to the
                    inhabitants, in like manner as the Rhodians had formerly given it to the
                    Athenians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After this, king Attalus returned
                    to his fleet at Aegina. From Aegina, the Rhodians sailed to Cia, and thence to
                    Rhodes, through the islands, all of which they brought to join in the alliance,
                    except Andros, Paros, and Cythnus, which were held by Macedonian garrisons.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Attalus, having sent messengers to
                    Aetolia, and expecting ambassadors from thence, was detained at Aegina for some
                    time in a state of inaction; failing also in his endeavours to excite the
                    Aetolians to arms, for they were rejoiced at having made peace with Philip on
                    any terms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Had Attalus and the Rhodians
                    pressed Philip vigorously, they might have acquired the illustrious title of the
                    deliverers of Greece, but by suffering him to pass over again into Hellespontus,
                    and to strengthen himself by seizing the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                    advantageous posts in Greece, they increased the difficulties of the war, and
                    yielded up to the Romans the glory of having conducted and finished it. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip acted with a spirit more becoming a
                    king; for, though he had found himself unequal to the forces of Attalus and the
                    Rhodians, yet he was not dismayed, even by the Roman war with which he was
                    threatened. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Sending Philocles, one of his
                    generals, with two thousand foot and two <pb n="1357" xml:id="p.1357"/> hundred
                    horse, to ravage the lands of the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> Athenians,
                    he gave the command of his fleet to Heraclides, to make for Maronea, and marched
                    thither himself by land, with two thousand foot lightly equipped, and two
                    hundred horse. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Maronea he took at the first
                    assault; and afterwards, with a good deal of trouble, got possession of Aenus,
                    which was at last betrayed to him by Ganymede, the lieutenant of Ptolemy. He
                    then seized on other forts, Cypselus, Doriscos, and Serrheus; and, advancing
                    from thence to the Chersonesus, received Elaeus and Alopeconnesus, which were
                    surrendered by the inhabitants. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Callipolis
                    also, and Madytos, were given up to him, with several forts of but little
                    consequence. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The people of Abydus shut their
                    gates against him, not admitting the ambassadors. This siege detained Philip a
                    long time; and it might have been relieved, had not Attalus and the Rhodians
                    been dilatory. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The king sent only three
                    hundred men for a garrison, and the Rhodians one quadrireme from their fleet,
                    although it was lying idle at Tenedos: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and
                    afterwards, when the besieged could with difficulty hold out any longer,
                    Attalus, going over in person, did nothing more than show them some hope of
                    relief being near, giving no assistance to these his allies either by land or
                    sea. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At first the people of Abydus, by means of
                    engines placed along the walls, not only prevented the approaches by land, but
                    annoyed the enemy's ships in their station. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Afterwards a part of the wall being thrown down, and the assailants having
                    penetrated by mines to an inner wall, which had been hastily raised to oppose
                    their entrance, they sent ambassadors to the king about the conditions of the
                    surrender of the city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They demanded
                    permission to send away the Rhodian quadrireme, with the crew, and the troops of
                    Attalus in the garrison; and that they themselves might depart from the city,
                    each with one suit of apparel. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When Philip's
                    answer afforded no hopes of accommodation, unless they surrendered at
                    discretion, this repudiation of their embassy so exasperated them, at once
                    through indignation and despair, that, seized with the same kind of fury which
                    had possessed the Saguntines, they ordered all the matrons to <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> be shut up in the temple of Diana, and the free-born youths
                    and virgins, and even the infants with their nurses, in the place of exercise;
                    the gold and silver to be carried into the forum; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> their valu- <pb n="1358" xml:id="p.1358"/> able garments to
                    be put on board the Rhodian ship, and another from Cyzicum, which lay in the
                    harbour; the priests and victims to be brought, and altars to be erected in the
                    midst. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There they appointed a select number,
                    who, as soon as they should see the army of their friends cut off in defending
                    the breach, were instantly to slay their wives and children; to throw into the
                    sea the gold, silver, and apparel that was on board the ships, and to set fire
                    to the buildings, public and private: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and to
                    the performance of this deed they were bound by an oath, the priests repeating
                    before them the verses of execration. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Those
                    who were of an age capable of fighting, then swore that they would not leave
                    their ranks alive unless victorious. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These,
                    regardful of the gods, (by whom they had sworn,) maintained their ground with
                    such obstinacy, that although the night would soon have put a stop to the fight,
                    yet the king, terrified by their fury, first desisted from the fight. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The chief inhabitants, to whom the more shocking
                    part of the plan had been given in charge, seeing that few survived the battle,
                    and that these were exhausted by fatigue and wounds, sent the priests (having
                    their heads bound with the fillets of suppliants) at the dawn of the next day to
                    surrender the city to Philip. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the surrender, one of the Roman
                    ambassadors, who had been sent to Alexandria, Marcus Aemilius, being the
                    youngest of them, on the joint resolution of the three, on hearing of the
                    present siege, came to Philip, and complained of his having made war on Attalus
                    and the Rhodians; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and particularly that he was
                    then besieging Abydus; and on Philip's saying that he had been forced into the
                    war by Attalus and the Rhodians commencing hostilities against him, — <quote>Did
                        the people of Abydus, too,</quote> said he, <quote>commence hostilities
                        against you?</quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To him, who was unaccustomed to hear truth,
                    this language seemed too arrogant to be used to a king, and he answered, —
                        <quote> Your youth, the beauty of your form, and, above all, the name of
                        Roman, render you too presumptuous. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        However, my first desire is, that you would observe the treaties, and
                        continue in peace with me; but if you begin an attack, I am, on my part,
                        determined to prove that the kingdom and name of the Macedonians is not less
                        formidable in war than that of the Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having dismissed the ambassador in this
                    manner, Philip got possession of <pb n="1359" xml:id="p.1359"/> the gold and
                    silver which had been thrown together in a heap, but lost his booty with respect
                    to prisoners: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> for such violent frenzy had
                    seized the multitude, that, on a sudden, taking up a persuasion that those who
                    had fallen in the battle had been treacherously sacrificed, and upbraiding one
                    another with perjury, especially the priests, who would surrender alive to the
                    enemy those persons whom they themselves had devoted, they all at once ran
                    different ways to put their wives and children to death; and then they put an
                    end to their own lives by every possible method. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> The king, astonished at their madness, restrained the violence of his
                    soldiers, and said, <quote>that he would allow the people of Abydus three days
                        to die in;</quote> and, during this space, the vanquished perpetrated more
                    deeds of cruelty on themselves than the enraged conquerors would have committed;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> nor did any one of them come into his
                    hands alive, except such as chains, or some other insuperable restraint, forbade
                    to die. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Philip, leaving a garrison in Abydus,
                    returned to his kingdom; and, just when he had been encouraged by the
                    destruction of the people of Abydus to proceed in the war against Rome, as
                    Hannibal had been by the destruction of Saguntum, he was met by couriers, with
                    intelligence that the consul was already in Epirus, and had drawn his land
                    forces to Apollonia, and his fleet to Corcyra, into winter quarters. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time, the ambassadors who had been
                    sent into Africa, on the affair of Hamilcar, the leader of the Gallic army,
                    received from the Carthaginians this answer: that <quote> it was not in their
                        power to do more than to inflict on him the punishment of exile, and to
                        confiscate his effects; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that they had
                        delivered up all the deserters and fugitives, whom, on a diligent inquiry,
                        they had been able to discover, and would send ambassadors to Rome, to
                        satisfy the senate on that head. </quote> They sent two hundred thousand
                    measures of wheat to Rome, and the same quantity to the army in Macedonia.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From thence the ambassadors proceeded into
                    Numidia, to the king; delivered to Masinissa the presents and the message
                    according to their instructions, and out of two thousand Numidian horsemen,
                    which he offered, accepted one thousand. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa superintended in person the embarkation of these, and sent them, with
                    two hundred thousand measures of wheat, and the same quantity of barley, into
                    Macedonia. Their third <pb n="1360" xml:id="p.1360"/> commission was with
                    Vermina. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He advanced to meet them as far as
                    the utmost limits of his kingdom, and left it to themselves to prescribe such
                    conditions of peace as they thought proper, declaring, that <quote>he should
                        consider any peace with the Roman people as just and advantageous.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The terms were then settled, and he was
                    ordered to send ambassadors to Rome to procure a ratification of the treaty. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time, Lucius Cornelius
                    Lentulus, proconsul, came home from Spain; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and
                    having laid before the senate an account of his brave and successful conduct,
                    during the course of many years, demanded that he might be allowed to enter the
                    city in triumph. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate gave their
                    opinion, that <quote> his services were, indeed, deserving of a triumph; but
                        that they had no precedent left them by their ancestors of any person
                        enjoying a triumph, who had not performed the service either of dictator,
                        consul, or praetor; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that he had held the
                        province of Spain in quality of proconsul, and not of consul, or praetor
                    </quote> They determined, however, that he might enter the city in ovation.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Against this, Tiberius Sempronius Longus,
                    tribune of the people, protested, alleging, that such proceedings would be no
                    more in accordance with the custom of their ancestors, or with any precedent,
                    than the other; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but, overcome at length by the
                    unanimous desire of the senate, the tribune withdrew his opposition, and Lucius
                    Lentulus entered the city in ovation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                    carried to the treasury forty-four thousand pounds weight of silver, and two
                    thousand four hundred pounds weight of gold. To each of the soldiers he
                    distributed, of the spoil, one hundred and twenty <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    7 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consular army had, by this time, been
                    conducted from Arretium to Ariminum, and the five thousand Latin confederates
                    had crossed from Gaul into Etruria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Lucius
                    Furius, therefore, advanced from Ariminum, by forced marches, against the Gauls,
                    who were then besieging Cremona, and pitched his camp at the distance of one
                    mile and a half from the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Furius had an
                    opportunity of performing a splendid exploit, had he, without halting, led his
                    troops directly to attack their camp; scattered hither and thither, they were
                    wandering through the country; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and the guard,
                    which they had left, was not sufficiently strong; but he was apprehensive that
                    his men were too much fatigued by <pb n="1361" xml:id="p.1361"/> their hasty
                    march. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Gauls, recalled from the fields by
                    the shouts of their party, returned to the camp without seizing the booty within
                    their reach, and, next day, marched out to offer battle. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman did not decline the combat, but had scarcely time
                    to draw up his forces, so rapidly did the enemy advance to the fight. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The right brigade (for he had the troops of the
                    allies divided into brigades) was placed in the first line, the two Roman
                    legions in reserve. Marcus Furius was at the head of the right brigade, Marcus
                    Caecilius of the legions, and Lucius Valerius Flaccus of the cavalry: these were
                    all lieutenant-generals. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Two other
                    lieutenant-generals, Cneius Laetorius and Publius Titinnius, the praetor kept
                    near himself, that, with their assistance, he might observe and take proper
                    measures against all sudden attempts of the enemy. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> At first, the Gauls, bending their whole force to one
                    point, were in hopes of being able to overwhelm, and trample under foot, the
                    right brigade, which was in the van; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but not
                    succeeding, they endeavoured to turn round the flanks, and to surround their
                    enemy's line, which, considering the multitude of their forces, and the small
                    number of the others, seemed easy to be done. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    On observing this, the praetor, in order to extend his own line, brought up the
                    two legions from the reserve, and placed them on the right and left of the
                    brigade which was engaged in the van; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> vowing
                    a temple to Jupiter, if he should rout the enemy on that day. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> To Lucius Valerius he gave orders, to make the horsemen of
                    the two legions on one flank, and the cavalry of the allies on the other, charge
                    the wings of the enemy, and not suffer them to come round to his rear.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> At the same time, observing that the
                    centre of the line of the Gauls was weakened, from having extended the wings, he
                    directed his men to make an attack there in close order, and to break through
                    their ranks. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The wings were routed by the
                    cavalry, and, at the same time, the centre by the foot; and suddenly, being
                    worsted in all parts with great slaughter, the Gauls turned their backs, and
                    fled to their camp in hurry and confusion. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    The cavalry pursued them as they fled; and the legions, coming up in a short
                    time after, assaulted the camp, from whence there did not escape so many as six
                    thousand men. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> There were slain and taken
                    above thirty-five thousand, with seventy standards, and above two hundred Gallic
                    waggons laden with much booty. Hamilcar, <pb n="1362" xml:id="p.1362"/> the
                    Carthaginian general, fell in that battle, and three distinguished generals of
                    the Gauls. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The prisoners taken at Placentia,
                    to the number of two thousand free-men, were restored to the colony. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was an important victory, and caused
                    great joy at Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On receipt of the praetor's
                    letter, a supplication for three days was decreed. In that battle, there fell of
                    the Romans and allies two thousand, most of them in the right brigade, against
                    which, in the first onset, the most violent efforts of the enemy had been
                    directed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Although the praetor had brought the
                    war almost to a conclusion, yet the consul, Cneius Aurelius, having finished the
                    business which was necessary to be done at Rome, set out for Gaul, and received
                    the victorious army from the praetor. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    other consul, arriving in his province towards the end of autumn, passed the
                    winter in the neighbourhood of Apollonia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Caius Claudius, and the Roman triremes which had been sent to Athens from the
                    fleet that was laid up at Corcyra, as was mentioned above, arriving at Piraeeus,
                    greatly revived the hopes of their allies, who were beginning to give way to
                    despair. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For not only did those inroads by
                    land cease, which used to be made from Corinth through Megara, but the ships of
                    the pirates from Chalcis, who <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> had been
                    accustomed to infest both the Athenian sea and coast, were afraid not only to
                    venture round the promontory of Sunium, but even to trust themselves out of the
                    straits of the Euripus. In addition to these came three quadriremes from Rhodes,
                    the Athenians having three open ships, which they had equipped for the
                    protection of their lands on the coast. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While
                    Claudius thought, that if he were able with his fleet to give security to the
                    Athenians it was as much as could be expected at present, a fortunate
                    opportunity was thrown in his way of accomplishing a much more important
                    enterprise. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some exiles driven from Chalcis, by ill
                    treatment received from the king's party, brought intelligence, that the place
                    might be taken without even a contest; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for
                    that both the Macedonians, being under no immediate apprehension from an enemy,
                    were straying idly about the country; and that the townsmen, depending on the
                    Macedonian garrison, neglected the guard of the city. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Claudius, on this authority, set out, and though he arrived
                    at Sunium early enough to have <pb n="1363" xml:id="p.1363"/> sailed forward to
                    the entrance of the strait of Eubœa, yet fearing that, on doubling the
                    promontory, he might be descried by the enemy, he lay by with the fleet until
                    night. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As soon as it grew dark he began to
                    move, and, favoured by a calm, arrived at Chalcis a little before day; and then,
                    approaching the city, on a side where it was thinly inhabited, with a small
                    party of soldiers, and by means of scaling ladders, he got possession of the
                    nearest tower, and the wall on each side; the guards being asleep in some
                    places, and in others no one being on the watch. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Thence they advanced to the more populous parts of the town, and having slain
                    the sentinels, and broke open a gate, they gave an entrance to the main body of
                    the troops. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These immediately spread
                    themselves throughout the whole city, and increased the tumult by setting fire
                    to the buildings round the forum, by <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> which
                    means both the granaries belonging to the king, and his armoury, with a vast
                    store of machines and engines, were reduced to ashes. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Then commenced a general slaughter of those who fled, as
                    well as of those who made resistance; and after having either put to the sword
                    or driven out every one who was of an age fit to bear arms, (Sopater also, the
                    Acarnanian, who commanded the garrison, being slain,) they first collected all
                    the spoils in the forum, and then carried it on board the ships. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The prison, too, was forced open by the Rhodians, and
                    those prisoners whom Philip had shut up there, as in the safest custody, were
                    set at liberty. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They next pulled down and
                    mutilated the statues of the king; and then, on a signal being given for a
                    retreat, re-embarked and returned to Piraeus, from whence they had set out.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If there had been so large a force of
                    Roman soldiers that Chalcis might have been retained and the protection of
                    Athens not neglected, Chalcis and Euripus might have been taken from the king;
                    —a most important advantage at the commencement of the war. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> For as the pass of Thermopylae is the principal barrier of
                    Greece by land, so is the strait of the Euripus by sea. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip was then at Demetrias, and as soon as
                    the news arrived there of the calamity which had befallen the city of his
                    allies, although it was too late to carry assistance to those who were already
                    ruined, yet <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> anxious to accomplish what was
                    next to assistance, revenge, he set out instantly with five thousand foot
                    lightly equipped, and three hundred horse. <pb n="1364" xml:id="p.1364"/> With a
                    speed almost equal to that of racing, he hastened to Chalcis, not doubting but
                    that he should be able to surprise the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Being disappointed in this expectation, and having arrived, with no other result
                    than a melancholy view of the smoking ruins of that friendly city, (so few being
                    left, that they were scarcely sufficient to bury those who had fallen in the
                    conflict,) with the same rapid haste which he had used in coming, he crossed the
                    Euripus by the bridge, and led his troops through Bœotia to Athens, in hopes
                    that a similar issue would correspond to a similar attempt. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And it would have corresponded, had not a scout, (one of
                    those whom the Greeks call day-runners, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Hemerodromoi.</note> because they run through a journey
                    of great length in one day,) descrying from his post of <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> observation the king's army in its march, set out at
                    midnight, and arrived before them at Athens. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The same sleep, and the same negligence, prevailed there which had proved the
                    ruin of Chalcis a few days before. Roused, however, by the alarming
                    intelligence, the praetor of the Athenians, and Dioxippus, commander of a cohort
                    of mercenary auxiliaries, called the soldiers together in the forum, and ordered
                    the trumpets to sound an alarm from the citadel, that all might be informed of
                    the approach of the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On which the people
                    ran from all quarters to the gates, and afterwards to the walls. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> In a few hours after, and still some time before day,
                    Philip approached the city, and observing a great number of lights, and hearing
                    the noise of the men hurrying to and fro, as usual on such an alarm, he halted
                    his troops, and ordered them to sit down and take some rest; resolving to use
                    open force, since his stratagem had not succeeded. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly he advanced on the side of Dipylos. This gate,
                    being situated in the principal approach of the city, is somewhat larger and
                    wider than the rest. Both within and without the streets are wide, so that the
                    townsmen could form their troops from the forum to the gate, while on the
                    outside a road of about a mile in length, leading to the school of the academy,
                    afforded open room to the foot and horse of the enemy. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The Athenians, who had formed their troops within the gate,
                    marched out with Attalus's garrison, and the cohort of Dioxippus, along that
                    road. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Which, when Philip observed, thinking
                    that he had the enemy in his power, and was now about to sate him- <pb n="1365"
                        xml:id="p.1365"/> self with their long wished for destruction, (being more
                    incensed against them than any of the Grecian states,) he exhorted his men to
                    keep their eyes on him during the fight, and to take notice, that wherever the
                    king was, there the standards and the army ought to be. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> He then spurred on his horse against the enemy, animated
                    not only with resentment, but with a desire of gaining honour, for he reckoned
                    it a glorious thing to be beheld fighting from the <milestone n="13??"
                        unit="section"/> walls, which were filled with an immense multitude, for the
                    purpose of witnessing the engagement. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Advancing far before the line, and, with a small body of horse, rushing into the
                    midst of the enemy, he inspired his men with great ardour, and the Athenians
                    equally with terror. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Having wounded many with
                    his own hand, both in close fight and with missive weapons, and driven them back
                    within the gate, he still pursued them closely; and having made greater
                    slaughter among them while embarrassed in the narrow pass, rash as the attempt
                    was, he yet had an unmolested retreat, because those who were in the towers
                    withheld their weapons <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> lest they should hit
                    their friends, who were mingled in confusion among their enemies. <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> The Athenians, after this, confining their troops
                    within the walls, Philip sounded a retreat, and pitched his camp at Cynosarges,
                    a temple of Hercules, and a school surrounded by a grove. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> But Cynosarges, and Lycaum, and whatever was sacred or
                    pleasant in the neighbourhood of the city, he burned to the ground, and levelled
                    not only the houses, but sepulchres, nor was any thing either in divine or human
                    possession preserved amidst the violence of his rage. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next day, the gates having at first been shut,
                    and afterwards suddenly thrown open, in consequence of a body of Attalus's
                    troops from Aegina, and the Romans from Piraeeus, having entered the city, the
                    king removed his camp to the distance of about three miles. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> From thence he proceeded to Eleusis, in hopes of surprising
                    the temple, and a fort which overlooks and surrounds it; but, finding that the
                    watches had not been neglected, and that the fleet was coming from Piraeeus to
                    support them, he laid aside the design, and led his troops, first to Megara, and
                    then to Corinth; where, on hearing that the council of the Achaeans was then
                    sitting at Argos, he went and joined the assembly, unexpected by the Achaeans.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were at the time consulting about a
                    war against <pb n="1366" xml:id="p.1366"/> Nabis, tyrant of the Lacedaemonians;
                    who, on the command being transferred from Philopœmen to Cycliades, a general by
                    no means his equal, perceiving that the confederates of the Achaeans were
                    falling off, had renewed the war, was ravaging the territories of his
                    neighbours, and had become formidable even to the cities. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> While they were deliberating what number of men should be
                    raised out of each of the states to oppose this enemy, Philip promised that he
                    would relieve them of that care, as far as concerned Nabis and the
                    Lacedaemonians; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and that he would not only
                    secure the lands of their allies from devastation, but transfer the whole terror
                    of the war on Laconia itself, by leading his army thither instantly. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> This discourse being received with general
                    approbation, he added, —"It is but reasonable, however, that while I am employed
                    in protecting your property by my arms, my own should not be deprived of
                    protection; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> therefore, if you think proper,
                    provide such a number of troops as will be sufficient to secure Orcus, Chalcis,
                    and Corinth; that my affairs being in a state of safety behind me, I may without
                    anxiety make war on Nabis and the Lacedaemonians. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The Achaeans were not ignorant of the tendency of this so
                    kind promise, and of his proffered assistance against the Lacedaemonians; that
                    his purpose was to draw the Achaean youth out of Peloponnesus as hostages, in
                    order to implicate the nation in a war with the Romans. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Cycliades, the Achaean praetor, thinking that it was
                    irrelevant to develope the matter by argument, said nothing more than that it
                    was not allowable, according to the laws of the Achaeans, to take any matters
                    into consideration except those on which they had been called together:
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and the decree for levying an army
                    against Nabis being passed, he dismissed the assembly, after having presided in
                    it with much resolution and public spirit, and until that day having been
                    reckoned among the partisans of the king. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Philip, disappointed in a high expectation, after having collected a few
                    voluntary soldiers, returned to Corinth, and from thence into the territories of
                    Athens. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In those days in which Philip was in Achaia,
                    Philocles, one of the king's generals, marching from Eubœa with two thousand
                    Thracians and Macedonians, in order to lay waste the territories of the
                    Athenians, crossed the forest of Cithaeron opposite to Eleusis. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Despatching half of his troops, <pb n="1367"
                        xml:id="p.1367"/> to make depredations in all parts of the country, he
                    himself lay concealed with the remainder in a place convenient for an ambush;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> in order that, if any attack should be
                    made from the fort at Eleusis on his men employed in plundering, he might
                    suddenly fall upon the enemy unawares, and while they were in disorder.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His stratagem did not escape discovery:
                    wherefore, calling back the soldiers, who had gone different ways in pursuit of
                    booty, and drawing them up in order, he advanced to assault the fort at Eleusis;
                    but being repulsed from thence with many wounds, he formed a junction with
                    Philip on his return from Achaia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The storming
                    of this fort was also attempted by the king in person: but the Roman ships
                    coming from Piraeeus, and a body of forces thrown into the fort, compelled him
                    to relinquish the design. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On this the king,
                    dividing his army, sent Philocles with one part to Athens, and went himself with
                    the other to Piraeeus; that, while his general, by advancing to the walls and
                    threatening an assault, might keep the Athenians within the city, he might be
                    able to make himself master of the harbour, when left with only a slight
                    garrison. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But he found the attack of Piraeeus
                    no less difficult than that of Eleusis, the same persons for the most part
                    acting in its defence. He therefore hastily led his troops to Athens, and being
                    repulsed by a sudden sally of both foot <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> and
                    horse, who engaged him in the narrow ground, enclosed by the half-ruined wall,
                    which, with two arms, joins Piraeeus to Athens, he desisted from the assault of
                    the city, and, dividing his forces again with Philocles, set out to complete the
                    devastation of the country. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As, in his former
                    ravages, he had employed himself in levelling the sepulchres round the city, so
                    now, not to leave any thing <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> unviolated, he
                    ordered the temples of the gods, of which they had one consecrated in every
                    village, to be demolished and burned. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    country of Attica afforded ample matter for the exercise of this barbarous rage:
                    being highly embellished with works of that kind, having plenty of indigenous
                    marble, and abounding with artists of exquisite ingenuity. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was he satisfied with merely destroying the temples
                    themselves, and overthrowing the images, but he ordered even the stones to be
                    broken, lest, remaining whole, they should give stateliness to the ruins;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and then, his rage not being satiated,
                    but no object remaining on which it could be exercised, he retired <pb n="1368"
                        xml:id="p.1368"/> from the country of the enemy into Bœotia, without having
                    performed in Greece any thing else worth mention. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, Sulpicius, who was at that time
                    encamped on the river Apsus, between Apollonia and Dyrrachium, having ordered
                    Lucius Apustius, lieutenant-general, thither, sent him with part of the forces
                    to lay waste the enemy's territory. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Apustius,
                    after ravaging the frontiers of Macedonia, and having, at the first assault,
                    taken the forts of Corragos, Gerrunios, and Orgessos, came to Antipatria, a city
                    situated in a narrow gorge; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> where, at first
                    inviting the leading men to a conference, he endeavoured to entice them to
                    commit themselves to the good faith of the Romans; but finding that from
                    confidence in the size, fortifications, and situation of their city, they paid
                    no regard to his discourse, he attacked the place by force of arms, and took it
                    by assault: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> then, putting all the young men to
                    death, and giving up the entire spoil to his soldiers, he razed the walls and
                    burned the city. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This proceeding spread such
                    terror, that Codrion, a strong and well-fortified town, surrendered to the
                    Romans without a struggle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Leaving a garrison
                    there, he took Ilion by force, a name better known than the town, on account of
                    that of the same name in Asia. As the lieutenant-general was returning to the
                    consul with a great quantity of spoil, Athenagoras, one of the king's generals,
                    falling on his extreme rear, in its passage over a river, threw the hindmost
                    into disorder. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On hearing the shouting and
                    tumult, Apustius rode back in full speed, ordered the troops to face about, and
                    drew them up in order, arranging the baggage in the centre. The king's troops
                    could not support the onset of the Roman soldiers, many of them were slain, and
                    more made prisoners. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The lieutenant-general,
                    having brought back the army without loss to the consul, was despatched
                    immediately to the fleet. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The war commencing thus brilliantly with this
                    successful expedition, several petty kings and princes, neighbours of the
                    Macedonians, came to the Roman camp: Pleuratus, son of Scerdilaedus, and
                    Amynander, king of the Athamanians; and from the Dardanians, Bato, son of
                    Longarus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This Longarus had, in his own
                    quarrel, supported a war against Demetrius, father of Philip. To their offers of
                    aid, the consul answered, that he would make use of the assistance of the
                    Dardanians, and of Pleuratus, when he should <pb n="1369" xml:id="p.1369"/> lead
                    his troops into Macedonia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To Amynander he
                    allotted the part of exciting the Aetolians to war. To the ambassadors of
                    Attalus, (for they also had come at the same time,) he gave directions that the
                    king should wait at Aegina, where he wintered, for the arrival of the Roman
                    fleet; and when joined by that, he should, as before, harass Philip with attacks
                    by sea. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To the Rhodians, also, an embassy was
                    sent, to engage them to contribute their share towards carrying on the war. Nor
                    was Philip, who had by this time arrived in Macedonia, remiss in his
                    preparations for the campaign. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He sent his son
                    Perseus, then very young, with part of his forces to block up the pass near
                    Pelagonia, appointing persons out of the number of his friends to direct his
                    inexperienced age. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Sciathus and Peparethus, no
                    inconsiderable cities, he demolished, lest they should become a prey and prize
                    to the enemy's fleet; despatching at the same time ambassadors to the Aetolians,
                    lest that restless nation might change sides on the arrival of the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The assembly of the Aetolians, which they call
                    Panetolium, was to meet on a certain day. In order to be present at this, the
                    king's ambassadors hastened their journey, and Lucius Furius Purpureo also
                    arrived, deputed by the consul. Ambassadors from the Athenians, likewise, came
                    to this assembly. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Macedonians were first
                    heard, as with them the latest treaty had been made; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and they declared, that <quote> as no change of
                        circumstances had occurred, they had nothing new to introduce: for the same
                        reasons which had induced them to make peace with Philip, after experiencing
                        the unprofitableness of an alliance with the Romans, should engage them to
                        preserve it, now that it was established. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Do you rather choose, </quote> said one of the ambassadors, <quote> to
                        imitate the inconsistency, or levity, shall I call it, of the Romans, who
                        ordered this answer to be given to your ambassadors at Rome: 'Why,
                        Aetolians, do you apply to us, when, without our approbation, you have made
                        peace with Philip?' Yet these same people now require that you should, in
                        conjunction with them, wage war against Philip. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Formerly, too, they pretended that they took arms on
                        your account, and in your defence against Philip: now they do not allow you
                        to continue at peace with him. To assist Messana, they first embarked for
                        Sicily; and a second time, that they might redeem Syracuse to freedom <pb
                            n="1370" xml:id="p.1370"/> when oppressed by the Carthaginians.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Both Messana and Syracuse, and all
                        Sicily, they hold in their own possession, and have reduced it into a
                        tributary province under their axes and rods. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> You imagine, perhaps, that in the same manner as you
                        hold an assembly at Naupactus, according to your own laws, under <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> magistrates created by yourselves, at liberty
                        to choose allies and enemies, and to have peace or war at your own option,
                        so the assembly of the states of Sicily is summoned to Syracuse, or Messana,
                        or Lilybaeum. No, a Roman praetor presides at the meeting; summoned by his
                        command they assemble; they behold him, attended by his lictors, seated on a
                        lofty throne, issuing his haughty edicts. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        His rods are ready for their backs, his axes for their necks, and every year
                        they are allotted a different master. Neither ought they, nor can they,
                        wonder at this, when they see all the cities of Italy bending under the same
                        yoke, —Rhegium, <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Tarentum, Capua, not to
                        mention those in their own neighbourhood, out of the ruins of which their
                        city of Rome grew into power. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Capua
                        indeed subsists, the grave and monument of the Campanian people, that entire
                        people having been either cut off or driven into banishment; the mutilated
                        carcass of a city, without senate, without commons, without magistrates; a
                        sort of prodigy, the leaving which to be inhabited, showed more cruelty than
                        if it had been utterly destroyed. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If
                        foreigners who are separated from us to a greater distance by their
                        language, manners, and laws, than by the distance by sea and land, are
                        allowed to get footing here, it is madness to hope that any thing will
                        continue in its present state. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Does the
                        sovereignty of Philip seem in any degree incompatible with your freedom,
                        who, at a time when he was justly incensed against you, demanded nothing
                        more of you than peace; and at present requires no more than the observance
                        of the peace which he agreed to? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Accustom
                        foreign legions to these countries, and receive the yoke; too late, and in
                        vain, will you look for Philip as an ally, when you shall have the Roman as
                        a master. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Trifling causes occasionally
                        unite and disunite the Aetolians, Acarnanians, and Macedonians, men speaking
                        the same language. With foreigners, with barbarians, all Greeks have, and
                        ever will have, eternal war: because they are enemies by nature, which is
                        always the same, and not from causes which change with the times. My
                        discourse shall <pb n="1371" xml:id="p.1371"/> conclude with the same
                        argument with which it began. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Three years
                        since, the same persons, assembled in this same place, determined on peace
                        with the same Philip, contrary to the inclinations of the same Romans, who
                        now wish that the peace should be broken, after it has been adjusted and
                        ratified. In the subject of your deliberation, fortune has made no change;
                        why you should make any, I do not see. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next, after the Macedonians, with the consent
                    and at the desire of the Romans, the Athenians were introduced; who, having
                    suffered grievously, could, with the greater justice, inveigh against the
                    cruelty and inhumanity of the king. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                    represented, in a deplorable light, the miserable devastation and spoliation of
                    their fields; adding, that <quote> they did not complain on account of having,
                        from an enemy, suffered hostile treatment; for there were certain rights of
                        war, according to which, as it was just to act, so it was just to endure.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Their crops being burned, their houses
                        demolished, their men and cattle carried off as spoil, were to be considered
                        rather as misfortunes to the sufferer than as ill-treatment. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> But of this they had good reason to complain,
                        that he who called the Romans foreigners and barbarians, had himself so
                        atrociously violated all rights, both divine and human, as, in his former
                        inroad, to have waged an impious war against the infernal gods, in the
                        latter, against those above. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That the
                        sepulchres and monuments of all within their country had been demolished,
                        the graves laid open, and the bones left unprotected by the soil. There had
                        been several temples, which, in former times, when their ancestors dwelt
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> in the country in their separate
                        districts, had been consecrated in each of their little forts and villages,
                        and which, even after they were incorporated into one city, they did not
                        neglect or forsake. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That around all these
                        temples Philip had scattered his destructive flames, and left the images of
                        the gods lying scorched and mutilated among the prostrated pillars of their
                        fanes. Such as he had rendered the country of Attica, formerly opulent and
                        adorned, such, if he were suffered, would he render Aetolia and the whole of
                        Greece. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That the mutilation of their own
                        city, also, would have been similar, if the Romans had not come to its
                        relief: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> for he had shown the same wicked
                        rage against the gods who are the guardians of the city, and Minerva who
                        presides over the citadel; the same against the temple of <pb n="1372"
                            xml:id="p.1372"/> Ceres at Eleusis; the same against Jupiter and Minerva
                        at Piraeeus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In a word, having been
                        repelled by force of arms, not only from their temples, but even from their
                        walls, he had vented his fury on those sacred edifices which were protected
                        by religion alone. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They therefore
                        entreated and besought the Aetolians, that, compassionating the Athenians,
                        and with the immortal gods for their leaders, and, under them, the Romans,
                        who, next to the gods, possessed the greatest power, they would take part in
                        the war. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman ambassador then replied: <quote> The
                        Macedonians first, and afterwards the Athenians, have obliged me to change
                        entirely the method of my discourse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For,
                        on the one hand, the Macedonians, by aggressively introducing charges
                        against the Romans, when I had come prepared to make complaint of the
                        injuries committed by Philip against so many cities in alliance with us,
                        have obliged me to think of defence rather than accusation; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> and, on the other hand, what have the Athenians, after
                        relating his inhuman and impious crimes against the gods both celestial and
                        infernal, left for me, or any one else, which I can further urge against
                        him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> You are to suppose, that the same
                        complaints are made by the Cianians, Abydenians, Aeneans, Maronites,
                        Thasians, Parians, Samians, Larissenians, Messenians, on the side of Achaia;
                        and complaints, still heavier and more grievous, by those whom he had it
                        more in his power to injure. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For as to
                        those proceedings which he censures in us, if they are not deserving of
                        honour, I will admit that they cannot be defended at all. He has objected to
                        us, Rhegium, and Capua, and Syracuse. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As
                        to Rhegium, during the war with Pyrrhus, a legion which, at the earnest
                        request of the Rhegians themselves, we had sent thither as a garrison,
                        wickedly possessed themselves of the city which they had been sent to
                        defend. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Did we then approve of that deed?
                        or did we exert the force of our arms against that guilty legion, until we
                        reduced them under our power; and then, after making them give satisfaction
                        to the allies, by their stripes and the loss of their heads, restore to the
                        Rhegians their city, their lands, and all their effects, together with their
                        liberty and laws? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To the Syracusans, when
                        oppressed, and that by foreign tyrants, which was a still greater indignity,
                        we lent assistance; and after enduring great fatigues in carrying on the
                        siege of so strong a city, both by land and sea, <pb n="1373"
                            xml:id="p.1373"/> for almost three years, (although the Syracusans
                        themselves chose to continue in slavery to the tyrants rather than be taken
                        to us,) yet, becoming masters of the place, and by exertion of the same
                        force setting it at liberty, we restored it to the inhabitants. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> At the same time, we do not deny that Sicily is
                        our province, and that the states which sided with the Carthaginians, and,
                        in conjunction with them, waged war against us, pay us tribute and taxes;
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> on the contrary, we wish that you and
                        all nations should know, that the condition of each is such as it has
                        deserved at our hands: and ought we to repent of the punishment inflicted on
                        the Campanians, of which even they themselves cannot complain? <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> These men, after we had on their account carried
                        on war against the Samnites for near seventy years, with great loss on our
                        side; had united them to ourselves, first by treaty, and then by
                        intermarriages, and the relationships arising thence; <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> and lastly, by the right of citizenship; yet, in the
                        time of our adversity, were the first of all the states of Italy which
                        revolted to Hannibal, after basely putting our garrison to death, and
                        afterwards, through resentment at being besieged by us, sent Hannibal to
                        attack Rome. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If neither their city nor
                        one man of them had been left remaining, who could take offence, or consider
                        them as treated with more severity than they had deserved? <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> From consciousness of guilt, greater numbers of them
                        perished by their own hands, than by the punishments inflicted by us.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> And while from the rest we took away
                        the town and the lands, still we left them a place to dwell in, we suffered
                        the city which partook not of the guilt to stand uninjured; so that he who
                        should see it this day would find no trace of its having been besieged or
                        taken. But why do I speak of Capua, when even to vanquished Carthage we
                        granted peace and liberty? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The greatest
                        danger is, that, by our too great readiness to pardon the conquered, we may
                        encourage others to try the fortune of war against us. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Let so much suffice in our defence, and against Philip,
                        whose domestic crimes, whose parricides and murders of his relations and
                        friends, and whose lust, more disgraceful to human nature, if possible, than
                        his cruelty, you, as being nearer to Macedonia, are better acquainted with.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> As to what concerns yourselves,
                        Aetolians, we entered into a war with Philip on your account: you made peace
                        with him without consulting us. <pb n="1374" xml:id="p.1374"/> Perhaps you
                        will say, that while we were occupied in the Punic war, you were constrained
                        by fear to accept terms of pacification, from him who at that time possessed
                        superior power; <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> and that on our side,
                        pressed by more urgent affairs, we suspended our operations in a war which
                        you had laid aside. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> At present, as we,
                        having, by the favour of the gods, brought the Punic war to a conclusion,
                        have fallen on Macedonia with the whole weight of our power, so you have an
                        opportunity offered you of regaining a place in our friendship and alliance,
                        unless you choose to perish with Philip, rather than to conquer with the
                        Romans. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these things had been said by the
                    ambassador, the minds of all leaning towards the Romans, Damocritus, praetor of
                    the Aetolians, (who, it was reported, had received money from the king,)
                    assenting in no degree to one party or the other, said, —that <quote> in
                        consultations of great and critical importance, nothing was so injurious as
                        haste. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That repentance, indeed, generally
                        followed, and that quickly, but yet too late and unavailing; because designs
                        carried on with precipitation could not be recalled, nor matters brought
                        back to their original state. The time, however, for determining the point
                        under consideration, which, for his part, he thought should not be too
                        early, might yet immediately be fixed in this manner. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As it had been provided by the laws, that no
                        determination should be made concerning peace or war, except in the
                        Panaetolic or Pylaic councils; let them immediately pass a decree, that the
                        praetor, when he chooses to treat respecting war and peace, may have full
                        authority to summon a council; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and that
                        whatever shall be then debated and decreed, shall be, to all intents and
                        purposes, legal and valid, as if it had been transacted in the Panaetolic or
                        Pylaic assembly. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And thus dismissing the ambassadors, with the
                    matter undetermined, he said, that therein he had acted most prudently for the
                    interest of the state; for the Aetolians would have it in their power to join in
                    alliance with whichever of the parties should be more successful in the war.
                    Such were the proceedings in the council of the Aetolians. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile Philip was making vigorous
                    preparations for carrying on the war both by sea and land. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> His naval forces he drew together at Demetrias in Thessaly;
                    supposing that Attalus, and the Roman fleet, would move from Aegina <pb n="1375"
                        xml:id="p.1375"/> in the beginning of the spring. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He gave the command of the fleet and of the sea-coast to
                    Heraclides, to whom he had formerly intrusted it. The equipment of the land
                    forces he took care of in person; considering that he had deprived the Romans of
                    two powerful auxiliaries, the Aetolians on the one side, and the Dardanians on
                    the other, by making his son Perseus block up the pass at Pelagonia. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The consul was employed, not in preparations, but in
                    the operations of war. He led his army through the country of the Dassaretians,
                    conveying the corn untouched which he had brought from his winter quarters, for
                    the fields afforded supplies sufficient for the consumption of the troops.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The towns and villages surrendered to him,
                    some through inclination, others through fear; some were taken by assault,
                    others were found deserted, the barbarians flying to the neighbouring mountains.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He fixed a standing camp at Lycus near the
                    river Bevus, and from thence sent to bring in corn from the magazines of the
                    Dassaretians. Philip saw the whole country filled with consternation, and not
                    knowing the designs of the consul, he sent a party of horse to discover whither
                    he was directing his course. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same state of
                    uncertainty possessed the consul; he knew that the king had moved from his
                    winter quarters, but in what direction he had proceeded he knew not: he also had
                    sent horsemen to gain intelligence. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These two
                    parties, having set out from opposite quarters, after wandering a long time
                    among the Dassaretians, through unknown roads, fell at length into the same
                    track. Neither doubted, as soon as the noise of men and horses was heard at a
                    distance, that the enemy was approaching, therefore, before they came within
                    sight of each other, they got their arms in readiness, nor, when they saw their
                    foe, was there any delay in engaging. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As they
                    happened to be nearly equal in number and valour, being picked men on both
                    sides, they fought during several hours with vigour, until fatigue, both of men
                    and horses, put an end to the fight, without deciding the victory. Of the
                    Macedonians there fell forty horsemen; of the Romans thirty-five. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Still, however, neither did the one party carry back
                    to the king, nor the other to the consul, any certain information in what
                    quarter the camp of his enemy lay. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But this
                    was soon made known to them by deserters, whom their <pb n="1376"
                        xml:id="p.1376"/> recklessness of disposition supplies in all wars in
                    sufficient number to discover the affairs of the contending parties. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, judging that he should make some
                    progress towards conciliating the affections of his men, and induce them to face
                    danger more readily on his account, if he <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    bestowed some pains on the burial of the horsemen who fell in that expedition,
                    ordered them to be conveyed into the camp, in order that all might be spectators
                    of the honours paid them at their funeral. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Nothing is so uncertain, or so difficult to form a judgment of, as the minds of
                    the multitude. That which seems calculated to increase their alacrity, in
                    exertions of every sort, often creates in them fear and inactivity. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly, those who, being always accustomed to
                    fight with Greeks and Illyrians, had only seen wounds made with javelins and
                    arrows, seldom even by lances, came to behold bodies dismembered by the Spanish
                    sword, some with their arms lopped off, with the shoulder or the neck entirely
                    cut through, heads severed from the trunk, and the bowels laid open, with other
                    frightful exhibitions of wounds: they therefore perceived, with horror, against
                    what weapons and what men they were to fight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Even the king himself was seized with apprehensions, having never yet engaged
                    the Romans in a regular battle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Wherefore,
                    recalling his son, and the guard posted at the pass of Pelagonia, in order to
                    strengthen his army by the addition of those troops, he thereby opened a passage
                    into Macedonia for Pleuratus and the Dardanians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Then, taking deserters for guides, he marched towards the enemy with twenty
                    thousand foot and four thousand horse, and at the distance of somewhat more than
                    a thousand paces from the Roman camp, and near Ithacus, he fortified a hill with
                    a trench and rampart. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From this place, taking
                    a view of the Roman station in the valley beneath, he is said to have been
                    struck with admiration, both at the general appearance of the camp, and the
                    regular disposition of each particular part; then with the disposition of the
                    tents, and the intervals of the passages; and to have declared, that, certainly,
                    that could not be regarded by any as the camp of barbarians. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> For two days, the consul and the king, each waiting for the
                    other's making some attempt, kept their troops within the ramparts. On the third
                    day, the Roman led out all his forces, and offered battle. <pb n="1377"
                        xml:id="p.1377"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the king, not daring to risk so hastily a
                    general engagement, sent four hundred Trallians, who are a tribe of the
                    Illyrians, as we have said in another place, and three hundred Cretans; adding
                    to this body of infantry an equal number of horse, under the command of
                    Athenagoras, one of his nobles honoured with the purple, to make an attack on
                    the enemy's cavalry. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When these troops arrived
                    within a little more than five hundred paces, the Romans sent out the light
                    infantry, and two cohorts of horse, that both cavalry and infantry might be
                    equal in number to the Macedonians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The king's
                    troops expected that the method of fighting would be such as they had been
                    accustomed to; that the horsemen, pursuing and retreating alternately, would at
                    one time use their weapons, at another time turn their backs; that the agility
                    of the Illyrians would be serviceable for excursions and sudden attacks, and
                    that the Cretans might discharge their arrows against the enemy, as they
                    advanced eagerly to the charge. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the onset
                    of the Romans, which was not more vigorous than persevering, entirely
                    disconcerted this method of fighting: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> for the
                    light infantry, as if they were fighting with their whole line of battle, after
                    discharging their javelins, carried on a close fight with their swords; and the
                    horsemen, when they had once made a charge, stopping their horses, fought, some
                    on horseback, while others dismounted and intermixed themselves with the foot.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By this means neither were the king's
                    cavalry, who were unaccustomed to a steady fight, a match for the others; nor
                    were the infantry, who were only skirmishing and irregular troops, and were
                    besides but half covered with the kind of harness which they used, at all equal
                    to the Roman infantry, who carried a sword and buckler, and were furnished with
                    proper armour, both to defend themselves and to annoy the <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> enemy': nor did they sustain the combat, but fled to their
                    camp, trusting entirely to their speed for safety. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After an interval of one day, the king,
                    resolving to make an attack with all his forces of cavalry and light-armed
                    infantry, had, during the night, placed in ambush, in a <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> convenient place between the two camps, a body of
                    targeteers, whom they call Peltastae, and given orders to Athenagoras and the
                    cavalry, if they found they had the advantage in the open fight, to pursue their
                    success; if otherwise, that they should <pb n="1378" xml:id="p.1378"/> retreat
                    leisurely, and by that means draw on the enemy to the place where the ambush
                    lay. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The cavalry accordingly did retreat; but
                    the officers of the body of targeteers, by bringing forward their men before the
                    time, and not waiting for the signal, as they ought, lost an opportunity of
                    performing considerable service. The Romans, having gained the victory in open
                    fight, and also escaped the danger of the ambuscade, retired to their camp.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Next day the consul marched out with all
                    his forces, and offered battle, placing his elephants in the front of the
                    foremost battalions. Of this resource the Romans then for the first time availed
                    themselves; having a number of them which had been taken in the Punic war.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Finding that the enemy kept himself quiet
                    behind his intrenchments, he advanced close up to them, upbraiding him with
                    cowardice; and as, notwithstanding, no opportunity of an engagement was
                    afforded, the consul, considering how dangerous foraging must be while the camps
                    lay so near each other, where the cavalry were ready at any moment to attack the
                    soldiers, when dispersed through the country, removed his camp to a place called
                    Ortholophus, distant about eight miles, <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    where by reason of the intervening distance he could forage with more safety.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While the Romans were collecting corn in
                    the adjacent fields, the king kept his men within the trenches, in order to
                    increase both the negligence and confidence of the enemy. But, when he saw them
                    scattered, he set out with all his cavalry, and the auxiliary Cretans, and
                    marching with such speed that <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> the swiftest
                    footmen could, by running, but just keep up with the horse, he planted his
                    standards between the camp of the Romans and their foragers. Then, dividing the
                    forces, he sent one part of them in quest of the marauders, with orders to leave
                    not one alive; with the other, he himself halted, and placed guards on the roads
                    through which the enemy seemed likely to fly back to their camp. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> And now carnage and flight prevailed in all
                    directions, and no intelligence of the misfortune had yet reached the Roman
                    camp, because those who fled towards the camp fell in <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> with the guards, which the king had stationed to intercept
                    them, and greater numbers were slain by those who were placed in the roads, than
                    by those who had been sent out to attack them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> At length, a few effected their escape, through the midst of the enemy's
                    posts, but were so filled with terror, that they ex- <pb n="1379"
                        xml:id="p.1379"/> cited a general consternation in the camp, rather than
                    brought intelligible information. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, ordering the cavalry to carry aid
                    to those who were in danger, in the best manner they could, drew out the legions
                    from the camp, and led them drawn up in a square towards the enemy. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The cavalry, taking different ways through the
                    fields, missed the road, being deceived by the various shouts raised in several
                    quarters. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some of them met with the enemy, and
                    battles began in many places at once. The hottest part of the action was at the
                    station where the king commanded; for the guard there was, in numbers both of
                    horse and foot, almost a complete army; and, as they were posted on the middle
                    road, the greatest number of the Romans fell in with them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Macedonians had also the advantage in this, that the
                    king himself was present to encourage them; and the Cretan auxiliaries, fighting
                    in good order, and in a state of preparation, against troops disordered and
                    irregular, wounded many at a distance, where no such danger was apprehended.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If they had acted with prudence in the
                    pursuit, they would have secured an advantage of great importance, not only in
                    regard to the glory of the present contest, but to the general interest of the
                    war; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but, greedy of slaughter, and following
                    with too much eagerness, they fell in with the advanced cohorts of the Romans
                    under the military tribunes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The horsemen who
                    were flying, as soon as they saw the ensigns of their friends, faced about
                    against the enemy, now in disorder; so that in a moment's time the fortune of
                    the battle was changed, those now turning their backs who had lately been the
                    pursuers. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Many were slain in close fight, many
                    in the pursuit; nor was it by the sword alone that they perished; several, being
                    driven into morasses, were, together with their horses, swallowed up in the deep
                    mud. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The king himself was in danger; for his
                    horse falling, in consequence of a wound, threw him headlong to the ground, and
                    he very narrowly escaped being overpowered while prostrate. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> He owed his safety to a trooper, who instantly leaped down
                    and mounted the affrighted king on his horse; himself, as he could not on foot
                    keep up with the flying horsemen, was slain by the enemy, who had collected
                    about the place where Philip fell. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The king,
                    in his desperate flight, rode about among the morasses, some of which were
                    easily passed, and others not; <pb n="1380" xml:id="p.1380"/> at length, when
                    most men despaired of his ever escaping in safety, he arrived in safety at his
                    camp. Two hundred Macedonian horsemen perished in that action; about one hundred
                    were taken: <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> eighty horses, richly
                    caparisoned, were led off the field; at the same time the spoils of arms were
                    also carried off. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There were some who found fault with the king,
                    as guilty of rashness on that day; and with the consul, for want of energy. For
                    Philip, they say, on his part, ought to have avoided coming to action, knowing
                    that in a few days the enemy, having exhausted all the adjacent country, must be
                    reduced to the extremity of want; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and that the
                    consul, after having routed the Macedonian cavalry and light infantry, and
                    nearly taken the king himself, ought to have led on his troops directly to the
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> enemy's camp, where, dismayed as they
                    were, they would have made no stand, and that he might have finished the war in
                    a moment's time. This, like most other matters, was easier to be talked about
                    than to be done. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For, if the king had brought
                    the whole of his infantry into the engagement, then, indeed, during the tumult,
                    and while, vanquished and struck with dismay, they fled from the field into
                    their intrenchments, (and even continued their flight from thence on seeing the
                    victorious enemy mounting the ramparts,) the king might have been deprived of
                    his camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But as some forces of infantry had
                    remained in the camp, fresh and free from fatigue, with outposts before the
                    gates, and guard properly disposed, what would he have done but imitated the
                    rashness of which the king had just now been guilty, by pursuing the routed
                    horse? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the other side, the king's first
                    plan of an attack on the foragers, while dispersed through the fields, would not
                    have been a subject of censure, could he have satisfied himself with a moderate
                    degree of success: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and it is the less
                    surprising that he should have made a trial of fortune, as there was a report,
                    that Pleuratus and the Dardanians had set out from home with very numerous
                    forces, and had already passed into Macedonia; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    so that if he should be surrounded on all sides by these forces, there was
                    reason to think that the Roman might put an end to the war without stirring from
                    his seat. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Philip, however, considered, that
                    after his cavalry had been defeated in two engagements, he could with much less
                    safety continue in the same post; accordingly, wish- <pb n="1381"
                        xml:id="p.1381"/> ing to remove from thence, and, at the same time, to keep
                    the enemy in ignorance of his design, he sent a herald to the consul a little
                    before sun-set, to demand a truce for the purpose of burying the horsemen;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and thus imposing on him, he began his
                    march in silence, about the second watch, leaving a number of fires in all parts
                    of his camp. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul was now taking refreshment, when he
                    was told that the herald had arrived, and on what business; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> he gave him no other answer, than that he should be
                    admitted to an audience early the next morning: by which means Philip gained
                    what he wanted —the length of that night, and part of the following day, during
                    which he might get the start on his march. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                    directed his route towards the mountains, a road which he knew the Romans with
                    their heavy baggage would not attempt. The consul, having, at the first light,
                    dismissed the herald with a grant of a truce, in a short time after discovered
                    that the enemy had gone off; but not knowing what course to take in pursuit of
                    them, he remained in the same camp for several days, which he employed in
                    collecting forage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then marched to Stubera,
                    and brought thither, from Pelagonia, the corn that was in the fields. From
                    thence he advanced to Pluvina, not having yet discovered to what quarter the
                    Macedonian had bent his course. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Philip, having
                    at first fixed his camp at Bryanium, marched thence through cross-roads, and
                    gave a sudden alarm to the enemy. The Romans, on this, removed from Pluvina, and
                    pitched their camp near the river Osphagus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The king also sat down at a small distance, forming his intrenchment on the bank
                    of a river which the inhabitants call Erigonus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Having there received certain information that the Romans intended to proceed
                    to Eordaea, he marched away before them, in order to take possession of the
                    defiles, and prevent the enemy from making their way, where the roads are
                    confined in narrow straits. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There, with great
                    haste, he fortified some places with a rampart, others with a trench, others
                    with stones heaped up instead of walls, others with trees laid across, according
                    as the situation required, or as materials lay convenient; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and thus a road, in its own nature difficult, he rendered,
                    as he imagined, impregnable by the works which he drew across every pass.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The adjoining ground, being mostly
                    covered with woods, was exceedingly incommodious to the phalanx of <pb n="1382"
                        xml:id="p.1382"/> the Macedonians, which is of no manner of use, except when
                    they extend their very long spears before their shields, forming as it were a
                    palisade; to perform which, they require an open plain. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The Thracians, too, were embarrassed by their lances, which
                    also are of a great length, and were entangled among the branches that stood in
                    their way on every side. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The body of Cretans
                    alone was not unserviceable; and yet even these, though, in case of an attack
                    made on them, they could to good purpose discharge their arrows against the
                    horses or riders, where they were open to a wound, yet against the Roman shields
                    they could do nothing, because they had neither strength sufficient to pierce
                    through them, nor was there any part exposed at which they could aim. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Perceiving, therefore, that kind of weapon to be
                    useless, they annoyed the enemy with stones, which lay in plenty in all parts of
                    the valley: the strokes made by these on their shields, with greater noise than
                    injury, for a short time retarded the advance of the Romans; <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> but quickly disregarding these missiles also, some, closing
                    their shields in form of a tortoise, forced their way through the enemy in
                    front; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> others having, by a short circuit,
                    gained the summit of the hill, dislodged the dismayed Macedonians from their
                    guards and posts, and even slew the greater part of them, their retreat being
                    embarrassed by the difficulties of the ground. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thus, with less opposition than they had
                    expected to meet, the defiles were passed, and they came to Eordaea; then,
                    having laid waste the whole country, the consul withdrew into Elimea. From
                    thence he made an irruption into Orestis, and attacked the city Celetrum,
                    situated in a peninsula: a lake surrounds the walls; and there is but one
                    entrance from the main land along a narrow isthmus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Relying on their situation, the townsmen at first shut the
                    gates, and refused to submit; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but afterwards,
                    when they saw the troops in motion, and advancing in the tortoise method, and
                    the isthmus covered by the enemy marching in, they surrendered in terror rather
                    than hazard a struggle. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From Celetrum he
                    advanced into the country of the Dassaretians, took the city Pelium by storm,
                    carried off the slaves with the rest of the spoil, and discharging the freemen
                    without ransom, restored the city to them, after placing a strong garrison in
                    it, for it was very conveniently situated for making inroads into Macedonia.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1383" xml:id="p.1383"/> Having thus traversed the enemy's country, the
                    consul led back his forces into those parts which were already reduced to
                    obedience near Apollonia, from whence the campaign had commenced. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Philip's attention had been drawn to other quarters
                    by the Aetolians, Athamanians, and Dardanians: so many were the wars that
                    started up on different sides of him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Against
                    the Dardanians, who were now retiring out of Macedonia, he sent Athenagoras with
                    the light infantry and the greater part of the cavalry, and ordered him to hang
                    on their rear as they retreated; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and, by
                    cutting off their hindmost troops, make them more cautious for the future of
                    leading out their armies from home. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As to the
                    Aetolians, Damocritus, their praetor, the same who at Naupactum had persuaded
                    them to defer passing a decree concerning the war, had in the next meeting
                    roused them to arms, after the report of the battle between the cavalry at
                    Ortholophus; the irruption of the Dardanians and of Pleuratus, with the
                    Illyrians, into Macedonia; of the arrival of the Roman fleet, too, at Oreus;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that Macedonia, besides being beset
                    on all sides by so many nations, was in danger of being invested by sea also. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These reasons had brought back Damocritus and
                    the Aetolians to the interest of the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Marching out, therefore, in conjunction with Amynander, king of the Athamanians,
                    they laid siege to Cercinium. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The inhabitants
                    here had shut their gates, whether of their own choice or by compulsion is
                    unknown, as they had a garrison of the king's troops. However, in a few days
                    Cercinium was taken and burned; and after great slaughter had been made, those
                    who survived, both freemen and slaves, were carried off amongst other spoil.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This caused such terror, as made all those
                    who dwelt round the lake Baebius abandon their cities and fly to the mountains:
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and the Aetolians, in the absence of
                    booty, turned away from thence, and proceeded into Perrhaebia. There they took
                    Cyretiae by storm and sacked it unmercifully. The inhabitants of Mallœa, making
                    a voluntary submission, were received into alliance. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> From Perrhaebia, Amynander advised to march to Gomphi,
                    because that city lies close to Athamania, and there was reason to think that it
                    might be reduced without any great difficulty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But the Aetolians, for the sake of plunder, directed their march to the rich
                    plains of Thessaly. Amynander following, though he <pb n="1384" xml:id="p.1384"
                    /> did not approve either of their careless method of carrying on their
                    depredations, or of their pitching their camp in any place which chance
                    presented, without choice, and without taking any care to fortify it. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Therefore, lest their rashness and negligence might
                    be the cause of some misfortune to himself and his troops, when he saw them
                    forming their camp in low grounds, under the city Phecadus, he took possession,
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> with his own troops, of an eminence
                    about five hundred paces distant, which could be rendered secure by a slight
                    fortification. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Aetolians seemed to have
                    forgotten that they were in an enemy's country, excepting that they continued to
                    plunder, some straggling about half-armed, others spending whole days and nights
                    alike in drinking and sleeping in the camp, neglecting even to fix guards, when
                    Philip unexpectedly came upon them. His approach being announced by those who
                    had fled out of the fields in a fright, Damocritus and the rest of the officers
                    were thrown into great confusion. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It happened
                    to be mid-day, and when most of the men after a hearty meal lay fast asleep.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their officers roused them, however, as
                    fast as possible; ordered them to take arms; despatched some to recall those who
                    were straggling through the fields in search of plunder; and so violent was
                    their hurry, that many of the horsemen went out without their swords, and but
                    few of them put on their corslets. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After
                    marching out in this precipitate manner, (the whole horse and foot scarcely
                    making up six hundred,) they met the king's cavalry, superior in number, in
                    spirit, and in arms. They were, therefore, routed at the first charge; and
                    having scarcely attempted resistance, returned to the camp in shameful flight.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Several were slain; and some taken,
                    having been cut off from the main body of the fugitives. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, when his troops had advanced almost to
                    the rampart, ordered a retreat to be sounded, because both men and horses were
                    fatigued, not so much by the action, as at once by the length of their march,
                    and the extraordinary celerity with which they had made it. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore despatched the horsemen by troops, and the
                    companies of light infantry in turn, to procure water and take refreshment.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The rest he kept on guard, under arms,
                    waiting for the main body of the infantry, which had marched with less
                    expedition, on account of the weight of their armour. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> As soon as these <pb n="1385" xml:id="p.1385"/> arrived,
                    they also were ordered to fix their standards, and, laying down their arms
                    before them, to take food in haste; sending two, or at most three, out of each
                    company, to provide water. In the mean time the cavalry and light infantry stood
                    in order, and ready, in case the enemy should make any movement. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Aetolians, as if resolved to defend their
                    fortifications, (the multitude which had been scattered about the fields having,
                    by this time, returned to the camp,) posted bodies of armed men at the gates,
                    and on the rampart, and from this safe situation looked with a degree of
                    confidence on the enemy, as long as they continued quiet. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But, as soon as the troops of the Macedonians began to
                    move, and to advance to the rampart, in order of battle, and ready for an
                    assault, they all quickly abandoned their posts, and fled through the opposite
                    part of the camp, to the eminence where the Athamanians were stationed. During
                    their flight in this confusion, many of the Aetolians were slain, and many made
                    prisoners. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Philip doubted not that, had there
                    been day-light enough remaining, he should have been able to make himself master
                    of the camp of the Athamanians also; but the day having been spent in the fight,
                    and in plundering the camp afterwards, he sat down under the eminence, in the
                    adjacent plain, determined to attack the enemy at the first dawn of the
                    following day. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the Aetolians, under the
                    same apprehensions which had made them desert their camp, dispersed, and fled
                    during the following night. Amynander was of the greatest service; for, by his
                    directions, the Athamanians, who were acquainted with the roads, conducted them
                    into Aetolia, whilst the Macedonians pursued them over the highest mountains,
                    through unknown paths. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In this disorderly
                    flight, a few, missing their way, fell into the hands of the Macedonian
                    horsemen, whom Philip, at the earliest dawn, on seeing the eminence abandoned,
                    had sent to harass the marching body of the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time also Athenagoras, one of
                    the king's generals, overtaking the Dardanians in their retreat homeward, at
                    first threw their rear into disorder; but these unexpectedly facing about, and
                    forming their line, the fight became like a regular engagement. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When the Dardanians began again to advance, the Macedonian
                    cavalry and light infantry harassed those who had no troops of that kind to aid
                        <pb n="1386" xml:id="p.1386"/> them, and were, besides, burdened with
                    unwieldy arms. The ground, too, favoured the assailants: very few were slain,
                    but many wounded; none were taken, because they rarely quit their ranks, but
                    both fight and retreat in a close body. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Thus
                    Philip, having checked the proceedings of those two nations by these well-timed
                    expeditions, gained reparation for the damages sustained from the operations of
                    the Romans; the enterprise being as spirited as the issue was successful.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> An occurrence which accidentally happened
                    to him lessened the number of his enemies on the side of AEtolia. Scopas, a man
                    of considerable influence in his own country, having been sent from Alexandria
                    by king Ptolemy, with a great sum of gold, hired and carried away to Egypt six
                    thousand foot and four hundred horse; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> nor
                    would he have suffered one of the young Aetolians to remain at home, had not
                    Damocritus, (it is not easy to say, whether out of zeal for the good of the
                    nation, or out of opposition to <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> Scopas, for
                    not having secured his interest by presents,) by sometimes reminding them of the
                    war which threatened them, at other times, of <milestone n="7??" unit="section"
                    /> the solitary condition in which they would be, detained some of them at home
                    by severe reproaches. Such were the actions of the Romans, and of Philip, during
                    that summer. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the same summer, the fleet
                    under Lucius Apustius, lieutenant-general, setting sail from Corcyra, and
                    passing by Malea, formed a junction with king Attalus, off Scyllaeum, which lies
                    in the district of Hermione. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Athenian
                    state, which had for a long time, through fear, restrained their animosity
                    against Philip within some bounds, in the expectation of approaching aid
                    afforded them, gave full scope to it all. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    There are never wanting in that city orators, who are ready on every occasion to
                    inflame the people; a kind of men, who, in all free states, and more
                    particularly in that of Athens, where eloquence flourishes in the highest
                    degree, are maintained by the favour of the multitude. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> These immediately proposed a decree, and the commons passed
                    it, that <quote> all the statues and images of Philip, with their inscriptions,
                        and likewise those of all his ancestors, male and female, should be taken
                        down and destroyed; that the festal days, solemnities, and priests, which
                        had been instituted in honour of him or of his predecessors, should all be
                        abolished; and that even the ground where any such statue <pb n="1387"
                            xml:id="p.1387"/> had been set up, and inscribed to his honour, should
                        be held abominable. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And it was resolved, that, <quote> for the
                        future, nothing which ought to be erected or dedicated in a place of purity
                        should be there erected; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and that the
                        public priests, as often as they should pray for the people of Athens, for
                        their allies, armies, and fleets, so often should they utter curses and
                        execrations against Philip, his offspring, his kingdom, his forces by sea
                        and land, and the whole race and name of the Macedonians. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was added to the decree, that, <quote> if
                        any person in future should make any proposal tending to throw disgrace and
                        ignominy on Philip, the people of Athens would ratify it in its fullest
                        extent: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> if, on the contrary, any one
                        should, by word or deed, endeavour to lessen his ignominy, or to do him
                        honour, that whoever slew him who should have so said or done, should be
                        justified in so doing. </quote> Lastly, a clause was annexed, that <quote>
                        all the decrees, formerly passed against the Pisistratidae, should be in
                        full force against Philip. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus the Athenians waged war against Philip
                    with writings and with words, in which alone their power consisted. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Attalus and the Romans, having, from Hermione,
                    proceeded first to Piraeus, and staid there a <milestone n="2??" unit="section"
                    /> few days, after being loaded with decrees of the Athenians, (in which the
                    honours paid to their allies were as extravagant as the expressions of their
                    resentment against <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> their enemy had been,)
                    sailed from Piraeeus to Andros, and, coming to an anchor in the harbour called
                    Gaureleos, sent persons to sound the inclinations of the townsmen, whether they
                    chose voluntarily to surrender their city, rather than run the hazard of an
                    assault. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On their answering, that they were
                    not at their own disposal, but that the citadel was occupied by the king's
                    troops, Attalus and the Roman lieutenant-general, landing their forces, with
                    every thing requisite for attacking towns, made their approaches to the city on
                    different sides. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman standards and arms,
                    which they had never seen before, together with the spirit of the soldiers, so
                    briskly approaching the walls, were particularly terrifying to the Greeks. A
                    retreat was immediately made into the citadel, and the enemy took possession of
                    the city. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After holding out for two days in
                    the citadel, relying more on the strength of the place than on their arms, on
                    the third both they and the garrison surrendered the city and citadel, on
                    condition of their being transported to Delium in Bœotia, and <pb n="1388"
                        xml:id="p.1388"/> being each of them allowed a single suit of apparel.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The island was yielded up by the Romans to
                    king Attalus; the spoil, and the ornaments of the city, they themselves carried
                    off. Attalus, desirous that the island, of which he had got possession, might
                    not be quite deserted, persuaded almost all the Macedonians, and several of the
                    Andrians, to remain there: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and, in some time
                    after, those who, according to the capitulation, had been transported to Delium,
                    were induced to return from thence by the promises made them by the king, in
                    which they were disposed the more readily to confide, by the ardent affection
                    which they felt for their native country. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From
                    Andros they passed over to Cythnus; there they spent several days, to no
                    purpose, in assaulting the city; when, at length, finding it scarcely worth the
                    trouble, they departed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At Prasiae, a place
                    on the main land of Attica, twenty barks of the Issaeans joined the Roman fleet.
                    These were sent to ravage the lands of the Carystians, the rest of the fleet
                    lying at Geraestus, a noted harbour in Eubœa, until the Issaeans returned from
                    Carystus: on which, setting sail all together, and steering their course through
                    the open sea, until they passed by Scyrus, they arrived at the island of Icus.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Being detained there for a few days by a
                    violent northerly wind, as soon as the weather was fair, they passed over to
                        <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> Sciathus, a city which had been lately
                    plundered and desolated by Philip. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    soldiers, spreading themselves over the country, brought back to the ships corn
                    and what other kinds of provisions could be of use to them. Plunder there was
                    none, nor had the Greeks deserved to be plundered. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Directing their course thence to Cassandrea, they first
                    came to Mendis, a village on the coast of that state; and, intending from thence
                    to double the promontory, and bring round the fleet to the very walls of the
                    city, a violent tempest arising, they were near being buried in the waves.
                    However, after being dispersed, and a great part of the ships having lost their
                    rigging, they escaped on shore. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> This storm at
                    sea was an omen of the kind of success which they were to meet on land; for,
                    after collecting their vessels together, and landing their forces, having made
                    an assault on the city, they were repulsed with many wounds, there being a
                    strong garrison of the king's troops in the place. Being thus obliged to retreat
                    without accom- plishing their design, they passed over to Canastrum in <pb
                        n="1389" xml:id="p.1389"/> Pallene, and from thence, doubling the promontory
                    of Torona, conducted the fleet to Acanthus. There they first laid waste the
                    country, then stormed the city itself, and plundered it. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> They proceeded no farther, for their ships were now heavily
                    laden with booty, but went back to Sciathus, and from Sciathus to Eubœa, whence
                    they had first set out. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Leaving the fleet there, they entered the
                    Malian bay with ten light ships, in order to confer with the Aetolians on the
                    method of conducting the war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Sipyrrhicas, the
                    Aetolian, was at the head of the embassy that came to Heraclea, to hold a
                    consultation with the king and the Roman lieutenant-general. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They demanded of Attalus, that, in pursuance of the treaty,
                    he should supply them with one thousand soldiers, which number he had engaged
                    for on condition of their taking part in the war against Philip. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> This was refused to the Aetolians, because on their
                    part they had formerly showed themselves unwilling to march out to ravage
                    Macedonia, at a time when Philip, being employed near Pergamus in destroying by
                    fire every thing sacred and profane, they might have compelled him to retire
                    from thence, in order to preserve his own territories. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Thus, instead of aid, the Aetolians were dismissed with
                    hopes, the Romans making them large promises. Apustius with Attalus returned to
                    the ships, where they began to concert measures for the siege of Oreus.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This city was well secured by
                    fortifications; and also, as an attempt had formerly been made on it, by a
                    strong garrison. After the taking of Andros, twenty Rhodian ships, all decked
                    vessels, had formed a junction with them, under the command of Agesimbrotus.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This squadron they sent to the station off
                    Zelasium, a promontory of Isthmia, very conveniently situate beyond Demetrias,
                    in order that, if the ships of the Macedonians should attempt any movement, they
                    might act as a defensive force. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Heraclides,
                    the king's admiral, kept his fleet there, rather with a view of laying hold of
                    any advantage which the negligence of the enemy might afford him, than with a
                    design of attempting any thing by open force. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans and king Attalus carried on their attacks against Oreus on different
                    sides; the Romans against the citadel next to the sea, the king's troops against
                    the lower part of the town, lying between the two citadels, where the city is
                    also divided by a wall. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As their posts were
                    different, so were their methods of <pb n="1390" xml:id="p.1390"/> attack: the
                    Romans made their approaches by means of covered galleries, applying also the
                    ram to the walls; the king's troops, by throwing in weapons with the balista,
                    catapulta, and every other kind of engine, and stones also of immense weight.
                    They formed mines, too, and made use of every expedient, which, on trial, had
                    been found useful in the former siege. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the
                    other side, not only did more Macedonians protect the town and the citadels,
                    than on the former occasion, but they exerted themselves with greater spirit, in
                    consequence of the reprimands which they had received from the king for the
                    misconduct they had committed, and also from remembrance both of his threats and
                    promises with regard to the future. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thus,
                    when time was being consumed there, contrary to their expectation, and there was
                    more hope from a siege and works than from a sudden assault, the
                    lieutenant-general thought that in the mean time some other business. might be
                    accomplished; wherefore, leaving such a number of men as seemed sufficient to
                    finish the works, he passed over to the nearest part of the continent, and,
                    arriving unexpectedly, made himself master of Larissa, except the citadel, —not
                    that celebrated city in Thessaly, but another, which they call Cremaste.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Attalus also surprised Aegeleos, where
                    nothing was less apprehended than such an enterprise during the siege of another
                    city. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The works at Oreus had now begun to
                    take effect, while the garrison within were almost spent with unremitted toil,
                    (keeping watch both by day and night,) and also with wounds. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Part of the wall, being loosened by the strokes of the ram,
                    had fallen down in many places; and the Romans, during the night, broke into the
                    citadel through the breach which lay over the harbour. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> Attalus, likewise, at the first light, on a signal given
                    from the citadel by the Romans, himself also assaulted the city, where great
                    part of the walls had been levelled; on which the garrison and townsmen fled
                    into the other citadel, and a surrender was made two days after. The city fell
                    to the king, the prisoners to the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The autumnal equinox now approached, and the
                    Eubœan gulf, called Cœla, is reckoned dangerous by mariners. Choosing,
                    therefore, to remove thence before the winter storms came on, they returned to
                    Piraeus, from whence they had set out for the campaign. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Apustius, leaving there thirty <pb n="1391" xml:id="p.1391"
                    /> ships, sailed by Malea to Corcyra. The king was delayed during the
                    celebration of the mysteries of Ceres, that he might assist at the solemnities,
                    immediately after which he also retired into Asia, sending home Agesimbrotus and
                    the Rhodians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Such, during that summer, were
                    the proceedings, by sea and land, of the Roman consul and lieutenant-general,
                    aided by Attalus and the Rhodians, against Philip and his allies. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The other consul, Caius Aurelius, on coming into his
                    province, and finding the war there already brought to a conclusion, did not
                    dissemble his resentment against the praetor, for having proceeded to action in
                    his absence; wherefore, sending him away to Etruria, he led on the legions into
                    the enemy's country, and, by laying it waste, carried on the war with more spoil
                    than glory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Lucius Furius, finding nothing in
                    Etruria that could give him employment, and at the same time intent <milestone
                        n="6??" unit="section"/> on obtaining a triumph for his success against the
                    Gauls, which he considered would be more easily accomplished in the absence of
                    the consul, who envied and was enraged against him, came to Rome unexpectedly,
                    and called a meeting of the senate in the temple of Bellona; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> where, after making a recital of the services which he had
                    performed, he demanded to be allowed to enter the city in triumph. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With a great part of the senate he prevailed,
                    owing to private interest and the importance of his services. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The elder part refused him a triumph, both <quote> because
                        the army, with which he had acted, belonged to another; and because he had
                        left his province through an ambitious desire of snatching that opportunity
                        of procuring a triumph, —but <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that he had
                        taken this course without any precedent. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senators of consular rank particularly
                    insisted, that <quote> he ought to have waited for the consul; for that he
                        might, by pitching his camp near the city, and thereby securing the colony
                        without coming to an engagement, have protracted the affair until his
                        arrival; and that, what the praetor had not done, the senate ought to do;
                        they should wait for the consul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After
                        hearing the business discussed by the consul and praetor in their presence,
                        they would be able, more correctly, to form a judgment on the case. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Great part were of opinion, that the senate
                    ought to consider nothing but the service performed, and whether he had
                    performed it while in office, and under his own auspices. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> For, <quote> when of two colonies, which had been <pb
                            n="1392" xml:id="p.1392"/> opposed, as barriers, to restrain the
                        tumultuous inroads of the Gauls, one had been already sacked and burned, the
                        flames being ready to spread (as if from an adjoining house) to the other
                        colony, which lay so near, what ought the praetor to have done? <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> For if it was improper to enter on any action
                        without the consul, then the senate had acted wrong in giving the army to
                        the praetor; because, if they chose that the business should be performed,
                        not under the praetor's auspices, but the consul's, they might have limited
                        the decree in such a manner, that not the praetor, but the consul, should
                        manage it; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> or else the consul had acted
                        wrong, who, after ordering the army to remove from Etruria into Gaul, did
                        not meet it at Ariminum, in order to be present at operations, which were
                        not allowed to be performed without him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        But the exigencies of war do not wait for the delays and procrastinations of
                        commanders; and battles must be sometimes fought, not because commanders
                        choose it, but because the enemy compels it. The fight itself, and the issue
                        of the fight, is what ought to be regarded now. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The enemy were routed and slain, their camp taken and
                        plundered, the colony relieved from a siege, the prisoners taken from the
                        other colony recovered and restored to their friends, and an end put to the
                        war in one battle. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And not only men
                        rejoiced at this victory, but the immortal gods also had supplications paid
                        to them, for the space of three days, on account of the business of the
                        state having been wisely and successfully, not rashly and unfortunately,
                        conducted by Lucius Furius, praetor. Besides, the Gallic wars were, by some
                        fatality, destined to the Furian family. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By means of discourses of this kind, made by
                    him and his friends, the interest of the praetor, who was present, prevailed
                    over the dignity of the absent consul, and the majority decreed a triumph to
                    Lucius Furius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Lucius Furius, praetor, during
                    his office, triumphed over the Gauls. He carried into the treasury three hundred
                    and twenty thousand <hi rend="italics">asses,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1033 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and one hundred and seventy thousand pounds' weight of silver.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There were neither any prisoners led
                    before his chariot, nor spoils carried before him, nor did any soldiers follow
                    him. It appeared that every thing, except the victory, belonged to the consul.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The games which Publius Scipio had vowed
                    when consul in Africa, were then celebrated, in a magnificent <pb n="1393"
                        xml:id="p.1393"/> manner, and with <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    respect to the lands for his soldiers, it was decreed, that whatever number of
                    years each of them had served in Spain or in Africa, he should, for every year,
                    receive two acres; and that ten commissioners should distribute that land.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Three commissioners were then appointed to
                    fill up the number of colonists at Venusia, because the strength of that colony
                    had been reduced in the war with Hannibal: Caius Terentius Varro, Titus Quintius
                    Flamininus, Publius Cornelius, son of Cneius Scipio, enrolled the colonists for
                    Venusia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During the same year, Caius Cornelius
                    Cethegus, who in the capacity of proconsul commanded in Spain, routed a numerous
                    army of the enemy in the territory of Sedeta; in which battle, it is said, that
                    fifteen thousand Spaniards were slain, and seventy-eight military standards
                    taken. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consul Caius Aurelius, on returning
                    from his province to Rome to hold the elections, made heavy complaints, not on
                    the subject on which they had supposed he would, that the senate had not waited
                    for his coming, nor allowed him an opportunity of arguing the matter with the
                    praetor; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but, that "the senate had decreed a
                    triumph in such a manner, without hearing the report of any one of those who had
                    taken part in the war, except the person who was to enjoy the triumph:
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that their ancestors had made it a rule
                    that the lieutenant-generals, the military tribunes, the centurions, and even
                    the soldiers, should be present at the triumph, in order that the Roman people
                    might ascertain the reality of his exploits, to whom so high an honour was paid.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Now, of that army which fought with the
                    Gauls, had any one soldier, or even a soldier's servant, been present, of whom
                    the senate could inquire how much of truth or falsehood was in the praetor's
                    narrative? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He then appointed a day for the
                    elections, at which were chosen consuls, Lucius Cornelius Lentulus and Publius
                    Villius Tappulus. The praetors were then appointed, Lucius Quintius Flamininus,
                    Lucius Valerius Flaccus, Lucius Villius Tappulus, and Cneius Baebius Tamphilus. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During that year provisions were remarkably
                    cheap. The curule aediles, Marcus Claudius Marcellus and Sextus Aelius Paetus,
                    distributed among the people a vast quantity of corn, brought from Africa, at
                    the rate of two <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> a peck. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They also celebrated the Roman games in a magnificent
                    manner, repeating them a second day; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and
                    erected in the treasury five brazen statues out of the money paid as fines.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1394" xml:id="p.1394"/> The plebeian games were thrice repeated entire,
                    by the aediles, Lucius Terentius Massa, and Cneius Baebius Tamphilus, who was
                    elected praetor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There were also funeral games
                    exhibited that year in the forum, for the space of four days, on occasion of the
                    death of Marcus Valerius Laevinus, by <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> his
                    sons Publius and Marcus, who gave also a show of gladiators, in which
                    twenty-five pairs fought. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcus Aurelius
                    Cotta, one of the decemviri of the sacred books, died, and Manius Acilius
                    Glabrio was substituted in his room. It happened that both the curule aediles,
                    who had been created at the elections, were persons who could not immediately
                    undertake the office: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> for Caius Cornelius
                    Cethegus was elected in his absence, when he was occupying Spain as his
                    province; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and Caius Valerius Flaccus, who was
                    present, being flamen Dialis, could not take the oath of observing the laws; and
                    no person was allowed to hold any office longer than five days without taking
                    the oath. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Flaccus petitioned to be excused
                    from complying with the law, on which the senate decreed, that if the aedile
                    produced a person approved of by the consuls, who would take the oath for him,
                    the consuls, if they thought proper, should make application to the tribunes,
                    that it might be proposed to the people. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Valerius Flaccus, praetor elect, was produced to swear for his brother.
                    The tribunes proposed to the commons, and the commons ordered that this should
                    be as if the aedile himself had sworn. With regard to the other aedile,
                    likewise, an order of the commons was made. On the tribunes putting the
                    question, what two persons they chose should go and take the command of the
                    armies in Spain, in order that Caius Cornelius, curule aedile, might come home
                    to execute his office, and that Lucius Manlius Acidinus might, after many years,
                    retire from the province; the commons ordered Cneius Cornelius Lentulus and
                    Lucius Stertinius, proconsuls, to command in Spain. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
