<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 31</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="book">
                <head>Rome and Macedon</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> I, too, feel as much relief in having
                        reached the end of the Punic War as if I had taken a personal part in its
                        toils and dangers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It ill befits one who
                        has had the courage to promise a complete history of Rome to find the
                        separate sections of such an extensive work fatiguing. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> But when I consider that the sixty-three years from the
                        beginning of the First Punic War to the end of the Second take up as many
                        books as the four hundred and eighty-seven years from the foundation of the
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> City to the consulship of Appius
                        Claudius under whom the First Punic War commenced, I see that I am like
                        people who are tempted by the shallow water along the beach to wade out to
                        sea; the further I progress, the greater the depth, as though it were a
                        bottomless sea, into which I am carried. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I
                        imagined that as I completed one part after another the task before me would
                        diminish; as it is, it almost becomes greater. The peace with Carthage was
                        very soon followed by war with Macedonia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        There is no comparison between them as regards the critical nature of the
                        contest, or the personality of the commander or the fighting quality of the
                        troops. But the Macedonian war was, if anything, more noteworthy owing to
                        the brilliant reputation of the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> former
                        kings, the ancient fame of the nation and the vast extent of its dominion
                        when it held sway over a large part of Europe and a still larger part of
                        Asia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The war with Philip which had
                        commenced some ten years previously had been suspended for the last three
                        years, and both the war and its cessation were due to the action of the
                        Aetolians. The peace with Carthage now left the Romans free. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> They were angry with Philip for his attacking the
                        Aetolians and the other friendly States in Greece while he was nominally at
                        peace with Rome, and also for his having given assistance in both men and
                        money to Hannibal and Carthage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He had
                        ravaged the Athenian territory and driven the inhabitants into the city, and
                        it was their request for help which decided the Romans to recommence the
                        war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just about the same time envoys arrived
                        from King Attalus and also from Rhodes with the information that Philip was
                        trying to gain the States of Asia Minor. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The reply made to both deputations was that the situation in Asia was
                        engaging the attention of the senate. The question of war with Macedonia was
                        referred to the consuls, who were at the time in their respective provinces.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the meanwhile, C. Claudius Nero, M.
                        Aemilius Lepidus and P. Sempronius Tuditanus were sent on a mission to
                        Ptolemy, king of Egypt, to announce the final defeat of Hannibal and the
                        Carthaginians and to thank the king for having remained a staunch friend to
                        Rome at a critical time, when even her nearest allies deserted her.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were further to request him, in
                        case Philip's aggressions compelled them to declare war against him, that he
                        would maintain his old friendly attitude towards the Romans. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> During this period P. Aelius, the consul who was
                        commanding in Gaul, learnt that the Boii, prior to his arrival, had been
                        raiding the territories of friendly tribes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> He hastily raised a force of two legions in view of this disturbance and
                        strengthened it with four cohorts from his own army. This force, thus
                        hurriedly collected, he entrusted to C. Ampius, a prefect of allies, and
                        ordered him to march through the canton of Umbria called Sapinia and invade
                        the country of the Boii. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He himself
                        marched over the mountains by an open road. Ampius crossed the enemy's
                        frontier, and after devastating his country without meeting any resistance,
                        he selected a position at the fortified post of Mutilum as a suitable place
                        for cutting the corn which was now ripe. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        He commenced the task without previously examining the neighbourhood or
                        posting armed parties in sufficient strength to protect the foragers, who
                        had laid aside their weapons and were intent on their work. Suddenly he and
                        his foragers were surprised by the Gauls who appeared on all sides.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The panic and disorder extended to the
                        men on guard; 7000 men who were dispersed through the cornfields were
                        killed, amongst them C. Ampius himself, the rest fled to the camp.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The following night the soldiers, as
                        they had no regular commander, decided to act for themselves, and leaving
                        most of their possessions behind made their way through almost impassable
                        forests to the consul. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Beyond ravaging
                        the Boian country and making a league with the Ligurian Ingauni the consul
                        did nothing worth mentioning in his province before his return to Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the first meeting of the senate after
                        his return there was a general demand that the action of Philip and the
                        grievances of the friendly States should take precedence of all other
                        business. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The question was at once put in
                        a crowded House and a decree was made that the consul P. Aelius should send
                        the man whom he thought best, with full command to take over the fleet which
                        Cn. Octavius was bringing back from Africa and proceed to Macedonia.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He selected M. Valerius Laevinus, who
                        was sent with the rank of propraetor. Laevinus took thirty-eight of
                        Octavius' ships which were lying at anchor off Vibo and with these he sailed
                        for Macedonia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He was met by M. Aurelius,
                        who gave him details about the strength of the land and sea forces which the
                        king had got <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> together and the extent to
                        which he was securing armed assistance not only from the cities on the
                        mainland, but also from the islands in the Aegean, partly by his own
                        personal influence, partly through his agents. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Aurelius pointed out that the Romans would have to
                        display far greater energy in the prosecution of this war, or else Philip,
                        encouraged by their slackness, would venture on the same enterprise which
                        Pyrrhus, whose kingdom was considerably smaller, had ventured on before. It
                        was decided that Aurelius should send this information in a despatch to the
                        consuls and the senate. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Towards the close of the year the question
                        was brought up as to the holdings which were to be assigned to the veteran
                        soldiers who had served with Scipio in Africa. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The senator decreed that M. Junius, the City praetor,
                        should at his discretion appoint ten commissioners for the purpose of
                        measuring and allotting that portion of the Samnite and Apulian territory
                        which had become State domain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        commissioners were P. Servilius, Q. Caecilius Marcellus, the two Servilii,
                        Caius and Marcus-who were known as "The Twins"-the two Hostilii Catones,
                        Lucius and Aulus, P. Villius Tappulus, M. Fulvius Flaccus, P. Aelius Paetus
                        and T. Quinctius Flamininus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The elections
                        were conducted by the consul P. Aelius. The consuls-elect were P. Sulpicius
                        Galba and C. Aurelius Cotta. The new praetors were Q. Minucius Rufus, L.
                        Furius Purpureo, Q. Fulvius Gillo and C. Sergius Plancus. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The Roman Scenic Games were celebrated this year with
                        unusual splendour by the curule aediles, L. Valerius Flaccus and T.
                        Quinctius Flamininus, and were repeated for a second day. They also
                        distributed to the people with strict impartiality and to the general
                        satisfaction a vast quantity of corn which Scipio had sent from Africa.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was sold at four ases the modius.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Plebeian Games were also exhibited
                        on three separate occasions by the aediles L. Apustius Fullo and Q. Minucius
                        Rufus; the latter after serving his aedileship was one of the newly-elected
                        praetors. The Festival of Jupiter was also celebrated. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the 551st year from the foundation of
                        the City, during the consulship of P. Sulpicius Galba and C. Aurelius and
                        within a few months of the conclusion of peace with Carthage, the war with
                        King Philip began. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On March 15, the day on
                        which the consuls entered office, P. Sulpicius made this the first business
                        before the senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A decree was made that
                        the consuls should sacrifice full-grown victims to those deities whom they
                        might decide upon, and should offer up the following prayer: <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> "May the will and purpose of the senate and
                        people of Rome as regards the commonwealth and the entrance upon a new war
                        have a prosperous and happy issue both for the Roman people and for the
                        Latin allies!" After the sacrifice and prayer the consuls were to consult
                        the senate as to the policy to be pursued and the allocation of provinces.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Just at this time the war-spirit was
                        stimulated by the receipt of the despatches from M. Aurelius and M. Valerius
                        Laevinus as well as by a fresh embassy from Athens which announced that the
                        king was nearing their frontiers and would soon be master of their territory
                        and of their city as well if Rome did not come to the rescue. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls reported the due performance of the
                        sacrifices and the declaration of the augurs that the gods had listened to
                        their prayer, for the victims had given favourable omens and portended
                        victory, triumph, and an enlargement of the dominion of Rome. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Then the despatches from Valerius and Aurelius
                        were read and an audience given to the Athenian envoys. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> A resolution was passed by the senate that thanks be
                        given to their allies for remaining loyal in spite of continual attempts to
                        seduce them and even when threatened with a siege. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> With regard to giving active assistance the senate
                        deferred a definite answer until the consuls had balloted for their
                        provinces, and the one to whom the Macedonian province fell had submitted to
                        the people the question of declaring war against Philip of Macedon. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This province fell to P. Sulpicius, and he
                        gave notice that he should propose to the Assembly that "owing to the
                        lawless actions and armed attacks committed against the allies of Rome, it
                        is the will and order of the Roman people that war be proclaimed against
                        Philip, King of Macedonia, and against his people, the Macedonians."
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The other consul, Aurelius, received
                        Italy for his province. Then the praetors balloted for their respective
                        commands. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> C. Sergius Plancus drew the
                        City; Q. Fulvius Gillo, Sicily; Q. Minucius Rufus, Bruttium, and L. Furius,
                        Gaul. The proposed declaration of war against Macedonia was almost
                        unanimously rejected at the first meeting of the Assembly. The length and
                        exhausting demands of the late war had made men weary of fighting and they
                        shrank from incurring further toils and dangers. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> One of the tribunes of the plebs, Q. Baebius, too, had
                        adopted the old plan of abusing the patricians for perpetually sowing the
                        seeds of fresh wars to prevent the plebeians from ever enjoying any rest.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The patricians were extremely angry
                        and the tribune was bitterly attacked in the senate, each of the senators in
                        turn urging the consul to call another meeting of the Assembly to consider
                        the proposal afresh and at the same time to rebuke the people for their want
                        of spirit and show them what loss and disgrace would <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> be entailed by the postponement of that war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Assembly was duly convened in the
                        Campus Martius, and before the question was put to the vote, the consul
                        addressed the centuries in the following terms: <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> "You seem to be unaware, Quirites, that what you have
                        to decide is not whether you will have peace or war; Philip will not leave
                        you any option as to that, he is preparing war on an enormous scale both by
                        land and sea. The only question is whether you will transport the legions
                        into Macedonia or wait for the enemy in Italy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> You have learnt by experience, if not before, at all
                        events in the late Punic War, what a difference it makes which you decide
                        upon. When Saguntum was beseiged and our allies were imploring us for help,
                        who doubts that if we had sent prompt assistance, as our fathers did to the
                        Mamertines, we should have confined within the borders of Spain that war
                        which, most disastrously for ourselves, we allowed through procrastination
                        to enter Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Why, this very Philip had
                        entered into an agreement with Hannibal through his agents and in his
                        despatches that he would invade Italy, and there is not the smallest doubt
                        that we kept him in Macedonia by sending Laevinus with a fleet to take the
                        offensive against him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Are we hesitating
                        to do now what we did then, when we had Hannibal for our enemy in Italy-now
                        that Hannibal has been driven out of Italy and out of Carthage, and Carthage
                        itself is completely vanquished? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If we
                        allow the king to make proof of our slackness by storming Athens as we
                        allowed Hannibal to do by storming Saguntum, it will not be in <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> five months-the time Hannibal took from
                        Saguntum-but in five days after he sails from Corinth that he will set foot
                        in Italy. </p>
                    <p> "Perhaps you do not put Philip on a par with Hannibal or consider the
                        Macedonians equal to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At
                        all events you will consider him the equal of Pyrrhus. Equal, do I say? How
                        greatly the one man surpasses the other, how superior is the one nation to
                        the other! <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Epirus always has been and is
                        today a very small accession to the kingdom of Macedonia. The whole of the
                        Peloponnese is under the sway of Philip, not excepting even Argos, famous
                        for the death of Pyrrhus, quite as much as for its ancient glory. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Now compare our position. Consider the
                        flourishing state of Italy when all those generals and armies were safe and
                        sound which have been since swept away by the Punic War. And yet when
                        Pyrrhus attacked it, he shook it to its foundations and all but reached Rome
                        itself in his victorious career! <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Not only
                        did the Tarentines revolt from us and the whole of that coastal district of
                        Italy called Magna Graecia, which you would naturally suppose would follow a
                        leader of the same language and nationality as themselves, but the
                        Lucanians, the Bruttians and the Samnites did the same. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Do you suppose that if Philip landed in Italy, these
                        nations would remain quiet and true to us? They showed their loyalty, I
                        suppose, in the Punic War. No, those nations will never fall to revolt from
                        us, unless there is no longer any one to whom they can revolt. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> If you had thought it too much to go to Africa
                        you would have had Hannibal and his Carthaginians in Italy today. Let
                        Macedonia rather than Italy be the seat of war, let it be the enemy's cities
                        and fields that are devastated with fire and sword. We have learnt by this
                        time that our arms are more potent and more successful abroad than they are
                        at home. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Go to the poll with the help of
                        the gods, and confirm the decision of the senate. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> It is not your consul only who urges you to take this
                        course, the immortal gods also bid you do it, for when I was offering up the
                        sacrifices and praying that this war might end happily for the senate, for
                        myself, for you, for our allies and Latin confederates, for our fleets and
                        armies, the gods vouchsafed every cheering and happy omen." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this speech they separated for the
                        voting. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The result was in favour of the
                        consul's proposal, they resolved on war. Thereupon, the consuls, acting on a
                        resolution of the senate, ordered special prayers and supplications for
                        three days, and at all the shrines intercessions were offered up that the
                        war which the Roman people had ordered against Philip might have a happy and
                        prosperous issue. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The fetials were
                        consulted by the consul as to whether it was necessary for the declaration
                        of war to be conveyed personally to King Philip, or whether it would be
                        sufficient if it were published in one of his frontier garrison towns.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They declared that either mode of
                        procedure would be correct. The senate left it to the consul to select at
                        his discretion one of them, not being a member of the senate, to make the
                        declaration of war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next business was
                        the formation of the armies for the consuls and praetors. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The consuls were ordered to disband the old armies and,
                        each of them, to raise two fresh legions. As the conduct of the new war,
                        which was felt to be a very serious one, was entrusted to Sulpicius, he was
                        allowed to reenlist as volunteers as many as he could out of the army
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> which P. Scipio had brought back
                        from Africa, but on no account to compel any of the veterans to join against
                        his will. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls were to give to each
                        of the praetors, L. Furius Purpurio and Q. Minucius Rufus, 5000 men from the
                        Latin contingents as an army of occupation for their provinces, the one in
                        Gaul, the other in Bruttium. Q. Fulvius Gallo also was ordered to select men
                        belonging to the Latin and allied contingents from the army which the consul
                        P. Aelius had commanded, beginning with <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                        those who had seen the shortest service until he had made up a force of 5000
                        men. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This army was for the defence of
                        Sicily. M. Valerius Falto, who had had Campania for his province during the
                        previous year, was to make a similar selection from the army in Sardinia,
                        which province he was to take charge of as propraetor. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The consuls received instructions to raise two legions
                        in the City as a reserve to be sent wherever there was need for their
                        services, as many of the Italian nationalities had taken the side of
                        Carthage in the late war, and were seething with anger. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the midst of these preparations for war
                        a deputation came from King Ptolemy to bring information that the Athenians
                        had sought his aid against Philip. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Although both States were allies of Rome, the king would not-so the deputies
                        stated-send either fleet or army to Greece to protect or attack any one
                        without the consent of Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If the Romans
                        were at liberty to defend their allies he should remain quietly in his
                        kingdom; if on the other hand the Romans preferred to remain inactive he
                        would himself send such assistance as would easily protect the Athenians
                        against Philip. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate passed a vote
                        of thanks to the king and assured the deputation that it was the intention
                        of the Roman people to protect their allies; if the need arose they would
                        point it out to the king, and they were fully aware that the resources of
                        his kingdom would prove a steady and loyal support for their commonwealth.
                        To each of the deputies the senate presented 5000 ases. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> While the consuls were raising troops and preparing for
                        war, the citizens were occupied with religious observances, especially those
                        which were usual when a fresh war began. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The special intercessions and prayers at all the shrines had been duly
                        offered, but that nothing might be omitted the consul to whom Macedonia was
                        allotted was authorised to vow Games in honour of Jupiter and an offering to
                        his temple. This matter was delayed through the action of the Pontifex
                        Maximus, Licinius, who laid it down that no vow ought to be made unless the
                        sum required to discharge it was paid, because the money so appropriated
                        could not be used in connection with the war, and ought to be at once set
                        apart and not mixed up with other money. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Unless this were done, the vow could not be duly discharged. Although the
                        pontiff's authority and the reasons he gave had great weight, the consul was
                        instructed to refer the question to the whole pontifical college as to
                        whether a vow could be properly undertaken when the expense incurred was
                        left uncertain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The pontiffs declared that
                        it could, and would be made with even greater propriety under these
                        conditions. The consul recited the words of the vow after the Pontifex
                        Maximus in the same form in which vows to be discharged <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> after an interval of five years were usually recited,
                        the exception being that the senate was to determine the cost of its
                        fulfilment at the time when it was discharged. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Up to this time when the Games and offerings were vowed
                        a definite sum had always been named; this was the first instance where the
                        cost was not fixed at the time. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst all men's minds were turned to the
                        Macedonian war, rumours suddenly arose of an outbreak of the Gauls, the last
                        thing that was apprehended. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Insubres
                        and Cenomani in conjunction with the Boii, who had induced the Celines and
                        Ilvates and the other Ligurian tribes to join them, had taken up arms under
                        Hamilcar, a Carthaginian general, who had held a command in Hasdrubal's army
                        and had remained in the country. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They had
                        stormed and sacked Placentia and in their blind rage had destroyed most of
                        the city by fire, hardly 2000 men being left amid the smoking ruins. Thence,
                        crossing the Po, they advanced with the intention of sacking Cremona.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hearing of the disaster which had
                        overtaken their neighbours the townsmen had time to close their gates and
                        man their walls so that they might, at all events, be able to stand a siege
                        and send a message to the Roman praetor before the final assault. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> I,. Furius Purpureo was in charge of that
                        province at the time, and acting under the resolution of the senate had
                        disbanded his army, retaining only 5000 from the Latin and allied
                        contingents. With this force he was encamped in the neighbourhood of
                        Ariminum. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In a despatch to the senate he
                        described the serious condition of his province; of the two military
                        colonies which had weathered the terrible storm of the Punic War one was
                        taken and destroyed by the enemy and the other was being attacked.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His own army could not render
                        assistance to the colonists in their distress unless he was willing to
                        expose his 5000 allied troops to be massacred by the 40,000 of the
                        enemy-that number was under arms-and by incurring such a fatal disaster
                        himself raise the courage of the enemy who were exulting over the
                        destruction of a Roman colony. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the despatch had been read the
                        senate decreed that the consul C. Aurelius should order his army to muster
                        at Ariminum on the day which he had previously fixed for their muster in
                        Etruria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If the state of public affairs
                        allowed, he was to go in person to suppress the disturbance, otherwise, he
                        was to send instructions to L. Furius requesting him, <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> as soon as the legions reached him, to send his 5000 of
                        the allied contingent to replace them in Etruria, and then raise the siege
                        of Cremona. The senate also decided to send a mission to Carthage and to
                        Masinissa in Numidia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their instructions
                        for Carthage were to inform the government that Hamilcar, one of their
                        citizens who had come with either Hasdrubal's or Mago's army, had been left
                        behind <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and in defiance of the treaty had
                        persuaded the Gauls and Ligurians to take up arms against Rome. If they
                        wished to remain at peace they must recall him and surrender him to the
                        Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The commissioners were also to
                        announce that the deserters had not all been given up, a great many of them
                        were stated to be openly walking about in Carthage; it was the duty of the
                        authorities to find them out and arrest them in order that they might be
                        handed over in accordance with the treaty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        These were their instructions for Carthage. To Masinissa they were to convey
                        the senate's congratulations on his having recovered his ancestral kingdom
                        and still more upon his having extended it by the annexation of the richest
                        portion of Syphax's dominions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were
                        also to inform him that a war had been undertaken against Philip in
                        consequence of his having lent the Carthaginians active <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> assistance, and when Italy was wrapped in the flames of
                        war he had inflicted injuries on the allies of Rome. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> She was thus compelled to send ships and armies to
                        Greece, and by thus dividing her forces Philip was primarily the cause of
                        the delay in sending an expedition to Africa. The commissioners were further
                        to request Masinissa to assist in that war by sending a contingent of
                        Numidian horse. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Some splendid presents
                        were placed in their charge for the king-gold and silver vases, a purple
                        robe, a tunica palmata together with an ivory sceptre, also a toga praetexta
                        together with a curule chair. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They were
                        instructed to assure him that if he required anything for the security and
                        extension of his kingdom and would intimate what he wanted, the Roman people
                        would do their utmost to meet his wishes in return for the services he had
                        rendered. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A deputation from Syphax's son, Vermina,
                        also appeared before the senate. They made excuses for his mistakes on the
                        ground of his youth and threw all the blame on the faithlessness of the
                        Carthaginians. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Masinissa had once been
                        the enemy and had now become the friend of Rome; Vermina, too, they said,
                        would make every effort not to be outdone in friendly offices to Rome either
                        by Masinissa or by any one else. They ended by petitioning the senate to
                        confer on him the title of "king, ally and friend." <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> The reply which the deputation received was to the
                        effect that "Syphax, his father, had suddenly without any reason become an
                        enemy to the people of Rome after being their ally and friend, and that
                        Vermina himself had commenced his military education by an attack on the
                        Romans. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He must therefore sue for peace
                        before he could have any title to be styled 'king, ally and friend.' The
                        Roman people were accustomed to confer that honourable distinction in return
                        for great services which kings have rendered to them. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> The Roman envoys would shortly be in Africa and the
                        senate would empower them to grant peace to Vermina on certain conditions,
                        providing that he left the fixing of those conditions absolutely to the
                        Roman people. If he wanted anything added or cancelled or altered in the
                        terms he must make a fresh appeal to the senate." <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> The men who were sent to conduct these negotiations
                        were C. Terentius Varro, Sp. Lucretius and Cn. Octavius; and they had each a
                        quinquereme placed at their disposal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A despatch was read in the House from Q.
                        Minucius, the praetor commanding in Bruttium, in which he stated that money
                        had been stolen by night from the treasury of Proserpine at Locri and there
                        was no clue to the perpetrators of the crime. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The senate were extremely angry at finding that acts of
                        sacrilege were still going on and that not even the example of Pleminius,
                        notorious alike for the guilt and the punishment which so swiftly followed,
                        acted in any way as a deterrent. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> C.
                        Aurelius was instructed to write to the praetor and tell him that the senate
                        wished an enquiry to be made into the circumstances of the robbery on the
                        same lines as the one which the praetor M. Pomponius had conducted three
                        years previously. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whatever money was
                        discovered was to be replaced, and the deficit made up; and should it be
                        thought necessary expiatory sacrifices were to be offered in accordance with
                        the instructions of the pontiffs on the previous occasions. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Their anxiety to atone for the violation of the temple
                        was made all the keener by the simultaneous announcements of portents from
                        numerous localities. In Lucania it was alleged that the heavens had been on
                        fire; at Privernum the sun had been glowing red through the whole of a
                        cloudless day; at the temple of Juno Sospita in Lanuvium a terrible noise
                        was heard in the night. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Numerous monstrous
                        births were also reported amongst the Sabines a child was born of doubtful
                        sex; another similar case was discovered where the child was already sixteen
                        years old; at Frusino a lamb was yeaned with a head like a pig; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> at Sinuessa a pig was littered with a human head,
                        and on the public domain-land in Lucania a foal appeared with five feet.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These were all regarded as horrid and
                        monstrous products of a nature which had gone astray to produce strange and
                        hybrid growths; the hermaphrodites were looked upon as of especially evil
                        omen and were ordered to be at once carried out to sea just as quite
                        recently in the consulships of C. Claudius and M. Nero similar ill-omened
                        births had been disposed of. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At the same
                        time the senate ordered the decemvirs to consult the Sacred Books about this
                        portent. Following the instructions found there, they ordered the same
                        ceremonies to be observed as on the occasion of its last appearance. A hymn
                        was to be sung through the City by three choirs, each consisting of nine
                        maidens, and a gift was to be carried to Queen Juno. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The consul C. Aurelius saw that the instructions of the
                        Keepers of the Sacred Books were carried out. The hymn in our fathers' days
                        was composed by Livius, on this occasion by P. Licinius Tegula. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When all the acts of expiation had been
                        duly performed, and the sacrilege at Locri had been investigated by Q.
                        Minucius, and the money, recovered from the sale of the goods of the guilty
                        persons, had been replaced in the treasury, the consuls were now anxious to
                        start for their provinces, but a delay arose. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> A number of persons had lent money to the State during
                        the consulship of M. Valerius and M. Claudius, and the repayment of the
                        third instalment was due this year. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        consuls informed them that the money in the treasury would hardly meet the
                        cost of the new war, which would have to be carried on with a large fleet
                        and large armies and that there was no means of paying them for the present.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They appealed to the senate and
                        pleaded that if the State chose to use the money which was lent for the
                        Punic War to defray the cost of the Macedonian War also, and one war arose
                        out of another, it would simply mean that their money would be confiscated
                        in return for the service they had rendered as though it had really been an
                        injury. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate acknowledged that they
                        had a grievance. The creditors' demands were just, but the State was unable
                        to meet its liabilities and the senate decided upon a course which was fair
                        to both sides and of practical utility. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Many of the applicants had stated that there was land everywhere for sale
                        and they wanted to become purchasers; the senate accordingly made a decree
                        that they should have the option of taking any part of the public
                        domain-land within fifty miles of the City. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The consuls would value the land and impose a nominal tax of one as per
                        jugerum as acknowledgment of its being public land, and when the State could
                        pay its debts <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> any of them who wished to
                        have his money rather than the land could have it and restore the land to
                        the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They gladly accepted these
                        terms, and the land thus occupied was called trientabulus because it was
                        given in lieu of a third part of their loan. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the recital of the customary prayers
                        in the Capitol P. Sulpicius was invested by his lictors with the
                        paludamentum and left the City for Brundisium. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Here he incorporated into his legions the veterans who
                        had volunteered out of the African army, and also selected the vessels out
                        of the fleet under Cn. Cornelius. Then he set sail, and the next day he
                        landed in, Greece. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here he was met by an
                        embassy from Athens who begged him to raise the siege which that city was
                        undergoing. C. Claudius Cento was at once despatched thither with 20
                        warships and 1000 men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king was not
                        personally directing the siege, he was just then attacking Abydos, after
                        trying his strength in naval encounters with the Rhodians and with Attalus,
                        and in neither battle had he been successful. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But his was not a nature to accept defeat quietly, and
                        now that he had leagued himself with Antiochus, king of Syria, he was more
                        determined on war than ever. They had agreed to divide the rich kingdom of
                        Egypt between them, and on hearing of the death of Ptolemy they both
                        prepared to attack it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Athenians, who
                        retain nothing of their ancient greatness but their pride, had become
                        involved in hostilities with Philip through a quite unimportant incident.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During the celebration of the
                        Eleusinian Mysteries two young Acarnanians who had not been initiated
                        entered the temple of Ceres with the rest of the crowd, quite unaware of the
                        sacrilegious nature of their action. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They
                        were betrayed by the silly questions which they asked, and were brought
                        before the temple authorities. Though it was quite evident that they had
                        sinned in ignorance, they were put to death as though guilty of a horrible
                        crime. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Acarnanians reported this
                        hostile and barbarous act to Philip and obtained his consent to their making
                        war on Athens supported by a Macedonian contingent. Their army began by
                        laying the land of Attica waste with fire and sword, after which they
                        returned to Acarnania with plunder of every description. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> So far there was only anger and exasperation on both
                        sides, subsequently, by a decree of the citizens, Athens made a formal
                        declaration of war. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For when King Attalus
                        and the Rhodians who were following up Philip in his retreat to Macedonia
                        had reached Aegina, the king sailed across to the Piraeus for the purpose of
                        renewing and confirming his alliance with the Athenians. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The whole body of the citizens came out to meet him
                        with their wives and children; the priests in their sacred robes received
                        him as he entered the city; even the gods themselves were almost summoned
                        from their shrines to welcome him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The people were at once summoned to an
                        assembly, in order that the king might lay his wishes before them.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was, however, thought to be more in
                        accordance with his dignity that he should put what he wanted into writing,
                        rather than let his blushes be called up by having to recount his services
                        to the city or his modesty be shocked by the fulsome flattery of the
                        applauding crowd. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly he drew up a
                        written statement which was read in the assembly, in which he enumerated the
                        benefits he had conferred on their <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> city
                        and described his contest with Philip, and urged them in conclusion to take
                        their part in the war while they had him and the Rhodians and, now
                        especially, the Romans to support them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If
                        they hung back now they would never have such an opportunity again. Then the
                        envoys from Rhodes were heard; they had quite lately done a good turn for
                        the Athenians, for they had recaptured and sent back to Athens four Athenian
                        warships which the Macedonians had taken. War against Philip was unanimously
                        decided upon. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Extraordinary honours were
                        paid to King Attalus and also to the Rhodians. A proposal was carried to add
                        to the old ten tribes a new one to be called the Attalis tribe. The people
                        of Rhodes were presented with a golden crown in recognition of their
                        bravery, and the full citizenship was granted to them just they had
                        previously granted it to the Athenians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        After this Attalus rejoined his fleet at Aegina and the Rhodians sailed to
                        Cia, and from there made their way home through the Cyclades. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> All the islands joined them with the exception of
                        Andros, Paros and Cythnos which were held by Macedonian garrisons. Attalus
                        had sent messengers to Aetolia and was waiting for the envoys who were
                        coming from there; their non-arrival kept him inactive for some time.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He could not induce the Aetolians to
                        take up arms, they were only too glad to remain at peace with Philip on any
                        terms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But had he in conjunction with the
                        Rhodians vigorously opposed Philip, they might have won the glorious title
                        of Liberators of Greece. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Instead of this,
                        they allowed him to cross the Hellespont a second time and seize an
                        excellent position in Thrace where he could concentrate his forces, and thus
                        they gave fresh life to the war and surrendered the glory of bringing it to
                        a close the Romans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip showed a more kingly spirit. Though
                        he had not held his own against Attalus and the Rhodians he was not alarmed
                        even at the prospect of a war with Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Philocles, one of his generals, was sent with a force of 2000 infantry and
                        200 cavalry to ravage the lands of the Athenians, and Heraclides was placed
                        in charge of the fleet with instructions to sail for Maronea. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Philip himself marched thither overland with 2000
                        men in light marching order, and took the place at the first assault.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Aenos gave him a good deal of trouble,
                        but he finally effected its capture through the treachery of Callimedes, who
                        was holding the place for Ptolemy. Cypsela, Doriscos and Serrheum were taken
                        in rapid succession and he then advanced to the Chersonese where Elaeus and
                        Alopeconnesus voluntarily surrendered. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Callipolis and Madytos fell through treachery; together with some other
                        unimportant fortified places. The people of Abydos would not even admit his
                        envoys and closed their gates against the king. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The siege of this place detained Philip for a
                        considerable time, and if Attalus and the Rhodians had shown the smallest
                        energy they might have saved the place. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Attalus sent only 300 men to assist in the defence and the Rhodians
                        despatched one quadrireme out of their fleet which was lying at anchor off
                        Tenedos. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Later on, when they could hardly
                        hold out any longer, Attalus himself sailed to Tenedos, and after raising
                        their hopes by his approach did not afford his allies any assistance either
                        by land or sea. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Abydenes in the first instance placed
                        engines all along their walls and in this way not only prevented any
                        approach by land, but also made the anchorage of the hostile ships unsafe.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When, however, a portion of the wall
                        was battered into ruins and the enemies' mines had been carried up to an
                        inner wall which the defenders had hastily constructed, they sent envoys to
                        the king to arrange terms for the surrender of the city. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They proposed that the Rhodian quadrireme with its crew
                        and the contingent which Attalus had sent should be allowed to depart and
                        that the inhabitants should be permitted to leave the city with simply the
                        clothes they were wearing. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Philip replied
                        that there was not the slightest hope of peace unless they surrendered
                        unconditionally. When this reply was brought back it created such an
                        outburst of indignation and rage that the citizens formed the same frenzied
                        resolution as the Saguntines had done in former years. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They gave orders for all the matrons to be shut up in
                        the temple of Diana, the freeborn boys and girls, even infants with their
                        nurses to be collected in the gymnasium, all gold and silver to be taken to
                        the forum, all costly apparel to <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> be
                        placed on board the vessels from Rhodes and Cyzicus which were lying in the
                        harbour, and altars set up in the middle of the city, round which the
                        priests were to be assembled with victims for sacrifice. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Here a body of men, selected for the purpose, took an
                        oath dictated to them by the priests, to carry out the desperate measure
                        which had been decided upon. As soon as they saw that their comrades who
                        were fighting in front of the levelled wall were all killed, they were to
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> put the wives and children to death,
                        throw the gold and silver and the apparel on board the ships into the sea
                        and set fire wherever they possibly could to all the public buildings and
                        private <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> houses, and the most horrible
                        curses were invoked on them if they broke their oath. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Following them, all the men of military age solemnly
                        swore that none should leave the battle alive, except as victor. So faithful
                        were they to their oath and with such desperation did they fight, that
                        before night could put an end to the battle, Philip withdrew from the
                        conflict appalled by their frenzied courage. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The leading citizens, to whom the more cruel part had
                        been assigned, finding that there were only a few survivors, and they
                        wounded and exhausted, sent the priests, wearing supplicatory fillets, as
                        soon as it was light to Philip to make a surrender of the city. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the surrender actually took place,
                        the Roman envoys who had been sent to Alexandria heard of the siege of
                        Abydos, and the youngest of the three, M. Aemilius, went at the suggestion
                        of his colleagues to Philip. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                        remonstrated against the war that had been made on Attalus and the Rhodians,
                        and especially against the attack on Abydos. On the king replying that
                        Attalus and the Rhodians had been the aggressors he asked, "Were the people
                        of Abydos also the first to take up arms?" <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        To one who seldom heard the truth this language seemed too bold to address
                        to a king. "Your youth, your good looks and, above all, the fact of your
                        being a Roman make you too venturesome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It
                        is my wish that you should remember treaty obligations and keep the peace
                        with me, but if you begin the attack, I too am quite ready to fight, and you
                        will find the kingdom and name of Macedon no less renowned in war than those
                        of Rome." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After dismissing thus the envoy
                        Philip took possession of the gold and silver which had been collected, but
                        he lost all chance of making prisoners. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        For such a madness fell on the people that they believed that all who had
                        met their death in battle had been suddenly betrayed, and they accused one
                        another of perjury, especially the priests, for they were surrendering to
                        the enemy those whom they had devoted to death. Seized by one sudden impulse
                        they all rushed off to kill their wives and children, and then they
                        inflicted death upon themselves in every possible form. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The king was utterly astounded at this outburst of
                        madness and called off his men from the assault, telling them that he would
                        allow the people of Abydos three days in which to die. During this interval
                        the vanquished wrought more horrors upon themselves than the victors would
                        have done, however infuriated they might have been. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Not a single man fell into the hands of the enemy
                        alive, save those for whom chains or some other cause beyond their control
                        made death impossible. After leaving a force in occupation of Abydos, Philip
                        returned to his kingdom. As the destruction of Saguntum strengthened
                        Hannibal's resolve to war against Rome, so the fall of Abydos encouraged
                        Philip to do the same. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On his way he was
                        met by couriers who announced that the consul was now in Epirus and was
                        wintering his troops in Apollonia and his naval force at Corcyra. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys who had been sent to Africa to
                        report the action of Hamilcar in assuming the leadership of the Gauls were
                        informed by the Carthaginian government that they could do nothing more than
                        sentence him to banishment and confiscate his property; <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> all the refugees and deserters whom after careful
                        search they had been able to discover had been given up, and they intended
                        to send envoys to Rome to give satisfactory assurances on this point. They
                        sent 200,000 modii of wheat to Rome and a similar amount to the army in
                        Macedonia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From Carthage the legates
                        proceeded to Numidia to visit the two kings. The presents destined for
                        Masinissa were given to him and the message delivered from the senate. He
                        offered to furnish 2000 horse, but only 1000 were accepted, and he
                        personally superintended their embarkation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> With them he sent to Macedonia 2,000,000 modii of wheat and the same
                        quantity of barley. The third mission was to Vermina. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He came to meet them at the frontier of his kingdom and
                        left it to them to put in writing what conditions of peace they wanted,
                        assuring them that any peace with Rome he should look upon as fair and
                        advantageous. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The terms were handed to
                        him, and he was instructed to send commissioners to Rome to obtain their
                        ratification. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time L. Cornelius Lentulus
                        returned from Spain where he had been acting as proconsul. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> After giving a report of the successful operations
                        which he had conducted there for several years, he asked to be allowed to
                        enter the City in triumph. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate were
                        of opinion that his services quite deserved a triumph, but they reminded him
                        that there was no precedent for a general who had not been Dictator or
                        consul or praetor enjoying a triumph, and he had held his command in Spain
                        as proconsul, not as consul or praetor. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        However, they went so far as to allow him to enter the City in <milestone
                            n="5??" unit="section"/> ovation, in spite of the opposition of Tiberius
                        Sempronius Longus, one of the tribunes of the plebs, who said that there was
                        no precedent or customary authority for that any more than for the other.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the end he gave way before the
                        unanimous feeling of the senate, and after they had passed their resolution,
                        Lentulus enjoyed his ovation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> 43,000
                        pounds of silver and 2450 pounds of gold, captured from the enemy, were
                        carried in the procession. Out of the spoil he distributed 120 ases to each
                        of his men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time the consular army in Gaul had
                        been transferred from Arretium to Ariminum, and the 5000 men of the Latin
                        contingent had moved from Gaul into Etruria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> L. Furius accordingly left Ariminum and hastened by forced marches to
                        Cremona which the Gauls were at the time besieging. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He fixed his camp a mile and a half distant from the
                        enemy and would have had a chance of winning a brilliant victory if he had
                        led his men straight from their march against the Gaulish camp. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The Gauls were scattered over the fields in all
                        directions and the camp had been left insufficiently guarded. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> But he was afraid that his men would be too much
                        fatigued after their rapid march, and the shouts of the Gauls recalled their
                        comrades, who, leaving the plunder which they had gathered behind, ran back
                        to their camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The next day they marched
                        out to battle. The Romans were not slow in accepting the challenge, but they
                        had hardly time to complete their formation, so rapidly did the enemy come
                        on. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Furius had formed the allied troops
                        into two divisions, and the right division was stationed in the first line,
                        the two Roman legions forming the reserve. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        M. Furius was in command of this division, M. Caecilius commanded the
                        legions and L. Valerius Flaccus the cavalry. These were all staff-officers.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The praetor kept two of his staff with
                        him-C. Laetorius and P. Titinius-to assist him in surveying the field and
                        meeting any sudden attempt of the enemy. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At first the Gauls brought their whole
                        strength to bear in one direction, hoping to be able to overwhelm the right
                        wing and smash it up. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Failing in this,
                        they endeavoured to work round the flanks and envelop the enemy's line,
                        which, considering their numbers and the fewness of their opponents, seemed
                        an easy task. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the praetor saw this
                        maneuver he extended his front by bringing up the two legions in reserve to
                        the right and left of the allied troops, and he also vowed a temple to
                        Diovis, in case he routed the enemy that day. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> He then ordered L. Valerius to launch the Roman cavalry
                        against one wing of the Gauls and the allied cavalry against the other to
                        check the enveloping movement. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As soon as
                        he saw that the Gauls had weakened their centre by diverting troops to the
                        wings, he ordered his infantry to advance in close order at the charge and
                        break through the opposing ranks. This was decisive; the wings were repulsed
                        by the cavalry and the centre by the infantry. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> As they were being cut down in all parts of the field,
                        the Gauls turned, and in wild flight sought shelter in their camp. The
                        cavalry followed in hot pursuit and the infantry soon came up and attacked
                        the camp. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Not 6000 men succeeded in
                        making their escape; more than 35,000 were killed or made prisoners; 70
                        standards were taken together with 200 Gaulish carts loaded with spoil.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian general Hamilcar
                        fell in that battle as well as three Gaulish nobles who were in command.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> 2000 men whom the Gauls had taken at
                        Placentia were set at liberty and restored to their homes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was a great victory and caused great
                        joy in Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the despatch arrived a
                        three days' thanksgiving was decreed. The Romans and allies lost 2000 men,
                        mostly belonging to the right division against which the enormous mass of
                        the enemy made their first attack. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Although the praetor had practically brought the war to a close, the consul
                        C. Aurelius after finishing the necessary business in Rome proceeded to Gaul
                        and took over the victorious army from the praetor. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The other consul reached his province quite late in the
                        autumn and wintered in the neighbourhood of Apollonia. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> As stated above, C. Claudius was sent to Athens with
                        twenty triremes out of the fleet which was laid up at Corcyra. When they
                        entered the Piraeus they brought great comfort and hope to their allies who
                        were now in a state of great despondency. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The depredations committed on their fields by the troops at Corinth, who
                        came through Megara, now ceased, and <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the
                        pirates from Chalcis who had infested the sea and harried the maritime
                        districts of Athens no longer ventured beyond Sunium and in fact would not
                        trust themselves outside the Euripus. In addition to the Roman ships there
                        were three quadriremes from Rhodes and three Athenian undecked vessels which
                        had been fitted out to protect their coast. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> As a chance of an important success offered itself to C. Claudius he
                        thought that it would be sufficient for the present if this fleet protected
                        the city and territory of Athens. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some refugees from Chalcis who had been
                        expelled by the king's adherents reported that the place could be seized
                        without any serious <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> resistance, for as
                        there was no enemy to be feared in the neighbourhood the Macedonians were
                        strolling about everywhere, and the townsmen, trusting to the Macedonians
                        for protection, made no attempt to guard the city. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> On this information C. Claudius proceeded to Chalcis,
                        and although he reached Sunium early enough to allow of his entering the
                        strait of Euboea the same day, he kept his fleet at anchor till nightfall
                        that his approach might not be observed. As soon as it was dark he sailed on
                        over a calm sea and reached Chalcis a little before dawn. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He selected the least populous part of the city for his
                        attempt, and finding the guards at some points asleep and other places
                        without any guard at all, he directed a small body of soldiers to place
                        their scaling-ladders against the nearest tower, which was taken with the
                        wall on either side of it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then they
                        advanced along the wall to where the buildings were numerous, killing the
                        guards <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> on their way, till they reached
                        the gate which they broke down and so admitted the main body of troops.
                        Dispersing in all directions they filled the city with tumult, and, to add
                        to the confusion, the buildings round the forum were set on fire. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> They burnt the king's granaries and the arsenal
                        with an immense number of military engines and artillery. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This was followed by an indiscriminate slaughter of
                        those who offered resistance and those who tried to escape, and at last
                        every man capable of bearing arms was either killed or put to flight.
                        Amongst the former was Sopater, an Acarnanian, the commandant of the
                        garrison. All the plunder was collected in the forum and then placed on
                        board the ships. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The gaol too was broken
                        open by the Rhodians, and the prisoners of war whom Philip had immured there
                        as being the safest place of custody were released. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> After the statues of the king had been thrown down and
                        mutilated the signal for embarkation was given, and they sailed back to the
                        Piraeus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Had there been a sufficient
                        force of Roman soldiery to allow of Chalcis being occupied without
                        interfering with the protection of Athens, Chalcis and the Euripus would
                        have been wrested from the king; a most important success at the very outset
                        of the war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For the Euripus is the key to
                        Greece by sea as the pass of Thermopylae is by land. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip was in Demetrias at the time. When
                        the disaster that had overtaken a friendly city was announced to him, he
                        determined, as he was too late to save it, to do the next best thing and
                        avenge it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With a force of 5000 infantry
                        in light marching order and 300 cavalry he went almost at a run to Chalcis,
                        not for a moment doubting that he would be able to take the Romans by
                        surprise. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Finding that there was nothing
                        to see but the uninviting spectacle of a smoking and ruined city in which
                        hardly enough men were left to bury the victims of the war, he hurried away
                        at the same speed and crossing the Euripus by the bridge marched through
                        Boeotia to Athens, thinking that as he had shown as much enterprise as the
                        Romans he would have the same success. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And
                        he would have had, if a scout had not observed the king's army on the march
                        from a watch-tower. This man was what the Greeks call a hemerodromos,
                        because these men cover enormous distances in a single day, and running on
                        in advance he reached Athens at midnight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Here there was the same somnolence and negligence which had brought about
                        the loss of Chalcis a few days before. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Roused by the breathless messenger, the Athenian commander-in-chief and
                        Dioxippus the prefect of the cohort of mercenaries mustered their soldiers
                        in the forum and ordered the trumpets to sound the alarm from the citadel so
                        that all might know that the enemy was at hand. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> There was a general rush to the gates and the walls. </p>
                    <p> Some hours later, though considerably before daybreak. Philip approached the
                        city. When he saw the numerous lights and heard the noise of men hurrying to
                        and fro in the inevitable confusion, he halted his force and ordered them to
                        lie down and rest. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As his attempt at a
                        surprise had failed he prepared for an open assault and made his advance on
                        the side of the Dipylon. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This gate, placed
                        as a mouth to the city, is considerably larger and wider than the rest, and
                        the road on both sides of it is broad, so that the townsmen were able to
                        form their line right up to it from the forum, whilst the road beyond it
                        stretching for about a mile as far as the Academy allowed plenty of room for
                        the infantry and cavalry of the enemy. After forming their line inside the
                        gate, the Athenians, together with the detachment which Attalus had left and
                        Dioxippus' cohort, sallied forth. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As soon
                        as he saw them Philip thought he had them in his power and would be able to
                        satisfy his long-cherished desire for their destruction, for there was not
                        one of the Greek States that he was more furious against than he was against
                        Athens. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After exhorting his men to keep
                        their eyes on him as they fought and to remember that where the king was,
                        there the standards and the fighting line ought to be, he put spurs to his
                        horse, animated not only by raging anger but also by a love of ostentation.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He thought it a splendid thing to be
                        seen fighting by the immense crowd who thronged the walls to view the
                        spectacle. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Galloping forward in front of
                        his lines with a few horsemen he charged into the middle <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> of the enemy and created as much alarm amongst them as
                        he inspired his own men with enthusiasm. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Many he wounded at close quarters, others by the missiles he flung, and he
                        drove them back to their gate where he inflicted greater losses as they
                        crowded through the confined space. Recklessly as he pursued them, he was
                        still able to draw off in safety because those who were on the turrets of
                        the gate forbore to throw their javelins for fear <milestone n="16??"
                            unit="section"/> of hitting their own comrades who were mixed up with
                        the enemy. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> After this the Athenians kept
                        within their walls, and Philip after giving the signal for retirement fixed
                        his camp at Cynosarges where there was a temple of Hercules and a gymnasium
                        with a grove round it. But Cynosarges and the Lyceum and every sacred and
                        delightful place round the city was burnt. <milestone n="18" unit="section"
                        /> Not only were buildings destroyed but even the tombs, nothing belonging
                        to either gods or men was spared in his uncontrollable fury. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following day the closed gates were
                        suddenly thrown open to admit a body of troops sent by Attalus and the
                        Romans from the Piraeus. The king now removed his camp to a distance of
                        about three miles from the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From
                        there he marched to Eleusis in the hope of securing by a coup-de-main the
                        temple of the fort which surrounded it and protected it on all sides. When,
                        however, he found that the defenders were quite on the alert, and that the
                        fleet was on its way from the Piraeus to render assistance, he abandoned his
                        project and marched to Megara, and then straight to Corinth. On learning
                        that the Council of the Achaeans was sitting at Argos he made his appearance
                        in the assembly quite unexpectedly. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They
                        were at the time discussing the question of war with Nabis, tyrant of the
                        Lacedaemonians. When the supreme command was transferred from Philopoemen to
                        Cycliades. who was by no means his equal as a general, Nabis, finding that
                        the Achaeans had dismissed their mercenaries, resumed hostilities, and after
                        devastating his neighbours' fields was now threatening their cities.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To oppose this enemy the council were
                        deliberating as to what proportion of troops should be furnished by each
                        State. Philip promised to relieve them from all anxiety so far as Nabis and
                        the Lacedaemonians were concerned; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> he
                        would not only protect the soil of his allies from their ravages, but he
                        would at once roll back all the terror of war upon Laconia itself by
                        marching his army thither. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When these
                        words were greeted with loud applause he went on to say, "If, however, your
                        interests are to be protected by my arms it is only fair that my own should
                        not be left undefended. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Furnish me then,
                        if you approve, with such a force as shall suffice to garrison Oreus,
                        Chalcis and Corinth, so that with all safe in my rear I may make war upon
                        Nabis and the Lacedaemonians free from misgivings." The Achaeans were not
                        slow to detect his motive in making such a generous promise and offering aid
                        against the Lacedaemonians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They saw that
                        his real aim was to draw the fighting strength of the Achaeans out of the
                        Peloponnese as hostages and so bind the nation to a war with Rome.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Cycliades, seeing that further
                        argument would be irrelevant, simply observed that the laws of the Achaeans
                        did not allow discussion on any matters other than those which the council
                        had been convened to consider. After a decree had been passed for raising an
                        army to act against Nabis, he dismissed the council over which he had
                        presided with courage and independence. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Before that day he had been looked upon as a strong supporter of the king.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Philip, whose high hopes were thus
                        suddenly dashed, succeeded in enlisting a few volunteers, after which he
                        returned to Corinth and from there to Attica. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the time that Philip was in Achaia,
                        Philocles, one of his generals, started from Euboea with 2000 Thracians and
                        Macedonians for the purpose of ravaging the Athenian territory. He crossed
                        the forest of Cithaeron in the neighbourhood of Eleusis, and there he
                        divided his forces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Half were sent forward
                        to harry and plunder the fields in all directions, the other half he
                        concealed in a position suitable for an ambuscade so that if an attack were
                        made from <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> the fort at Eleusis upon his
                        plunderers he might take the assailants by surprise. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> His ruse, however, was detected, so he recalled the
                        scattered pillagers and made a regular attack upon the fort. After a
                        fruitless attempt in which many of his men were wounded he retired and
                        joined forces with Philip who was on his way from Achaea. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The king himself made an attempt on the same fort but
                        the arrival of the Roman ships from the Piraeus and the presence of a
                        reinforcement which had been thrown into the place compelled him to abandon
                        the undertaking. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then sent Philocles
                        with a part of his army to Athens, and with the rest he proceeded to the
                        Piraeus in order that while Philocles kept the Athenians within their city
                        by approaching the walls and threatening an assault, he might seize the
                        opportunity of storming the Piraeus whilst it was left with a feeble guard.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the assault on the Piraeus proved
                        to be quite as difficult as the one on Eleusis, as practically the same
                        troops defended both. Leaving the Piraeus he hurried up to Athens.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Here a force of infantry and cavalry
                        from the city attacked him within the dilapidated Long Walls which connect
                        the Piraeus with Athens and he was repulsed. Seeing that any attempt on the
                        city was hopeless he divided his army with Philocles and set himself to
                        complete the devastation of the country. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        His former work of destruction had been confined mainly to the sepulchres
                        round the city; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> now he determined to
                        leave nothing free from profanation and gave orders for the temples which
                        the people had consecrated in every deme to be destroyed and set on fire.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The land of Attica was famous for
                        that class of building as well as for the abundance of native marble and the
                        genius of its architects, and therefore it afforded abundant material for
                        this destructive fury. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He was not
                        satisfied with overthrowing the temples with their statues, he even ordered
                        the blocks of stone to be broken in pieces lest if they retained their shape
                        they might form imposing ruins. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> When
                        there was nothing left on which his rage, still insatiate, could wreak
                        itself he left the enemy's territories for Boeotia and did nothing more
                        worth mentioning in Greece. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul Sulpicius was at the time
                        encamped by the river Apsus in a position lying between Apollonia and
                        Dyrrhachium. He recalled L. Apustius and sent him with a portion of his
                        force to ravage the enemy's frontiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        After devastating the borders of Macedon and capturing at the first assault
                        the fortified posts of Corrhagum, Gerrunium and Orgessus, Apustius came to
                        Antipatrea, a place situated in a gorge between two mountain ranges.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He first invited the chief men of the
                        city to a conference, and tried to persuade them to trust themselves to the
                        Romans. Confident in the size of their city, its fortifications, and its
                        strong position, they treated his overtures with contempt. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He then resorted to force and carried the place by
                        assault. After putting the adult males to death and allowing the soldiers to
                        appropriate all the plunder he levelled the walls and burnt the city.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Fear of similar treatment brought
                        about the surrender of Codrion-a fairly strong and fortified town-without
                        offering any resistance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A detachment was
                        left there to garrison the place, and Cnidus-a name better known as that of
                        a city in Asia-was taken by storm. As Apustius was on his way back to the
                        consul with a considerable amount of plunder he was attacked during his
                        passage of the river by Athenagoras, one of the king's prefects, and his
                        rear was thrown into confusion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On hearing
                        the shouting and tumult he galloped back, made his men face about and throw
                        their kits into the centre of the column, and formed his line. The king's
                        soldiers did not stand the charge of the Romans, many were killed and more
                        taken prisoners. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Apustius brought back his
                        army safely to the consul, and was at once sent off to rejoin the fleet.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the commencement of the war was marked
                        by this successful expedition, various princes and leading men from the
                        countries bordering on Macedonia visited the Roman camp; amongst them
                        Pleuratus, the son of Scerdilaedus, Amynander, king of the Athamanians, and
                        Bato, the son of Longarus, who represented the Dardanians. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Longarus had been warring on his own account with
                        Demetrius, Philip's father. In reply to their offers of help the consul said
                        that he would avail himself of the services of the Dardanians and of
                        Pleuratus when he led his army into Macedonia. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> With Amynander he arranged that he should induce the
                        Aetolians to take part in the war. Envoys from Attalus had also come, and he
                        instructed them to ask the king to meet the Roman fleet at Aegina where it
                        was wintering and in conjunction with it to harass Philip, as he had
                        previously done, by naval operations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Emissaries were also sent to the Rhodians urging them to take their share in
                        the war. Philip, who had now arrived in Macedonia, showed no less energy in
                        making preparations for the war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His son
                        Perseus, a mere boy, to whom he had assigned some members of his council to
                        direct and advise him, was sent to hold the pass which leads to Pelagonia.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Sciathos and Peparethos, cities of
                        some importance, were destroyed that they might not enrich the hostile fleet
                        with plunder. He sent envoys to the Aetolians to prevent that people,
                        excited at the arrival of the Romans, from breaking faith with him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The meeting of the Aetolian League which
                        they call the Pan-Aetolium was to be held on a certain day. The king's
                        envoys hastened their journey in order to be in time for it and Lucius
                        Furius Purpurio was also present as representing the consul, as was also a
                        deputation from Athens. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Macedonians
                        were allowed to speak first, as the treaty with them was the latest that had
                        been made. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They said that as no new
                        circumstances had arisen they had nothing new to urge in support of the
                        existing treaty. The Aetolians, having learnt by experience how little they
                        had to gain by alliance with the Romans, had made peace with Philip, and
                        they were bound to keep it now that it was made. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> "Would you prefer," asked one of the envoys, "to copy
                        the unscrupulousness-or shall I call it the levity? of the Romans? When
                        your ambassadors were in Rome, the reply they received was 'Why do you come
                        to us, Aetolians, after you have made peace with Philip without our
                        consent?' And now the very same men insist upon your joining them in war
                        against Philip. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Formerly they pretended
                        that they had taken up arms against him on your account and for your
                        protection, now they forbid you to be at peace with Philip. In the first
                        Punic war they went to Sicily, ostensibly to help Messana; in the second, to
                        deliver Syracuse from Carthaginian tyranny and restore her freedom.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now Messana and Syracuse and in fact
                        the whole of Sicily are tributary to them: they have reduced the island to a
                        province in which they exercise absolute power of life and death. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> You imagine, I suppose, that the Sicilians enjoy
                        the same rights as you, and that as you hold your council at <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> Naupactus under your own laws, presided over by
                        magistrates of your own choice, and with full power of forming alliances or
                        declaring war as you please, so it is with the councils which meet in the
                        cities of Sicily, in Syracuse or Messana or Lilybaeum. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> No: a Roman governor manages their meetings; it is at
                        his summons that they have to assemble; they see him issuing his edicts from
                        his lofty tribunal like a despot, and surrounded by his lictors; their backs
                        are threatened with the rod, their necks with the axe, and every year they
                        have a different master allotted them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Nor ought they, nor can they wonder at this when they see the cities of
                        Italy, such as Regium, Tarentum and Capua, lying prostrate beneath the same
                        tyranny, to say nothing of those close to Rome out of whose ruin she has
                        grown to greatness. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Capua does indeed survive as the
                        sepulchre and memorial of the Campanian nation, the people themselves are
                        either dead and buried, or else cast forth as exiles. It is a headless and
                        limbless city without a senate, without a plebs, without magistrates, an
                        unnatural portent in the land. To leave it as a habitation for men was an
                        act of greater cruelty than its utter destruction would have been.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If men of an alien race, separated
                        from you more widely by language, customs and laws than by intervening sea
                        and land, obtain a hold here, it is folly and madness to hope that anything
                        will remain as it is now. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> You think that
                        Philip's sovereignty is a danger to your liberty. It was your own doing that
                        he took up arms against you, and his sole aim was to have a settled peace
                        with you. All that he asks today is that you will keep that peace unbroken.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Once make foreign legions familiar
                        with these shores and bow your necks to the yoke, then you will seek in vain
                        and too late for Philip's support as your ally; you will have the Romans for
                        your masters. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Aetolians, Acarnanians,
                        Macedonians are united and disunited by slight and purely temporary causes;
                        with foreigners and barbarians, all Greeks ever have been and ever will be
                        at war. For they are our enemies by nature, and nature is unchanging; their
                        hostility is not due to causes which vary from day to day. But I will end
                        where I began. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Three years ago you
                        decided on this very spot to make peace with Philip. You are the same men
                        that you were then, he is the same that he was, the Romans who were opposed
                        to it then are just those who want to upset it now. Fortune has altered
                        nothing, I do not see why you should alter your minds." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Macedonians were followed, at the
                        instance of the Romans, by the Athenians, who after the shocking way they
                        had been treated, had every justification for protesting against Philip's
                        barbarous cruelty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They mourned over the
                        piteous devastation and pillaging of their fields, but it was not because
                        they had suffered hostile treatment from an enemy that they complained.
                        There were certain rights of war which could be justly exercised and
                        therefore must be justly submitted to; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the
                        burning of crops, the destruction of dwellings, the carrying off of men and
                        cattle as plunder, cause suffering to those who endure them, but are not
                        felt to be an indignity. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What they did
                        complain of was that the man who called the Romans foreigners and barbarians
                        had so completely outraged all law, human and divine, that in his first
                        ravages he made impious war upon the infernal deities, and in his subsequent
                        ones he defied the powers above. All the sepulchres and monuments within
                        their borders were destroyed, the dead in all their graves laid bare, their
                        bones no longer covered by the earth. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        There were shrines which their ancestors in the day when they dwelt in
                        separate <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> demes had consecrated in their
                        little fortified posts and villages, and which even when they had been
                        enrolled as citizens of one city they did not abandon or neglect. All these
                        temples Philip had enveloped in sacrilegious flames, the images of their
                        gods, blackened, burnt, mutilated, were lying among the prostrate pillars of
                        their temples. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What he had made the land
                        of Attica, once so fair in its beauty and its wealth, such, if he were
                        allowed, would he make Aetolia and the whole of Greece. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Even Athens itself would have been similarly disfigured
                        if the Romans had not come to the rescue, for the <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> same impious rage was driving him to attack the gods
                        who dwell in the city, Minerva the protectress of the citadel, the Ceres of
                        Eleusis and the Jupiter and Minerva of the Piraeus. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> But he had been repulsed by force of arms, not only
                        from their temples, but even from the walls of the city, and had turned his
                        savage fury against those shrines whose sanctity was their only protection.
                        They closed with an earnest appeal to the Aetolians that they would out of
                        compassion to the Athenians take part in <milestone n="11??" unit="section"
                        /> the war, under the leadership of the immortal gods and of the Romans who
                        next to the gods possessed the greatest power and might. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the Roman legate spoke as follows:
                        "The Macedonians and then the Athenians have compelled me to alter entirely
                        the address I was going to make. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I came to
                        protest against Philip's wrongful action against all those cities of our
                        allies, but the Macedonians by the charges they have brought against Rome
                        have made me a defendant rather than an accuser. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The Athenians, again, by their recital of his impious
                        and inhuman crimes against the gods above and those below, have left nothing
                        more for me or for any one else to bring up against him. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Consider that the same things have been said by the
                        inhabitants of Chios and Abydos, by the Aeneans, the Maronites, the
                        Thasians, by the natives of Paros and Samos, of Larissa and Messene, and by
                        the people over there in Achaia, and that those upon whom he was able to
                        inflict most injury have made the gravest and most serious charges.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As to those actions which he has
                        brought up against us as crimes, I frankly admit that if they do not deserve
                        praise they cannot be defended. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        mentioned, as instances, Regium, Capua and Syracuse. In the case of Regium,
                        the inhabitants themselves begged us during the war with Pyrrhus to send a
                        legion for their protection, and the soldiers, forming a criminal
                        conspiracy, took forcible possession of the town which they were sent to
                        defend. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Did we therefore approve their
                        action? Did we not on the contrary take military measures against the
                        criminals, and when we had them within our power did we not compel them to
                        make satisfaction to our allies by scourgings and executions, and then did
                        we not restore to the Regians their city, their lands and all their
                        possessions, together with their liberty and their laws? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As to Syracuse, when it was oppressed by foreign
                        tyrants-a still greater indignity-we came to its help and spent three weary
                        years in making attacks by sea and land upon its almost impregnable
                        fortifications. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And though the Syracusans
                        themselves would rather have remained under that servile tyranny than let
                        their city be taken by us, we captured it, and the same arms which effected
                        its capture won and secured its freedom. At the same time we do not deny
                        that Sicily is one of our provinces, and the communities which took the side
                        of the Carthaginians and in full sympathy with them urged war against us are
                        now tributary, and pay us the tenth of all their produce. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> We do not deny this; on the contrary we with you and
                        the whole world know that each has been treated in accordance with its
                        deserts. It was the same with Capua. Do you suppose that we regret the
                        punishment meted out to the Capuans, a punishment which they themselves
                        cannot make a ground of complaint? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was
                        on their behalf that we remained at war with the Samnites for nearly seventy
                        years, during which time we suffered severe defeats; we were united with
                        them by treaty, then by intermarriage, and at last by common citizenship.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And yet these men were the first of
                        all the Italian nationalities to take advantage of our difficulties and
                        revolt to Hannibal after massacring our garrison, and then in revenge for
                        our besieging them sent him to attack Rome. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> If neither their city nor a single inhabitant had survived, who could
                        feel any indignation at their fate or charge us with having adopted harsher
                        measures than they deserved? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Those whom a
                        consciousness of guilt drove to suicide were more numerous than those who
                        were punished by us, and though we deprived the survivors of their city and
                        territory we gave them land and a place to dwell in. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> The city itself had not injured us, and we left it
                        standing uninjured, so much so that any one who sees it today would find no
                        trace of its having been stormed and captured. </p>
                    <p> But why do I speak of Capua when even to conquered Carthage we have given
                        peace and liberty? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The danger is rather
                        that by showing too much leniency to the conquered we should incite them all
                        the more to try the fortune of war against us. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> So much in defence of our conduct. With respect to the
                        charges against Philip-the bloodshed in his own family, the murders of his
                        kinsmen and friends, his lust almost more inhuman than his cruelty-you who
                        live nearest to Macedonia know most about them. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> As regards you Aetolians, it was on your behalf that we
                        undertook war against him; you made peace with him without any reference to
                        us. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Perhaps you will say that as we were
                        fully occupied with the Punic War, you were compelled to accept terms of
                        peace from the man whose power was at that time in the ascendant, to which
                        we should reply that it was only after you had laid aside hostilities that
                        we too abandoned them, as greater matters claimed our attention. <milestone
                            n="20" unit="section"/> Now, however, that through the favour of the
                        gods the Punic War is over, we have thrown our whole strength on Macedonia
                        and the opportunity offers itself for you to regain our friendship and
                        support, unless indeed you prefer to perish with Philip rather than conquer
                        with the Romans." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the conclusion of this speech the
                        unanimous feeling was in favour of the Romans. Damocritus, the chief
                        magistrate of the Aetolians, who was currently reported to have been bribed
                        by the king, refused to support either side. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> "In a matter of such serious consequence," he said, "nothing is so fatal
                        to wise counsels as doing things in a hurry. This is followed by quick
                        repentance which, however, is too late, and quite unavailing; decisions
                        hastily and precipitately formed cannot be recalled, nor can the mischief be
                        undone." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He thought that an interval ought
                        to be allowed for mature deliberation, and the time could be fixed there and
                        then. As they were forbidden by law to discuss questions of peace and war
                        anywhere but in the Pan-Aetolian Council, they ought at once to pass a
                        decree exempting the chief magistrate from all penalties, if he summoned a
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> council when he thought the time had
                        come to submit the question of peace and war, and the decrees of that
                        council should have the same force and validity as though they had been
                        passed in a regular Pan-Aetolian Council. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        After the matter was adjourned the envoys were dismissed, and Damocritus
                        said that the decision come to was in the highest degree favourable to the
                        nation, for whichever side had the better fortune in the war, that side they
                        would be able to join. Such were the proceedings in the Pan-Aetolian
                        Council. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip was making vigorous preparations
                        both by land and sea. He concentrated his naval strength at Demetrias in
                        Thessaly, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> as he expected that Attalus
                        and the Roman fleet would move from Aegina at the beginning of the spring.
                        Heraclides was continued in command of the fleet and coast-line. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The gathering of his land forces he conducted in
                        person, encouraged by the belief that he had deprived the Romans of two
                        important auxiliaries, the Aetolians on the one side and the Dardanians on
                        the other, as the pass at Pelagonia was closed by his son Perseus.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> By this time the consul was not
                        preparing for war but actually engaged in it. He led his army through the
                        country of the Dessaretii, and the corn which they had brought from their
                        winter quarters they were carrying with them untouched, as the fields
                        through which they marched supplied all that they wanted. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Some of the towns and villages on his route surrendered
                        voluntarily, others through fear, some were taken by storm, others were
                        found to be abandoned, the inhabitants having fled to the neighbouring
                        mountains. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He formed a standing camp at
                        Lyncus near the river Bevus, and from there he sent parties to collect corn
                        from the granaries of the Dessaretii. </p>
                    <p> Philip saw that there was consternation everywhere and that the population
                        were in a state of panic, but he did not know what part the consul was
                        making for, and accordingly he sent a cavalry detachment to reconnoitre and
                        find out in what direction the enemy were marching. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The consul was equally in the dark, he knew that the
                        king had moved out of his winter quarters, but was ignorant of his
                        whereabouts, so he too sent out cavalry to reconnoitre. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> After each party had wandered for a considerable time
                        along unknown roads amongst the Dassaretii, they at last took the same road.
                        When the noise of men and horses was heard in the distance, they both became
                        aware that an enemy was approaching. So before they came in sight of one
                        another they put their horses and weapons in readiness, and as soon as they
                        saw their enemy they charged. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They were
                        not unfairly matched in numbers and courage, for each corps consisted of
                        picked men, and for some hours they kept up an even fight, until the
                        exhaustion of men and horses put a stop to the battle without either side
                        gaining the victory. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Forty of the
                        Macedonians fell and thirty-five of the Romans. Neither side gained any
                        information as to the whereabouts of their opponents' camp, which they could
                        carry back either to the consul or to the king. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> This information was ultimately conveyed by deserters,
                        a class of persons whom want of principle renders useful in all wars for
                        finding out things about the enemy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the view of doing more to win the
                        affections of his men and make them more ready to meet danger on his behalf,
                        Philip paid <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> special attention to the
                        burial of the men who had fallen in the cavalry action and ordered the
                        bodies to be brought into camp that all might see the honour paid to the
                        dead. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But nothing is so uncertain or so
                        difficult to gauge as the temper of a mass of people. The very thing which
                        was expected to make them keener to face any conflict only inspired them
                        with hesitancy and fear. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Philip's men had
                        been accustomed to fighting with Greeks and Illyrians and had only seen
                        wounds inflicted by javelins and arrows and in rare instances by lances. But
                        when they saw bodies dismembered with the Spanish sword, arms cut off from
                        the shoulder, heads struck off from the trunk, bowels exposed and other
                        horrible wounds, they recognised the style of weapon and the kind of man
                        against whom they had to fight, and a shudder of horror ran through the
                        ranks. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even the king himself felt
                        apprehensive, though he had not yet met the Romans in a pitched battle, and
                        in order <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> to augment his forces he
                        recalled his son and the troops who were stationed in the Pelagonian pass,
                        thus leaving the road open to Pleuratus and the Dardanians for the invasion
                        of Macedonia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He now advanced against the
                        enemy with an army of 20,000 infantry and 4000 cavalry, and came to a hill
                        near Athacus where he strongly intrenched himself about a mile from the
                        Roman camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is said that as he looked
                        down on it and gazed with admiration on the appearance of the camp as a
                        whole and its various sections marked off by the rows of tents and the roads
                        crossing each other, he exclaimed, "No one can possibly take that for a camp
                        of barbarians." For two whole days the king and the consul kept their
                        respective armies in camp, each waiting for the other to attack. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> On the third day the Roman general led out his
                        whole force to battle. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king, however, was afraid of hazarding
                        a general engagement so soon, and contented himself with sending forward a
                        detachment of 400 Trallians-an Illyrian tribe, as we have explained
                        above-and 300 Cretan infantry with an equal number of cavalry under
                        Athenagoras, one of the nobles of his court, to challenge the enemies'
                        cavalry. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans, whose main line was
                        about half a mile distant, sent forward their velites and about two
                        squadrons of cavalry, so that the number of their mounted and unmounted men
                        was equal to that of the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The king's
                        troops expected the style of fighting to be that with which they were
                        familiar; the cavalry would make alternate charges and retirements, at one
                        moment using their missiles, then galloping to the rear; the swift-footed
                        Illyrians would be employed in sudden onsets and rushes; the Cretans would
                        discharge their arrows on the enemy as he dashed forward to attack.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But this order of combat was
                        completely upset by the method of the Roman attack, which was as sustained
                        as it was fierce. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They fought as steadily
                        as though it had been a regular engagement; the velites after discharging
                        their javelins came to close quarters with their swords; the cavalry, when
                        once they had reached the enemy, halted their horses and fought, some on
                        horseback whilst others dismounted and took their places amongst the
                        infantry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Under these conditions Philip's
                        cavalry, unaccustomed to a stationary combat, were no match for the Roman
                        horse, and his infantry, trained to skirmish in loose order and unprotected
                        by armour, were at the mercy of the velites who with their swords and
                        shields were equally prepared for defence and attack. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Incapable of sustaining the conflict and trusting
                        solely to their mobility they fled hack to their camp. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After one day's interval the king decided
                        to bring the whole of his cavalry and light-armed troops into action.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During the night he concealed a body
                        of caetrati, whom they call peltasts, in a position between the two camps
                        well adapted for an ambush, and instructed Athenagoras and his cavalry in
                        case the main battle went favourably to push their advantage, but if not, to
                        give ground slowly and draw the enemy to the place where the ambush was set.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The cavalry did retire, but the
                        officers of the corps of caetrati did not wait long enough for the signal,
                        and by sending their men forward before the right moment lost their chance
                        of success. The Romans, victorious in the open battle and safe from the
                        danger of ambuscade, returned to camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        next day the consul went out to battle with his whole force. In front of his
                        line were posted some elephants which the Romans were using for the first
                        time, having captured some in the Punic war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> When he saw that the enemy were keeping quiet within their lines, he
                        mounted some rising ground close to their rampart and taunted them with
                        their timidity. Even then no chance of fighting was offered him, and as
                        foraging was by no means safe while the camps were in such close proximity
                        since Philip's cavalry would attack his men when they were dispersed amongst
                        the fields, he shifted his camp to a place called Ottolobum, about eight
                        miles off, <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> to allow of his foraging more
                        safely owing to the greater distance. As long as the Romans were cutting
                        corn in the neighbourhood of <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> their camp
                        the king kept his men within their lines in order that the enemy might grow
                        more venturesome and careless. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When he saw
                        them scattered far afield he set off with the whole of his cavalry and the
                        Cretan auxiliaries at such a rapid pace that only the fleetest of the
                        infantrymen could keep up with the troopers. On reaching a position between
                        the foragers and their camp he divided his force. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> One division was sent in pursuit of the scattered
                        foragers, with orders not to leave a single man alive; with the other he
                        beset the various roads by which the enemy would have to return to their
                        camp. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Now men were fleeing and being cut
                        down in all directions, and no one had yet reached the Roman camp with
                        tidings of the disaster because those who fled thither fell into the hands
                        of the king's troops who were waiting for them; more were killed by those
                        who were blocking the roads than by those who had been sent in pursuit.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At last some who had managed to elude
                        the enemy brought, in their excitement, more confusion into the camp than
                        definite information. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul ordered his cavalry to go
                        wherever they could to the rescue of their comrades and at the same time led
                        the legions out of the camp and marched in close order against the enemy.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Some of the cavalry lost their way in
                        the fields owing to the various cries that were raised in different places,
                        others came face to face with the enemy and fighting began at many points
                        simultaneously. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was hottest where the
                        king's stationary troops were posted, for owing to their numbers, both horse
                        and foot, they almost formed a regular army, and as they held the road most
                        of the Romans encountered them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        Macedonians, too, had the advantage of the king's presence to encourage
                        them, whilst the Cretan auxiliaries, in close order and prepared for
                        fighting, made sudden onsets and wounded many of their opponents, who were
                        dispersed without any order or formation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        If they had kept their pursuit within bounds they would not only have come
                        off with flying colours in the actual contest, but they would have gone far
                        to influence the course of the war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As it
                        was, they were carried away by thirst for blood and fell in with the
                        advancing Roman cohorts and their military tribunes; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> the cavalry, too, as soon as they saw the standards of
                        their comrades, turned their horses against the foe who was now in disorder,
                        and in a moment the fortune of the day was reversed, those who had been the
                        pursuers now turned and fled. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Many were
                        killed in hand-to-hand fighting, many whilst fleeing; they did not all
                        perish by the sword, some were driven into bogs and were sucked down
                        together with their horses in the bottomless mud. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Even the king was in danger, for he was flung to earth
                        by his wounded and maddened horse and all but overpowered as he lay.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He owed his safety to a trooper who
                        instantly leaped down and put the king on his own horse, but as he could not
                        keep up on foot with the cavalry in their flight he was speared by the
                        enemy, who had ridden up to where the king fell. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Philip galloped round the swamp and made his way in
                        headlong flight through paths and pathless places until he reached his camp
                        in safety, where most of the men had given him up for lost. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Two hundred Macedonians perished in that battle,
                        about a hundred prisoners were taken and eighty well-equipped horses were
                        secured together with the spoils of their fallen riders. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There have been some who blamed the king's
                        rashness and the consul's want of energy on that day. They said that Philip
                        ought to have remained quiet, for he knew that the enemy would in a few days
                        have cleared all the country round of corn and would have come to the
                        extremity of want. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul, on the
                        other hand, after routing the enemy's cavalry and light infantry and almost
                        capturing the king himself, ought to have marched at once to the enemy's
                        camp; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the enemy were too much demoralised
                        to make any stand and the war could have been finished in a moment.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As in most cases, this was easier to
                        say than to do. Had the king engaged with the whole of his infantry it is
                        possible that he might have lost his camp after they had been completely
                        defeated and fled from the field to their camp, and then continued their
                        flight as the enemy broke through their intrenchments. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But as the infantry force in camp remained intact and
                        the outposts and guards were all at their stations, what would the consul
                        have gained beyond imitating the rashness of the king in his wild pursuit of
                        the routed horses? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nor could any fault be
                        found with the king in his plan of attacking the foragers whilst dispersed
                        through the fields, had he been contented with that success. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> That he should have tempted fortune as he did is
                        the less surprising since a report was current that Pleuratus and the
                        Dardanians had already invaded Macedonia with an immense force. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> With this force assailing him in the rear he
                        might well believe that the Romans would finish the war without striking a
                        blow. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After the two unsuccessful cavalry
                        actions Philip thought that he would be running considerable risk in
                        remaining any longer in his standing camp. As he wanted to conceal his
                        departure from the enemy he sent a flag of truce just after sunset to ask
                        for an armistice for the purpose of burying the dead. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Having thus deceived the enemy he marched out at the
                        second watch in perfect silence, leaving numerous fires alight all through
                        the camp. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul was resting when the news was
                        brought to him of the arrival of the herald and the reason of his coming.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> All his reply was that an interview
                        would be granted on the following morning. This was just what Philip wanted,
                        as it gave him the night and a part of the following day in which to get the
                        start of his opponent. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He took the road
                        over the mountains, which he knew that the Roman general would not attempt
                        with his heavy column. At daybreak the consul granted the armistice and
                        dismissed the herald and not long afterwards became aware that the enemy had
                        disappeared. Not knowing in what direction to follow him he spent some days
                        in camp, collecting corn. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then he marched
                        to Stuberra and gathered out of Pelagonia the corn which was in the fields.
                        From there he advanced to Pluinna without, so far, discovering the route
                        which the enemy had taken. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Philip at first
                        fixed his camp at Bryanium and then advancing by cross-roads created a
                        sudden alarm amongst the enemy. The Romans in consequence left Pluinna and
                        encamped by the river Osphagus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The king
                        pitched his camp not far away by a river which the natives call Erigonus,
                        and carried his intrenchment along the bank. Then, having definitely
                        ascertained that the Romans intended to march to Eordaea, <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> he determined to anticipate them and occupied a narrow
                        pass with the object of making it impossible for the enemy to pass through
                        it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He barricaded it in various ways, in
                        some parts with rampart, in others with fosse, in other places with piled-up
                        stones to serve as a wall, and elsewhere with tree-trunks as the nature of
                        the ground or the materials allowed, until, as he <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> believed, he had made a road which was naturally
                        difficult, absolutely impassable by the obstacles which he had placed across
                        every exit. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The country was mostly
                        forest, difficult for troops to work in, especially for the Macedonian
                        phalanx, for unless they can make a kind of chevaux de frise with the
                        extraordinarily long spears which they hold in front of their shields-and
                        this requires a free and open space-they are of no use whatever. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The Thracians with their pikes, which were also
                        of an enormous length, were hampered and obstructed by the branches on all
                        sides. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Cretan cohort was the only one
                        that was of any service, and this only to a very limited extent, for though
                        when attacked by an unprotected horse and rider they could discharge their
                        arrows with effect, there was not sufficient force in their missiles to
                        penetrate the Roman shields nor was there any exposed part of the body at
                        which they could take aim. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Finding
                        therefore that mode of attack useless, they pelted the enemy with the stones
                        which were lying all over the ravine. This caused more noise than injury,
                        but the drumming on their shields checked the advance of the Romans for a
                        few minutes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> They soon ceased to pay any
                        attention to them, and some of them forming a shield-roof over their heads
                        forced their way through the enemy in front, while others by making a short
                        circuit gained the crest of the hill and drove the Macedonians from their
                        posts of observation. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Escape was almost
                        impossible on such difficult ground, and the greater number were slain. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thus the pass was surmounted with less
                        trouble than they had anticipated, and they entered the district of Eordaea.
                        After ravaging the fields in all directions, the consul moved into Elimia.
                        Here he made an attack on Orestis and approached the town of Celetrum.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was situated on a peninsula, the
                        walls were surrounded by a lake and there was only one road to the adjacent
                        country over a narrow neck of land. At first the townsmen, relying upon
                        their position, closed their gates and rejected the summons to surrender.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When, however, they saw the standards
                        advancing and the legions marching under their shield-roof up to the gate
                        and the narrow neck of land covered by the hostile column, their hearts
                        failed them and they surrendered without risking a battle. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> From Celetrum he advanced into Dassaretia and took the
                        city of Pelion by assault. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The slaves and
                        the rest of the booty he carried off, but the free citizens he set at
                        liberty without ransom, and he restored their town to them after placing a
                        strong garrison in it. It was well adapted from its position to serve as a
                        base for his operations against Macedonia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        After thus scouring the enemy's country, the consul returned to friendly
                        territories and led his force back to Apollonia, which had been his
                        starting-point for the campaign. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Philip
                        had been called away by the Aetolians, the Athamanians, the Dardanians and
                        the numerous wars which had broken out in various quarters. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The Dardanians were already retiring from Macedonia
                        when he sent Athenagoras with the light infantry and the greater part of the
                        cavalry to attack them from the rear as they retreated, and by harassing
                        their rear make them less eager to send their armies away from home.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As to the Aetolians, Damocritus their
                        supreme magistrate, who had advised them at Naupactus to delay resolving
                        upon war, had at their next meeting urged them strongly to take up arms
                        after all that had happened-the cavalry action at Ottolabrum, the invasion
                        of Macedonia by the Dardanians and Pleuratus in conjunction with the
                        Illyrians, and especially the arrival of the Roman <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> fleet at Oreum and the certainty of Macedonia, beset by
                        all those States, being blockaded at sea. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These considerations brought Damocritus
                        and the Aetolians back to the side of the Romans, and in conjunction with
                        Amynander king <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> of the Athamanians they
                        proceeded to invest Cercinium. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        townsmen had closed their gates, whether spontaneously or under compulsion
                        is not clear, as Philip's troops were holding the place. However, in a few
                        days Cercinium was taken and burnt, and those who survived the wholesale
                        slaughter, slaves and citizens alike, were carried off with the rest of the
                        booty. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Dread of a similar fate drove the
                        inhabitants of all the cities round Lake Boebeis to abandon their homes and
                        take to the mountains. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There being no
                        further chance of plunder, the Aetolians left that part of the country and
                        proceeded to go into Perrhaebia. Here they took Cyretiae by storm and
                        ruthlessly sacked it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The population of
                        Maloea surrendered voluntarily and were admitted into the Aetolian League.
                        Leaving Perrhaebia, Amynander advised them to attack Gomphi, as it was close
                        to Athamania and there was every probability of its being carried without
                        much fighting. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Aetolians, however,
                        wanted plunder and made for the fertile plains of Thessaly. Amynander
                        accompanied them, though he did not approve of the disorderly way in which
                        they carried on their depredations nor of their careless method of pitching
                        their camp on any chance ground without taking the trouble to select a good
                        position or throw up proper intrenchments. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        He was afraid that their recklessness and carelessness might bring disaster
                        to him and his men, and when he saw them fixing their camp on flat open
                        ground below the hill on <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> which the city
                        of Phaeca stood, he took possession of some rising ground little more than a
                        mile away which needed very slight fortifying to make it safe. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Except that they continued their depredations
                        the Aetolians seemed to have almost forgotten that they were in an enemy's
                        country; some were roaming about unarmed, others were turning day into night
                        with wine and sleep, leaving the camp altogether unguarded. </p>
                    <p> Suddenly, when no one expected him, Philip came on the scene. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Some who rushed back from the fields announced
                        his appearance, and Damocritus and the other generals were in dire
                        consternation. It happened to be midday, when most of the soldiers were
                        asleep after their heavy meal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their
                        officers roused them, ordered some to arm themselves and sent off others to
                        recall the plundering parties dispersed over the fields. So great was the
                        hurry and confusion that some of the cavalry went off without their swords
                        and most of them had not put on their body-armour. Sent out thus hurriedly,
                        barely amounting to 600 horse and foot they met the king's cavalry, who were
                        superior to them in numbers, equipment and moral. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> They were naturally routed at the first shock, and
                        after showing hardly any fight, broke into a cowardly flight and made for
                        their camp. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Many whom the cavalry cut off
                        from the main body of the fugitives were either killed or captured. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .His men were already coming up to the
                        enemy's rampart when Philip ordered the retreat to be sounded, for horses
                        and men alike were tired, not so much by fighting as by the length and
                        extraordinary celerity of their march. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Orders were given to the cavalry to get water and take their dinner a troop
                        at a time, and the light infantry to do the same, a maniple at a time;
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the others he kept in position under
                        arms waiting for the main body of infantry, who owing to the weight of their
                        armour had marched more slowly. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When these
                        arrived they were ordered to plant their standards and put their arms down
                        in front of them and then take a hasty meal, while two or three at the most
                        were sent from each company to fetch water. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> The cavalry and light infantry were in the meantime standing ready for
                        instant action in case of any movement on the part of the enemy. By this
                        time the crowds of Aetolians who had been dispersed in the fields had
                        regained their camp, and troops were posted about the gates and rampart as
                        though they were prepared to defend their lines. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As long as they saw that the enemy were quiet and they
                        felt safe, they were quite courageous, but as soon as the Macedonians got
                        into motion and began to advance towards their camp fully prepared for
                        battle, they all promptly deserted their posts and made their escape through
                        the gate in the rear of the camp to the eminence on which the Athamanian
                        camp stood. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Philip felt quite certain that
                        he could have deprived the Athamanians also of their camp, had sufficient
                        light remained, but the day had been consumed, first in the battle and then
                        in plundering the Aetolian camp. So he took up his position on the level
                        ground near the hill, prepared to attack at dawn. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But the Aetolians, who had not recovered from the panic
                        in which they had abandoned their camp, fled in various directions during
                        the night. Amynander proved of the greatest assistance to them; under his
                        leading the Athamanians who were familiar with the paths over the mountain
                        summits conducted them into Aetolia by ways unknown to the enemy who was
                        following in pursuit. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A few who had lost
                        their way in the scattered flight fell into the hands of the cavalry whom
                        Philip on finding that the camp was abandoned had sent to harass their
                        retreat. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Athenagoras, Philip's lieutenant, in the
                        meanwhile caught up the Dardanians as they were retiring within their
                        frontiers and created considerable confusion in the rear of their column.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They faced about and formed in line of
                        battle, and a regular engagement ensued in which neither side gained the
                        advantage. When the Dardanians began again to go forward the king's cavalry
                        continued to harass them, as they had no troops of the same kind to protect
                        them, and their equipment rendered them immobile. The ground, too, was in
                        favour of the assailants. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Very few were
                        actually killed, but there were many wounded; no prisoners were taken
                        because they were cautious about leaving their ranks and kept up the
                        retreating fight in close order. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thus
                        Philip through his bold initiative as much as by its successful results kept
                        the two nations in check by his well-timed movements and so made good the
                        losses he had sustained in the war with Rome. An incident which occurred
                        subsequently gave him a further advantage by diminishing the number of his
                        Aetolian enemies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Scopas, one of their
                        principal men, who had been sent by King Ptolemy from Alexandria with a
                        considerable amount of gold, conveyed to Egypt a mercenary army consisting
                        of 6000 infantry and 500 cavalry. He would not have left a single man of
                        military age in Aetolia if Damocritus had not kept some of them at home by
                        sternly reminding them <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> of the war which
                        was imminent and the defenceless condition of a country deprived of its
                        manhood. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It is uncertain whether his
                        action was dictated by patriotism or by personal enmity to Scopas who had
                        not bribed him. Such were the various undertakings in which the Romans and
                        Philip were engaged during this summer. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was in the early part of this summer
                        that the fleet under L. Apustius left Corcyra and after rounding the Cape of
                        Malea was joined by Attalus off Scyllaeum, a place situated in the district
                        of Hermione. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On this the Athenians, who
                        had for a long time been afraid to show their hostility to Philip too
                        openly, now at the prospect of immediate assistance gave full vent to their
                        rage against him. There is never any lack of tongues there to stir up the
                        populace. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> People of this sort thrive on
                        the applause of the mob, and are found in all free States, particularly in
                        Athens where oratory had so much influence. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> A proposal was introduced and at once adopted by the people that all the
                        statues and busts of Philip and of all his ancestors, male and female alike,
                        with the inscriptions on them should be removed and destroyed; the
                        festivals, sacrifices and priests which had been instituted in honour of him
                        or of his predecessors should be abolished; <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> even the localities in which anything had been set up, or where there was
                        any inscription to perpetuate his name, were to be placed under a curse, and
                        nothing which it was right to erect or consecrate on undesecrated ground
                        could be erected or consecrated in these places. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> On every occasion on which the official priests offered
                        up prayers for the people of Athens and the armies and fleets of their
                        allies, they were always to invoke solemn curses on Philip, his children and
                        his realm, al1 his forces, military and naval, and on the whole nation of
                        the Macedonians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was further decreed
                        that if any one should in future introduce any measure calculated to brand
                        Philip with ignominy the Athenians should at once adopt it, and if any one
                        by word or deed tried to vindicate him or do him honour the man who slew him
                        would be justified in doing so. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Finally it
                        was enacted that all the decrees which had been formerly made against
                        Pisistratus should be in force against Philip. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> As far as words went the Athenians made war on Philip,
                        but it was only in these that their strength lay. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Attalus and the Romans arrived at the
                        Piraeus they stayed there a <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> few days and
                        then left for Andros with a heavy cargo of decrees quite as extravagant in
                        their praises of their friends as in their expressions of wrath against
                        their enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They brought up in the
                        harbour of Gaurelum, and a party was sent ashore to test the feelings of the
                        citizens and find out whether they preferred to surrender voluntarily or to
                        await an assault. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They replied that they
                        were not their own masters, as the place was held by Philip's troops.
                        Thereupon the forces were landed and all the usual preparations for an
                        assault were made, Attalus approached the city on one side and the Roman
                        commander on the other. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The novel sight of
                        the Roman arms and standards and the spirit with which the soldiers without
                        the slightest hesitation mounted the walls utterly appalled the Greeks, who
                        promptly fled to the citadel, leaving the enemy in possession of the city.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There they held out for two days,
                        trusting more to the strength of the place than to their own arms; on the
                        third they, together with the garrison, surrendered the town and citadel on
                        condition of being allowed to retire with one garment apiece to Delium in
                        Boeotia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The city itself was made over by
                        the Romans to Attalus; they themselves carried off the plunder and all that
                        adorned the city. Anxious not to have the island a solitude, Attalus
                        persuaded nearly all the Macedonians, as well as some of the Andrians, to
                        remain there. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Subsequently those who had,
                        in accordance with the terms of surrender, migrated to Delium were induced
                        by the king's promises to return, for the love of country made them more
                        ready to trust his word. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From Andros the fleets sailed to Cythnos.
                        Here they spent some days in a fruitless attack on the city, and as it
                        seemed hardly worth while to continue their efforts, they sailed away.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At Prasiae, a place on the mainland
                        of Attica, the Issaeans joined the Roman fleet with twenty fast
                        sailing-vessels. They were sent off to ravage the Carystian country; pending
                        their return the rest of the fleet lay at Geraestus, a well-known port in
                        Euboea. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then they all set sail for the
                        open sea, and leaving Scyros on their right, reached Icus. Here a violent
                        gale from the north detained them for a few days, and as soon as the weather
                        moderated they sailed across to Sciathos, <milestone n="12??" unit="section"
                        /> a city which had been devastated and plundered by Philip. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The soldiers dispersed through the fields and
                        brought back to the ships a supply of corn and whatever other food they
                        could find. There was no plunder, nor had the Greeks done anything to
                        deserve being plundered. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> From there they
                        directed their course to Cassandrea, and touched at Mendae, a village on the
                        coast. Rounding the cape they were purposing to bring their ships right up
                        to the walls when they were caught and scattered by a violent storm in which
                        the vessels almost foundered. It was with difficulty that they gained the
                        land after losing most of their tackle. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        This storm was also a presage of their land operations, for after they had
                        collected their vessels and landed their troops they were repulsed in their
                        attack on the city with heavy loss, owing to the strength of the garrison
                        which held the place for Philip. After this failure they withdrew to
                        Canaestrum in Pallene, and from there sailing round the promontory of Torone
                        they headed for Acanthus. After ravaging the territory they took the city by
                        assault and sacked it. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> As their ships
                        were by this time heavily laden with booty they did not go any further, and
                        retracing their course they reached Sciathus, and from Sciathus they sailed
                        to Euboea. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .Leaving the rest of the fleet there they
                        entered the Maliac Gulf with ten swift vessels to discuss the conduct of the
                        war with the Aetolians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Pyrrhias the
                        Aetolian was the head of the deputation which came to Heraclea to share
                        their views with Attalus and the Roman commander. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Attalus was requested to furnish a thousand soldiers,
                        as under the terms of the treaty he was bound to supply that number if they
                        made war on Philip. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The demand was refused
                        on the ground that the Aetolians had declined to march out and ravage the
                        Macedonian country at the time that Philip was burning everything round
                        Pergamum, sacred and profane, and so draw him off to look after his own
                        interests. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So the Aetolians were dismissed
                        with expectations rather than with actual assistance, as the Romans confined
                        themselves to promises. Apustius returned with Attalus to the fleet. Plans
                        were now discussed for attacking Oreus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        This was a strongly fortified city and, after the former attempt upon it,
                        had been held by a strong garrison. After the capture of Andros twenty
                        Rhodian vessels commanded by Agesimbrotus, all decked ships, joined the
                        Roman fleet. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This squadron was sent to
                        take its station off Zelasium, a promontory in Phthinia beyond Demetrias,
                        where it would be admirably placed for meeting any movement on the part of
                        the Macedonian ships. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Heraclides, the
                        king's admiral, was anchored at Demetrias, waiting for any chance which the
                        enemy's negligence might offer him rather than venturing on open battle. </p>
                    <p> The Romans and Attalus attacked Oreus on different sides; the former
                        directed their assault against the citadel which faced the sea, whilst
                        Attalus directed his towards the hollow between the two citadels where a
                        wall separates one portion of the city from the other. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> And as they attacked at different points, so they
                        employed different methods. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Romans
                        brought their vineae and battering rams close up to the wall, protecting
                        themselves with their shield-roof; the king's troops poured in a hail of
                        missiles from their ballistae and catapults of every description. They
                        hurled huge pieces of rock, and constructed mines and made use of every
                        expedient which they had found useful in the former siege. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The Macedonians, however, who were defending city and
                        citadel were not only in greater force but they not forgotten Philip's
                        censures for their former misconduct nor his threatenings and promises in
                        the respect of the future, and so they exhibited more courage and
                        resolution. The Roman general found that more time was being spent there
                        than he expected and that there was a better prospect of success in a
                        regular investment than in a sudden assault. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Other operations might be conducted during the siege,
                        so, leaving a sufficient force to complete the investment, he sailed to the
                        nearest point on the mainland, and suddenly appearing before Larissa-not the
                        well-known city in Thessaly, but another, called Cremaste-he captured all
                        the city but the citadel. Attalus, too, surprised Aegeleon, where the
                        inhabitants were not in the least apprehending an attack from an enemy who
                        was engaged in the siege of another city. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        By this time the siege-works round Oreus had begun to tell upon the place
                        and the garrison were weakened by <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> their
                        losses and exhausted by the incessant labour of watches and guards by night
                        and day alike. A part of the wall had been loosened by the blows of the
                        battering-rams and had fallen down in several places. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans broke through the breach during the night
                        and forced their way into the citadel commanding the harbour. On receiving a
                        signal from the Romans in the citadel Attalus entered the city at daybreak
                        where a large portion of the wall lay in ruins. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> The garrison and townsmen fled to the other citadel and
                        in two days' time surrendered. The city fell to Attalus, the prisoners to
                        the Romans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The autumnal equinox was now at hand, and
                        the straits of Euboea, which are called Coela, are considered dangerous to
                        navigation. As they were anxious to get away before the winter storms began,
                        the fleets sailed back to the Piraeus, their starting-point for the war.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Leaving thirty ships there Apustius
                        sailed with the remainder past Malea to Corcyra. Atticus was detained by the
                        celebration of the Eleusinian Mysteries at which he wished to be present,
                        and when they were over he withdrew into Asia after sending Agesimbrotus and
                        the Rhodians home. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Such were the
                        operations against Philip and his allies conducted by the Roman consul and
                        his lieutenant with the assistance of King Attalus and the Rhodians.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the other consul, C. Aurelius,
                        came into his province he found the war brought to a close, and he did not
                        conceal his chagrin at the praetor's activity in his absence. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He sent him into Etruria and then took his
                        legions into the enemy's country to plunder it: an expedition from which he
                        returned with more booty than glory. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> L.
                        Furius, finding no scope for his activity in Etruria, and bent upon
                        obtaining a triumph for his victories in Gaul, which he thought he might
                        more easily do while the angry and jealous consul was out of the way,
                        suddenly returned to Rome and convened a meeting of the senate in the temple
                        of Bellona. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After giving a report of what
                        he had done, he asked to be allowed to enter the City in triumph. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A considerable number of the senators
                        supported him in view of the great services he had rendered, and also on
                        personal grounds. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The older members were
                        for refusing him a triumph, partly because the army which he had employed
                        had been assigned to another commander, and partly because in his eagerness
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> to snatch the chance of a triumph he
                        had quitted his province, an act contrary to all precedent. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The consulars, in particular, insisted that he ought to
                        have waited for the consul, for he could then have fixed his camp near the
                        city and so have afforded sufficient protection to the colony to hold the
                        enemy in hand without fighting until the consul came. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> What he failed to do, the senate ought to do, namely,
                        wait for the consul; after hearing what the consul and the praetor had to
                        say, they would form a truer judgment about the case. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Many of those present urged that the senate ought not
                        to consider anything beyond the praetor's success and the question whether
                        he had achieved it as a magistrate with full powers and under his own
                        auspices. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "Two colonies," it was argued,
                        "had been planted as barriers to check risings amongst the Gauls. One had
                        been plundered and burnt, and the conflagration was threatening the other
                        colony which was so near it, like a fire running from house to house. What
                        was the praetor to do? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If no action ought
                        to have been taken in the consul's absence, either the senate was at fault
                        in furnishing the praetor with an army-for as it had decided that the
                        campaign should be fought by the consul's army and not by the praetor's
                        which was far away, so it could have passed a special resolution to the
                        effect that it should be fought under the consul and not under the
                        praetor-or else the consul was in the wrong in not joining <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> his army at Ariminum, after he had ordered it
                        to move from Etruria into Gaul, so that he might take his part in the war,
                        which you say ought not to have been undertaken without him. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The critical moments in war do not wait upon the
                        procrastination and delays of commanders, and you sometimes have to fight,
                        not because you wish to do so, but because the enemy compels you. We ought
                        to keep in view the battle itself and its consequences. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The enemy were routed and cut to pieces; their camp
                        taken and plundered; one colony relieved from siege; those of the other
                        colony who had been made prisoners recovered and restored to their homes and
                        friends; the war was finished in a single battle. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Not to men only was that victory a cause of rejoicing;
                        thanksgivings for three days ought to be offered to the immortal gods
                        because L. Furius had upheld the cause of the republic well and happily, not
                        because he had acted ill and rashly. War with the Gauls was the destined
                        prerogative of the house of the Furii." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Through speeches of this kind delivered by
                        him and his friends, the personal influence of the praetor, who was on the
                        spot, outweighed the dignity and authority of the absent consul, and by an
                        overwhelming majority a triumph was decreed to L. Furius. So L. Furius as
                        praetor celebrated a triumph over the Gauls during his magistracy.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He brought into the treasury 320,000
                        ases and 100,500 pounds of silver. No prisoners were led in procession
                        before his chariot, nor were any spoils exhibited, nor was he followed by
                        his soldiers. It was obvious that everything except the actual victory was
                        at the disposal of the consul. The Games which Scipio had vowed when he was
                        proconsul in Africa were celebrated with great splendour. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> A decree was made for the allotment of land to his
                        soldiers; each man was to receive two jugera for every year he had served in
                        Spain or in Africa, and the decemviri managed the allotment. Commissioners
                        were also appointed to fill up the number of colonists at Venusia, as the
                        strength of that colony had been diminished in the war with Hannibal.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> C. Terentius Varro, T. Quinctius
                        Flamininus and P. Cornelius, the son of Cnaeus Scipio, were the
                        commissioners who undertook the task. During this year C. Cornelius Cethegus
                        who was holding Spain as propraetor routed a large army of the enemy in the
                        Sedetan district. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> 15,000 Spaniards are
                        said to have been killed in that battle and seventy-eight standards taken.
                        On his return to Rome to conduct the elections, C. Aurelius did not, as was
                        anticipated, make it a ground of complaint that the senate had not awaited
                        his return or given him the opportunity of discussing the matter with the
                        praetor. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What he did complain of was the
                        way in which the senate had passed the decree granting the triumph without
                        hearing any of those who had taken part in the war or indeed any one at all
                        except the man who was to enjoy the triumph. "Our ancestors," he said, "laid
                        it down that the lieutenants-general, the military tribunes, the centurions
                        and the soldiers should be present in order that the people of Rome might
                        have visible proof of the victory won by the man for whom such an honour was
                        decreed. Was there a single soldier out of the army which fought with the
                        Gauls, or even a single camp-follower from whom the senate might have
                        enquired as to the truth or falsehood of the praetor's report?" <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> After making this protest he fixed the day for
                        the elections. The new consuls were L. Cornelius Lentulus and P. Villius
                        Tappulus. Then followed the election of praetors. Those returned were L.
                        Quinctius Flamininus, L. Valerius Flaccus, L. Villius Tappulus and Cn.
                        Baebius Tamphilus. </p>
                    <p> Provisions were remarkably cheap that year. A great quantity of corn had
                        been brought from Africa and the curule aediles, M. Claudius Marcellus and
                        Sex. Aelius Paetus, distributed it to the people at two ases the modius.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They also celebrated the Roman Games
                        on a splendid scale and repeated them a second day. Five bronze statues from
                        the proceeds of fines were placed by them in the treasury. The Plebeian
                        Games were celebrated three times by the aediles, L. Terentius Massiliota
                        and Cn. Baebius Tamphilus, the latter being praetor-designate. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Funeral Games were also exhibited in the Forum
                        for four days on the occasion of the death of M. Valerius Laevinus by his
                        sons, Publius and Marcus; they also gave a gladiatorial spectacle in which
                        five-and-twenty pairs fought together. One of the Keepers of the Sacred
                        Books, M. Aurelius Cotta, died and Manlius Acilius Glabrio was appointed to
                        succeed him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It so happened that the
                        curule aediles who were elected were both unable to take up their duties at
                        once; Gaius Cornelius Cethegus was elected while absent in Spain where he
                        held command; C. Valerius Flaccus was in Rome when he was elected, but as he
                        was a Flamen of Jupiter he could not take the oaths, and it was not
                        permitted to hold any magistracy for more than five days without doing so.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Flaccus asked that this condition
                        might be waived in his case and the senate decreed that if an aedile should
                        provide some one, with the approval of the consuls, to take the oaths for
                        him, the consuls might if they thought good arrange with the tribunes for
                        the matter to be referred to the plebs. L. Valerius Flaccus,
                        praetor-designate, was brought forward to take the oaths for his brother.
                        The tribunes brought the matter before the plebs, and the plebs decided that
                        it should be just as though the aedile himself had taken them. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> In the case of the other aedile, the tribunes
                        requested the plebs to appoint two men to command the armies in Spain, and
                        the plebs resolved that the curule aedile C. Cornelius should come home to
                        take up his duties and that L. Manlius Acidinus should retire from his
                        province after having held it for many years. They then made an order that
                        Cn. Cornelius Lentulus and T, Stertinius should have the full powers of
                        proconsuls in Spain. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
