<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Art of Beauty</title>
				<author>P. Ovidius Naso</author>
				<editor role="editor">various</editor>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:FIPSE">The Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education
					(FIPSE)</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>

			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>P. Ovidius Naso</author>
						<title>Ovid's Art of Love (in three Books), the Remedy of Love, the Art of
							Beauty, the Court of Love, the History of Love, and Amours</title>
						<respStmt>
							<name>Anne Mahoney</name>
							<resp>edited for Perseus</resp>
						</respStmt>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Calvin Blanchard</publisher>
							<date>1855</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
     <refsDecl n="NTS">
        <cRefPattern n="line" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']//tei:l[@n='$1'])">
            <p>This pointer pattern extracts line</p>
        </cRefPattern>
    </refsDecl>
     <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="card" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']//tei:div[@n='$1' and @subtype='card'])">
            <p>This pointer pattern extracts card</p>
        </cRefPattern>
    </refsDecl>
	      <refsDecl>
		        <refState unit="poem"/>
		        <refState unit="line"/>
	      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English </language>
				<language ident="lat">Latin </language>
				<language ident="fre">French </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2014-11-06" who="Thibault Clerice">Moving to Epidoc with new URN</change>
    </revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0959.phi003.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
			<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="1">
				<div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="card">
					<l n="1">Once more, ye fair, attend your master's song,</l>
					<l n="2">And learn what method will your charms prolong;</l>
					<l n="3">What happy heart best recommends a face;</l>
					<l n="4">What heightens beauty; what preserves a grace.</l>
					<l n="5">Art improves nature; 'twas by art we found</l>
					<l n="6">The vast advantages of furrow'd ground:</l>
					<l n="7">The soil manur'd, a fruitful harvest bore,</l>
					<l n="8">Where thorns and hungry brambles grew before.</l>
					<l n="9">By art the gard'ner grafts his trees, to bear</l>
					<l n="10">A kinder fruit, and recompense his care.</l>
					<l n="11">A gilded roof delights our captive eyes,</l>
					<l n="12">And stately monuments the sight surprise,</l>
					<l n="13">Tho' sordid earth beneath the polish'd marble lies.</l>
					<l n="14">The fleece may be with royal purple died,</l>
					<l n="15">And <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> precious ivory provide,</l>
					<l n="16">To please your fancies and supply your pride.</l>
					<l n="17">When Tatius rul'd the ancient <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName>
						race,</l>
					<l n="18">Then, rough and careless of a handsome face,</l>
					<l n="19">The women took more pains to earn their bread</l>
					<l n="20">At plough and cart, than how to dress the head;</l>
					<l n="21">All day their task the busy matrons plied,</l>
					<l n="22">Or spinning sat, as to their distaffs tied.</l>
					<l n="23">The mother then at night would fold the sheep</l>
					<l n="24">Her little daughter us'd by day to keep;</l>
					<l n="25">And when at home, would cleave out logs of wood,</l>
					<l n="26">Or kindle up a fire to boil their food.</l>
					<l n="27">But you, by nature form'd in finer moulds,</l>
					<l n="28">Must wrap your tender limbs in silken folds;</l>
					<l n="29">Wear lawns and tissue, sleep in damask beds,</l>
					<l n="30">And with gay knots and wires adorn your heads:</l>
					<l n="31">Your ears with pendants, lockets on your arms,</l>
					<l n="32">Besides a thousand other nameless charms.</l>
					<l n="33">Nor needs this care to please a blush create;</l>
					<l n="34">The men themselves have learned to dress of late.</l>
					<l n="35">You are not now particular in clothes,</l>
					<l n="36">The husband and the bridegroom both are beaux;</l>
					<l n="37">Dress then, and 'tis no sin to dress with art,</l>
					<l n="38">For that's the way to wound the lover's heart.</l>
					<l n="39">E'en those that live remote in country towns,</l>
					<l n="40">Will dress their hair with flowers and daisy crowns,</l>
					<l n="41">And deck and prank themselves, to please the clowns.</l>
					<l n="42">Besides, all women take a secret pride</l>
					<l n="43">In being fine, or else they are belied;</l>
					<l n="44">For when the conscious maid her glass explores,</l>
					<l n="45">And finds she's handsome, she herself adores.</l>
					<l n="46">Thus Juno's bird with silent pride will raise</l>
					<l n="47">And spread his starry plumes, whene'er he meets with praise.</l>
					<l n="48">This method will oblige our sex to love,</l>
					<l n="49">And more than magic herbs their passions move.</l>
					<l n="50">Trust not to philtres; all such stuff forbear;</l>
					<l n="51">Nor try the venom of the lustful mare.</l>
					<l n="52">'Tis all a jest; no snakes by such a force</l>
					<l n="53">Enchanted burst, no rivers change their course;</l>
					<l n="54">Nor can they make the moon from heaven descent</l>
					<l n="55">Whate'er some superstitious fools pretend.</l>
					<l n="56">First learn good breeding; that I first advise;</l>
					<l n="57">Good carriage oft the other wants supplies.</l>
					<l n="58">For when ill-natur'd age shall rudely plough</l>
					<l n="59">Injurious furrows on your wrinkled brow,</l>
					<l n="60">You then perhaps may chide the tell-tale glass,</l>
					<l n="61">That shews the frightful ruins of your face;</l>
					<l n="62">But if good humour to the last remain,</l>
					<l n="63">E'en age may please, and love his force retain. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" n="50" subtype="card">
					<l n="64">Now on, my muse, and tell 'em, when they rise,</l>
					<l n="65">When downy sleep forsakes their tender eyes,</l>
					<l n="66">How they may look as fair as morning skies.</l>
					<l n="67">Vetches, and beaten barley, let 'em take,</l>
					<l n="68">And with the whites of eggs a mixture make;</l>
					<l n="69">Then dry the precious paste with sun and wind</l>
					<l n="70">And into powder very gently grind.</l>
					<l n="71">Get hart's-horn next (but let it be the first</l>
					<l n="72">That creature sheds), and beat it well to dust.</l>
					<l n="73">Six pound in all; then mix and sift 'em well,</l>
					<l n="74">And think the while how fond Narcissus fell;</l>
					<l n="75">Six roots to you that pensive flower must yield</l>
					<l n="76">To mingle with the rest, well bruis'd and cleanly pill'd.</l>
					<l n="77">Two ounces next of gum, and thural seed,</l>
					<l n="78">That for the gracious gods does incense breed,</l>
					<l n="79">And let a double share of honey last succeed.</l>
					<l n="80">With this whatever damsel paints her face,</l>
					<l n="81">Will need no flattering glass to show a grace.</l>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
		</body>
	</text>

</TEI>