<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>In Defense of Lucius Cornelius Balbus </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <pb n="310"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF LUCIUS CORNELIUS BALBUS.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>Lucius Cornelius Balbus was a native of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                        >Gades</placeName><note anchored="true">The modern <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002813">Cadiz</placeName></note> in <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, and of an illustrious family in that
                    city. He had been of great service to the Roman generals in <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, both generally, and also especially at
                    the time of the war with Sertorius, and, as a reward for his fidelity, he had
                    had the freedom of the city given to him by Pompeius, by virtue of a law which
                    authorized him to grant it to as many people as he chose. But the validity of
                    this act of Pompeius was now disputed, on the ground that <placeName
                        key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> was not one of the cities whose
                    inhabitants were capable of receiving such a privilege, and that the law of
                    Lucius Gellius Publicola and of Cnaeus Cornelius Lentulus Clodianus did not
                    apply to them; the prosecution against Balbus being instigated in reality out of
                    hatred to Pompeius and Caesar, in whose army he had at this moment an important
                    command, and by whom he was highly trusted in many most important affairs. </p>
                <p>He was defended by Pompeius and Crassus, and at their request by Cicero also, to
                    whom they gave the post of honour. He was confirmed by the judges in his
                    privileges as a citizen, and was afterwards (A. U. C. 714) made consul, being
                    the first foreigner and adopted citizen who had ever attained that honour in
                        <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>If the authority of those who are advocates in a person's defence be of any weight,
                the cause of Lucius Cornelius has been defended by the most honourable men; if their
                experience is to be regarded, it has been defended by the most skillful lawyers; if
                we look to their ability, by the most eloquent of orators; or if it is their
                sincerity and zeal that we should regard, it has been upheld by those who are his
                greatest friends, and who are united to Lucius Cornelius not merely by mutual
                services, but by the greatest intimacy. What part, then, have I in this defence?
                That which is given to me by such influence as you have been pleased to allow me; by
                moderate experience; and by an ability which is by no means equal to my inclination
                to serve him. For as to the other men by whom he has been defended, I see that to
                them <pb n="311"/> he is under great obligations; but how much I am under
                obligations to him I will explain to you at another time. This I assert at the
                beginning of my speech,—that if I cannot by my exertions properly requite all those
                men who have been friendly to my safety and to my dignity, I will at all events
                recompense them as far as in my power by at all times both feeling and declaring my
                obligations and my gratitude. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> How great was the
                energy displayed by Cnaeus Pompeius in speaking yesterday, O judges, how great his
                fluency, how great the riches of his eloquence, was shown plainly enough, not only
                by the secret feelings of your minds, but by your evident and unconcealed
                admiration. For I never heard anything which appeared to me more acute as regards
                the state of the law, <gap reason="* * *"/> I never heard a more copious
                recollection of precedents; I never heard a more skillful argument concerning
                treaties, nor any statements of more illustrious authority concerning our wars, or
                of more weight and dignity with reference to the general interests of the republic;
                I never heard any one speak more modestly concerning himself, or more eloquently
                concerning the cause and the charge. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So that that
                saying appeared to me to be a true one, which though some men devoted to literature
                and to learned studies were said to have given utterance to it, appeared
                nevertheless to be something incredible; namely, that the man whose soul contained
                every virtue, could with the most perfect ease do everything which he might wish to
                do. For how could there have been a greater fertility and variety and richness of
                eloquence in Lucius Crassus, a man born to a most singular gift of oratory if even
                he had pleaded this cause than was displayed by that man who was able to devote just
                so much time to this study as he spared from the uninterrupted succession of wars
                and victories in which his life has been passed from childhood up to this time?
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And all this makes my task of summing up the more difficult. For, in truth, I am
                coming after an oration which has not just passed by your ears, but has sunk deep
                into the minds of all of you, so that you may very probably derive more pleasure
                from the recollection of that speech, than you can from the hearing not only of
                mine, but of any one else's speech whatever. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But in this I am forced to comply with the wishes not <pb n="312"/> only of
                Cornelius, whose desires I cannot possibly thwart in this his hour of danger, but
                also with those of Cnaeus Pompeius, who has wished me the panegyrist of and the
                assistant in this action, and this determination, and this kindness of his, as I
                lately was in another cause which was pleaded before you, O judges. </p>
            <p><milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And it appears to me that this is what the
                defendant himself deserves, that this is what the unexampled renown of this
                excellent man deserves, that this is what essentially belongs to the discharge of
                your duty, and that this is due to the cause itself, that, what it is quite
                notorious that Cnaeus Pompeius did, all men should allow he had a lawful right to
                do. For there is nothing more true than that which he himself said yesterday, that
                Lucius Cornelius had now all his fortunes at stake, without being accused of any
                single crime of any description. For he is not said to have stolen the rights of a
                citizen, nor to have given any false account of his family, nor to have proceeded in
                an underhand manner by any shameless falsehood, nor to have crept fraudulently into
                the register. One thing alone is imputed to him, that he was born at <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>; a fact which no one denies. All the rest
                the prosecutor admits. He admits that he served in <placeName key="tgn,1000095"
                    >Spain</placeName>, in a most severe war, with Quintus Metellus, with Caius
                Memmius; that he served both in the fleet and in the army; and, when Pompeius came
                into <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName> and began to have Memmius for
                his quaestor, that he never left Memmius; that he went to take possession of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>; that he was present at
                those two hardly contested and most important battles of Sucro and the <placeName
                    key="tgn,7010409">Durius</placeName>; that he remained with Pompeius to the end
                of the war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These are the battles of Cornelius.
                Such were his exertions; such was his industry; such were his dangers encountered on
                behalf of our republic; such was his valour, worthy of a general; while his hopes
                were hopes of a reward in proportion to his dangers. The rewards themselves are not
                the actions of him who obtained them, but of him who conferred them. <milestone
                    n="3" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Therefore on account of this conduct he was presented by Cnaeus Pompeius with the
                freedom of the city. That the prosecutor does not deny; but he finds fault with it,
                in such a manner that, as far as Balbus himself is concerned, his cause is approved
                of even at the moment that it is sought to punish <pb n="313"/> him; in the case of
                Pompeius, his conduct is disapproved of, but no punishment is designed for him. And
                this is the way in which they wish to condemn the fame and fortune of a most
                innocent man and the conduct of a most admirable commander. Therefore it is the
                status of Cornelius as a citizen, and the action of Pompeius that are now on their
                trial before this court. For you admit that this man was born of a most honourable
                rank in that state to which he belongs, and that from his earliest manhood
                disregarding all his private affairs, he has passed his whole time in our wars in
                the company of our own generals, and that he has been absent from no labour, from no
                siege, and from no battle. All these things are full of glory, and are the peculiar
                glory of Cornelius; nor is there any crime in any part of such conduct. </p>
            <p><milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Where then is his crime? Is it because Pompeius
                presented him with the freedom of the city? Is that a crime of Balbus's? By no
                means, unless honour is to be accounted ignominy. Whose crime is it then? In reality
                nobody's at all; but if we look at the pleading of the prosecutor, it is clearly the
                crime of that man alone who gave him the freedom of the city. But if he had been
                influenced by interest, he would probably have selected some less worthy man for
                that reward. Even had he selected a good man, he would not have chosen one who had
                deserved as well of the state as Balbus; even if his action had been one of which it
                could not have been said that it was contrary to what was lawful, it would have been
                said that it was contrary to what was becoming. But all such vituperation would have
                deserved to be rejected by you, O judges. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But at
                present what is it that is said? What does the prosecutor say? That Pompeius did
                what it was not lawful for him to do; which is a more serious charge than if he were
                to say that that had been done by him which was not expedient. For there are things
                which are not expedient even if they are lawful. But whatever is not lawful is most
                certainly not expedient. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Am I now, O judges, to hesitate to urge that it is impossible to doubt that we ought
                to confess that what it is notorious that Cnaeus Pompeius did was not only lawful,
                but also expedient for him to do? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For what
                qualification is wanting in this man, that, if he had it, we should consider that
                this liberty might lawfully be given and allowed to him? <pb n="3145"/> Is it
                experience in affairs? a man who during even the latter days of his childhood was
                beginning his course of the most important wars and commands? most of whose equals
                in age have seen a camp less frequently than he has celebrated a triumph? who has
                celebrated as many triumphs as there are countries and parts of the world? who has
                won as many victories in war as there are kinds of war in the nature of things? Is
                it ability? when even the very results and terminations of transactions have been,
                not the guides, but the companions of his counsels? a man in whom the most
                extraordinary good fortune has so kept pace with extraordinary valour, that, in the
                opinion of all men, more credit was due to the man than to the goddess; Have
                modesty, or integrity, or religion, or diligence ever been wanting in that man? a
                man than whom our provinces, and all free nations, and all kings, and the very most
                distant people of the earth have not only never seen one more chaste, more moderate,
                and more religious, but have never in their hopes or wishes even imagined one.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Why need I speak of his authority, which is
                as great as it ought to be, springing from such great virtue and glory? </p>
            <p> Is it not then, O judges, a shameful thing for the Roman people, that after the
                senate and people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> have conferred
                on that man the rewards of the most honourable dignity; when he not only did not ask
                for commands, but when he even refused them, an inquiry into his conduct should be
                now taking place, in such terms that there should be a discussion as to whether it
                was lawful for him to do what he has done; or whether, I will not say, it was
                lawful, but whether it was impious for him to do so? (for he is said to have done it
                in contravention of a treaty,—that is to say, in contradiction to the religion and
                good faith of the Roman people.) Is it not disgraceful to you yourselves? <milestone
                    n="5" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="11" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I, when a boy, have heard my father say this. When Quintus Metellus, the son of
                Lucius, was prosecuted for extortion and peculation, he, that man to whom the safety
                of his country was dearer than the sight of it, who had rather abandon his city than
                his opinion; when he, I say, was before the court, and when his account-books were
                being carried round to the judges that they might see the entry of one item, I have
                heard that there was not one judge among them <pb n="315"/> Roman knights, most
                excellent men as they were, who did not avert his eyes, and turn himself altogether
                away, lest any one of them should appear for a moment to have doubted whether what
                such a man had entered in his public accounts was true or false. And shall we open
                the question of the legality of a decree of Cnaeus Pompeius, pronounced in
                accordance with the vote of the senate? Shall we compare it with the words of the
                laws? with the treaties? Shall we scrutinise everything with the most unfriendly
                minuteness? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They say that at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, when some man, who had lived among the
                Athenians with a high character for piety and wisdom, had given his evidence in
                public, and (as is the custom of the Greeks) was approaching the altar for the
                purpose of taking an oath in confirmation of it, all the judges cried out that he
                need not take the oath. When Greeks were unwilling to appear to imagine that the
                good faith of a well-proved man felt itself more bound by the formality of an oath
                than by the simple obligation of truth, shall we have a doubt as to what sort of man
                Cnaeus Pompeius has been in respect of his regard for the religious observance of
                laws and treaties? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For do you mean that he acted
                in violation of the treaties ignorantly, or knowingly? If you say that he did so
                knowingly, O, for the name of our empire! O, for the preeminent dignity of the Roman
                people! O, for the glory of Cnaeus Pompeius, so widely and universally diffused, in
                such a manner that the home of his renown has but the same boundaries and limits as
                our common empire! O you nations and cities; and peoples, and kings, and tetrarchs,
                and tyrants, you witnesses not only of the valour of Cnaeus Pompeius in war, but
                also of his conscientiousness in peace! You too I implore, you, O voiceless lands,
                and you, O soil of the most remote districts; you, O seas, O harbours, O islands, O
                shores! For what land is there what place of habitation what spot in which there are
                not the deeply imprinted traces of this man's courage, and humanity, and spirit and
                wisdom? Will any one venture to say that this man endued with such incredible and
                unheard of dignity and wisdom and virtue and consistency, has knowingly neglected
                and violated and broken treaties! <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="14"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>The prosecutor indulges me with a gesture. He intimates that Cnaeus Pompeius acted
                ignorantly. As if it were <pb n="316"/> a lighter charge, when one has been occupied
                in affairs of state in so important a republic, and been presiding over the most
                serious transactions, to do anything which you know not to be legal, or to be
                utterly ignorant what is legal. Do you really mean that he did not know, he who had
                waged a most formidable and important war in <placeName key="tgn,1000095"
                    >Spain</placeName>, what were the rights of the city of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>? or that he did not catch the correct
                interpretation of a treaty made with the people, as not understanding their
                language? Will any one then dare to say that Cnaeus Pompeius is ignorant of that
                which the most ordinary men, men of no knowledge of the world, of no military
                experience, which every common amanuensis professes to be acquainted with?
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I, indeed, think on the contrary, O judges,
                that while Cnaeus Pompeius excels in every kind and variety of accomplishment, even
                of those which are not easily learnt without the most perfect leisure for their
                study, his most extraordinary credit and his most admirable knowledge consists in
                his thorough acquaintance with the treaties, and agreements, and conditions of other
                peoples, kings, and foreign nations, in short, with the entire laws of war and
                peace; unless, indeed, you mean to make out that the things which our books teach us
                while in the shade and at our leisure, Cnaeus Pompeius was incapable of learning,
                either from books, when he was in the enjoyment of peace, or from the actual
                transactions, when he was engaged in the business of the state. </p>
            <p>It is my opinion, O judges,<note anchored="true">Orellius considers the text here as
                    hopelessly corrupt, I have translated the reading of Hottomann, which Orellius
                    approves, and gives in his note.</note> this action is more to be attributed to
                the fault of the times than of the individual. Nor will I say any more about a trial
                of so scandalous a description. For it is the stain and disgrace of this age to envy
                virtue, and to seek to crush the budding flower of worth and dignity. In truth, if
                Cnaeus Pompeius had lived five hundred years ago, <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                that man from whom, while a young man and a Roman knight, the senate had often
                sought aid for the general safety; whose exploits had had all nations for their
                stage, being crowned everywhere by the most illustrious victories, both by land and
                sea; of which three triumphs had been the witnesses, proving that the whole world
                was made subject to <pb n="317"/> our empire; whom the Roman people had
                distinguished with unexampled honours, in that case if it were now said among you
                that anything that he had done had been done in contravention of a treaty, who would
                listen to such a statement? No one. For his death would have put an end to the envy
                of him, his achievements would rest in the glory of his undying name. As then his
                virtue, if it were only heard of by us, would leave no room for doubt or question,
                shall it when present among us, when it has been experienced and beheld by
                ourselves, be injured by the voice of detractors? <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="17" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I will, therefore, say nothing about Pompeius in the rest of my speech; but I entreat
                you, O judges, to retain in your minds and memories what I have said. On the subject
                of the law, of the treaty, of precedents and of the uninterrupted usage of our
                state, I shall repeat those things which have been said already. For neither has
                Marcus Crassus who, as was natural to expect from his eloquence and from his
                honesty, has in the most careful manner explained the whole bearings of the case to
                you nor has Cnaeus Pompeius whose speech abounded in every possible ornament of
                oratory, left me anything new, anything untouched by them to dilate upon: but since,
                though I drew back, they both wished that this last labour of putting, as it were, a
                finishing stroke to their work, should be undertaken by me, I beg of you that you
                will consider that I have undertaken this office and employment more out of regard
                for what I thought my duty, than from any desire of making a display as an orator.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And, before I approach the law of the case and the cause of Cornelius, it seems to me
                desirable to say a little about the common condition of all of us, for the sake of
                deprecating the malevolence of any one. If, O judges, whatever may be the rank in
                which any one is born or whatever the station in which he is placed by birth in
                respect of fortune that same station he ought to maintain to his old age, and if all
                men whom either fortune has raised or whom their own labour or industry has
                ennobled, are to be visited with punishment, then there does not appear to have been
                a more severe law or condition of life imposed on Lucius Cornelius than on many
                other virtuous and gallant men. But if the virtue and genius and humanity of many
                men, though born in the meanest class of life, and in the lowest degree of fortune,
                has not only <pb n="318"/> obtained them friendship and a plentiful estate, but has
                gained them also the greatest praise and honour and glory and dignity, then I cannot
                understand why envy should be more prompt to attack Lucius Cornelius, than your
                justice should to come to the assistance of his modesty. <milestone n="19"
                    unit="section"/> And therefore I do not ask of you what it is very important to
                ask, in order that I may not seem to throw any doubts on your wisdom or your
                humanity; but I must beg of you not to feel any hatred towards genius, not to be
                enemies of industry, not to think that humanity deserves to be oppressed, or virtue
                to be punished. This I beg also; that if you see that my client's cause is of itself
                a sound and just one, you will allow his personal good qualities and accomplishments
                to be an assistance to him now that he is on his trial, rather than a hindrance.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>The cause of Cornelius, O judges, arises from the law which Lucius Gellius and Cnaeus
                Cornelius passed in accordance with the resolution of the senate. By that law we see
                that it is provided that those men shall be Roman citizens whom Cnaeus Pompeius
                shall separately present with the freedom of the city in accordance with the opinion
                of his council. Pompeius here in court asserts that Lucius Cornelius was so
                presented with it. The public records prove this to be the fact: the prosecutor
                admits it. But he says that no man of a people joined to us by treaty was capable by
                law of becoming one of our citizens, unless his own people ratified the measure.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Oh what a splendid interpreter of the law!
                what a fine authority on points of antiquity! what an admirable corrector and
                reformer of our state, to imagine that treaties impose such a penalty on those who
                are bound by them, as to make them all incapable of receiving our rewards and
                kindnesses! For what can possibly be said more ignorant than that it is requisite
                for the federate cities to ratify such a transaction? For that is not a right
                peculiar to federate cities, but to all free nations. But the whole of this, O
                judges, has at all times depended on this consideration, and on this intention,—that
                when the Roman people had ordered anything, if the allied peoples and the Latins had
                adopted and ratified it, and if the law which we had among ourselves was in this
                manner established among some people on a firm footing, then that people should be
                bound by the obligations of that law; not in such a manner as to detract in the
                least from our privileges, <pb n="319"/> but that those nations might enjoy either
                that law which was established among us, or some other advantage and benefit. </p>
            <p><milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Caius Furius, in the time of our ancestors, passed
                a law concerning wills Quintus Voconius passed another concerning the inheritances
                of women; innumerable other laws have been passed about civil law; the Latins have
                adopted whatever of them they have chosen; even by the Julian law itself, by which
                the rights of citizenship were given to the allies and to the Latins, it was decreed
                that those people who did not ratify the law should not have the freedom of the
                city, which circumstance gave rise to a great contention among the people of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName>, and among the people of
                    <placeName key="tgn,1094981">Neapolis</placeName>,<note anchored="true">
                    <placeName key="tgn,7004474">Naples</placeName>
                </note> as a great part of the population in those states preferred the liberty
                which they enjoyed by virtue of their treaty with us to the rights of citizenship. </p>
            <p>Lastly, this is the meaning both of that law and of that expression, that the peoples
                who do ratify it enjoy its advantages owing to our kindness, and not owing to any
                right of their own. </p>
            <p><milestone n="22" unit="section"/> When the Roman people has enacted anything, if it
                be a matter of that sort, that it appears it may be granted also to some other
                nations, whether joined to us by a treaty, or free to decide themselves which law
                they prefer using, not about our affairs, but about their own; then it seems
                necessary to inquire whether they have adopted and ratified our law, or not; but the
                senate never intended that those peoples should have the power of ratifying or
                declining to ratify measures which concern our republic, our empire our wars, our
                victory, and our safety.<note anchored="true">
                    <p>In the seventh century of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, the
                        terms <foreign xml:lang="la">foederatae civitates</foreign>, <foreign
                            xml:lang="la">foederati socii</foreign> expressed those Italian states
                        which were connected with <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> by
                        a treaty. These names did not include Roman colonies or Latin colonies, or
                        any place which had obtained the Roman <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >civitas</foreign>, or right of citizenship. They were independent
                        states, yet under a general liability to furnish a contingent to the Roman
                        army. It was the discontent among the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >foederati</foreign> and their claim to be admitted to the privileges of
                        Roman citizen, that led to the Social war. </p>
                    <p>The <foreign xml:lang="la">Julia Lex</foreign> mentioned in the text, gave
                        the <foreign xml:lang="la">civitas</foreign> to the Socii and Latini. It was
                        passed B.C. <date when="-0090">90</date>. </p>
                    <p>The expression <foreign xml:lang="la">fundus fio</foreign> occurs frequently
                        in the text here, for this <foreign xml:lang="la">lex Julia</foreign>, and
                        another law passed the next year contained a condition that the federate
                        states should consent to accept what the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >lex</foreign> offered or, as it was technically expressed, <foreign
                            xml:lang="la">populus fundus fieret.</foreign> Those who did not become
                            <foreign xml:lang="la">fundi populi</foreign> did not obtain the
                            <foreign xml:lang="la">civitas</foreign>. There were a few <foreign
                            xml:lang="la">foederatae civitates</foreign> out of <placeName
                            key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, of which, as we see, <placeName
                            key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> was one. <placeName
                            key="tgn,7008781">Massilia</placeName> (<placeName key="tgn,7008781"
                            >Marseilles</placeName>) and <placeName key="tgn,7008559"
                            >Saguntum</placeName> (<placeName key="tgn,7008559"
                            >Murviedro</placeName>) were so too. <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 427, v. <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >foederatae civitates</foreign>. In which article Professor Long says,
                        with reference to this cause, “It was objected to Balbus that he could not
                        have the <foreign xml:lang="la">civitas</foreign>, unless the state to which
                        he belonged <foreign xml:lang="la">fundes factus esset</foreign>, which was
                        a complete misapprehension; for the term <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >fundus</foreign> in this sense applied to the whole state or community,
                        whether federate or other free state, which accepted what was offered, and
                        not to an individual of such state or community, who might accept the Roman
                            <foreign xml:lang="la">civitas</foreign> without asking the consent of
                        his fellow-citizens at home, or without all of them receiving the same
                        privilege that was offered to himself.”</p>
                </note>
                <pb n="320"/>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But if it is not to be lawful for our generals, and for the senate, and for the Roman
                people, by holding out rewards to them, to tempt all the bravest and most virtuous
                men out of the cities of our allies and friends to encounter dangers in behalf of
                our safety, then we shall be deprived of what is a most exceeding advantage to us,
                and of what has often been a very great protection and support to us in dangerous
                and critical times. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> But, in the name of the
                immortal gods! what sort of alliance, what sort of friendship, what sort of treaty
                is that by virtue of which our city in its time of danger is to have no defender
                from <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Massilia</placeName>, or from <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, or from <placeName key="tgn,7008559"
                    >Saguntum</placeName>; or, if there should arise an assistant to us from those
                cities, any one who may have aided our generals with the help afforded by his
                labour, or by his riches, or by his personal danger,—any one who may have often
                fought hand to hand in our ranks against our enemies, who may have repeatedly
                exposed himself to the weapons of the enemy, to battle for his life, to imminent
                death,—that such a one can by no possible means be rewarded with the honours
                contained in our rights of citizenship? <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> For it is
                a very serious consideration for the Roman people, if they are not to be able to
                avail themselves of the help of allies who are endued with any extraordinary virtue,
                and who may be willing to join themselves to us, and to consider our danger their
                own; and it is also an injurious and insulting thing towards the allies, and for
                those federate states that we are now discussing, that our most faithful and united
                allies should be shut out from these rewards and from these honours, which are open
                to our mercenary troops, which are open to <pb n="321"/> our enemies, which are open
                often even to our slaves. For we see that mercenary troops in numbers from
                    <placeName key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
                    >Sicily</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7003121">Sardinia</placeName> and other
                provinces have had the freedom of the city conferred on them, and we know that those
                enemies who have come over to our commanders and have been of great use to our
                republic have been made citizens and lastly that slaves,—beings whose rights, and
                fortune, and condition are the lowest of all,—who have deserved well of the republic
                we see constantly presented publicly with liberty, that is to say, with the rights
                of citizenship. <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="25" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>Do you then, O you patron of all treaties and federate states, lay down this as the
                condition of the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, your
                fellow-citizens, that what is lawful for those nations which we have subdued with
                our arms, and reduced under our dominion, having the people of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> for our assistants while doing so, namely,
                that if the Roman people shall permit it, they may have the rights of citizenship
                conferred on them by the senate or by our generals,—is not to be lawful for the men
                of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> themselves? </p>
            <p>Suppose they had determined by their own decrees or laws that no one of their fellow
                citizens should enter the camp of a general of the Roman people, that no one should
                incur any personal risk or danger of his life in defence of our empire, that we
                should not be allowed to avail ourselves of the assistance of the people of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> whenever we chose, and that in
                his private capacity no individual, being eminent for courage and valour, should
                dare to struggle to his own personal danger, in defence of our empire; we should
                naturally be very indignant at that, at the resources of the Roman people being
                diminished, at the courage of brave men being damped, and at our being deprived of
                the aid afforded us by the zeal of nations unconnected with us in our behalf, and by
                the valour of foreign peoples. </p>
            <p><milestone n="26" unit="section"/> But it makes no difference, O judges, whether the
                federate states enact these laws that no one shall be permitted to leave those
                states for the purpose of sharing in the dangers of our wars, or that those things
                cannot possibly be ratified which we have given to their citizens on account of
                their virtue. For we should not any the more have the advantage of these men for our
                assistants if we once take away all the rewards of virtue, than we should if we were
                to make it <pb n="322"/> absolutely unlawful for them to meddle at all in our laws.
                In truth, as, ever since the original birth of man, there have been but few men
                found, who, without any hope of reward, have been willing to expose their lives to
                the weapons of the enemy even for the sake of their own country, do you suppose that
                there will be any one who will expose himself to dangers in the defence of a
                republic with which he has not any connection, when not only no reward is held out
                to him, but when all reward for such conduct is prohibited from being bestowed?
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="27" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But not only was that a most ignorant thing to say, which was said, about states
                ratifying and accepting our laws, as that is a privilege common to all free peoples,
                and not peculiar to federate cities; from which it must inevitably be understood,
                either that no one of the allies can be made a Roman citizen, or else that an
                inhabitant of the federate states may likewise be made one; but this great teacher
                of ours is ignorant also of the whole bearings of the law respecting a man's change
                of citizenship; which, O judges, is a thing which is not only clearly laid down in
                the public laws, but which depends also on the inclination of individuals. For,
                according to our law, no one can change his city against his will, nor can he be
                prevented from changing it, if he pleases, provided only that he be adopted by that
                state of which he wishes to become a citizen. As, for instance, if the people of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> passed a bill concerning any
                Roman citizen by name, that he should become a citizen of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, our citizen would in consequence of that
                bill acquire a complete power of changing his city, and would not be hindered by any
                treaty from becoming a citizen of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>
                after having been a citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>According to our civil law, no one can be a citizen of two cities at the same time; a
                man cannot be a citizen of this city, who has dedicated himself to another city. And
                he may do so not only by dedication, which is a thing which we have seen happen in
                their misfortunes to most illustrious men, to Quintus Maximus, and Caius Laenas, and
                Quintus Philippus at Nuceria, and to Caius Cato at <placeName key="tgn,7008715"
                    >Tarraco</placeName>, to Quintus Caepio and Publius Rutilius at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Smyrna">Smyrna</placeName>, who all became citizens of those
                cities. (They could not lose their rights of citizenship here, before they had as it
                were changed their country by their change of citizenship.) </p>
            <p>But a change of citizenship can also take place by a man's <pb n="323"/> returning to
                his original city. Nor was it without reason that a motion was submitted to the
                people concerning Cnaeus Publicius Menander, a freedman, whom in the time of our
                ancestors some ambassadors of ours when going into <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                    >Greece</placeName> wished to take with them as an interpreter, that that
                Publicius if he returned to his home, and after that again came back to <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, should still be a Roman citizen. For, in
                the recollection of earlier times, many Roman citizens of their own free will, not
                having been condemned by any process of law, nor having been in danger, have left
                our state and joined themselves as citizens to other cities. <milestone n="12"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="29" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But if it is lawful for a Roman citizen to become a citizen of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, either by exile, or by a return to his
                original city, or by a discarding of his rights of citizenship here, (to come now to
                the treaty, which, however, in fact has nothing to do with the cause in hand; for
                what we are discussing is the right of citizenship, and not the treaties,) what
                reason is there why a citizen of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> may
                not be allowed to become a citizen of this city? My opinion, indeed, goes quite the
                other way. For as there is a path from all cities to our city, and as the road to
                all other cities is open to our citizens, so also, in proportion as each city is
                more closely united with us in alliance and friendship, by agreement, and covenant,
                and treaty, the more does that state appear to me to be entitled to a participation
                in our kindness and in our rewards. <gap reason="* * *"/></p>
            <p>But all other cities would without any hesitation receive our men into the rights of
                citizenship with them if we also had the same laws that other nations have. But we
                cannot he citizens of this city and of any other city at the same time though in all
                other cities this is allowed. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/> Therefore in the
                Greek cities we see that Rhodians and Lacedaemonians and men from all quarters are
                enrolled among the citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                and that the same individuals are citizens of many cities at the same time. And I
                have seen some ignorant men, citizens of ours, led by this mistake, sitting at
                    <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> among the judges and members
                of the Areopagus, in a regular tribe and class of Athenian citizens, being ignorant
                that it they acquired the rights of citizenship there they lost their rights here,
                unless they recovered them by a subsequent return to their rights here, and a
                renunciation of the others. But no one who had any acquaintance with our laws or our
                customs, <pb n="3245"/> who wished to retain his rights as a citizen of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, ever dedicated himself to another city.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But the whole of this topic of my speech, and the whole of this discussion, O judges,
                has reference to the common right of changing one's city; it has nothing in it which
                is peculiar to the religious observance of treaties. For I am defending the
                universal principle, that there is no nation on the whole face of the earth,—whether
                at variance with the Roman people through some quarrel and hatred, or, on the other
                hand, united with us by the closest loyalty and mutual good-will,—as to which we are
                forbidden to adopt any one of its citizens as our own, or to present any one of them
                with the freedom of our city. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/> Oh how admirable
                are our laws, and with what god-like wisdom were they established by our ancestors
                from the very first beginning of the Roman name, especially the law that no one of
                our people can be a citizen of more than one city, (for it is inevitable that
                dissimilar states must have a great variety in their laws,) and that no one can be
                compelled against his will to change his city, nor against his will to remain a
                citizen of any city. For these are the firmest foundations of our liberty, that
                every individual should have it in his own power to retain or abandon his
                privileges. </p>
            <p>And without any dispute, that has been the most solid foundation of our empire, and
                the thing which has above all others increased the renown of the Roman name, that
                that first man, the creator of this city, Romulus, taught by the treaty which he
                made with the Sabines, that it was expedient to increase the population of this city
                by the adoption of even enemies as citizens. And in compliance with his authority
                and with the precedent which he established, the presentation of the freedom of our
                city to others has never been interrupted by our ancestors. Therefore, many tribes
                from <placeName key="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName>, the people of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName>, the people of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Lanuvium">Lanuvium</placeName>, and all other peoples of all other
                races, have been received into the privileges of our city;—as, for instance, the
                Sabines, the Hernici, and the Volsci; the citizens of which cities were not
                compelled to change the city to which they belonged, if they were unwilling to do
                so; nor if any of them had acquired the privileges of our citizens by the kindness
                of the Roman people, would the treaty made with them appear to have been violated.
                    <pb n="325"/>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="32" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But some treaties are in existence, as for instance those with the Germans, the
                Insubres, the Helvetians, and the Iapidae, and with some of the barbarian tribes in
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> in which there is a special
                exception made that no one of them is to be received by us as a citizen of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. And if the exception prevents
                such a step from being lawful, it is quite evident that it is lawful where there is
                no such exception made. Where, then, is the exception made in the treaty between us
                and the city of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, that the Roman
                people is not to receive any one of the citizens of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName> into their citizenship? Nowhere. And if there were any such
                clause, the Gellian and Cornelian law would have annulled it which expressly gave to
                Pompeius a power of giving the freedom of the city to anybody whatever. “The whole
                treaty,” says the prosecutor, “is such an exception, because it was ratified with
                solemn oaths.” I can excuse you if you do not know much about the laws of the
                Carthaginians, for you had left your own city; and you were not able to examine our
                laws very strictly; for they prevented your having any opportunity of instituting
                such an examination by a public sentence. </p>
            <p><milestone n="33" unit="section"/> What was there in that enactment which was passed
                concerning Pompeius by Gellius and Lentulus in their consulship in which any
                exception appears to have been made of treaties which had been ratified by an oath?
                For first of all, nothing can be ratified in such a manner except what the burgesses
                or the common people have so ratified. In the second place, such ratifications are
                to be accounted sacred, either because of the form of ratification itself, or
                because the invocation of the gods and dedication of the law, <gap reason="* * *"/>
                or else, because of some punishment to which the life of that man is devoted who
                acts in contravention of it. What argument, then, of this sort can you allege with
                respect to our treaty with the city of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName>?<note anchored="true">There is a good deal of corruption and
                    conjecture in the text here and whatever reading may be adopted, the sense is
                    far from plain.</note> Do you assert that that treaty was solemnly ratified by
                the devotion of the life of any offender against it, or by any invocation of the
                gods to uphold the law? I assert that nothing was ever submitted to the burgesses or
                to the common people with respect to that treaty [I assert that no law was enacted,
                and no punishment appointed.] </p>
            <p>When, therefore even if it had been enacted that we were <pb n="326"/> not to receive
                any man as a citizen, still that would have been ratified which the people enacted
                subsequently, nor would any exception have appeared to have been made by that
                expression, “If anything had been formally ratified by an oath,” do you venture to
                say that anything is formally ratified in this way, with respect to which the Roman
                people has never come to any decision at all? <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="34" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Nor, O judges, has this argument of mine any tendency to invalidate our treaty with
                the city of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>. For it would not become
                me to say anything against the rights of a city which has deserved very well at our
                hands, against the invariable opinion of antiquity, and against the authority of the
                senate. For once, at a very critical period of this republic, when <placeName
                    key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, being exceedingly powerful by sea
                and land, relying on the two Spains, was threatening this empire, and when those two
                thunderbolts of our empire, Cnaeus and Publius Scipio, had suddenly perished in
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, Lucius Marcius, a centurion<note
                    anchored="true">“Polybius, in the fragments of the sixth book, has left an
                    accurate account of the election of centurions. From each division of the
                    legion, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="la">hastati principes</foreign>, and <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">triarii</foreign>, they elect ten men in order of merit to
                    command in their own division. After this a second election of a like number
                    takes place, in all sixty, who are called centurions. The centurions of the
                    first election usually command the right of the <emph>maniple</emph>; but if
                    either of the two is absent, the whole command of the <emph>maniple</emph>
                    devolves on the other. He who is chosen first is admitted to the councils of the
                    general (<foreign xml:lang="la">principilus</foreign>). The <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">principilus</foreign> was the first centurion of the first
                        <emph>maniple</emph> of the <foreign xml:lang="la">Triarii</foreign>. He was
                    entrusted with the care of the eagle, and had the right of attending the
                    councils of the general.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. v. <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >Centurio</foreign>.</note> of the first division, is said to have made a
                treaty with the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>. And as
                this treaty was maintained more in consequence of the loyalty of that people, of our
                justice, and, indeed, of its own antiquity, than because it was ratified by any
                public bond of religion, the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName>, being wise men and well instructed in public law, when
                Marcus Lepidus and Quintus Catulus were consuls, made a request to the senate for a
                more regular treaty; and then the treaty was renewed or made (whichever you please
                to call it) with the men of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>. And
                concerning that treaty the Roman people never recorded any vote; and they cannot
                possibly be bound by any religious obligation which has been contracted without
                their orders. </p>
            <p><milestone n="35" unit="section"/> And so the city of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName> obtained what it was well entitled <pb n="327"/> to obtain by
                its services done to our republic, by the testimony borne in its favour by our
                commanders by the antiquity of its alliance with us, by the authority of Quintus
                Catulus, a most illustrious man by the formal decision of the senate, and by a
                regular treaty; but it has not received any additional sanction from any public
                religious ceremonies of ratification. For the people has in no respect whatever
                bound itself, nor is the cause of the men of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName> any the worse for that; for it is upheld by many and those
                the very wealthiest of circumstances. But however there is at present no room for
                that discussion; for nothing can be so ratified as to be sacred unless it be
                something that has been adopted by the burgesses or by the common people. <milestone
                    n="16" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But if this treaty, which the Roman people, with the authority of the senate with the
                recommendation and decision of antiquity in its favour approves not only by its
                tacit inclination, but also by its open expression of opinion, had been also
                sanctioned by its votes, what reason was there, from the words of the treaty itself,
                why it should not have been lawful to receive a citizen of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> into our city? For there is nothing else
                provided for in the treaty except that there be a pious and everlasting peace. What
                has that to do with the rights of citizenship? That also is added which does not
                occur in every treaty: “Preserve, with all courtesy and respect, the majesty of the
                Roman people.” And that expression carries this force with it, that it shows that
                the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> is the inferior party
                in the treaty. <milestone n="36" unit="section"/> First of all, the very description
                of word used “Preserve” which is a form that we are more accustomed to use in laws
                than in treaties is an expression of one giving a command, not of one addressing an
                entreaty. In the next place, as the majesty of the one people is ordered to be
                preserved and no mention is made of the other, most certainly that people is placed
                on the higher footing and in the superior condition whose majesty is defended by the
                sanction of the treaty. And in respect of this the interpretation of the prosecutor
                is quite undeserving of any reply, who said that the expression “with courtesy and
                respect,” meant the same as “respectively” just as if he were explaining some
                ancient and nearly obsolete word. Men are called courteous, kind, affable, pleasant. <quote>
                    <l>A man who courteously points out the way to a wanderer:</l>
                </quote>—<pb n="328"/>good-naturedly, not sulkily;—“respectively” has surely no
                connection with the rest of the sentence, or with the subject. <milestone n="37"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And, at the same time, it is a perfect absurdity for a provision to be made in the
                treaty that they should “respectively” preserve the majesty of the Roman people;
                that is to say, that the Roman people is to wish its own majesty to be uninjured.
                And if it were so now, as it cannot be, still the fact would remain, that provision
                had been made for our majesty, but none at all for theirs. Can our majesty then be
                preserved with good feeling by the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName>, if we are not able to tempt the men of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> by rewards to be anxious for its
                preservation? Can there, in fact be any majesty at all, if we are prevented from
                availing ourselves of the consent of the Roman people to confer on our
                commander-in-chief the power of distributing honours and kindnesses as a reward of
                virtue? <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="38" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But why am I arguing against statements which it would seem to me might be uttered
                with truth, if the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> were
                speaking against me? for, if they were to demand back Lucius Cornelius, I should
                reply, that the Roman people had enacted a law with respect to giving the freedom of
                the city; and that there was no occasion, nor was it usual for the entire people to
                ratify laws of this sort; that Cnaeus Pompeius, in accordance with the advice of his
                council, had given the freedom of the city to this man, and that the people of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> had no single law whatever of the
                Roman people in their favour. Therefore, that nothing had been sanctified by any
                peculiar solemnity, which appeared to be excepted against by the law; that if there
                were, still there had been no provision made in the treaty respecting anything but
                peace. That this clause also was added, that they were bound to preserve our majesty
                unimpaired; which certainly would be diminished, if it was unlawful either for us to
                avail ourselves of the citizens of those nations as assistants in our wars, or if we
                were to have no power whatever of rewarding them. <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But, now, why should I speak against the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName>, when the very thing which I am defending is sanctioned by
                their desire, by their authority, and by a deputation which they have sent hither on
                purpose? For they, from the very first beginning of their existence as a separate
                people, and of their republic, have turned all their affections from zeal for the
                    <pb n="329"/> Carthaginians and eagerness in their cause, to the upholding of
                our empire and name. And accordingly, when the Carthaginians were waging most
                tremendous wars against us, they excluded them from their city, they pursued them
                with their fleets, they repelled them with their personal exertions, and with all
                their resources and power. They have at all times considered that phantom of a
                treaty made by Marcius as more inviolable than any citadel; and by this treaty and
                by that of Catulus, and by the authority of the senate, they have considered
                themselves as most intimately connected with us. Their ambition, and our ancestors'
                wish, has been, that their walls, their temples, their lands, should be the
                boundaries of the Roman name and Roman empire, as Hercules wished them to be of his
                journeys and of his labours. <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>They invoke as witnesses our deceased generals, whose memory and glory survive for
                everlasting,—the Scipios, the Bruti, the Horatii, the Cassii, the Metelli, and this
                man also, Cnaeus Pompeius whom you see before you; whom when he was carrying on a
                great and formidable war far from their walls, they assisted with supplies and money
                and at this very time they invoke as witnesses the Roman people whom now, at a time
                of great dearness of provisions they have relieved with a large supply of corn as
                they had often done before. They call them, I say, to witness that they wish this to
                be their privilege,—to have a place permitted to them and to their children,
                whenever there are any of distinguished virtue in our camps and in the tent of the
                general and among our standards; and in our line of battle; and that by these steps
                they should have a power of rising up to the freedom of the city. <milestone n="18"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="41" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And if it be lawful to Africans, to Sardinians, to Spaniards,—men who have been
                punished by the deprivation of their lands and by the imposition of tribute,—to
                acquire the rights of citizenship among us by their virtue, but if it be not allowed
                to the men of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, who are united to us
                by duty, and by the antiquity of their alliance with us, and by their loyalty, and
                by our mutual dangers, and by an express treaty, to acquire the same rights, then
                they will think that they have not a treaty with us, but that most iniquitous laws
                have been imposed on them by us. And, O judges, the very circumstances of this case
                show that this assertion is <pb n="330"/> not one just invented by me for the
                purpose, but that I am saying what the men of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName> have instructed me to say. I say that the men of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> publicly entered into a connection of mutual
                hospitality many years before this time with Lucius Cornelius. I will produce
                witnesses, I will produce ambassadors who will prove this; I will bring forward
                panegyrists, whom you see here, having been sent expressly to this trial,—men of the
                highest character and of the most noble birth,—to seek to avert the danger of my
                client by their prayers. Lastly, by an act perfectly unheard-of among the people of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> before this time, the moment that
                it was known that the prosecutor was preparing to bring Balbus before this court,
                the men of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> passed most solemn
                resolutions of their senate respecting their own fellow-citizen. <milestone n="42"
                    unit="section"/> Could the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512"
                    >Gades</placeName> have ratified this act of Pompeius more decidedly, (since I
                have taken a great fancy to the expression,)—if what is meant by ratifying is, to
                approve of our decrees and commands by its decision,—than when it enters into
                connections of hospitality for the express purpose of admitting, by so doing, that
                Balbus had changed his city, and of showing that it considered him entirely worthy
                of the honour of this city? Was it possible for it to exhibit its own opinion and
                inclination more undeniably, than when it imposed a fine and a penalty on my
                client's prosecutor? Was it possible for it to give its decision on the subject more
                plainly, than when it sent its most honourable citizens as deputies to this trial
                which is now taking place before you, to be the witnesses of Balbus's rights, and
                the panegyrists of his conduct through life, and his saviours from danger by their
                prayers? <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>In truth, who is there so insane as not to perceive that it is an object with the men
                of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> to retain this right, and to
                prevent the road to this the most honourable reward which the city can confer from
                being closed against them for ever? and that they have cause to rejoice exceedingly
                that this goodwill of Lucius Cornelius towards his friends is still in existence at
                    <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, and that his interest and power
                of serving his friends is now settled in this city? For who is there of us to whom
                that city of Gades is not the more recommended owing to his zeal and care and
                diligence? <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I say nothing of the great distinction with which Caius Caesar, when he was praetor
                in <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, loaded that people;—<pb n="331"/>
                how he put an end to their disputes, how he established laws among them with their
                own permission, how he eradicated from the manners and customs of the citizens of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> a sort of barbarism that had
                become almost inveterate among them; and how, at the request of this my client, he
                displayed the greatest zeal for and conferred the greatest services on that city. I
                pass over many things which they obtain every day in consequence of this man's
                exertions and zeal either wholly, or at all events with more facility than they
                otherwise would have done. Therefore the chief men of the city are here to stand by
                him and to defend him: with affection, as being their fellow citizen with their
                evidence as a citizen of ours; with kindness, as one who is now their most
                religiously-connected friend, from having been one of their noblest citizens; and
                with earnestness as a most diligent advocate of all their interests. <milestone
                    n="44" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And that the people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName> may not
                think,—although they suffer no actual personal inconvenience,—if it is lawful for
                their citizens to acquire the freedom of our city as a reward for their virtue, that
                still in this respect their treaty is a more unfavourable one than that which has
                been made with the other states, I will console those who are present here,—most
                excellent men,—and also that city which has ever been most faithful and most
                friendly to us, and at the same time I will put you in mind, O judges, though you
                are not ignorant of the truth, that there has never hitherto been the slightest
                doubt expressed about that privilege concerning which this trial has been appointed.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Who, then are the men whom we consider the wisest interpreters of treaties and the
                men of the greatest experience in military law, and the most diligent authorities in
                examining into the different conditions and states of towns? Surely those men who
                have already been placed in command and have had the conduct of wars. <milestone
                    n="20" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>In truth if that celebrated augur Quintus Scaevola, when he was consulted about the
                laws relating to mortgages;—a man most skillful in law,—occasionally referred those
                who consulted him to Furius and Cascellius as men who had invested their money in
                such securities and if we in the transaction referring to our aqueduct consulted
                Marcus Tugio, rather than Caius Aquillius, because constant practice devoted <pb
                    n="332"/> to one particular line of business often proves superior to ability
                and to general information, who can hesitate to prefer our generals to all the most
                experienced lawyers on earth in any case respecting treaties, and the whole state of
                the law of peace and war? <milestone n="46" unit="section"/> May I not therefore,
                mention, with your approbation, Caius Marius, the original author of that conduct
                and of that precedent which is found so much fault with by you? Do you require any
                more weighty example? any one of more consistent wisdom? any one more eminent for
                virtue and prudence, and conscientiousness and equity? Did he, then, confer the
                freedom of the city on Marcus Annius Appius, a most gallant man, and one endued with
                the most admirable virtue, when he knew that the treaty made with Camertum had been
                most solemnly ratified, and was in all respects a most equitable one? Is it
                possible, then, O judges, that Lucius Cornelius should be condemned, without
                condemning also the conduct of Caius Marius? <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Let then, that great man be present for a while to your thoughts, as he cannot appear
                before you in reality, so that you may behold him with your minds whom you cannot
                behold with your eyes. Let him state to you that he has not been altogether unversed
                in treaties, nor wholly inexperienced in the nature of precedents, nor entirely
                ignorant of war; that he was the pupil and soldier of Publius Africanus; that he was
                trained in campaigns and in many warlike lieutenancies; that if he had read of as
                many wars as he has served in and conducted, and brought to a termination,—that if
                he had served under consuls as often as he himself was consul, he might have learnt
                and become thoroughly acquainted with all the laws of war; that he never doubted for
                a moment that no treaty could hinder him from doing anything which was for the
                advantage of the republic; that he carefully selected all the bravest men out of
                every city which was closely connected with and friendly to us; that none of the
                people of <placeName key="perseus,Iguvium">Iguvium</placeName> or of Camertum were
                excepted by treaty, so that their citizens were incapable of receiving from the
                Roman people the rewards of their virtue. <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="48" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Therefore, when, a few years after this present of the freedom of the city, a very
                important and strenuously-contested question arose concerning the rights of
                citizenship according to the previsions of the Licinian and Mucian law, <pb n="333"
                /> was any prosecution instituted against any one of those men of the federate
                states who had had the freedom of the city conferred on him? For Titus Matrinius, of
                Spoletum, one of those men whom Caius Marius had presented with the freedom of the
                city, was indeed prosecuted, being a man of a Latin colony, which was among the
                first for vigour and high character. And when Lucius Antistius, a very eloquent man,
                prosecuted him, he never said that the people of Spoletum had not ratified the deed
                of Marius; for he saw that states were accustomed to ratify laws which concerned
                their own rights, not those which affected ours. But as colonies had not been
                established by the law of Appuleius, by which law Saturninus had carried, in favour
                of Marius, a proposition that he should have authority to make three Roman citizens
                in every colony, he said that this power which was so granted could have no
                validity, since the case for which it had been intended to provide did not exist. </p>
            <p><milestone n="49" unit="section"/> There is no resemblance to this case in the
                present prosecution. But still so great was the authority of Caius Marius, that he
                did not employ true oratory of Lucius Crassus his own relation, a man of
                extraordinary eloquence, but himself in a few words defended his conduct with the
                weight and wisdom which belonged to him, and proved his case to everybody's
                satisfaction. For who could there be, O judges who would wish that the power of
                selecting men for distinction on account of their valour in war, in the line of
                battle, and in the army, should be taken from our generals; or that all hope of
                rewards for the energy shown in defending the republic should be taken from our
                allies, and from the federate states? But if the countenance of Caius Marius, and
                his voice,—if that quickness of eye so advantageous to a general,—if his recent
                triumphs, and the authority of his presence, had such influence, then let his
                authority, and his exploits, and his memory, and the undying name of that most
                illustrious man, prevail still. Let there be this difference between agreeable
                citizens and brave ones,—that the former, while living, may have all the enjoyment
                of their influence, but that the authority of the latter may flourish without decay
                even after they are dead themselves, (if indeed any defender of this empire can be
                properly said to die at all.) <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="50"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>What? Did not Cnaeus Pompeius, the father of <pb n="334"/> this man, after he had
                performed mighty achievements in the Italian war, present Publius Caesius, a Roman
                knight and a virtuous man, who is still alive, a native of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Ravenna">Ravenna</placeName>, a city of a federate state, with the
                freedom of the city of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>? What? did he
                not give the same gift also to two entire troops of the Camertines? What? Did not
                Publius Crassus, that most distinguished man, give the same gift to Alexas, the
                Heraclean, a man of that city with which there was a treaty, such as I may almost
                say there is no other instance of, made in the time of Pyrrhus, by Caius Fabricius,
                the consul? What? did not Sulla do the same to Aristo of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7008781">Massilia</placeName>? What? Since we are speaking of the
                people of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, did not that same man<note
                    anchored="true">There is some great corruption in the text here.</note> make
                nine men of the citizens of <placeName key="tgn,7007512">Gades</placeName>, citizens
                of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> at the same time? What? Did not
                that most scrupulously correct man, that most conscientious and modest man, Quintus
                Metellus Pius, give the freedom of the city to Quintus Fabius, of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7008559">Saguntum</placeName>? What? Did not this very man who is here
                in court, by whom all these cases, which I am now lightly running over, were all
                most carefully wrought up and set before you; did not Marcus Crassus give the
                freedom of the city to a man of <placeName key="perseus,Aletrium"
                    >Aletrium</placeName>, which is a federate town,—Marcus Crassus, I say, a man
                not only eminent for wisdom and sobriety of conduct but also one who is usually even
                too sparing in admitting men as citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName>? <milestone n="51" unit="section"/> And do you now attempt to
                disparage Cnaeus Pompeius's kindness, or I should rather say, his discretion and
                conduct, in doing what he had heard that Caius Marius had done; and what he had
                actually seen done in his own town by Publius Crassus, by Lucius Sulla, by Quintus
                Metellus; and, though last not least, what he had a family precedent for in his own
                father? Nor was Cornelius the only instance of his doing this. For he also presented
                Hasdrubal, of <placeName key="tgn,7008559">Saguntum</placeName>, after that
                important war in <placeName key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, and several of the
                    Mamertines<note anchored="true">There is probably corruption in both these
                    names; especially in the latter. The Mamertines were a people of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>.</note> who came across him, and some
                of the inhabitants of <placeName key="tgn,7018163">Utica</placeName>, and the Fabii
                from <placeName key="tgn,7008559">Saguntum</placeName>, with the freedom of the
                city. </p>
            <p>In truth, as those men are worthy of all other rewards too who defend our republic
                with their personal exertions and at the expense of their own personal danger, so
                certainly those <pb n="335"/> men are of all others the most worthy of being
                presented with the freedom of the city in defence of which they have encountered
                dangers and wounds. And I wish that those men in all quarters of the world who are
                the defenders of this empire, could all enter this city as citizens, and, on the
                other hand, that all the enemies of the republic could be got rid or out of it. Nor,
                indeed did that great poet of our country intend that exhortation which he put into
                the mouth of Hannibal to be peculiarly his language, but rather the common address
                of all generals <quote>
                    <l>The man who slays a foe, whate'er his race, </l>
                    <l>Come whence he will, I call my countryman.</l>
                </quote> And from what country an ally comes, all men consider and always have
                considered unimportant. Therefore, they have at all times adopted brave men as
                citizens from all quarters, and have often preferred the valour of men who may have
                been meanly born to the inactivity of the nobility. <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="52" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You have before you the interpretation put upon the law and upon treaties by the most
                consummate generals, by the wisest men and the most illustrious citizens. I will add
                now that given by the judges who presided at this investigation; I will add that of
                the whole Roman people; I will add the most conscientious and sensible decision of
                the senate. When the judges were stating openly and were explaining without any
                disguise what they intended to decide with respect to the Papian law in the case of
                Marcus Crassus, when the Mamertines claimed him back as a citizen of theirs, the
                Mamertines, though they had commenced the cause under the sanction of the public
                authority of their state abandoned it. <milestone n="53" unit="section"/> Many men
                who had been admitted to the freedom of this city from the free states, or the
                federate cities, were released from all apprehension on the subject. No one was ever
                prosecuted on account of his rights as a citizen, either because his own state had
                not ratified his admission, or because his right to change his city was hindered by
                any treaty. I will venture also to assert even this, that no one ever lost his
                action who was proved to have been presented with the freedom of the city by any one
                of our generals. </p>
            <p>Listen now to the decision of the Roman people given on many different occasions, and
                approved of in the most important causes, in consequence both of the facts of the
                case, and <pb n="336"/> of precedent. Who is there that does not know that a treaty
                was made with all the Latins in the consulship of Spurius Cassius and Postumus
                Cominius? <milestone n="54" unit="section"/> Which, indeed, we recollect to have
                been in existence till quite lately, engraved and written on a brazen column at the
                back of the <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign>. How then was Lucius Cossinius,
                a man of <placeName key="perseus,Tibur">Tibur</placeName>, the father of our present
                Roman knight of the same name, a most excellent and most accomplished man, after
                Titus Caelius had been condemned; and how was Titus Coponius, of the same city, he
                also being a citizen of the very greatest virtue and dignity, (his grandsons Titus
                and Caius Coponius you are all acquainted with,) after Caius Masso had been
                condemned, made a Roman citizen? Are we going to affirm that the path to the freedom
                of the city is open to eloquence and genius, but shall not be open to courage and
                virtue? Was it lawful for the federate states to acquire spoils from us, and shall
                it not be lawful for them to carry them off from the enemy? Or shall it be
                impossible for them to acquire by fighting what they are enabled to acquire by
                speaking? Or did our ancestors intend that the rewards of a prosecutor should be
                greater than those of a warrior? <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But if by that most severe Servilian law, the chief men of the city, men of the
                greatest dignity, citizens of the most profound wisdom, allowed this road to the
                freedom of the city to be opened, in accordance with the resolution of the people,
                to the Latins, that is to say to the federate states, and if this was found no fault
                with by the Licinian and Mucian law, especially when the very nature and name of a
                prosecution, and the reward which no one could obtain except through the misfortune
                of some senator,<note anchored="true">Orellius considers all this sentence corrupt
                    and unintelligible.</note> could not be over pleasant either to a senator or to
                any virtuous man; was it possible to doubt that the decisions of our generals were
                to be of force with respect to that kind of reward in which the decisions of the
                judges had already been ratified? Do we suppose, then, that the sanction of the
                Latin tribes was given to the Servilian law, or to the other laws in which the
                reward of the freedom of the city was held out to men of the Latin towns, as an
                encouragement to such and such conduct? <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Listen now to the decision of the senate, which has at all times been approved of by
                the decision of the people. Our <pb n="337"/> ancestors, O judges, ordained that the
                sacred rites of <placeName key="tgn,7010621">Ceres</placeName> should be performed
                with the very strictest religious reverence and the greatest solemnity; which, as
                they had been originally derived from the Greeks, had always been conducted by Greek
                priestesses, and were called Greek rites. But when they were selecting a priestess
                from <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> to teach us that Greek sacred
                ceremony, and to perform it, still they thought it right that it should be a citizen
                who was sacrificing for citizens, in order that she might pray to the immortal gods
                with knowledge, indeed, derived from a distant and foreign source but with feelings
                belonging to one of our own people and citizens. I see that these priestesses were
                for the most part Neapolitans or Velians, and those are notoriously federate cities.
                I am not speaking of any ancient cases, I am only mentioning things that have
                happened lately, as, for instance, that before the freedom of the city was conferred
                on the Velians, Caius Valerius Flaccus being the city praetor, did, in accordance
                with a resolution passed by the senate, submit a motion to the people concerning a
                woman of <placeName key="perseus,Velia">Velia</placeName>, called Calliphana,
                mentioning her expressly by name, for the purpose of making her a Roman citizen. Are
                we then to suppose that the Velians ratified the law which was then passed about
                her; or that that priestess was not made a Roman citizen; or that the treaty was
                violated by the senate and people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>?
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="56" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I am aware, O judges, that in a cause that is so plain and so little liable to any
                doubt, many more arguments have been adduced and more men of great experience have
                spoken than the case at all required. But that has been done, not in order by our
                speaking to prove to you a matter which required proof so little, but in order to
                check the hostile disposition of all spiteful, and wicked, and envious men, whom the
                prosecutor has sought to inflame, hoping that some of the reports current among men
                who grieve over the prosperity of another might reach your ears, and have their
                effect on the result of this trial; and on that account you saw aspersions scattered
                about with great art in every part of his speech; especially with respect to the
                riches of Lucius Cornelius, which do not deserve to be brought into odium, and
                which, whatever their amount may be, are such as to seem to have been rather
                acquired by care than by any illicit or <pb n="333"/> unfair means; and with respect
                to his luxury, which he attacked, not by bringing any definite charge of
                licentiousness against him, but by mere general abuse. Then, too, he attacked him
                about his farm at <placeName key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName>, which he
                recollected had belonged to Quintus Metellus, and to Lucius Crassus; but he was not
                aware that Crassus had bought it of a man who was a freedman, Sotericus Marcius by
                name; that it had come to Metellus as part of the property of Venonius Vindicius;
                and also, he did not know that lands do not belong to any particular family, that
                they are accustomed to pass by sale to strangers, often even to the very lowest
                people, not being protected by the laws like guardianships. <milestone n="57"
                    unit="section"/> It has been imputed to him also that he has become one of the
                tribe Crustumina, a privilege which he obtained by means of the law concerning
                bribery, and which is less invidious than the advantages acquired by those men who,
                by the assistance of the laws, obtain the power of delivering their opinion as
                praetor, and of wearing the <foreign xml:lang="la">praetexta</foreign>. And then,
                too, the adoption of Theophanus was discussed; by means of which Cornelius gained
                nothing beyond being confirmed in his possession of the inheritances of his own
                relations. <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Although it is not a very difficult matter to propitiate the minds of those men who
                themselves are envious of Cornelius. They show their envy in the ordinary way; they
                attack him at their feasts; they abuse him at their conversations; they carp at him,
                not in a downright hostile spirit, but in a disparaging manner. <milestone n="58"
                    unit="section"/> They who are enemies to the friends of Lucius Cornelius, or who
                envy them, are much more greatly to be feared by him. For who has ever been found
                who would confess himself an enemy to the man himself? Or who could be so with any
                reason? What good man has he not cultivated the friendship of? Who is there whose
                fortune and dignity he has not promoted? Living in the closest intimacy with the
                most influential man in the state, at a time of our greatest misfortunes and most
                bitter dissensions, he has never offended any one of either party, either by act or
                word, or even by a look. It was my fate, or the fate of the republic, that the whole
                weight of distress and ill-will at that time should fall upon me alone. Cornelius
                was so far from exulting in my disasters or in your dissensions, that while I was
                absent, he aided all my friends with his kind <pb n="339"/> assistance, with his
                tears, with his exertions, and with consolation. <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                And I have been induced by their testimony in his behalf, and by their entreaties,
                to offer him my service now, which he has so well deserved, and which on my part is
                only a repayment of just and reasonable gratitude. And I hope, O judges, as you love
                and consider dear to you those men who were the chief agents in my preservation and
                safety, and in the restoration of my dignity, that so also the things which were
                done by this man to the extent of his power and of the opportunities which were
                afforded him, will be grateful to and approved of by you. He, then, is not now
                attacked by his own enemies, for he has none, but by those of his friends; enemies
                who are both numerous and powerful; men whom yesterday Cnaeus Pompeius, in a very
                eloquent and dignified oration, desired to come forward and contend with him if they
                chose, but to abandon the unequal contest and unjust persecution which they were
                carrying on against this man. <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="60"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And it was a fair condition, and one very advantageous, O judges, for us and for all
                those who are connected with us in intimacy that we should carry on our own enmities
                against one another as we chose, but that we should spare the friends of our
                enemies. And if my authority had in this matter much weight with those men,
                especially as they see that I am well instructed in such matters both by the variety
                of circumstances in which I have found myself, and by special experience in cases of
                this sort, I would exhort them to give up even those greater dissensions. For I have
                at all times considered it the part both of fearless citizens and of virtuous men to
                labour in the administration of the affairs of the republic in such a way as to
                defend whatever one really thinks best; nor have I myself ever failed in this labour
                or duty or line of exertion. But contention is only wise so long as it either does
                some good or, if it does not do any good, at all events does no harm to the state.
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/> We ourselves have had wishes, we have urged
                points, we have tried to carry measures, and we have not succeeded. Other men have
                felt indignation; we have undergone real sorrow and distress. Why should we choose
                to destroy those things which exist rather than to preserve them if merely because
                we are not allowed to alter them exactly as we wish? The senate complimented Caius
                Caesar with the most honourable distinction of a supplication <pb n="340"/> lasting
                for a number of days which was quite unprecedented. The senate again, though at a
                time when the treasury was in great difficulties, gave his victorious army a large
                sum for pay, appointed ten lieutenants to assist the commander-in-chief at his
                request, and by the Sempronian law decided not to send any one to supersede him. Of
                all these resolutions, I was the prime mover and the chief author; nor did I think
                myself bound to preserve a consistency with the previous differences which I had had
                with him, rather than to consult what was advantageous with regard to the present
                necessities of the republic and to unanimity. Other men may perhaps think
                differently. They are, maybe, firmer in their opinions. I find fault with no one;
                but I do not agree with all of them. Nor do I think it any proof of inconsistency to
                regulate one's opinions, as one would do a ship or a ship's course on a voyage,
                according to the weather which might be prevailing in the republic. <milestone
                    n="62" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But if there be any people who never abandon any dislike which they have ever
                conceived against anybody,—(and I see that there are some such people,)—then let
                them fight with the leaders themselves, not with their train and followers. Some of
                them, perhaps, will consider that conduct obstinacy, and some will think it courage;
                but this attacking of the subordinate parties all will look upon as injustice, mixed
                with some little cruelty. But if there be some men, O judges, whose minds we cannot
                propitiate by any means whatever, at all events we feel sure that your inclinations
                are favourable to us, not because of our speeches, but because of your own natural
                humanity. <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="63" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For, what reason is there why the intimate friendship of Caesar should not avail to
                procure this my client the highest praise rather than the very slightest injury?
                Caesar knew him when a young man; he, that most able man, thought highly of him, and
                though he had a most excessive multitude of friends, Balbus was accounted by him one
                of his most intimate friends of all. In his praetorship and in his consulship he
                appointed him prefect of the engineers; he thought highly of his prudence, he loved
                him for his integrity, he was grateful to him for his constant assistance and
                attention. He was at different times the partner of very many of his labours; he is
                perhaps even now the partaker of some of <pb n="341"/> his benefits. And if they are
                to be an injury to my client in your judgment, I do not see what is ever to be an
                advantage to any one before such judges. <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But since Caius Caesar is a great distance off, and is now in those places which, if
                we regard their situation, are the boundaries of the world, or, if we regard his
                exploits, of the Roman empire, do not, I entreat you, in the name of the immortal
                gods, O judges, do not allow such bitter news to be taken to him, as that his own
                prefect of engineers, the man of all others most dear to and most intimate with him,
                is crushed by your decision, not on account of any offence of his own, but because
                of his intimacy with him. Pity the man who is now before the court at his own peril,
                not on account of any offence of his own, but because of the action of this great
                and most illustrious man,—who is contesting not any charge which is brought against
                him, but a point of public law and of general interest. And if Cnaeus Pompeius, and
                Publius Crassus, and Quintus Metellus, and Cnaeus Pompeius the father of this man,
                and Lucius Sulla, and Marcus Crassus, and Caius Marius, and the senate and people of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> and all those who have ever given
                a decision under similar circumstances and the federate states, and the allies and
                those ancient men of the Latin tribes whom I have mentioned are all ignorant of this
                law, consider whether it may not be more advantageous and honourable for you to err
                with those men for your guides than to be rightly instructed with this man for your
                teacher. </p>
            <p>But if you see that you are now come to a decision about a law which is certain and
                clear and advantageous and well established and determined, then beware of
                establishing any new principle in a case which has been so loud and so repeatedly
                decided on. <milestone n="65" unit="section"/> And at the same time, O judges, place
                all these considerations before you:—first of all, that all those most illustrious
                men who have ever given any man of a federate city the freedom of this city are now
                on their trial after death; secondly, that the senate is so too, which has
                repeatedly decided in favour of such an act and the people which has voted it and
                the judges who have approved of it. Then consider this also that Cornelius does live
                and always has lived in such a manner that though investigations are appointed for
                every imaginable offence, still he is now brought before the court, not for the sake
                of any punishment which is sought to be inflicted on his vices, but for that at the
                rewards <pb n="342"/> which have been conferred on his virtue. Add this
                consideration also; that you by your decision are about to determine whether you
                choose that for the future the friendship of illustrious men should be a calamity to
                men, or an ornament. Lastly of all, O judges, keep this fixed in your minds, that in
                this action you are about to decide, not on any crime imputed to Lucius Cornelius,
                but on a kindness shown by Cnaeus Pompeius.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
