<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Inst." type="work">Institutio Oratoria, books 1-3: index - 2</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
                <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Quintilian</author>
                        <title>With an English Translation</title>
                        <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1920</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
	    <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="Section"
                         matchPattern="(\\w+).(\\w+).(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\']/tei:div[@n=\'$2\']/tei:div[@n=\'$3\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter and Section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Chapter"
                         matchPattern="(\\w+).(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\']/tei:div[@n=\'$2\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Book"
                         matchPattern="(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="page"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><change who="GRC" when="2006">tagging</change><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
	   <change who="Zach Himes" when="2015-11-17">Edited teiHeader, converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="p.205"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" subtype="book" type="translation">
                <head>Book II</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    THE custom has prevailed and is daily growing
commoner of sending boys to the schools of rhetoric
much later than is reasonable: this is always the
case as regards Latin rhetoric and occasionally
applies to Greek as well. The reason for this is
twofold: the rhetoricians, more especially our own,
have abandoned certain of their duties and the
teachers of literature have undertaken tasks which
rightly belong to others.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For the rhetorician considers that his duty is merely to declaim and give
instruction in the theory and practice of declamation
and confines his activities to deliberative and judicial
themes, regarding all others as beneath the dignity
of his profession; while the teacher of literature is
not satisfied to take what is left him (and we owe
him a debt of gratitude for this), but even presumes
to handle declamations in character and deliberative
themes,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">suasoriae</hi>
                        are declamations on deliberative themes (e.g.
Hannibal deliberates whether he should cross the Alps).
                    </note>
                    tasks which impose the very heaviest burden
on the speaker.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently subjects which once
formed the first stages of rhetoric have come to
form the final stages of a literary education, and
boys who are ripe for more advanced study are kept
back in the inferior school and practise rhetoric
under the direction of teachers of literature. Thus
we get the absurd result that a boy is not regarded
as fit to go on to the schools of declamation till he
knows how to declaim.
                    <pb xml:id="p.207"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The two professions must each be assigned their
proper sphere.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Grammatice,</hi>
                    which we translate as
the science of letters, must learn to know its own
limits, especially as it has encroached so far beyond
the boundaries to which its unpretentious name
should restrict it and to which its earlier professors
actually confined themselves. Springing from a tiny
fountain-head, it has gathered strength from the
historians and critics and has swollen to the dimensions of a brimming river, since, not content with the
theory of correct speech, no inconsiderable subject,
it has usurped the study of practically all the highest
departments of knowledge.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand
rhetoric, which derives its name from the power of
eloquence, must not shirk its peculiar duties nor rejoice to see its own burdens shouldered by others.
For the neglect of these is little less than a surrender
of its birthright.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    I will of course admit that there
may be a few professors of literature who have
acquired sufficient knowledge to be able to teach rhetoric as well; but when they do so, they are performing the duties of the rhetorician, not their own.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    A further point into which we must enquire concerns the age at which a boy may be considered
sufficiently advanced to profit by the instructions of
the rhetorician. In this connexion we must consider
not the boy's actual age, but the progress he has
made in his studies. To put it briefly, I hold that
the best answer to the question
                    <quote>When should a boy be sent to the school of rhetoric?</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    is this,
                    <quote>When he is fit.</quote>
                    But this question is really dependent on that previously raised. For if the duties of
the teacher of literature are prolonged to include
instruction in deliberative declamation, this will
                    <pb xml:id="p.209"/>
                    postpone the need for the rhetorician. On the other
hand if the rhetorician does not refuse to undertake
the first duties of his task, his instruction will be required from the moment the boy begins to compose
narratives and his first attempts at passages of praise
or denunciation.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    We know that the orators of
earlier days improved their eloquence by declaiming
themes and common-places
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">communes loci</hi>
                        = passages dealing with some general
principle or theme. For
                        <hi rend="italic">theses</hi>
                        see
                        <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        iv. 24.
                    </note>
                    and other forms of
rhetorical exercises not involving particular circumstances or persons such as provide the material for
real or imaginary causes.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">controversiae</hi>
                        are declamations on controversial or judicial
themes. A general rule or law is stated: then a special case,
which has to be solved in accordance with the law. An
abbreviated
                        <hi rend="italic">controversia</hi>
                        is to be found in I. x. 33, and they
occur frequently hereafter (cp. esp.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        vi. 96).
                    </note>
                    From this we can clearly
see what a scandalous dereliction of duty it is for
the schools of rhetoric to abandon this department
of their work, which was not merely its first, but
for a long time its sole task.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    What is there in
those exercises of which I have just spoken that
does not involve matters which are the special concern of rhetoric and further are typical of actual
legal cases? Have we not to narrate facts in
the law-courts? Indeed I am not sure that this is
not the most important department of rhetoric in
actual practice.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Are not eulogy and denunciation
frequently introduced in the course of the contests
of the courts? Are not common-places frequently
inserted in the very heart of lawsuits, whether, like
those which we find in the works of Cicero, they are
directed against vice, or, like those published by
Quintus Hortensius, deal with questions of general
interest such as
                    <quote>whether small points of argument should carry weight,</quote>
                    or are employed to
defend or impugn the credibility of witnesses?
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    These are weapons which we should always have
stored in our armoury ready for immediate use as
occasion may demand. The critic who denies that
                    <pb xml:id="p.211"/>
                    such matters concern an orator is one who will
refuse to believe that a statue is being begun
when its limbs are actually being cast. Some will
think that I am in too great a hurry, but let no one
accuse me of thinking that the pupil who has been
entrusted to the rhetorician should forthwith be
withdrawn from the teacher of literature.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The latter
will still have certain hours allotted him, and there
is no reason to fear that a boy will be overloaded by
receiving instruction from two different masters. It
will not mean any increase of work, but merely the
division among two masters of the studies which
were previously indiscriminately combined under one:
and the efficiency of either teacher will be increased.
This method is still in vogue among the Greeks, but
has been abandoned by us, not perhaps without some
excuse, as there were others ready to step into the
rhetorician's shoes.
                </p>
                <p>
                    II. As soon therefore as a boy has made sufficient
progress in his studies to be able to follow what I
have styled the first stage of instruction in rhetoric,
he should be placed under a rhetorician. Our first
task must be to enquire whether the teacher is of
good character.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The reason which leads me to deal
with this subject in this portion of my work is not
that I regard character as a matter of indifference
where other teachers are concerned, (I have already
shown how important I think it in the preceding
book), but that the age to which the pupil has now
attained makes the mention of this point especially
necessary.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For as a rule boys are on the verge of
manhood when transferred to the teacher of rhetoric
and continue with him even when they are young
men: consequently we must spare no effort to secure
                    <pb xml:id="p.213"/>
                    that the purity of the teacher's character should
preserve those of tenderer years from corruption,
while its authority should keep the bolder spirits
from breaking out into licence.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Nor is it sufficient
that he should merely set an example of the highest
personal self-control; he must also be able to govern
the behaviour of his pupils by the strictness of his
discipline.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Let him therefore adopt a parental attitude to his
pupils, and regard himself as the representative of
those who have committed their children to his
charge. Let him be free from vice himself and
refuse to tolerate it in others. Let him be strict but
not austere, genial but not too familiar: for austerity
will make him unpopular, while familiarity breeds
contempt. Let his discourse continually turn on what
is good and honourable; the more he admonishes,
the less he will have to punish. He must control
his temper without however shutting his eyes to
faults requiring correction: his instruction must be
free from affectation, his industry great, his demands
on his class continuous, but not extravagant.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    He
must be ready to answer questions and to put
them unasked to those who sit silent. In praising
the recitations of his pupils he must be neither
grudging nor over-generous: the former quality will
give them a distaste for work, while the latter will
produce a complacent self-satisfaction.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    In correcting
faults he must avoid sarcasm and above all abuse:
for teachers whose rebukes seem to imply positive
dislike discourage industry.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He should declaim
daily himself and, what is more, without stint, that
his class may take his utterances home with them.
For however many models for imitation he may
                    <pb xml:id="p.215"/>
                    give them from the authors they are reading, it will
still be found that fuller nourishment is provided by
the living voice, as we call it, more especially when
it proceeds from the teacher himself, who, if his
pupils are rightly instructed, should be the object
of their affection and respect. And it is scarcely
possible to say how much more readily we imitate
those whom we like.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    I strongly disapprove of the prevailing practice of
allowing boys to stand up or leap from the seats in
the expression of their applause. Young men, even
when they are listening to others, should be
temperate in manifesting their approval. If this
be insisted upon, the pupil will depend on his
instructor's verdict and will take his approval as
a guarantee that he has spoken well.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The worst
form of politeness, as it has come to be called, is
that of mutual and indiscriminate applause, a practice
which is unseemly, theatrical and unworthy of a
decently disciplined school, in addition to being the
worst foe to genuine study. For if every effusion is
greeted with a storm of ready-made applause, care
and industry come to be regarded as superfluous.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The audience no less than the speaker should therefore keep their eyes fixed on their teacher's face, since
thus they will learn to distinguish between what is
praiseworthy and what is not: for just as writing
gives facility, so listening begets the critical
faculty.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    But in the schools of to-day we see boys
stooping forward ready to spring to their feet: at
the close of each period they not merely rise, but
rush forward with shouts of unseemly enthusiasm.
Such compliments are mutual and the success of a
declamation consists in this kind of applause. The
                    <pb xml:id="p.217"/>
                    result is vanity and empty self-sufficiency, carried to
such an extent that, intoxicated by the wild enthusiasm of their fellow-pupils, they conceive a spite
against their master, if his praise does not come up
to their expectation.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    But teachers must also insist
on receiving an attentive and quiet hearing from the
class when they themselves declaim. For the
master should not speak to suit his pupil's standard,
but they should speak to suit his. Further he should,
if possible, keep his eyes open to note the points
which each boy praises and observe the manner in
which he expresses his approval, and should rejoice
that his words give pleasure not only for his own
sake, but for that of those who show sound judgment in their appreciation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    I do not approve of boys sitting mixed with young
men. For even if the teacher be such an one as we
should desire to see in charge of the morals and
studies of the young, and can keep his youthful
pupils under proper control, it is none the less
desirable to keep the weaker members separate from
the more mature, and to avoid not only the actual
charge of corruption but the merest suspicion of it.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    I have thought it worth while to put my views on
this subject quite briefly. For I do not think it
necessary even to warn the teacher that both he and
his school must be free from the grosser vices. And
should there be any father who does not trouble to
choose a teacher for his son who is free from the
obvious taint of immorality, he may rest assured
that all the other precepts, which I am attempting
to lay down for the benefit of our youth, will be
absolutely useless to him, if he neglects this.
                </p>
                <p>
                    III. I do not think that I should pass by in silence
                    <pb xml:id="p.219"/>
                    even the opinion of those who, even when they
regard boys as ripe for the rhetorician, still do not
think that they should at once be placed under the
most eminent teacher available, but prefer to keep
them for a while under inferior masters, on the
ground that in the elementary stages a mediocre
instructor is easier to understand and to imitate, and
less reluctant to undertake the tiresome task of teaching the rudiments as being beneath his notice.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    I do
not think that I need waste much time in pointing
out how much better it is to absorb the best possible
principles, or how hard it is to get rid of faults which
have once become engrained; for it places a double
burden on the shoulders of the later teacher and
the preliminary task of unteaching is harder than
that of teaching.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    It is for this reason that the
famous piper Timotheus is said to have demanded
from those who had previously been under another
master a fee double the amount which he charged
for those who came to him untaught. The mistake
to which I am referring is, however, twofold. First
they regard these inferior teachers as adequate for
the time being and are content with their instruction
because they have a stomach that will swallow anything:
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    this indifference, though blameworthy in
itself, would yet be tolerable, if the teaching provided
by these persons were merely less in quantity and
not inferior in quality as well. Secondly, and this
is a still commoner delusion, they think that those
who are blest with greater gifts of speaking will not
condescend to the more elementary details, and that
consequently they sometimes disdain to give attention to such inferior subjects of study and sometimes
are incapable of so doing.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For my part I regard the
                    <pb xml:id="p.221"/>
                    teacher who is unwilling to attend to such details
as being unworthy of the name of teacher: and as
for the question of capacity, I maintain that it is the
most capable man who, given the will, is able to do
this with most efficiency. For in the first place it is a
reasonable inference that a man blest with abnormal
powers of eloquence will have made careful note of
the various steps by which eloquence is attained,
and in the second place the reasoning faculty,
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    which
is specially developed in learned men, is all-important
in teaching, while finally no one is eminent in the
greater things of his art if he be lacking in the lesser.
Unless indeed we are asked to believe that while
Phidias modelled his Jupiter to perfection, the
decorative details of the statue would have been
better executed by another artist, or that an orator
does not know how to speak, or a distinguished
physician is incapable of treating minor ailments.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Yes</quote>
                    it may be answered
                    <quote>
                        but surely you do not
deny that there is a type of eloquence that is
too great to be comprehended by undeveloped
boys?
                    </quote>
                    Of course there is. But this eloquent
teacher whom they fling in my face must be a
sensible man with a good knowledge of teaching and
must be prepared to stoop to his pupil's level, just as
a rapid walker, if walking with a small child, will
give him his hand and lessen his own speed and
avoid advancing at a pace beyond the powers of his
little companion.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Again it frequently happens that
the more learned the teacher, the more lucid and
intelligible is his instruction. For clearness is the
first virtue of eloquence, and the less talented a man
is, the more he will strive to exalt and dilate himself,
just as short men tend to walk on tip-toe and weak
                    <pb xml:id="p.223"/>
                    men to use threats.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    As for those whose style is
inflated or vicious, and whose language reveals a
passion for high-sounding words or labours under
any other form of affectation, in my opinion they
suffer not from excess of strength but of weakness,
like bodies swollen not with the plumpness of
health but with disease, or like men who weary of
the direct road betake them to bypaths. Consequently the worse a teacher is, the harder he will
be to understand.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    I have not forgotten that I stated in the preceding book, when I urged that school was preferable
to home education, that pupils at the commencement of their studies, when progress is as yet
but in the bud, are more disposed to imitate their
schoolfellows than their masters, since such imitation
comes more easily to them. Some of my readers
may think that the view which I am now maintaining
is inconsistent with my previous statement.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But I
am far from being inconsistent: for my previous
assertion affords the strongest reason for selecting the
very best teachers for our boys; since pupils of a
first rate master, having received a better training,
will when they speak say something that may be
worthy of imitation, while if they commit some
mistake, they will be promptly corrected. But the
incompetent teacher on the other hand is quite
likely to give his approval to faulty work and by the
judgment which he expresses to force approval
on the audience.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The teacher should therefore be
as distinguished for his eloquence as for his good
character, and like Phoenix in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi>
                    be able to
teach his pupil both how to behave and how to
speak.
                    <pb xml:id="p.225"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I shall now proceed to indicate what I think
should be the first subjects in which the rhetorician
should give instruction, and shall postpone for a
time our consideration of the art of rhetoric in the
narrow sense in which that term is popularly used.
For in my opinion it is most desirable that we
should commence with something resembling the
subjects already acquired under the teacher of
literature.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Now there are three forms of narrative, without
counting the type used in actual legal cases. First
there is the fictitious narrative as we get it in
tragedies and poems, which is not merely not true
but has little resemblance to truth.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        With special reference to the element of the miraculous.
Ovid's
                        <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi>
                        would give a good example.
                    </note>
                    Secondly, there
is the realistic narrative as presented by comedies,
which, though not true, has yet a certain verisimilitude. Thirdly there is the historical narrative, which
is an exposition of actual fact. Poetic narratives
are the property of the teacher of literature. The
rhetorician therefore should begin with the historical narrative, whose force is in proportion to its
truth.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    I will, however, postpone my demonstration
of what I regard as the best method of narration
till I come to deal with narration as required in the
courts.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Book IV. chap. ii.</note>
                    In the meantime, it will be sufficient to
urge that it should be neither dry nor jejune (for
why spend so much labour over our studies if a bald
and naked statement of fact is regarded as sufficiently
expressive?); nor on the other hand must it be
tortuous or revel in elaborate descriptions, such
as those in which so many are led to indulge
by a misguided imitation of poetic licence.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Both
these extremes are faults; but that which springs
from poverty of wit is worse than that which is due
                    <pb xml:id="p.227"/>
                    to imaginative excess. For we cannot demand or
expect a perfect style from boys. But there is
greater promise in a certain luxuriance of mind, in
ambitious effort and an ardour that leads at times to
ideas bordering on the extravagant.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    I have no objection to a little exuberance in the young learner.
Nay, I would urge teachers too like nurses to be
careful to provide softer food for still undeveloped
minds and to suffer them to take their fill of the milk
of the more attractive studies. For the time being
the body may be somewhat plump, but maturer years
will reduce it to a sparer habit.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Such plumpness
gives hope of strength; a child fully formed in
every limb is likely to grow up a puny weakling.
The young should be more daring and inventive
and should rejoice in their inventions, even though
correctness and severity are still to be acquired.
Exuberance is easily remedied, but barrenness is
incurable, be your efforts what they may.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    To my
mind the boy who gives least promise is one in
whom the critical faculty develops in advance of the
imagination. I like to see the first fruits of the mind
copious to excess and almost extravagant in their
profusion. The years as they pass will skim off
much of the froth, reason will file away many
excrescences, and something too will be removed
by what I may perhaps call the wear and tear of
life, so long as there is sufficient material to admit
of cutting and chiselling away. And there will
be sufficient, if only we do not draw the plate too
thin to begin with, so that it runs the risk of being
broken if the graver cut too deep.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Those of my
readers who know their Cicero will not be surprised
                    <pb xml:id="p.229"/>
                    that I take this view: for does he not say
                    <quote>I would have the youthful mind run riot in the luxuriance of its growth</quote>
                    ?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        i. xxi. 88.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    We must, therefore, take especial care, above
all where boys are concerned, to avoid a dry
teacher, even as we avoid a dry and arid soil for
plants that are still young and tender.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For with
such a teacher their growth is stunted and their
eyes are turned earthwards, and they are afraid to
rise above the level of daily speech. Their leanness
is regarded as a sign of health and their weakness as
a sign of sound judgment, and while they are content that their work should be devoid of faults they
fall into the fault of being devoid of merit. So let
not the ripeness of vintage come too soon nor the
must turn harsh while yet in the vat; thus it will
last for years and mellow with age.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It is worth while too to warn the teacher that
undue severity in correcting faults is liable at times
to discourage a boy's mind from effort. He loses
hope and gives way to vexation, then last of all
comes to hate his work and fearing everything attempts nothing.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    This phenomenon is familiar to
farmers, who hold that the pruning-hook should not
be applied while the leaves are yet young, for they
seem to
                    <quote>shrink from the steel</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        Verg.
                        <hi rend="italic">G.</hi>
                        ii. 369,
                        <hi rend="italic">ante reformidat ferrum.</hi>
                    </note>
                    and to be unable
as yet to endure a scar.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The instructor therefore
should be as kindly as possible at this stage; remedies, which are harsh by nature, must be applied with
a gentle hand: some portions of the work must be
praised, others tolerated and others altered: the
reason for the alterations should however be given,
and in some cases the master will illumine an
obscure passage by inserting something of his own.
                    <pb xml:id="p.231"/>
                    Occasionally again the teacher will find it useful to
dictate whole themes himself that the boy may
imitate them and for the time being love them as if
they were his own.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    But if a boy's composition is so
careless as not to admit of correction, I have found
it useful to give a fresh exposition of the theme and
to tell him to write it again, pointing out that he
was capable of doing better: for there is nothing
like hope for making study a pleasure.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Different
ages however demand different methods: the task
set and the standard of correction must be proportioned to the pupil's strength. When boys ventured
on something that was too daring or exuberant, I
used to say to them that I approved of it for the
moment, but that the time would come when I
should no longer tolerate such a style. The result
was that the consciousness of ability filled them with
pleasure, without blinding their judgment.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    However, to return to the point from which I had
digressed. Written narratives should be composed
with the utmost care. It is useful at first, when a
child has just begun to speak, to make him repeat
what he has heard with a view to improving his
powers of speech; and for the same purpose, and
with good reason, I would make him tell his story
from the end back to the beginning or start in the
middle and go backwards or forwards, but only so
long as he is at his teacher's knee and while he is
incapable of greater effort and is beginning to connect words and things, thereby strengthening the
memory. Even so when he is beginning to understand the nature of correct and accurate speech,
extempore effusions, improvised without waiting
for thought to supply the matter or a moment's
                    <pb xml:id="p.233"/>
                    hesitation before rising to the feet, must not be permitted: they proceed from a passion for display that
would do credit to a common mountebank.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Such
proceedings fill ignorant parents with senseless pride,
while the boys themselves lose all respect for their
work, adopt a conceited bearing, and acquire the
habit of speaking in the worst style and actually practising their faults, while they develop an arrogant conviction of their own talents which often proves fatal
even to the most genuine proficiency.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    There will be
a special time for acquiring fluency of speech and I
shall not pass the subject by unnoticed. For the meantime it will suffice if a boy, by dint of taking pains and
working as hard as his age will permit, manages to
produce something worthy of approval. Let him get
used to this until it becomes a second nature. It is
only he who learns to speak correctly before he can
speak with rapidity who will reach the heights that
are our goal or the levels immediately below them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    To narratives is annexed the task of refuting and
confirming them, styled
                    <hi rend="italic">anaskeue</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">kataskeue,</hi>
                    from
which no little advantage may be derived. This may
be done not merely in connexion with fiction and
stories transmitted by the poets, but with the actual
records of history as well. For instance we may discuss the credibility of the story that a raven settled
on the head of Valerius in the midst of a combat and
with its wings and beak struck the eyes of the Gaul
who was his adversary, and a quantity of arguments
may be produced on either side:
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    or we may discuss
the tradition that Scipio
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See Aul. Gell. VII. i.</note>
                    was begotten by a serpent,
or that Romulus was suckled by the she-wolf, or the
story of Numa and Egeria. As regards Greek history, it allows itself something very like poetic
                    <pb xml:id="p.235"/>
                    licence. Again the time and place of some particular occurrence and sometimes even the persons concerned often provide matter for discussion: Livy for
instance is frequently in doubt as to what actually
occurred and historians often disagree.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    From this our pupil will begin to proceed to more
important themes, such as the praise of famous men
and the denunciation of the wicked. Such tasks are
profitable in more than one respect. The mind is
exercised by the variety and multiplicity of the subject matter, while the character is moulded by the
contemplation of virtue and vice. Further wide
knowledge of facts is thus acquired, from which examples may be drawn if circumstances so demand,
such illustrations being of the utmost value in every
kind of case.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    It is but a step from this to practice
in the comparison of the respective merits of two
characters. This is of course a very similar theme
to the preceding, but involves a duplication of the
subject matter and deals not merely with the nature
of virtues and vices, but with their degree as well.
But the method to be followed in panegyric and invective will be dealt with in its proper place, as it
forms the third department of rhetoric.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Book III. chap. vii.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    As to
                    <hi rend="italic">commonplaces</hi>
                    (I refer to those in which
we denounce vices themselves such as adultery,
gambling or profligacy without attacking particular persons), they come straight from the courts
and, if we add the name of the defendant, amount
to actual accusations. As a rule, however, the
general character of a commonplace is usually
given a special turn: for instance we make our
adulterer blind, our gambler poor and our profligate
far advanced in years. Sometimes too they entail
                    <pb xml:id="p.237"/>
                    defence:
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    for we may speak on behalf of luxury or
love, while a pimp or a parasite may be defended in
such a way that we appeal as counsel not for the
character itself, but to rebut some specific charge
that is brought against him.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Theses</hi>
                    on the other hand are concerned with
the comparison of things and involve questions such
as
                    <quote>Which is preferable, town or country life?</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Which deserves the greatest praise, the lawyer or the soldier?</quote>
                    These provide the most attractive
and copious practice in the art of speaking, and are
most useful whether we have an eye to the duties
of deliberative oratory or the arguments of the
courts. For instance Cicero in his
                    <hi rend="italic">pro Murena</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Mur.</hi>
                        ix. 21
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    deals
very fully with the second of the two problems
mentioned above.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Other
                    <hi rend="italic">theses</hi>
                    too belong entirely
to the deliberative class of oratory, as for instance
the questions as to
                    <quote>Whether marriage is desirable</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Whether a public career is a proper object of ambition.</quote>
                    Put such discussions into
the mouths of specific persons and they become
deliberative declamations at once.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    My own teachers used to prepare us for conjectural cases by a form of exercise which was at once
useful and attractive: they made us discuss and
develop questions such as
                    <quote>Why in Sparta is Venus represented as wearing armour?</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The reason according to Lactantius (
                        <hi rend="italic">Inst. Div.</hi>
                        i. 20) was
the bravery of the Spartan women in one of the Messenian wars.
                    </note>
                    or
                    <quote>Why is Cupid believed to be a winged boy armed with arrows and a torch?</quote>
                    and the like. In these exercises our aim
was to discover the intention implied, a question
which frequently occurs in controversial declamations.
Such themes may perhaps be regarded as a kind of
                    <hi rend="italic">chria</hi>
                    or moral essay.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    That certain topics such as the question as to
                    <pb xml:id="p.239"/>
                    whether we should always believe a witness or
whether we should rely on circumstantial evidence,
are part and parcel of actual forensic pleading is so
obvious that certain speakers, men too who have
held civil office with no small distinction, have
written out passages dealing with such themes, committed them to memory and kept them ready for
immediate use, with a view to employing them when
occasion arose as a species of ornament to be inserted
into their extempore speeches.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    This practice—
for I am not going to postpone expressing my judgment on it—I used to regard a confession of extreme weakness. For how can such men find appropriate arguments in the course of actual cases which
continually present new and different features?
How can they answer the points that their opponents
may bring up? how deal a rapid counterstroke in
debate or cross-examine a witness? if, even in those
matters which are of common occurrence and crop
up in the majority of cases, they cannot give expression to the most familiar thoughts except in words
prepared so far in advance.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    And when they produce
the same passage in a number of different cases, they
must come to loathe it like food that has grown cold
or stale, and they can hardly avoid a feeling of shame
at displaying this miserable piece of furniture to an
audience whose memory must have detected it so
many times already: like the furniture of the
ostentatious poor, it is sure to shew signs of wear
through being used for such a variety of different
purposes.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Also it must be remembered that there
is hardly a single commonplace of such universal
application that it will fit any actual case, unless
some special link is provided to connect it with
                    <pb xml:id="p.241"/>
                    the subject: otherwise it will seem to have been
tacked on to the speech, not interwoven in its
texture,
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    either because it is out of keeping with the
circumstances or like most of its kind is inappropriately
employed not because it is wanted, but because it is
ready for use. Some speakers, for example, introduce
the most long-winded commonplaces just for the sake
of the sentiments they contain, whereas rightly the
sentiments should spring from the context.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Such
disquisitions are at once ornamental and useful, only if
they arise from the nature of the case. But the most
finished eloquence, unless it tend to the winning of
the case, is to say the least superfluous and may even
defeat its own purpose. However I must bring this
digression to a close.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    The praise or denunciation of laws requires greater
powers; indeed they should almost be equal to the
most serious tasks of rhetoric. The answer to the
question as to whether this exercise is more nearly
related to deliberative or controversial oratory
depends on custom and law and consequently varies
in different states. Among the Greeks the proposer
of a law was called upon to set forth his case before
a judge,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        a court of
                        <hi rend="italic">nomothetae</hi>
                        appointed by the Athenian
assembly, who examined the provisions of the proposed law.
                    </note>
                    while in Rome it was the custom to urge
the acceptance or rejection of a law before the public
assembly. But in any case the arguments advanced
in such cases are few in number and of a definite
type. For there are only three kinds of law,
                    <hi rend="italic">sacred, public</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">private.</hi>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    This division is of rhetorical value
chiefly when a law is to be praised. For example the
orator may advance from praise to praise by a series of
gradations, praising an enactment first because it is
                    <hi rend="italic">law,</hi>
                    secondly because it is
                    <hi rend="italic">public,</hi>
                    and, finally, designed
for the support of
                    <hi rend="italic">religion.</hi>
                    As regards the questions
                    <pb xml:id="p.243"/>
                    which generally arise, they are common to all cases.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    Doubts may be raised as to whether the mover is
legally in a position to propose a law, as happened in
the case of Publius Clodius, whose appointment as
tribune of the plebs was alleged to be unconstitutional.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Clodius was a patrician and got himself made a plebeian
by adoption to enable him to hold the tribunate. The
question of the legality of this procedure is discussed by
Cicero in the
                        <hi rend="italic">de Domo,</hi>
                        13–17.
                    </note>
                    Or the legality of the proposal itself may
be impugned in various ways; it may for instance be
urged that the law was not promulgated within
seventeen
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Lit. within the space of three market-days.
                        <hi rend="italic">nundinum</hi>
                        =9 days, the second market-day being the ninth, and
forming the last day of the first
                        <hi rend="italic">nundinum</hi>
                        and the first of the second. Similarly the third market-day is the last day
of the second
                        <hi rend="italic">nundinum</hi>
                        and the first of the third.
                    </note>
                    days, or was proposed, or is being proposed on an improper day, or in defiance of the
tribunicial veto or the auspices or any other legal
obstacle, or again that it is contrary to some existing law.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    But such points are not suitable to
elementary rhetorical exercises, which are not concerned with persons, times or particular cases.
Other subjects, whether the dispute be real or fictitious, are generally treated on the following lines.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    The fault must lie either in the words or the
matter. As regards the words, the question will
be whether they are sufficiently clear or contain
some ambiguity, and as regards the matter whether
the law is consistent with itself or should be retrospective or apply to special individuals. The point
however which is most commonly raised is the
question whether the law is right or expedient.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    I
am well aware that many rhetoricians introduce a
number of sub-divisions in connexion with this latter
enquiry. I however include under the term
                    <hi rend="italic">right</hi>
                    all such qualities as justice, piety and religion.
Justice is however usually discussed under various
aspects. A question may be raised about the acts
with which the law is concerned, as to whether they
                    <pb xml:id="p.245"/>
                    deserve punishment or reward or as to the degree of
punishment or reward that should be assigned, since
excess in either direction is open to criticism.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    Again
expediency is sometimes determined by the nature
of things, sometimes by the circumstances of the time.
Another common subject of controversy is whether
a law can be enforced, while one must not shut one's
eyes to the fact that exception is sometimes taken
to laws in their entirety, but sometimes only in
part, examples of both forms of criticism being
found in famous speeches.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    I am well aware, too,
that there are laws which are not proposed with
a view to perpetuity, but are concerned with temporary honours or commands, such as the
                    <hi rend="italic">lex Manilia</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <hi rend="italic">lex Manilia</hi>
                        proposed to give Pompey the command
against Mithridates.
                    </note>
                    which is the subject of one of Cicero's speeches.
This however is not the place for instructions on
this topic, since they depend on the special circumstances of the matters under discussion, not on their
general characteristics.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    Such were the subjects on which the ancients as
a rule exercised their powers of speaking, though
they called in the assistance of the logicians as well
to teach them the theory of argument. For it is
generally agreed that the declamation of fictitious
themes in imitation of the questions that arise in
the law courts or deliberative assemblies came into
vogue among the Greeks about the time of Demetrius of Phalerum.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    Whether this type of exercise was actually invented by him I have failed to
discover, as I have acknowledged in another work.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Probably the lost treatise on
                        <quote>The causes of the decline of oratory</quote>
                        (
                        <hi rend="italic">De causis corruptae eloquentiae).</hi>
                    </note>
                    But not even those who most strongly assert his
claim to be the inventor, can produce any adequate
authority in support of their opinion. As regards
Latin teachers of rhetoric, of whom Plotius was the
                    <pb xml:id="p.247"/>
                    most famous, Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        iii. 24, 93.
                    </note>
                    informs us that they came into
existence towards the end of the age of Crassus.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I will speak of the theory of declamation a
little later. In the mean time, as we are discussing
the elementary stages of a rhetorical education, I
think I should not fail to point out how greatly the
rhetorician will contribute to his pupils' progress, if
he imitates the teacher of literature whose duty it is
to expound the poets, and gives the pupils whom he
has undertaken to train, instruction in the reading
of history and still more of the orators. I myself
have adopted this practice for the benefit of a few
pupils of suitable age whose parents thought it
would be useful.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But though my intentions were
excellent, I found that there were two serious obstacles to success: long custom had established a
different method of teaching, and my pupils were
for the most part full-grown youths who did not
require this form of teaching, but were taking my
work as their model.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    However, the fact that I
have been somewhat late in making the discovery is
not a reason why I should be ashamed to recommend
it to those who come after me. I now know that this
form of teaching is practised by the Greeks, but is
generally entrusted to assistants, as the professors
themselves consider that they have no time to give
individual instruction to each pupil as he reads.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And I admit that the form of lecture which this
requires, designed as it is to make boys follow the
written word with ease and accuracy, and even that
which aims at teaching the meaning of any rare
words that may occur, are to be regarded as quite
below the dignity of the teacher of rhetoric.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On
the other hand it is emphatically part of his
                    <pb xml:id="p.249"/>
                    prosession and the undertaking which he makes in
offering himself as a teacher of eloquence, to point
out the merits of authors or, for that matter, any
faults that may occur: and this is all the more the
case, as I am not asking teachers to undertake the
task of recalling their pupils to standat their knee once
more and of assisting them in the reading of whatever book they may select.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    It seems to me at once
an easier and more profitable method to call for
silence and choose some one pupil—and it will be
best to select them by turns—to read aloud, in
order that they may at the same time learn the
correct method of elocution.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The case with which
the speech selected for reading is concerned should
then be explained, for if this be done they will
have a clearer understanding of what is to be read.
When the reading is commenced, no important
point should be allowed to pass unnoticed either
as regards the resourcefulness or the style shown
in the treatment of the subject: the teacher must
point out how the orator seeks to win the favour
of the judge in his
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium,</hi>
                    what clearness, brevity
and sincerity, and at times what shrewd design and
well-concealed artifice is shown in the statement of
facts.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For the only true art in pleading is that
which can only be understood by one who is a
master of the art himself. The teacher will proceed
further to demonstrate what skill is shown in the division into heads, how subtle and frequent are the thrusts
of argument, what vigour marks the stirring and
what charm the soothing passage, how fierce is the
invective and how full of wit the jests, and in
conclusion how the orator establishes his sway
over the emotions of his audience, forces his way
                    <pb xml:id="p.251"/>
                    into their very hearts and brings the feelings of the
jury into perfect sympathy with all his words.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Finally as regards the style, he will emphasise the
appropriateness, elegance or sublimity of particular
words, will indicate where the amplification of the
theme is deserving of praise and where there is
virtue in a diminuendo; and will call attention to
brilliant metaphors, figures of speech and passages
combining smoothness and polish with a general
impression of manly vigour.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It will even at times be of value to read speeches
which are corrupt and faulty in style, but still meet
with general admiration thanks to the perversity of
modern tastes, and to point out how many expressions in them are inappropriate, obscure, high-flown,
grovelling, mean, extravagant or effeminate, although
they are not merely praised by the majority of critics,
but, worse still, praised just because they are bad.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    For
we have come to regard direct and natural speech
as incompatible with genius, while all that is in any
way abnormal is admired as exquisite. Similarly we
see that some people place a higher value on figures
which are in any way monstrous or distorted than
they do on those who have not lost any of the advantages of the normal form of man.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    There are
even some who are captivated by the shams of artifice
and think that there is more beauty in those who
pluck out superfluous hair or use depilatories, who
dress their locks by scorching them with the curling
iron and glow with a complexion that is not their
own, than can ever be conferred by nature pure and
simple, so that it really seems as if physical beauty
depended entirely on moral hideousness.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    It will, however, be the duty of the rhetorician
                    <pb xml:id="p.253"/>
                    not merely to teach these things, but to ask frequent
questions as well, and test the critical powers of his
class. This will prevent his audience from becoming
inattentive and will secure that his words do not fall
on deaf ears. At the same time the class will be led
to find out things for themselves and to use their
intelligence, which is after all the chief aim of this
method of training. For what else is our object in
teaching, save that our pupils should not always
require to be taught?
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    I will venture to say that
this particular form of exercise, if diligently pursued,
will teach learners more than all the text-books of
all the rhetoricians: these are no doubt of very
considerable use, but being somewhat general in
their scope, it is quite impossible for them to deal
with all the special cases that are of almost daily
occurrence.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The art of war will provide a parallel:
it is no doubt based on certain general principles,
but it will none the less be far more useful to know
the methods employed, whether wisely or the reverse, by individual generals under varying circumstances and conditions of time and place. For there
are no subjects in which, as a rule, practice is not
more valuable than precept.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Is a teacher to declaim
to provide a model for his audience, and will not
more profit be derived from the reading of Cicero or
Demosthenes? Is a pupil to be publicly corrected
if he makes a mistake in declaiming, and will it not
be more useful, and more agreeable too, to correct
some actual speech? For everyone has a preference
for hearing the faults of others censured rather than
his own. I might say more on the subject.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    But
every one can see the advantages of this method.
Would that the reluctance to put it into practice
                    <pb xml:id="p.255"/>
                    were not as great as the pleasure that would undoubtedly be derived from so doing!
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    This method once adopted, we are faced by the
comparatively easy question as to what authors
should be selected for our reading. Some have recommended authors of inferior merit on the ground
that they were easier to understand. Others on the
contrary would select the more florid school of writers
on the ground that they are likely to provide the
nourishment best suited to the minds of the young.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    For my part I would have them read the best authors
from the very beginning and never leave them,
choosing those, however, who are simplest and most
intelligible. For instance, when prescribing for boys,
I should give Livy the preference over Sallust;
for, although the latter is the greater historian,
one requires to be well-advanced in one's studies
to appreciate him properly.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero, in my opinion,
provides pleasant reading for beginners and is sufficiently easy to understand: it is possible not only
to learn much from him, but to come to love him.
After Cicero I should, following the advice of Livy,
place such authors as most nearly resemble him.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    There are two faults of taste against which boys
should be guarded with the utmost care. Firstly
no teacher suffering from an excessive admiration
of antiquity, should be allowed to cramp their
minds by the study of Cato and the Gracchi and
other similar authors. For such reading will give
them a harsh and bloodless style, since they will as
yet be unable to understand the force and vigour of
these authors, and contenting themselves with a
style which doubtless was admirable in its day, but
is quite unsuitable to ours, will come to think (and
                    <pb xml:id="p.257"/>
                    nothing could be more fatal) that they really resemble great men.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Secondly the opposite extreme must
be equally avoided: they must not be permitted to
fall victims to the pernicious allurements of the
precious blooms produced by our modern euphuists,
thus acquiring a passion for the luscious sweetness
of such authors, whose charm is all the more attractive to boyish intellects because it is so easy of
achievement.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Once, however, the judgment is
formed and out of danger of perversion, I should
strongly recommend the reading of ancient authors,
since if, after clearing away all the uncouthness of
those rude ages, we succeed in absorbing the robust
vigour and virility of their native genius, our more
finished style will shine with an added grace:
I also approve the study of the moderns at
this stage, since even they have many merits.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    For nature has not doomed us to be dullards,
but we have altered our style of oratory and indulged our caprices over much. It is in their ideals
rather than their talents that the ancients show
themselves our superiors. It will therefore be
possible to select much that is valuable from modern
writers, but we must take care that the precious
metal is not debased by the dross with which it is
so closely intermingled.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Further I would not
merely gladly admit, but would even contend that
we have recently had and still have certain authors
who deserve imitation in their entirety.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    But it is
not for everyone to decide who these writers are.
Error in the choice of earlier authors is attended
with less danger, and I have therefore postponed
the study of the moderns, for fear that we should
imitate them before we are qualified to judge of
their merits.
                    <pb xml:id="p.259"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I come now to another point in which the
practice of teachers has differed. Some have not been
content with giving directions as to the arrangement of the subjects set them as themes for
declamation, but have developed them at some
length themselves, supplying not merely the proofs,
but the lines upon which the emotional passages
should proceed.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Others have merely suggested a
bare outline, and then when the declamations were
over, have indicated the points missed by each
speaker and worked up certain passages with no less
care than they would have used, had they been going
to stand up to speak themselves. Both practices
have their advantages, and therefore I will not give
either the pre-eminence. But if we must choose one
of the two, it will be found more profitable to point
out the right road at the outset, and not merely to
recall the pupil from his error when he has already
gone astray,
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    since in the first place the correction
is only received by the ear, whereas when he is
given a sketch of the various heads of the declamation, he has to take them down and think about
them: secondly instruction is always more readily
received than reproof. Indeed those of our pupils
who have a lively disposition are liable in the
present condition of manners to lose their temper
when admonished and to offer silent resistance.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    That, however, is no reason for refraining from
the public correction of faults; for we must take
the rest of the class into account, who will believe
that whatever has not been corrected by the master
is right. The two methods should be employed
conjointly and in such a way as circumstances may
demand.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Beginners must be given a subject
                    <pb xml:id="p.261"/>
                    sketched out ready for treatment and suitable to
their respective powers. But when they show that
they have formed themselves sufficiently closely on
the models placed before them, it will be sufficient
to give them a few brief hints for their guidance
and to allow them to advance trusting in their own
strength and without external support.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes
they should be left entirely to their own devices,
that they may not be spoilt by the bad habit of
always relying on another's efforts, and so prove incapable of effort and originality. But as soon as
they seem to have acquired a sound conception of
what they ought to say, the teacher's work will be
near completion: if they still make some mistakes,
they must be brought back under his guidance.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    We
may draw a lesson from the birds of the air, whom
we see distributing the food which they have collected in their bills among their weak and helpless
nestlings; but as soon as they are fledged, we see
them teaching their young to leave the nest and fly
round about it, themselves leading the way; finally,
when they have proved their strength, they are given
the freedom of the open sky and left to trust in
themselves.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    There is one practice at present in vogue
for boys of the age under discussion, which ought
in my opinion undoubtedly to be changed. They
should not be forced to commit all their own compositions to memory and to deliver them on an
appointed day, as is at present the custom. This
practice is especially popular with the boys' fathers,
who think that their sons are not really studying
unless they declaim on every possible occasion,
although as a matter of fact progress depends
                    <pb xml:id="p.263"/>
                    mainly on industry.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For though I strongly approve of boys writing compositions and would have
them spend as much time as possible over such
tasks, I had much rather that for the purpose of
learning by heart passages should be selected from
the orators or historians or any other works that
may be deserving of such attention.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For it is a
better exercise for the memory to learn the words
of others than it is to learn one's own, and those
who have practised this far harder task will find
no difficulty in committing to memory their own
compositions with which they are already familiar.
Further they will form an intimate acquaintance
with the best writings, will carry their models
with them and unconsciously reproduce the style
of the speech which has been impressed upon the
memory.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    They will have a plentiful and choice
vocabulary and a command of artistic structure and
a supply of figures which will not have to be
hunted for, but will offer themselves spontaneously from the treasure-house, if I may so call it,
in which they are stored. In addition they will
be in the agreeable position of being able to
quote the happy sayings of the various authors, a
power which they will find most useful in the
courts. For phrases which have not been coined
merely to suit the circumstances of the lawsuit of
the moment carry greater weight and often win
greater praise than if they were our own.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    I
would however allow boys occasionally to declaim
their own compositions that they may reap the reward of their labours in the applause of a large
audience, that most coveted of all prizes. But this
should not be permitted until they have produced
                    <pb xml:id="p.265"/>
                    something more finished than usual: they will thus
be rewarded for their industry and rejoice in the
thought that the privilege accorded them is the
recompense of merit.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    It is generally and not unreasonably regarded
as the sign of a good teacher that he should be able
to differentiate between the abilities of his respective
pupils and to know their natural bent. The gifts of
nature are infinite in their variety, and mind differs
from mind almost as much as body from body.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This
is clear from a consideration of the orators themselves, who differ in style to such an extent that no
one is like another, in spite of the fact that numbers
have modelled their style on that of their favorite
authors.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Many again think it useful to direct their
instruction to the fostering of natural advantages and
to guide the talents of their pupils along the lines
which they instinctively tend to follow. Just as an
expert gymnast, when he enters a gymnasium full of
boys, after testing body and mind in every way, is
able to decide for what class of athletic contest they
should be trained, even so, they say,
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    a teacher of
oratory after careful observation of a boy's stylistic
preferences, be they for terseness and polish, energy,
dignity, charm, roughness, brilliance or wit, will so
adapt his instructions to individual needs that each
pupil will be pushed forward in the sphere for which
his talents seem specially to design him;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    for nature,
when cultivated, goes from strength to strength,
while he who runs counter to her bent is ineffective
in those branches of the art for which he is less
suited and weakens the talents which he seemed
born to employ.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Now, since the critic who is
guided by his reason is free to dissent even from
                    <pb xml:id="p.267"/>
                    received opinions, I must insist that to my thinking this view is only partially true. It is undoubtedly necessary to note the individual gifts of
each boy,
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    and no one would ever convince me
that it is not desirable to differentiate courses of
study with this in view. One boy will be better
adapted for the study of history, another for poetry,
another for law, while some perhaps had better be
packed off to the country. The teacher of rhetoric
will distinguish such special aptitudes, just as our
gymnast will turn one pupil into a runner, another
into a boxer or wrestler or an expert at some other
of the athletic accomplishments for which prizes are
awarded at the sacred games.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But on the other
hand, he who is destined for the bar must study not
one department merely, but must perfect himself in
all the accomplishments which his profession demands, even though some of them may seem too hard
for him when he approaches them as a learner. For if
natural talent alone were sufficient, education might
be dispensed with.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Suppose we are given a pupil
who, like so many, is of depraved tastes and swollen
with his own conceit; shall we suffer him to go his
own sweet way? If a boy's disposition is naturally
dry and jejune, ought we not to feed it up or at any
rate clothe it in fairer apparel? For, if in some cases
it is necessary to remove certain qualities, surely
there are others where we may be permitted to add
what is lacking.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Not that I would set myself against
the will of nature. No innate good quality should be
neglected, but defects must be made good and weaknesses made strong.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    When Isocrates, the prince of
instructors, whose works proclaim his eloquence no
less than his pupils testify to his excellence as a
                    <pb xml:id="p.269"/>
                    teacher, gave his opinion of Ephorus and Theopompus
to the effect that the former needed the spur and the
latter the curb, what was his meaning? Surely not
that the sluggish temperament of the one and the
headlong ardour of the other alike required modification by instruction, but rather that each would gain
from an admixture of the qualities of the other.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In the case of weaker understandings however some
concession must be made and they should be directed
merely to follow the call of their nature, since thus
they will be more effective in doing the only thing
that lies in their power. But if we are fortunate
enough to meet with richer material, such as justifies
us in the hope of producing a real orator, we must
leave no oratorical virtue uncared for.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For though he
will necessarily have a natural bent for some special
department of oratory, he will not feel repelled by
the others, and by sheer application will develop his
other qualities until they equal those in which he
naturally excels. The skilled gymnast will once again
provide us with a parallel: if he undertakes to train
a pancratiast,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <hi rend="italic">pancration</hi>
                        was a mixture of wrestling and boxing.
                    </note>
                    he will not merely teach him how
to use his fists or his heels, nor will he restrict
his instructions to the holds in wrestling, giving
special attention to certain tricks of this kind,
but will train him in every department of the
science. Some will no doubt be incapable of attaining proficiency in certain exercises; these must
specialise on those which lie within their powers.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    For there are two things which he must be most
careful to avoid: first, he must not attempt the impossible, secondly he must not switch off his pupil
from what he can do well to exercises for which he is
less well suited. But if his pupil is like the famous
                    <pb xml:id="p.271"/>
                    Nicostratus, whom we saw when he was old and we
were boys, he will train him equally in every department of the science and will make him a champion
both in boxing and wrestling, like Nicostratus himself
who won the prize for both contests within a few days
of each other.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    And how much more important is the
employment of such methods where our future orator
is concerned! It is not enough to be able to speak
with terseness, subtlety or vehemence, any more than
it would be for a singing master to excel in the upper,
middle or lower register only, or in particular sections
of these registers alone. Eloquence is like a harp
and will never reach perfection, unless all its strings
be taut and in tune.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Though I have spoken in some detail of the
duties of the teacher, I shall for the moment confine
my advice to the learners to one solitary admonition,
that they should love their masters not less than
their studies, and should regard them as the parents
not indeed of their bodies but of their minds.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Such
attachments are of invaluable assistance to study.
For under their influence they find it a pleasure to
listen to their teachers, believe what they say and
long to be like them, come cheerfully and gladly to
school, are not angry when corrected, rejoice when
praised, and seek to win their master's affection by
the devotion with which they pursue their studies.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For as it is the duty of the master to teach, so it is
the duty of the pupil to show himself teachable. The
two obligations are mutually indispensable. And just
as it takes two parents to produce a human being,
and as the seed is scattered in vain, if the ground is
hard and there is no furrow to receive it and bring it
to growth, even so eloquence can never come to
                    <pb xml:id="p.273"/>
                    maturity, unless teacher and taught are in perfect
sympathy.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    These elementary stages are in themselves
no small undertaking, but they are merely members
and portions of the greater whole; when therefore
the pupil has been thoroughly instructed and exercised in these departments, the time will as a rule
have come for him to attempt deliberative and
forensic themes. But before I begin to discuss
these, I must say a few words on the theory of
declamation, which is at once the most recent and
most useful of rhetorical exercises.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For it includes
practically all the exercises of which we have been
speaking and is in close touch with reality. As a
result it has acquired such a vogue that many think
that it is the sole training necessary to the formation
of an orator, since there is no excellence in a formal
speech which is not also to be found in this type of
rhetorical exercise.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand the actual
practice of declamation has degenerated to such an
extent owing to the fault of our teachers, that it has
come to be one of the chief causes of the corruption
of modern oratory; such is the extravagance and
ignorance of our declaimers. But it is possible to
make a sound use of anything that is naturally sound.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The subjects chosen for themes should, therefore, be
as true to life as possible, and the actual declamation
should, as far as may be, be modelled on the pleadings for which it was devised as a training.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For we
shall hunt in vain among
                    <hi rend="italic">sponsions</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">sponsio (=</hi>
                        a wager) was a form of lawsuit in which the
litigant promised to pay a certain sum of money if he lost
his case. The
                        <hi rend="italic">interdict</hi>
                        was an order issued by the praetor
commanding or prohibiting certain action. It occurred
chiefly in disputes about property.
                    </note>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">interdicts</hi>
                    for magicians and plagues and oracles and stepmothers more cruel than any in tragedy, and other
                    <pb xml:id="p.275"/>
                    subjects still more unreal than these.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The themes of the
                        <hi rend="italic">controversiae</hi>
                        often turned on the
supernatural and on crimes and incidents such as rarely or
never occur in actual life.
                    </note>
                    What then?
are we never to permit young men to handle unreal
or, to be more accurate, poetic themes that they may
run riot and exult in their strength and display their
full stature?
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    It were best to prohibit them absolutely.
But at any rate the themes, however swelling and
magnificent, should not be such as to seem foolish
and laughable to the eye of an intelligent observer.
Consequently, if we must make some concession, let
us allow the declaimer to gorge himself occasionally, as long as he realises that his case will be like
that of cattle that have blown themselves out with a
surfeit of green food: they are cured of their disorder
by blood-letting and then put back to food such as
will maintain their strength; similarly the declaimer
must be rid of his superfluous fat, and his corrupt
humours must be discharged, if he wants to be
strong and healthy.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Otherwise, the first time he
makes any serious effort, his swollen emptiness will
stand revealed. Those, however, who hold that
declamation has absolutely nothing in common with
pleading in the courts, are clearly quite unaware of
the reasons which gave rise to this type of exercise.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For if declamation is not a preparation for the actual
work of the courts, it can only be compared to the
rant of an actor or the raving of a lunatic. For what
is the use of attempting to conciliate a non-existent
judge, or of stating a case which all know to be
false, or of trying to prove a point on which judgment will never be passed? Such waste of effort
is, however, a comparative trifle. But what can be
more ludicrous than to work oneself into a passion
and to attempt to excite the anger or grief of
our hearers, unless we are preparing ourselves by
                    <pb xml:id="p.277"/>
                    such mimic combats for the actual strife and the
pitched battles of the law-courts?
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Is there then no
difference between our declamations and genuine
forensic oratory? I can only reply, that if we speak
with a desire for improvement, there will be no
difference. [ wish indeed that certain additions
could be made to the existing practice; that we made
use of names, that our fictitious debates dealt with
more complicated cases and sometimes took longer
to deliver, that we were less afraid of words drawn
from everyday speech and that we were in the habit
of seasoning our words with jests. For as regards
all these points, we are mere novices when we come
to actual pleading, however elaborate the training
that the schools have given us on other points.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And
even if display is the object of declamation, surely
we ought to unbend a little for the entertainment of
our audience.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    For even in those speeches which,
although undoubtedly to some extent concerned
with the truth, are designed to charm the multitude (such for instance as panegyrics and the oratory
of display in all its branches), it is permissible to
be more ornate and not merely to disclose all the
resources of our art, which in cases of law should as
a rule be concealed, but actually to flaunt them
before those who have been summoned to hear us.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Declamation therefore should resemble the truth,
since it is modelled on forensic and deliberative
oratory. On the other hand it also involves an
element of display, and should in consequence
assume a certain air of elegance.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    In this connexion
I may cite the practice of comic actors, whose delivery is not exactly that of common speech, since
that would be inartistic, but is on the other hand not
                    <pb xml:id="p.279"/>
                    far removed from the accents of nature, for, if it were,
their mimicry would be a failure: what they do therefore is to exalt the simplicity of ordinary speech
by a touch of stage decoration.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    So too we shall
have to put up with certain inconveniences arising
from the nature of our fictitious themes; such drawbacks occur more especially in connexion with those
numerous details which are left uncertain and which
we presume to suit our purpose, such as the ages of
our characters, their wealth, their families, or the
strength, laws and manners of the cities where our
scenes are laid, and the like.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes we even
draw arguments from the actual flaws of the assumptions involved by the theme. But each of these
points shall be dealt with in its proper place. For
although the whole purpose of this work is the
formation of an orator, I have no intention of passing
over anything that has a genuine connexion with the
practice of the schools, for fear that students may
complain of the omission.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I have now arrived at the point when I must
begin to deal with that portion of the art at which
those who have omitted the preceding stages generally commence. I can see, however, that certain
critics will attempt to obstruct my path at the very
outset: for they will urge that eloquence can dispense with rules of this kind and, in smug satisfaction with themselves and the ordinary methods
and exercises of the schools, will laugh at me for
my pains; in which they will be only following the
example of certain professors of no small reputation.
One of these gentlemen, I believe, when asked to
define a
                    <hi rend="italic">figure</hi>
                    and a
                    <hi rend="italic">thought,</hi>
                    replied that he did not
know what they were, but that, if they had anything
                    <pb xml:id="p.281"/>
                    to do with the subject, they would be found in
his declamation.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Another when asked whether he
was a follower of Theodorus or Apollodorus, replied,
                    <quote>Oh! as for me, I am all for the Thracians.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        I care naught for your rival schools of rhetoric. I
give all my favour to the men armed with the buckler (the
gladiators known as
                        <hi rend="italic">Thraces).</hi>
                        Such contests of the amphitheatre interest me far more than the contests between rival
schools of rhetoric.
                    </note>
                    To do him justice, he could hardly have found a
neater way to avoid confessing his ignorance. These
persons, just because, thanks to their natural gifts,
they are regarded as brilliant performers and have,
as a matter of fact, uttered much that deserves to
be remembered, think that, while most men share
their careless habits, few come near them for talent.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently they make it their boast that they
speak on impulse and owe their success to their
native powers; they further assert that there is no
need of proof or careful marshalling of facts when
we are speaking on fictitious themes, but only of
some of those sounding epigrams, the expectation of
which has filled the lecture-room; and these they
say are best improvised on the spur of the moment.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Further, owing to their contempt for method, when
they are meditating on some future effusion, they
spend whole days looking at the ceiling in the hope
that some magnificent inspiration may occur to
them, or rock their bodies to and fro, booming
inarticulately as if they had a trumpet inside them
and adapting their agitated movements, not to the
delivery of the words, but to their pursuit.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Some
again settle on certain definite openings long before they have thought what they are going to say,
with a view to using them as pegs for subsequent
snatches of eloquence, and then after practising
their delivery first in silent thought and then
aloud for hours together, in utter desperation of
providing any connecting links, abandon them and
                    <pb xml:id="p.283"/>
                    take refuge in one formula after another, each no
less hackneyed and familiar than the last.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The
least unreasonable of them devote their attention not to the actual cases, but to their purple
patches, in the composition of which they pay no
attention to the subject-matter, but fire off a series
of isolated thoughts just as they happen to come to
hand.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The result is a speech which, being composed of disconnected passages having nothing in
common with each other, must necessarily lack
cohesion and can only be compared to a schoolboy's
notebook, in which he jots down any passages from
the declamations of others that have come in for a
word of praise. None the less they do occasionally
strike out some good things and some fine epigrams,
such as they make their boast. Why not? slaves
and barbarians sometimes achieve the same effects,
and if we are to be satisfied with this sort of thing,
then good-bye to any theory of oratory.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I must, however, admit that the general
opinion is that the untrained speaker is usually
the more vigorous. This opinion is due primarily
to the erroneous judgment of faulty critics, who
think that true vigour is all the greater for its lack
of art, regarding it as a special proof of strength to
force what might be opened, to break what might
be untied and to drag what might be led.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Even a
gladiator who plunges into the fight with no skill at
arms to help him, and a wrestler who puts forth the
whole strength of his body the moment he has got
a hold, is acclaimed by them for his outstanding
vigour, although it is of frequent occurrence in such
cases for the latter to be overthrown by his own
strength and for the former to find the fury of his
                    <pb xml:id="p.285"/>
                    onslaught parried by his adversary with a supple
turn of the wrist.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But there are many details in this
department of our art which the unskilled critic will
never notice. For instance, careful division under
heads, although of the utmost importance in actual
cases, makes the outward show of strength seem
less than the reality; the unhewn block is larger
than the polished marble, and things when scattered
seem more numerous than when placed together.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    There is moreover a sort of resemblance between
certain merits and certain defects: abuse passes for
freedom of speech, rashness for courage, prodigality
for abundance. But the untrained advocate will
abuse too openly and too often, even though by so
doing he imperils the success of the case which he
has undertaken and not seldom his own personal
safety as well.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    But even such violence will win
men's good opinion, since they are only too pleased
to hear another say things which nothing would
have induced them to utter themselves. Such
speakers are also less careful to avoid that other
peril, the pitfall of style, and are so reckless in their
efforts that sometimes in their passion for extravagance they light upon some really striking expression. But such success is rare and does not
compensate for their other defects.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    For the same reason the uninstructed sometimes
appear to have a richer flow of language, because
they say everything that can be said, while the
learned exercise discrimination and self-restraint.
To this must be added the fact that such persons
take no trouble to prove their contentions, and
consequently steer clear of the chilly reception
given in our decadent law-courts to arguments and
                    <pb xml:id="p.287"/>
                    questions and seek only for such themes as may
beguile the ears of the public even at the cost of
appealing to the most perverted tastes.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Again,
their epigrams, the sole objects of their quest, seem
all the more striking because of the dreariness and
squalor of their context, since flashes are more
clearly seen against a background, not of mere
                    <quote>shade,</quote>
                    as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        III. xxvi. 101.
                    </note>
                    says, but of pitchy darkness.
Well, let the world credit them with as much genius
as it pleases, so long as it is admitted that such
praise is an insult to any man of real eloquence.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    None the less it must be confessed that learning
does take something from oratory, just as the file
takes something from rough surfaces or the whetstone from blunt edges or age from wine; it takes
away defects, and if the results produced after subjection to the polish of literary study are less, they
are less only because they are better.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But these creatures have another weapon in their
armoury: they seek to obtain the reputation of
speaking with greater vigour than the trained orator
by means of their delivery. For they shout on all
and every occasion and bellow their every utterance
                    <quote>with uplifted hand,</quote>
                    to use their own phrase,
dashing this way and that, panting, gesticulating
wildly and wagging their heads with all the frenzy
of a lunatic.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Smite your hands together, stamp
the ground, slap your thigh, your breast, your forehead, and you will go straight to the heart of the
dingier members of your audience.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pullatus</hi>
                        = wearing dark clothes,
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        the common people,
as opposed to the upper classes wearing the white or purple bordered
                        <hi rend="italic">toga.</hi>
                    </note>
                    But the educated speaker, just as he knows how to moderate
his style, and to impart variety and artistic form to
his speech, is an equal adept in the matter of delivery and will suit his action to the tone of each
                    <pb xml:id="p.289"/>
                    portion of his utterances, while, if he has any one
canon for universal observance, it is that he should
both possess the reality and present the appearance
of self-control.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But the ranters confer the title of
force on that which is really violence. You may
also occasionally find not merely pleaders, but, what
is far more shameful, teachers as well, who, after a
brief training in the art of speaking, throw method
to the winds and, yielding to the impulse of the
moment, run riot in every direction, abusing those
who hold literature in higher respect as fools without life, courage or vigour, and calling them the
first and worst name that occurs to them.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Still let
me congratulate these gentlemen on attaining eloquence without industry, method or study. As for
myself I have long since retired from the task of
teaching in the schools and of speaking in the
courts, thinking it the most honourable conclusion to
retire while my services were still in request, and all
I ask is to be allowed to console my leisure by
making such researches and composing such instructions as will, I hope, prove useful to young men of
ability, and are, at any rate, a pleasure to myself.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Let no one however demand from me a rigid
code of rules such as most authors of textbooks have
laid down, or ask me to impose on students of rhetoric a system of laws immutable as fate, a system in
which injunctions as to the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium</hi>
                    and its nature
lead the way; then come the
                    <hi rend="italic">statement of facts</hi>
                    and
the laws to be observed in this connexion: next the
                    <hi rend="italic">proposition</hi>
                    or, as some prefer, the
                    <hi rend="italic">digression,</hi>
                    followed
by prescriptions as to the order in which the various
questions should be discussed, with all the other rules,
which some speakers follow as though they had no
                    <pb xml:id="p.291"/>
                    choice but to regard them as orders and as if it were
a crime to take any other line.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    If the whole of rhetoric could be thus embodied in one compact code,
it would be an easy task of little compass: but
most rules are liable to be altered by the nature of
the case, circumstances of time and place, and by
hard necessity itself. Consequently the all-important
gift for an orator is a wise adaptability since he is
called upon to meet the most varied emergencies.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    What if you should instruct a general, as often as he
marshals his troops for battle, to draw up his front in
line, advance his wings to left and right, and station
his cavalry to protect his flank? This will perhaps be
the best plan, if circumstances allow. But it may
have to be modified owing to the nature of the ground,
if, for instance, he is confronted by a mountain, if a
river bars his advance, or his movements are hampered
by hills, woods or broken country.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Or again it may
be modified by the character of the enemy or the
nature of the crisis by which he is faced. On one
occasion he will fight in line, on another in column,
on one he will use his auxiliary troops, on another his
legionaries; while occasionally a feint of flight may
win the day. So, too, with the rules of oratory.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Is
the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium</hi>
                    necessary or superfluous? should it be
long or short? addressed entirely to the judge or
sometimes directed to some other quarter by the
employment of some figure of speech?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        by the figure known as
                        <hi rend="italic">apostrophe,</hi>
                        in which the
orator diverts his speech from the judge to some other
person: see IX. ii. 38.
                    </note>
                    Should the
statement of facts be concise or developed at some
length? continuous or divided into sections? and
should it follow the actual or an artificial order of
events? The orator will find the answers to all these
questions in the circumstances of the case. So, too,
with the order in which questions should be discussed,
                    <pb xml:id="p.293"/>
                    since in any given debate it may often suit one party
best that such and such a question come up first,
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    while their opponents would be best suited by another.
For these rules have not the formal authority of laws
or decrees of the plebs, but are, with all they contain,
the children of expediency.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    I will not deny that it
is generally expedient to conform to such rules, otherwise I should not be writing now; but if our friend
expediency suggests some other course to us, why,
we shall disregard the authority of the professors
and follow her.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For my part above all things
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">This I enjoin and urge and urge anew</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">Verg. Aen. iii. 436.</bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    that in all his pleadings the orator should keep two
things constantly in view, what is becoming and what
is expedient. But it is often expedient and occasionally becoming to make some modification in the
time-honoured order. We see the same thing in
pictures and statues. Dress, expression and attitude
are frequently varied.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The body when held bolt
upright has but little grace, for the face looks straight
forward, the arms hang by the side, the feet are
joined and the whole figure is stiff from top to toe.
But that curve, I might almost call it motion, with
which we are so familiar, gives an impression of action
and animation. So, too, the hands will not always be
represented in the same position, and the variety
given to the expression will be infinite.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Some figures
are represented as running or rushing forward, others
sit or recline, some are nude, others clothed, while
some again are half-dressed, half-naked. Where can
we find a more violent and elaborate attitude than
that of the Discobolus of Myron? Yet the critic who
                    <pb xml:id="p.295"/>
                    disapproved of the figure because it was not upright,
would merely show his utter failure to understand the
sculptor's art, in which the very novelty and difficulty
of execution is what most deserves our praise.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    A
similar impression of grace and charm is produced by
rhetorical figures, whether they be
                    <hi rend="italic">figures of thought</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">figures of speech.</hi>
                    For they involve a certain departure from the straight line and have the merit of
variation from the ordinary usage.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In a picture the
full face is most attractive. But Apelles painted
Antigonus in profile, to conceal the blemish caused
by the loss of one eye. So, too, in speaking, there
are certain things which have to be concealed, either
because they ought not to be disclosed or because
they cannot be expressed as they deserve.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Timanthes,
who was, I think, a native of Cythnus, provides an
example of this in the picture with which he won the
victory over Colotes of Teos. It represented the
sacrifice of Iphigenia, and the artist had depicted an
expression of grief on the face of Calchas and of still
greater grief on that of Ulysses, while he had given
Menelaus an agony of sorrow beyond which his art
could not go. Having exhausted his powers of emotional expression he was at a loss to portray the
father's face as it deserved, and solved the problem
by veiling his head and leaving his sorrow to the
imagination of the spectator.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Sallust
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jug.</hi>
                        xix.
                    </note>
                    did something similar when he wrote
                    <quote>I think it better to say nothing of Carthage rather than say too little.</quote>
                    It
has always, therefore, been my custom not to tie myself down to
                    <hi rend="italic">universal</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">general</hi>
                    rules (this being the
nearest equivalent I can find for the Greek
                    <hi rend="italic">catholic rules</hi>
                    ). For rules are rarely of such a kind that their
validity cannot be shaken and overthrown in some
                    <pb xml:id="p.297"/>
                    particular or other.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    But I must reserve each of these
points for fuller treatment in its proper place. For
the present I will only say that I do not want young
men to think their education complete when they
have mastered one of the small text-books of which
so many are in circulation, or to ascribe a talismanic
value to the arbitrary decrees of theorists. the art
of speaking can only be attained by hard work and
assiduity of study, by a variety of exercises and repeated trial, the highest prudence and unfailing
quickness of judgement.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    But rules are helpful all the
same so long as they indicate the direct road and do
not restrict us absolutely to the ruts made by others.
For he who thinks it an unpardonable sin to leave the
old, old track, must be content to move at much the
same speed as a tight-rope walker. Thus, for example,
we often leave a paved military road to take a short
cut or, finding that the direct route is impossible
owing to floods having broken down the bridges, are
forced to make a circuit, while if our house is on fire
and flames bar the way to the front door, we make
our escape by breaking through a party wall.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The
orator's task covers a large ground, is extremely
varied and develops some new aspect almost every
day, so that the last word on the subject will never
have been said. I shall however try to set forth the
traditional rules and to point out their best features,
mentioning the changes, additions and subtractions
which seem desirable.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Rhetoric is a Greek term which has been
translated into Latin by
                    <hi rend="italic">oratoria</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">oratrix. I</hi>
                    would
not for the world deprive the translators of the
praise which is their due for attempting to increase
the vocabulary of our native tongue; but translations
                    <pb xml:id="p.299"/>
                    from Greek into Latin are not always satisfactory,
just as the attempt to represent Latin words
in a Greek dress is sometimes equally unsuccessful.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    And the translations in question are fully as
harsh as the
                    <hi rend="italic">essentia</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">queentia</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">sc.</hi>
                        essence and possibility.
                    </note>
                    of Plautus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A Stoic.
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        x. i. 124.
                    </note>
                    and have not even the merit of being exact.
For
                    <hi rend="italic">oratoria</hi>
                    is formed like
                    <hi rend="italic">elocutoria</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">oratrix</hi>
                    like
                    <hi rend="italic">elocutrix,</hi>
                    whereas the rhetoric with which
we are concerned is rather to be identified with
                    <hi rend="italic">eloquentia,</hi>
                    and the word is undoubtedly used in two
senses by the Greeks.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    In the one case it is an
adjective i.e.
                    <hi rend="italic">ars rhetorica,</hi>
                    the rhetorical art, like
piratic in the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">nauis piratica,</hi>
                    in the other it is
a noun like philosophy or friendship. It is as a substantive that we require it here; now the correct
translation of the Greek
                    <hi rend="italic">grammatice</hi>
                    is
                    <hi rend="italic">litteratura</hi>
                    not
                    <hi rend="italic">litteratrix or litteratoria,</hi>
                    which would be the forms
analogous to
                    <hi rend="italic">oratrix</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">oratoria.</hi>
                    But in the case of
                    <quote>rhetoric</quote>
                    there is no similar Latin equivalent.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    It is
best therefore not to quarrel about it, more especially
as we have to use Greek terms in many other cases.
For I may at least use the words
                    <hi rend="italic">philosophus, musicus</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">geometres</hi>
                    without outraging them by changing
them into clumsy Latin equivalents. Finally,
since Cicero gave a Greek title
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 6 of next chapter.</note>
                    to the earlier works
which he wrote on this subject, I may without fear
of rashness accept the great orator as sufficient
authority for the name of the art which he professed.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    To resume, then, rhetoric (for I shall now use the
name without fear of captious criticism) is in my
opinion best treated under the three following heads,
the art, the artist and the work. The art is that
which we should acquire by study, and is the art of
                    <pb xml:id="p.301"/>
                    speaking well. The artist is he who has acquired the
art, that is to say, he is the orator whose task it is
to speak well. The work is the achievement of
the artist, namely good speaking. Each of these
three
                    <hi rend="italic">general</hi>
                    divisions is in its turn divided into
                    <hi rend="italic">species.</hi>
                    Of the two latter divisions I shall speak
in their proper place. For the present I shall proceed to a discussion of the first.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The first question which confronts us is
                    <quote>What is rhetoric?</quote>
                    Many definitions have been
given; but the problem is really twofold. For the
dispute turns either on the quality of the thing
itself or on the meaning of the words in which it
is defined. The first and chief disagreement on the
subject is found in the fact that some think that
even bad men may be called orators, while others,
of whom I am one, restrict the name of orator and
the art itself to those who are good.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Of those who
divorce eloquence from that yet fairer and more desirable title to renown, a virtuous life, some call
rhetoric merely a power, some a science, but not a
virtue, some a practice, some an art, though they will
not allow the art to have anything in common with
science or virtue, while some again call it a perversion of art or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kakotexni/a.</foreign>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    These persons have as a
rule held that the task of oratory lies in persuasion
or speaking in a persuasive manner: for this is
within the power of a bad man no less than a good.
Hence we get the common definition of rhetoric as
the power of persuading. What I call a power,
many call a capacity, and some a faculty. In order
therefore that there may be no misunderstanding I
will say that by power I mean
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">du/namis.</foreign>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This view
is derived from Isocrates, if indeed the treatise on
                    <pb xml:id="p.303"/>
                    rhetoric
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This treatise is lost. It may have been the work of the
younger Isocrates.
                    </note>
                    which circulates under his name is really
from his hand. He, although far from agreeing
with those whose aim is to disparage the duties of
an orator, somewhat rashly defined rhetoric as
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">peiqou=s dhmiourgo/s,</foreign>
                    the
                    <quote>worker of persuasion</quote>
                    : for
I cannot bring myself to use the peculiar derivative
which Ennius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ann.</hi>
                        ix. 309 (Vahlen). The derivative to which he
objects is the rare word
                        <hi rend="italic">suada.</hi>
                    </note>
                    applies to Marcus Cethegus in the
phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">suadae medulla,</hi>
                    the
                    <quote>marrow of persuasion.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Again Gorgias,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorg.</hi>
                        453 A.
                    </note>
                    in the dialogue of Plato that takes
its title from his name, says practically the same
thing, but Plato intends it to be taken as the opinion
of Gorgias, not as his own. Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Inv.</hi>
                        I. v. 6,
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. xxxi. 138
                    </note>
                    in more than
one passage defined the duty of an orator as
                    <quote>speaking in a persuasive manner.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    In his
                    <hi rend="italic">Rhelorica</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        III. i. 20 and Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. ii. 5. The work in question
is better known as the
                        <hi rend="italic">de Inventione.</hi>
                    </note>
                    too,
a work which it is clear gave him no satisfaction, he
makes the end to be persuasion. But many other
things have the power of persuasion, such as money,
influence, the authority and rank of the speaker, or
even some sight unsupported by language, when
for instance the place of words is supplied by the
memory of some individual's great deeds, by his
lamentable appearance or the beauty of his person.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Thus when Antonius in the course of his defence of
Manius Aquilius tore open his client's robe and revealed the honourable scars which he had acquired
while facing his country's foes, he relied no longer
on the power of his eloquence, but appealed directly
to the eyes of the Roman people. And it is believed
that they were so profoundly moved by the sight as
to acquit the accused.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Again there is a speech of
Cato, to mention no other records, which informs us
that Servius Galba escaped condemnation solely by
                    <pb xml:id="p.305"/>
                    the pity which he aroused not only by producing his
own young children before the assembly, but by
carrying round in his arms the son of Sulpicius
Gallus.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    So also according to general opinion Phryne
was saved not by the eloquence of Hyperides, admirable as it was, but by the sight of her exquisite
body, which she further revealed by drawing aside
her tunic. And if all these have power to persuade, the end of oratory, which we are discussing,
cannot adequately be defined as persuasion.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently those who, although holding the same
general view of rhetoric, have regarded it as the
                    <hi rend="italic">power of persuasion by speaking,</hi>
                    pride themselves on
their greater exactness of language. This definition
is given by Gorgias, in the dialogue
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorg.</hi>
                        p. 452 E.
                    </note>
                    mentioned
above, under compulsion from the inexorable logic of
Socrates. Theodectes agrees with him, whether the
treatise on rhetoric which has come down to us
under his name is really by him or, as is generally
believed, by Aristotle. In that work the end of
rhetoric is defined as the
                    <hi rend="italic">leading of men by the power of speech to the conclusion desired by the orator.</hi>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But even this definition is not sufficiently comprehensive, since others besides orators persuade by
speaking or lead others to the conclusion desired, as
for example harlots, flatterers and seducers. On
the other hand the orator is not always engaged on
persuasion, so that sometimes persuasion is not his
special object, while sometimes it is shared by
others who are far removed from being orators.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    And
yet Apollodorus is not very far off this definition
when he asserts that the first and all-important task
of forensic oratory is
                    <hi rend="italic">to persuade the judge and lead his mind to the conclusions desired by the speaker.</hi>
                    For
                    <pb xml:id="p.307"/>
                    even Apollodorus makes the orator the sport of fortune by refusing him leave to retain his title if he
fails to persuade.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Some on the other hand pay no
attention to results, as for example Aristotle,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rhet.</hi>
                        i. 2.
                    </note>
                    who
says
                    <quote>
                        <hi rend="italic">rhetoric is the power of discovering all means of persuading by speech.</hi>
                    </quote>
                    This definition has not merely
the fault already mentioned, but the additional defect of including merely the power of invention,
which without style cannot possibly constitute
oratory.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Hermagoras, who asserts that its end is to
                    <hi rend="italic">speak persuasively,</hi>
                    and others who express the same
opinion, though in different words, and inform us
that the end is to
                    <hi rend="italic">say everything which ought to be said with a view to persuasion,</hi>
                    have been sufficiently
answered above, when I proved that persuasion was
not the privilege of the orator alone.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Various additions
have been made to these definitions. For some hold
that rhetoric is concerned with everything, while
some restrict its activity to politics. The question
as to which of these views is the nearer to the truth
shall be discussed later in its appropriate place.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Aristotle seems to have implied that the sphere of the
orator was all-inclusive when he defined rhetoric as
the
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        power to detect every element in any given subject
which might conduce to persuasion;
                    </hi>
                    so too does Patrocles who omits the words
                    <hi rend="italic">in any given subject,</hi>
                    but
since he excludes nothing, shows that his view is
identical. For he defines rhetoric as the
                    <hi rend="italic">power to discover whatever is persuasive in speech.</hi>
                    These definitions like that quoted above include no more than
the power of
                    <hi rend="italic">invention</hi>
                    alone. Theodorus avoids this
fault and holds that it is the
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        power to discover and to
utter forth in elegant language whatever is credible in
every subject of oratory.
                    </hi>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    But, while others besides
                    <pb xml:id="p.309"/>
                    orators may discover what is credible as well as persuasive, by adding the words
                    <hi rend="italic">in every subject</hi>
                    he, to a
greater extent than the others, concedes the fairest
name in all the world to those who use their gifts as
an incitement to crime
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    . Plato makes Gorgias
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorg.</hi>
                        454 B.
                    </note>
                    say
that he is a master of persuasion in the law-courts
and other assemblies, and that his themes are justice
and injustice, while in reply Socrates allows him the
power of persuading, but not of teaching.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Those
who refused to make the sphere of oratory allinclusive, have been obliged to make somewhat forced
and long-winded distinctions: among these I may
mention Ariston, the pupil of the Peripatetic Critolaus, who produced the following definition,
                    <quote>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            Rhetoric
is the science of seeing and uttering what ought to be
said on political questions in language that is likely to
prove persuasive to the people.
                        </hi>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Being a Peripatetic he
regards it as a science, not, like the Stoics, as a
virtue, while in adding the words
                    <quote>
                        <hi rend="italic">likely to prove persuasie to the people</hi>
                    </quote>
                    he inflicts a positive insult on
oratory, in implying that it is not likely to persuade the
learned. The same criticism will apply to all those who
restrict oratory to political questions, for they exclude thereby a large number of the duties of an
orator, as for example panegyric, the third department of oratory, which is entirely ignored.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Turning
to those who regard rhetoric as an art, but not as a
virtue, we find that Theodorus of Gadara is more
cautious. For he says (I quote the words of his
translators),
                    <quote>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            rhetoric is the art which discovers and
judges and expresses, mith an elegance duly proportioned
to the importance of all such elements of persuasion as
may exist in any subject in the field of politics.
                        </hi>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Similarly Cornelius Celsus defines the end of rhetoric as
                    <pb xml:id="p.311"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">to speak persuasively on any doubtful subject within the field of politics.</hi>
                    Similar definitions are given by
others, such for instance as the following:—
                    <quote>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            rhetoric
is the power of judging and holding forth on such political subjects as come before it with a certain persuasiveness, a certain action of the body and delivery of the
words.
                        </hi>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    There are countless other definitions,
either identical with this or composed of the same
elements, which I shall deal with when I come to
the questions concerned with the subject matter of
rhetoric. Some regard it as neither a power, a
science or an art; Critolaus calls it the
                    <hi rend="italic">practice of speaking</hi>
                    (for this is the meaning of
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">tribh/</foreign>
                    ),
Athenaeus styles it the
                    <hi rend="italic">art of deceiving,</hi>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    while the
majority, content with reading a few passages from
the Gorgias of Plato, unskilfully excerpted by
earlier writers, refrain from studying that dialogue
and the remainder of Plato's writings, and thereby
fall into serious error. For they believe that in
Plato's view rhetoric was not an art, but a certain
                    <hi rend="italic">adroitness in the production of delight and gratification,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorg.</hi>
                        462 c.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    or with reference to another passage the
                    <hi rend="italic">shadow of a small part of politics</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">ib.</hi>
                        463
                        <hi rend="italic">p.</hi>
                    </note>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italic">fourth department of flattery.</hi>
                    For Plato assigns
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">ib.</hi>
                        464 B.
                    </note>
                    two departments of politics to the body, namely medicine and
gymnastic, and two to the soul, namely law and
justice, while he styles the art of cookery
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">ib.</hi>
                        464 B-465 E.
                    </note>
                    a form of
flattery of medicine, the art of the slave-dealer a
flattery of gymnastic, for they produce a false complexion by the use of paint and a false robustness
by puffing them out with fat: sophistry he calls a
dishonest counterfeit of legal science, and rhetoric of
justice.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    All these statements occur in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Gorgias</hi>
                    and
are uttered by Socrates who appears to be the
                    <pb xml:id="p.313"/>
                    mouthpiece of the views held by Plato. But some of his
dialogues were composed merely to refute his
opponents and are styled
                    <hi rend="italic">refutative,</hi>
                    while others are
for the purpose of teaching and are called
                    <hi rend="italic">doctrinal.</hi>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Now it is only rhetoric as practised in their own day
that is condemned by Plato or Socrates, for he
speaks of it as
                    <quote>the manner in which you engage in public affairs</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">500 c.</note>
                    : rhetoric in itself he regards as a
genuine and honourable thing, and consequently the
controversy with Gorgias ends with the words,
                    <quote>The rhetorician therefore must be just and the just man desirous to do what is just.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">460 c.</note>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    To this Gorgias
makes no reply, but the argument is taken up by
Polus, a hot-headed and headstrong young fellow,
and it is to him that Socrates makes his remarks
about
                    <quote>shadows</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>forms of flattery.</quote>
                    Then
Callicles,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">508 c.</note>
                    who is even more hot-headed, intervenes,
but is reduced to the conclusion that
                    <quote>he who would truly be a rhetorician ought to be just and possess a knowledge of justice.</quote>
                    It is clear therefore that
Plato does not regard rhetoric as an evil, but holds
that true rhetoric is impossible for any save a just
and good man. In the
                    <hi rend="italic">Phaedrus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">261 A-273 E.</note>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    he makes it even
clearer that the complete attainment of this art is
impossible without the knowledge of justice, an
opinion in which I heartily concur. Had this not
been his view, would he have ever written the
Apology of Socrates or the Funeral Oration
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Menexenus.</hi>
                    </note>
                    in
praise of those who had died in battle for their
country, both of them works falling within the
sphere of oratory.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    It was against the class of men
who employed their glibness of speech for evil purposes that he directed his denunciations. Similarly
Socrates thought it incompatible with his honour to
                    <pb xml:id="p.315"/>
                    make use of the speech which Lysias composed for
his defence, although it was the usual practice in
those days to write speeches for the parties concerned to speak in the courts on their own behalf,
a device designed to circumvent the law which forbade the employment of advocates.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Further the
teachers of rhetoric were regarded by Plato as quite
unsuited to their professed task. For they divorced
rhetoric from justice and preferred plausibility to
truth, as he states in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Phaedrus.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">267 A, with special reference to Tisias and Gorgias.</note>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Cornelius Celsus
seems to have agreed with these early rhetoricians,
for he writes
                    <quote>The orator only aims at the semblance of truth,</quote>
                    and again a little later
                    <quote>The reward of the party to a suit is not a good conscience, but victory.</quote>
                    If this were true, only the worst of men
would place such dangerous weapons at the disposal
of criminals or employ the precepts of their art for
the assistance of wickedness. However I will leave
those who maintain these views to consider what
ground they have for so doing.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    For my part, I have undertaken the task of moulding the ideal orator, and as my first desire is that he
should be a good man, I will return to those who
have sounder opinions on the subject. Some however identify rhetoric with politics, Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Inv.</hi>
                        I. v. 6.
                    </note>
                    calls it a
                    <hi rend="italic">department of the science of politics</hi>
                    (and science of
politics and philosophy are identical terms), while
others again call it a
                    <hi rend="italic">branch of philosophy,</hi>
                    among
them Isocrates.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    The definition which best suits its
real character is that which makes rhetoric the
                    <hi rend="italic">science of speaking well.</hi>
                    For this definition includes all the
virtues of oratory and the character of the orator as
well, since no man can speak well who is not good
himself.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    The definition given by Chrysippus, who
                    <pb xml:id="p.317"/>
                    derived it from Cleanthes, to the effect that it is the
                    <hi rend="italic">science of speaking rightly,</hi>
                    amounts to the same thing.
The same philosopher also gives other definitions,
but they concern problems of a different character
from that on which we are now engaged. Another
definition defines oratory as the power of
                    <hi rend="italic">persuading men to do what ought to be done,</hi>
                    and yields practically
the same sense save that it limits the art to the result
which it produces.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    Areus again defines it well as
                    <hi rend="italic">speaking according to the excellence of speech.</hi>
                    Those who
regard it as the science of political obligations, also
exclude men of bad character from the title of orator,
if by science they mean virtue, but restrict it overmuch by confining it to political problems. Albutius,
a distinguished author and professor of rhetoric,
agrees that rhetoric is the science of speaking well,
but makes a mistake in imposing restrictions by the
addition of the words
                    <hi rend="italic">on political questions</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">with credibility;</hi>
                    with both of these restrictions I have
already dealt.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    Finally those critics who hold that
the aim of rhetoric is
                    <hi rend="italic">to think and speak rightly,</hi>
                    were
on the correct track.
                </p>
                <p>
                    These are practically all the most celebrated and
most discussed definitions of rhetoric. It would be
both irrelevant and beyond my power to deal with all.
For I strongly disapprove of the custom which has
come to prevail among writers of text-books of refusing
to define anything in the same terms as have been
employed by some previous writer. I will have
nothing to do with such ostentation.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    What I say
will not necessarily be my own invention, but it will
be what I believe to be the right view, as for instance
that oratory is the science of speaking well. For
when the most satisfactory definition has been
                    <pb xml:id="p.319"/>
                    found, he who seeks another, is merely looking for a
worse one.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Thus much being admitted we are now in
a position to see clearly what is the end, the
highest aim, the ultimate goal of rhetoric, that
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">te/los</foreign>
                    in fact which every art must possess. For if rhetoric
is the science of speaking well, its end and highest
aim is to speak well.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    There follows the question as to whether
rhetoric is useful. Some are in the habit of
denouncing it most violently and of shamelessly
employing the powers of oratory to accuse oratory
itself.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>It is eloquence</quote>
                    they say
                    <quote>
                        that snatches
criminals from the penalties of the law, eloquence
that from time to time secures the condemnation of the innocent and leads deliberation astray,
eloquence that stirs up not merely sedition and
popular tumult, but wars beyond all expiation, and
that is most effective when it makes falsehood prevail
over the truth.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The comic poets even accuse
Socrates of teaching how to make the worse cause
seem the better, while Plato says that Gorgias and
Tisias made similar professions.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And to these they
add further examples drawn from the history of
Rome and Greece, enumerating all those who used
their pernicious eloquence not merely against individuals but against whole states and threw an ordered
commonwealth into a state of turmoil or even brought
it to utter ruin; and they point out that for this
very reason rhetoric was banished from Sparta, while
its powers were cut down at Athens itself by the fact
that an orator was forbidden to stir the passions of
his audience.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On the showing of these critics not only
orators but generals, magistrates, medicine and
                    <pb xml:id="p.321"/>
                    philosophy itself will all be useless. For Flaminius was a
general, while men such as the Gracchi, Saturninus
and Glaucia were magistrates. Doctors have been
caught using poisons, and those who falsely assume the
name of philosopher have occasionally been detected
in the gravest crimes.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Let us give up eating, it
often makes us ill; let us never go inside houses,
for sometimes they collapse on their occupants;
let never a sword be forged for a soldier, since
it might be used by a robber. And who does
not realise that fire and water, both necessities of
life, and, to leave mere earthly things, even the sun
and moon, the greatest of the heavenly bodies, are
occasionally capable of doing harm.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand will it be denied that it was
by his gift of speech that Appius the Blind broke
off the dishonourable peace which was on the point
of being concluded with Pyrrhus? Did not the
divine eloquence of Cicero win popular applause
even when he denounced the Agrarian laws,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        though denouncing laws which would naturally be
popular.
                    </note>
                    did it
not crush the audacious plots of Catiline and win,
while he still wore the garb of civil life, the highest
honour that can be conferred on a victorious general,
a public thanksgiving to heaven?
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Has not oratory
often revived the courage of a panic-stricken army
and persuaded the soldier faced by all the perils of
war that glory is a fairer thing than life itself? Nor
shall the history of Sparta and Athens move me
more than that of the Roman people, who have
always held the orator in highest honour.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Never in
my opinion would the founders of cities have induced their unsettled multitudes to form communities had they not moved them by the magic of their
eloquence: never without the highest gifts of oratory
                    <pb xml:id="p.323"/>
                    would the great legislators have constrained mankind to submit themselves to the yoke of law.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Nay,
even the principles which should guide our life,
however fair they may be by nature, yet have greater
power to mould the mind to virtue, when the beauty
of things is illumined by the splendour of eloquence.
Wherefore, although the weapons of oratory may
be used either for good or ill, it is unfair to regard
that as an evil which can be employed for good.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    These problems, however, may be left to those
who hold that rhetoric is the power to persuade. If
our definition of rhetoric as the science of speaking
well implies that an orator must be a good man,
there can be no doubt about its usefulness.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    And
in truth that god, who was in the beginning, the
father of all things and the architect of the universe,
distinguished man from all other living creatures
that are subject to death, by nothing more than
this, that he gave him the gift of speech.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For as
regards physical bulk, strength, robustness, endurance or speed, man is surpassed in certain cases by
dumb beasts, who also are far more independent of
external assistance. They know by instinct without
need of any teacher how to move rapidly, to feed
themselves and swim.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Many too have their bodies
clothed against cold, possess natural weapons and
have not to search for their food, whereas in all
these respects man's life is full of toil. Reason
then was the greatest gift of the Almighty, who
willed that we should share its possession with the
immortal gods.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    But reason by itself would help us
but little and would be far less evident in us, had
we not the power to express our thoughts in speech;
for it is the lack of this power rather than thought
                    <pb xml:id="p.325"/>
                    and understanding, which they do to a certain extent possess, that is the great defect in other living
things.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    The construction of a soft lair, the weaving
of nests, the hatching and rearing of their young, and
even the storing up of food for the coming winter,
together with certain other achievements which we
cannot imitate, such as the making of honey and
wax, all these perhaps indicate the possession of a
certain degree of reason; but since the creatures that
do these things lack the gift of speech they are called
dumb and unreasoning beasts.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Finally, how little
the heavenly boon of reason avails those who are
born dumb. If therefore we have received no fairer
gift from heaven than speech, what shall we regard
as so worthy of laborious cultivation, or in what
should we sooner desire to excel our fellow-men,
than that in which mankind excels all other living
things?
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    And we should be all the more eager to do
so, since there is no art which yields a more grateful
recompense for the labour bestowed upon it. This
will be abundantly clear if we consider the origins
of oratory and the progress it has made; and it is
capable of advancing still further.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    I will not stop
to point out how useful and how becoming a task it is
for a good man to defend his friends, to guide the
senate by his counsels, and to lead peoples or armies
to follow his bidding; I merely ask, is it not a
noble thing, by employing the understanding which
is common to mankind and the words that are used
by all, to win such honour and glory that you seem
not to speak or plead, but rather, as was said of
Pericles, to thunder and lighten?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        Aristoph.
                        <hi rend="italic">Ach. 530:</hi>
                        <quote>
                            Then in his wrath Pericles
the Olympian lightened and thundered and threw all Greece
into confusion.
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    However, if I were to indulge my own inclinations in expatiating on this subject, I should go
                    <pb xml:id="p.327"/>
                    on for ever. Let us therefore pass to the next
question and consider whether rhetoric is an art.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    No one of those who have laid down rules for
oratory has ever doubted that it is an art. It is clear
even from the titles of their books that their theme
is the art of rhetoric, while Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Inv.</hi>
                        I. v. 6. The titles in question are such as
                        <hi rend="italic">Ars rhetorica, Ars Hermagorae,</hi>
                        etc.
                    </note>
                    defines rhetoric
as
                    <hi rend="italic">artistic eloquence.</hi>
                    And it is not merely the orators
who have claimed this distinction for their studies
with a view to giving them an additional title to
respect, but the Stoic and Peripatetic philosophers for
the most part agree with them.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed I will confess
that I had doubts as to whether I should discuss this
portion of my inquiry, for there is no one, I will not
say so unlearned, but so devoid of ordinary sense, as
to hold that building, weaving or moulding vessels
from clay are arts, and at the same time to consider
that rhetoric, which, as I have already said, is the
noblest and most sublime of tasks, has reached such
a lofty eminence without the assistance of art.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For
my own part I think that those who have argued
against this view did not realise what they were
saying, but merely desired to exercise their wits by
the selection of a difficult theme, like Polycrates,
when he praised Busiris and Clytemnestra; I may
add that he is credited with a not dissimilar performance, namely the composition of a speech which
was delivered against Socrates.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Some would have it that rhetoric is a natural gift
though they admit that it can be developed by practice.
So Antonius in the
                    <hi rend="italic">de Oralore</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">II. lvii. 232.</note>
                    of Cicero styles it a
                    <hi rend="italic">knack derived from experience,</hi>
                    but denies that it is an art:
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    this statement is however not intended to be accepted
by us as the actual truth, but is inserted to make
                    <pb xml:id="p.329"/>
                    Antonius speak in character, since he was in the
habit of concealing his art. Still Lysias is said to
have maintained this same view, which is defended
on the ground that uneducated persons, barbarians
and slaves, when speaking on their own behalf, say
something that resembles an
                    <hi rend="italic">exordiam,</hi>
                    state the facts
of the case, prove, refute and plead for mercy just as
an orator does in his peroration.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    To this is added
the quibble that nothing that is based on art can
have existed before the art in question, whereas men
have always from time immemorial spoken in their
own defence or in denunciation of others: the
teaching of rhetoric as an art was, they say, a later
invention dating from about the time of Tisias and
Corax: oratory therefore existed before art and
consequently cannot be an art.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For my part I am not
concerned with the date when oratory began to be
taught. Even in Homer we find Phoenix
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        ix. 432.
                    </note>
                    as an
instructor not only of conduct but of speaking, while
a number of orators are mentioned, the various styles
are represented by the speeches of three of the
chiefs
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        the copious style by Nestor, the plain by Menelaus,
the intermediate by Ulysses.
                    </note>
                    and the young men are set to contend among
themselves in contests of eloquence:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        xv. 284.
                    </note>
                    moreover lawsuits and pleaders are represented in the engravings
on the shield of Achilles.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        xviii. 497
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    It is sufficient to call
attention to the fact that everything which art has
brought to perfection originated in nature. Otherwise we might deny the title of art to medicine,
which was discovered from the observation of
sickness and health, and according to some is
entirely based upon experiment: wounds were bound
up long before medicine developed into an art, and
fevers were reduced by rest and abstention from food,
long before the reason for such treatment was
                    <pb xml:id="p.331"/>
                    known, simply because the state of the patient's
health left no choice.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    So too building should not be
styled an art; for primitive man built himself a hut
without the assistance of art. Music by the same
reasoning is not an art; for every race indulges in
some kind of singing and dancing. If therefore any
kind of speech is to be called eloquence, I will admit
that it existed before it was an art.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    If on the other
hand not every man that speaks is an orator and
primitive man did not speak like an orator, my
opponents must needs acknowledge that oratory is
the product of art and did not exist before it. This
conclusion also rules out their argument that men
speak who have never learnt how to speak, and that
which a man does untaught can have no connexion
with art.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In support of this contention they adduce
the fact that Demades was a waterman and Aeschines
an actor, but both were orators. Their reasoning is
false. For no man can be an orator untaught and it
would be truer to say that these orators learned
oratory late in life than that they never learned at all;
although as a matter of fact Aeschines had an
acquaintance with literature from childhood since his
father was a teacher of literature, while as regards
Demades, it is quite uncertain that he never studied
rhetoric and in any case continuous practice in
speaking was sufficient to bring him to such proficiency as he attained: for experience is the best of all
schools.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand it may fairly be asserted
that he would have achieved greater distinction, if he
had received instruction: for although he delivered
his speeches with great effect, he never ventured to
write them for others.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Aristotle, it is true, in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Gryllus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A lost treatise, named after Gryllus, the son of
Xenophon.
                    </note>
                    produces some tentative arguments to
                    <pb xml:id="p.333"/>
                    the contrary, which are marked by characteristic
ingenuity. On the other hand he also wrote three
books on the art of rhetoric, in the first of which
he not merely admits that rhetoric is an art, but
treats it as a department of politics and also of
logic.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Critolaus and Athenodorus of Rhodes have
produced many arguments against this view, while
Agnon renders himself suspect by the very title of
his book in which he proclaims that he is going to
indict rhetoric. As to the statements of Epicurus
on this subject, they cause me no surprise, for he is
the foe of all systematic training.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    These gentlemen talk a great deal, but the
arguments on which they base their statements are
few. I will therefore select the most important of
them and will deal with them briefly, to prevent the
discussion lasting to all eternity.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Their first contention is based on the subject-matter; for they
assert that all arts have their own subject-matter
(which is true) and go on to say that rhetoric has
none, which I shall show in what follows to be false.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Another slander is to the effect that no art will
acquiesce in false opinions: since an art must be
based on direct perception, which is always true:
now, say they, rhetoric does give its assent to false
conclusions and is therefore not an art.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    I will admit
that rhetoric sometimes substitutes falsehood for
truth, but I will not allow that it does so because its
opinions are false, since there is all the difference
between holding a certain opinion oneself and
persuading someone else to adopt an opinion. For
instance a general frequently makes use of falsehood: Hannibal when hemmed in by Fabius
persuaded his enemy that he was in retreat by
                    <pb xml:id="p.335"/>
                    tying brushwood to the horns of oxen, setting fire
to them by night and driving the herds across
the mountains opposite.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See Livy, XXII. xvi.</note>
                    But though he deceived
Fabius, he himself was fully aware of the truth.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Again when the Spartan Theopompus changed
clothes with his wife and escaped from custody
disguised as a woman, he deceived his guards,
but was not for a moment deceived as to his own
identity.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Probably a king of Sparta, 770–720 B.C.</note>
                    Similarly an orator, when he substitutes
falsehood for the truth, is aware of the falsehood
and of the fact that he is substituting it for the
truth.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore deceives others, but not himself. When Cicero boasted that he had thrown
dust in the eyes of the jury in the case of
Cluentius, he was far from being blinded himself.
And when a painter by his artistic skill makes us
believe that certain objects project from the picture,
while others are withdrawn into the background, he
knows perfectly well that they are really all in the
same plane.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    My opponents further assert that every
art has some definite goal towards which it directs its
efforts, but that rhetoric as a rule has no such goal,
while at other times it professes to have an aim, but
fails to perform its promise. They lie: I have already
shown that rhetoric has a definite purpose and have
explained what it is.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    And, what is more, the orator
will always make good his professions in this respect,
for he will always speak well. On the other hand
this criticism may perhaps hold good as against those
who think persuasion the end of oratory. But our
orator and his art, as we define it, are independent of
results. The speaker aims at victory, it is true, but if
he speaks well, he has lived up to the ideals of his art,
even if he is defeated.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Similarly a pilot will desire
                    <pb xml:id="p.337"/>
                    to bring his ship safe to harbour; but if he is swept
out of his course by a storm, he will not for that
reason cease to be a pilot, but will say in the wellknown words of the old poet
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ennius,
                        <hi rend="italic">Ann.</hi>
                        483 (Vahlen).
                    </note>
                    <quote>Still let me steer straight on!</quote>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    So too the doctor seeks to heal the
sick; but if the violence of the disease or the refusal
of the patient to obey his regimen or any other
circumstance prevent his achieving his purpose, he
will not have fallen short of the ideals of his art,
provided he has done everything according to reason.
So too the orator's purpose is fulfilled if he has spoken
well. For the art of rhetoric, as I shall show later,
is realised in action, not in the result obtained.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    From
this it follows that there is no truth in yet another
argument which contends that arts know when they
have attained their end, whereas rhetoric does not.
For every speaker is aware when he is speaking well.
These critics also charge rhetoric with doing what
no art does, namely making use of vices to serve its
ends, since it speaks the thing that is not and excites
the passions.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    But there is no disgrace in doing
either of these things, as long as the motive be good:
consequently there is nothing vicious in such action.
Even a philosopher is at times permitted to tell a lie,
while the orator must needs excite the passions, if
that be the only way by which he can lead the
judge to do justice.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    For judges are not always
enlightened and often have to be tricked to prevent
them falling into error. Give me philosophers as
judges, pack senates and assemblies with philosophers,
and you will destroy the power of hatred, influence,
prejudice and false witness; consequently there will
be very little scope for eloquence whose value will
lie almost entirely in its power to charm.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    But if, as is
                    <pb xml:id="p.339"/>
                    the case, our hearers are fickle of mind, and truth is
exposed to a host of perils, we must call in art to aid
us in the fight and employ such means as will help
our case. He who has been driven from the right road
cannot be brought back to it save by a fresh detour.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    The point, however, that gives rise to the greatest
number of these captious accusations against rhetoric,
is found in the allegation that orators speak indifferently on either side of a case. From which they
draw the following arguments: no art is self-contradictory, but rhetoric does contradict itself; no art
tries to demolish what itself has built, but this does
happen in the operations of rhetoric; or again:—
rhetoric teaches either what ought to be said or what
ought not to be said; consequently it is not an art
because it teaches what ought not to be said, or
because, while it teaches what ought to be said, it
also teaches precisely the opposite.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Now it is obvious
that all such charges are brought against that type
of rhetoric with which neither good men nor virtue
herself will have anything to do; since if a case be
based on injustice, rhetoric has no place therein and
consequently it can scarcely happen even under the
most exceptional circumstances that an orator, that
is to say, a good man, will speak indifferently on either
side.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Still it is in the nature of things conceivable
that just causes may lead two wise men to take
different sides, since it is held that wise men may fight
among themselves, provided that they do so at the
bidding of reason. I will therefore reply to their
criticisms in such a way that it will be clear that these
arguments have no force even against those who concede the name of orator to persons of bad character.
For rhetoric is not self-contradictory.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    The conflict is
                    <pb xml:id="p.341"/>
                    between case and case, not between rhetoric and
itself. And even if persons who have learned the
same thing fight one another, that does not prove
that what they have learned is not an art. Were
that so, there could be no art of arms, since gladiators
trained under the same master are often matched
against each other;
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    nor would the pilot's art exist,
because in sea-fights pilots may be found on different
sides; nor yet could there be an art of generalship,
since general is pitted against general. In the same
way rhetoric does not undo its own work. For the
orator does not refute his own arguments, nor does
rhetoric even do so, because those who regard persuasion as its end, or the two good men whom chance has
matched against one another seek merely for probabilities: and the fact that one thing is more credible
than another, does not involve contradiction between
the two.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    There is no absolute antagonism between
the probable and the more probable, just as there is
none between that which is white and that which is
whiter, or between that which is sweet and that
which is sweeter. Nor does rhetoric ever teach that
which ought not to be said, or that which is contrary
to what ought to be said, but solely what ought to be
said in each individual case.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    But though the orator
will as a rule maintain what is true, this will not
always be the case: there are occasions when the
public interest demands that he should defend what
is untrue.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The following objections are also put forward in
the second book of Cicero's
                    <hi rend="italic">de Oratore:</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">II. vii. 30.</note>
                    —
                    <quote>
                        Art deals
with things that are known. But the pleading of an
orator is based entirely on opinion, not on knowledge,
because he speaks to an audience who do not know,
                        <pb xml:id="p.343"/>
                        and sometimes himself states things of which he has
no actual knowledge.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    Now one of these points,
namely whether the judges have knowledge of what
is being said to them, has nothing to do with the art
of oratory. The other statement, that art is concerned
with things that are known, does however require an
answer. Rhetoric is the art of speaking well and the
orator knows how to speak well.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>But,</quote>
                    it is urged,
                    <quote>he does not know whether what he says is true.</quote>
                    Neither do they, who assert that all things derive
their origin from fire or water or the four elements
or indivisible atoms; nor they who calculate the
distances of the stars or the size of the earth and sun.
And yet all these call the subject which they teach
an art. But if reason makes them seem not merely
to hold opinions but, thanks to the cogency of the
proofs adduced, to have actual knowledge, reason will
do the same service to the orator.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>But,</quote>
                    they say,
                    <quote>he does not know whether the cause which he has undertaken is true.</quote>
                    But not even a doctor can tell
whether a patient who claims to be suffering from a
headache, really is so suffering: but he will treat him
on the assumption that his statement is true, and
medicine will still be an art. Again what of the fact
that rhetoric does not always aim at telling the truth,
but always at stating what is probable? The answer
is that the orator knows that what he states is no
more than probable.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    My opponents further object
that advocates often defend in one case what they
have attacked in another. This is not the fault of the
art, but of the man. Such are the main points that
are urged against rhetoric; there are others as well,
but they are of minor importance and drawn from the
same sources.
                    <pb xml:id="p.345"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    That rhetoric is an art may, however,
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    be proved in
a very few words. For if Cleanthes
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Fr. 790.</note>
                    definition be
accepted that
                    <quote>Art is a power reaching its ends by a definite path, that is, by ordered methods,</quote>
                    no one
can doubt that there is such method and order in
good speaking: while if, on the other hand, we accept
the definition which meets with almost universal
approval that art consists in perceptions agreeing
and cooperating to the achievement of some useful
end, we shall be able to show that rhetoric lacks none
of these characteristics.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    Again it is scarcely necessary
for me to point out that like other arts it is based on
examination and practice. And if logic is an art, as
is generally agreed, rhetoric must also be an art, since
it differs from logic in
                    <hi rend="italic">species</hi>
                    rather than in
                    <hi rend="italic">genus.</hi>
                    Nor must I omit to point out that where it is possible
in any given subject for one man to act without art
and another with art, there must necessarily be an
art in connexion with that subject, as there must also
be in any subject in which the man who has received
instruction is the superior of him who has not.
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    But
as regards the practice of rhetoric, it is not merely
the case that the trained speaker will get the better
of the untrained. For even the trained man will
prove inferior to one who has received a better
training. If this were not so, there would not be so
many rhetorical rules, nor would so many great men
have come forward to teach them. The truth of this
must be acknowledged by everyone, but more
especially by us, since we concede the possession of
oratory to none save the good man.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        since our ideals are so high.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Some arts, however, are based on examination, that is to say on the knowledge and proper
appreciation of things, as for instance astronomy,
                    <pb xml:id="p.347"/>
                    which demands no action, but is content to understand
the subject of its study: such arts are called
                    <hi rend="italic">theoretical.</hi>
                    Others again are concerned with action: this is their
end, which is realised in action, so that, the action
once performed, nothing more remains to do: these
arts we style
                    <hi rend="italic">practical,</hi>
                    and dancing will provide us
with an example.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Thirdly there are others which
consist in producing a certain result and achieve their
purpose in the completion of a visible task: such we
style
                    <hi rend="italic">productive,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">painting</hi>
                    may be quoted as an
illustration. In view of these facts we must come to
the conclusion that, in the main, rhetoric is concerned
with action; for in action it accomplishes that which
it is its duty to do.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    This view is universally accepted,
although in my opinion rhetoric draws largely on the
two other kinds of art. For it may on occasion be
content with the mere examination of a thing.
Rhetoric is still in the orator's possession even though
he be silent, while if he gives up pleading either
designedly or owing to circumstances over which he
has no control, he does not therefore cease to be an
orator, any more than a doctor ceases to be a doctor
when he withdraws from practice.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Perhaps the
highest of all pleasures is that which we derive from
private study, and the only circumstances under
which the delights of literature are unalloyed are
when it withdraws from action, that is to say from
toil, and can enjoy the pleasure of self-contemplation.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    But in the results that the orator obtains by writing
speeches or historical narratives, which we may reasonably count as part of the task of oratory, we shall
recognise features resembling those of a productive
art. Still, if rhetoric is to be regarded as one of these
three classes of art, since it is with action that its
                    <pb xml:id="p.349"/>
                    practice is chiefly and most frequently concerned, let
us call it an active or administrative art, the two
terms being identical.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I quite realise that there is a further question as to whether eloquence derives most from
nature or from education. This question really lies
outside the scope of our inquiry, since the ideal
orator must necessarily be the result of a blend of
both. But I do regard it as of great importance
that we should decide how far there is any real
question on this point.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For if we make an absolute
divorce between the two, nature will still be able to
accomplish much without the aid of education,
while the latter is valueless without the aid of
nature. If, on the other hand, they are blended in
equal proportions, I think we shall find that the
average orator owes most to nature, while the perfect orator owes more to education. We may take
a parallel from agriculture. A thoroughly barren
soil will not be improved even by the best cultivation,
while good land will yield some useful produce
without any cultivation; but in the case of really
rich land cultivation will do more for it than its own
natural fertility.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Had Praxiteles attempted to carve
a statue out of a millstone, I should have preferred
a rough block of Parian marble to any such statue.
On the other hand, if the same artist had produced
a finished statue from such a block of Parian marble,
its artistic value would owe more to his skill than
to the material. To conclude, nature is the raw
material for education: the one forms, the other is
formed. Without material art can do nothing,
material without art does possess a certain value,
while the perfection of art is better than the best
material.
                    <pb xml:id="p.351"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    More important is the question whether rhetoric is to be regarded as one of the indifferent arts,
which in themselves deserve neither praise nor blame,
but are useful or the reverse according to the character of the artist; or whether it should, as not a few
even among philosophers hold, be considered as a
virtue.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part I regard the practice of rhetoric which so many have adopted in the past and still
follow to-day, as either no art at all, or, as the Greeks
call it,
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)texni/a</foreign>
                    (for I see numbers of speakers without the least pretension to method or literary training rushing headlong in the direction in which
hunger or their natural shamelessness calls them);
or else it is a bad art such as is styled
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kakotexni/a.</foreign>
                    For there have, I think, been many persons and
there are still some who have devoted their powers
of speaking to the destruction of their fellow-men.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    There is also an unprofitable imitation of art, a kind
of
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">mataiotexni/a</foreign>
                    which is neither good nor bad, but
merely involves a useless expenditure of labour, reminding one of the man who shot a continuous
stream of vetch-seeds from a distance through the
eye of a needle, without ever missing his aim, and
was rewarded by Alexander, who was a witness of
the display, with the present of a bushel of vetch-seeds, a most appropriate reward.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    It is to such men
that I would compare those who spend their whole
time at the expense of much study and energy in
composing declamations, which they aim at making
as unreal as possible. The rhetoric on the other
hand, which I am endeavouring to establish and the
ideal of which I have in my mind's eye, that rhetoric
which befits a good man and is in a word the only
true rhetoric, will be a virtue.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Philosophers arrive
                    <pb xml:id="p.353"/>
                    at this conclusion by a long chain of ingenious
arguments; but it appears to me to be perfectly
clear from the simpler proof of my own invention
which I will now proceed to set forth.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The philosophers state the case as follows. If
self-consistency as to what should and should not
be done is an element of virtue (and it is to this
quality that we give the name of prudence), the
same quality will be revealed as regards what should
be said and what should not be said,
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    and if there are
virtues, of which nature has given us some rudimentary sparks, even before we were taught anything
about them, as for instance justice, of which there are
some traces even among peasants and barbarians, it
is clear that man has been so formed from the
beginning as to be able to plead on his own behalf,
not, it is true, with perfection, but yet sufficiently to
show that there are certain sparks of eloquence
implanted in us by nature.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The same nature, however, is not to be found in those arts which have no
connexion with virtue. Consequently, since there are
two kinds of speech, the continuous which is called
rhetoric, and the concise which is called dialectic (the
relation between which was regarded by Zeno as being
so intimate that he compared the latter to the closed
fist, the former to the open hand), even the art of
disputation will be a virtue. Consequently there can
be no doubt about oratory whose nature is so much
fairer and franker.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    I should like, however, to consider the point
more fully and explicitly by appealing to the
actual work of oratory. For how will the orator
succeed in panegyric unless he can distinguish between what is honourable and the reverse? How
                    <pb xml:id="p.355"/>
                    can he urge a policy, unless he has a clear perception of what is expedient? How can he plead in
the law-courts, if he is ignorant of the nature of
justice? Again, does not oratory call for courage,
since it is often directed against the threats of
popular turbulence and frequently runs into peril
through incurring the hatred of the great, while
sometimes, as for instance in the trial of Milo, the
orator may have to speak in the midst of a crowd of
armed soldiers? Consequently, if oratory be not a
virtue, perfection is beyond its grasp.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    If, on the
other hand, each living thing has its own peculiar
virtue, in which it excels the rest or, at any rate, the
majority (I may instance the courage of the lion
and the swiftness of the horse), it may be regarded
as certain that the qualities in which man excels
the rest are, above all, reason and powers of speech.
Why, therefore, should we not consider that the
special virtue of man lies just as much in eloquence as in reason? It will be with justice then
that Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        III. xiv. 55.
                    </note>
                    makes Crassus say that
                    <quote>eloquence is one of the highest virtues,</quote>
                    and that Cicero himself
calls it a virtue in his letters to Brutus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Lost.</note>
                    and in
other passages.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>But,</quote>
                    it may be urged,
                    <quote>
                        a bad
man will at times produce an
                        <hi rend="italic">exordium</hi>
                        or a
                        <hi rend="italic">statement of facts,</hi>
                        and will argue a case in a manner that
leaves nothing to be desired.
                    </quote>
                    No doubt; even a
robber may fight bravely without courage ceasing to
be a virtue; even a wicked slave may bear torture
without a groan, and we may still continue to regard
endurance of pain as worthy of praise. We can
point to many acts which are identical with those of
virtue, but spring from other sources. However,
what I have said here must suffice, as I have already
dealt with the question of the usefulness of oratory.
                    <pb xml:id="p.357"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    As to the material of oratory, some have
asserted that it is speech, as for instance Gorgias
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorg.</hi>
                        449
                        <hi rend="italic">E.</hi>
                    </note>
                    in
the dialogue of Plato. If this view be accepted in
the sense that the word
                    <quote>speech</quote>
                    is used of a discourse composed on any subject, then it is not the
material, but the work, just as a statue is the work
of the sculptor. For speeches like statues require
art for their production. If on the other hand
we interpret
                    <quote>speech</quote>
                    as indicating the words
themselves, they can do nothing unless they are
related to facts. Some again hold that the material
consists of persuasive arguments. But they form
part of the work, are produced by art and require
material themselves.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Some say that political
questions provide the material. The mistake made
by these lies not in the quality of their opinion
but in its limitation. For political questions are
material for eloquence but not the only material.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Some, on the ground that rhetoric is a virtue, make the
material with which it deals to be the whole of life.
Others, on the ground that life regarded as a whole
does not provide material for every virtue, since
most of them are concerned only with departments
of life (justice, courage and self-control each having
their own duties and their own end), would consequently restrict oratory to one particular department
of life and place it in the practical or pragmatic
department of ethics, that is to say the department
of morals which deals with the business of life.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part, and I have authority to support
me, I hold that the material of rhetoric is composed of
everything that may be placed before it as a subject
for speech. Plato, if I read him aright, makes
Socrates
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorg.</hi>
                        449 E.
                    </note>
                    say to Gorgias that its material is to be
                    <pb xml:id="p.359"/>
                    found in things not words; while in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Phaedrus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phaedr.</hi>
                        261 A.
                    </note>
                    he clearly proves that rhetoric is concerned not
merely with law-courts and public assemblies, but with
private and domestic affairs as well: from which it is
obvious that this was the view of Plato himself.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero
also in a passage
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Inv.</hi>
                        i. 5.
                    </note>
                    of one of his works, states that
the material of rhetoric is composed of the things
which are brought before it, but makes certain restrictions as to the nature of these things. In
another passage,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. vi. 21.
                        <quote>I will not demand omniscience from an orator, although</quote>
                        etc.
                    </note>
                    however, he expresses his opinion
that the orator has to speak about all kinds of things;
I will quote his actual words:
                    <quote>
                        although the very
meaning of the name of orator and the fact that
he professes to speak well seem to imply a promise
and undertaking that the orator will speak with
elegance and fullness on any subject that may be
put before him.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And in another passage
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">ib.</hi>
                        iii. xiv. 54.
                    </note>
                    he says,
                    <quote>
                        It is the duty of the true orator to seek out, hear,
read, discuss, handle and ponder everything that befalls in the life of man, since it is with this that the
orator is concerned and this that forms the material
with which he has to deal.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But this material, as we call it, that is to say
the things brought before it, has been criticised by
some, at times on the ground that it is limitless, and
sometimes on the ground that it is not peculiar to
oratory, which they have therefore dubbed a
                    <hi rend="italic">discursive</hi>
                    art, because all is grist that comes to its mill.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    I have no serious quarrel with these critics, for they
acknowledge that rhetoric is concerned with every
kind of material, though they deny that it has any
peculiar material just because of that material's multiplicity. But in spite of this multiplicity, rhetoric
is not unlimited in scope, and there are other minor
                    <pb xml:id="p.361"/>
                    arts whose material is characterised by the same
multiplicity: such for instance is architecture, which
deals with everything that is useful for the purpose
of building: such too is the engraver's art which
works on gold, silver, bronze, iron.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    As for sculpture,
its activity extends to wood, ivory, marble, glass and
precious stones in addition to the materials already
mentioned.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And things which form the material for
other artists, do not for that reason cease forthwith
to be material for rhetoric. For if I ask what is the
material of the sculptor, I shall be told bronze; and
if I ask what is the material of the maker of vessels
(I refer to the craft styled
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">xalkeutikh/</foreign>
                    by the Greeks),
the answer will again be bronze: and yet there is
all the difference in the world between vessels and
statues.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Similarly medicine will not cease to be an
art, because, like the art of the gymnast, it prescribes rubbing with oil and exercise, or because it
deals with diet like the art of cookery.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Again, the
objection that to discourse of what is good, expedient
or just is the duty of philosophy presents no difficulty. For when such critics speak of a philosopher,
they mean a good man. Why then should I feel
surprised to find that the orator whom I identify with
the good man deals with the same material?
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    There
is all the less reason, since I have already shown in
the first book
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Pref. § 10
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    that philosophers only usurped this
department of knowledge after it had been abandoned by the orators: it was always the peculiar
property of rhetoric and the philosophers are really
trespassers. Finally, since the discussion of whatever is brought before it is the task of dialectic,
which is really a concise form of oratory, why should
not this task be regarded as also being the appropriate material for continuous oratory?
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.363"/>
                <p>
                    There is a further objection made by certain
critics, who say
                    <quote>
                        Well then,
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        if an orator has to speak on
every subject, he must be the master of all the arts.
                    </quote>
                    I might answer this criticism in the words of Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. vi. 20.
                    </note>
                    in whom I find the following passage:—
                    <quote>
                        In my
opinion no one can be an absolutely perfect orator
unless he has acquired a knowledge of all important
subjects and arts.
                    </quote>
                    I however regard it as sufficient that an orator should not be actually ignorant
of the subject on which he has to speak.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For he
cannot have a knowledge of all causes, and yet he
should be able to speak on all. On what then
will he speak? On those which he has studied.
Similarly as regards the arts, he will study those
concerning which he has to speak, as occasion may
demand, and will speak on those which he has
studied.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    What then?—I am asked—will not a builder
speak better on the subject of building and a musician on music? Certainly, if the orator does not
know what is the question at issue. Even an illiterate peasant who is a party to a suit will speak
better on behalf of his case than an orator who does
not know what the subject in dispute may be. But
on the other hand if the orator receive instruction
from the builder or the musician, he will put forward what he has thus learned better than either,
just as he will plead a case better than his client,
once he has been instructed in it.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The builder and
the musician will, however, speak on the subject of
their respective arts, if there should be any technical
point which requires to be established. Neither will
be an orator, but he will perform his task like an
orator, just as when an untrained person binds up a
                    <pb xml:id="p.365"/>
                    wound, he will not be a physician, but he will be
acting as one.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Is it suggested that such topics
never crop up in panegyric, deliberative or forensic
oratory? When the question of the construction of
a port at Ostia came up for discussion, had not the
orator to state his views? And yet it was a subject
requiring the technical knowledge of the architect.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Does not the orator discuss the question whether
livid spots and swellings on the body are symptomatic of ill-health or poison? And yet that is a
question for the qualified physician. Will he not
deal with measurements and figures? And yet we
must admit that they form part of mathematics. For
my part I hold that practically all subjects are
under certain circumstances liable to come up for
treatment by the orator. If the circumstances do
not occur, the subjects will not concern him.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    We were therefore right in asserting that the
material of rhetoric is composed of everything that
comes before the orator for treatment, an assertion
which is confirmed by the practice of everyday
speech. For when we have been given a subject
on which to speak, we often preface our remarks by
calling attention to the fact that the matter has
been laid before us.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Gorgias indeed felt so strongly
that it was the orator's duty to speak on every subject, that he used to allow those who attended his
lectures to ask him questions on any subject they
pleased. Hermagoras also asserted that the material
of oratory lay in the cause and the questions it
involved, thereby including every subject that can
be brought before it.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    If he denies that general
questions
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III V. 12–16.</note>
                    are the concern of oratory, he disagrees
with me: but if they do concern rhetoric, that
                    <pb xml:id="p.367"/>
                    supports my contention. For there is nothing which
may not crop up in a cause or appear as a question
for discussion.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rhet.</hi>
                        I. iii. 3.
                    </note>
                    himself also by his tripartite
division of oratory, into forensic, deliberative and
demonstrative, practically brought everything into the
orator's domain, since there is nothing that may not
come up for treatment by one of these three kinds of
rhetoric.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    A very few critics have raised the question as to
what may be the
                    <hi rend="italic">instrument</hi>
                    of oratory. My definition of an instrument is
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        that without which the material
cannot be brought into the shape necessary for the effecting of our object.
                    </hi>
                    But it is not the art which requires an instrument, but the artist. Knowledge
needs no instruments, for it may be complete
although it produces nothing, but the artist must
have them. The engraver cannot work without his
chisel nor the painter without his brush. I shall
therefore defer this question until I come to treat of
the orator as distinct from his art.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
