<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>On the Agrarian Law</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl n="CTS">
				<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts speech and section.</p>
				</cRefPattern>
				<cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts speech.</p>
				</cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech" delim="."/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>

<!--<encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
-->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-04-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Review of changes.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-11" who="Zach Himes">Converted section milestones to divs. Moved some sections that weren't in the correct locations (based my understanding of the corresponding Latin text)</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
<div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi011.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
<div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="speech">
 
<head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN OPPOSITION TO PUBLIUS SERVILIUS RULLUS, A TRIBUNE OF THE
 PEOPLE, CONCERNING THE AGRARIAN LAW. DELIVERED IN THE SENATE. THE FIRST ORATION ON THIS SUBJECT.</head>

     <div type="commentary" subtype="textpart" resp="editor">
      <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
      <p><milestone unit="para"/>A short time before Cicero's inauguration as consul, which took place on the first of
      January, Publius Servilius Rullus, one of the new tribunes, (who entered on their office on
      the tenth of December,) had been alarming the senate with the proposal of a new agrarian law,
      the purport of which was to appoint ten commissioners, (<foreign xml:lang="lat">decemviri</foreign>) with absolute power for five years over all the revenues of the
      republic; to distribute them at pleasure to the citizens; to sell and buy what lands they
      thought fit; to determine the rights of the present possessors; to require an account from all
      the generals abroad, except, Pompey, of the spoils taken in their wars; to settle colonies
      wherever they judged it proper, and especially at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>; and, in short, the entire command of the money and forces of the empire.
        (<persName><surname>Middleton</surname></persName>, ch. iii.) 
     <milestone unit="para"/>This oration (of which some of the beginning is lost), was addressed to the senate on the
      first of January, to relieve them of their apprehensions respecting this law, by assuring them
      that he would oppose the law and all its promoters to the uttermost of his power; and that he
      would not suffer the state to be injured or its liberties to be impaired, while the
      administration remained in his hands.</p></div>
 
     <milestone unit="para"/>
     <gap reason="lost"/>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4fr" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>The <foreign xml:lang="lat">decemviri</foreign> will sell the booty, the spoils, the division
     of the plunder, the very camp of Cnaeus Pompeius, while the general is forced to sit still.</p></div>
 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1fr" resp="perseus">
        <p><milestone unit="para"/>In beardless youth<gap reason="lost"/></p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2fr" resp="perseus">
  <p><milestone unit="para"/><gap reason="omitted"/></p></div>
 
 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3fr" resp="perseus">
       <p><milestone unit="para"/>[The whole of the Propontis and of the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>
     will therefore come under the power of the praetor; the whole coast of the Lycians and
     Cilicians will be advertised for sale; <placeName key="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName> and
      <placeName key="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName> will be subjected to the same conditions
      <note anchored="true">Rhunck has enclosed this sentence in brackets, as the gloss and
      interpolation of an ignorant man; but Orellius thinks some part of it really Cicero's, though
      not free from corruptions.</note>] </p></div>
 
    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>. . . . That which was then openly sought, is now endeavoured to be effected secretly by
     mines. For the decemvirs will say, what indeed is said by many, and has often been said,—that
     after the consulship of those men, all that kingdom became the property of the Roman people, by
     the bequest of the king Alexander. Will you then give <placeName key="tgn,7002256">Alexandria</placeName>
     <note anchored="true">Alexander, king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, had
      died at <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName> in the consulship of Cotta and
      Torquatus, two years before, and had bequeathed <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> to the Roman
      people, and in consequence many people advocated the course of claiming that inheritance, and
      depriving Ptolemy the king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. The subject will
      be mentioned again in the next oration.</note> to those men when they ask for it in an
     underhand way, whom you resisted when they openly fought against you? Which, in the name of the
     immortal gods, do these things seem to you,—the designs of sober men, or the dreams of drunken
     ones? the serious thoughts of wise men, or the frantic wishes of madmen? </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p> See, now, in the second chapter of this law, how that profligate debauchee is
     disturbing the republic,—how he is ruining and dissipating the possessions left us by our
     ancestors; so as to be not less a spendthrift in the patrimony of the Roman people than in his
     own. He is advertising for sale by his law all the revenues, for the decemvirs to sell them;
     that is to say, he is advertising an auction of the property of the state. He wants lands to be
     bought, in order to be distributed; he is seeking money. No doubt he will devise something, and
     bring it forward; for in the preceding chapters the dignity of the Roman people was attacked;
     the name of our dominion was held up as an object of common hatred to all the nations of the
     earth; cities which were at peace with us, lands belonging to the allies, the ranks of kings in
     alliance with us, were all made a present of to the decemvirs; and now they want actual ready
     money paid down to them. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p> I am waiting to see what this
     vigilant and clever tribune is contriving. Let the Scantian <note anchored="true">The Scantian
      wood was in <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>.</note> wood, says he, be sold.
     Did you then find this wood mentioned among the possessions that were left, or in the pasture
     lands of the lessors? If there is anything which you have hunted out, and discovered, brought
     to light out of darkness, although it is not just, still use that, since it is convenient, and
     since you yourself were the person to bring it forward. But shall you sell the Scantian wood
     while we are consuls, and while this senate is in existence? Shall you touch any of the
     revenues? Shall you take away from the Roman people that which is their strength in time of
     war, their ornament in time of peace? But then indeed, I shall think myself a lazier consul
     than those fearless men who filled this office in the times of our ancestors; because the
     revenues which were acquired by the Roman people when they were consuls, will be considered not
     able to be preserved when I am consul.</p></div>
 
    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>He is selling all the possessions in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, in
     regular order. Forsooth, he is very busy in that occupation. For does not omit one. He goes
     through the whole of <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> in the account-books of
     the censors. He does not omit one single house, or one single field. You have heard an auction
     of the property of the Roman people given notice of by tribune of the people, and fixed for the
     month of January and I suppose you do not doubt, that they who procured these things by their
     arms and their valour, did not sell the for the sake of the treasury, on purpose that we might
     have something to sell for the sake of bribery. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>See, now, how much more undisguisedly than before he proceeds on his course. For it has been
     already shown by how they attacked Pompeius in the earlier part of the law; and now they shall
     show it also themselves. He orders the lands belonging to the men of <placeName key="tgn,7002378">Attalia</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> to
     be sold. These lands the victory of Publius Servilius, that most gallant general, had made the
     property of the Roman people. After that, the royal domains in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, which were acquired partly by the valour of Titus Flamininus, and part
     by that of Lucius Paullus, who conquered Perses. After that, that most excellent and productive
     land which belongs <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, which was added to the
     revenues of the Roman people by the campaigns and successes of Lucius Mummius. After that, they
     sell the lands in <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName> near Carthagena, acquired by
     the distinguished valour of the two Scipios. Then Carthagena itself, which Publius Scipio,
     having stripped it of all its fortifications, consecrated to the eternal recollection of men,
     whether his purpose was to keep up the memory of the disaster of the Carthaginians, or to bear
     witness to our victory, or to fulfill some religious obligation. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> Having sold all these ensigns and crowns, as it were, of the empire, with
     which the republic was adorned, and handed down to you by your ancestors, they then order the
     lands to be sold which the king Mithridates possessed in <placeName key="tgn,7016760">Paphlagonia</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,6003016">Cappadocia</placeName>. Do they not seem to be pursuing without much
     disguise, and almost with the crier's spear, the army of Cnaeus Pompeius, when they order those
     lands to be sold in which he is now engaged and carrying on war?</p></div>
 
    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But what is the meaning of this, that they fix no place for this auction which they are
     establishing? For power is given to the decemvirs by this law, of holding their sales in any
     places which seem convenient to them. The censors are not allowed to let the contracts for
     farming the revenues, except in the sight of the Roman people. Shall these men be allowed to
     sell them in the most distant countries? But even the most profligate men, when they have
     squandered their patrimony, prefer selling their property in the auctioneer's rooms, rather
     than in the roads, or in the streets. This man, by his law, gives leave to the decemvirs to
     sell the property of the Roman people in whatever darkness and whatever solitude they find it
     convenient. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> Do you not, moreover, see how grievous, how
     formidable, and how pregnant with extortion that invasion of the decemvirs and of the multitude
     that will follow in their train will be to all the provinces, and kingdoms, and free nations?
     In the case of those men on whom you have conferred lieutenancies for the sake of entering on
     inheritances, though they went as private men, on private business, invested with no excessive
     power and no supreme authority, you have still heard how burdensome their arrival has proved to
     your allies. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p> What alarm and what misfortune, then must you
     think all nations are threatened with by this law, when decemvirs are sent all over the world
     with supreme power,—men of the greatest avarice, and with an insatiable desire for every sort
     of property? whose arrival will be grievous, whose forces will be formidable, whose judicial
     and arbitrary power will be absolutely intolerable. For they will have the power of deciding
     whatever they please to be public property, and of selling whatever they decide to be such.
     Even that very thing which conscientious men will not do, namely, taking money to abstain from
     selling, is to be made <pb n="206"/> lawful for them to do by the express provisions of the
     law. From this provision what plunderings, what bargainings, what a regular auction of all law
     and of every one's fortunes must inevitably arise! </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> Even that
     which in the former pert of the law made in the consulship of Sulla and Pompeius was strictly
     defined, that they have now left at the discretion of these men, without any restriction or
     limitation. 
     
     <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>He orders these same decemvirs to impose an exceedingly heavy tax on all the public domains,
     in order that they might be able both to release what lands they choose and to confiscate what
     they choose. And in this proceeding it is hard to see whether their severity will be more cruel
     or their kindness more gainful. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>However, there are in the whole law two exceptions, not so much unjust as suspicious. In
     imposing the tax it makes an exception with respect to the Recentoric district in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>; and in selling the land, he excepts those with respect
     to which there was an express provision in the treaty. These lands are in <placeName key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, in the occupation of Hiempsal. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p> Here I ask, if sufficient protection is afforded to Hiempsal by the treaty
     and if the Recentoric district is private property, what was use of excepting these lands by
     name in the law? If that treaty itself has some obscurity in it, and if the Recentoric is
     sometimes said to be public property, who do you suppose will believe that there have been two
     interests found in the world, and only two, which he spared for nothing? Does there appear to
     have been any coin in the world so carefully hidden that the architects of this law have failed
     to scent it out? They are draining the provinces, the free cities, our allies, our friends, and
     even the kings who are confederate with us. They are laying bands on the revenue of the Roman
     people. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>That is not enough. Listen—listen, you who, by the most honourable vote of the people and
     senate, have commanded armies and carried on wars:—“Whatever has come or shall come to anyone,
     of booty, of spoils, of money given for gold crowns, which has neither been spent on a
     monument, nor paid into the treasury, is all to be paid over to the decemvirs.” From this
     chapter they expect a great deal. The propose by their resolution an investigation into the
     affairs of all our generals and all their heirs. But they expect to go the greatest quantity of
     money from Faustus. That cause which the judges upon their oath would not undertake, these
     decemvirs have undertaken. They think, perhaps, that it was declined by the judges, on purpose
     to be reserved to them. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> After that, the law most carefully
     provides for the future, that, whatever money any general receives, he is at once to pay over
     to the decemvirs. But here he excepts Pompeius, very much as, as it seems to me, in that law by
     which aliens are sent away from <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> an exception is
     made in favour of Glaucippus. For the effect of this exception is not to confer a kindness on
     one man, but merely to save one man from injustice. But the man whose spoils the law thus
     spares, has his revenues invaded by the same law. For it orders all the money which is received
     after our consulship from the new revenues, to be placed to the use of the decemvirs. As if we
     did not see that they were thinking of selling the revenues which Cnaeus Pompeius has added to
     the wealth of the Roman people.</p></div>
 
    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>You see now, O conscript fathers, that the money which is to belong to the decemvirs is
     collected and heaped together from every possible source, and by every imaginable expedient.
     The unpopularity arising from their possession of this large sum is to be diminished, for it
     shall be spent in the purchase of lands. Exceedingly well. Who then is to buy those lands?
     These same decemvirs. You, O Rullus— for I say nothing of the rest of them,—are to buy whatever
     you like; to sell whatever you like, to buy or sell at whatever price you please. For that
     admirable man takes care not to buy of any one against his will. As if we did not understand
     that to buy of a man against his will is an injurious thing to do; but to buy of one who has no
     objection, is profitable. How much land (to say nothing of other people) will your
     father-in-law sell you? and, if I have formed a proper estimate of the fairness of his
     disposition, will have no objection to sell you? The rest will do the same willingly; they will
     be glad to exchange the unpopularity attaching to the possession of land for money; to receive
     whatever they demand, and to part with what they can scarcely retain. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> Now just see the boundless and intolerable licentiousness of all these
     measures. Money has been collected for the purchase of lands. More-over, the lands are not to
     be bought of people against their will. Suppose all the owners agree not to sell, what is to
     happen then? Is the money to be refunded? That cannot <pb n="208"/> be. Is it to be collected?
     The law forbids that. However, let that pass. There is nothing which cannot be bought, if you
     will only give as much as the seller asks. Let us plunder the whole world, let us sell our
     revenues, let us exhaust the treasury, in order that, whether men be owners of wealth, or of
     odium, or even of a pestilence, still their lands may be bought.</p></div>
 
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> What is to happen then? what sort of men are to be
     established as settlers in those lands? what is to be the system and plan adopted in the whole
     business? Colonies, say the law, shall be led thither, and settled there. How many? Of what
     class of men? Where are they to be established? For who is there who does not see that all
     these things have got to be considered when we are talking of colonies? Did you think, O
     Rullus, that we would give up the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> to
     you and to those contrivers of everything whom you have set up, in an unarmed and defenceless
     state, for you to strengthen it with garrisons afterwards? for you to occupy it with colonies?
     to hold it bound and fettered by every sort of chain? For where is there any clause to prevent
     your establishing a colony on the Janiculan Hill? or from oppressing and overwhelming this city
     with some other city? We will not do so, says he. In the first place, I don't know that; in the
     next place, I am afraid of you; lastly, I will never permit our safety to depend on your
     kindness rather than on our own prudence.</p></div>
 
    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But as you wanted to fill all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> with your
     colonies, did you think that not one of us would understand what sort of a measure that was?
     For it is written, “The decemvirs may lead whatever settlers they choose into whatever
     municipalities and colonies they like; and they may assign them lands in whatever places they
     please;” so that, when they have occupied all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>
     with their soldiers, you may have no hope left you, I will not say of retaining your dignity,
     but none even of recovering your liberty. And these things, indeed, I object to on suspicion
     and from conjecture. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> But now all mistake on any side shall
     be removed; now they shall show openly that the very name of this republic, and the situation
     of this city and empire, that even this very temple of the good and great
       <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, and this citadel of all nations, is odious
     to them. They wish settlers to be conducted to <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>. They wish again to oppose that city to this city. They think of removing
     all their riches thither of transferring thither the name of the empire. That place which,
     because of the fertility of its lands and its abundance of every sort of production, is said to
     be the parent of pride and cruelty—in that our colonists, men selected as fit for every
     imaginable purpose, will be settled by the decemvirs. No doubt, in that city, in which men,
     though born to the enjoyment of ancient dignities and hereditary fortunes, were still unable to
     bear with moderation the luxuriance of their fortunes, your satellites will be able to restrain
     their insolence and to behave with modesty. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> Our ancestors
     removed from <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> the magistrates, the senate, the
     general council, and all the ensigns of the republic, and left nothing there except the bare
     name of <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>; not out of cruelty, (for what was
     ever more merciful than they were? for they often restored their property even to foreign
     enemies when they had been subdued;) but out of wisdom; because they saw that if any trace of
     the republic remained within those walls, the city itself might be able to afford a home to
     supreme power. And would not you too see how mischievous these things were, if you were not
     desirous of overturning the republic, and of procuring a new sort of power for your own selves?</p></div>
 
     <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>For what is there that is especially to be guarded against in the establishment of colonies?
     If it be luxury—<placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> corrupted Hannibal himself. If
     it be pride—that appears from the general arrogance of the Campanians to be innate there. If we
     want a bulwark for the state—then I say, that <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>
     is not placed in front of this city as an outwork, but is opposed to it as an enemy. But how is
     it armed? O ye immortal gods! For in the Punic war all the power that <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> had, it had from its unassisted resources; but now, all
     the cities which are around <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> will be occupied
     by colonists, by the order of these same decemvirs. For, for this reason, the law itself
     allows, “that the decemvirs may lead whoever they please as settlers to every town which they
     choose.” And it orders the Campanian district, and that of <placeName key="tgn,1047002">Stella</placeName>, to be divided among these colonists.</p></div>
 
 <milestone unit="para"/>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p>I do not complain of the diminution of the revenues; nor
     of the wickedness of this loss and injury. I pass over those things which there is no one who
     cannot complain of with the greatest weight and the greatest truth; that we have not been able
     to preserve the most important part of the public patrimony of the state, that which has been
     to us the source of our supply of corn, our granary in time of war, our revenue placed under
     custody of the seals and bolts of the republic; that we, in short, have abandoned that district
     to Publius Rullus, which itself by its own resources had resisted both the absolute power of
     Sulla, and the corrupting liberality of the Gracchi. I do not say that, now that so much has
     been lost, this is the only revenue which remains in the republic; the only one which, while
     other sources of income are interrupted, does not fail us; the only one which is splendid in
     peace, is; not worn out in war; which supports our soldiery, and is not afraid of our enemies.
     I pass over all this which I might say; I reserve that for the assembly of the people. I am
     speaking now of the danger to our safety and to our liberty. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
     For what do you think will remain to you unimpaired in the whole republic, or in your liberty,
     or in your dignity, when Rullus, and those whom you are much more afraid of than you are of
     Rullus, with his whole band of needy and unprincipled men, with all his forces, with all his
     silver and gold, shall have occupied <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> and the
     cities around <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>? These things, O conscript
     fathers, I will resist eagerly and vigorously; and I will not permit men, while I am consul, to
     bring forth those plans against the republic which they have long been meditating.</p></div>
 <milestone unit="para"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>You made a great mistake, O Rullus, you and some of your
     colleagues, when you hoped that, in being in opposition to a consul who studied the interests
     of the people in reality, not by making a vain parade of so doing, you would be able to gain
     popularity while overturning the republic. I challenge you; I invite you to the assembly; I
     will accept the Roman people as an umpire between us <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>In fact, if we look round to survey everything which is; pleasant and acceptable to the
     people, we shall find that nothing is so popular as peace, and concord, and ease. You have
     given up to me a city made anxious with suspicion, in suspense from fear, harassed to death by
     your proposed laws, and assemblies, and seditions. You have inflamed the hopes of the wicked;
     you have filled the virtuous with alarms; you have banished good faith from the forum, and
     dignity from the republic. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> Amid all this commotion and
     agitation of minds and circumstances, when the voice and authority of the consul has suddenly,
     from amid such great darkness, dawned on the Roman people; when it has shown that nothing need
     be feared; that no regular army, no band of extempore ruffians, no colony, no sale of the
     revenues, no new of command, no reign of decemvirs, no new <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> or opposition seat of empire, will be allowed to exist while we are consuls;
     that the greatest tranquillity of peace and ease will be secured; then, no doubt, we shall have
     much reason to ear that this beautiful agrarian law of yours will appear popular. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> But when I have displayed the wickedness of your counsels, the
     dishonesty of your law, and the treachery which is planned by those popular tribunes of the
     people against the Roman people; then, I suppose, I shall have reason to fear that I shall not
     be allowed to appear in the assembly, for the purpose of opposing you; especially when I have
     determined and resolved so to conduct myself in my consulship, (and the duties of the
     consulship cannot be discharged with dignity and freedom, in any other manner,) as neither to
     desire any province, nor honour, nor dignity nor advantage nor anything whatever which can have
     any hindrance thrown in its way by any tribune of the people. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p> The consul states, in full senate, on the calends of January, that if the present condition
     of the republic continues, and if no new event arises, on account of which he cannot with
     honour avoid it, he will not go to any province. By that means I shall be able, O conscript
     fathers, so to behave myself in this magistracy, as to be able to restrain any tribune of the
     people who is hostile to the republic,—to despise any one who is hostile to myself. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, in the name of the immortal gods! I entreat you, recollect yourselves, O tribunes
     of the people; desert those men by whom, in a short time, unless you take great care, you will
     yourselves be deserted. Conspire with us; agree with all virtuous men defend our common
     republic with one common zeal and affection. There are many secret wounds sustained by the
     republic. There are many mischievous counsels of abandoned citizens designed against her. There
     is no external danger. There is no king no nation, no people in the world whom we need fear.
     The evil is confined within our own walls internal and domestic very one of us to the best of
     his power ought to resist and to remedy this. </p></div>
 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p> You mistake if
     you think that the senate approves of what is said by me, but that the inclinations of the
     people are different. All men, who wish to be safe themselves, will follow the authority of the
     consul, a man uninfluenced by evil passion; free from all suspicion of guilt; cautious in
     danger; not fearful in contest. But if any one of you cherishes a hope that he may be able in a
     turbulent state of affairs to promote his own interests, first of all, let him give up hoping
     any such thing as long as I am consul. In the next place, let him take me myself as a proof—(me
     whom he sees now consul, though born only in the equestrian rank)—of what course of life most
     easily conducts virtuous men to honour and dignity. But if you, O conscript father, assist me
     with your zeal and energy in defending our common dignity, then, in truth, I shall accomplish
     that of which our republic is at present in the greatest possible need. I shall make the
     authority of this order, which existed so long among our ancestors, appear after a long
     interval to be again restored to the republic.</p></div></div>
   
   <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="Speech">
    <head> THE SECOND SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO <lb/>IN OPPOSITION TO PUBLIUS SERVILIUS RULLUS, A
     TRIBUNE OF THE PEOPLE, <lb/>CONCERNING THE AGRARIAN LAW. <lb/>DELIVERED TO THE PEOPLE.</head>
    
     <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>A few days after the preceding speech in the senate, Cicero came into the assembly of the
      people, and made the following speech to them; dilating on the different particulars of the
      proposed law, and on its evils, at much greater length than he had done when he addressed the
      senate. And he succeeded so much, that, as he says himself, no one had ever had more success
      in arguing in favour of an agrarian law, (which was always likely to be a popular proposal,)
      than he had in haranguing the people against this one.</p>
    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> It is in accordance with the customs and established usages
     of our ancestors, O Romans, that those who, by your kindness, have overtaken the images of
     their family,<note anchored="true">“Those Romans who had passed through one of the high offices
      of aediles, praetor, or consul were allowed to have their likenesses handed down to posterity.
      These likenesses were, according to Casaubon, busts; but according to Schweighauser, masks;
      they were kept in the hall of the house, in niches appropriated for their reception, and were
      brought forth on occasions of funerals, together with their robes of office, to impersonate
      the dead. Whoever had such images in his possession was <foreign xml:lang="lat">nobilis</foreign>.”—Riddle, Lat. Dict. v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Imago</foreign>.</note>
     should, the first time that they hold an assembly of the people, take an opportunity of uniting
     thanks to you for your kindness with a panegyric on their ancestors, and in the speech then
     made, some men are, on some occasions, found worthy of the rank of their ancestors. But most
     men only accomplish this,—namely, to make it seem that so vast a debt is due to their
     ancestors, that there is something still left to be paid to their posterity. I, indeed, have no opportunity of speaking before you of my ancestors, not
     because they were not such men as you see me also to be, who am born of their blood, and
     educated in their principles, but because they had never any share of popular praise, or of the
     light of honours conferred by you.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>And of myself I fear lest it may look like arrogance to
     speak, and yet like ingratitude to be silent.
     For it is a very troublesome thing for me myself to enumerate to you the pursuits by which I have earned
     this dignity; and, on the other hand, I cannot possibly be silent about your great kindnesses
     to me. Wherefore I will employ a reasonable moderation in speaking, so as to mention the
     kindness which I have received from you. I will speak slightly of the reasons why I am thought
     to have deserved the greatest honour you can confer, and your singularly favourable judgment of
      me.<gap reason="lost"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p> After a very long interval, almost beyond the memory of our
     times, you have for the first time made me, a new man, consul; and you have opened that rank
     which the nobles have held strengthened by guards, and fenced round in every possible manner,
     in my instance first, and have resolved that it should in future be open to virtue. Nor have
     you only made me consul, though that is of itself a most honourable thing, but you have made me
     so in such a way as very few nobles in this city have ever been made consuls before in, and no
     new man whatever before me. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>For, in truth, if you please to recollect, you will find that those new men who have at any
     time been made consuls without a repulse, have been elected after long toil, and on some
     critical emergency, having stood for it many years after they had been praetors, and a good
     deal later than they might have done according to the laws regulating the age of candidates for
     the office; but that those who stood for it in their regular year were not elected without a
     repulse; that I am the only one of all the new men whom we can remember who have stood for the
     consulship the first moment that by law I could,—who have been elected consul the first time
     that I have stood; so that this honour which you have conferred on me, having been sought by me
     at the proper time, appears not to have been filched by me on the occasion of some unpopular
     candidate offering himself,—not to have been gained by long perseverance in asking for it, but
     to have been fairly earned by my worth and dignity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p> This,
     also, is a most honorable thing for me, O Romans, which I mentioned a few minutes ago,—that I
     am the first new man for many years on whom you have conferred this honour,—that you have
     conferred it on my first application, in my proper year. But yet nothing can be more splendid
     or more honourable for me than this circumstance,—that at the comitia at which I was elected
     you delivered not your ballot, <note anchored="true"><persName><surname>Middleton</surname></persName> says (with express reference to this
      passage,) “the method of choosing consuls was not by an open vote, but by a kind of ballot or
      little tickets of wood distributed to the citizens with the names of the candidates severally
      inscribed on each; but in Cicero's case, the people were not content with this secret and
      silent way of testifying their inclinations but before they came to any scrutiny, loudly and
      universally proclaimed Cicero the first consul; so that, as he himself declared in his speech
      to them after his election he was not chosen by the votes of particular citizens, but by the
      common suffrage of the city; nor declared by the voice of the crier, but of the whole Roman
      people.”</note> the vindication of your silent liberty, but your eager voices as the witnesses
     of your good-will towards, and zeal for me. And so it was not the last tribe of the votes, but
     the very first moment of your meeting,—it was not the single voices of the criers, but the
     whole Roman people with one voice that declared me consul. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I think this eminent and unprecedented kindness of yours, O Romans, of great weight as a
     reward for my courage, and as a source of joy to me, but still more calculated to impress me
     with care and anxiety. For, O Romans, many and grave thoughts occupy my mind, which allow me
     but little rest day or night. First, there is anxiety about discharging the duties of the
     consulship which is a difficult and important business to all men, and especially to me above
     all other men; for if I err, I shall obtain no pardon—if I do well, I shall get but little
     praise, and that, too, extorted from unwilling people—if I am in doubt, I have no faithful
     counselors to whom I can apply—if I am in difficulty, I have no sure assistance from the nobles
     on which I can depend.</p></div>
    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But, if I alone were in danger, I would bear it, O Romans, with more equanimity; but there
     appears to me to be some men determined, if they think that I have done anything wrongly not
     only intentionally, but even by chance, to blame all of you for having preferred me to the
     nobles. But I think, O Romans that I ought to endure everything rather than not discharge the
     duties of my consulship in such a manner, as by all my actions and counsels to compel men to
     praise your action and counsel with respect to me. There is also this added to the great labour
     and difficulty which I see before me in discharging the duties of my office, that I have made
     up my mind that I ought not to adopt the same rule and principle of conduct which former
     consuls have; some of whom have carefully avoided all approach to this place, and the sight of
     you, and others have at all events not been very fond of it. But I not only declare in this
     place where it is exceedingly easy to do it, but I said in my very first speech on the first of
     January, in the senate itself, which did not seem likely to be so favourable a place for the
     expression, that I would be a consul in the interests of the people. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p> Nor is it possible for me, knowing, as I do, that I have been made consul,
     not by the zeal of the powerful citizens, nor by the preponderating influence of a few men, but
     by the deliberate judgment of the Roman people, and that, too, in such a way as to be preferred
     to men of the very highest rank, to avoid, both in this magistracy and throughout my whole
     life, devoting myself to the interests of the people. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>When, however, I speak of the interests of the people, I have great need of your wisdom in
     giving the proper meaning and interpretation to this expression. For there is a great error
     abroad, by reason of the treacherous pretences made by some people, who, though they oppose and
     hinder not only the advantage but even the safety of the people, still endeavour by their
     speeches to make men believe them zealous for the interests of the people.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> I, O Romans, know in what condition I received the republic on the first of
     January: full of anxiety, full of fear. There was no evil, no misfortune which the good were
     not dreading and the bad looking out for. Every sort of seditious design against the existing
     constitution of the republic, and against your tranquillity, was said to be in
     contemplation,—some such to have been actually set on foot the moment we were elected consuls.
     All confidence was banished from the forum, not by the stroke of any new calamity, but by the
     general suspicion entertained of the courts of justice, and by the disorder into which they had
     fallen, and by the constant reversal of previous decisions. New authority, extraordinary
     powers, suited not to commanders, but to kings, were supposed to be aimed at.</p></div>
    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And as I did not only suspect these things, but clearly saw them, (for indeed there was no
     secret made of what was being done,) I said in the senate that I would in this magistracy prove
     a consul devoted to the interests of the people. For what is there so advantageous to the
     people as peace? in which not only the animals to whom nature has given sense, but even the
     houses and fields appear to me to rejoice. What is so advantageous to the people as liberty?
     which is sought out and preferred to everything, not only by men, but even by the beasts. What
     is so advantageous to the people as tranquillity? which is so delightful a thing, that both you
     and your ancestors, and every brave man, thinks it worth his while to encounter the greatest
     labours, in order at length to enjoy tranquillity, particularly if he be a man in command, or a
     man of high rank. And we, therefore, are bound to give great praise and to show great gratitude
     to our ancestors, because it is owing to their labours that we are able to enjoy tranquillity
     without risk. How then can I avoid being devoted to the interests of the people, O Romans, when
     I see all these things,—our peace abroad, and the liberty which belongs to the Roman race and
     Roman name, and our domestic tranquillity, and everything, in short, which is considered by you
     as valuable or honourable, entrusted to the good faith, and, as it were, to the protection of
     my consulship? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> And, O Romans, a promised liberality which,
     however you may be encouraged by words to expect it, cannot be performed by any possible means
     without exhausting the treasury, ought not to appear to you an agreeable measure, or one
     calculated to promote your real interests. Nor are the disturbances of the courts of justice,
     and the reversals of judicial decisions, and the restoration of convicted persons to be
     considered as measures advantageous to the people; for they are rather the preludes to the
     total ruin of cities whose affairs are already in a falling and almost desperate state. Nor, if
     any men promise lands to the Roman people, or if they hold out to you, under false pretences,
     hopes of such things, while in secret they are keeping entirely different objects in view, are
     they to be thought devoted to the true interests of the people. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>For I will speak the truth, O Romans; I cannot find fault with the general principle of an
     agrarian law, for it occurs to my mind that two most illustrious men, two most able men, two
     men most thoroughly attached to the Roman people, Tiberius and Caius Gracchus, established the
     people on public domains which had previously been occupied by private individuals. Nor am I a
     consul of such opinions as to think it wrong, as most men do, to praise the Gracchi; by whose
     counsels, and wisdom, and laws, I see that many parts of the republic have been greatly
     strengthened. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, when at the very beginning, I,
     being the consul elect, was informed that the tribunes elect of the people were drawing up an
     agrarian law, I wished to ascertain what their plans were. In truth, I thought that, since we
     were both to act as magistrates in the same year, it was right that there should be some union
     between us, for the purpose of governing the republic wisely and successfully. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> When I wished to join them familiarly in conversation, I was shut out;
     their projects were concealed from me: and when I assured them that, if the law appeared to me
     to be advantageous to the Roman people, I would assist them in it and promote it, still they
     rejected this liberality of mine with scorn, and said that I could not possibly be induced to
     approve of any liberal measures. I ceased to offer myself to them, lest perchance my
     importunity should seem to them treacherous or impudent. In the meantime they did not cease to
     have secret meetings among themselves, to invite some private individuals to them, and to
     choose night and darkness for their clandestine deliberations. And what great alarm this
     conduct of theirs caused us, you may easily divine by your own conjectures founded on the
     anxiety which you yourselves experienced at that time. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>At last the tribunes of the people enter on their office. The assembly to be convened by
     Publius Rullus was anxiously looked for, both because he was the chief mover of the agrarian
     law, and because he behaved with more violence than his colleagues. From the moment that he was
     elected tribune, he put on another expression of countenance, another tone of voice, a
     different gait; he went about in an old-fashioned dress, without any regard to neatness in his
     person, with longer hair and a more abundant beard than before; so that he seemed by his eyes
     and by his whole aspect to be threatening every one with the power of the tribunes, and to be
     meditating evil to the republic. I was waiting in expectation of his law and of the assembly.
     At first no law at all is proposed. He orders an assembly to be summoned as his first measure.
     Men flock to it with the most eager expectation. He makes a long enough speech, expressed in
     very good language. There was one thing which seemed to me bad, and that was, that out of all
     the crowd there present, not one man could be found who was able to understand what he meant.
     Whether he did this with any insidious design, or whether that is the sort of eloquence in
     which he takes pleasure, I do not know. Still, if there was any one in the assembly cleverer
     than another, he suspected that he was intending to say something or other about an agrarian
     law. At last, after I had been elected consul, the law is proposed publicly. By my order
     several clerks meet at one time, and bring me an accurate copy of the law.</p></div>
    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I assure you with the most real sincerity, O Romans, that I applied myself to the reading and
     understanding of this law with these feelings, that if I had thought it well adapted to your
     interests, and advantageous to them, I would have been a chief mover in and promoter of it. For
     the consulship has not, either by nature, or by any inherent difference of object, or by any
     instinctive hatred, any enmity against the tribuneship, though good and fearless consuls have
     often opposed seditious and worthless tribunes of the people, and though the power of the
     tribunes has sometimes opposed the capricious licentiousness of the consuls. It is not the
     dissimilarity of their powers, but the disunion of their minds, that creates dissension between
     them. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, I applied myself to the consideration of
     the law with these feelings, that I wished to find it calculated to promote your interests, and
     such an one as a consul who was really, not in word only, devoted to the people; might honestly
     and cheerfully advocate. And from the first clause of the proposed law to the last, O Romans, I
     find nothing else thought of, nothing else intended, nothing else aimed at, but to appoint ten
     kings of the treasury, of the revenues, of all the provinces, of the whole of the republic, of
     the kingdoms allied with us, of the free nations confederate with us—ten lords of the whole
     world, under the pretence and name of an agrarian law.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> I do assert to you, O Romans, that by this beautiful
     agrarian law, by this law calculated solely for the good of the people, nothing whatever is
     given to you, everything is sacrificed to a few particular men; that lands are displayed before
     the eyes of the Roman people, liberty is taken away from them; that the fortunes of some
     private individuals are increased, the public wealth is exhausted; and lastly, which is the
     most scandalous thing of all, that by means of a tribune of the people, whom our ancestors
     designed to be the protector and guardian of liberty, kings are being established in the city.
     And when I have shown to you all the grounds for this statement, if they appear to you to be
     erroneous, I will yield to your authority, I will abandon my own opinion, but if you become
     aware that plots are laid against your liberty, under a pretence of liberality, then do not
     hesitate, now that you have a consul to assist you, to defend that liberty which was earned by
     the sweat and blood of your ancestors, and handed down to you, without any trouble on your
     part. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>The first clause in this agrarian law is one by which, as they think, you are a little
     proved, to see with what feelings you can bear a diminution of your liberty. For it orders “the
     tribune of the people who has passed this law to create ten decemvirs by the votes of seventeen
     tribes, so that whomsoever a majority consisting of nine tribes elects, shall be a <foreign xml:lang="lat">decemvir</foreign>.” </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p> On this I ask, on what
     account the framer of this law has commenced his law and his measures in such a manner, as to
     deprive the Roman people of its right of voting? As often as agrarian laws have been passed,
     commissioners, and <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumvirs</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="lat">quinquevirs</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="lat">decemvirs</foreign> have been appointed. I
     ask this tribune of the people, who is so attached to the people, whether they were ever
     created except by the whole thirty-five tribes? In truth, as it is proper for every power, and
     every command, and every charge which is committed to any one, to proceed from the entire Roman
     people, so especially ought those to do so, which are established for any use and advantage of
     the Roman people; as that is a case in which they all together choose the man who they think
     will most study the advantage of the Roman people, and in which also each individual among them
     by his own zeal and his own vote assists to make a road by which he may obtain some individual
     benefit for himself. This is the tribune to whom it has occurred above all others to deprive
     the Roman people of their suffrages, and to invite a few tribes not by any fixed condition of
     law, but by the kindness of lots drawn, and by chance, to usurp the liberties belonging to all.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> “Also in the same manner,” it says in the second clause,
     “as in the comitia for the election of a Pontifex Maximus.” He did not perceive even this, that
     our ancestors did really study the good of the people so much, that, though it was not lawful
     for that office to be conferred by the people, on account of the religious ceremonies then
     used, still, they chose, in order to do additional honour to the priesthood, that the sanction
     of the people should be asked for it. And Cnaeus Domitius, a tribune of the people, and a most
     eminent man, passed the same law with respect to the other priesthoods; enacting, because the
     people, on account of the requirements of religion, could not confer the priesthoods, that a
     small half of the people should be invited; and that whoever was selected by that half should
     be chosen into their body by the sacred college. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> See now how
     great a difference there is between Cnaeus Domitius, a tribune of the people, a man of the
     highest rank, and Publius Rullus, who tried your patience, as I imagine, when he said that he
     was a noble. Domitius contrived a way by which, as far as he was able, as far as was consistent
     with the laws of men and of gods, he might confer on a portion of the people what could not be
     done by any regular proceeding on the part of the entire people. But this man, when there was a
     thing which had always belonged to the people, which no one had ever impaired, and which no one
     had ever altered,—the principle, namely, that those who were to assign lands to the people,
     should receive a kindness from the Roman people before they conferred one on it; that this man
     has endeavoured entirely to take away from you, and to wrest out of your hands. The one
     contrived somehow or other to give that which could not really be given formally to the people;
     the other endeavours somehow or other to take away from them by manoeuvre, what could not
     possibly be taken from them by direct power. </p></div>
    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Some one will ask what was his purpose in such injustice and such impudence. He was not
     without an object. But good faith towards the Roman people, just feelings towards you and your
     liberty, he was utterly without. For he orders the man who has passed the law to hold the
     comitia for the creation of the decemvirs. I will state the case more plainly. Rullus, as a man
     far from being covetous or ambitious, orders Rullus to hold the comitia. I do not find fault
     yet. I see that others have done the same thing. Now see what is the object of this, which no
     one else ever did, with respect to the smaller half of the people. He will hold the comitia; he
     wishes to have the appointment of those officers for whom kingly power is sought to be procured
     by this law. He himself will not entrust it to the entire people, nor do those who were the
     original instigators of these designs think it ought to be entrusted to them. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p> The same Rullus will cast lots between the tribes. He, happy man, will pick
     out the tribes which he prefers. Those decemvirs whom the nine tribes selected by this same
     Rullus may choose to appoint, we shall have, as I shall presently show, for our absolute
     masters in everything. And they, that they may appear to be grateful men, and to be mindful of
     kindness, will confess that they are indebted to the leading men of these nine tribes. But as
     for the other six-and-twenty tribes, there will be nothing which they will not think that they
     have a right to refuse them. Who are they, then, whom he means to have elected tribunes? In the
     first place, himself. How can that be lawful? For there are old laws, and those too not laws
     made by consuls, if you think that that makes any difference, but made by tribunes, very
     pleasing and agreeable to you and to your ancestors. There is the Licinian law, and the second
     Aebutian law; which excepts not only the man who has caused a law to be passed concerning any
     commission or power, but also all his colleagues and all his connections, and incapacitates
     them from being appointed to any power or commission so established. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p> In truth, if you consult the interests of the people, remove yourself from
     all suspicion of any advantage to yourself; allow the power to accrue to others, gratitude for
     the good you have done must be enough for yourself. For such conduct as this is scarcely
     becoming in a free people, it is scarcely consistent with your spirit and dignity. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Who passed the law? Rullus. Who prevented the greater portion of the people from having a
     vote? Rullus. Who presided over the comitia? Who summoned to the election whatever tribes he
     pleased, having drawn the lots for them without any witness being present to see fair play? Who
     appointed whatever decemvirs he chose? This same Rullus. Whom did he appoint chief of the
     decemvirs? Rullus. I hardly believe that he could induce his own slaves to approve of this;
     much less you, who are the masters of all nations. Therefore, the most excellent laws will be
     repealed by this law without the least suspicion of the fact. He will seek for a commission for
     himself by virtue of his own law; he will hold comitia, though the greater portion of the
     people is stripped of their votes; he will appoint whomsoever he pleases, and himself among
     them; and forsooth he will not reject his own colleagues, the backers of this agrarian law by
     whom the first place in the unpopularity which may possibly arise from drawing the law, and
     from having his name at the head of it, has indeed been conceded to him, but the profit from
     the whole business, they, who in the hope of it are placed in this position, reserve to
     themselves in equal shares with him. <note anchored="true">The last four lines of this
      paragraph are very corrupt in the original, and there is a good deal of variety in the
      readings.</note></p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But now take notice of the diligence of the man, if indeed
     you think that Rullus contrived this, or that it is a thing which could possibly have occurred
     to Rullus. Those men who first projected these measures saw, that, if you had the power of
     making your selection out of the whole people, whatever the matter might be in which good
     faith, integrity, virtue, and authority were required, you would beyond all question entrust it
     to Cnaeus Pompeius as the chief manager. In truth, after you had chosen one man out of all the
     citizens, and appointed him to conduct all your wars against all nations by land and sea, they
     saw plainly that it was most natural that, when you were appointing decemvirs, whether it was
     to be looked on as committing a trust to, or conferring an honour on a man, you would commit
     the business to him, and most reasonable that he should have this compliment paid him.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, an exception is made by this law, mentioning not
     youth, nor any legal impediment, nor any command or magistracy, which might be encumbered with
     obstacles arising either from the business with which it was already loaded, or from the laws.
     There is not even an exception made in the case of any convicted person, to prevent his being
     made a <foreign xml:lang="lat">decemvir</foreign>. Cnaeus Pompeius is excepted and disabled from
     being elected a colleague of Publius Rullus (for I say nothing of the rest). For he has worded
     the law so that only those who are present can stand for the office; a clause which was never
     yet found in any other law, not even in the laws concerning those magistrates who are
     periodically elected. But this clause was inserted, in order that if the law passed you might
     not be able to give him a colleague who would be a guardian over him, and a check upon his
     covetousness. <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Here, since I see that you are moved by the dignity of the man, and by the insult put upon
     him by this law, I will return to the assertion that I made at the beginning, that a kingly
     power is being erected, and your liberties entirely taken away by this law. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> Did you think, otherwise, that when a few men had cast the eyes of
     covetousness on all your possessions, they would not in the very first place take care that
     Cnaeus Pompeius should be removed from all power of protecting your liberty, from all power to
     promote, from all commission to watch over, and from all means of protecting your interests?
     They saw, and they see still, that if, through your own imprudence and my negligence, you adopt
     this law, without understanding its effect, you would afterwards, when you were creating
     decemvirs, think it expedient to oppose Cnaeus Pompeius as your defence against all defects and
     wickednesses in the law. And is this a slight argument to you, that these are men by whom
     dominion and power over everything is sought, when you see that he, whom they see will surely
     be the protector of your liberty, is the only one to whom that dignity is denied?</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Now consider what a power is given to the decemvirs, and how
     great is its extent. In the first place be gives the decemvirs the honour of a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>. <note anchored="true">
      <milestone unit="para"/>The <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia curiata</foreign>, at which alone a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign> could he passed, was a meeting of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">populus</foreign> of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, assembled
       in its tribes of houses; and no member of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">plebs</foreign> could
       vote at such a meeting. They met principally for the sake of confirming some ordinance of the
       senate; a <foreign xml:lang="lat">senatus consultum</foreign> was an indispensable
       preliminary, and with regard to elections and laws, they had merely the power of confirming
       or rejecting what the senate had already decreed. The <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex
        curiata</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="lat">de imperio</foreign>),which was the same as the
        <foreign xml:lang="lat">auctoritas patrum</foreign>, was necessary in order to confer upon
       the dictator, the consuls, and the other magistrates the <foreign xml:lang="lat">imperium</foreign> or military command. The <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia
        curiata</foreign> were held by the patrician magistrates, and they voted by their
       curies.
      <milestone unit="para"/>The <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia centuriata</foreign> were the assembly of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">populus</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat">plebs</foreign> together, and
       they voted by their centuries by ballot.
      <milestone unit="para"/>The <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia tributa</foreign> were not established till B. C. <date when="-0491">491</date>. They were an assembly of the people according to the local tribes
       into which the <foreign xml:lang="lat">Plebs</foreign> was originally divided. No
       qualification of birth or property was necessary to enable a them to vote in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia tributa</foreign>. They were summoned by the <foreign xml:lang="lat">tribuni plebis</foreign>, who were also the presiding magistrates in general; but the
       consuls or praetors might preside if they were convoked for the election of inferior
       magistrates, such as the quaestor, propraetor, or proconsul. Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 274, v.
        <foreign xml:lang="lat">Comitia</foreign>, q. v. 
     </note> But this is unheard-of and absolutely without precedent, that a magistracy should be
     conferred by a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign> on a man who has not previously
     received it in some comitia. He orders the law to be brought in by that praetor who is
     appointed first praetor. But how? In order that these men may receive the decemvirate whom the
     people has elected. He has forgotten that none have been elected by the common people. Here is
     a pretty fellow to bind the whole world with laws, who does not recollect in the third clause
     what is set down in the second! This, too, is quite plain; both what privileges you have
     received from your ancestors, and what is left to you by this tribune of the people. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Our ancestors chose that you should give your votes twice about every magistrate. For as a
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">centuriata lex</foreign>
     <note anchored="true">This and the preceding chapter are exceedingly obscure, and almost
      unintelligible to us; perhaps also the text is a little corrupt. Manutius says, “An
      exceedingly difficult passage, which has perplexed men of the greatest ability and learning.”
      His explanation is as follows: “The ancient Romans had chosen that the people should decide on
      the election of every magistrate in two <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>; but the
      magistracies are distinguished into patrician and plebeian; the patrician magistrates are the
      quaestor, the curule aedile, the praetor, the consul, and the censor; the plebeian are the
      tribune of the people, the aedile of the people, and others. But there were two <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> first about the patrician magistrates before the plebeian
      ones were elected, namely the <foreign xml:lang="lat">centuriata comitia</foreign>, and the
       <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiata</foreign>. I except the censors, who, although they were
      patrician magistrates, still were elected by one <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>
      only, the <foreign xml:lang="lat">centuriata</foreign>. But when the plebeian magistrates were
      elected, then the <foreign xml:lang="lat">tributa comitia</foreign> succeeded to the place of
      the <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiata</foreign>, for the <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiata</foreign>
      had nothing to do with the plebeian magistrates. For they were instituted for the sake of the
      patrician magistrates long before the origin of the plebeian ones. Some one may say, Why were
      not the <foreign xml:lang="lat">centuriata</foreign> taken away for the same reason, as they
      were instituted by king Servius when there were not yet any plebeian magistrates? The answer
      is, In order that there might be some <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> held with
      proper auspices at which the patrician magistrates might be created, for the auspices were not
      taken at the <foreign xml:lang="lat">tributa comitia</foreign>. As, therefore, in the case of
      the patrician magistrates, (with the exception, as I have said before, of the censor,) the
      people gave their votes first in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">centuriata comitia</foreign> and
      then in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiata</foreign>, before the plebeian magistrates were
      elected; so, when the plebeian magistrates were elected, the same people voted in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">centuriata</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat">tributa
      comitia</foreign>.”</note> was passed for the censors, and a <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiata
      lex</foreign> for the other patrician magistrates, by this means a decision was come to a
     second time about the same men, in order that the people might have an opportunity of
     correcting what they had done, if they repented of the honour they had conferred on any one.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p> Now, because you have preserved the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia centuriata</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat">tributa</foreign>, the <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiata</foreign> have remained only for the sake of the auspices. But this
     tribune of the people, because he saw that no man could possibly have any authority conferred
     on him without the authority of the burghers <note anchored="true">The Latin terms are <foreign xml:lang="lat">populus</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat">plebs</foreign>. For the best
      account of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">populus</foreign> to be found in a small space, see
      Smith's Dict. Ant. p. 726, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Patricii</foreign>; and consult the same
      admirable book, p. 765, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Plebes</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="lat">plebs</foreign>. The word <foreign xml:lang="lat">potestas</foreign>, which I have translated
      “authority,” means strictly only civil authority, in opposition to <foreign xml:lang="lat">imperium</foreign>, military command.</note> or of the commonalty, confirmed that authority
     which he proposed to give by the <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiata comitia</foreign>, with which
     you have nothing to do, and took away the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia tributa</foreign>
     which belonged to you. So, though your ancestors intended you to decide at two <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> about each magistrate, this man, so attached to the interests
     of the people, did not leave the people the power of even one <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p> But just note the scrupulousness and
     the diligence of the man. He saw, and was thoroughly aware, that without a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign> the decemvirs could not have authority, since they were
     elected by only nine tribes. So he directs that there should be a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex
      curiata</foreign> passed about them, and orders the praetor to propose it. How ridiculous such
     a contrivance was, it is no business of mine to say. For he orders that “he who has been
     elected first praetor, shall propose a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>; but if he
     be able to propose it, then the last praetor shall do it.” So that he seems either to have been
     playing the fool in this business, or else to have been aiming at something I know not what.
     But, however, let us pass over this, which is either so perverse, or so ridiculous, or so
     malicious and cunning, as to be unintelligible, and return to the scrupulousness of the man.He sees that nothing can be done by the decemvirs except by a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>What was to happen afterwards, if a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign> were not passed? Remark the ingenuity of the man. “Then,”
     says he, “the decemvirs shall be in the same condition as those who are appointed in the
     strictest accordance with the law.” If this can be brought about, that, in this city which is
     far superior to all other states in its rights of liberty, any one may be able to obtain either
     military command or civil authority without the sanction of any <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>, then what is the necessity for ordering in the third chapter that some one
     shall propose a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>, when in the fourth chapter you
     permit men to have the same rights without a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>,
     which they would have if they were elected by the burghers according to the strictest form of
     law? Kings are being appointed, O Romans, not decemvirs; and they are starting with such
     beginnings and on such foundations, that the whole of your rights, and powers, and liberties
     are destroyed not only from the moment that they begin to act, but from the moment that they
     are appointed.</p></div>
    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But remark how carefully he preserves the rights of the tribunitian power. The consuls are
     often interrupted in proposing a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>, by the
     intercession of the tribunes of the people. Not that we complain that the tribunes should have
     this power; only, if any one uses it in a random and inconsiderate manner, we form our own
     opinion. But this tribune of the people, by his <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>,
     which the praetor is to bring forward, takes away the power of intercession. And while he is
     made to be blamed for causing the tribunitian power to be diminished by his instrumentality, he
     is also to be laughed at, because a consul, if he be not invested with the authority by a
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign>, has no power to interfere in military affairs;
     and yet he gives this man whom he prohibits from interceding, the very same power, even if the
     veto be interposed, as if a <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex curiata</foreign> had been passed. So
     that I am at a loss to understand either why he prohibits the intercession, or why he thinks
     that any one will intercede; as the intercession will only prove the folly of the intercessor,
     and will not hinder the business. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Let there then be decemvirs, appointed neither by the genuine <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>,—that is to say, by the votes of the people,—nor by that <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> convened in appearance, to keep up an ancient custom, by the
     thirty lictors for the sake of the auspices. <note anchored="true">“In after times, when the
       <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia curiata</foreign> were little more than a matter of form,
      their suffrages were represented by the thirty lictors of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiae</foreign>, whose duty it was to summon the <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiae</foreign>
      when the meetings actually took place.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 273 a, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Comitia</foreign>.</note> See now, also, how much greater honours he confers on these men
     who have received no authority from you, than we have received, to whom you have given the most
     ample authority, He orders the decemvirs, <note anchored="true">The Latin has, “<foreign xml:lang="lat">decemviri pullarii</foreign>”. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Pullarius</foreign> was
      the officer appointed to feed and take care of the sacred chickens that were kept for the
      purpose of taking the auspices; and much was inferred from the way in which they took their
      food, or perhaps refused it.</note> who have the care of the auspices, to take auspices for
     the sake of conducting the colonies. “According,” says he, “to the same right which the
     triumvirs had by the Sempronian law.” Do you venture, O Rullus, even to make mention of the
     Sempronian law? and does not that law itself remind you that these triumvirs have been created
     by the suffrages of the tribes? And while you are <pb n="228"/> very far
     removed from the justice and modesty of Tiberius Gracchus, do you think that a law made on so
     different a principle ought to have the same authority? </p></div>
    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Besides all this, he gives them authority praetorian in name, but kingly in reality. He
     describes their power, as a power for five years; but he makes it perpetual. For he strengthens
     it with such bulwarks and defences that it will be quite impossible to deprive them of it
     against their own consent. Then he adorns them with apparitors, and secretaries, and clerks,
     and criers, and architects; besides that, with mules, and tents, and centuries, <note anchored="true">There is, no doubt, some corruption here in the text.</note> and all sorts of
     furniture; he draws money for their expenses from the treasury; he supplies them with more
     money from the allies; he appoints them two hundred surveyors from the equestrian body every
     year as their personal attendants, and also as ministers and satellites of their power. You
     have now, O Romans, the form and very appearance of tyrants; you see all the ensigns of power,
     but not yet the power itself. For, perhaps, some one may say, “Well, what harm do all those
     men, secretary, lictor, crier, and chicken-feeder do me?” I will tell you. These things are of
     such a nature that the man who has them without their being conferred by your vote, must seem
     either a monarch with intolerable power, or if he assumes them as a private individual, a
     madman.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Just see what great authority they are invested with, and
     you will say that it is not the insanity of private individuals, but the immoderate arrogance
     of kings. First of all, they are entrusted with boundless power of acquiring enormous sums of
     money out of your revenues, not by farming them but by alienating them. In the next place, they
     are allowed to pursue an inquiry into the conduct of every country and of every nation, without
     any bench of judges; to punish without any right of appeal being allowed; and to condemn
     without there being any means of procuring a reversal of their sentence. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p> They will be able for five years to sit in judgment on the consuls, or even
     on the tribunes of the people themselves; but all that time no one will be able to sit in
     judgment on them. They will be allowed to fill magisterial offices; but they will not be
     allowed to be prosecuted. They will have power to purchase lands, from whomsoever they choose,
     whatever they choose, and at whatever price they choose. They are allowed to establish new
     colonies, to recruit old ones, to fill all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> with
     their colonists; they have absolute authority for visiting every province, for depriving free
     people of their lands, for giving or taking away kingdoms, whenever they please. They may be at
      <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> when it is convenient to them; but they have a
     right also to wander about wherever they like with supreme command, and with a power of sitting
     in judgment on everything. They are allowed to put an end to all criminal trials; to remove
     from the tribunals whoever they think fit; to decide by themselves on the most important
     matters; to delegate their power to a quaestor; to send about surveyors; and to ratify whatever
     the surveyor has reported to that single decemvir by whom he has been sent.</p></div>
    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>It is a defect in my language, O Romans, when I call this power a kingly power. For in truth,
     it is something much more considerable; for there never was any kingly power that, if it was
     not defined by some express law, was not at least understood to be subject to certain
     limitations. But this power is absolutely unbounded; it is one within which all kingly powers,
     and your own imperial authority, which is of such wide extent, and all other powers, whether
     freely exercised by your permission, or existing only by your tacit countenance, are, by
     express permission of the law, comprehended. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>The first thing which is given to them is, a liberty of selling everything concerning the
     sale of which resolutions of the senate were passed in the consulship of Marcus Tullius and
     Cnaeus Cornelius or afterwards. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p> Why is this so obscure and
     so concealed? What is the meaning of it? Could not those matters concerning which the senate
     passed resolutions, be mentioned in the law by name? There are two reasons for this obscurity,
     O Romans; one, a reason of modesty, if there can be any modesty in such inordinate impudence;
     the other, a reason of wickedness. For it does not dare to name those things which the senate
     resolved were to he sold, mentioning them by name; for they are public places in the city, they
     are shrines, which since the restoration of the tribunitian power no one has touched, and which
     our ancestors partly intended to be refuges in times of danger in the heart of the city. But
     all these things the decemvirs will sell by this law of this tribune of the people. Besides
     them, there will be Mount Gaurus; besides that, there will be the osier-beds at <placeName key="perseus,Minturnae">Minturnae</placeName>; besides them, that very salable road to
      <placeName key="perseus,Herculaneum">Herculaneum</placeName>, a road of many delights and of
     considerable value; and many other things which the senate considered it advisable to sell on
     account of the straits to which the treasury was reduced, but which the consuls did not sell on
     account of the unpopularity which would have attended such a measure. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p> However, perhaps it is owing to shame that there is no mention of all these
     things in the law. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>What is much more to be guarded against, what is a much more real object of fear, is, that
     great power is permitted to the boldness of these decemvirs of tampering with the public
     documents, and forging decrees of the Senate, which have never been made; as a great many of
     those men who have been consuls of late years are dead. Unless, perhaps, I may be told, that it
     is not reasonable for you to entertain any suspicions of their audacity, for whose cupidity the
     whole world appears too narrow.</p></div>
    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>You see now one kind of sale, which I am aware appears very important to you; but pray give
     your attention to what follows, and you will see that this is only a kind of step and road to
     other measures. “Whatever lands, whatever places, whatever buildings.” What is there besides?
     There is much property in slaves, in cattle, in bullion, in money, in ivory, in robes, in
     furniture, in all sorts of other things. What shall that say? Did he think it would cause
     unpopularity to name all these things? He was not afraid of unpopularity. What then was his
     motive? He thought the catalogue a long one, and he was afraid of passing over anything; so he
     wrote in addition, “or anything else;” by which brief formula you see that nothing can be
     omitted. Whatever, therefore, there is out of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,
     that has been made the property of the Roman people by Lucius Sulla and Quintus Pompeius in
     their consulships, or afterwards, that he orders the decemvirs to sell. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p> By this clause, I say, O Romans, that all nations, and people, and provinces,
     and kingdoms, are given up and handed over to the dominion, and judgment, and power of the
     decemvirs. This is the first thing; for I ask what place there is anywhere in the world which
     the decemvirs may not be able to say has been made the property of the Roman people? For, when
     the same person who has made the assertion is also to judge of the truth of it, what is there
     which he may not say, when he is also the person to decide in the question? It will be very
     convenient to say, that <placeName key="tgn,7016140">Pergamus</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Smyrna">Smyrna</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,7002359">Tralles</placeName>,
     and <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Cyzicus">Cyzicus</placeName>, and, in short,
     all <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, which has been recovered since the
     consulship of Lucius Sulla and Quintus Pompeius, has become the property of the Roman people.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus"><p>Will language fail him in which to assert such a doctrine? or, when the same person makes the
     statement and judges of the truth of it, will it be impossible to induce him to give a false
     decision? or, if he is unwilling to pass sentence on <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, will he not estimate at his own price its release from the dread of
     condemnation? 
     What will he say—(and it is quite impossible
     for any one to argue against this, since it has been already settled and decided by you, and
     since we have already voted it to be our inheritance,)—what will he say to the kingdom of
      <placeName key="tgn,7016608">Bithynia</placeName>? which has undoubtedly become the public
     property of the Roman people. Is there any reason why the decemvirs should not sell all the
     lands, and cities, and military stations and harbours, and in short all <placeName key="tgn,7016608">Bithynia</placeName>? <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>What will they do at <placeName key="tgn,7002672">Mitylene</placeName>? which has undoubtedly
     become yours, O Romans, by the laws of war and by the rights of victory; a city both by nature
     and situation, and by the description of its houses, and by its general beauty, most eminently
     remarkable; and its lands are pleasant and productive. That city, forsooth, comes under the
     same head. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p> What will become of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, and of all <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>? How much it is out of sight! how completely is it hidden! how stealthily
     is it abandoned entirely to the decemvirs! For who is there among you who is ignorant that that
     kingdom has become the property of the Roman people by the will of king Alexander? Here now I,
     the consul of the Roman people, not only give no decision, but I do not even express my
     opinion. For it appears to me a most important matter not merely to decide oil, but even to
     speak of. I see a man who assures me that the will was certainly made; I know that there is a
     resolution of the senate extant to the effect that it accepted the inheritance; which was
     passed when, after the death of Alexander, we sent ambassadors to <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName>, to recover for the people money which had been deposited there by him.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus"><p> I recollect that Lucius Philippus has often stated these
     things positively in the senate. I see that is agreed upon by all men, that he, who is at this
     present moment in possession of the kingdom, is neither of the royal family nor of any royal
     disposition. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>It is said, on the other hand, that there is no will; that the Roman people ought not to seem
     to covet every kingdom under the sun; that our citizens will emigrate to those regions, on
     account of the fertility of the soil and the abundance of everything which exists there.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p> Will Publius Rullus, with the rest of the decemvirs, his
     colleagues, decide upon so important an affair as this? And which way will he decide? For each
     alternative is so important that it is quite impossible for you to entrust the decision to him,
     or to put up with his sentence. Will he desire to be popular? He will adjudge the kingdom to
     the Roman people. In consequence, he will also, in accordance with his own law, sell <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, and sell <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. He will be found to be the judge, the arbiter, the master, of a most
     wealthy city, and of a most beautiful country; yes, he will be found to be the king of a most
     opulent kingdom. Will he abstain from taking all this? from desiring all this? He will decide
     that <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> belongs to the king; he will by
     his sentence deprive the Roman people of it.</p></div>
    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Now, in the first place, shall decemvirs give a decision about the inheritance of the Roman
     people, when you require centumvirs to judge in the case of private inheritances? In the next
     place, who is to plead the cause of the Roman people? Where is the cause to be tried? Who are
     those decemvirs whom we think likely to adjudge the kingdom of <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> to Ptolemy for nothing? But, if <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> was the object, why did not they at this time
     proceed by the same course which they adopted in the consulship of Lucius Cotta and Lucius
     Torquatus? Why did they not proceed openly, as they did before? Why did they not act as they
     did when they before sought that country, in a straightforward and open manner? Did they, who,
     when they had a fair wind, could not hold their course straight on to the kingdom they coveted,
     think that they could reach <placeName key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> amid
     foul mists and darkness? <note anchored="true">This sentence and the succeeding one are
      considered very corrupt, and there is a great variety of readings proposed; for <foreign xml:lang="lat">qui Etesiis</foreign> some read <foreign xml:lang="lat">quietis iis</foreign>;
      for <foreign xml:lang="lat">directo</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">decreto</foreign>.
       <foreign xml:lang="lat">Unaque</foreign> is quite unintelligible.</note></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p> Just revolve these things in your minds. . . . . Foreign nations can scarcely
     endure our lieutenants, though they are men of but slight authority, when they go on free
     lieutenancies, on account of some private business. For the name of power is a hard one to
     bear, and is dreaded even in ever so inconsiderable a person; because, when they have once left
      <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> they conduct their proceedings not in their own
     name, but in yours. What do you suppose will happen, when those decemvirs wander all over the
     world with their supreme power, and their <foreign xml:lang="lat">faces</foreign>, and their
     chosen band of surveyors? What do you suppose will be the feelings, what the alarm, what the
     actual danger of those unhappy nations? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus"><p> Is there any terror
     in absolute power? they will endure it;—is there any expense entailed by the arrival of such
     men? they will bear it;—are any presents exacted from them? they will not refuse them. But what
     a business is that, O Romans, when a decemvir, who either has come to some city after being
     expected, as a guest, or unexpectedly, as a master, pronounces that very place to which he has
     come, that identical hospitable house in which he is received, to be the public property of the
     Roman people? How great will be the misery of the people if he says that it is so! How great
     will be his own private gain, if he says that it is not! And the same men who desire all this,
     are accustomed sometimes to complain that every land and every sea has been put under the power
     of Cnaeus Pompeius. But are these two cases, the one, of many things being entrusted to a man,
     the other, of everything being sacrificed to him, at all similar? Is there any resemblance
     between a man's being appointed as chief manager of a business requiring toil and labour, and a
     man's having the chief share in booty and gain allotted to him? in a man's being sent to
     deliver allies, and a man's being sent to oppress them? Lastly, if there be airy extraordinary
     honour in question, does it make no difference whether the Roman people confers that honour on
     any one it chooses, or whether he impudently filches it from the Roman people by an underhand
     trick of law?</p></div>
    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>You have now seen how many things and what valuable things the decemvirs are likely to sell
     with the sanction of the law. That is not enough. When they have sated themselves with the
     blood of the allies, and of foreign nations, and of kings, they will then cut the sinews of the
     Roman people; they will lay hands on your revenues; they will break into your treasury. For a
     clause follows, in which he is not content with permitting, if by chance any money should be
     wanting, (which, however, can be amassed in such quantities from the effect of the previous
     clauses, that it ought not to be wanting,) but which actually (as if that was likely to be the
     salvation of you all) orders and compels the decemvirs to sell all your revenues, naming each
     item separately. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p> And do you now read to me in regular order,
     the catalogue of the property of the Roman people which is for sale according to the written
     provisions of this law. A catalogue which I think, in truth, will be miserable and grievous to
     the very crier himself. He is as prodigal a spendthrift with regard to the property of the
     republic, as a private individual is with regard to his own estate, who sells his woods, before
     he sells his vineyards. You hare gone all through <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, now go on into <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>. There is
     nothing in that province which your ancestors have left to you as your own property, either in
     the towns, or in the fields, which he does not order to be sold. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p> All that property, which, having been gained by their recent victory, your
     ancestors left to you in the cities and territories of the allies, as both a bond of peace and
     a monument of war, will you now, though you received it from them, sell it at this man's
     instigation? Here for a moment I seem, O Romans, to move your feelings, while I make plain to
     you the plots when they think have escaped every one's notice, as having been laid by them
     against the dignity of Cnaeus Pompeius. And, I beseech you, pardon me if I am forced to make
     frequent mention of that man's name. You, O Romans, imposed this character on me, two years
     ago, in this very same place, and bound me to share with you in the protection of his dignity
     during his absence, in whatever manner I could. I have hitherto done all that I could, not
     because I was persuaded to it by my intimacy with him, nor from any hope of honour; or of any
     most honourable dignity; which I have gained by your means, in his absence, though no doubt
     with his perfect goodwill. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus"><p> Wherefore, when I perceive that
     nearly the whole of this law is made ready, as if it were an engine, for the object of
     overthrowing his power, I will both resist the designs of the men who have contrived it, and I
     will enable you not only to perceive, but to be entire masters of the whole plot which I now
     see in preparation. <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>He orders everything to be sold which belonged to the people of <placeName key="tgn,7002378">Attalia</placeName>, and of Phaselus, and of <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>, and the land of Agera, of Orindia, and of Gedusa. All this became your
     property owing to the campaigns and victory of that most illustrious man, Publius Servilius. He
     adds the royal domain of <placeName key="tgn,7016608">Bithynia</placeName>, which is at present
     farmed by the public contractors; after that, he adds the lands belonging to Attalus in the
      <placeName key="tgn,7012057">Chersonesus</placeName>; and those in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, which belonged to king Philip or king Perses; which
     also were let out to contractors by the censors, and which are a most certain revenue.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus"><p> He also puts up to auction the lands of the Corinthians,
     rich and fertile lands; and those of the Cyrenaeans, which did belong to Apion; and the lands
     in <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName> near Carthagena; and those in <placeName key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName> near the old <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> itself—a place which Publius Africanus consecrated, not on account of
     any religious feeling for the place itself and for its antiquity, but in accordance with the
     advice of his counselors, in order that the place itself might bear record of the disasters of
     that people which had contended with us for the empire of the world. But Scipio was not as
     diligent as Rullus is; or else, perhaps, he could not find a purchaser for that place. However,
     among these royal districts, taken in our ancient wars by the consummate valour of our
     generals, he adds the royal lands of Mithridates, which were in <placeName key="tgn,7016760">Paphlagonia</placeName>, and in <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>, and in
      <placeName key="tgn,6003016">Cappadocia</placeName>, and orders the decemvirs to sell them.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p> Is it so indeed? when no law has been passed to that
     effect, when the words of our commander-in-chief have not yet been heard, when the war is not
     yet over, when king Mithridates, having lost his army, having been driven from his kingdom, is
     even now planning something against us in the most distant corners of the earth, and while he
     is still defended by the Maeotis, and by those marshes, and by the narrow defiles through which
     the only passes lie in those countries, and by the height of the mountains, from the invincible
     band of Cnaeus Pompeius; when our general is actually engaged in the war against him; and while
     the name of war still lingers in those districts; shall the decemvirs sell those lands over
     which the military command and civil authority of Cnaeus Pompeius still extends and ought to
     extend, according to the principles and usages of our ancestors? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus"><p> And, I make no doubt, Publius Rullus (for he now conducts himself in such a
     manner as shows that he already fancies himself a decemvir elect) will hasten to attend that
     auction in preference to every other. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>He, forsooth, before he arrives in <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>, will send
     letters to Cnaeus Pompeius, of which I suppose a copy has already been composed in these
     terms:—“Publius Servilius Rullus, tribune of the people, decemvir, to Cnaeus Pompeius, the son
     of Cnaeus, greeting.” I do not suppose that he will add “Magnus;” for it is not likely that he
     will grant him by a word that dignity which he is endeavouring to diminish. “I wish you to take
     care to meet me at <placeName key="perseus,Sinope">Sinope</placeName>, and to bring me
     assistance, while I am selling, in accordance with the provisions of my law, those lands which
     you acquired by your labour.” Or will he not invite Pompeius? Will he sell the spoils of the
     general in his own province? Just place before your eyes Rullus, in <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>, holding his auction between your camp and that of the
     enemy, and knocking down lands surrounded by his beautiful band of surveyors. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus"><p> Nor does the insult consist solely in this, though this is very preposterous,
     and very unprecedented, that anything which has been acquired in war, while the general is
     still carrying on the war, should be sold, or even let. But these men have something more in
     view than mere insult. They hope, if it is allowed to the enemies of Cnaeus Pompeius, not only
     to stroll about other countries, but even to come to his very army with absolute authority,
     with a power of sitting as judges in every case, with boundless power, and with countless sums
     of money, that some plot may be laid against him himself; and that something may be taken from
     his army, or power, or renown. They think that, if the army reposes any hope in Cnaeus Pompeius
     with respect to either lands, or any other advantages, it will do so no longer when it sees
     that the supreme power in all those matters is transferred to the decemvirs. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus"><p> I am not concerned at those men being so foolish, as to hope for these
     things; and so impudent, as to attempt to cause them. What I do complain of is, that I am so
     much despised by them, that they should select the period of my consulship, of all times in the
     world, for seeking to bring about such prodigious absurdities. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>And in the sale of all these lands and houses leave is given to the decemvirs “to hold their
     sales in whatever places they think fit.” Oh their perverted senses! Oh their licentiousness,
     so necessary to be checked! Oh their profligate and wicked intentions! <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>It is not lawful to let the revenues anywhere except in this city, in this very spot, in the
     presence of this assembly here present. Shall it be lawful for your own property to be sold and
     alienated from you for ever in the darkness or <placeName key="tgn,7016760">Paphlagonia</placeName>, or in the deserts of <placeName key="tgn,6003016">Cappadocia</placeName>? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus"><p> When Lucius Sulla was selling at
     that fatal auction of his the property of citizens who had not been condemned, and when he said
     that he was selling his plunder, still he sold it on this spot where I am standing now; nor did
     he venture to avoid the sight of those men to whose eyes he was so hateful. Shall the decemvirs
     sell your revenues, not only where you yourselves are not witnesses of the sale, but where
     there is not even a public crier present as a spectator? 
    <milestone unit="para"/>Then follows—“All the lands out of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,” without
     any limit as to time, not (as was enacted before) those acquired by Sulla and Pompeius when
     they were consuls. There is an inquiry to be made by the decemvirs, whether the land be private
     or public property; and by this means a heavy tax is laid on the laud. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57" resp="perseus"><p> Who is there who does not see how great a judicial power this is, how
     intolerable, how tyrannical? for them to be able, in whatever places they please, without any
     discussion or formal decision, without any assessors, to confiscate private property, and to
     release public property? In this clause the Recentoric district in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> is excepted; which I am exceedingly delighted is excepted, O Romans, both
     on account of my connection with the people of that district, and because of the justice of the
     exception. But what impudence it is! Those who are the occupiers of the Recentoric district,
     defend themselves on the ground of length of occupation, not of right; they rely on the pity of
     the senate, not on the conditions on which they hold their lands. For they confess that it is
     part of the public domain; but still they say that they ought not to be removed from their
     possessions, and their much-loved homes, and their household gods. But if the Recentoric
     district be private property, why do you except it? But if it be public, where then is the
     justice of allowing other lands, even if they are private lands, to be adjudged to be public,
     and to except this district by name which confesses that it is public property? Therefore the
     land of those men is excepted who have had any means of influencing Rullus; all otter lands,
     wherever they are—without any selection being made, without any examination being instituted by
     the people, without any decision being come to by the senate, are to be sold by the decemvirs.</p></div>
    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is also another profitable exception made in the former chapter according to which
     everything is to be sold. An exception which comprehends those lands which are protected by
     treaty. He heard that this matter was often agitated in the senate, not by me, but by others,
     and sometimes also in this place; that king Hiempsal was in possession of lands on the sea
     coast, which Publius Africanus adjudged to the Roman people; and yet afterwards express
     provision was made respecting them in a treaty, by Caius Cotta, when consul. But, because you
     did not order this treaty to be made, Hiempsal is in fear lest it may not be considered firm
     and properly ratified. What? What sort of proceeding is this? Your decision is not waited for;
     the whole treaty is excepted. It is approved by Rullus. As it limits the power of sale to be
     given to the decemvirs, I am glad of it; as it protects the interests of a king who is our
     friend, I find no fault with it; but my opinion is that the exception was not made for nothing;
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59" resp="perseus"><p> for there is constantly fluttering before those men's eyes
       <persName><surname>Juba</surname></persName>, the king's son, whose purse is every bit as
     long as his hair. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>Even now there scarcely appears to be any place capable of containing such vast heaps of
     money. He increases the sums, he adds to them, he keeps on accumulating. “To whomsoever gold or
     silver comes, from spoils, from money given for crowns, if it has neither been paid into the
     public treasury, nor spent in any monument.” Of that treasure he orders a return to be made to
     the decemvirs, and the treasure is to be paid over to them. By this case you see that an
     investigation even into the conduct of the most illustrious men, who have carried on the wars
     of the Roman people, and that judicial examinations into charges of peculation or extortion,
     are transferred to the decemvirs. They will have a power of deciding what is the value of the
     spoils which have been gained by each individual, what return he has made, and what he has
     left. But this law is laid down for all your generals for the future, that, whoever leaves his
     province, must make a return to these same decemvirs, of how much booty, and spoils, and gold
     given for the purpose of crowns he has. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60" resp="perseus"><p> But here this
     admirable man excepts Cnaeus Pompeius, whom he is so fond of. Whence does this affection so
     sudden and previously unknown originate? for he is excluded from the honour of the decemvirate
     almost by name; his power of deciding judicially, of giving laws, or of making any formal
     inquiry respecting the lands which have been taken by his your, is taken from him; decemvirs
     are sent not only into his province but into his very camp, with military authority, with
     immense sums of money, with unlimited power, and with a right of deciding on everything. His
     rights as a general, which have hitherto always been most jealously preserved to every general
     are for the first time taken from him. But he is excepted as the only one who is not bound to
     make a return of his booty. Does it seem that the real object of this clause is to do honour to
     the man, or to excite a feeling of unpopularity against him? </p></div>
    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Cnaeus Pompeius will make a present of this to Rullus. He has no desire to avail himself of
     that kindness of the law, and of the good-nature of the decemvirs. For if it be just for
     generals not to devote their spoils and booty either to monuments of the immortal gods, or to
     the decorations of the city,—but if they are to carry it all to the decemvirs as their
     masters,—then Pompeius wishes for nothing particular for himself; nothing. He wishes to live
     under the common law, under the same law as the rest. If it be unjust, O Romans—if it be
     shameful, if it be intolerable for these decemvirs to be appointed as comptrollers of all the
     money collected by every body, and as plunderers not only of foreign kings and citizens of
     foreign nations, but of even our own generals, then they do not seem to me to have excepted
     Pompeius for the sake of doing him honour, but to be afraid that he may not be able to put up
     with the same insult as the rest. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62" resp="perseus"><p> But as Pompeius's feelings
     will be these, that he will think it becomes him to bear whatever seems fitting to you; on the
     other hand, if there be anything which you cannot bear, he will take care that you are not long
     compelled to bear it against your will. But the law makes a provision that, “if any money is
     received from any new source of revenue after our consulship, the decemvirs are to be allowed
     to use it.” Moreover, he sees that the new sources of revenue will be those which Pompeius has
     added to the republic. And so, he lets off his spoils, but thinks that it is right for him to
     reap the benefit of all the revenues acquired by his valour. Let then, O Romans, all the money
     which there is in the world conic into the hands of the dictators; let nothing be omitted; let
     every city, every district, every kingdom, and lastly even your own revenues be sold by them;
     let the spoils won by your generals be added to the heap. You see now what enormous, what
     incredible riches are sought to be acquired by your decemvirs by such extensive sales, by so
     many decisions which they have the power to make, and by such unlimited authority over
     everything.</p></div>
    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Now remark their other immense and intolerable gains, in order to understand that this
     popular name of an agrarian law has only been hunted out as a means of gratifying the
     unreasonable avarice of particular men. He orders lands to be bought with this money, to which
     you are to be conducted as colonists. I am not accustomed, O Romans, to speak or men with
     unnecessary harshness unless I am provoked. I wish it were possible for those men to be named
     by me without speaking ill of them, who hope to be themselves appointed decemvirs; and you
     should quickly see what sort of men they are to whom you have committed the power of selling
     and buying everything. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64" resp="perseus"><p> But, that which I have made up my
     mind that I ought not to say, yet you can still form an idea of in your minds. This one thing
     at all events I appear to myself to be able to say with the greatest truth,—that in former
     times when this republic had the Luscini, the Calatini, the Acidini, men adorned not only with
     the honours conferred on them by the people, and by their own great exploits, but also by the
     patience with which they endured poverty; and then also when the Catos, and the Phili, and
     Laelii lived, men whose wisdom and moderation you had obtained a thorough knowledge of in
     public, and private, and forensic, and domestic affairs; still such a charge as this was
     entrusted to no one, so as to allow the same man to be both judge and seller, and to be so for
     five years over the whole world, and also to have power to alienate the lands of the Roman
     people from which their revenues are derived; and when by these means he had amassed a vast sum
     of money according to his own pleasure, without any witness, then he was to buy whatever he
     pleased from any one he pleased. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65" resp="perseus"><p> Now then do you, O Romans,
     commit all these things to these men whom you suspect of aiming at this decemvirate; you will
     find some of them to whom nothing appears sufficient to possess, some to whom nothing seems
     sufficient to squander. <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Here I will not discuss what is sufficiently notorious, O Romans, or argue that it is not a
     custom handed down to you from your ancestors, that lands may be bought from private
     individuals for the purpose of settling portions of the common people in them by the public
     authority; or that there are not many laws by which private individuals have been established
     in the public domains. I will admit that I expected something of this sort from this illiterate
     and ill-mannered tribune of the people; but this most profitable and at the same time most
     discreditable traffic in buying and selling, I have always thought wholly inconsistent with the
     duty of a tribune, wholly inconsistent with the dignity of the Roman people. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66" resp="perseus"><p> He orders that lands be sold. First of all I ask, What lands? in what
     situations? I do not wish the Roman people to be kept in suspense and uncertainty with obscure
     hopes and ignorant expectation. There is the <placeName key="tgn,1031727">Alban</placeName>,
     and the Setino, and the Privernate, and the Fundan, and the Vescine, and the Falernian
     district; there is the district of Linternum, and <placeName key="tgn,7006931">Cuma</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Casinum">Casinum</placeName>. I hear. Going out
     at the other gate there is the Capenate, and Faliscan, and <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> territory; there are the lands of Reati, and <placeName key="perseus,Venafrum">Venafrum</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Allifae">Allifae</placeName>, and Trebula. You have money enough to be able not only to buy all these
     lands and others like them, but even to surround them with a ring fence. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67" resp="perseus"><p> Why do you not define them, nor name them, so that at least the Roman people
     may be able to consider what its own interests are-what is desirable for it—how much trust it
     thinks it desirable to repose in you in the matter of buying and selling things ? I do define
      <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, says he. It is a district sufficiently marked
     out. Indeed, how little difference does it make whether you are led down to the roots of the
     Massic Hill, or into some other part of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, or
     somewhere else! Come, you do not define the exact spot. What do you mean? Do you mean the
     nature of the land? But, says he, the law does say, “which can be ploughed or cultivated.”
     Which can be ploughed or cultivated, he says; not, which has been ploughed or cultivated. Is
     this now a law, or is it an advertisement of some sale of Neratius <note anchored="true">It is
      unknown who this man was. Perhaps some puffing auctioneer.</note>; in whose descriptions
     people used to find such sentences as these:—“Two hundred acres in which an olive garden may be
     made. Three hundred acres where vines can be planted.” Is this what you are going to buy with
     all your countless sums of money,—something which can be ploughed up or cultivated? Why, what
     soil is there so thin and miserable that it cannot be broken up by a plough? or what is there
     which is such a complete bed of stones that the skill of an agriculturist cannot get something
     out of it? Oh but, says he, I cannot name any lands positively, because I touch none against
     the will of the owner. This also is much more profitable than if one took land from a man
     against his will. For a calculation of gain will be entered into with reference to your money,
     and then only will land be sold when the sale is advantageous to both buyer and seller.</p></div>
    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But now see the force of this agrarian law. Even those men who are in occupation of the
     public domains will not quit possession, unless they are tempted by favourable conditions and
     by a large sum of money. Matters are changed. Formerly when mention of an agrarian law was made
     by a tribune of the people, immediately every one who was in occupation of any public lands, or
     who had any possessions the tenure of which was in the least unpopular, began to be alarmed.
     But this law enriches those men with fortunes, and relieves them from unpopularity. For how
     many men, O Romans, do you suppose there are, who are unable to stand under the extent of their
     possessions, who are unable to bear the unpopularity incurred by the ownership of lands granted
     by Sulla? who wish to sell them, but cannot find a purchaser? who, in fact, would be glad to
     get rid of those lands by any means whatever? They who, a little while ago, were in constant
     dread, day and night, of the name of a tribune; who feared your power, dreaded every mention of
     an agrarian law; they now will be begged and entreated to he so good as to give up to the
     decemvirs those lands which are partly public property, the possession of which is full of
     unpopularity and danger, at their own price. And this song this tribune of the people is
     singing now, not to yell, but in his own heart to himself. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69" resp="perseus"><p>
     He has a father-in-law, a most excellent man, who in those dark times of the republic got as
     much land as he wanted. He now seeing him yielding, oppressed weighed down with the burdens
     which Sulla put upon him, wishes to come to his assistance with this law of his, so as to
     enable him to get rid of the odium attached to him, and to get a sum of money too. And will not
     you hesitate to sell your revenues, acquired by the profuse expenditure of labour and blood on
     the part of your ancestors, for the purpose of heaping more riches on the landowners who have
     become so through Sulla, and of releasing them from danger? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70" resp="perseus"><p>
     For there are two kinds of lands concerned, O Romans, in this purchase of the decemvirs. One of
     them the owners avoid on account of its unpopularity; the other on account of its miserable
     condition. The land seized and distributed by Sulla, and extended as far as possible by
     particular individuals, has so much unpopularity attached to it, that it cannot bear the rustle
     of a genuine fearless tribune of the people. All this land, at whatever price it is purchased,
     will be returned to you at a great price. There is another sort of lands—uncultivated on
     account of their barrenness, desolate and deserted on account of the unhealthiness of the
     situation—which will be bought of those men, who see that they must abandon them if they do not
     sell them. And in truth, that is what was said by this tribune of the people in the
     senate,—that the common people of the city had too much influence in the republic; that it must
     be drained off. For this is the expression which he used; as if he were speaking of some sewer,
     and not of a class of excellent citizens.</p></div>
    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But do you, O Romans, if you will be guided by me, preserve your present possession of
     popularity, of liberty, of your votes, of your dignity, of the city, of the forum, of the
     games, of the days of festivals, and of all your other enjoyments. Unless, by chance, you
     prefer leaving all these things and this light of the republic, to be settled in the midst of
     the droughts of <placeName key="perseus,Sipontum">Sipontum</placeName>, or in the pestilential
     districts of <placeName key="perseus,Salapia">Salapia</placeName>, under the leadership of
     Rullus. But let him tell us what lands he is going to buy; let him show what he is going to
     give, and to whom he is going to give it. But can you possibly, tell me, allow him the power of
     selling any imaginable city, or land, or revenue, or kingdom that he likes, and then buying
     some tract of sand or some swamp? Although this is a very remarkable point, that according to
     this law everything is to be sold, all the money is to be collected and amassed together,
     before one perch of ground is bought. Then the law orders him to proceed to buy; but forbids
     any purchases to be made against the inclination or the owner.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> I ask now, suppose there is no one who is willing to sell,
     what is to become of the money? The law says it is not to be brought into the treasury. It
     forbids its being refunded. The decemvirs, then, will keep all that money. Land will not be
     bought for you. After having alienated your revenues, harassed your allies, drained the
     confederate kings and all nations of their whole property, they will have the money, and you
     will not have the lands. Oh, says he, they will easily be induced by the magnitude of the sums
     offered to sell the lands. Then the effect of the law is to be thus: that we are to sell our
     property at whatever price we can get for it; and that we are to buy other men's property at
     whatever price they choose to put upon it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73" resp="perseus"><p> And does the law
     order men to be conducted as settlers by those decemvirs, into those lands which have been
     bought in accordance with the provisions of this law? 
    <milestone unit="para"/>What? Is not the whole plan of such a nature that it does not make any difference to the
     republic whether a colony is led into that place or not? Is it a place which requires a colony?
     [a place which refuses one?] <gap reason="lost"/>And in this class of places, as in the other
     parts of the republic, it is worthwhile to recollect the diligence exhibited by our ancestors;
     who established colonies in such suitable places to guard against all suspicion of danger, that
     they appeared to be not so much towns of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> as
     bulwarks of the empire. These men are going to lead colonies into those lands which they have
     bought. Will they do so, even if it be not for the interests of the republic to do so?
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74" resp="perseus"><p> “And into whatever places besides they shall think fit.”
     What is the reason, therefore, that they may not be able to settle a colony on the Janiculan
     Hill; and to place a garrison of their own for their own protection on your heads and necks?
     Will you not define how many colonies you choose to have led forth, into what districts they
     are to be led, and of what number of colonists they are to consist? Will you occupy a place
     which you consider suitable for the violence which perhaps you are meditating? Will you
     complete the number of the colony, and will you strengthen it by whatever garrison you may
     think advisable? Will you employ the revenues and all the resources of the Roman people to
     coerce and oppress the Roman people itself, and to bring it under the dominion and power of
     those intolerable decemvirs?</p></div>
    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But I beg you now, O Romans, to take notice how he is planning to besiege and occupy all
      <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> with his garrison. He permits the decemvirs to
     lead colonists, whomsoever he may choose to select, into every municipality and into every
     colony in all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; and he orders lands to be
     assigned to those colonists. Is there any obscurity here in the way in which greater powers and
     greater defences than your liberty can tolerate are sought after? Is there any obscurity here
     in the manner in which kingly power is established? Is there any disguise about your liberty
     being wholly destroyed? For when it is one and the same body of men who with their resources
     lay siege, as it were, to all the riches and all the population,—that is to say, to all
      <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,—and who propose to hold all your liberties in
     blockade by their garrisons and colonies,—what hope, yes, what possibility even is left to you
     of ever recovering your liberty? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76" resp="perseus"><p> But the Campanian district,
     the most fertile section of the whole world, is to be divided in accordance with the provisions
     of this law; and a colony is to be led to <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, a
     most honourable and beautiful city. But what can we say to this? I will speak first of your
     advantage, O Romans. Then I will recur to the question of honour and dignity; so that, if any
     one takes particular pleasure in the excellence of any town or any district, he may not expect
     anything; and if any one is influenced by the idea of the dignity of the business, he may
     resist this fictitious liberality. And first of all I will speak of the town, in case there is
     any one whose fancy is more taken with <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> than
     with <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. He orders five thousand colonists to be
     enrolled for the purpose of being settled at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>;
     and to make up this number, each of the decemvirs is to choose five hundred men.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77" resp="perseus"><p>I entreat you,
     do not deceive yourselves about this matter. Consider it in
     its true light, and with due care. Do you think that in this number there will be room for you
     yourselves, or for any men like you—quiet, easy men? If there be room for all of you, or even
     for the greater part of you—although my regard for your honour compels me to keep awake day and
     night, and to watch with eager eyes every part of the republic—still I will close my eyes for a
     time, if your advantage will be at all promoted by my doing so. But, if a place and a city is
     being looked out for five thousand men, picked out as fit instruments for violence, and
     atrocity, and slaughter, from which they may be able to make war, and which may be able to
     equip them properly for war,—will you still suffer a power to be raised and garrisons to be
     armed in your own name against yourselves? Will you allow cities and lands and forces to be
     arrayed against your interest? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78" resp="perseus"><p> For they themselves have
     desired the Campanian district which they hold out a hope of to you. They will lead thither
     their own friends, in whose name they themselves may occupy it and enjoy it. Besides all this,
     they will make purchases; they will add the other ten acres to their present estate. For if
     they say that that is not lawful by the law; by the Cornelian law it certainly is not. But we
     see (to say nothing about lands at a distance) that the district of <placeName key="perseus,Praeneste">Praeneste</placeName> is occupied by a few people. And I do not see
     that anything is wanting to their fortunes, except farms of such a description that they may be
     able by the supplies which they derive from them to support their very large households, and
     the expense of their farms near <placeName key="perseus,Cumae">Cumae</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Puteoli">Puteoli</placeName>. But if he be thinking of what is for your
     advantage, then let him come, and let him discuss with me, face to face, the decision of the
     Campanian district.</p></div>
    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I asked him on the first of January, to what men he was going to distribute that land, and on
     what principles. He answered that he should begin with the Romilian tribe. In the first place
     now, what is the object of such pride and arrogance as to cut off one portion of the people,
     and to neglect the order of the tribes? to contrive to give land to the country people who have
     it already, before any is given to the city people, to whom the hope of land and the pleasure
     they are to derive from it is held out as an inducement ? Or if he says that this is not what
     he said, and if he has some plan in his head to satisfy all of you, let him produce it; let him
     allot it in divisions of ten acres; let him put forth your names in a regular arrangement from
     the district of the Subura to that of the Arnus. If you perceive not only that ten acres are
     not given to you, but that it is actually impossible for such a body of men to be collected
     together in the district of <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>, will you
     nevertheless allow the republic to be harassed, the majesty of the Roman people to be despised,
     and you yourselves to be deluded any longer by the tribune of the people? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But if that land could possibly come to you, would you not rather that it remained as part of
     your patrimony? Will you allow the most beautiful estate belonging to the Roman people—the main
     source of your riches, your chief ornament in time of peace, your chief source of supply in
     time of war, the foundation of your revenues, the granary from which your legions are fed, your
     consolation in time of scarcity—to be ruined? Have you forgotten what great armies you
     supported by means of the produce of <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>, in the
     Italian war, when you had lost all your ordinary sources of revenue? Are you ignorant that all
     those magnificent revenues of the Roman people are often dependent on a very slight impulse of
     fortune-on a critical moment? What will all the harbours of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, what will the plains of <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>,
     what will all our transmarine revenues avail us, if the very slightest alarm of pirates or
     enemies be once given? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81" resp="perseus"><p> But as our revenues derived from the
     territory of <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName> are of such a nature that they
     are always at home, and that they are protected by the bulwark of all our Italian towns, so
     they are neither hostile to us in time of war, nor variable in their productiveness, nor
     unfortunate from any accidents of climate or soil. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>Our ancestors were so far from diminishing what they had taken from the Campanians, that they
     even bought additional lands to be added to it, from those from whom they could not reasonably
     take it without purchase. For which reason, neither the two Gracchi, who thought a great deal
     of what was advantageous for the Roman people, nor Lucius Sulla, who gave away everything
     without the slightest scruple to any one he pleased, ever ventured to touch the Campanian
     territory. Rullus was the first man to venture to remove the republic from that property, of
     which neither the liberality of the Gracchi nor the uncontrolled power of Sulla had deprived
     it. <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>That land which now, as you pass by it, you say is yours, and which foreigners whose road
     lies through it hear is yours, when it is divided will neither be nor be said to be yours.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82" resp="perseus"><p> And who are the men who will possess it? In the first place
     they are active men, prepared for deeds of violence, willing for sedition, who, the very moment
     the decemvirs clap their hands, may be armed against the citizens and ready for slaughter. In
     the next place, you will see the whole district of <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName> distributed among a few men already rich in wealth and power. Meanwhile
     you, who have received from your ancestors those most beautiful homes, if I may so say, of your
     revenues, which they won by their arms, will not have left to you one single clod of earth of
     all your paternal hereditary possessions. And there will be this difference between your
     diligence and that or private individuals, that when Publius Lentulus, while he was chief of
     the senate, had been sent into those parts by our ancestors, in order to purchase at the public
     expense those lands, being private property, which projected into the public domain in
      <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName>, he is said to have reported that he had not
     been able to purchase a certain man's estate for money; and that he who had refused to sell it,
     had given this reason why he could not possibly be induced to sell it, that, though he had many
     farms, this was the only farm from which he never had had any bad news. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83" resp="perseus"><p> Is it so? Did this reason weigh with a private individual and shall it not
     weigh with the Roman people to prevent their giving up the district of <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName> to private individuals for nothing, at the request of
     Rullus? And the Roman people may say the very same thing about this revenue, that he is said to
     have said about his farm. <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> for many years during
     the Mithridatic war produced you no revenue. There was no revenue from the Spains in the time
     of Sertorius. Manius Aquilius even lent corn to the Sicilian cities at the time of the Servile
     war. But from this tributary land no bad news was ever heard. Other of our revenues are at
     times weighed down by the distresses of war; but the sinews of war are even supplied to us by
     this tributary land. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84" resp="perseus"><p> Besides, in this allotment of lands
     which is to take place, even that, which is said in other cases, cannot be said here, namely,
     that lands ought not to be left deserted by the people, and without the cultivation of free
     men. <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>For this is what I say,—if the Campanian land be divided, the common people is driven out of
     and banished from the lands, not settled and established in them. For the whole of the
     Campanian district is cultivated and occupied by the common people, and by a most virtuous and
     moderate common people. And that race of men of most virtuous habits, that race of excellent
     farmers and excellent soldiers, is wholly driven out by this tribune who is so devoted to the
     people. And these miserable men, born and brought up on those lands, practised in tilling the
     ground, will have no place to which, when so suddenly driven out, they can betake themselves.
     The entire possession of the Campanian district will be given over to these robust, vigorous,
     and audacious satellites of the decemvirs. And, as you now say of your ancestors, “Our
     ancestors left us these lands,” so your posterity will say of you, “Our ancestors received
     these lands from their ancestors, but lost them.” </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85" resp="perseus"><p> I think,
     indeed, that if the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName> were to be divided,
     and if every one of you had two feet of standing ground allotted to him in it, still you would
     prefer to enjoy the whole of it together, than for each individual to have a small portion for
     his own private property. Wherefore, even if some portion of these lands were to come to every
     individual among you.—which is now indeed held out to you as a lure, but is in reality destined
     for others,—still they would be a more honourable possession to you when possessed by the whole
     body, than if distributed in bits to each citizen. But now when you are not to have any share
     in them, but when they are being prepared for others and taken from you, will you not most
     vigorously resist this law as you would an armed enemy, fighting in defence of your lands. He
     adds the Stellate plain to the Campanian district, and in the two together he allots twelve
     acres to each settler. As if the difference was slight between the Stellate and Campanian
     districts! </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86" resp="perseus"><p> And now a multitude is sought out, by which those
     towns are to be peopled. For I have said before that leave is given by the law for them to
     occupy with their settlers whatever municipalities and whatever old colonies they choose. They
     will fill the municipality of <placeName key="perseus,Cales">Cales</placeName>; they will
     overwhelm Teanum; they will extend a chain of garrisons through <placeName key="perseus,Atella">Atella</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Cumae">Cumae</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,7004474">Naples</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Pompeii">Pompeii</placeName>, and Nuceria; and the whole of <placeName key="perseus,Puteoli">Puteoli</placeName>, which is at present a free city, in the full enjoyment of its ancient
     rights and liberties, they will occupy with a new people, and with a foreign body of men.
      <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Then that standard of a Campanian colony, greatly to be dreaded by this empire, will be
     erected at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> by the decemvirs. Then that other
      <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, which has been heard of before, will be sought
     in opposition to this <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, the common country of all
     of us. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87" resp="perseus"><p> Impious men are endeavouring to transfer our republic
     to that town in which our ancestors decided that there should be no republic at all, when they
     resolved that there were but three cities in the whole earth, <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, which could aspire to the power and name of the
     imperial city. <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> has been destroyed,
     because, both from its vast population, and from the natural advantages of its situation, being
     surrounded with harbours, and fortified with walls, it appeared to project out of <placeName key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, and to threaten the most productive islands of the Roman
     people. Of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> there is scarcely a vestige
     left. For it was situated on the straits and in the very jaws of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, in such a way that by land it held the keys of many countries, and that
     it almost connected two seas, equally desirable for purposes of navigation, which were
     separated by the smallest possible distance. These towns, though they were out of the sight of
     the empire, our ancestors not only crushed, but, as I have said before, utterly destroyed, that
     they might never be able to recover and rise again and flourish. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88" resp="perseus"><p> Concerning <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> they deliberated
     much and long. Public documents are extant, O Romans; many resolutions of the senate are
     extant. Those wise men decided that, if they took away from the Campanians their lands, their
     magistrates, their senate, and the public council of that city, they would leave no image
     whatever of the republic; there would be no reason whatever for their fearing <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>. Therefore you will find this written in ancient
     records, that there should be a city which might be able to supply the means for the
     cultivation of the Campanian district, that there should be a place for collecting the crops
     in, and storing them, in order that the farmers, when wearied with the cultivation of the
     lands, might avail themselves of the homes afforded them by the city; and that on that account
     the buildings of the city were not destroyed.</p></div>
    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>See, now, how wide is the distance between the counsels of our ancestors and the insane
     projects of these men. They chose <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> to be a
     refuge for our farmers,—a market for the country people,—a barn and granary for the Campanian
     district. These men, having expelled the farmers, have wasted and squandered your revenues, are
     raising this same <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> into the seat of a new
     republic, are preparing a vast mass to be an enemy to the old republic. But if our ancestors
     had thought that any one in such an illustrious empire, in such an admirable constitution as
     that of the Roman people, would have been like Marcus Brutus or Publius Rullus, (for these are
     the only two men whom we have hitherto seen, who have wished to transfer all this republic to
      <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>,) they would not, in truth, have left even
     the name of that city in existence. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90" resp="perseus"><p> But they thought, that
     in the case of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, even if they had taken away their senates and
     their magistrates, and deprived the citizens of the lands, still men would not be wanting who
     would restore those cities, and change the existing state of things in them before we could
     hear of it. But here, under the very eyes of the senate and Roman people, they thought that
     nothing could take place which might not be put down and extinguished before it had got to any
     head, or had assumed any definite shape. Nor did that matter deceive those men, endued as they
     were with divine wisdom and prudence. For after the consulship of Quintus Fulvius and Quintus
     Fabius, by whom, when they were consuls, <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> was
     defeated and taken, I will not say there has been nothing done, but nothing has been even
     imagined in that city against this republic. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>Many wars have been waged since that time with kings,—with Philip, and Antiochus, and Perses,
     and Pseudophilippus, and Aristonicus, and Mithridates, and others. Many terrible wars have
     existed beside-—the Carthaginian, the Corinthian, and the Numantian wars. There have been also
     many domestic seditions, which I pass over. There have been wars with our allies,—the Fregellan
     war, the Marsic war; in all which domestic and foreign wars <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> has not only not been any hindrance to us, but has afforded us most
     seasonable assistance, in providing the means of war, in equipping our armies, and receiving
     them in their houses and homes.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="91" resp="perseus"><p>There were no men in the city, who, by evil-disposed assemblies, by turbulent resolutions of the senate, or by unjust exertions of authority, threw
     the republic into confusion, and sought pretexts for revolution.
     For no one had any power of summoning an assembly, or of convening any public
     council. Men were not carried away by any desire for renown, because where there are no honours
     publicly conferred, there there can be no covetous desire of reputation. They were not
     quarreling with one another out of rivalry or out of ambition; for they had nothing left to
     quarrel about,—they had nothing which they could seek for in opposition to one another,—they
     had no room for dissensions. Therefore, it was in accordance with a deliberate system, and with
     real wisdom, that our ancestors changed the natural arrogance and intolerable ferocity of the
     Campanians into a thoroughly inactive and lazy tranquillity. And by this means they avoided the
     reproach of cruelty, because they did not destroy from off the face of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> a most beautiful city; and they <pb n="252"/> provided
     well for the future, in that, having cut out all the sinews of the city, they left the city
     itself enfeebled and disabled.</p></div>
     <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="92" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>These designs of our ancestors seemed, as I have said before, blamable in the eyes of Marcus
     Brutus and Publius Rullus. Nor, O Publius Rullus, do those omens and auspices encountered by
     Marcus Brutus deter you from similar madness. For both he who led a colony to <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>
     <gap reason="lost"/> and they who took upon themselves the magistracy there, and who had any
     share in the conducting a colony to that spot, and in the honours to be had there, or in the
     offices to be enjoyed there, have all suffered the most terrible punishments allotted to the
     wicked. And since I have made mention of Brutus and that time, I will also relate what I saw
     myself when I had arrived at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>,—when the colony
     had been just established there by Lucius Considius and Sextus Saltius the praetors, (as they
     called themselves,) that you may understand how much pride the situation itself inspires its
     inhabitants with; so great that it was very intelligible and visible when the colony had only
     been settled there a few days. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="93" resp="perseus"><p> For in the first place, as I
     said, though similar officers in the other colonies are called duumvirs, these men chose to
     call themselves praetors. But if their first year of office inspired them with such desires as
     that, do not you suppose that in a few years they would be likely to take a fancy to the name
     of consuls? In the next place, they were preceded by lictors, not with staves, but with two
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">faces</foreign>, just as lictors go before the praetors here. The
     greater victims were placed in the forum, which, after they had been approved by the college of
     priests, were sacrificed at the voice of the crier, and the music of a flute-player, by the
     praetors from their tribunal, as they are at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> by
     us who are consuls. After that, the conscript fathers were summoned. But after this, it was
     almost more than one could endure, to see the countenance of Considius. The man whom we had
     seen at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> shriveled and wasted away, in a
     contemptible and abject condition, when we saw him at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> with Campanian haughtiness and royal pride, we seemed to be looking at the
     Magii, and Blossii and Jubelii. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="94" resp="perseus"><p> And now, in what alarm all
     the common people were! In the <placeName key="tgn,1031727">Alban</placeName> and Seplasian
     road, what crowds assembled, of men inquiring what edict the praetor had issued? where he was
     supping? what he had said? And we who had come to <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> from <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, were not called
     guests, but foreigners and strangers.</p></div>
    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="95" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Ought we not to think that those men who foresaw all these things, O Romans, ought to be
     venerated and worshipped by us, and classed almost in the number of the immortal gods? For what
     was it which they saw? They saw this, which I entreat you now to remark and take notice of.
     Manners are not implanted in men so much by the blood and family, as by those things which are
     supplied by the nature of the plan towards forming habits of life, by which we are nourished,
     and by which we live. The Carthaginians, a fraudulent and lying nation, were tempted to a
     fondness for deceiving by a desire of gain, not by their blood, but by the character of their
     situation because, owing to the number of their harbours, they had frequent intercourse with
     merchants and foreigners. The Ligurians, being mountaineers, are a hardy and rustic tribe. The
     land itself taught them to be so by producing nothing which was not extracted from it by
     skillful cultivation, and by great labour. The Campanians were always proud from the excellence
     of their soil, and the magnitude of their crops, and the healthiness, and position, and beauty
     of their city. From that abundance, and from this affluence in all things, in the first place,
     originated those qualities; arrogance, which demanded of our ancestors that one of the consuls
     should be chosen from <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>: and in the second
     place, that luxury which conquered Hannibal himself by pleasure, who up to that time had proved
     invincible in arms. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="96" resp="perseus"><p> When those decemvirs shall, in
     accordance with the law of Rullus, have led six hundred colonists to that place; when they
     shall have established there a hundred decurions, ten augurs, and six priests, what do you
     suppose their courage, and violence, and ferocity will be then? They will laugh at and despise
      <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, situated among mountains and valleys, stuck
     up, as it were, and raised aloft, amid garrets, with not very good roads, and with very narrow
     streets, in comparison with their own <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>,
     stretched out along a most open plain, and in comparison of their own beautiful thoroughfares.
     And as for the lands, they will not think the <placeName key="tgn,7001168">Vatican</placeName>
     or Pupinian district fit to be compared at all to their fertile and luxuriant plains. And all
     the abundance of neigbouring towns which surround us they will compare in laughter and scorn
     with their neighbours. They will compare <placeName key="tgn,7010297">Labici</placeName>,
     Fidenae, Collatia,—even <placeName key="perseus,Lanuvium">Lanuvium</placeName> itself, and
      <placeName key="perseus,Aricia">Aricia</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName>, with <placeName key="perseus,Cales">Cales</placeName>, and Teanum, and
      <placeName key="tgn,7004474">Naples</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Puteoli">Puteoli</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Cumae">Cumae</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Pompeii">Pompeii</placeName>, and Nuceria. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="97" resp="perseus"><p> By
     all these things they will be elated and puffed up, perhaps not at once, but certainly when
     they have got a little more age and vigour they will not be able to restrain themselves; they
     will go on further and further. A single individual, unless he be a man of great wisdom, can
     scarcely, when placed in situations of great wealth or power, contain himself within the limits
     of propriety; much less will those colonists, sought out and selected by Rullus, and others
     like Rullus, when established at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, in that
     abode of pride, and in the very home of luxury, refrain from immediately contracting some
     wickedness and iniquity. Yes, and it will be much more the case with them, than with the old
     genuine Campanians, because they were born and trained up in a fortune which was theirs of old,
     but were depraved by a too great abundance of everything; but these men, being transferred from
     the most extreme indigence to a corresponding affluence, will be affected, not only by the
     extent of their riches, but also by the strangeness of them.</p></div>
    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="98" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>You, O Publius Rullus, have chosen to follow in the footsteps of Marcus Brutus's wickedness,
     rather than to be guided by the monuments of the wisdom of our ancestors. You have flavoured
     all this with these advices of yours—to sell the old revenues, and to waste the new ones,—to
     oppose <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> to this city in a rivalry of dignity—to
     subject all cities, nations and provinces, all free peoples, and kings, and the whole world in
     short, to your laws, and jurisdiction, and power, in order that, when you have drained all the
     money out of the treasury, and exacted all that may be due from the taxes, and extorted all
     that you can from kings, and nations, and even from our own generals, all men may still be
     forced to pay money to you at your nod; that you, also, or your friends, may buy up from those
     who have become possessed of them, as members of Sulla's party, their lands—some of which
     produce too much unpopularity to their owners to be worth keeping; some of which are unhealthy,
     and deserted on that account and charge them to the Roman people at whatever price you please;
     that you may occupy all the municipalities and colonies of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> with new settlers; that you may establish colonies in whatever places you
     think fit, and in as many places as seems desirable to you,</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="99" resp="perseus"><p>
     that you may surround, and hold in subjection, the whole republic with your soldiers, and your
     cities and your garrisons , that you may be able to proscribe and to deprive of the sight of
     these men Cnaeus Pompeius himself by whose protection and assistance the Roman people has
     repeatedly been triumphant over its most active enemies and its most worthless citizens that
     there may be nothing, which is either capable of being tampered with by means of gold and
     silver, or carried by numbers and votes, or accomplished by force and violence, which you do
     not hold in your own power, and under your dominion; that meanwhile you may go at full speed
     through every nation and every kingdom with the most absolute power,—with unrestricted
     authority as judges, and with immense sums of money; that you may come into the camp of Cnaeus
     Pompeius, and sell his very camp itself, if it be desirable for you to do so; that in the
     meantime, you, being freed from every restraint of law, and from all fear of the courts of
     justice, and from all danger, may be able to stand for all the other magistracies; so that no
     one may be able to bring you before the Roman people, or summon you before any court,—so that
     the senate may not be able to compel you, nor the consul to restrain you, nor the tribune of
     the people to offer any impediment to you. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="100" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I do not wonder that you, men of such folly and intemperance as you are, should have desired
     these things—I do marvel that you should have hoped that you could obtain them while I am
     consul. For as all consuls ought to exercise the greatest care and diligence in the protection
     of the republic, so, above all others, ought they to do so who have not been made consuls in
     their cradles, but in the Campus. No ancestors of mine went bail to the Roman people for me;
     you gave credit to me; it is from me that you must claim what I am bound to pay; all your
     demands must be made on me. As, when I stood for the consulship, no authors of my family
     recommended me to you; so, if. I commit any fault, there are no images of my ancestors which
     can beg me off from you. <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, if only life be granted me, as far as I can I will defend the state from the
     wickedness and insidious designs of those men. I promise you this, O Romans, with good faith;
     you have entrusted the republic to a vigilant man, not to a timid one; to a diligent man, not
     to an idle one. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="101" resp="perseus"><p> I am consul; how should I fear an assembly
     of the people? How should I be afraid of the tribunes of the people? How should I be frequently
     or causelessly agitated? How should I fear lest I may have to dwell in a prison, if a tribune
     of the people orders me to be led thither? for I, armed with your arms, adorned with your most
     honourable ensigns, and with command and authority conferred by you, have not been afraid to
     advance into this place, and, with you for my backers, to resist the wickedness of man; nor do
     I fear lest the republic, being fortified with such strong protection, may be conquered or
     overwhelmed by those men. If I had been afraid before, still now, with this assembly, and this
     people, I should not fear. For who ever had an assembly so well inclined to hear him while
     advocating an agrarian law, as I have had while arguing against one? if, indeed, I can be said
     to be arguing against one, and not rather upsetting and destroying one. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="102" resp="perseus"><p> From which, O Romans, it may be easily understood that there is nothing so
     popular, as that which I, the consul of the people, am this year bringing to you; namely,
     peace, tranquillity and ease. All the things which when we were elected you were afraid might
     happen, have been guarded against by my prudence and caution. You not only will enjoy ease,—you
     who have always wished for it; but I will even make those men quiet, to whom our quiet has been
     a source of annoyance. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>In truth, however, power, riches, are accustomed to be acquired by them out of the tumults
     and dissensions of the citizens. You, whose interest consists in the votes of the people, whose
     liberty is based on the laws, whose honours depend on the courts of justice and on the equity
     of the magistrates, and whose enjoyment of your properties depends on peace, ought to preserve
     tranquillity by every means. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="103" resp="perseus"><p> For if those men who, on
     account of indolence, are living in tranquillity, still take pleasure in their own base
     indolence; you, if in the calm quiet with which you govern fortune, you think such a condition
     as you enjoy better, should maintain it diligently; not as one that has been acquired by
     laziness, but as one that has been earned by virtue. <note anchored="true"> This and the next
      sentence are given up as corrupt by every one. Many different readings have been proposed; and
      I have endeavoured to extract what appears to have been Cicero's meaning from them, keeping as
      closely as possible to the text of Orellius.</note> And I, by the unanimity which I have
     established between myself and my colleague, have provided against those men whom I knew to be
     hostile to my consulship both in their dispositions and actions. I have provided against
     everything; and I have sought to recall those men to their loyalty. I have also given notice to
     the tribunes of the people, to try no disorderly conduct while I am consul. My greatest and
     firmest support in our common fortunes, O Romans, will be, if you for the future behave, for
     the sake of it, to the republic in the same manner as you have this day behaved to me in this
     most numerous assembly, for the sake of your own safety. I promise you most certainly, and
     pledge myself to manage matters so that they who have envied the honours which I have gained,
     shall at last confess, that in selecting a consul you all showed the greatest possible
     foresight.</p></div>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="Speech">
    <head>THE THIRD SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN OPPOSITION TO PUBLIUS SERVILIUS RULLUS, A TRIBUNE OF
     THE PEOPLE, CONCERNING THE AGRARIAN LAW. DELIVERED TO THE PEOPLE.</head>
    
     <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>The tribunes had declined debating the subject of the Agrarian law with Cicero before the
      people, but attacked him with calumnies behind his back; saying that his opposition to the law
      proceeded from his affection to Sulla's party, and from a desire to secure to the members of
      it the properties which Sulla had granted to them, and that he was only making this opposition
      to this law out of a desire to pay court to those whom they called the seven tyrants, the two
      Luculli, Crassus, Catulus, Hortensius, Metellus, and Philippus, who were known to be the
      greatest favourers of Sulla's cause, and to have been the chief gainers by it. And as these
      insinuations were making a great impression on the city, he thought it necessary to make this
      third speech to defend himself against them. And after this speech the tribunes let the whole
      matter drop.</p>
    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>The tribunes of the people, O Romans, would have pursued a more convenient course, if they
     had said to my face, in my presence, the things which they allege to you concerning me. For
     then, they would have given you an opportunity for a more just decision in the matter, and they
     would have followed the usages of their predecessors, and have maintained their own privileges
     and power. But, since they have shunned any open contest and debate with me at present, now, if
     they please, let them come forth into the assembly which I have convened, and though they would
     not come forward willingly when challenged by me, let them at least return to it now that I
     openly invite them back. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I see, O Romans, that some men are making a noise to imply something or other, and that they
     no longer show me the same countenance in this present assembly which they showed me at the
     last assembly in which I addressed you. Wherefore, I entreat you, who have believed none of my
     enemies' stories about me, to retain the same favourable disposition towards me that you always
     had; but from you, whom I perceive to be a little changed towards me, I beg the loan of your
     good opinion of me for a short time, on condition of your retaining it forever, if I prove to
     you what I am going to say, but abandoning it and trampling it under foot in this very place if
     I fail to establish it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Your minds and ears, O Romans, are blocked up with the assertion that I am opposing the
     agrarian law and your interest, out of a desire to gratify the seven tyrants, and the other
     possessors of Sulla's allotments. If there be any men who have believed these things, they must
     inevitably first have believed this, that by this agrarian law which has been proposed, the
     lands allotted by Sulla are taken away from their present possessors and divided among you, or
     else, that the possessions of private individuals are diminished, in order that you may be
     settled on their lands. If I show you, not only that not an atom of laud of Sulla's allotments
     is taken from any one, but even that that description of property is ensured to its possessors,
     and confirmed in a most impudent manner; if I prove, that Rullus, by his law, provides so
     carefully for the case of those lands which have been allotted by Sulla, that it is perfectly
     plain that that law was drawn up, not by any protector of your interests, but by the twin law
     of Valgius; is there then any reason at all, why he should disparage not only my diligence and
     prudence, but yours also, by the accusations which he has employed against me in my absence?</p></div>
    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>The fortieth clause of the law is one, O Romans, the mention of which I have hitherto
     purposely avoided, lest I should seem to be reopening a wound of the republic which was now
     scarred over, or to be renewing, at a most unseasonable time, some of our old dissensions. And
     now too I will argue that point, not because I do not think that this present condition of the
     republic deserving of being most zealously maintained, especially after I have professed myself
     to be for this year at least the patron of all tranquillity and unanimity in the republic; but
     in order to teach Rullus for the future to be silent at least in those matters with respect to
     which he wishes silence to be observed as to himself and his actions. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p> Of all laws I think that one is the most unjust and the most unlike a law,
     which Lucius Flaccus, the interrex, passed respecting Sulla—“That everything which he has done
     should be ratified.” For, as in other states, when tyrants are established, all laws are
     extinguished and destroyed this man established a tyrant of the republic by law. It is an
     invidious law, as I said before; but still it has some excuse. For it appears to be a law not
     urged by the man but by the time. What shall we say if this law is a far more impudent one?
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> For by the Valerian and Cornelian law this power is taken
     away at the same time that it is given. <note anchored="true">There is probably some corruption
      in the text here and in the next few sentences; Orellius marks them with a dagger.</note> An
     impudent courting of the people is joined with a bitter injury done to them. But still a man
     from whom any property is taken always has some hope arising from those laws; and he, to whom
     any is given, has some scruples. The provision in Rullus's law is, “Whatever has been done
     since the consulship of Caius Marius and Cnaeus Papirius.” How carefully does he avoid
     suspicion, when he names those consuls most especially who were the greatest adversaries of
     Sulla. For, if he had named Sulla, he thought that that would have been a palpable and also an
     invidious measure. And yet, which of you did he expect to be so stupid, as not to be able to
     recollect that immediately after the consulship of those men Sulla became dictator? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p> What then does this Marian tribune of the people say, when he is trying
     to make us, who are Sulla's friends, unpopular? “Whatever has been given, or assigned, or sold,
     or granted by public authority, whether lands, or houses, or lakes, or marshes, or sites, or
     properties,” (he has omitted to mention the sky and sea, but he has omitted nothing else,)
     “since the consulship of Marius and <persName><surname>Carbo</surname></persName>.” By whom, O
     Rullus? Who has allotted anything whatever since the Consulship of Marius and Carbo? Who has
     given anything, who has granted anything, except Sulla? “Let all those things remain in the
     same condition.” In what condition? He is undermining something or other. This over active and
     too energetic tribune of the people is rescinding the acts of Sulla. “As those things which
     have become private property according to the most regular possible course of law.” Are they
     then to be held on a surer tenure than a man's paternal and hereditary property? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> Just so. But the Valerian law does not say this; the <placeName key="tgn,2257061">Cornelian</placeName> laws do not sanction this; Sulla himself does not
     demand this. If those lands have any connection with legal right, if they have any resemblance
     to private property, if they have the least hope of becoming permanent property, then there is
     not one of those men so impudent as not to think that he is excellently well treated. But you,
     O Rullus, what is your object? That they may retain what they have got? Who hinders them? That
     they may retain it as private property? But the law is framed in such a way that the farm of
     your father-in-law in the Hirpine district, or the whole Hirpine district, for he is in
     possession of all of it, is held by him on a surer tenure than my paternal hereditary estate at
     Arpinum. For that is the effect of the provision of your law. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
     For those farms in truth are held by the best right, which are held on the best conditions.
     Free tenures are held by a better tenure than servile ones. By this clause all tenures which
     have hitherto been servile <note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Serva praedia</foreign>
      mean such estates as were liable to certain burdens or duties; held by the performance of
      certain services.</note> tenures will be so no longer. Enfranchised estates are in a better
     condition than those which are liable to no obligations; by the same clause all lands subject
     to the payment of any fine, if only they were assigned by Sulla, are released from such
     payments. Lands which are exempt from payment are in a better condition than those which pay a
     fine. I, in my Tusculan villa, must pay a tax for the Crabran <note anchored="true"> The
       <foreign xml:lang="lat">Crabra aqua</foreign> is several times mentioned by Cicero in his
      letters as a small artificial stream running through his Tusculan property. He even had a
      law-suit respecting it, as appears from one of his letters. </note> water, because I received
     my estate subject to this liability; but, if I had only had the land given me by Sulla, I
     should not pay it, according to the law of Rullus.</p></div>
    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I see you, O Romans, moved either by the impudence of the law or of the speech, as indeed you
     must be from the nature of the case; by the impudence of the law, which gives a better title to
     estates possessed by virtue of Sulla's donation than to hereditary property; by the impudence
     of the speech which, in such a cause is that, dares to accuse any one, and yet vehemently, too
     vehemently, to defend the principles of Sulla. But if the law only ratified all the allotments
     which had been given by Sulla, I should not say a word, provided he would confess himself to be
     a partisan of Sulla's. But he does not only protect their existing interests, but he even adds
     to their present possessions some sort of gift. And he, who accuses me, saying that the
     possessions resting on Sulla's title are defended by me, not only con firms them him sell, but
     even institutes fresh allotments, and rises up among us a new Sulla. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p> For just take notice what great grants of lands this reprover of ours
     endeavours to make by one single word. “Whatever has been given, or presented, or granted, or
     sold”—I can bear it; I hear it; what comes next?—“shall be held as absolute property.” has a
     tribune of the people ventured to propose that whatever any one has become possessed of' since
     the consulship of Marius and <persName><surname>Carbo</surname></persName>, he shall hold by
     the firmest right that any one can hold private property? Suppose he drove out the former
     proprietors by violence? Suppose he became possessed of it in some underhand manner, or only by
     some one's permission for a time? By this law then all civil rights, all legitimate titles, all
     interdicts of the praetors will be put an end to. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> It is no
     unimportant case, it is no insignificant injury that is concealed under this expression, O
     Romans. For there were many estates confiscated by the <placeName key="tgn,2257061">Cornelian</placeName> law, which were never assigned or sold to any one, but which are
     occupied in the most impudent manner by a few men, These are the men for whom he provides,
     these are the men whom he defends, whom he makes private proprietors. These lands, I say, which
     Sulla gave to no one, Rullus does not choose to assign to you, but to sacrifice to the men who
     are in occupation of them. I ask the reason why you should allow those lands in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, in
     the two Spains, in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, and <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, which your ancestors acquired for you, to be sold, when
     you see those lands which are your own sacrificed by the same law to their existing occupiers?
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> Now you will understand the whole law, and perceive, <pb n="262"/> that it is framed to secure the power of a few individuals, and admirably adapted to
     the circumstances of Sulla's allotments. For this man's father-in-law is a most excellent man,
     nor am I saying a word against his character; but I am discussing the impudence of his
     son-in-law. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>For he wishes to keep what he has got possession of, and does not conceal that he
     is one of Sulla's party.
    <milestone unit="para"/>He now, by your instrumentality, in order that he may himself have what be has not got wishes
     to establish those titles which at present are doubtful. And as he is more covetous than Sulla
     himself, I am accused of defending the actions of Sulla which I am resisting. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> My father-in-law, says he, has some hitherto deserted and distant fields. By
     my law he will be able to sell them at his own price. He holds them at present by an uncertain
     title; in fact he has no right at all to them: they will be confirmed to him by the best
     possible title. He has them as public property; I will make them private property. Lastly, he
     shall possess, without having the slightest anxiety about them for the future, those farms
     which be has procured (by the proscription of their former owners) to be joined to the
     admirable and productive estate which be had in the district of <placeName key="perseus,Casinum">Casinum</placeName>, being contiguous to it before; so as to make all
     the different farms into one uninterrupted estate as far as the eye can reach; and respecting
     which at present he is not without apprehension. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And since I have shown for what reason and for whose sake be has proposed this, let him show
     whether I am defending any particular proprietor, while I resist this agrarian law. You are
     selling the Scantian wood. The Roman people is in possession of it. I am defending the Roman
     people. You are dividing the district of Campania It is you, O Romans, who are now its
     proprietors. I will not give it up. In the next place, I see possessions in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> and in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>,
     and in the other provinces, put up for sale and advertised. The farms are yours, the
     possessions are yours, O Romans. I will resist and oppose such a measure; and I will not permit
     the Roman people to be ousted from its possessions by any one, while I am consul. Especially
     when no advantage is sought for you by the proceeding. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> For
     you ought no longer to lie under this mistake. Is any one of you a man inclined to violence, or
     atrocity, or murder? Not one. And, believe me, it is for such a race of men as that that the
     district of <placeName key="tgn,7003005">Campania</placeName> and that beautiful <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> is reserved. It is against you, against your liberty,
     against Cnaeus Pompeius that an army is being raised. <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> is being got ready in opposition to this city; bands of audacious men are
     being equipped against you; ten generals are being appointed to counterbalance Cnaeus Pompeius.
     Let them meet me face to face, and since they have summoned me to this assembly of yours, at
     your request let them here argue the case with me.
    </p></div>
   </div>
 </div>
 </body>
 </text>

</TEI>
