<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>On Stilicho's Consulship</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
               <sourceDesc>
                  <biblStruct>
                     <monogr>
                        <title>Claudian, with an English translation, in Two Volumes, Vol. I</title>
                        <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                        <editor role="editor">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                        <imprint>
                           <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                           <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
                           <date type="printing">1922</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                     </monogr>
                     <ref target="http://www.archive.org/stream/claudian01clau#page/364/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
                  </biblStruct>
               </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">            
                              <state unit="book" delim="."/>
                              <state unit="poem"/>
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa004.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.365" TEIform="pb"/>
               <div1 type="book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>

Ceaseless are the blessings the gods shower with
full bounty upon Rome, crowning success with new
successes. Scarce had the happy songs of marriage
ceased to echo in the palace when the defeat of
Gildo brought material for a hymn of triumph.
</p>
         <p>Hard upon the garlands of passionate love followed
the crown of laurel, so that the emperor won alike
the name of husband and the fame of conqueror.
</p>
         <p>After the war in Africa eastern sedition waned;
the Orient once more was laid low and, guarded
by the consul Stilicho, the axes rose in triumph.
</p>
         <p>In due order are vows fulfilled. Should I hope to
roll into one poem all my lofty themes, more easily
should I pile Pelion on frozen Ossa. Were I silent
anent a part, what I leave unsung will prove the
greater. Am I to recall his deeds of old and earliest
manhood? His present deeds lure away my mind.
</p>
         <p>Am I to tell of his justice? His military glory
outshines it. Shall I mention his prowess in war?
</p>
         <p>He has done more in peace. Shall I relate how
Latium flourishes, how Africa has returned to her
allegiance and service, how Spain knows no more
<pb id="v.1.p.367"/>
the Moor as her neighbour, how Gaul has now
nought to fear from a disarmed Germany? Or
shall I sing of wintry Thrace and those fierce
struggles whereof Hebrus was witness? Limitless
is the expanse that opens before me and even
on the slopes of Helicon this weight of praise
retards my muse's chariot.
</p>
         <p>For truly since man inhabited this globe never
has one mortal been granted all earth's blessings
without alloy. This man's face is fair but his character
is evil; another has a beauteous soul but an
ugly body. One is renowned in war but makes
peace hideous with his vices. This man is happy in
his public but unhappy in his private life. Each
takes a part; each owes his fame to some one gift,
to bodily beauty, to martial prowess, to strength,
to uprightness of life, to knowledge of law, to
his offspring and a virtuous wife. To all men else
blessings come scattered, to thee they flow commingled,
and gifts that separately make happy are
all together thine.
</p>
         <p>I will not unfold the tale of thy sire's 1 warlike
deeds. Had he done nothing of note, had he in
loyalty to Valens never led to battle those yellow-
haired companies, yet to be the father of Stilicho
would have spread abroad his fame. Ever from thy
cradle did thy soul aspire, and in the tender years
of childhood shone forth the signs of loftier estate.
</p>
         <p>Lofty in spirit and eager, nothing paltry didst thou
essay; never didst thou haunt any rich man's
doorstep; thy speech was such as to befit thy future
dignities. A mark wert thou even then for all
eyes, even then an object of reverence; the fiery
brightness of thy noble countenance, the very mould
<pb id="v.1.p.369"/>
of thy limbs, greater even than poets feign of
demi-gods, marked thee out for a leader of men.
</p>
         <p>Whithersoever thy proud form went in the city
thou didst see men rise and give place to thee;
yet thou wast then but a soldier. The silent suffrage
of the people had already offered thee all the honours
the court was soon to owe.
</p>
         <p>Scarce hadst thou reached man's estate when thou
wast sent to negotiate peace with Assyria 1; to
make a treaty with so great a people was the charge
entrusted to thy youth. Crossing the Tigris and
the deep Euphrates thou cam'st to Babylon. The
grave lords of Parthia looked at thee in amaze and
the quiver-bearing mob burned with desire to
behold, while the daughters of Persia gazing on their
beauteous guest sighed out their hidden love. The
peace is sworn at altars sweet with the fragrance of
incense and the harvests of Saba. Fire is brought
forth from the innermost sanctuary and the Magi
sacrifice heifers according to the Chaldean ritual.
</p>
         <p>The king himself dips the jewelled bowl of sacrifice
and swears by the mysteries of Bel and by Mithras
who guides the errant stars of heaven. Whenever
they made thee sharer of their hunting, whose
sword struck down the Hon in close combat before
that of Stilicho, whose arrow pierced the striped tiger
afar before thine? When thou didst guide the easy
rein the Mede gave way to thee, and the Parthian
marvelled at the bow thou didst discharge in flight.
</p>
         <p>Meanwhile a maiden of years full ripe for marriage
troubled a father's heart, and the emperor doubted
whom to select as her husband and as future ruler
of the world; right anxiously did he search east
and west for a son-in-law worthy of being wedded
<pb id="v.1.p.371"/>
to Serena. Merit alone had to decide; through
camps, through cities, through nations roamed his
poised and hesitating thoughts. But thou wast
chosen, thus in the opinion and judgement of him
who selected thee surpassing all the candidates of the
whole world and becoming a son-in-law in the
imperial family where thou wast shortly to become
a father-in-law. The marriage - bed was ablaze
with flashing gold and regal purple. The maiden
steps forth accompanied by her parents clad in
scarlet. On one side stood her sire, famed for his
triumphs, on the other was the queen, fulfilling a
mother's loving office and ordering the bridal veil
beneath a weight of jewels. Then, so men say, the
horses of the sun and the stars of heaven danced
for joy, pools of honey and rivers of milk welled
forth from the earth. Bosporus decked his banks
with vernal flowers, and Europe, entwined with rosy
garlands, uplifted the torches in rivalry with Asia.
</p>
         <p>Happy our emperor in his choice; he judges
and the world agrees; he is the first to value what
we all see. Ay, for he has allied to his children
and to his palace one who never preferred ease to
war nor the pleasures of peace to danger, nor yet
his hfe to his honour. Who but he could have
driven back the savage Visigoths to their wagons or
overwhelmed in one huge slaughter the Bastarnae
puffed up with the slaying of Promotus 1? Aeneas
avenged the slaughter of Pallas with the death of
Turnus, Hector, dragged behind the chariot-wheels,
was to wrathful Achilles either revenge or gain;
thou dost not carry off in mad chariot dead bodies
for ransom nor plot idle savagery against a single
corpse; thou slayest at thy friend's tomb whole
<pb id="v.1.p.373"/>
squadrons of horse, companies of foot, and hordes of
enemies. To his ghost a whole nation is offered up.
</p>
         <p>Neither Vulcan's fabulous shield nor such armour as
that of which poets sing the forging assisted thine
efforts. Single-handed thou didst succeed in penning
within the narrow confines of a single valley the vast
army of barbarians that were long since ravaging the
land of Thrace. For thee the fearful shriek of the
onrushing Alan had no terrors nor the fierceness of
the nomad Hun nor the scimitar of the Geloni, nor
the Getae's bow or Sarmatian's club. These nations
would have been destroyed root and branch had not
a traitor by a perfidious trick abused the emperor's
ear and caused him to withhold his hand; hence the
sheathing of the sword, the raising of the siege, and
the granting of a treaty to the prisoners.
</p>
         <p>He was always with the army, seldom in Rome,
and then only when the young emperor's anxious
love summoned him thither. Scarce had he greeted
the gods of his home, scarce seen his wife when,
still stained with the blood of his enemies, he hastened
back to the battle. He did not stay to catch at
least a kiss from Eucherius through his vizor; the
anxieties of a general o'ercame a father's yearning
and a husband's love. How often has he bivouacked
through the Thracian winter and endured beneath
the open sky the blasts that slow Boötes sends from
mount Riphaeus. When others, huddled over
the fire, could scarce brook the cold, he would
ride his horse across the frozen Danube and
climb Athos deep in snow, his helmet on his head,
thrusting aside the frozen branches of the ice-laden
trees with his far gleaming targe. Now he pitched
his tent by the shores of Cimmerian Pontus, now
<pb id="v.1.p.375"/>
misty Rhodope afforded him a winter's bed. I call
you to witness, cold valleys of Haemus, that Stilicho
has often filled with bloody slaughter; and you,
rivers of Thrace, your waters turned to blood;
say, ye Bisaltae, or you whose oxen plough Pangaeus'
slopes, how many a rotting helm has not your
share shattered neath the soil, how oft have not
your mattocks rung against the giant bones of
slaughtered kings.
</p>
         <p>Fain would I embrace each separate one; but
thine exploits press on in too close array, and I am
overwhelmed by the pursuing flood of glorious
deeds. When Theodosius had warred against, and
slain, the tyrant 1 he ascended into heaven, leaving
the governance of the world to thee. With a
strength equal to his thou dost bear up the tottering
structure of the empire that threatens each moment
to collapse. Thus, when once Hercules upheld the
world, the universal frame hung more surely poised,
the Standard-bearer did not reel with tottering
stars, and old Atlas, relieved for a moment of the
eternal load, was confounded as he gazed upon his
own burden.
</p>
         <p>Barbary was quiet, no revolution troubled the
empire's peace and though so great a prince was dead
the world knew not that the reins had passed into
another's hands. No company in the two armies 2
dared aught as though set loose from control. Yet
surely never had such diversities of language and
arms met together to form one united people.
</p>
         <p>Theodosius had unified the whole East beneath his
rule. Here were mingled Colchian and Iberian,
mitred Arab, beautifully coifed Armenian; here the
Sacian had pitched his painted tent, the Mede his
<pb id="v.1.p.377"/>
stained tent, the dusky Indian his embroidered tent:
here were the tall company of warriors from the
Rhone and the warlike children of Ocean. Stilicho
and Stilicho alone commanded all the nations looked
on by the rising and the setting sun. Amid this company
so diverse in blood and speech such peace
reigned beneath thy rule, so did fear of justice secure
right, that not a single vineyard was robbed, nor did
a single field cheat the husbandman of its plundered
crop; rage incited to no violence, passion to no
deeds of shame; the peaceful sword was obedient
to law. Of a truth their leaders' pattern passes to
the crowd, and the soldier follows not only the
standards but also the example of his general.
</p>
         <p>Whithersoever thou didst lead thy victorious eagles
there rivers grew dry, drunk up by so many thousands
of men. Didst thou march towards Illyria, plain and
mountain were hidden; didst thou give the signal
to thy fleet, the Ionian main was lost beneath thy
ships. Cloud-girt Ceraunia, the storms that dash
the waves in foam on Leucas' promontory — these
could not affright any. Shouldst thou bid them
explore some frozen sea, thy untroubled soldiers
would shatter the congealed waters with countervailing
oar; had they to seek the deserts of
the south, to search out the sources of the Nile,
their sails would penetrate into Ethiopia's midmost
heat.
</p>
         <p>Thee mindful Eurotas, thee Lycaeus' rustic muse,
thee Maenalus celebrates in pastoral song, and therewith
the woods of Parthenius, where, thanks to thy
victorious arms, weary Greece has raised once more
her head from amid the flames . Then did Ladon, river
of Arcadia, stay his course amid the countless bodies,
<pb id="v.1.p.379"/>
and Alphaeus, choked with heaps of slaughtered
Getae, won his way more slowly to his Sicilian love.1
Do we wonder that the foe so swiftly yields in
battle when they fall before the sole terror of his
name? We did not declare war on the Franks;
yet they were overthrown. We did not crush in
battle the Suebi on whom we now impose our laws.
</p>
         <p>Who could believe it? Fierce Germany was our
slave or ever the trumpets rang out. Where are
now thy wars, Drusus, or thine, Trajan? All that
your hands wrought after doubtful conflict that
Stilicho did as he passed along, and o'ercame the
Rhine in as many days as you could do in years;
you conquered with the sword, he with a word; you
with an army, he single-handed. Descending from
the river's source to where it splits in twain and to
the marshes that connect its mouths he flashed his
lightning way. The speed of the general outstripped
the river's swift course, and Peace, starting with him
from Rhine's source, grew as grew Rhine's waters.
</p>
         <p>Chieftains whose names were once so well known,
flaxen-haired warrior-kings whom neither gifts nor
prayers could win over to obedience to Rome's
emperors, hasten at his command and fear to offend
by dull delay. Crossing the river in boats they
meet him wheresoever he will. The fame of his
justice did not play them false: they found him
merciful, they found him trustworthy. Him whom
at his coming the German feared, at his departure
he loved. Those dread tribes whose wont it was
ever to set their price on peace and let us purchase
repose by shameful tribute, offered their children
as hostages and begged for peace with such suppliant
looks that one would have thought them
<pb id="v.1.p.381"/>
captives, their hands bound behind their backs,
and they mounting the Tarpeian rock with the
chains of slavery upon their necks. All those lands
that lie between Ocean and the Danube trembled
at the approach of one man. Boreas was brought
into servitude without a blow; the Great Bear was
disarmed.
</p>
         <p>In so short a time didst thou win so many battles
without loss of blood, and, setting out with the moon
yet new, thou didst return or ever it was full; so
didst thou compel the threatening Rhine to learn
gentleness with shattered horns, that the Salian now
tills his fields, the Sygambrian beats his straight
sword into a curved sickle, and the traveller, as
he looks at the two banks, asks over which Rome
rules. The Belgian, too, pastures his flock across the
river and the Chauci heed it not; Gallic herds cross
the middle Elbe and wander over the hills of the
Franks. Safe it is to hunt amid the vast silence of
the distant Hercynian forest, and in the woods that
old-established superstition has rendered awful our
axes fell the trees the barbarian once worshipped
and nought is said.
</p>
         <p>Nay more, devoted to their conqueror this people
offers its arms in his defence. How oft has Germany
begged to add her troops to thine and to join her
forces with those of Rome! Nor yet was she angered
when her offer was rejected, for though her aid was
refused her loyalty came off with praise. Provence
will sooner drive out the governor thou sendest
than will the land of the Franks expel the ruler
thou hast given them. Not to rout rebels in the
field but to punish them with chains is now the
law; under our judge a Roman prison holds inquest
<pb id="v.1.p.383"/>
on the crimes of kings. Marcomeres and Sunno 1
give proof: the one underwent exile in Etruria, the
other, proclaiming himself the exile's avenger, fell
beneath the swords of his own soldiers. Both were
eager to arouse rebellion, both hated peace — true
brothers in character and in a common love of crime.
</p>
         <p>After the conquest of the north arose a fresh storm
in another quarter. The trumpets of war rang out
in the south that there might be no part of the world
untouched by thy victories. Gildo stirred up all
the Moorish tribes living beneath mount Atlas and
those whom the excessive heat of the sun cuts off from
us in the interior of Africa, those too whom Cinyps'
wandering stream waters, and Triton, neighbour of
the garden of the Hesperides; those who dwell
beside the waters of Gir, most famous of the rivers of
Ethiopia, that overflows his banks as it had been
another Nile. There came at his summons the
Nubian with his head-dress of short arrows, the fleet
Garamantian, the Nasamonian whose impetuous
ardour not even the sinister predictions of Ammon
could restrain. The plain of Numidia was overrun,
their dust covered the Gaetulian Syrtes; the sky
of Carthage was darkened with their arrows. Some,
mounted, guide their horses with sticks, others are
clad in tawny lion-skins and pelts of the nameless
animals that range the vast deserts of Meroe.
</p>
         <p>Severed heads of serpents with gaping jaws serve
them for helmets, the bright scaly skin of the viper
fashions their quivers. Simois trembled not so
violently when swart Memnon led his dusky troops
o'er Ida's summit. Not so fearful was Ganges when
Porus approached, mounted on his towering elephant
and surrounded with his far-shooting Indian soldiery.
<pb id="v.1.p.385"/>
Yet Porus was defeated by Alexander, Memnon by
Achilles, and Gildo by thee.
</p>
         <p>It was not, however, only the South that fierce
Mars aroused but also the East. Though loyalty
cried out against it Gildo had transferred the nominal
rule of Libya to the Eastern empire, cloaking his
base treason under the name of legitimate government.1
Thus with diverse terror a twofold war
arose; here were arms, there were wiles. Africa
supported the one with her savage tribes, the other
the conspiring East nurtured with treachery. From
Byzantium came edicts to subvert the loyalty of
governors; from Africa that refused her crops black
famine pressed and had beleaguered trembling Rome.
</p>
         <p>Libya openly meditated our destruction; over the
civic strife shame had laid her veil of silence.
</p>
         <p>Though such storms raged on either hand, though
the twofold tempest buffeted the torn empire
on this side and on that, no whit did our consul's
courage yield to weariness, but ever watchful
against threatening doom and soon to win prosperous
issue, shone greater amid dangers: as the
ship's pilot, tossed in mid Aegean by the storms of
rainy Orion, eludes the waves' buffeting by the
least turn of the tiller, skilfully guiding his vessel
now on straight, now on slanting course, and struggles
successfully against the conjoint fury of sea and sky.
</p>
         <p>At what, Stilicho, shall I first marvel? At the
providence that resisted all intrigues, whereby no
treacherous missive, no bribe-fraught hand escaped
thy notice? Or because that amid the general
terror thou spakest no word unworthy of Latium?
</p>
         <p>Or because thou didst ever give haughty
answer to the East and later made that answer
<pb id="v.1.p.387"/>
good? They held thy goods, thy lands, thy houses,
yet wast thou unmoved. This thou didst account a
trifling loss nor ever preferred private to public
interest. Thy mighty task thou dost parcel out,
yet dost thou face it all alone, debating the problems
that must needs be thought out, acting where
deeds are called for, ever ready to dictate where
aught is to be accomplished by writing. What
hundred-handed monster, what Briareus, whose
arms ever grew more numerous as they were lopped
off, could cope with all these things at once? To
avoid the snares of treachery, to strengthen existing
regiments and enroll new ones, to equip two fleets,
one of corn-ships, one of men-of-war, to quell the
tumult of the court and alleviate the hunger of the
Roman populace — what eyes, never visited by the
veil of sleep, have had the strength to turn their
gaze in so many directions and over so many lands
or to pierce so far? Fame tells how Argus girt
with a hundred eyes could guard but one heifer with
his body's watch.
</p>
         <p>Whence comes this mass of com? What forest
fashioned all those vessels? Whence has sprung
this untutored army with all its young recruits?
</p>
         <p>Whence has Gaul, its age once more at the spring,
won back the strength that Alpine blows twice
shattered 1? Methinks 'tis no levy but the plough-
share of the Phoenician Cadmus that has raised up
thus suddenly a host sprung from the sowing of the
dragon's teeth; 'tis like the crop that in the fields
of Thebes drew the sword of kin in threatened battle
with its own sower when, the seed once sown, the
earth-born giants clave the earth, their mother's
womb, with their springing helms and a harvest of
<pb id="v.1.p.389"/>
young soldiery burgeoned along the armèd furrows.
</p>
         <p>This too must not be passed over without full meed
of praise, that the avenging expedition did not
embark until the senate had, in accordance with
antique usage, declared war. Stilicho re-established
this custom, neglected for so many ages, that the
Fathers should give generals charge to fight, and
by decree of the toga-clad Senate the battle-token
pass auspiciously among the legions. We acknowledge
that the laws of Romulus have now returned
when we see arms obedient to our ministers.
</p>
         <p>Thou couldst have filled the Tyrrhene sea with
all thy standards, the Syrtes with thy fleet and Libya
with thy battalions, but wrath was stayed o'ercome
by prudent fear lest Gildo, terrified at the thought
that thou wast in arms against him and suspecting
that thy forces were of overwhelming strength,
might retire into the hot desert and the torrid zone,
or travel east in flight or, to console him for the
certainty of death, might destroy his cities with
fire. Marvellous it is to tell: thou wast fearful of
being feared and forbade him to despair whom thy
vengeance awaited. How greatly was his confidence
our gain! Safe are the towers of hostile Carthage,
and the Phoenician fields rejoice in their unharmed
husbandmen, fields he might have laid waste in his
flight. Deluded by a vain hope he spared what
was ours without escaping chastisement for himself.
</p>
         <p>Madman, to measure Rome by the numbers instead
of the valour of her soldiers! He advanced as
though he would ride them all down by means
of his fleet cavalry and, as he often boasted, would
overwhelm in the dust the Gauls enervated by the
sun's heat. But he soon learned that neither wounds
<pb id="v.1.p.391"/>
made more deadly by the poisoned arrow of Ethiopia
nor thick hail of javelins nor clouds of horsemen
can withstand Latin spears. The cowardly Nasamonian
troops are scattered, the Garamantian hurls
not his spears but begs for mercy, the swift-footed
Autololes fly to the desert, the terror-stricken
Mazacian flings away his arms, in vain the Moor
urges on his flagging steed. The brigand flees in
a small boat and driven back by the winds met
with his just fate in the harbour of Tabraca, discovering
that no element offered refuge, Stilicho, to
thine enemies. There he was destined to undergo
the insults of the overjoyed populace and to bow
his guilty head before a lowly judgement-seat.
</p>
         <p>Let not Fortune claim aught for herself. Let
her be ever favourable; but we trusted not the issue
to a single fight, nor was the hazard set with all our
force to be lost at a single throw. Had hard chance
at all prevailed, a second fleet pressed on behind, a
greater leader was yet to come.
</p>
         <p>Never was a more famous victory nor one that
was the object of more heart-felt prayers. Will
anyone compare with this the defeat of Tigranes,
of the king of Pontus, the flight of Pyrrhus or
Antiochus, the capture of Jugurtha, the overthrow
of Perses or Philip? Their fall meant but the
enlargement of the empire's bounds; on Gildo's
depended the very existence of Rome. In those
cases delay entailed no ill; in this a late-won victory
was all but a defeat. On this supreme issue, while
leanness racked her people, hung the fate of Rome;
and to win back Libya was a greater gain than its
first conquest, even as to lose a possession stirs a
heavier pain than never to have had it. Who would
<pb id="v.1.p.393"/>
now be telling of the Punic wars, of you, ye Scipios,
or of thee, Regulus; who would sing of cautious
Fabius, if, destroying right, the fierce Moor were
trampling on an enslaved Carthage? This victory,
Rome, has revived the laurels of thy heroes of old;
Stilicho has restored to thee all thy triumphs.
         </p>
               </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.3" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="book" n="2" id="poem.22" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>

Thus far the warrior's praise ! Now let my gentler
Muse relax the strings and tell by what virtues he
governs the world, tempering fear with love, say
what counsel moved him at last to assume those
consular robes that cried out to him, and bestowed
on our annals a year named after himself.
In the beginning Love 1 was the guardian of this
vast universe, she who dwelt in the sphere of Jove,
who attempers the sky 'twixt cold and heat, who is
eldest of the immortals. For Love, pitying the
elemental confusion, first disentangled Chaos ; with
a smile she scattered the darkness and bathed the
world in light. She dwelleth now not in temples
nor by altars warm with incense but in thy heart
wherein she has made her home. Taught by her
thou accountest it cruel and barbarous to batten on
suffering and human slaughter ; the sword that
drips blood in war thou wearest unstained in peace ;
Roman coins. See, also, for Clementia as a goddess, Claud,
xvii. 166, and Stat. Theh. xii. 481 et sqq.
<pb id="v.2.p.5"/>
though angered thou feedest with no fuel the flame
of hatred ; thou forgivest the guilty even before they
ask, thou lay est aside thy wrath more readily than
thou art moved to wrath, thou never turnest a deaf
ear to prayers, all who oppose thee thou overthrowest,
but deignest not to touch them when overthrown,
like a Hon who lusts to rend in pieces the fierce bull,
but passes by the cowering prey. At her bidding
thou extendest pardon to the conquered ; at her
prayer thou refrainest the dread fires of thine anger
and those threats, not the less terrible for being
unfulfilled ; it is enough for thee to inspire awe, even
as the heavenly Father who, shaking the world with
his loud thunder, hurls the bolts of the Cyclopes upon
rocks and sea-monsters and, sparing the blood of
man, expends his lightnings on the forests of Oeta.
Good Faith too, Love's sister, has made her shrine
in thy heart and joins herself to all thine actions.
She has taught thee to practise no hypocrisy, never
to speak falsehood, never to postpone the fulfilment
of thy promises ; to hate openly those thou hatest,
and not to hide the poison of resentment in thy
heart nor let a false smile mask treachery but to
make thy countenance the sure mirror of thy mind.
She gainsayeth secret vengeance but encourageth
secret benefits. She strengthens friendships also,
that grow more firm by lapse of time and
binds them with chains of lasting adamant ; not
hers is the fickle change of mood, nor does she
permit close ties to be broken by the rumour of
some petty injury, nor is she lured to scorn the old
friend when a new one comes. Mindful of past
benefits, quick to forget wrongs, she remembers
services alike small or great and strives to outdo
<pb id="v.2.p.7"/>
them, overcoming friends -with devotion as an enemy
with arms. She safeguards the absent and is the
sole protector of those far away ; she opens not a
greedy ear to rumours, so that never does the
stealthy whisper that would injure some unsuspecting
client estrange thy sympathies.
Nor does the love that clings to the living forget
the dead, and the gratitude a father earned is
paid to his children. This kept thee loyal to
Theodosius while yet he wielded the sceptre, loyal,
too, after his death ; nor carest thou more for
thine own offspring than for the sons he entrusted
to thy guidance and protection. Just and most
faithful does Fame account those, who, though
they might deny a trust, have chosen rather to
fulfil it, unpolluted by greed of gain ; but it is not
riches, not a huge heritage of gold that Stilicho
holds in trust for the young heirs, but two hemispheres
and all that is embraced within the sun's
fiery orbit. What wouldst thou not fearlessly entrust
to him to whom a kingdom is entrusted safely ?

Defended by this buckler Honorius did not mourn
his noble sire, and on life's very threshold, ne'er
scorned by any, he dictates laws to conquered races
and sees his triumphs increase with his years. Him
thou dost seek to shape as with kindly so with severe
mind ; neither to sloth dost thou deliver him by a
ready yielding to all his wishes, nor by opposing
dost thou crush his eager spirit : as a youth thou
teachest him in secret a king's lesson — his duty to
his people ; as a reverend senior thou payest him
honour and governest the empire at a father's
bidding ; to thy lord thou givest humble worship ;
thou guidest thy master with obedience, thy sire
<pb id="v.2.p.9"/>
with love. Hence it was that he knew not passion
before matrimony and preferred to vindicate his
manhood not in a youth of debauchery, but in the
chaste bonds of legal wedlock. Blessed art thou
in having an emperor for a son-in-law ; more blessed
he with thee for father.
Care no less tender watched over Honorius'
brother, Arcadius. Rightly thou ascribest not to that
youth the outrages of the feeble, vicious mob that
seeks to screen its own mad folly behind the name
of a king. Nay, even when discord raged never
did Stilicho so burn with anger, though oft assailed
by insult, oft attacked with the sword, that he
sought to avenge the frenzy he endured by unholy
war and give a handle to civil strife ; stayed on his
loyalty, mid all the factions of a court, the hallowed
friendship of those brothers stood inviolate. Nay
more, thou dividedst equally with him Sidonian
cloaks, belts studded with pearls, jewelled togas,
breastplates thick with green emeralds, helmets
flashing with sapphires, swords with gleaming
handles thy sire had wielded, crowns bright with
the glint of manifold jewels, that both might be
equal heirs of their imperial sire's rich furniture and
apparel. Thou didst send soldiers to Byzantium
also, though civil strife was already raising its head.
Rather wouldst thou reinforce a foe than fail thy
pledge ; all that he fairly asks thou grantest and
refusest only that the withholding of which he
himself will shortly approve, and that to obtain
which were shameful.
Moreover, all the virtues whose pure aspect
puts all wickedness to flight live conjoined in thee
and, dwelling within thine heart, aid thee in the
<pb id="v.2.p.11"/>
manifold businesses of life. Justice teaches thee
to prefer the right to the useful, to obey the general
laws of mankind and never to enrich thy friends at
others' cost. Patience strengthens thy body so that
it seeks never to yield to toil. Temperance guides
thee to chaste desires. Prudence will have thee
do nought without forethought, Constancy nought
without decision and firm purpose. The deadly vices
which Tartarus sends up from his monstrous abyss
fly far from thee ; but first and foremost thou
banishest Avarice, mother of crimes, greedy for more
the more she possesses, searching ever open-mouthed
for gold ; with her thou drivest out her most foul
nurse, Ambition, who watches at the gate of the
powerful and haunts their dwelling-places, cherishing
the sale of honours for gold. This age's more turbid
stream of corruption has not drawn thee to follow its
examples — corruption which had with lapse of time
established crime and turned the custom of rapine
into a law. Beneath thy rule the rich tremble not
for the safety of ancestral lands or houses ; no
informer stalks the world set on making no matter
whom his victim. Virtue suffers no eclipse by
poverty. Thou exaltest men of all countries, asking
what are their merits not their place of birth, what
their character not whence their origin. A generous
prince takes note of our life ; rewards allure into
the ways of virtue. Hence it comes that the arts
of old flourish once more ; the path to fortune is
open to genius, while poesy again raises her despised
head. Rich and poor strive with equal zeal towards
their ends, for both see that, as poverty cannot
depress merit, so riches cannot elevate incapacity.
Fair-fronted wantonness deceives thee not, wanton-
<pb id="v.2.p.13"/>
ness, that sweet curse, which surrendering to the
arbitrament of the body dulls the wits with darkness,
enervating the limbs with bane more deadly than
that of Circe. Fair, indeed, is her face but none
is fouler within ; dyed are her cheeks ; clothed
about is she with treacherous lures, and deadly
vipers hide them in her golden hair. Many hath
she caught with the bait of pleasure, thee, though
often has she tried, she has never ensnared. No
lust bids thee wake for adultery's sake, nor does
sleep cheat the hours of toil. Neither the strains
of the lyre nor the wanton song of boys accompany
thy repast. Has any seen thee free from care, thy
mind entirely at rest, or indulging in the banquet
unless some public rejoicing commanded ? No
shameful expenditure strains the resources of the
treasury, no pitiless missive in a tiny roll disposes
of the property of the absent. Though thrifty thou
art beloved of the army, for thou neglectest not thy
soldiers in peace, and dost not only enrich them when
war is toward. Thou knowest that belated gifts,
offered in fear to those hitherto scorned, earn no
gratitude : 'tis but a useless flinging away of gold as
uselessly hoarded. Thou preventest thy soldiers'
needs and art generous over and above their expectations;
thou callest them to thy board and addressest
each by his name, mindful of all the brave deeds ever
done by each beneath thy banners. To thy gifts
thou addest praises that will ever be remembered,
whereby the grace of your close bond is doubled.
When bountiful thou dost not also turn the bounty
into a reproach, nor dost thou address those whom
thou hast advanced with the language of disdainful
patronage ; nor yet does prosperity make thee
<pb id="v.2.p.15"/>
puffed up. Nay, pride itself is far removed from
thee, pride, a vice so familiar in success, ungracious
attendant on the virtues. All, no matter when or
where, may meet and address thee. Talk over
the wine is not watched, but each guest, at liberty
to say just what he pleases, mingles grave converse
with gay and fears not for his words. Each
marvels to find an equal in the emperor's father-in-law
and the father of his country, when one so
powerful acts the citizen so graciously. With the
learned thou discoursest of antiquity, with the aged
of experience, with the soldier of valiant deeds, and
dost mingle thy talk with such pleasant wit that none
would rather hear the strains whereby Amphion
built the walls of Thebes or Orpheus' lute drew the
woods to follow him.
Hence all love thee, all anxiously pray heaven for
thee with no feigned intercession, all shout applause
at the mention of thy name and reproduce thy
form in gilded statues. What anvil should not
ring, what forge be idle, from what vast furnaces
should bronze not flow that is to shape thine image ?
What corner of the world, what region so remote
but should worship thy beloved countenance as
divine, — hadst thou not always refused such honour ?
Nay, let him snatch at such glory whom hollow
gifts inspired by fear can beguile and who despairs
of a people's love. He who in truth deserves can
alone afford to despise them.
Embassies arrive from every quarter and in
the presence of thy son-in-law pray for a hundred
voices to herald thy renown. The Gallic envoy gives
thee thanks for that, safe from attack though no
legion guards his frontier, and fearing no hostile
<pb id="v.2.p.17"/>
incursion, he builds new dwelling-places along the
banks of the Rhine and fringes the river, famed
once for the savagery of its tribes, with houses as
pleasant as those by Tiber's stream. Here Carthaginians
crown thy praise, because they possess their
lands delivered from the tyrant's rule ; there the
Pannonian, freed from the blockade, and he who
drinks the Save, grateful because he now dare
throw open the gates of cities closed for so many
years. Such sharpen once more upon the whetstone
their sickles dark with rust and cause their mattocks,
foul with want of use, to shine as of old. Each sees
again his well-remembered cottage, kisses his native
hills, and can scarce believe real the furrows cut by
his heavy plough. He hews down the forests and
renders again fit for cultivation fields which generations
had let run wild. Once more he covers the
banks of the Danube with vineyards and rejoices
to pay the taxes his forefathers paid, for it was
bloodshed that brought immunity. While thou art
safe, heaven allows the harassed body of our distracted
empire to regain its youthful vigour. Thou
dost restore all that we have lost of old under so
many princes. Only when Stilicho's hand brings
remedy can grow a scar to hide Roman wounds,
and when at last the husbandman of Illyria returns
to his farms the treasury will again be enriched
with Illyrian tribute.
But heaven's judgement is not a whit behind man's
favour. The gods unite for thine especial protection
and deliver thine enemy into thy hands upon the
sea shore or hinder his flight by the ocean's immense
barrier or make him turn his arms madly against
himself; and so, a second Pentheus, he is hewn in
<pb id="v.2.p.19"/>
pieces by his own soldiers' frenzied blades. The gods
discover for thee plots against thy life and lead
thee to the very lair of treason, even as Molossan
hounds guide the huntsman with their subtle scent.
They show forth the future by omens or by birds or
they deign to give thee clear warning in dreams.
For which things' sake countless lands in rivalry
have sought for thee the consul's robe, but thou
thyself didst oppose their desire, and thy mind,
so ready to grant favour to another, so rigorous a
critic of itself, kindling with the torch of modesty,
with bashful pleading deprecates that late reward.
And so, anxious to see accomplished the hopes, vainly
conceived through so many years, of seeing in thee
their new consul, they hasten to the gates of royal
Rome, determined, should she not listen to their
entreaties, to constrain her hesitation, and prepared
to sweep away all hindrances that delay their
prayer. They meet at the temple of the goddess
that shines bright upon the Palatine. 1 First to
speak was Spain, her head crowned with a greyleaved
garland from Minerva's olive and golden
Tagus woven into her shining robe : <q direct="unspecified"> Everything
that I have ever asked of Stilicho he has granted
me, and has begrudged only honour for himself.
Once he found it in his heart to refuse the consulship
at the hands of an emperor, his father-in-law ;
he now refuses it also from his son-in-law. If not as
a guardian from the world he rules, at least let him
receive it as a kinsman from his emperor. Counts
he it a small thing that, taking my offspring to his
arms, he so upholds my grandsons 2 in their undisturbed
rule, that the purple ennobles their native
Baetis ? That by means of fair Maria he dowers
<pb id="v.2.p.21"/>
Rome with a dynasty ? That he is looked to as
the ancestor of kings?</q>
Then warlike Gaul, her hair combed back, a rich
necklace about her neck, and javelins twain in her
hands, thus spake with kindling heart : <q direct="unspecified"> Why is
his title not yet read in the annals of Rome, who
by his own might o'ercame for me the Germans and
the Franks ? Why is the page of history still ignorant
of a name that by now should have been inscribed
therein so often ? Is, then, bringing peace to the
Rhine so light a title to fame?</q>
Next spake Britain clothed in the skin of some
Caledonian beast, her cheeks tattooed, and an azure
cloak, rivalling the swell of ocean, sweeping to her
feet : <q direct="unspecified"> Stilicho gave aid to me also when at the
mercy of neighbouring tribes, what time the Scots
roused all Hibernia against me and the sea foamed
to the beat of hostile oars. Thanks to his care I
had no need to fear the Scottish arms or tremble at
the Pict, or keep watch along all my coasts for the
Saxon who would come whatever wind might blow.</q>
Then up spake Africa, her hair gay with wheat
ears and an ivory comb and her face all sun-burned :
<q direct="unspecified"> I hoped that after Gildo's death no obstacle could
prevent Stilicho 's acceptance of the consulship. Does
he even yet refuse and hesitate to honour with the
fasces so great a triumph — he who has enabled me
utterly to forget the tearful name of Moor?</q>
After these came Italy, pliant vine and ivy interlacing
on her head, pressing the wine from plentiful
ripe grapes. Said she : <q direct="unspecified"> If you are thus eager that
Stilicho should augment the dignity of the curule
chair, you to whom the mere report can bring
delight, how much more rightly does a longing
<pb id="v.2.p.23"/>
inspire me to enjoy his presence, to attend him as
he mounts his seat and to salute his opening of the
new year's course ? </q>
One after another they pour forth these entreaties
and beg Rome to approach Stilicho in the name of
them all. Right swiftly she obeyed their behest
and seizing at once her arms winged her way quicker
than a shooting star through the clouds of heaven.
Over Etruria she flew, grazed the Apennines in her
flight, and lit Eridanus' wave with the reflexion of
her shield. She stood before the general, imposing
as mighty Pallas, terrible as Mars. The palace
trembled at the glitter of her aegis and her
helmet plumes brushed the pannelled ceiling.
Then as he stood astonished she first addressed him
with flattering reproaches : <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>I acknowledge, revered
Stilicho, that thou hast saved but not yet brought
honour to the curule chair. Of what avail to have
rid the year of the brand of slavery ? Dost thou
defend a dignity thou shunnest ? scorn what with
all thy might thou madest ? reject when offered
what thou didst save when falling ? Why dost
thou hold back ? Why disappoint my prayers ?
No danger threatens from the north, the south is
quiet ; the Moors have been subdued, Germany
has yielded, profound peace holds fast the doors of
Janus' temple. Am I not yet worthy to have thee
for my consul ? Can we believe that office unimportant
and of slender dignity to hold which
emperors think themselves honoured, that office by
means of which I have caused conquered peoples
and captive kings to pass beneath the yoke ?
</p>
               <p>If nature by her portents foreshadow coming ills
I am not besmirched therewith. Nay, that thou
<pb id="v.2.p.25"/>
countest ill omen was for the East. Yet no facts
confirm the tale I have heard ; Rumour's self
scarce smiled at such a tale of guilt. 1 The disgrace
has no proof ; no letter came to divulge the wicked
secret. In this lies thine especial virtue, that, while
consulting the senate on every question, thou hast
not mentioned this portent. No decree for the suppression
of this scandal has impaired the dignity of
this august assembly, nor has that ill-omened name
been heard in my senate. To have hesitated would
have been to share his guilt. All letters telling of
this profanation that came from the far East were
destroyed e'er they could cross the sea, that fortune's
shameful turn should not offend the chaste ears of
Italy. That infatuation of a people was best rewarded
with silence — and how strenuous were thine endeavours
that it should so be ! Joy should be his who
needs no longer pen the annals of the East. Our
Latin story knows no such blot : let others take
pains to conceal their own disgrace. Why should
I applaud the downfall of one of whose elevation
I never heard nor knew ? 'Tis for the guilty to
repent ; we have never even believed.
</p>
               <p>Yet had the guilt of all been one and this
pollution stained our axes, all the more shouldst
thou have taken the high office thou dost shun lest
that ancient dignity — ever the goal of all dignities—should
be destroyed. No consul, save Stilicho alone,
can repair that ruin. With what foreknowledge
had thy soul delayed the hour : once it would have
added lustre unto thee, now thou dost add lustre
unto it. Do thou as consul wipe out the insult
offered to all consuls that have been and yet shall
be. Give thy name to the year that posterity
<pb id="v.2.p.27"/>
may dwell thereafter securely, and that antiquity,
thus vindicated, may cease from her complaints.
Brutus was the founder of the office, let Stilicho be
its avenger. Brutus, the first consul, won liberty for
the Roman people by means of the consular fasces :
Stilicho banished the taint of slavery from those fasces.
Brutus instituted this supreme dignity ; Stilicho saved
it ; and it is greater to preserve what already is than
to create that which is not. Why do thy blushes
grant so tardy an acceptance of our prayers ? Why
does the accustomed flush o'erspread thy brow ?
World-conqueror, conquer now thine own diffidence.
</p>
               <p>Full well I know that no gift can seduce thee, yet
be pleased to admire and receive this cloak, woven
for thee on no mortal loom by Minerva and myself.
Twice together have we dipped the thread that goes
to make the cloth in purple dye and interwoven
therewith that same gold of which Lachesis has woven
the golden centuries that are to be mine beneath
thy rule. See here I have prefigured thy destined
progeny, those thy children for whom the world
prays ; soon shalt thou confess me a true prophet
and coming fate prove that my embroidery is true.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>
She spake and drew from her bosom the gift, a
consul's cloak, stiff and heavy with gold. The
glorious woof breathes Minerva's skill. Here is
depicted a palace with columns of red marble and
Maria's sacred travail. Lucina eases her labour. On
a splendid couch lies the young mother, by her side
sits her own mother, pale with anxiety yet happy
withal. The flower-crowned Nymphs take up the
babe and wash him in a golden basin. Almost could
one hear rising from the embroidery the little child's
mingled laughter and wailing. And now the babe
<pb id="v.2.p.29"/>
had grown up, recalling his father in countenance ;
Stilicho, riper in years, teaches his grandson, the
emperor that is to be, the science of war. In another
part Eucherius, the down of early manhood on his
cheeks, rode his horse that flecked its silken reins
with bloody foam. Woven himself of gold he smites
with javelin or arrow the purple stags that raise their
golden horns. Here Venus, borne in her dove-drawn
chariot, unites for the third time the hero's family
with the princely house ^ and the winged Loves
throng the affianced bride, daughter and sister of an
emperor. Eucherius now lifts the veil from the
bashful maiden's face ; Thermantia smiles upon her
brother's joy. This house now seeks the crown in the
person of either sex, it gives birth to queens and the
husbands of queens.
</p>
         <p>
Such are the gifts wherewith the goddess sought
to win Stilicho, handing to him at the same time the
ivory staff.^ She shook the urn to obtain the
customary signs and confirmed the beginning of
his task by favourable auspices. Then she clothed
with the vesture of Romulus those shoulders better
accustomed to armour. The garb of Latium covers
his breast and the toga graces what erstwhile the
cuirass protected. Thus Mars, returning victorious
from the Danube or the Scythian clime, a god of
peace now his shield is laid aside, enters the city
wearing the consul's cloak and in a chariot drawn
by white horses ; Quirinus directs the ample reins and
Bellona marches before her father's car holding aloft
the bloody oak-branch decked with the spoils won in
single combat ; Fear and his brother Terror are the
lictors and cast chains of iron on the necks of captive
<pb id="v.2.p.31"/>
barbarians, their helmets wreathed with laurel, while
Panic, her robe up-girt, walks by the yoke-horses,
brandishing a mighty battle-axe.
When Rome saw herself possessed of the consul for
whom she had prayed, <q direct="unspecified"> Now,</q> she said, <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>fain
would I hasten to the fields and woods of Elysium to
bear the news of this wondrous answer to our universal
prayer to the Curii and Fabricii who have
wept for the dignity of the consul's toga so lately
outraged. Let them now tread the meads in
joyous dance and the austere Catos not blush to
join their sport. Let the elder Brutus hear the
news and the Scipios, terror of Carthage, learn that
by one man's help I have been rescued from a
double danger and have recovered both Libya and
the fasces. One thing only is left, and do thou,
brave consul, add it to my prayers — bestow awhile
that presence she entreats upon the city which thou
hast rescued from war and famine, and restored to
the overlordship of the world. Let our famous
rostrum welcome a second Camillus and our citizens
look upon their avenger and saviour, ay, and the
common people whom thou, their leader, lovest,
the people to whom Africa, because of thee, offers
her harvests and the Rhone her crops till now unheard
of, whereby Libyan fields and Gallic abundance
are at my service and now the rainy south-wind
and now the north wafts grain to my shores and my
granaries are full whatever breeze may blow.
</p>
               <p>What thousands will then throng the Flaminian
Way ! How often will the deceptive dust disappoint
the loving expectation of those who trust to see thee
arrive every minute ! Anxiously our mothers watch
for thee ; every road will be strewn with flowers
<pb id="v.2.p.33"/>
while the consul, true image of Rome's ancient
senate, climbs the steep summit of the Pincian hill.
What applause from the theatre of Pompey ! How
often will the Murcian valley raise to heaven thy name
re-echoed by Aventine and Palatine ! Leave the
camp and let me behold thee now, soon to see thee,
consul for a second time, along with thy son-in-law.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>
While Rome so spake, Fame, on wings of rumour,
flies over the sea and with her thousand tongues bids
the chiefs speed to the capital. Not one can age
hold back, nor the long journey, nor the Alps' wintry
blasts ; Love wins the victory. Veterans whom the
fasces ennobled long since hasten to greet the year of
their colleague and avenger. So when by that birth
in death the Phoenix renews its youth and gathers its
father's ashes and carries them lovingly in its talons,
winging its way, sole of its kind, from the extreme
east to Nile's coasts, the eagles gather together and
all the fowls from every quarter to marvel at the bird
of the sun ; afar its living plumage shines, itself
redolent of the spices of its father's fragrant pyre.
There is like joy in heaven : the two Theodosii and
thine own protecting deities are glad ; the Sun himself,
decking his chariot with spring flowers, prepares
a year worthy of thee.
Far away, all unknown, beyond the range of
mortal minds, scarce to be approached by the
gods, is a cavern of immense age, hoary mother
of the years, her vast breast at once the cradle and
the tomb of time. A serpent 1 surrounds this cave,
engulfing everything with slow but all-devouring
jaws ; never ceases the glint of his green scales.
His mouth devours the back-bending tail as with
silent movement he traces his own beginning. Before
<pb id="v.2.p.35"/>
the entrance sits Nature, guardian of the threshold,
of age immense yet ever lovely, around whom throng
and flit spirits on every side. A venerable old man
writes down immutable laws : he fixes the number
of stars in each constellation and causes these to move
and those to be at rest, whereby everything lives or
dies by pre-ordained laws. 'Tis he decides Mars'
uncertain orbit, Jupiter's fixed course through the
heaven, the swift path of the moon, and the slow
march of Saturn ; he limits the wanderings of
Venus' bright chariot and of Mercury, Phoebus'
companion.
When the Sun rested upon the spacious threshold
of this cavern dame Nature ran to meet him and the
old man bent a hoary head before his proud rays.
The adamantine door swung open of its own accord
and revealed the vast interior, displaying the house
and the secrets of Time. Here in their appointed
places dwell the ages, their aspect marked by
varying metals : there are piled those of brass ;
here those of iron stand stiff ; there the silver ones
gleam bright. In a fairer part of the cave, shy of
contact with the earth, stood the group of golden
years ; of these Phoebus chooses the one of richest
substance to be marked with the name of Stilicho.
Then, bidding the rest follow behind him, he
addresses them thus as they pass. <q direct="unspecified"> Lo ! the
consul is at hand for whom we have delayed an
age of nobler ore. Go ye, years long prayed for
by man, bring back virtue ; let genius flourish once
more ; may Bacchus give you joy and fruitful Ceres
bless you. Let not the constellation of the Serpent
breathe forth too icy an air from between the two
Ploughing Oxen nor the Bear vent his excessive
<pb id="v.2.p.37"/>
cold ; let not the Lion rage with his gaping maw
nor pitiless summer inflame the claws of Cancer.
Let not Aquarius, too prodigal of his rainy urn,
flood the young seedlings with sudden storms. Let
Phrixus' ram, his horns twined with roses, extend
the fertile spring and let not the Scorpion beat
down the ripe olives with his hail. Let the Virgin
mature the fruits of Autumn and the Dog-star,
more gentle than his wont, refrain from barking at
the heavy grape-clusters.</q>
So saying he entered his garden starred with fiery
dew, the valley round which runs a river of flame
feeding with its bounteous rays the dripping weeds
whereon the horses of the sun do pasture. Here he
gathers flaming flowers wherewith he decks the
heads, the golden reins, and manes of his steeds.
With leaves from hence Lucifer and Aurora entwine
their oozy locks. Hard by the golden year, displaying
the consul's name, smiles upon his chariot, and
the stars, recommencing their courses, inscribe the
name of Stilicho in the annals of the sky.
<pb id="v.2.p.39"/>
         </p>
            </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.40" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="book" n="3" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <div2 type="poem" n="praef" id="poem.23" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PREFACE</head>
         <p>

The elder Scipio, who single-handed turned the
Punic wars back from Italy's coasts to their own
home, fought not his battles unmindful of the
Muse's art ; poets were ever the hero's special
care. For valour is always fain to seek alliance
with the Muses that they may bear witness to
her deeds ; he loves song whose exploits deserve
the meed of song. Therefore, whether to avenge his
sire's 1 death the young warrior brought into subjection
the Spanish seas or embarked upon the Libyan
wave his dreadful standards, resolved to break
with sure spear the strength of Carthage, the poet
Ennius was ever at his side and in all his campaigns
followed the trumpet's call into the midst of the fray.
Him after the battle the soldiers loved to hear sing,
and the trooper, still dripping with blood, would
applaud his verses. When Scipio had triumphed over
either Carthage — over the one to avenge his sire, over
the other his fatherland— and when at last, after the
<pb id="v.2.p.41"/>
disasters of a long war, he drove weeping Libya a
captive before his chariot wheel, Victory brought back
the Muses in her train and Mars' laurel crowned the
poet's brow.
Thee, Stilicho, our new Scipio, conqueror of a
second Hannibal more terrible than the first, — thee
after five long years Rome has given back to me and
bidden me celebrate the completion of her vows.
<pb id="v.2.p.43"/>
         </p>
               </div2>
               <div2 type="poem" id="poem.24" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N" n="1">
               <p>
Behold, O Rome, the hero whose presence the
cries of thy people and the voice of thy nobles has
long demanded. Cease now to count the stages of
his long journey and to rise as though to greet him at
the sight of every storm of dust ; no further shall uncertainty
torment thee. Full before thine eye is he
who was long before thy mind, greater than thy hopes,
more glorious than his fame. Honour thou the consul
who has restored its dignity to the consulship ; grasp
the hand which has made the Carthaginians pass once
more under the Roman yoke. Welcome the noble
heart that directs the reins of empire and secures
by its providence the equipoise of the world. Look
with joy upon the sacred face thou worshippest cast
in bronze and adorest in gold. Behold the Warrior
successful in every field, the defender of Africa,
the conqueror of Rhine and Danube.
Should he wish in accordance with ancient custom
to display the picture of his labours and show to
the people the tribes he has subdued, crowns of
laurel from north and south would contend in equally
matched rivalry. Here is a triumph rich with the
spoils of the Germans, there with those of the South ;
here would pass the Sygambri with their yellow
<pb id="v.2.p.45"/>
locks, there the black-haired Moors. He himself
would be drawn in a laurel-decked chariot by white
horses, and followed by his soldiers chanting their
festive songs. Some would lead captive kings,
others carry conquered towns wrought in bronze
or mountains or rivers. Here would go in sad
procession the river-gods of Libya, their horns
broken, there Germany and the Rhine god in
chains. Yet is not thy consul, O Rome, an unbridled
boaster of his own prowess. 'Tis not the
rewards of toil but the toil itself that he loves.
He scorns empty applause and celebrates a happier
triumph in the hearts of his fellow-citizens.
Of a surety the citadel of Rome has never welcomed
home any of her generals with greater magnificence,
no, not even Fabricius when he returned after the
surrender of Pyrrhus, nor Aemilius Paulus, conqueror
of Pella's king, when he ascended the Capitol in his
chariot. No such triumph as this threw open the
gates of Rome to Marius after his conquest of
Numidia or to Pompey after his victories in the East.
Each of these suffered from a rival faction that
murmured uneasily against their success, and envy
pursued their actions, no matter how noble, with
spiteful stings. Stilicho alone was raised above the
range of envy and the measure of mankind. For
who could be jealous of the stars' eternity, of Jove's
ancient rule in heaven, of Phoebus' omniscience 1 ?
There are some merits so transcendent that furious
envy's bounds cannot contain them. Moreover,
those other heroes owed a divided allegiance :
one gained the favour of the nobles, but was hated
of the people, one, supported by the suffrage of the
commons, enjoyed but faintly the favour of the
<pb id="v.2.p.47"/>
senate. In Stilicho's case alone class rivalry has
not raised its head : the knights welcome him with
joy, the senate with enthusiasm, while the people's
prayers rival the goodwill of the nobles.
Blessed mortal, whom the Rome that thou hast
saved calls her father ; darling of the world to whose
banner flocks the whole of Gaul, whom Spain connects
by marriage with the imperial house, for whose
advent the citizens cried with ceaseless prayer, and
whose presence the senate owed to thine illustrious
son-in-law. Not such a girl's delight in flowers, not
such the desire of the crops for rain, or of weary
sailors for a prosperous breeze as is the longing of
thy people for the sight of thee. Under no such
influence as this do the prophetic laurels wave on
Delos' coast when the brightness of Apollo's bow
announces the deity's approach. Never did Pactolus'
golden wave so swell in pride when Bacchus from
conquered Ind visited his banks. Markest thou not
how the roads cannot be seen for the people, the
roofs for the matrons ? Thanks to thy victories,
Stilicho, salvation has dawned on all beyond their
hopes. Look round on Rome's seven hills whose
sheen of gold rivals the very sun's rays ; see the
arches decked with spoil, the temples towering to
the sky, and all the buildings that celebrate this
signal triumph. Let thine astonished glance measure
the magnitude of the city thou hast saved and the
immensity of thy services. All this would live but in
the memory were the African still master of the south.
It was the custom in campaigns of olden time to
crown with oak the brow of him who by his valour
had put the enemy to flight and succeeded in
rescuing a fellow - citizen from imminent death.
<pb id="v.2.p.49"/>
But to thee what civic crown can we give for the
salvation of so many cities ? Or what honours can
recompense thy deeds ? Nor is it only for her
people's life that Rome owns herself a debtor to
thine arms, but that so she might have sweeter
enjoyment of this glorious dawn she has won back
her ancient burden of renown, her lost strength and
her conquered kingdoms. No longer do her ambassadors
kneel suppliant before the proud East and beg
that Libya may be given back to her ; gone the
shameful spectacle of our city a suitor to her own
slaves. No, relying now on her native Latin vigour,
Rome under thy leadership fights her own battles with
Roman spirit. She herself bids the standards advance ;
the toga-clad consul directs the future conqueror,
and the eagles wait upon the orders of the senate.
Of her own free choice hath Rome bestowed on
thee the consul's robe, offered thee, her avenger, the
curule chair and compelled thee to adorn her annals.
Nothing of her ancient dignity hath she lost, no
regret has she for the age of republican freedom,
since it is she who bestows the consular honour,
she who gives the order for battle. Nay, she sees
the growth of her power. Whose memory can
recall a time when the fields of Gaul and the hoes
of the Senones were at our service ? Has it ever
happened before that Tiber's wave has carried grain
from the fertile north over the ploughing of whose fields
the Lingones have toiled ? Such a harvest not only
fulfilled Rome's needs but also demonstrated the
greatness of her power ; it reminded the peoples
who was their mistress and brought in triumph from
those chill climes a tribute never before paid.
This, too, augments the majesty of Rome that the
<pb id="v.2.p.51"/>
chiefs of Libya tremble before the judgement-throne
of our people, and that, his office ended, each
governor must account under pain of death for all
the corn the Carthaginian farmer has brought in,
all that the rainy south-wind has dispatched to
Rome. Those who of late uttered their proud
judgements to broad domains here are cowed and
tremble ; those whom Africa held in dread Rome's
forum sees accused.
Stihcho gives scope for the virtues of a bygone
age and rouses a people, forgetful of their former
glory, to resume their accustomed sovereignty, to
make themselves feared, to tread powerful magistrates
beneath their heel, to mete out to crime its due
reward, to show mercy towards the erring, favour
to the innocent, punishment to the guilty, and to
exercise once more their native virtue of clemency.
He errs who thinks that submission to a noble
prince is slavery ; never does liberty show more
fair than beneath a good king. Those he himself
appoints to rule he in turn brings before the judge-ment-seat
of people and senate, and gladly yields
whether they claim reward for merit or seek for
punishment. Now the purple lays aside its pride and
disdains not to have judgement passed upon itself.
Such were the principles of rule taught by Stilicho
to his son-in-law, Honorius ; 'twas thus he guided
his youth with the reins of prudence, and with
precepts such as these directed his tender years, a
truer father to the emperor than Theodosius, his
stay in war, his adviser in peace. Thanks to him
dishonour is banished and our age blossoms with
Rome's ancient virtues ; thanks to him power, long
degraded and all but transferred, 1 no longer, forgetful
<pb id="v.2.p.53"/>
of itself, is exiled in lands of servitude but, returned
to its rightful home, restores to Italy its victorious
destiny, enjoys the promised auspices of its foundation
and gives back its scattered limbs to the head of
the empire.
Consul, all but peer of the gods, protector of a city
greater than any that upon earth the air encom-passeth,
whose amplitude no eye can measure,
whose beauty no imagination can picture, whose
praise no voice can sound, who raises a golden head
amid the neighbouring stars and with her seven
hills imitates the seven regions of heaven, mother
of arms and of law, who extends her sway o'er all
the earth and was the earliest cradle of justice, this
is the city which, sprung from humble beginnings,
has stretched to either pole, and from one small
place extended its power so as to be co-terminous
with the sun's light. Open to the blows of fate
while at one and the same time she fought a thousand
battles, conquered Spain, laid siege to the cities of
Sicily, subdued Gaul by land and Carthage by sea,
never did she yield to her losses nor show fear at
any blow, but rose to greater heights of courage
after the disasters of Cannae and Trebia, and,
while the enemy's fire threatened her, and her
foe 1 smote upon her walls, sent an army against
the furthest Iberians. Nor did Ocean bar her way ;
launching upon the deep, she sought in another
world for Britons to be vanquished. 'Tis she alone
who has received the conquered into her bosom
and like a mother, not an empress, protected the
human race with a common name, summoning those
whom she has defeated to share her citizenship
and drawing together distant races with bonds of
<pb id="v.2.p.55"/>
affection. To lier rule of peace we owe it that the
world is our home, that we can live where we please,
and that to visit Thule and explore its once dreaded
wilds is but a sport ; thanks to her all and sundry-
may drink the waters of the Rhone and quaff Orontes'
stream, thanks to her we are all one people. Nor
will there ever be a limit to the empire of Rome,
for luxury and its attendant vices, and pride with
sequent hate have brought to ruin all kingdoms else.
Twas thus that Sparta laid low the foolish pride
of Athens but to fall herself a victim to Thebes ;
thus that the Mede deprived the Assyrian of empire
and the Persian the Mede. Macedonia subdued
Persia and was herself to yield to Rome. But Rome
found her strength in the oracles of the Sibyl, her
vigour in the hallowed laws of Numa. For her
Jove brandishes his thunderbolts ; 'tis she to whom
Minerva offers the full protection of her shield ; to
her Vesta brought her sacred flame, Bacchus his
rites, and the turret-crowned mother of the gods
lier Phrygian lions. Hither to keep disease at bay
came, gliding with steady motion, the snake whose
home was Epidaurus, and Tiber's isle gave shelter
to the Paeonian 1 serpent from beyond the sea.
This is the city whom thou, Stilicho, and heaven
guard, her thou protectest, mother of kings and
generals, mother, above all, of thee. Here Eucherius
first beheld the light, here the queen his mother showed
the babe to his imperial grandsire who rejoiced to
lift a grandson upon his knee and to let him crawl
upon his purple robes. Rome had foreknowledge of
his destined glory and was glad, for so dear a pledge
would keep thee ever her faithful citizen.
But think not this people ungrateful nor such as
<pb id="v.2.p.57"/>
knows not how to repay benefits. Turn but the
pages of history and thou wilt find how often it
has faced war for an ally's sake, how often bestowed
as a gift on friendly monarchs lands won at the
expense of Italian blood. Yet never were public
thanks poured forth with such consent. For what
prince has not sought with every blandishment to
be called lord and father — titles which the amphi-theatres
echo back to thee day after day ? Hail,
consul, to thy new titles ! Mars' people calls thee
lord and Brutus gainsays them not ; what till now
no terror could compel Rome's free citizens to endure,
they freely offered to their love for Stilicho. Wheresoever
thy shining form is seen they haste to greet
thee and raise to heaven thy name ; nor is their
wandering gaze ever sated with looking upon thee
whom they love when thou enterest the Circus in thy
shining robes of gold or art present at the games or,
seated on thine ivory throne, dispensest justice in the
forum or, with thine attendant lictors, mountest the
rostrum thronged with the dense and surging crowd.
But what were the acclamations of the great, how
unfeigned their rejoicings when Victory, soaring
aloft with outspread wings, herself threw open her
holy temple to the hero ? Maiden that rejoicest in
the green bay and lovest the tokens of triumphant
fight, guardian of our empire, sole healer of our
wounds, that makest our toils as though they were not,
whether it pleaseth thee to dwell amid the stars of
Ariadne's crown or nearer to the fervid Lion, whether
thou art seated on the lofty sceptre of Jove or Pallas'
shield or calmest the sighs of weary Mars, be ever
present to Latium and grant, goddess, the prayers
of thy senate. May Stilicho often crown thy portals
<pb id="v.2.p.59"/>
and bear thee back with him to his armies. Accompany
and bless him in war and give him back in
robes of peace to our council-chambers. Always
has he brought thee home in a spirit of mercy and
kept thee kindly to the vanquished nor ever stained
thy laurels with cruelty. He neither looks with
disdain on his fellow-citizens nor harries the anxious
city with his legionaries ; but true consul now that
the war is ended he comes accompanied only by his
lictors nor seeks the useless protection of the sword,
guarded only by a people's love.
Handling his great wealth in no niggard spirit he
does not hesitate to double his lavish expenses and
after giving wondrous games in honour of his
soldiery and of Honorius reserves yet greater for
Rome. They say that Jove at Minerva's birth
showered gold upon lucky Rhodes ; that while
Bacchus forced an egress from his father's thigh
Hermus grew pale and turned to that same metal ;
that Midas, fated to suffer hunger as a punishment
for his greed, converted to shining gold everything
that he touched. Be these stories true or false thy
liberality exceeds the waters of Hermus, the touch
of Midas, the Thunderer's shower. Thy hands, as
prodigal of gifts as of daring deeds, o'ershadow the
past and will o'ershadow the future. Should fire
have melted the countless mass of silver thou
bestowest as though it were the cheapest of metals,
lakes and rivers of silver might have been formed.
Thou too, Latonia, queen alike of the woods and
of the stars, art moved by no small care for Stilicho ;
thou toilest to distinguish our spectacles with the
forest's noblest denizens, and on the dizzy summits
of Alpine rocks layest aside thy bow and summonest
<pb id="v.2.p.61"/>
thy virgin companions and the chaste band of thy
quiver-bearing followers. Thither they come, their
shoulders and arms bare, spears in their hands and
arrows slung across their backs, beautiful though
unadorned ; red their cheeks, dusty and suffused with
sweat ; their fierce virginity betrays not their sex ;
disordered their hair ; girdles twain prevent their
dresses from flowing down below their knees. Golden-haired
Leontodame precedes her comrades, Nebro-phone,
foster child of Mount Lycaeus, follows her,
and Thero whose arrows hold Maenalus in subjection.
Fiery Britomartis hastens from Cretan Ida and
Lycaste, peer of the western winds in flight. There
join them the twin sisters Hecaërge, terror of beasts,
and Opis, deity beloved of hunters, Scythian maids ;
their preference for Delos 1 over the frosts of the
north made them goddesses and queens of the woods.
These were the seven chiefs who came ; there
followed them a second band of Nymphs, Diana's
lovely company, a hundred from Taygetus, a hundred
from Cynthus' summit, a hundred more whose first
home was beside the chaste waters of Ladon. When
she saw these gathered together Delia thus began :
<q direct="unspecified"> Friends who hate the rites of wedlock even as
I hate them, who scour the snowy mountains in
virgin companies, mark you how the gods with
unanimous favour glorify this year for Latium ?
How many herds of horses Neptune provides from
every quarter of the world ? How that none of my
brother Apollo's lyres can refrain from sounding
the praises of Stilicho ? From us too let Stilicho
receive the favour we justly owe him ; the task needs
no javelin ; let our arrows remain bloodless in our
unopened quivers. Let every bow refrain from its
<pb id="v.2.p.63"/>
wonted hunting and the blood of our prey be spilled
but in the arena. Not for now their death ; close
the glades with net and cages and lead the beasts
captive ; withhold your impatient arrows ; spare
the monsters of the forest whose death shall win
applause for our consul. Divide and haste in every
direction ; my breathless course is towards the
Syrtes ; do you, Cretan Lycaste and Opis, bear me
company. My purpose is to traverse the unfruitful
desert ; Mauretania has given ere now her animals
to other consuls as a gift, to this consul alone she
owes them as a conquered land owes tribute.
While we track out the dread progeny of Libya do
you hunt the glades and rocks of Europe. Let
joy banish fear from the shepherd's breast and his
pipe hymn Stilicho in the dreadless forests. As his
laws have given peace to the cities so let his shows
give peace to the mountains.</q>
She spake and straightway is borne from the
leafy Alps across the sea. Hinds bow their necks
to her chariot's yoke, hinds whom the dewy moon
conceived in her fertile caverns beneath the threshold
of the morning sky to be the glory of the goddess.
White their skins as driven snow ; gold marks their
foreheads whence spring branching golden horns
lofty as the tallest beech-trees. Opis holds the
reins. Lycaste carries the fine-wrought nets and
golden snares, and deathless Molossian hounds run
barking about the chariot amid the clouds. Five
others thus equipped (such were Diana's orders)
hasten this way and that, each at the head of her
own company ; there follow them dogs of various
shape, breed and character ; some whose heavy
jowls fit them for big game, some swift of foot,
<pb id="v.2.p.65"/>
some keen of scent ; shaggy Cretans bay, slender
Spartans, and Britons that can break the backs of
mighty bulls. Britomartis scours the woods of
Dalmatia and the precipitous ridges of Pindus, her
hair flying in the wind. Thou, Leontodame, surroundest
the glades of Gaul and huntest the marshes
of Germany, tracking out any huge boar, his tusks
flexed with age, that may have taken shelter among
the sedges that flank the Rhine. Swift Hecaërge
tires the cloud-capped Alps, the valleys of the
Apennines, and the snows of Garganus. Thero with
her dogs explores the caves of Spain and from their
recesses ousts the horrid bears of whose bloody jaws
full oft Tagus' flood has failed to quench the thirst,
and whose bodies, numbed with cold, the holm oak
of the Pyrenees o'ershadows with its leaves. The
manlike maiden Nebrophone hunts the mountains
of Corsica and Sicily and captures deer and other
harmless beasts, beasts that are the joy of the rich
amphitheatre and the glory of the woods.
Whatsoever inspires fear with its teeth, wonder
with its mane, awe with its horns and bristling coat — all
the beauty, all the terror of the forest is taken.
Guile protects them not ; neither strength nor
weight avails them ; their speed saves not the fleet
of foot. Some roar enmeshed in snares ; some are
thrust into wooden cages and carried off. There
are not carpenters enough to fashion the wood ;
leafy prisons are constructed of unhewn beech and
ash. Boats laden with some of the animals traverse
seas and rivers ; bloodless from terror the rower's
hand is stayed, for the sailor fears the merchandise
he carries. Others are transported over land in
wagons that block the roads with the long pro-
<pb id="v.2.p.67"/>
cession, bearing the spoils of the mountains. The
wild beast is borne a captive by those troubled cattle
on whom in times past he sated his hunger, and
each time that the oxen turned and looked at their
burden they pull away in terror from the pole.
By now Phoebus' sister had wandered o'er the
torrid plains of Libya and chosen out superb Hons
who had often put the Hesperides to flight, filled
Atlas with alarm at their wind-tossed manes, and
plundered far and wide the flocks of Ethiopia, lions
whose terrible cries had never struck upon the
herdsmen's ears but as heralding their destruction.
To catch them had been used no blazing torches,
no twigs strewn over turf undermined ; the voice
of a tethered kid had not allured their hunger nor
had a diggèd pit ensnared them : of their own free
will they gave themselves up to capture and rejoiced
at being seen the prey of so great a goddess.
At length the countryside breathes again and
the Moorish farmers unbar their now safe huts.
Then Latonia collected grey-spotted ^ leopards and
other marvels of the south and huge ivory tusks
which, carved with iron into plaques and inlaid
with gold to form the glistening inscription of
the consul's name, should pass in procession among
lords and commons. All India stood in speechless
amaze to see many an elephant go shorn of the glory
of his tusks. Seated upon their black necks despite
their cries the goddess shook the fix fed ivory and
tearing it up from its bloody roots disarmed the
monstrous mouths. Nay, she fain would have
brought the elephants themselves as a spectacle but
feared that their vast weight would retard the ships.
Fiercely o'er the Tyrrhene wave echoes the fleet
<pb id="v.2.p.69"/>
that holds the Libyan breed, and, as he coils his
tail upon the stern, a lion stretches to the prow ;
that single beast the labouring bark can scarce
uplift ; deep down below the waters is heard the
roaring. Out rushes the leviathan. Neptune compares
these land prodigies to his and admits that
his are not their equal. So whene'er victorious
Bacchus ploughs the Red Sea's waves, Silenus
sways the helm, the urgent Satyrs sweat upon
their oars and the oxhide drums, smitten by the
Bacchants, summon the rowers of Bromius to toil
at the thwarts ; ivy-wreaths deck the benches,
the pliant vine entwines the mast ; a drunken snake
glides out upon the yardarms ; lynxes run and leap
along the sheets that drip with wine, and unaccustomed
tigers stare in amaze at the canvas.
<pb id="v.2.p.71"/>
               </p>
                  </div2>
            </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>