<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 43-45 - 43</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Schlesinger" role="editor">Alfred C. Schlesinger, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XLIII-XLV With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1951: published without copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.3"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="book">
                <head>Book XLIII</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same summer in which this campaign
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> was
                    fought in Thessaly, the staff-officer . . ., <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The name is lost; perhaps it was the ex-consul Gaius
                        Claudius (cf. XLII. xlix. 9), since the other ex-consul, Mucius, was made a
                            <hi rend="italics">legatus</hi> (XLII. lxvii. 9, cf. also lviii. 13).
                    </note> sent by the consul into Illyricum, besieged two rich cities. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Ceremia <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The name is uncertain, and is not mentioned elsewhere; the location of the
                        town can only be conjectured. </note> he compelled by force of arms to
                    surrender; and he left to its inhabitants all their possessions, in order by his
                    reputation for clemency <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The usual
                        practice was to plunder a city which had been stormed, and spare one which
                        surrendered (XXXVII. xxxii. 12). </note> to entice the dwellers in the
                    walled city of Carnuns. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After he had been
                    unable either to induce them to surrender or to capture them by blockade, in
                    order that his soldiery might not be worn out by two sieges and gain nothing, he
                    plundered the city which he had previously left untouched. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Gaius Cassius the second consul failed to
                    accomplish anything of note in Gaul, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The active sector of his province of Italy (XLII. xxxii. 4). </note> which
                    had fallen to his lot, and made a vain attempt to lead his legions through
                    Illyricum into Macedonia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul's venture
                    on this journey became known to the senate through an <pb n="p.5"/> embassy from
                    Aquileia, which complained that their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 171</note> colony was new <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">It had been founded ten years before, cf. XL. xxxiv.
                        2.</note> and weak and had been as yet insufficiently fortified against the
                    surrounding hostile tribes of Histrians and Illyrians; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> on their requesting that the senate should concern itself
                    with means for fortifying this colony, they were asked if they wished this
                    matter to be entrusted to Gaius Cassius the consul, but replied that Cassius,
                    having mustered his army at Aquileia, had set out through Illyricum for
                    Macedonia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This report seemed unbelievable at
                    first, and the senators each thought to himself that perhaps a campaign against
                    the Carnians or Histrians had been begun. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then
                    the envoys from Aquileia said that they knew and dared assert nothing more than
                    that thirty days' grain had been issued to the soldiery, and that guides who
                    knew the roads from Italy into Macedonia had been sought out and taken along.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then indeed the senate was incensed that
                    the consul had such effrontery as to leave his own district, trespass upon his
                    colleague's, lead his army by a dangerous, untried route <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Cassius would either have had to traverse
                        uninterruptedly mountainous country, as he followed the coast, or to go far
                        inland, approximately to the line of the modern railway to Saloniki, as
                        Philip planned for the Bastarnae; but these would have been aided by
                        friendly tribes, whereas Cassius would have been beyond aid. The Romans had
                        always used the short sea-route from Brundisium to Illyricum and Greece,
                        little as they liked seafaring. </note> among foreign peoples, and leave
                    open to so many tribes the way into Italy. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The most recent threat from this direction had been in
                        186- <date when="-0183">183 B.C.</date> , cf. XXXIX. xxii. 6, xlv. 6-7, liv,
                        though the Transalpine Gauls who had moved in near Aquileia had acted
                        peaceably enough. Cf. the plans of Philip for an invasion of Italy by the
                        Bastarnae, XL. lvii. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A full senate decreed that the praetor Gaius
                    Sulpicius should name three envoys from among the senators, who should that very
                    day set out from the city and with all possible speed overtake the consul
                    Cassius, wherever he might be; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> they were to
                    declare to him that he must not engage in war with any people unless <pb n="p.7"
                    /> the senate had determined on war against them. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Strictly speaking, both the senate and the people had
                        to approve the undertaking of a war; cf. the condemnations of similar
                        unauthorized forays in XXXVIII. xlv. 5 and XLI. vii. 7-8. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> The
                    following envoys set out: Marcus Cornelius Cethegus, Marcus Fulvius, Publius
                    Marcius Rex. Fear for the consul and his army displaced for the present any
                    consideration of fortifying Aquileia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next, envoys of several peoples from each of
                    the Spains were presented to the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After
                    complaining of the greed and arrogance of Roman officials, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On the overbearing attitude of Roman officials at this
                        time, cf. below, vii-viii. </note> they begged of the senate on bended knees
                    that it would not permit them, its allies, to be more wretchedly despoiled and
                    harassed than its enemies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Since they
                    complained of other acts of injustice also and it was in fact obvious that money
                    had been extorted, the task was assigned to the praetor Lucius Canuleius, to
                    whom Spain <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The two provinces
                        recognized in <date when="-0197">197 B.C.</date> (XXXII. xxviii. 11 and the
                        note) were combined during this war in order to leave one praetor free to
                        command the fleet ( <date when="-0171">171 B.C.</date> , XLII. xxxi. 9;
                        presumably in 170; 168, XLIV. xvii. 9; in 167, the two provinces were again
                        separated, XLV. xvi. 1). </note> had been allotted, to assign for each man,
                    from whom the Spaniards were seeking to recover money, five judges <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Sometimes such a board was chosen by
                        the parties to the case, either from their own number, or from a panel
                        proposed by the magistrate in charge, but several inscriptions ( <hi
                            rend="italics">e.g.,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">C.I.L.</hi> 2 I. 585, p. 460. xxxiv) mention choice of
                        the arbiters by the magistrate. <hi rend="italics">Recuperatores</hi>
                        (literally <quote>recoverers</quote> ) were usually concerned with a claim
                        involving Romans <hi rend="italics">vs.</hi> foreigners. As foreigners, the
                        Spaniards had to be represented by Roman advocates. </note> of senatorial
                    rank and to permit the Spaniards to choose any advocates they might wish.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The decree of the senate was read to the
                    envoys, who had been summoned to the senate-house, and they were ordered to name
                    their advocates. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They named four, Marcus <pb
                        n="p.9"/> Porcius Cato, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He had
                        benefited the province in <date when="-0195">195 B.C.</date> by establishing
                        order and developing mining, cf. XXXIV. xxi. A speech in this case seems to
                        have been once extant under the title <hi rend="italics">Pro Hispanis de
                            frumento</hi> (Charisius II. 198. 224 Keil) in which Cato attacked
                        Publius Furius Philus, praetor of Nearer Spain in <date when="-0174">174
                            B.C.</date> (XLI. xxi. 3, cf. below, 8) for unjust valuation of grain
                        received as tribute (Asconius on Cicero <hi rend="italics">Divinatio in</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">M. Caecilium</hi> 66, <hi rend="italics">Cato
                            accusavit</hi> . . . <hi rend="italics">P. Furium pro iisdem</hi> ( <hi
                            rend="italics">Lusitanis) propter iniquissimam aestimationem
                            frumenti</hi> ), cf. below, 12. </note> Publius Cornelius Scipio son of
                    Gnaeus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note>
                    Lucius Aemilius Paulus son of Lucius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Scipio had been praetor in Farther Spain in <date when="-0193">193
                            B.C.</date> (XXXIV. xliii. 7 records his assignment, XXXV. i. 3-12, his
                        exploits), and Paulus had been in Farther Spain as praetor and propraetor
                        from 191 to <date when="-0189">189 B.C.</date> (his assignment in XXXVI. ii.
                        6; his activities, XXXVII. lvii. 5-6). </note> and Gaius Sulpicius Gallus.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The case of Marcus Titinius, who had been
                    praetor in Nearer Spain during the consulship of Aulus Manlius and Marcus
                    Junius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In <date when="-0178">178
                            B.C.</date> ; Titinius was also in Spain the following two years (XLI.
                        ix. 3, xv. 11, xxvi. 1). A namesake was City Praetor in 178. </note> was
                    first taken up by a board of judges. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This is the earliest known trial of an official thus accused by provincials;
                        previous complaints of like nature (cf. XXIX. xvi-xix, XXXIX. iii. 1-3,
                        below, v) had been adjusted by the senate directly, or through the consuls.
                    </note> The trial was twice adjourned, and at the third session the defendant
                    was acquitted. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A dispute arose between the
                    envoys of the two provinces; the peoples of Nearer Spain chose as advocates
                    Marcus Cato and Publius Scipio, those of Farther Spain took Lucius Paulus and
                    Sulpicius Gallus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There were brought before
                    judges by the peoples of the nearer province Publius Furius Philus, by those of
                    the farther province Marcus Matienus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cf. XLI. xxviii. 5, where the first name is given as Gaius. </note> ; the
                    former had been praetor three years before, in the <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> consulship of Spurius Postumius and Quintus Mucius, the
                    latter had served two years before, when Lucius Postumius and Marcus Popilius
                    were consuls. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Both were accused on most
                    serious charges and the cases were adjourned; when the time came for a fresh
                    trial, the defence reported that they had left Roman territory to go into exile.
                    Furius went for his exile to Praeneste, Matienus to <pb n="p.11"/> Tibur. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius VI. xiv. 7 mentions these
                        towns and Naples as <hi rend="italics">asyla</hi> for exiles, and praises as
                        a form of Roman moderation the institution of voluntary exile. In these
                        private suits the exile was apparently not made official by the <quote>ban
                            of fire and water,</quote> as in cases prosecuted by the state, cf.
                        XXVI. iii. 12. Exiles automatically surrendered their Roman citizenship and
                        took up that of the town in which they took refuge. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There was a rumour that the advocates <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> would not
                    allow accusations against men of rank and influence; this suspicion was
                    increased by Canuleius the praetor, who gave up this investigation, began to
                    hold a levy, and then suddenly left for his province, so that no more men should
                    be assailed by the Spaniards. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Though bygones
                    were thus shrouded in silence, the senate voted for the future what the
                    Spaniards had requested —that a Roman official should not set the price for
                    grain, nor compel the Spaniards to sell their five-per-cent quotas <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Roman officials are forbidden to demand
                        an arbitrary money-equivalent for grain furnished them, perhaps for their
                        own use and that of their army; nor are they arbitrarily to set the price
                        paid for the grain which the Spaniards were required to sell to the Romans,
                        in order to help maintain the flow of grain to Italy. Whereas in Sicily
                        tithes of grain constituted a tax traditional in the region and continued by
                        the Romans, in Spain the tax ( <hi rend="italics">stipendium</hi> ) paid to
                        the Romans as overlords seems to have been in money, or perhaps in precious
                        metals; the twentieths here mentioned were not a tax, but a compulsory sale,
                        like the <hi rend="italics">second</hi> tithe which might on occasion be
                        required of Sicily. The size of the quota perhaps reflects the lesser
                        fertility of Spain. Special levies of money and grain from Spain are
                        mentioned in XXIX. iii. 5 (a punitive levy), XXX. iii. 2 (a war-levy for the
                        army in Africa) and XXX. xxvi. 6 (perhaps the regular tax). </note> at the
                    price he wished, and that no officers should be placed over their towns to
                    collect money. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Another embassy, also from Spain, of a novel
                    class of people, arrived. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Stating that they
                    were the children of Roman soldiers and of Spanish women, between whom legal
                    marriage could not exist, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Children of
                        such unrecognized marriages were not illegitimate in the modern sense, but
                        had the mother's status, so that these people were legally Spaniards.
                    </note> and that they numbered over four thousand souls, they asked that a town
                    be given them in which to live. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate
                    decreed that they should declare before Lucius Canuleius the praetor their own
                    names and the names of any slaves they might have set free, <pb n="p.13"/> and
                    that it was the pleasure of the senate that these <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> people should be settled
                    at Carteia near the Ocean; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Carteia
                        was at the head of the Bay of Algeciras, just west of Gibraltar. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> any present inhabitants of Carteia who wished
                    to remain at home would have the opportunity to be members of the colony, but on
                    assigned land. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> they might not keep their former land, but
                        must take a share along with the newcomers. </note> This colony was to have
                    Latin rights <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was the first
                        colony outside of the Italian peninsula to be given Latin rights; it was, in
                        legal theory, an autonomous ally of Rome, whose citizens had the rights of
                        trade and intermarriage with Romans. </note> and to be called the freedmen's
                    colony. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At the same time there came from Africa both
                    Prince Gulussa, the son of Masinissa, as ambassador for his father, and
                    Carthaginian envoys. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The previous
                        story of the boundary dispute between these parties is told in XLII.
                        xxiii-xxiv. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Gulussa was presented to the senate first, and
                    set forth what supplies had been sent by his father for the Macedonian campaign
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As related in XLII. Ixii. 2, lxv.
                        12-14, lxvii. 8.</note> ; he also promised that if they wished to order
                    anything further, his father would furnish it, as due return to the Roman
                    people, and he warned the senators to beware of treachery from the
                    Carthaginians; they had adopted the plan, he added, of preparing a large fleet,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Carthaginians had been left
                        with only ten triremes (the cruisers of this period) at the end of the
                        Second Punic War (XXX. xxxvii. 3); the treaty did not expressly forbid the
                        rebuilding of the fleet, but the Romans would no doubt have prevented such
                        action, except for the reason here alleged by the Carthaginians; on naval
                        help to Rome by the Carthaginians, cf. XXXVI. xlii. 2 and XLII. lvi. 6.
                    </note> ostensibly for the Romans and against the Macedonians; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> when this fleet should be ready and equipped, the
                    Carthaginians would be free to decide for themselves who should be considered an
                    enemy or who an ally. The instilling of this [suspicion caused the senate] . . .
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Four quaternions are lost from
                        the MS. at this point. The following matters were treated: the outcome of
                        the dispute between Masinissa and Carthage; the choice of magistrates and
                        their provinces for <date when="-0170">170 B.C.</date> —the consuls were
                        Aulus Hostilius Mancinus for Macedonia and Aulus Atilius Serranus for Italy
                        (cf. below), while the praetor Lucius Hortensius received the fleet; the
                        mistreatment of Coronea by Licinius (cf. below, iv. 5 and 11, and the
                        Summary); the defeat of the praetor Lucretius at Oreüs (Plutarch, <hi
                            rend="italics">Aemilius Paullus</hi> ix); the secession of the Epirotes
                        and Hostilius' narrow escape from them (cf. below, xxi. 4, Polybius XXVII.
                        13-14, Diodorus XXX. 5); Hostilius' unsuccessful campaign (cf. XLIV. ii. 6
                        and xxxvi. 10); Macedonian successes against the Dardani and Illyrians (cf.
                        below, xix. 14, the Summary, and Orosius iv. 20); and the flare-up in Spain
                        (cf. the Summary), the account of which comes to a conclusion as the text
                        resumes. </note>
                </p>
                <pb n="p.15"/>
                <p> . <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> . . they thereafter <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <quote>thereafter</quote> is a conjecture not usually accepted by editors.
                        The <quote>heads</quote> evidently belonged to two leaders of the revolt;
                        those who brought them to the Spanish camp may have been released prisoners.
                    </note> caused such terror as <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 170</note> they entered the camp, displaying the heads,
                    that if the army had been brought up at once, the camp might have been taken.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Even as it was, a great panic took place,
                    and there were those who advised sending envoys to beg for peace; many cities,
                    too, on hearing this news, offered themselves in surrender. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> These cities cleared themselves and placed the blame on the
                    folly of two men <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Olonicus was the
                        chief rebel, according to the Summary.</note> who had of their own accord
                    gone to meet their punishment, and the praetor, having accepted these excuses,
                    set out at once for the other cities and, since everybody obeyed his <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> commands, passed without using his army through a
                    region, now peaceful, which shortly before had been aflame with a huge uprising.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This clemency of the praetor, whereby
                    without bloodshed he had tamed a very war-like people, was the more pleasing to
                    the Roman commons and the Fathers because the campaign in Greece had been
                    conducted with too much cruelty and greed by both the consul Licinius and
                    Lucretius the praetor. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Lucretius was assailed
                    in his absence by the tribunes of the people in meeting after meeting, although
                    it was stated in his behalf that he was absent in the service of the state; but
                    in that day even the neighbourhood of the city was such unknown territory that
                    he was at that time on his estate at Antium <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Less than 35 miles from Rome.</note> and was engaged in
                    bringing water to Antium from the River Loracina <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">A small stream east of the city.</note> at the <pb
                        n="p.17"/> cost of his spoils. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He is said
                    to have let the contract <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 171</note> for this work at one hundred and thirty thousand <hi
                        rend="italics">asses;</hi> he also decorated with paintings from the booty
                    the temple of Aesculapius. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According
                        to Valerius Maximus I. viii. 2 this temple was earlier than that of
                        Aesculapius at Rome. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Disapprobation and disgrace were diverted from
                    Lucretius to Hortensius, his successor, by envoys from Abdera, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Abdera was apparently a free ally of
                        Rome.</note> who wept before the senate-house and complained that their city
                    had been stormed and plundered by Hortensius; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    the reason for the destruction of the city had been, they said, that when the
                    praetor had ordered a hundred thousand <hi rend="italics">denarii</hi> and fifty
                    thousand peeks of wheat, they had asked for a stay, during which they might send
                    envoys about the matter to the consul Hostilius and to Rome. Hardly had they
                    come to the consul when they heard that their town had been stormed, their
                    leading men beheaded with the axe, and the rest sold at auction. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> This seemed to the senate a disgraceful occurrence,
                    and they issued the same decree about the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                    people of Abdera which they had issued the preceding year about the people of
                    Coronea, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This city of Boeotia, an
                        opponent of Rome, cf. XLII. xliv. 4, lxiii. 3, had been severely handled by
                        the consul Licinius, cf. above, sec. 5, and the Summary, also Zonaras 9. 22.
                        Livy's account of the event has been lost, cf. above, p. 13, n. 7. </note>
                    and instructed Quintus Maenius the praetor <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Apparently the praetor in charge of aliens ( <hi
                            rend="italics">peregrinus</hi> ), since in ch. vi. 10 he receives the
                        Lampsacenes as allies; the city praetor, Marcus Raecius, was absent, cf.
                        below, ix. 6 and the note. </note> to make a similar proclamation before an
                    assembly. Furthermore, two envoys, Gaius Sempronius Blaesus and Sextus Julius
                    Caesar, were sent to restore the people of Abdera to freedom. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> To these same envoys instructions were given to inform both
                    Hostilius the consul and Hortensius the praetor that <milestone n="13??"
                        unit="section"/> the senate had resolved that an improper war had been
                    undertaken against the people of Abdera, and that it was just that all who were
                        <pb n="p.19"/> enslaved should be sought out and restored to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> freedom. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this same time complaints were made to the
                    senate about Gaius Cassius, who had been consul the year before and was then a
                    tribune of the soldiers <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cassius seems
                        to have obtained this position directly after his consulship, to avoid
                        returning to Rome and giving an account of his hare-brained attempt to reach
                        Macedonia from north Italy (above, ch. i. 4-12). </note> in Macedonia with
                    Aulus Hostilius, and envoys of Cincibilus, a king of the Gauls, arrived.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king's brother spoke before the
                    senate, complaining that Gaius Cassius had ravaged the land of the Alpine
                    tribes, their allies, and had dragged thence into slavery many thousand persons.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> About the same time envoys of the
                    Carnians, Histrians, and Iapydes arrived; they said, first, that guides had been
                    demanded of them by the consul Cassius, to show him the way as he was leading
                    his army to Macedonia; he had left them peaceably as if to wage a war elsewhere.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Next, that returning from the middle of
                    his journey, he had traversed their territory as an enemy; slaughter, pillage
                    and burning had taken place everywhere; nor did they know to that very minute
                    why they had been treated as enemies by the consul. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Both to the absent prince of the Gauls and to these peoples
                    the answer was given that the senate neither had known that these occurrences of
                    which they complained would take place nor, if they had taken place, did the
                    senate approve. But to condemn an ex-consul in his absence without a trial would
                    be an injustice, since he was absent in the service of the state; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> when Gaius Cassius should have returned from
                    Macedonia, then, if they wished <pb n="p.21"/> to accuse him to his face, on
                    hearing the case the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 171</note> senate would see to it that amends were made. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> It was voted not only to make a reply to these
                    peoples, but to send envoys, two to the prince beyond the Alps and three to the
                    several other peoples; the envoys were to announce what the opinion pronounced
                    by the Fathers was. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They determined to send to
                    the envoys gifts of two thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> apiece and to the
                    two princely brothers the following special gifts, two twisted necklaces made of
                    five pounds of gold and five silver vessels of twenty pounds, and two horses
                    with trappings for head and chest, along with their grooms, and cavalry weapons
                    and military cloaks, and to the princes' attendants, both free and slave,
                    garments. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These things were sent; the
                    following was granted at their request-that they should have the privilege of
                    buying ten horses apiece and of exporting them from Italy. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> As envoys there were sent with the Gauls across the Alps
                    Gaius Laelius and Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Lepidus was chief of the Senate for the second time,
                        and <hi rend="italics">pontifex maximus,</hi> cf. XL. li. 1, and below, ch.
                        xv. 6; Laelius was probably the noted friend of Scipio Africanus; this
                        embassy seems then to have been regarded as very important; the members of
                        the other embassy are not otherwise known, unless Sicinius was not Gaius,
                        but the Gnaeus Sicinius mentioned in XLII. ix. 8 and elsewhere. </note> and
                    to the other peoples, Gaius Sicinius, Publius Cornelius Blasio, and Titus
                    Memmius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time envoys from a large number of
                    the states of Greece and Asia gathered in Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The Athenians were presented first; they pointed out that they had sent their
                    whole fleet and army to Publius Licinius the consul and Gaius Lucretius the
                    praetor; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> these officers had not employed their
                    forces, but had ordered a hundred thousand pecks of grain; although they tilled
                    a barren soil and supported even their farmers on imported grain, yet they had
                        <pb n="p.23"/> gathered this amount so as not to fail in their duty; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> and they
                    were ready to furnish other things too which might be ordered. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Milesians, without mentioning anything which they had
                    furnished, promised that if the senate wished to order anything for the war they
                    were ready to furnish it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The envoys of
                    Alabanda announced that they had built a temple to the City of Rome, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Such a temple had been built by Smyrna
                        in <date when="-0195">195 B.C.</date> , Tacitus, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Annals</hi> IV. 56. The conception of Rome as a goddess was quite
                        un-Roman; it was invented by Greeks, adopted by Roman poets ( <hi
                            rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Vergil, <hi rend="italics">Aeneid</hi> VI.
                        781-7, Lucan, <hi rend="italics">Pharsalia</hi> I. 186-192), but not
                        officially adopted as part of Roman religion till the reign of Hadrian
                        (Cassius Dio LXIX. 4. 3). The divinity of cities, either personified or
                        represented by their <quote>Fortune,</quote> seems like a last freakish form
                        of the glorification of the <quote>polls</quote> found in Aristotle ( <hi
                            rend="italics">Politics I.</hi> i. 11: <quote> Thus also the city-state
                            is prior in nature to the household and to each of us individually. For
                            the whole must necessarily be prior to the part ... </quote> tr.
                        Rackham, <hi rend="italics">L.C.L.</hi> ). </note> and had established
                    annual games in honour of that divinity; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> they
                    had also brought with them a golden crown of fifty pounds' weight to place in
                    the Capitol as a gift to Jupiter Greatest and Best, besides three hundred
                    cavalry shields; these they would deliver to whomever the senate ordered. They
                    asked permission to place their gift in the Capitol and to offer sacrifice.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same request was also made by the
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> people of Lampsacus, who brought a crown
                    of eighty pounds' weight, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps a
                        gift to the goddess Roma, like the similar but more lavish gift of Rhodes
                        when in the bad graces of the Romans (Polybius XXX. 5. 4). </note> and
                    called to mind that they had abandoned Perseus, after a Roman army had come into
                    Macedonia, although they had been subject to Perseus and previously to Philip.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This statement may be inaccurate;
                        Lampsacus declared itself independent of Antiochus in <date when="-0196">196
                            B.C.</date> (XXXIII. xxxviii. 3) and when last heard of (XXXVII. xxxv.
                        2, <date when="-0190">190 B.C.</date> ) was apparently recognized as
                        independent; perhaps Livy or his source has assumed that Lampsacus had
                        abandoned Perseus at the time when it came forward as an ally of Rome. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In return for this and for their action in
                    furnishing the Roman generals with everything, they asked only that they might
                    be <pb n="p.25"/> admitted to friendship <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Apparently they wanted an entente with Rome, without
                        the precise and formal undertakings of an alliance ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >societas).</hi> Usually, <quote>friendship</quote> and
                            <quote>alliance</quote> go hand in hand ( <hi rend="italics">e.g.,</hi>
                        XXXVI. iii. 8, XLV. xx. 8), but Rhodes maintained a state of
                            <quote>friendship</quote> without alliance for 140 years (cf. below,
                        XLV. xxv. 7-9) because, in the words of Polybius (XXX. 5. 8, tr. White, <hi
                            rend="italics">L.C.L.),</hi>
                        <quote> As they wished none of the kings and princes to despair of gaining
                            their help and alliance, they did not desire to run in harness with Rome
                            and engage themselves by oaths and treaties, but preferred to remain
                            unembarrassed and able to reap profit from any quarter </quote> ; they
                        sought alliance only when threatened with possible conquest as the
                        alternative. </note> with the Roman people, and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> that if peace should be
                    made with Perseus, provision should be made for them, to prevent their reverting
                    to the control of the king. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A kindly answer
                    was given the other envoys; as for the Lampsacenes, the praetor Quintus Maenius
                    was ordered to enroll them as allies. Gifts of two thousand <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses</hi> apiece were given to all the envoys. Those from Alabanda were
                    ordered to carry the shields back to Aulus Hostilius, the consul in Macedonia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Envoys from Africa also arrived, both
                    Carthaginians and those of Masinissa together. The Carthaginian envoys reported
                    that they had conveyed to the sea a million pecks of wheat and five hundred
                    thousand of barley, in order that they might deliver it wherever the senate
                    should determine; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> they said that this gift
                    and act of duty of theirs was, they knew, less than a return for the favours of
                    the Roman people and less than they would wish; but they had often, on other
                    occasions when both peoples had been prospering, fulfilled the duties of
                    grateful and faithful allies. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Likewise the
                    envoys of Masinissa promised the same total of wheat as well as twelve hundred
                    cavalry and twelve elephants; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He had
                        previously sent a thousand cavalry, a thousand infantry, and twenty-two
                        elephants (XLII. lxii. 2). </note> they requested the senate to order
                    anything else which might be needed, for the king would furnish such things with
                    as good a will as he gave what he, of his own accord, had <pb n="p.27"/>
                    promised. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Thanks both to the Carthaginians
                    and to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note>
                    the king were expressed and they were asked to deliver what they had promised to
                    Hostilius the consul in Macedonia. To each of the envoys a gift of two thousand
                        <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> was sent. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Cretan envoys reported that they had sent
                    to Macedonia as large a force of archers as the consul Publius <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> Licinius had stipulated, but when they did not
                    deny, on being questioned, that a larger number of their archers were serving
                    with Perseus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A force of nearly three
                        thousand is mentioned in XLII. li. 7; they participated in at least one
                        battle (XLII. lviii. 6). </note> than with the Romans, they were told in
                    reply that if <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> the people of Crete intended
                    truly and zealously to prize the friendship of the Roman People above that of
                    King Perseus, the Roman senate would also respond to them as it did to
                    indubitable allies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, let them report
                    to their people that it was the pleasure of the senate that the people of Crete
                    should make a point of recalling home at the first possible moment those
                    soldiers whom they might have within the lines of King Perseus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the Cretans had been dismissed with this
                    reply, the envoys of Chalcis were summoned; their embassy stirred sympathy by
                    its very entrance, because Micythion, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The name is given in the MS. as Micion; but it seems probable that the
                        Romanophile mentioned in XXXV. xxxviii. 1 and I-li is meant. </note> their
                    chief, having an affliction of the feet, was borne in on a litter; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> at once the occasion seemed one of direst necessity,
                    in which an excuse on grounds of health for one so afflicted either had seemed
                    to the victim himself something for which he should not ask, or had not been
                    granted at his request. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After he had begun by
                    saying that no part of him was still living except the tongue <pb n="p.29"/>
                    wherewith to bewail the disasters of his fatherland, he set <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> forth,
                    first, the good services of his state, both in earlier times and those which,
                    during the war with Perseus, they had performed for the Roman commanders
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> and armies, and next the acts of
                    arrogance, greed, and cruelty which in the first instance had been committed
                    against Micythion's fellow-countrymen by Gaius Lucretius the Roman praetor, and,
                    furthermore, were being committed more than ever at that time by Lucius
                    Hortensius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Just as they considered that,
                    rather than depart from their loyalty, they should suffer everything, even more
                    grievous injuries than those which they were now suffering, so also, as far as
                    Lucretius and Hortensius were concerned, they were aware that it would have been
                    safer to bar their gates than to receive those Romans into their city.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Those cities which had shut them out
                    —Emathia, Amphipolis, Maronea, Aenus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The approach to these cities seems to have been during a naval raid like
                        that of Marcius, XLIV. x. </note> —were unharmed. In Chalcis, temples had
                    been stripped of all their adornments and the loot of these profanations Gaius
                    Lucretius had transported in his ships to Antium; free persons had been rushed
                    away to slavery; the possessions of allies of the Roman people had been
                    plundered and daily were being plundered. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    For, according to the precedent set by Gaius Lucretius, Hortensius too was
                    quartering his sailors, in summer no less than in winter, in private houses, and
                    the homes of Chalcis were full of the mob from the fleet; at large among the
                    Chalcideans and their wives and their children there were men utterly reckless
                    in word and deed. </p>
                <pb n="p.31"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was voted to summon Lucretius before <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> the senate
                    in order that he might plead in person and attempt to clear himself. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> However, when he appeared he heard many more
                    reproaches than had been hurled at him in his absence; and more influential and
                    powerful accusers joined in, namely, two tribunes of the people, Manius
                    Iuventius Talna and Gnaeus Aufidius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These not
                    only assailed him in the senate, but also dragged him before an assembly, and
                    after casting many reproaches at him, then set a day for his trial. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> By order of the senate Quintus Maenius the praetor
                    replied to the envoys of Chalcis that, as to the services to the Roman People,
                    both previously and in the war now being waged, which the envoys mentioned, the
                    senate knew that they had spoken truly and, also, these services were
                    appreciated exactly as they should be. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As to
                    their complaints about what the Roman praetor Gaius Lucretius had done, and what
                    Lucius Hortensius the Roman praetor was doing, no one could be unaware that
                    these things had been done and were being done without the consent of the
                    senate, —no <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> one, that is, who knew that the
                    Roman People had declared war on Perseus and previously on Philip, his father,
                    to preserve the freedom of Greece, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The slogan for Roman intervention to the eastward, cf. XXXIV. lviii. 11-12,
                        XXXVII. liv. 17. </note> and not to inflict on allies and friends such
                    injuries from Roman officers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His
                    fellow-senators, said Maenius, would send a letter to the praetor Lucius
                    Hortensius, saying that the senate was displeased with those actions of which
                    the people of Chalcis complained; that if any free persons had been sold into
                    slavery, he should take steps at the first possible moment to search them out
                        <pb n="p.33"/> and restore them to freedom; that the senate <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> deemed it
                    just that none of the sailors, except the captains, should be quartered in
                    private houses. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These instructions were by
                    order of the senate written to Hortensius. Gifts of two thousand <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi> apiece were sent to the envoys, and carriages were
                    hired at public expense for Micythion, to convey him comfortably to Brundisium.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As for Gaius Lucretius, on the day set for
                    his trial, the tribunes accused him before the people <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In the <hi rend="italics">comitia tributa;</hi> a few
                        more details in the account of the similar trial, below, xvi. 11-16. </note>
                    and proposed a fine of one million <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the vote was taken, all the thirty-five
                    tribes approved his condemnation. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Among the Ligurians nothing noteworthy was
                    accomplished that year. For neither did the enemy take up arms, nor did the
                    consul lead his legions into enemy territory; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and having sufficiently assured himself of peace for that year, he sent home
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably on furlough, subject to
                        further call; the consul would not have formally discharged the army without
                        action by the senate. </note> the soldiers of the two Roman legions within
                    sixty days after arriving in his province. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    After having at an early time led the force of allies of the Latin Name into
                    winter-quarters at Luna and Pisa, he himself visited with the cavalry several
                    towns of the province of Gaul. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nowhere else was there war except in
                    Macedonia. However, they still regarded Gentius, the king of the Illyrians,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Gentius had been suspected of
                        piracy in <date when="-0180">180 B.C.</date> (XL. xlii. 2-5, XLII. xxix.
                        11). Efforts to attach him to the Roman cause had been misconducted and were
                        valueless (XLII. xxxvii. 2, and xlv. 8). On Perseus' overtures to Gentius,
                        see below, xix. 13-xx. 3, and xxiii. 8. </note> with suspicion. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> And so, on the one hand, the senate decided that
                    eight fully-equipped ships should be sent from Brundisium to Gaius Furius, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Very likely the naval <hi
                            rend="italics">duumvir</hi> mentioned in XLI. i. 2-3, who had been in
                        charge of the north-eastern coast of Italy in <date when="-0178">178
                            B.C.</date>
                    </note> the staff-officer at Issa, who was in charge of <pb n="p.35"/> the
                    island with a force of two Issaean ships-two <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> thousand soldiers were put
                    aboard the eight <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The number of
                        soldiers to be transported on the ships, which had their own crews, seems
                        too large (cf. XXXVII. ii. 10-a force of three thousand transported in
                        twenty ships (cf. XXII. xxii. 1), XXI. 1. 5-1700 soldiers and sailors in 7
                        ships) and the number of ships should perhaps be larger (eighteen?). </note>
                    ships, a force raised, in accordance with a decree of the senate, by Marcus
                    Raecius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The city praetor, cf. below,
                        xi. 4; he was evidently absent from Rome on coast-defence duty, hence the
                        appearance of Maenius (above, iv. 11, and viii. 4) as presiding officer of
                        the senate. </note> the praetor, in that part of Italy which faced
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> Illyricum-and, on the other hand, the
                    consul Hostilius sent Appius Claudius into Illyricum with four thousand
                    infantry, to protect the peoples bordering on Illyricum. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Claudius, being unsatisfied with the force that he had
                    brought, by collecting auxiliaries from the allies brought under arms about
                    eight thousand men of various sorts, and after traversing all that region took
                    up his position at Lychnidus of the Dassaretii. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Garrisons had been placed in their territory the
                        preceding year, XLII. xxxvi. 9. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not far from there lay Uscana, a town
                    belonging to the lands and realm of Perseus. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> But below, xviii. 5-xxi. 1, Livy relates, presumably
                        after Polybius, that Uscana was held by a Roman garrison until captured by
                        Perseus, and that Lucius Coelius led an abortive attempt to recover it.
                        There seems to be a duplication of the story here, of which Livy is unaware;
                        the account here given presumably comes from a Roman source. </note> It had
                    ten thousand inhabitants and a moderate garrison of Cretans to protect it.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From there, secret messengers kept coming
                    to Claudius, declaring that if he would bring his troops up closer, there were
                    those who were ready to betray the city. And it would be worth his while, they
                    added, for he would not only satisfy himself and his friends, but also his
                    soldiers with the booty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hope joined to greed
                    so blinded his mind <pb n="p.37"/> that neither did he keep with him any of the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note>
                    messengers who had come, nor did he demand hostages as security that there would
                    be no treachery in the carrying out of the plan, nor did he send men to
                    reconnoitre, nor did he receive any solemn promise. Having merely agreed upon a
                    day, he set out from Lychnidus and pitched camp twelve miles from the city to
                    which he was marching. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thence in the fourth
                    watch he began to advance, leaving about a thousand to garrison the camp. The
                    soldiers arrived near the city in disorder, scattered in along column, and
                    straggling, since wandering by night had dispersed them. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Their carelessness increased after they saw no armed man on
                    the walls. However, as soon as they were within range of missiles, a sally was
                    made from two gates at once; and together with the battle-cry of the sallying
                    parties, there arose from the walls a great uproar of women howling and of
                    bronze clashing everywhere, while an unorganized crowd, with disorderly bands of
                    slaves amongst them, clamoured with various outcries. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> This appalling surprise, presented from all directions in
                    so many forms, brought it about that the Romans could not withstand the first
                    storm-blast of the sally. And so more were slaughtered in the flight than in the
                    combat; hardly two thousand men, together with the commander himself, escaped to
                    the camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Since the way to the camp was long,
                    the enemy had the opportunity to overtake more of the weary men. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Appius, not even lingering in camp to gather his men
                    scattered in flight-an action which would have been the means of saving those
                    who were wandering through the countryside-at once led back to Lychnidus the
                    remnants of the disaster. </p>
                <pb n="p.39"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This and other affairs in Macedonia conducted
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> with
                    no success were reported by Sextus Digitius, a tribune of the soldiers, who had
                    come to Rome to offer a sacrifice. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The result
                    was that the Fathers, solicitous lest some greater disgrace might befall, sent
                    as commissioners to Macedonia Marcus Fulvius Flaccus and Marcus Caninius
                    Rebilus, who were to report after investigation on what was taking place;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the Fathers also decided that Aulus
                    Atilius the consul should proclaim the assembly for the election of consuls for
                    such a time that it might be completed during the month of January, and that he
                    should return to the city at the first possible moment. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Meanwhile Marcus Raecius the praetor was charged with
                    recalling to Rome by proclamation all senators from the whole of Italy, except
                    those who were absent on public business, while those <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> who were in Rome were not to go more than a mile away from
                    Rome. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A similar, but even stricter,
                        emergency measure is recorded in XXXVI. iii. 3 ( <date when="-0191">191
                            B.C.</date> ), just before the campaigns against Antiochus. </note>
                    These matters were carried out as the senate voted. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The consular elections were held on the twenty-sixth of
                    January. The consuls elected were Quintus Marcius Philippus for the second time
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> His previous consulship was in
                            <date when="-0186">186 B.C.</date> , cf. XXXIX. viii ff.; he had been
                        envoy to Greece and to Perseus just before the outbreak of the war, XLII.
                        xxxviii-xlvii. </note> and Gnaeus Servilius Caepio. Two days later there
                    were elected as praetors Gaius Decimius, Marcus Claudius Marcellus. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He was tribune in <date when="-0171"
                            >171 B.C.</date> (XLII. xxxii. 7), going out of office on December 9th
                        of that year; the interval of a year and three months was apparently
                        regularly regarded as fulfilling the requirement of two years which,
                        according to the Lex Villia Annalis (XL. xliv. 1), cf. Cicero, <hi
                            rend="italics">Philippics</hi> 5, 17, <hi rend="italics">de Legibus</hi>
                        3, 3, had to elapse between two terms in office. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Gaius Sulpicius Gallus, Gaius Marcius Figulus,
                    Servius Cornelius Lentulus, Publius Fonteius Capito. For the praetors-elect four
                    assign <pb n="p.41"/> ments besides the two in the city were decreed: <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> Spain,
                    Sardinia, Sicily, and the fleet. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The commissioners from Macedonia returned when
                    the month of February was just ended. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These
                    reported the successes achieved by King Perseus during that summer, and how
                    great a panic had seized the allies of the Roman people when so many cities were
                    brought under the control of the king. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    army of the consul, said the commissioners, was reduced in numbers because
                    leaves of absence had been lavishly granted as a means of currying political
                    favour; blame for this situation was placed by the consul on the tribunes of the
                    soldiers, but by them, on the other hand, on the consul. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The Fathers took it that <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The text is uncertain here; other interpretations
                        proposed by scholars include, <quote>The Fathers accused the commissioners
                            of minimizing ... because they reported,</quote> and, <quote>The Fathers
                            were glad to hear the commissioners minimize .. .</quote> (see critical
                        note). </note> the commissioners were minimizing the disgrace inflicted by
                    the rashness of Claudius, since they reported that very few soldiers of Italian
                    stock, but chiefly those enrolled on the spot in an irregular levy, had been
                    lost. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The consuls-elect were ordered to
                    present to the senate, as soon as they entered upon their office, the problem of
                    Macedonia; and Italy and Macedonia were designated as their provinces. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In this year there was an intercalation; the
                    additional month began on the third day after the Terminalia. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">See appendix following this Book, pp.
                        87-88.</note> There died of the priests in that year Lucius Flamininus . . .
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The priesthood held by Flamininus
                        and the name of his successor are missing; he was probably the augur elected
                        in <date when="-0213">213 B.C.</date> , XXV. ii. 2. </note> two pontiffs
                    passed away, Lucius Furius Philus and Gaius Livius Salinator. <pb n="p.43"/> In
                    place of Furius the pontiffs chose Titus Manlius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 171</note> Torquatus, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Probably a praetor of this year.</note>
                    in place of Livius, Marcus Servilius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the following year, when
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> the
                    new consuls Quintus Marcius and Gnaeus Servilius put the question of provinces,
                    it was voted that at the first possible moment they should either arrange with
                    each other or draw lots for Italy and Macedonia; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> before the lot should decide this question, while it was still in doubt, so
                    that favouritism should have no weight, it was voted to decree for each province
                    the reinforcements called for by the situation —for <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Macedonia, of infantry, six thousand Romans, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Below, XLIV. i. 1, the figure of 5000
                        (perhaps incomplete) is given, presumably following Polybius. The figures
                        here would seem then to come from an exaggerating Roman source. </note> and
                    six thousand allies of the Latin Name, of cavalry, two hundred and fifty Romans
                    and three hundred allies —also <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> to discharge
                    old soldiers so that there should be in each Roman legion not more than six
                    thousand infantry and three hundred cavalry. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For the other consul no fixed number of Roman citizens whom he might select as
                    reinforcements was defined. This only was fixed that he should enroll two
                    legions, each of which was to have five thousand and two hundred infantry and
                    three hundred cavalry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Of the Latins, a larger
                    number was assigned than to his colleague, ten thousand infantry and six hundred
                    cavalry. Four additional legions were ordered enrolled, to be led out if needed
                    anywhere. For these, the consuls were not allowed <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Presumably by the senate (cf. XLIV. xxi. 2), or by the
                        people on motion of the senate (XLII. xxxi. 5). </note> to appoint tribunes;
                    the people elected them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the allies of the
                    Latin Name sixteen thousand <pb n="p.45"/> infantry and a thousand cavalry were
                    levied. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> voted that this force
                    should merely be got ready so as to march out if circumstances anywhere should
                    demand. Macedonia was especially an object of concern. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> For the fleet, a thousand sailors, Roman citizens of the
                    class of freedmen, and five hundred from Italy, were ordered enrolled; as many
                    were to be enrolled from Sicily, and the governor-to-be of that province was
                    instructed to see to their transportation to Macedonia, wherever the fleet might
                    be. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For Spain, three thousand Roman infantry
                    and three hundred cavalry were decreed as reinforcement. The number of soldiers
                    for the legions was fixed for that region also —five thousand and two hundred
                    infantry and three hundred cavalry for each legion. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The praetor to whom Spain should fall, was ordered to levy
                    from the allies also four thousand infantry and three hundred cavalry. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> I am not unaware that, as a result of the same
                    disregard <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On the decline of religion
                        and scruple, cf. III. xx. 5 and X. xl. 10, and the note; restoration of
                        former religious observances was one of the objectives of Augustus, and he
                        served on several priestly boards. Prodigies were noted in later times (cf.
                            <hi rend="italics">e.g.,</hi> Tacitus, <hi rend="italics">Annals</hi>
                        XIII. lviii; XIV. xii; Suetonius, <hi rend="italics">Gaius</hi> lvii) if not
                        officially reported. </note> that leads men generally to suppose nowadays
                    that the gods foretell nothing, no portents at all are reported officially, or
                    recorded in our histories. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> However, not only
                    does my own mind, as I write of old-time matters, become in some way or other
                    old-fashioned, but also a certain conscientious scruple keeps me from regarding
                    what those very sagacious men of former times thought worthy of public concern
                    as something unworthy to be reported in my history. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> At Anagnia, two portents were announced in that year, a
                    fiery meteor seen in <pb n="p.47"/> the sky, and a cow which spoke; this animal,
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    report stated, was being kept at public expense. At Minturnae also during these
                    very days the sky presented the appearance of being on fire. At Reate there was
                    a rain of stones. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Cumae the Apollo on the
                    citadel shed tears for three days and three nights. In the city of Rome two
                    temple-attendants announced portents; one, that a crested snake had been seen by
                    many people in the temple of Fortune; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the
                    other announced two different portents in the temple of Fortune the First-Born
                    which is on the hill, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> the Quirinal, as distinguished from another
                        temple on the Capitol. </note> that a palm had sprung up in the courtyard
                    and that during the day blood had rained down. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Two portents were not treated as public matters, the one because it took place
                    in a privately-owned spot-Titus Marcius Figulus reported that a palm had sprung
                    up in his catch-basin <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was an
                        ornamental basin in the floor at the centre of the atrium, or principal
                        room, which caught rain entering through the central opening of the roof (
                            <hi rend="italics">compluvium</hi> ). </note> —the other because it
                    occurred in a non- Roman place <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Fregellae was a Latin colony, therefore legally autonomous, and its
                        territory not Roman; Minturnae was a Roman colony, hence part of Rome;
                        Anagnia was either subject territory, or its inhabitants had been granted
                        Roman citizenship; Cumae and Reate were <quote>allied states</quote> ( <hi
                            rend="italics">civitates foederatae</hi> ), but their territory was
                        evidently regarded as part of the Roman domain ( <hi rend="italics">ager
                            publicus</hi> ). </note> —at Fregellae, in the house of Lucius Atreus, a
                    spear which he had bought for his son's service in the army was said to have
                    blazed during the day for more than two hours in such a way that the fire
                    consumed none of it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Because of the public
                    portents the books were approached by the Board of Ten; they proclaimed the gods
                    to whom the consuls were to offer forty full-grown victims, and also that a day
                    of prayer should be observed, that all the magistrates should sacrifice
                    full-grown victims at all the <pb n="p.49"/> principal temples and that the
                    people should wear <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        169</note> wreaths. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably of
                        laurel; wreath-wearing was a mark of especially earnest supplication in time
                        of emergency, cf. XXXIV. Iv. 4, XXXVI. xxxvii. 5, XL. xxxvii. 3. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Everything was carried out as the Board of Ten
                    prescribed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thereupon the assembly for electing censors
                    was announced. The leading men of the state sought the censorship, Gaius
                    Valerius Laevinus, Lucius Postumius Albinus, Publius Mucius Scaevola, Marcus
                    Junius Brutus, Gaius Claudius Pulcher, Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus. The last
                    two were elected censors by the Roman people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Since concern over holding the levy was greater, because of the Macedonian war,
                    than at other times, the consuls blamed the commons before the senate because
                    even <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This word is usually omitted by
                        editors, on the ground that of the whole citizen-army only men of military
                        age (the <hi rend="italics">iuniores,</hi> 17-46 years old) were involved in
                        the levy; but for the Macedonian campaign, older men (the <hi rend="italics"
                            >seniores,</hi> 47-60 years old) also were drafted or volunteered, cf.
                        XLII. xxxi. 4 and xxxii. 6. </note> the men of military age were not
                    presenting themselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Retorting to them Gaius
                    Sulpicius and Marcus Claudius the praetors pleaded the cause of the commons; the
                    levy, they said, was difficult, not for consuls, but for politically-minded
                    consuls; they never enrolled a soldier against his will. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> That the Conscript Fathers might also be sure that this was
                    so, they themselves, though praetors, whose powers of office and importance were
                    less, would, if it seemed best to the senate, complete the levy. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Conduct of a levy by praetors when the
                        consuls were otherwise occupied was not without precedent, cf. XXXIX. xx. 4,
                        xxxviii. 10; XLII. xviii. 6; but the supplanting of the consuls was peculiar
                        to this occasion. </note> This task was entrusted to the praetors with great
                    enthusiasm on the part of the Fathers, not without jeers at the consuls.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The censors, to further the business, made
                    the following proclamation before a meeting; that they were going to lay down a
                    rule for taking the <pb n="p.51"/> census that, besides the general oath for all
                    citizens, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        169</note> they would require assent on oath to the following: <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Are you less than forty-six years of age, and have you, in accordance
                        with the proclamation of Gaius Claudius and Tiberius Sempronius the censors,
                        come forward for the levy, and as often as there shall be a levy, as long as
                        these censors shall hold office, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            Either for a year and a half, during which the censors were allowed to
                            be active, by the Aemilian law ( <date when="-0434">434 B.C.</date> ,
                            IV. xxiv. 5, cf. IX. xxxiii. 3 ff.), or for three years, as the censors'
                            authority over construction and repairs was, according to XLV. xv. 9,
                            customarily continued for a second period of equal length; hardly for
                            the full five years till other censors were chosen. </note> if you have
                        not entered the army, will you come forward for the levy? </quote> ;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> again, since it was rumoured that many
                    were absent on leave from the legions in Macedonia without specific reason
                    because of the popularity-hunting of the generals, they proclaimed concerning
                    the soldiers enrolled for Macedonia in the consulship of Publius Aelius and
                    Gaius Popilius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <date when="-0172">172 B.C.</date> ; a small force crossed over to the towns
                        of the west coast in that year, cf. XLII. xxvii. </note> or after that
                    consulship, that whoever of them were in Italy should within thirty days, having
                    first appeared before the censors, return to their province, and that the names
                    of those who were subject to the authority of father or grandfather <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Such men would not appear before the
                        censors, as their property belonged to the estate of their controlling
                        relative. </note> should be reported to the censors. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> They would also review, they said, the reasons for
                    discharges, and those whose discharge before completion of their <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> military service seemed to the censors to result
                    from indulgence they would order to be enrolled as soldiers. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Through this proclamation of the censors, and through their
                    letters sent about throughout the markets and hamlets, so large a crowd of men
                    of military age assembled at Rome that the unusual throng was burdensome to the
                    city. </p>
                <pb n="p.53"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Besides the levy of those who were needed
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> to
                    be sent as reinforcements four legions were enrolled by Gaius Sulpicius the
                    praetor, and within eleven days the levy was completed. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls then drew lots for their provinces. For the
                    praetors had drawn lots more promptly to secure the administration of justice.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The city praetorship fell to Gaius
                    Sulpicius, the jurisdiction over aliens to Gaius Decimius; Spain was drawn by
                    Marcus Claudius Marcellus, Sicily by Servius Cornelius Lentulus, Sardinia by
                    Publius Fonteius Capito, the fleet by Gaius Marcius Figulus. Of the consuls,
                    Italy fell to Gnaeus Servilius, and Macedonia to Quintus Marcius; when the Latin
                    Festival had been held, Marcius at once set out. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> When Caepio then consulted the senate as to which two of the new legions he
                    should take with him to Gaul, the Fathers voted that Gaius Sulpicius and Marcus
                    Claudius the praetors should give the consul what legions they chose from those
                    they had enrolled. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Feeling insulted that a
                    consul should be subject to the decision of praetors, Servilius dismissed the
                    senate and, taking his stand at the judgment-seat of the praetors, demanded
                    that, in accordance with the decree of the senate, they assign him two legions.
                    The praetors gave the consul his choice in the selection. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thereupon the censors chose the senate; Marcus
                    Aemilius Lepidus was chosen chief. This was the third time the censors had
                    chosen him. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> His previous elections
                        are recorded in XL. li. 1 and XLI. xxvii. 1. </note> Seven were expelled
                    from the senate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In receiving the census of
                    the people they forced the soldiers from the army in Macedonia —the census
                    showed how numerous were these absentees from the ranks —to <pb n="p.55"/>
                    return to their province; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> they reviewed the
                    excuses <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    of those discharged from service, and in the case of any whose discharge seemed
                    premature they compelled assent on oath to the following: <quote> With your
                        whole heart will you, in accordance with the decree of Gaius Claudius and
                        Tiberius Sempronius the censors, return to the province of Macedonia, as you
                        are able, in all sincerity, to do this? </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In reviewing the knights, the censorship of
                    these officials was rather stern and harsh; they deprived many of their horses.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When in this matter they had offended the
                    order of knights, they added fire to the grudge by a proclamation, in which they
                    proclaimed that none of those who in the censorship of Quintus Fulvius and Aulus
                    Postumius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The previous censors, XLI.
                        xxvii.</note> had farmed the public revenues or the public works should
                    appear at the auction of Claudius and Sempronius, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Literally, <quote>to their spear,</quote> since a spear
                        was the sign of an auction; at the censors' auction contracts for public
                        works and for collecting the revenues were to be made, cf. XXXIX. xliv. 8
                        and the note. </note> or should be a partner or sharer in the contracting.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When, after many complaints about this
                    decree, the veteran tax-gatherers were unable to induce the senate to set a
                    limit to the censors' power, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Compare
                        the Pyrrhic victory of the contractors in <date when="-0184">184 B.C.</date>
                        , XXXIX. xliv. 8. </note> at last in a tribune of the people, Publius
                    Rutilius, who was angry with the censors over a dispute concerning a private
                    matter, they found an advocate for their cause. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> A freedman client of Rutilius had been ordered by the censors to pull down a
                    house-wall on the Sacred Way opposite the public temples, because the wall was
                    built on state land. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> An appeal was made by the
                    citizen to the tribunes. When no one but Rutilius intervened in his behalf, the
                    censors <pb n="p.57"/> sent agents to secure bonds <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Such bonds, designed to secure the appearance for trial
                        of a person charged with a crime, were secured, not directly from the
                        defendant, but from bondsmen from among his friends. For this practice, cf.
                        III. xiii. 8, XXV. iv. 8-10, XXXIX. xli. 7, and Summary XLVIII. Aulus
                        Gellius, XVI. x. 8, mentions bondsmen as one of the obsolete legal forms
                        abolished by the <hi rend="italics">lex Aebutia</hi> (exact date unknown).
                        After this time, bonds were posted by the defendant. </note> and announced
                    before <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> a
                    meeting a fine for the citizen. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        veto of one tribune sufficed to debar an action, but the censors apparently
                        expected the other tribunes to suppress Rutilius, as had been done on
                        various other occasions, cf. II. xliii. 4, IV. xlix. 6 and liii. 7, IX.
                        xxxiv. 26, XXIV. xliii. 3, or that the senate would support them, cf. XXIX.
                        xxxvii. 17. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A dispute having arisen from this cause, when
                    the veteran tax-gatherers had resorted to the tribune, a proposed law was
                    suddenly published under the name of the one tribune, stating that whereas Gaius
                    Claudius and Tiberius Sempronius had let certain public revenues and public
                    works, the letting of these should be void; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    they should be let anew, and everyone without restriction should have the right
                    of farming and contracting. The tribune of the people announced for the assembly
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> An Assembly of the Commons ( <hi
                            rend="italics">concilium plebis</hi> ). </note> a day for voting on this
                    proposal. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> An attempt is made here to
                        translate the MS. text, without the usual alterations (see critical note). I
                        accept the suggestion of Duker that the phrase, if completed, would be <hi
                            rend="italics">ad eius rogationis rogationem, rogatio</hi> meaning (a) a
                        bill or proposed law, ( <hi rend="italics">b</hi> ) the process of putting
                        it to a vote. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When this day came, as the censors came
                    forward to advise against the law, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In
                        a meeting ( <hi rend="italics">contio</hi> ) held before the voting
                        assembly. </note> while Gracchus was speaking there was silence; when
                    heckling greeted Claudius, he ordered the herald to bring the meeting to order.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When this was done, the tribune,
                    complaining that the meeting had been taken out of his hands and that he had
                    been deprived of his authority, left the Capitol, where the assembly was. Next
                    day he raised a great uproar. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He first
                    dedicated to the gods the property of Tiberius Gracchus because in the matter of
                    the fine and the bonds imposed on one who had appealed to a tribune, <pb
                        n="p.59"/> Gracchus had, by not obeying the tribune's interposition, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> deprived
                    him of his authority; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> he set a day for the
                    trial of Gaius Claudius on the charge of taking the meeting away from him; and
                    he announced that he judged each censor guilty of treason, and asked of Gaius
                    Sulpicius the city praetor a day for an assembly. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Rutilius proceeds under the law mentioned in III. Iv.
                        7, that one who injured a tribune should forfeit his head to Jupiter, and
                        that his property should be sold at the temple of Ceres, Liber and Libera;
                        the ceremony of dedicating the man and his property to the gods might be
                        performed by a tribune, cf. Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Domo Sua</hi> 47
                        (123-5), but apparently had to be confirmed by action of the people. Livy's
                        phrasing seems to make Rutilius arrange for two trials for Claudius, but we
                        hear of only one (below, 14-16) and it seems probable that the trial for
                        treason, based on the charges mentioned, was the one action which was to
                        confirm the sentence already pronounced by the tribune; also this sentence
                        was probably directed equally against both, though Gracchus is named alone.
                        For a trial of treason, the <hi rend="italics">comitia centuriata</hi> was
                        called, since a death-sentence was involved, not the <hi rend="italics"
                            >comitia tributa,</hi> as above, viii. 9, cf. the note, nor the <hi
                            rend="italics">concilium plebis.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Since the censors did not object to having
                    the people pass judgment on them at the first possible moment, the day for the
                    assembly-trial for treason was set for the twenty-third and twenty-fourth of
                    September. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A day for each defendant,
                        see XXV. iv. 10.</note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The censors immediately mounted to the Hall
                    of Liberty <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This appears to have been
                        next to the Senate-house, and perhaps a sort of annex to it. A rebuilding of
                        the <hi rend="italics">atrium</hi> in <date when="-0194">194 B.C.</date> is
                        mentioned in XXXIV. xliv. 5; hostages were kept there, according to XXV.
                        vii. 12; archives for laws were maintained there (Festus 241); and the
                        enrolment of freedmen in the city tribes took place there (XLV. xv. 5). The
                        anniversary day of the sanctuary of Freedom was April thirteenth (Ovid, <hi
                            rend="italics">Fasti</hi> IV. 623). In the first century B.C., slaves
                        were imprisoned there (Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Pro Milone</hi> 59), and,
                        following a plan of Julius Caesar's, Asinius Pollio founded there the first
                        public library in Rome, with rich sculptural adornment (Ovid, <hi
                            rend="italics">Tristia</hi> III. 1. 71-2, Suetonius, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Augustus</hi> 29). </note> and, having there sealed the public accounts
                    and closed the account room and sent away the public slaves, declared that they
                    would transact no public business until the judgment of the people upon them had
                    been passed. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Claudius pleaded his cause
                    first; and when of the twelve centuries of knights eight had condemned the
                    censor, along with many other centuries of the first class, at once the leading
                    men of the state, in the sight of the people, laid aside their gold rings and
                        <pb n="p.61"/> put on mourning, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> a dark toga; with it jewellery was not worn,
                        and senators and magistrates did not wear the purple stripe on their togas
                        of mourning. </note> in order to go about entreating <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> the commons. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Chiefly, however, Tiberius Gracchus is said to have
                    changed men's minds, because, although there was everywhere shouting from the
                    commons that Gracchus was in no danger, he swore in formal terms that if his
                    colleague were condemned he would not await the outcome of his own trial, but
                    would accompany Claudius into exile. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Except for the knights, among whom were the hostile tax-gatherers, the
                        danger to Claudius obviously arose from his harsh and arbitrary behaviour;
                        cf. his actions during his consulate in <date when="-0177">177 B.C.</date> ,
                        XLI. x. 5-13. </note> None the less, so near did the defendant come to the
                    last ray of hope that only eight centuries were lacking for condemnation.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> When Claudius had been acquitted, the
                    tribune of the people said that he did not care about the case of Gracchus.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The later activities of these
                        censors are told below, XLIV. xvi. and XLV. xv. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In that year, at the request of envoys from
                    Aquileia that the number of colonists be increased, fifteen hundred households
                    were enrolled in accordance with a decree of the senate, and a board of three,
                    Titus Annius Luscus, Publius Decius Subulo, and Marcus Cornelius Cethegus, were
                    sent to lead the settlement. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        reinforcement was sent two years after it was requested, cf. above, i. 5-12.
                        The sending of settlers may have been easier during the censors' activity,
                        cf. XXXIX. xliv. 10. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the same year <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> At this point Livy begins to draw on Polybius XXVIII,
                        3; but Polybius says that the envoys urged the Thebans to loyalty, and read
                        the senate's resolution only in the Peloponnese. </note> Gaius Popilius and
                    Gnaeus Octavius, the envoys who had been sent into Greece, first caused to be
                    read at Thebes and then to be carried about to all the cities of the Peloponnese
                    the decree of the senate that no one should contribute anything to Roman
                    officers for the war except what the senate should have voted. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This resolution had <pb n="p.63"/> produced confidence for
                    the future, too, that they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 169</note> had been relieved of both burdens and outlays,
                    by which, as one and another ordered various things, they were being drained
                    dry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before an Achaean council held for them
                    at Aegium the Roman envoys both spoke and were heard with cordiality, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. Polybius XXVIII. 3. 7-10.</note> and
                    leaving this most loyal people with extraordinary hope for their future
                    position, they crossed to Aetolia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There no
                    revolt indeed had as yet broken out, but every move was suspected and replete
                    with the mutual recriminations of the Aetolians; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> having, because of these, called for the giving of hostages, but without
                    bringing the trouble to an end, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf.
                        Polybius XXVIII. 4.</note> the envoys set out thence for Acarnania.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At Thyrreum the Acarnanians held a council
                    for the envoys. There too a contest between factions was under way; some of the
                    chief men demanded that garrisons be brought into their cities to guard against
                    the madness of those who were dragging the tribe toward the Macedonians;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> some objected to this, on the ground that
                    the disgrace which was customary for those captured in war and hostile should
                    not be inflicted on peaceful and allied cities. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> This plea in opposition seemed sound. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. Polybius XXVIII. 5.</note> The envoys returned to
                    Hostilius the proconsul at Larisa —for they had been sent by him. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Octavius he kept with him, Popilius he sent with
                    about a thousand soldiers into winter quarters at Ambracia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus did not dare to leave the limits of
                    Macedonia at the outset of winter, for fear that at some point the Romans might
                    raid his undefended realm. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> About the winter
                    solstice, however, when <pb n="p.65"/> the depth of snow makes the mountains
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> That is, the western passes, cf.
                        XLII. liii. 6; Tempe was held by the Macedonian garrison at Gonnus, XLII.
                        liv, 8; and cf. XLIV. ii. </note> impassable <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> from Thessaly, he thought
                    that here was an opportunity to shatter the hopes and spirits of his neighbours,
                    so that no danger might arise from them while his attention was turned toward
                    the campaign against the Romans. On the side of Thrace Cotys assured peace, as
                    did Cephalus on the side of Epirus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Livy's account of affairs in Epirus and the campaign against the Dardani is
                        lost, cf. above, iii. 7 and the note. Concerning the latter, Plutarch, <hi
                            rend="italics">Aemilius Paullus</hi> IX. 3, says that Perseus killed
                        10,000 Dardanians and acquired much booty. </note> by his sudden desertion
                    of the Romans, while the recent campaign had subdued the Dardani. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Perceiving then that the only quarter hostile to
                    Macedonia was that which allowed access from Illyricum, where the Illyrians
                    themselves were restless and were providing the Romans with an approach, and
                    that if he conquered the nearest Illyrians, he might also entice King Gentius,
                    who had long been wavering, into an alliance, Perseus set <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> out with ten thousand infantry, some of whom were
                    phalanx-men, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The rest were peltasts,
                        cf. Perseus' muster-roll in XLII. li. 3-11. </note> two thousand light
                    troops, and five hundred cavalry, and reached Stuberra. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Thence, taking grain for a number of days and ordering
                    equipment for besieging cities to follow, on the third day he pitched camp by
                    Uscana <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. above, x. and the note,
                        for a Roman counter-attack on this town, the account of which Livy has not
                        harmonized with Polybius' account reproduced here. </note> —which is the
                    largest city of the Penestian region —but sent, before bringing an attack to
                    bear, men to test the mood, now of the commanders of the garrison, now of the
                    townspeople. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For there was in the city, along
                    with the young men of the Illyrians, a Roman garrison. After the messengers
                    reported <pb n="p.67"/> nothing in the way of terms, Perseus began to press
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> the
                    siege and tried to capture the city with a surrounding attack. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Although without interruption through day and night relay
                    of men after relay here brought ladders against the walls, and there fire
                    against the gates, nevertheless, the defenders of the city withstood this
                    tempest, because they had <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> hopes that the
                    Macedonians could not longer endure the violence of winter in the open, and that
                    the lull in the Roman campaign would not long permit the king to linger.
                    However, after they saw sheds being brought up and towers raised, their
                    determination was overcome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For apart from the
                    fact that they were not equally matched against the assault, there was no supply
                    even of grain or of anything else in the city, as was natural when the siege was
                    unexpected. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And so, since there was no hope
                    of holding out, Gaius Carvilius of Spoletium and Gaius Afranius were sent from
                    the Roman garrison to request of Perseus, first, that he should permit them to
                    depart under arms and carrying their possessions with them, and next, if they
                    failed to obtain this, that they should at least receive assurances of life and
                    freedom. The king's generosity was greater in promise than in performance; for
                    after bidding them to depart carrying their possessions with them, he deprived
                    them first of their arms, then of their freedom. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> After the Romans had left the city, both the force of
                    Illyrians —there were five hundred of them —and the people of Uscana surrendered
                    themselves and their city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After placing a garrison in Uscana, Perseus
                        <pb n="p.69"/> took the whole mass of prisoners, which almost <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> equalled
                    his army in numbers, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to ch.
                        x. above, the population of Uscana was 10,000. </note> to Stuberra.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There, after assigning the Romans —of whom
                    there were four thousand <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In view of
                        the numbers given elsewhere for garrison details (XLII. xxxvi. 9, forts of
                        Dassaretii and Illyrians, 2000 Romans; lxvii. 9, Ambracia, 2000 men; XLIII.
                        ix. 6, force of Claudius, 4000 Romans, 4000 local levies, to protect
                        Illyricum in general), this number seems exaggerated. </note> —, except the
                    chief officers, to various cities to guard, and selling the people of Uscana and
                    the Illyrians, he led the army back among the Penestae in order to bring
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> under his control the town of Oaeneum,
                    which was in many ways strategically situated, particularly in that the route to
                    the Labeates, where Gentius was king, passes this way. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> As he was passing a populous fort, Draudacum by name, one
                    who knew this region said that there was no use of capturing Oaeneum unless
                    Draudacum too was under his control; for it was even more strategically situated
                    for all purposes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On his bringing up his army,
                    all at once surrendered. </p>
                <p> Encouraged by this surrender, more prompt than he had hoped, after he noticed
                    how great was the fear caused by his column, -he brought under his control
                    eleven other forts because of this same dread. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    At only a very few was there need of force; the rest were voluntarily
                    surrendered; and in these there were taken prisoner fifteen hundred <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In view of the numbers given elsewhere
                        for garrison details (XLII. xxxvi. 9, forts of Dassaretii and Illyrians,
                        2000 Romans; lxvii. 9, Ambracia, 2000 men; XLIII. ix. 6, force of Claudius,
                        4000 Romans, 4000 local levies, to protect Illyricum in general), this
                        number seems exaggerated. </note> Roman soldiers who had been distributed
                    among the garrisons. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Carvilius of Spoletium
                    was most useful in the parleys, in saying that no harshness had been used
                    against him and his comrades. Next, Perseus arrived at Oaeneum, which could not
                    be taken without a regular <pb n="p.71"/> siege. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> The city was strong both because of a somewhat <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> larger force of young men
                    than the others had had and because of its walls; moreover, on the one side a
                    river, Artatus by name, on the other a very high mountain, difficult to ascend,
                    girt the city about. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These defences gave the
                    people of the city hope of holding out. Perseus, after encircling the town with
                    earthworks, began to build up a mound on the higher side, high enough to bring
                    him above the wall. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While this work was in
                    progress, the frequent battles which meanwhile took place, as the townspeople
                    resorted to sallies to protect their walls and to hinder the siege-works of the
                    enemy, caused a great wastage in casualties of one kind or another, while those
                    townspeople who survived were incapacitated by daily and nightly toil and by
                    wounds. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as the mound was joined to
                    the wall, the royal company, whom they call the Conquerors, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It is not clear to what sort of unit
                        Livy is referring; one would suppose a <hi rend="italics">corps
                            d'élite,</hi> and the reference, in XXVIII. v. 15, to a royal company
                        kept by Philip as a mobile reserve under his personal command, would seem to
                        confirm this; so also the royal company of Antiochus, called the Silver-
                        Shields, in XXXVII. xl. 7; but the royal company mentioned in XL. vi. 3, at
                        a review of the Macedonian army, would seem to be the group of young nobles
                        described in XLV. vi. 7, as serving as royal pages or squires, cf. Arrian
                        IV. xiii. 1, Diodorus XVII. 65, Curtius Rufus VIII. vi. 2-7, and X. vii. 16.
                        The only other reference to the name <quote>Conquerors</quote> is Hesychius'
                        definition: <quote>the most excellent in the units</quote> ( <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">nikath=res oi( a)kmaio/tatoi e)n tai=s
                            ta/cesi</foreign> ) </note> passed over it, and also at the same time an
                    attack was made with ladders against many parts of the city. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> All the adult males were killed; their wives and children
                    Perseus put under guard; the other items of booty fell to the soldiers.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Returning thence victoriously to
                    Stuberra, he sent as envoys to Gentius, Pleuratus the Illyrian, who was in exile
                    at his court, and Adaeus, a Macedonian from Beroea; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Taken from Polybius XXVIII. 8; who adds the Epirotes to
                        the list of Perseus' opponents, cf. above, xviii. 2. </note> he instructed
                    them to relate his achievements of that summer and winter against <pb n="p.73"/>
                    the Romans and Dardanians; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> they were to add
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    recent operations of his winter march into Illyricum; and they were to urge
                    Gentius to join in friendship with Perseus and the Macedonians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After crossing the ridge of Mount Scordus, and
                    passing through the desert regions of Illyricum, which the Macedonians had
                    purposely made desert by ravaging, so that there might be no easy passage for
                    the Dardanians to Illyricum or Macedonia, these envoys came at last with great
                    toil to Scodra. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> King Gentius was at Lissus.
                    Thither the envoys were summoned, and their message was given a favourable
                    hearing; but the reply which they took away accomplished nothing; it was to the
                    effect that Gentius did not lack the will to fight the Romans, but to try to
                    effect his will he did especially lack money. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    These words the envoys reported at Stuberra to the king, who was at that moment
                    engaged in selling the prisoners from Illyricum. At once the same envoys, with
                    the addition of Glaucias from among the king's bodyguard, were sent back with no
                    word about money, by which alone the poverty-stricken barbarian could be urged
                    into war. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On Perseus' stinginess, cf.
                        XLII. lxvii. 5 and the note, XLIV. xxvi. 1, Polybius XXVIII. 9; Plutarch,
                            <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xii. 4-xiii. 2 mentions the Bastarnae
                        as also victims of Perseus' greed, and points out the contrast to Alexander
                        the Great and Philip, his father, who disregarded money for the sake of
                        conquest. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thence, after ravaging Ancyra, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The situation of Ancyra is unknown; we
                        cannot be sure whether it is a town, a district, or a mistake. In Polybius
                        XXVIII. 8. 11, in place of a corrupt word ( <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >e)pakkwnan</foreign> ), Ursinus proposed reading <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">e)p' )/Agkuran,</foreign> on the basis of this
                        reference in Livy; but modern editors prefer the emendation <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">e)f' (/Gskana.</foreign>
                    </note> Perseus led his army back again among the <pb n="p.75"/> Penestae and,
                    having strengthened the garrisons in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 169</note> Uscana and in all the forts that he had
                    captured round about it, retired to Macedonia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Coelius, a Roman staff-officer, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The relative positions of Coelius and
                        Claudius, above, ix-x. below, §§ 4-5, xxiii. 1-2 and 6, and XLIV. xx. 5,
                        cannot be exactly determined; perhaps they had different sectors, in spite
                        of the story of Claudius' fiasco before Uscana, cf. note 4, p. 35. </note>
                    was in charge of Illyricum; he had not dared to stir while the king was in those
                    parts, but after his departure at last attempted in the Penestian country to
                    retake Uscana, and, being driven back with many wounded by the Macedonian
                    garrison which was there, led his forces back to Lychnidus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Thence after a few days he sent Marcus Trebellius of
                    Fregellae with a strong enough detachment among the Penestae to receive hostages
                    from those cities which had remained loyal to the alliance; he ordered
                    Trebellius to proceed also to the Parthini, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> They had been recognized as allies of the Romans in
                            <date when="-0205">205 B.C.</date> (Polybius II. 11. 11, VII. 9. 13,
                        Livy XXIX. xii. 13), but seem to have come again under Philip's rule; in
                            <date when="-0196">196 B.C.</date> , XXXIII. xxxiv. 11, they were put
                        under Pleuratus, the father of Gentius (not the exile mentioned above, xix.
                        13), who had aided Rome against Philip (XXXI. xxviii. 1-3, xl. 10; cf. also
                        below, xxiii. 6). </note> for they had likewise promised to give hostages.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From both peoples Trebellius exacted the
                    hostages without disturbance. The knights of the Penestae were sent to
                    Apollonia, those of the Parthini to Dyrrachium —at that time the name Epidamnus
                    was more generally in use among the Greeks. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Including Polybius, e.g., XXXIV. 7.</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius, eager to atone for the
                    disgrace he had received in Illyricum, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Cf. above, ix-x.</note> attempted to besiege Phanote, a fort of Epirus. He
                    took with him auxiliaries from the Chaonians <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Phanote lay in their territory; the Chaonians were
                        divided in their attachment, some holding with Perseus. </note> and The
                    sprotians, besides his Roman army, a total of about six <pb n="p.77"/> thousand
                    men; he did not accomplish anything <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 169</note> worth his trouble, since Cleuas, who had been
                    left by Perseus, was defending it with a strong garrison. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Perseus also, setting out for Elimea, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Here the city, not the district as in XXXI. xl. 1,
                        XLII. liii. 5, and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> ix. 3. </note>
                    and purifying his army in that neighbourhood, led his force, at the invitation
                    of the Epirotes, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Epirote exiles, cf.
                        below xxii. 9, unless this is a mistake for <quote>Aetolians.</quote>
                    </note> to Stratus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Stratus was at that time
                    the strongest city of Aetolia; it is situated inland from the Ambracian Gulf
                    near the River Inachus. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Until <date
                            when="-0270">270 B.C.</date> the chief city of Acarnania, Stratus was
                        then given to the Aetolians. The river is properly the Acheloös (cf. <hi
                            rend="italics">e.g.,</hi> Polybius V. 13. 10); the name Inachus was
                        sometimes applied to the upper portion of the Acheloös which was mistakenly
                        regarded as a tributary, hence, perhaps, Livy's mistake. </note> Perseus set
                    out thither with ten thousand infantry and three handred cavalry, a smaller
                    number of which <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Two hundred less
                        cavalry (and apparently the two thousand light-troops were also omitted)
                        than on the previous expedition; above, xviii. 4. </note> he took with him
                    because of the narrowness and roughness of the roads. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> When on the third day he had arrived at Mount Citium, the
                    snow was so deep that he barely succeeded incrossing and had difficulty also in
                    finding a place for his camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Setting out
                    thence, more because he could not stay than because either the way or the
                    weather was bearable, with great suffering, especially of the baggage-animals,
                    on the second day he pitched camp at the temple of Jupiter whom they call the
                    Victorious. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Zeus Nikaios. is named in
                        inscriptions from Asia Minor; Cassius Dio XLVII. 40. 2 uses this name as a
                        translation of <quote>Jupiter Victor</quote> at Rome. </note> Thence having
                    traversed a huge march to the Aratthus River, he halted . . . delayed by the
                    depth of the river. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In this length of time a
                    bridge was finished, and, leading his troops across, he proceeded one day's
                    march and effected a meeting with <pb n="p.79"/> Archidamus, a prominent
                    Aetolian, who was trying <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 169</note> to hand over Stratus to him. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Archidamus is mentioned by Polybius XXVIII. 4. 8 as
                        accused of anti-Romanism by Lyciscus, a professional pro-Roman, cf. Vol.
                        XII. p. 403, and 478, note 1. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On that day camp was pitched at the edge of
                    Aetolian territory; thence on the second day they arrived at Stratus. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Although, when he pitched camp there near the Inachus
                    River, Perseus expected the Aetolians to come streaming out of every gate to put
                    themselves under his protection, he found that the gates were closed and that on
                    the very night when he had arrived a Roman garrison, under the staff-officer
                    Gaius Popilius, had been received. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The leading
                    men, driven by the influence of Archidamus while he was there, had summoned the
                    king, but had become less active when Archidamus had gone out to meet Perseus,
                    and had given an opportunity to the opposing party of summoning Popilius with a
                    thousand infantry from Ambracia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf.
                        above, xvii, 10.</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Just in time, too, came Dinarchus, the chief
                    of cavalry <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This officer was second in
                        command of the Aetolian League, cf. XXXVIII. xi. 7. </note> of the Aetolian
                    League, with six hundred infantry and a hundred cavalry. It was well known that
                    he had come to Stratus as if on his way to Perseus, but then, changing his mind
                    with his <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> luck, had joined the Romans,
                    against whom he had come. Popilius, for his part, was not more off his guard
                    than he should have been, considering the fickle temperaments which encompassed
                    him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He at once took control of the keys of
                    the gates and the guarding of the walls, and removed to the citadel, ostensibly
                    as <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> its garrison, Dinarchus and his
                    Aetolians, along with the young men of Stratus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Perseus, after attempting parleys from the hills which overhang the upper
                    part of the <pb n="p.81"/> city, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> To
                        the north; ruins of the small citadel are traceable in this quarter. </note>
                    on seeing that they were determined and were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> even keeping him at a
                    distance with missiles, pitched his camp five miles from the city across the
                    river Petitarus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There he called a council
                    and, although Archidamus and the Epirote deserters tried to keep him where he
                    was, when the leading Macedonians were of the opinion that he should not fight
                    against the unfavourable season of the year without having arranged for
                    supplies, since the <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> blockaders were bound
                    to feel the want of them before the blockaded, especially when winter-quarters
                    of the enemy were not far distant, Perseus in fear moved his camp into
                    Aperantia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Taken by the Aetolians
                        from Philip in <date when="-0189">189 B.C.</date> , XXXVIII. iii. 4. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Aperantians, because of their great
                    regard for Archidamus and his influence with that people, by general agreement
                    received Perseus; Archidamus himself, with a garrison of eight hundred men, was
                    put in charge of the city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With no less suffering of beasts and men than
                    when he had come, the king returned to Macedonia; Appius, however, was drawn
                    away from the siege of Phanote by the report that Perseus was marching on
                    Stratus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Cleuas, following with a force of
                    vigorous young men beneath the almost impassable spurs of the mountains, killed
                    about a thousand men of the burdened column and captured about two hundred.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After passing over the narrows, Appius
                    remained in camp a few days in the plain which they call Meleon. Meanwhile
                    Cleuas, taking along Philostratus, who had five hundred of the Epirote people,
                    crossed over to the territory of <pb n="p.83"/> Antigonea. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Macedonians set out to plunder; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> Philostratus with his
                    detachment settled down in ambush in a hidden spot. When armed men sallied forth
                    from Antigonea against the scattered plunderers, as they pursued in too open
                    order after these fugitives, they burst into the valley ambushed by the enemy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the killing there of about a
                    thousand and the capturing of nearly a hundred, the campaign was successfully
                    conducted everywhere, and they moved their camp near the settled camp of Appius,
                    so that no violence might be inflicted by the Roman army on their allies.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Appius, who was wasting time to no purpose
                    in these parts, after sending away the forces of Chaonians, The sprotians and
                    whatever other Epirotes there were, retired to Illyricum with his Italian
                    soldiers, divided his men in winter-quarters among the allied cities of the
                    Parthini, and himself returned to Rome to offer sacrifices. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Perseus sent to Cassandrea to act as its garrison a
                    thousand infantry and two hundred cavalry recalled from the people of the
                    Penestae. The envoys returned from Gentius with the same reply. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> On the one hand, Perseus did not cease thereafter to make
                    overtures to him by sending embassy after embassy, and, on the other hand,
                    although it was obvious how much reinforcement Gentius could provide, yet he
                    could not induce himself to incur expense for a matter of the greatest
                    importance in every respect. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf.
                        above, p. 73, note 1.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
