<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to forty-five -
                    41</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">William A. McDevitte, Sen. Class. Mod. Ex. Schol.
                    A.B.T.C.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title> History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to the end,
                                with the epitomes and fragments of the lost books </title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>William A. McDevitte</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XLI.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> The sacred fire was extinguished in the temple of Vesta. Tiberius Sem-
                        pronius Gracchus conquered the Celtiberians and received their submis- sion,
                        and built the town Gracchuris in Spain, as a memorial of his exploits. The
                        Vaccaeans and Lusitanians also were subdued by the pro- consul Postumius
                        Albinus. Both generals triumphed. Antiochus, the son of Antiochus, having
                        been delivered to the Romans by his father, as a hostage, on the death of
                        his brother Seleucus, who had succeeded his father on his demise, being sent
                        from Rome to the sovereignty of Syria, acted the part of a very worthless
                        king, with the exception of his attention to religion, owing to which he
                        erected many magnificent temples in various places; at Athens to Olympian,
                        and at Antioch to Capitoline Jupiter. The lustrum was closed by the censors.
                        Two hundred and sixty-three thousand two hundred and ninety-four citizens
                        are said to have been rated. Quintus Voconius Saxa, tribune of the people,
                        pro- posed a law, that no one should make a woman his heir. Marcus Cato
                        advocated the law: his speech is extant. This book contains besides the
                        successes against the Ligurians, Istrians, Sardinians, and Celtiberians, and
                        the commencement of the Macedonian war, which Perseus, the son of Philip,
                        was planning; for he had sent an embassy to the Carthaginians, which had
                        been heard by them at night; and besides he was tampering with different
                        states of Greece. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This book is
                            very imperfect; a great part of the beginning of it is lost; and there
                            are, besides, considerable chasms in other parts of it. The supplemental
                            passages which the translator has introduced, to complete the connexion,
                            are taken from Crevier. They are printed in a different character.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ... <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Supplement from Crevier: <p>
                            <milestone n="1" unit="suppl-chapter"/> The Roman people had now carried
                            their victorious arms over all parts of the world, and far and wide had
                            pene- trated countries at a vast distance, and separated by several
                            seas. Nevertheless, in such a tide of success flowing according to their
                            wishes, having obtained a high character for modera- <pb n="1916"
                                xml:id="p.1916"/> tion, they were more powerful by their influence
                            than by their military sway; and they boasted frequently that they
                            carried more measures with foreign nations by policy, than by violence
                            and terror. Never insulting conquered nations and kings, generous to
                            their allies, seeking for themselves the honour of victory only, to
                            kings they had preserved their rank, to nations their laws, rights, and
                            liberty, whether in a treaty formed with an equal or with an inferior;
                            and although they had so encompassed, by their arms, both coasts of the
                            Mediter- ranean, from Cadiz even as far as Syria, and had gained respect
                            for the Roman name through immense tracts of terri- tory, yet the only
                            subjects they had, were the nations of Sicily, and the islands on the
                            coast of Italy, and the tribes of the greater part of Spain, which had
                            not yet learned to bear their yoke with resignation. It was the
                            ill-timed treachery of their enemies and rivals, rather than their own
                            ambition, that afforded them cause and material for the increase of
                            their sway. As a special instance: the cruelty of Perseus, who obtained
                            the kingdom of Macedon by treachery and crime, displayed towards his
                            subjects, detested by all, his frantic avarice in the midst of boundless
                            wealth, his inconsiderate levity in the adoption and prosecution of his
                            plans, both destroyed him, and whatever could remain independent, as
                            long as he existed, the principal restraint on the Roman power; for his
                            fall recoiled upon others, and brought with it not only the downfal of
                            his neighbours, but also that of those who were far removed from him.
                            The fall of Carthage and of the Achaeans followed the ruin of the
                            Macedonians: and when the state of all was convulsed by their disasters,
                            the rest of the empires, already tottering for some time, were
                            overthrown shortly after, and all fell beneath the Roman sway. It was my
                            intention to lay here before the reader at a glance these events, so
                            intimately connected in interest, though occurring at different times
                            and places, whilst he contemplated the war impending over the Romans
                            from Perseus, from which especi- ally the Roman power drew the sources
                            of its growth. Perseus was then concocting that war in secret; the
                            Ligurians and Gauls provoked rather than employed the Roman arms. </p>
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        <p>
                            <milestone n="2" unit="suppl-chapter"/> Gaul and the Ligurians were the
                            provinces assigned to the consuls, Marcus Junius Brutus, Aulus Manlius
                            Vulso: Gaul was assigned to Manlius, Liguria to Junius. As to the
                            praetors, <pb n="1917" xml:id="p.1917"/> the city jurisdiction fell to
                            Marcus Titinius Curvus; the foreign, to Tiberius Claudius Nero; Sicily,
                            to Publius Aelius Ligus; Sardinia, to Titus Aebutius; Hither Spain, to
                            the other Marcus Titinius, for there were two of that name praetors in
                            that year; and the Farther Spain, to Titus Fonteius Capito. A fire broke
                            out in the forum, by which very many buildings were burnt to the ground,
                            and the temple of Venus was entirely consumed. The sacred fire of Vesta
                            was extinguished: the virgin who had the care of it was punished with
                            stripes, by order of Marcus Aemilius, the chief pontiff, and
                            supplication was performed, as usual in such cases. In this year the
                            lustrum was closed by Marcus Aemilius Lepidus and Marcus Fulvius
                            Nobilior, censors, in which were rated two hundred and seventy-three
                            thousand two hundred and forty-four citizens. The ambassadors of Perseus
                            arrived, requiring that he should be saluted by the senate as hang,
                            ally, and friend, and that the treaty should be renewed with him which
                            had existed with his father Philip. Perseus was an object of hatred and
                            suspicion to the Romans, and most of them had no <milestone n="3??"
                                unit="section"/> doubt, that as soon as an opportunity was
                            presented, and his strength appeared to him adequate to the struggle, he
                            would wage against the Romans the war, pre- pared in secret by Philip,
                            for so many years. However, that they might not appear to have provoked
                            him when quiet and desirous of peace, and to have themselves furnished
                            him with a cause for war, they conceded to him his demands. Perseus,
                            when this answer was received, supposing that the kingdom was secured to
                            him, began to acquire influence among the Greeks. Being desirous
                            therefore of procuring their friend- ship, he recalled into Macedon all,
                            without exception, who had gone into exile, when condemned for debt or
                            by any judicial proceeding, and those who had left Macedon for high
                            treason, by edicts, openly announced in the island of Delos, and at
                            Delphi, and at the temple of Minerva at Itone, in which he granted to
                            those returning not only pardon, but also restora- tion of all their
                            property, with the income, from that period in which each became an
                            exile. He also remitted to those who were living in Macedon whatever was
                            due to the royal ex- chequer; and released all those imprisoned for high
                            treason. When by these acts he had encouraged the minds of many, he
                            turned the attention of all Greece towards himself, and filled <pb
                                n="1918" xml:id="p.1918"/> it with great hope. And besides, in the
                            entire deportment of the rest of his life, he preserved the dignity of a
                            king; for his mien was noble, and his person well-fitted to discharge
                            all the duties of war and peace; and his age, now matured, possessed a
                            graceful majesty, beaming from brow and forehead. He had none of his
                            father's wantonness, and licentious passions for women and wine. By
                            these praise-worthy acts Perseus ren- dered the beginning of his reign
                            agreeable, although it was des- tined to have a termination very
                            different from its commencement. </p>
                        <p>
                            <milestone n="3" unit="suppl-chapter"/> Before those praetors who had
                            obtained by lot the Spains could come to their provinces, great exploits
                            were there per- formed by Postumius and Gracchus. But the praise of </p>
                        <p>
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Gracchus was extraordinary, for he
                            being in the prime of life, since he far surpassed all his coevals in
                            courage and prudence, even then was lauded greatly by fame, and raised
                            greater hope of himself with regard to the future. Twenty thousand
                            Celtiberians were besieging Carabi, a city in alli- ance with the
                            Romans. Gracchus hastened to bear aid to his allies. That anxiety
                            tortured him, how he could signify his intention to the besieged, while
                            the enemy pressed the city with so close a blockade, that it scarcely
                            appeared possible that an enemy could reach it. The daring of Cominius
                            executed the difficult task. He being prefect of a troop of horse,
                            having pre- viously weighed over the matter with himself, and having
                            inform- ed Gracchus of what he was preparing, dressed himself in a
                            Spanish military cloak, and mixed with the enemy's foragers. Having
                            entered the camp with them he galloped from it to the city, and
                            announced the approach of Tiberius. The townsmen, being aroused by this
                            intelligence from the depth of despair to cheerfulness and daring, and
                            having determined to fight bravely to the last, were relieved from
                            blockade on the third day, in con- sequence of the enemy having departed
                            on the arrival of Grac- chus. He himself having been afterwards attached
                            by a stra- tagem of the barbarians, by the union of skill and strength,
                            so repelled the danger, that the artifice recoiled on its originators.
                            There was a town, Complega by name, that had been built several years
                            before, but strengthened by fortifications and increased by speedy
                            additions, into which many of the Spani- ards had flocked, who
                            previously straggled here and there in need of territory. About twenty
                            thousand men coming forth from that city in the garb of suppliants, and
                            holding forth <pb n="1919" xml:id="p.1919"/> branches of olive, stood in
                            view of the camp as <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> if entreating
                            peace. Immediately, having cast away the emblems of sup- pliants, and
                            having suddenly attached the Romans, they fill every place with alarm
                            and consternation. Gracchus, by a prudent counsel, deserted the camp
                            under the pretence of flight: and whilst they were plundering it with
                            the usual greediness of barbarians, and were encumbering themselves with
                            the spoil, he suddenly returned, and attacking them when in no
                            apprehensions of such an evil, slew the most of them, and even made
                            himself master of their town. There are some who tell the story
                            differently: that Gracchus, when he had dis- covered that the enemy were
                            distressed from want of food, abandoned his camp, which was very well
                            furnished with all articles of food; that the enemy, having taken
                            possession of it, and having intemperately filled themselves with what
                            they had found, and gorged themselves to repletion, were suddenly cut
                            off by the return of the Roman army. </p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        <p>
                            <milestone n="4" unit="suppl-chapter"/> But whether this is a different
                            way of telling the same exploit, or quite a different affair and
                            dfferent victory, it is certain that Gracchus completely conquered
                            several tribes, and moreover the entire nation of the Celtiberians. I
                            would not however have the hardihood to assert that he took and
                            destroyed three hundred of their cities, although Polybius, a writer of
                            the highest authority, makes mention of it; unless that under the name
                            of cities we include towers and castles: by which description of
                            falsehood both the generals in wars and the writers of histories take
                            delight in setting off exploits. For Spain, with its dry and
                            uncultivated soil, could not sup- port a large number of cities. The
                            wild and uncivilized manners of the Spaniards, with the exception of
                            those that dwell on our sea, are also at variance with the assertion,
                            since the dispositions of men are accustomed to become more mild by the
                            meeting with fellow-citizens which occurs in towns. But whatever we may
                            determine concerning the number or description of the cities taken by
                            Sempronius, (for writers vary also in the number, and some have related
                            that one hundred and fifty towns were taken by him, others that one
                            hundred and three was the number,) he certainly performed noble
                            achievements; nor was he distinguished by the praises he received in war
                            only; but he also proved himself unparal- leled in arranging and
                            arbitrating peace and laws for the <pb n="1920" xml:id="p.1920"/>
                            conquered nations. For he distributed lands among the poor and assigned
                            them habitations, and by giving and receiving an oath, secured to, all
                            the tribes inhabiting that country, laws clearly defined, according to
                            which they were to live in friend- ship and alliance with the Roman
                            people. And posterity often appealed to the authority of this treaty in
                            the wars which afterwards broke out. Gracchus appointed that the town
                            which was hitherto called Illurcis, should be distinguished by his own
                            name, and called Gracchuris, as a monument of his merit and actions. The
                            report of the acts of Postumius is more involved in obscurity. However
                            the Vaccaeans and .Lusitanians were conquered by him, and forty thousand
                            of these nations were slain. These affairs being transacted, they both,
                            when they had delivered up the armies and provinces to their successors
                            on their arrival, went home to triumph. In Gaul, Manlius the consul, to
                            whom that province had fallen, when material for a triumph was wanting,
                            eagerly seized an opportunity presented by fortune, of waging war
                            against the Istrians. They had aided the Aetolians on a former occasion
                            when making war against the Romans, and lately too had given trouble. At
                            that time Aepulo, a king of a violent dis- position, ruled them, who was
                            said to have armed the nation trained to peace by his father, ... </p>
                    </note> and therefore was much endeared to the youth desirous of plundering. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the consul held a council on the subject
                    of a war with Istria, some were of opinion that it ought to be begun
                    immediately, before the enemy could collect forces; others, that the senate
                    ought first to be consulted; the opinion was adopted which opposed delay.
                    Accordingly the consul, marching from Aquileia, pitched his camp at the lake
                    Timavus, which lies very near the sea. Thither came Caius Furius, one of the
                    naval commanders, with ten ships; for two naval commanders had been appointed
                    against the fleet of the Illyrians, and these commanders, with twenty ships for
                    the protection of the coast of the Hadriatic, were to make Ancona, as it were,
                    the pivot of their position; so that Lucius Cornelius had to guard the coasts on
                    the right, extending from the latter place to Tarentum; and Caius Furius those
                    on the left, as far as Aquileia. This squadron was sent to the nearest port in
                    the Istrian territory, with a number of transports and a large store of
                    provisions; while the consul, following with the <pb n="1921" xml:id="p.1921"/>
                    legions, encamped at the distance of about five miles from the <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> coast. A plentiful market was soon established at
                    the port, and every thing conveyed thence to the camp. That this might be done
                    with greater safety, out-posts were fixed around the camp; a newly-levied cohort
                    of Placentines was posted between the camp and the sea, as a picket in the
                    direction of Istria; and that the watering-parties might likewise have
                    protection at the river, orders were given to Marcus Aebutius, military tribune,
                    to take thither two companies of the second legion. Titus and Caius Aelius,
                    military tribunes, led out the third legion on the road towards Aquileia, in
                    support of those that went for food and forage. In the same quarter, nearly a
                    mile distant, was the camp of the Gauls: Catmelus acted as their chieftain, and
                    they were not more than three thousand armed men. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Roman army first reached the lake
                    Timavus, the Istrians took post behind a hill, where they could not be seen; and
                    on its march thence followed it through by-ways, watching attentively for some
                    opportunity that might give them an advantage; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    nor did any thing that was done, either on land or sea, escape their
                    observation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they saw that the advanced
                    guards of the Romans were weak, and that the market-place was filled with an
                    unarmed crowd of persons trafficking between the camp and the sea, and that they
                    had not fortified themselves either by works on land, or by the help of ships,
                    they made an assault on two of their posts at once, that of the Placentine
                    cohort, and that of the two companies of the second legion. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> A morning fog concealed their design; and when this began
                    to disperse as the sun grew warm, the light piercing through it in some degree,
                    yet still being far from clear, and, as usual in such cases, magnifying the
                    appearance of every thing, deceived the Romans, and made the army of the enemy
                    appear much greater to them than it really was. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> And when the troops in both the posts, terrified, had fled in the utmost
                    confusion to the camp, there they caused much greater alarm than that which they
                    were under themselves: for they could neither tell what made them fly, nor
                    answer any question that was asked. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then a
                    shouting was heard at all the gates, since there were no guards at them which
                    could withstand an attack: and the crowding together of the soldiers, who fell
                    one against the other in the <pb n="1922" xml:id="p.1922"/> dark, raised a doubt
                    as to whether the enemy was within the rampart. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> One only cry was heard, that of those urging to the sea. This cry uttered by
                    one, and without an object and by chance, resounded every where throughout the
                    entire camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At first, therefore, a few with
                    their arms and a greater part without them, as if they had received orders so to
                    do, ran off to the sea shore; then followed more, and at length almost the whole
                    of the army, and the consul himself, when, having attempted in vain to call back
                    the fugitives, he had effected nothing by commands, advice, and, at last, by
                    entreaties. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcus Licinius Strabo, a military
                    tribune of the third legion, with three companies alone, remained, being left
                    behind by his legion. The Istrians having made an attack on the empty camp,
                    after that no other had met them in arms, came upon him while he was drawing up
                    and encouraging his men at the general's quarters; the fight was maintained with
                    more resolution than might be anticipated, from the small number of the
                    defenders; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> nor did it cease until the
                    tribune, and those who stood round him, were all slain. The enemy then, tearing
                    down the general's tent, and seizing on all they could find, went on to the
                    quaestor's quarters, and the adjoining forum, called Quintana. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Thereupon, when they found all kinds of food dressed and
                    laid out in <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> the quaestor's tent, and the
                    couches placed in order, their chieftain lay down and began to feast. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Presently all the rest, thinking no more of fighting
                    or of the enemy, did the same; and being unaccustomed to any sort of rich food,
                    they greedily gorged themselves with meat and wine. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The appearance of affairs among the Romans was
                    by no means the same. There was confusion both on land and sea; the mariners
                    struck their tents, and hastily conveyed on board the provisions which had been
                    sent on shore; the soldiers in a panic rushed into the boats, and even into the
                    water. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Some of the seamen, in fear lest their
                    vessels should be overcrowded, opposed the entrance of the multitude, while
                    others pushed off from the shore into the deep. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Hence arose a dispute, and in a short time a fight, accompanied by wounds and
                    loss of lives, both of soldiers and seamen; until by order of the consul, the
                    fleet was removed to a distance from the shore. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> He next set about separating the armed from the unarmed; out of so large a
                    number, there were scarcely found <pb n="1923" xml:id="p.1923"/> twelve hundred
                    who had preserved their arms; very few horsemen who had brought their horses
                    with them; while the rest were an ill-looking throng, like servants and sutlers,
                    and would certainly have fallen a prey, if the enemy had not neglected the war.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At length an express was despatched to
                    call in the third legion and the out-post of the Gauls; and at the same time the
                    troops began to march back from all parts in order to retake the camp, and wipe
                    off their disgrace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The military tribunes of
                    the third legion ordered their men to throw away the forage and wood, and
                    commanded the centurions to mount two elderly soldiers on horses from which the
                    loads were thrown down, and each of the cavalry to take a young foot soldier
                    with him on his horse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He told them, <quote>
                        it would be a great honour to their legion, if they should recover, by
                        bravery, the camp which had been lost by the cowardice of the second; and
                        that this might be easily effected, if the barbarians were surprised while
                        busied in plundering. In like manner as they had taken it, so might it be
                        retaken. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His exhortation was received by the army with
                    the utmost alacrity; they eagerly bear on the standards, nor do the soldiers
                    delay the standard-bearers. However the consul, and the troops which were led
                    back from the shore, reached the rampart first. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> Lucius Atius, first tribune of the second legion, not only urged on his men,
                    but informed them also, that <quote> if the Istrians meant to retain the camp,
                        which they had taken, by the same arms by which they took it, they would, in
                        the first place, have pursued their enemy driven from his camp to the sea;
                        and, in the next place, they would certainly have stationed guards outside
                        the rampart; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that it was very likely
                        that they were lying in sleep, or drowned in wine. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately after this, he ordered his own
                    standard-bearer, Aulus Baeculonius, a man of known bravery, to bear in the
                    standard; who replied, that if the men were willing to follow him, he would
                    cause it to be done more quickly. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then,
                    exerting all his strength, after throwing the standard across the intrenchment,
                    he was the first that entered the gate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And on
                    the other side, Titus Aelius and Caius Aelius, military tribunes of the third
                    legion, with their cavalry arrived; and, quickly after them, the soldiers whom
                    they had mounted in pairs on the beasts of burden; also the consul with the main
                        <pb n="1924" xml:id="p.1924"/> body. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Only
                    a few of the Istrians, who had drunk in moderation, betook themselves to flight:
                    death succeeded as the continuation of the sleep of the others; and the Romans
                    recovered all their effects unimpaired, except the victuals and wine which had
                    been consumed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The soldiers, too, who had been
                    left sick in the camp, when they saw their countrymen within the trenches,
                    snatched up arms, and committed great slaughter. The bravery of Caius Popilius,
                    a horseman, was pre-eminent above that of all. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    His surname was Labellus. He had been left behind in the camp, on account of a
                    wound in his foot, notwithstanding which he slew by far the greatest number of
                    the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> About eight thousand Istrians were
                    killed, but not one prisoner taken; for rage and indignation had made the Romans
                    regardless of booty. The king of the Istrians, though drunk after his banquet,
                    was hastily mounted on a horse by his people, and effected his escape.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of the conquerors there were lost two
                    hundred and thirty-seven men; more of whom fell in the fight in the morning,
                    than in the retaking of the camp. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened that Cneius and Lucius Cavillius,
                    new citizens of Aquileia, coming with a convoy of provisions, and not knowing
                    what had passed, were very near going into the camp after it was taken by the
                    Istrians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These men, when, leaving their
                    baggage, they had fled back to Aquileia, filled all things with consternation
                    and alarm, not only there, but, in a few days after, at Rome also; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> to which intelligence was brought, not only that the
                    camp was taken, and that the troops ran away, as was really the case, but that
                    every thing was lost and that the whole army was entirely cut off. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Wherefore, as is usual in a dangerous emergency,
                    extraordinary levies were ordered by proclamation, both in the city and
                    throughout all Italy. Two legions of Roman citizens were raised, and ten
                    thousand foot and five hundred horse were demanded from the allies of the Latin
                    nation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul Marcus Junius was ordered
                    to pass on into Gaul, and demand from the several states of that province,
                    whatever number of troops each was able to supply. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time it was decreed that Tiberius Claudius, the
                    praetor, should issue orders for the fourth legion, and five thousand foot and
                    two hundred and fifty horse, of the Latins, to assemble at Pisae; and that he
                    should guard that province during the consul's absence; and <pb n="1925"
                        xml:id="p.1925"/> that Marcus Titinius, the praetor, should order the first
                    legion, and an equal number of allied foot and horse, to meet at Ariminum.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nero, habited in general's robes, set out
                    for Pisae, which was in his province. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Titinius, after sending Caius Cassius, military tribune, to Ariminum, to take
                    the command of the legion there, held a levy at Rome. The consul, Marcus Junius,
                    passed over from Liguria into the province of Gaul, and having immediately
                    ordered <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> a levy of auxiliaries through the
                    states of Gaul, and having ordered the colonies to send soldiers, came to
                    Aquileia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There he learned that the army was
                    safe; wherefore, after despatching a letter to Rome, that they might be no
                    longer alarmed, he sent home the auxiliaries, which he had ordered the Gauls to
                    furnish, and proceeded himself to join his colleague. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> There was great joy at Rome after the unexpected news; the
                    levies were stopped, the soldiers who had taken the military oath were
                    discharged, and the troops at Ariminum, who were afflicted with a pestilential
                    sickness, were remanded home. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Istrians,
                    when they with a numerous force were encamped at no great distance from the
                    consul, after they heard that the other consul was arrived with a new army,
                    dispersed, and returned to their several states. The consuls led back their
                    legions into winter quarters at Aquileia. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The alarm caused by the affairs of Istria
                    being at length composed, a decree of the senate was passed, that the consuls
                    should settle between themselves which of them should come to Rome, to preside
                    at the elections. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When two plebeian tribunes,
                    Aulus Licinius Narva and Caius Papirius Turdus, in their harangues to the
                    people, uttered severe reflections on Manlius, then abroad; and proposed the
                    passing of an order, that although the government of their provinces had already
                    been continued to the consuls for a year, yet Manlius should not hold command
                    beyond the ides of March; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> in order that he
                    might immediately, after going out of office, be brought to trial. Against this
                    proposition, Quintus Aelius, another tribune, protested; and, after violent
                    struggles, prevailed so far, as to prevent its being passed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> About this time, when Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus and
                    Lucius Postumius Albinus came home from Spain, an audience of the senate is
                    granted to them, by Marcus Titinius the praetor, to speak of the services which
                    they had rendered, and demand the honours they had merited, and also that
                    thanksgiving should be offered <pb n="1926" xml:id="p.1926"/> to the immortal
                    gods. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At the same time also it was known, by
                    the letters of Titus Aebutius the praetor, which his son brought to the senate,
                    that there was great commotion in Sardinia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Iliensians, having added to their forces Balearian auxiliaries, had invaded
                    the province though at peace with them; nor could resistance be offered to them
                    by a weak army, which had besides lost great numbers by a pestilence. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Ambassadors from the Sardinians made the same
                    representations, entreating the senate to send relief to their cities; for as to
                    the country, it was already entirely ruined. This embassy, and every thing which
                    referred to Sardinia, was referred to the new magistrates. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> There was an embassy from the Lycians, no less entitled to
                    commiseration, who complained of the cruel treatment which they suffered from
                    the Rhodians, to whose government they had been annexed by Lucius Cornelius
                    Scipio. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>They had formerly,</quote> they said, <quote> been under the dominion of
                        Antiochus, and their bondage under that king, compared to their present
                        condition, appeared an honourable state of liberty; that they were not only
                        oppressed by acts of government, but individually underwent real slavery.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That they themselves, their wives,
                        and children, were abused alike by them; that cruelties were practised on
                        their persons, and their character blotted and dishonoured, a circumstance
                        which would excite the indignation of every one. They were openly treated
                        with contemptuous insults, merely for the purpose of exercising an usurped
                        prerogative, that they might not doubt that there was no difference between
                        them and purchased slaves. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The senate was highly displeased at such
                    proceedings, and gave the Lycians a letter to the Rhodians, acquainting them,
                    that <quote> it was the will of the senate, that neither the Lycians should be
                        subjected to the Rhodians as slaves, nor should any other men who were born
                        free become the slaves of any one; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but
                        that the Lycians should be under the government, and, at the same time, the
                        protection of the Rhodians, in like manner as the allied states were
                        subjected to the Roman people. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Two triumphs for conquests in Spain were then
                    successively celebrated. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> First, Sempronius
                    Gracchus triumphed over the Celtiberians and their allies; next day, Lucius
                    Postumius triumphed over the Lusitanians, and the other Spaniards in that
                    quarter. Tiberius Gracchus carried in the procession forty <pb n="1927"
                        xml:id="p.1927"/> thousand pounds' weight of silver, Albinus twenty
                    thousand. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They distributed to each of their
                    soldiers twenty-five denariuses, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 15
                            <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 7 1/2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> double that sum to a centurion, triple it to a horseman; the same sums
                    to the allied troops as to the Roman. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    consul, Marcus Junius, happened to arrive at Rome at this time from Istria, in
                    order to hold the elections. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The plebeian
                    tribunes, Papirius and Licinius, after harassing him in the senate, with
                    questions relative to what had passed in Istria, brought him into the assembly
                    of the people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To which inquiries the consul
                    answered, that <quote> he had been not more than eleven days in that province;
                        and that as to what had happened when he was not present, he, like
                        themselves, gained his information from report. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But they still proceeded to ask, <quote> why,
                        then, did not Manlius rather come to Rome, that he might account to the
                        Roman people for his having quitted Gaul, the province allotted to him, and
                        gone into Istria? When had the senate decreed a war with that nation? When
                        had the people ordered it? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But he will
                        say, 'Though the war was indeed undertaken by private authority, yet it was
                        conducted with prudence and courage.' On the contrary, it is impossible to
                        say, whether it was undertaken with greater injustice than the rashness with
                        which it was conducted. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Two advanced
                        guards were surprised by the Istrians; a Roman camp was taken, with whatever
                        infantry and cavalry were in it; the rest in disorder, without arms, and
                        among the foremost the consul himself, fled to the shore and the ships.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But he should answer for all these
                        matters when he became a private citizen, since he had been unwilling to do
                        so while consul. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The elections were then held, in which Caius
                    Claudius Pulcher and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus were chosen consuls. Next day
                    the following persons were elected praetors, Publius Aelius Tubero, a second
                    time, Caius Quintus Flamininus, Caius Numisius, Lucius Mummius, Cneius Cornelius
                    Scipio, and Publius Valerius Laevinus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    city jurisdiction fell, by lot, to Tubero; the foreign, to Quintus; Sicily, to
                    Numisius; and Sardinia, to Mummius; but this last, on account of the importance
                    of the war there, was made a consular province. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Gracchus obtains it by lot; Claudius, Istria; Scipio and Laevinus received
                    Gaul, which was divided into two provinces. On the ides of March, the day when
                    Sempronius and <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> Claudius <pb n="1928"
                        xml:id="p.1928"/> assumed the administration, a cursory mention only was
                    made of the provinces of Sardinia and of Istria, and of those who had commenced
                    hostilities there; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but on the day following,
                    the ambassadors of the Sardinians, who had been referred to the new magistrates,
                    were introduced, and Lucius Minucius Thermus, lieutenant-general under the
                    consul Manlius in Istria, attended; and by them the senate was accurately
                    informed how far these provinces were involved in war. Ambassadors from the
                    confederate states of Latium, who, after having ineffectually applied to the
                    former consuls and censors, were at last introduced to an audience, made a
                    powerful impression on the senate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The amount
                    of their complaints was, that <quote> their citizens, having been rated in the
                        general survey at Rome, had most of them removed thither; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> and that if this practice were allowed, it would come
                        to pass, in the course of a very few lustrums, that their deserted towns and
                        country would be unable to furnish any soldiers. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Samnites and the Pelignians also
                    represented, that four thousand families had emigrated to Fregellae; and that
                    neither of these places furnished less soldiers on that account. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> That there had been practised two species of fraud in
                    individuals changing their citizenship: there was a law, which granted liberty
                    to any of the allies or Latins, who should not leave his offspring at home, to
                    be enrolled a citizen of Rome; yet, by an abuse of this law, some did injury to
                    the allies, others to the Roman people. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For,
                    at first, to evade the leaving offspring at home, they made over their children
                    as slaves to some Roman, under an agreement that they should be again set free,
                    and thus become citizens by emancipation; and then those men, who had now no
                    children to leave, became Roman citizens. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Afterwards, they neglected even these appearances of law; and, without any
                    regard either to the ordinances or to progeny, passed indiscriminately into the
                    Roman state by migration, and getting themselves included in the survey.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To prevent such proceedings in future,
                    the ambassadors requested the senate to order the allies to return to their
                    respective states, and to provide by a law that no one should make any man his
                    property, or alienate such property for the purpose of a change of citizenship;
                    and that if any person should by such means be made a citizen of Rome, he should
                    not enjoy the rights of a citizen." <pb n="1929" xml:id="p.1929"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate granted their petitions; and then
                    Sardinia and Istria, the provinces which were in arms, were disposed of.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two legions were ordered to be enrolled
                    for Sardinia, each containing five thousand two hundred foot and three hundred
                    horse; and of allies and Latins, twelve thousand foot and six hundred horse; and
                    it was decided that the consul should have ten ships, of five banks of oars, if
                    he should think it requisite to take them from the docks. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The same numbers of infantry and cavalry were decreed for
                    Istria as for Sardinia. The consuls were ordered to send into Spain to Marcus
                    Titinius, one legion, with three hundred horse and five thousand foot, and two
                    hundred and fifty horse of the allies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before
                    the consuls cast lots for their provinces, several prodigies were reported:
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that in the Crustumine territory, a stone
                    fell from the sky into the grove of Mars; that in the Roman territory, a boy was
                    born defective in his limbs; that a serpent with four feet had been seen; that
                    at Capua, many buildings in the forum were struck by lightning; and, that at
                    Puteoli, two ships were burned by lightning. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Amidst these prodigies which were reported from abroad, a wolf also, after
                    entering Rome by the Colline gate, was chased during the day, and, to the great
                    consternation of its pursuers, escaped through the Esquiline gate. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> On account of these prodigies, the consuls sacrificed
                    victims of the larger kinds, and there was a supplication, for one day, at all
                    the shrines. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the sacrifices were duly
                    performed, they cast lots for their provinces; Istria fell to Claudius, Sardinia
                    to Sempronius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then Caius Claudius, by
                    direction of the senate, proposed a law and issued a proclamation, that <quote>
                        any of the allies and Latin confederates, who themselves, or whose
                        ancestors, had been surveyed among the associated states of Latium in the
                        censorship of Marcus Claudius and Titus Quintius, or at any time since,
                        should all return, each to his respective state, before the calends of
                        November. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Inquiry concerning such as did not obey, was
                    intrusted to Lucius Mummius the praetor. To the law and the proclamation of the
                    consul, <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> was added a decree of the senate,
                    that <quote> the dictator, consul, interrex, censor, or praetor, who then should
                        be in office, before whom any slave should be brought, to receive
                        manumission, should cause the said slave who was about to be made free, to
                        make oath, that the person giving him liberty did not do it for the purpose
                        of his changing his citizenship; </quote> they <pb n="1930" xml:id="p.1930"
                    /> ordered that he, whoever would not swear this oath, should not be manumitted.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The cognizance and jurisdiction in this
                    business was, for the future, assigned to Caius Claudius the consul. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these matters passed at Rome, Marcus
                    Junius and Aulus Manlius, the consuls of the preceding year, after remaining
                    during the winter at Aquileia, led their army early in the spring into the
                    Istrian territories; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> where when they spread
                    their depredations through a great part of the country, grief and indignation,
                    rather than any well-grounded hope of being able to make head against these
                    joint forces, roused the Istrians, on perceiving the plunder of their property.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A hasty levy of their young men being made
                    from all their cantons, this raw and tumultuary army made its first onset with
                    more vigour than perseverance. About four thousand of them were slain in the
                    field; and the rest, giving over the war, fled in different directions to their
                    respective states. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Soon after, they sent
                    ambassadors to the Roman camp to sue for peace, and then delivered up the
                    hostages required of them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When these
                    transactions were made known at Rome, by letters from the proconsul, Caius
                    Claudius, the consul, fearing that this proceeding might, perhaps, take the
                    province and the army out of his hands, without offering vows, without assuming
                    the military habit, and unaccompanied by his lictors, having acquainted his
                    colleague alone with his intention, set out in the night, and with the utmost
                    speed hastened to the province, where he conducted himself even with less
                    prudence than he had shown in coming. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For, in
                    an assembly which he called, after making severe remarks on Manlius's running
                    away from the camp, which were very offensive to the ears of the soldiers, as
                    they themselves had begun the flight, and after railing at Marcus Junius, as
                    having made himself a sharer in the disgrace of his colleague, he at last
                    ordered both of them to quit the province. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And
                    when they replied, that when the consul should come, in the regular manner,
                    agreeably to ancient practice; when he should set out from the city, after
                    offering vows in the Capitol, attended by his lictors and dressed in the
                    military habit, then they would obey his orders. Maddened by anger, he summoned
                    the person who acted as quaestor to Manlius, and ordered him to bring fetters,
                    threatening to send Junius and Manlius to Rome in chains. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The consul's command was slighted by this man too; and the
                    sur- <pb n="1931" xml:id="p.1931"/> rounding crowd of soldiers, who favoured the
                    cause of their commanders, and were incensed against the consul, supplied him
                    with resolution to refuse obedience. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At last
                    the consul, overpowered by the reproaches of individuals and the scoffs of the
                    multitude, for they even turned him into ridicule, went back to Aquileia in the
                    same ship in which he had come. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thence he
                    wrote to his colleague, desiring him to give notice to that part of the
                        <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> new-raised troops who were enlisted for
                    Istria, to assemble at Aquileia, in order that he should have no delay at Rome,
                    but set out, in the military habit, as soon as the ceremony of offering vows was
                    finished. These directions his colleague punctually executed, and an early day
                    was appointed for the assembling of the troops. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> Claudius almost overtook his own letter. On his arrival he called an
                    assembly, that he might represent the conduct of Manlius and Junius; <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> and, staying only three days in Rome, he offered his
                    vows in the Capitol, put on the military habit, and, attended by his lictors,
                    set out to his province with the same rapid speed which he had used in the
                    former journey. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days before his arrival, Junius and
                    Manlius had laid vigorous siege to the town of Nesatium, in which the principal
                    Istrians, and Epulo their king, had shut themselves up. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Claudius, bringing thither the two new legions, dismissed
                    the old army, with its commanders; invested the town himself; and prosecuted the
                    siege with regular works. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He by the labour of
                    many days changed the course of, and carried away in a new channel, a river
                    which flowed on the outside of the wall, and greatly impeded the proceedings of
                    the besiegers, while it supplied the Istrians with water. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This event, of the water being cut off, terrified the
                    barbarians, as if effected by some supernatural power; yet still they
                    entertained no thoughts of peace, but set about killing their wives and
                    children; exhibiting a spectacle shocking even to their enemies; and, after
                    putting them to death in open view on the walls, tumbled them down. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Amid the simultaneous shrieking of women and
                    children, and this horrid carnage, the soldiers, scaling the walls, effected an
                    entrance into the town. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as the king
                    heard the uproar of the captured city, from the cries of terror uttered by the
                    flying inhabitants, he <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> plunged his sword
                    into his breast, that he might not be taken alive; the rest were either killed
                    or <pb n="1932" xml:id="p.1932"/> taken prisoners. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> After this, two other towns, Mutila and Faveria, were
                    stormed and destroyed. The booty, which exceeded expectation, considering the
                    poverty of the nation, was all given up to the soldiers. Five thousand six
                    hundred and thirty-two persons were sold by auction, and the fomenters of the
                    war were beaten with rods and beheaded. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By the
                    destruction of these three towns, and the death of the king, the whole country
                    of Istria was brought to terms of peace; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    every one of its states, giving hostages, submitted to the dominion of the
                    Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For some time before the conclusion of the war
                    with Istria, consultations were held among the Ligurians about the renewal of
                    hostilities. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Tiberius Claudius, proconsul, who
                    had been consul the year before, with a garrison of one legion, held the command
                    of Pisae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when the senate was informed by
                    his letter of their proceedings, they vote that <quote>the same letter should be
                        carried to Caius Claudius,</quote> for the other consul had already crossed
                    over into Sardinia; and they added a decree, that, since the province of Istria
                    was subdued, he might, if he thought proper, lead his army into Liguria.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the same time, a supplication for two
                    days was decreed, in consequence of the letter which he wrote concerning his
                    actions in Istria. The other consul, Sempronius, likewise was successful in his
                    operations in Sardinia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He carried his army
                    into the territory of the Ilian tribe of Sardinians. Powerful reinforcements
                    from the Balarians had come to the Ilians. He fought a pitched battle against
                    the combined forces of the two states. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    enemy were routed and put to flight, and driven from their camp; twelve thousand
                    armed men were slain. Next day, the consul ordered their arms to be gathered
                    into a heap and burned, as an offering to Vulcan. He then led back his
                    victorious troops into winter quarters in the allied cities. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Caius Claudius, on receipt of the letter of Tiberius
                    Claudius and the decree of the senate, marched his legions out of Istria into
                    Liguria. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The enemy, having advanced into the
                    plains, were encamped on the river Scultenna: here a pitched battle was fought,
                    in which fifteen thousand of the enemy were killed, and about seven hundred
                    captured in the fight, and in the camp, for that too was stormed; and also
                    fifty-one military standards were taken. The Ligurians who survived the
                    slaughter, fled back in every direction into the mountains. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1933" xml:id="p.1933"/> No appearance of arms any where met the consul
                    while ravaging the low country. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Claudius,
                    having thus in one year subdued two nations, and, what has rarely been achieved
                    in a single consulate, completed the reduction of two provinces, came home to
                    Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Several prodigies were reported this year:
                    that at Crustuminum a bird, which they call the ospray, cut a sacred stone with
                    its beak; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that a cow spoke in Campania; that
                    at Syracuse a brazen statue of a cow was mounted by a farmer's bull, which had
                    strayed from the herd. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A supplication of one
                    day was performed in Crustuminum, on the spot; the cow at Campania was ordered
                    to be maintained at the public expense, and the prodigy at Syracuse was
                    expiated, the deities to whom supplications should be offered, being declared by
                    the aruspices. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This year died, in the office
                    of pontiff, Marcus Claudius Marcellus, who had been consul and censor; and his
                    son, Marcus Marcellus, was chosen into the vacant place. The same year a colony
                    of two thousand Roman citizens was settled at Luca. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The triumvirs, Publius Aelius, Lucius Egilius, and Cneius
                    Sicinius, planted it. Fifty-one acres and a half of land were given to each.
                    This land had been taken from the Ligurians, and had been the property of the
                    Etrurians, before it fell into their possession. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Caius Claudius, the consul, arrived at the city, and after laying before the
                    senate a detail of his successful services in Istria and Liguria, a triumph was
                    decreed to him on demanding it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He triumphed,
                    in office, over the two nations at once. In this procession he carried three
                    hundred and seven thousand denariuses, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > 9593 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 15 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
                    </note> and eighty-five thousand seven hundred and two quinariuses. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1339 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 10 1/2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> To each soldier fifteen denariuses <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 9 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 1/2 <hi rend="italics"
                            >d.</hi>
                    </note> were given, double that sum to a centurion, triple it to a horseman.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The allied soldiers received less, by
                    half, than the native troops, for which reason they followed his chariot in
                    silence to show their disgust. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While this triumph over the Ligurians was
                    celebrated, that people, perceiving that not only the consular army returned to
                    Rome, but also <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> that the legion at Pisae had
                    been disbanded by Tiberius Claudius, shaking off their fears, and collecting an
                    army secretly, crossed the mountains by winding paths, and came down into the
                    plains, and after ravaging the lands of Mutina, by a sudden assault they gained
                    possession <pb n="1934" xml:id="p.1934"/> of the colony itself. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When this account was brought to Rome, the senate ordered
                    Caius Claudius, the consul, to hold the elections as soon as possible, and
                    (after appointing magistrates for the ensuing year) to go back to his province,
                    and rescue the colony out of the hands of the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The elections were held as the senate had directed; and
                    Cneius Cornelius Scipio Hispalus, with Quintus Petillius Spurinus, were chosen
                    consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then Marcus Popillius Laenas, Publius
                    Licinius Crassus, Marcus Cornelius Scipio, Lucius Papirius Maso, Marcus Aburius,
                    and Lucius Aquilius Gallus, were elected proctors. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> To Caius Claudius, the consul, his command was prolonged
                    for a year, and likewise the administration of the province of Gaul; and he was
                    ordered, lest the Istrians should follow the example of the Ligurians, to send
                    into Istria the allied Latin troops, which he had brought home to attend his
                    triumph. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the consuls, Cneius Cornelius
                    and Quintus Petillius, on the day of entering into office, according to custom,
                    sacrificed each an ox to Jupiter, the head of the liver was not found in the
                    victim sacrificed by Petillius; which being reported to the senate, he was
                    ordered to sacrifice oxen until the omens should be favourable. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The senate being then consulted concerning the provinces,
                    decreed Pisae and Liguria to be the provinces of the consuls. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> They ordered that he to whose lot Pisae fell, should, at
                    the time of the elections, come home to preside at them; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and that they should severally enlist two new legions and
                    three hundred horse; and should order the allies, and Latin confederates, to
                    furnish ten thousand foot and six hundred horse to each. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The command was prolonged to Tiberius Claudius, until such
                    time as the consul should arrive in the province. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the senate was employed in these
                    affairs, Caius Cornelius, being called by a beadle, went out of the
                    senate-house; and, after a short time, returned with a troubled countenance, and
                    told the conscript fathers that the liver of a fat ox, which he had sacrificed,
                    had melted away; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that, when this was told him
                    by the person who dressed the victims, he did not believe it, and he himself
                    ordered the water to be poured out of the vessel in which the entrails were
                    boiled; and he saw all entire but the liver, which had been unaccountably
                    consumed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While the fathers were under much
                    terror on account of this prodigy, their alarm was augmented by <pb n="1935"
                        xml:id="p.1935"/> the other consul, who informed them that, on account of
                    the first victim having wanted the head of the liver, he had sacrificed three
                    oxen, and had not yet found favourable omens. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The senate ordered him to continue sacrificing the larger victims until he
                    should find favourable omens. They say that the victims offered to the other
                    deities at length presented good omens; but that in those offered to Health,
                    Petillius could find none such. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then the
                    consuls and praetors cast lots for their provinces, when Pisae fell to Cneius
                    Cornelius; Liguria, to Petillius. Of the praetors, Lucius Papirius Maso obtained
                    the city jurisdiction; Marcus Abutius, the foreign; Marcus Cornelius Scipio
                    Maluginensis, the Farther Spain; Lucius Aquilius Gallus, Sicily. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Two of them petitioned to be excused from going into
                    their provinces. First, Marcus Popillius requested that he might not be obliged
                    to go to Sardinia, alleging that <quote> Gracchus was bringing that province
                        into a state of tranquillity; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that Titus
                        Aebutius the praetor had been given to him by the senate as his assistant;
                        and that it was by no means expedient to interrupt the train of business,
                        for the completion of which there was no method so efficacious as the
                        continuing the management in the same hands; <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> that, amid the transfer of command and initiation of the successors, who
                        must be impressed with a knowledge of <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                        circumstances before they can proceed to action, opportunities of
                        successfully transacting matters were frequently lost. </quote> The excuse
                    of Popillius was admitted. Then Publius Licinius Crassus alleged that he was
                    prevented from going into his province by solemn sacrifices. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> That which had fallen to his lot was Hither Spain. But he
                    was ordered either to proceed thither, or to swear in the public assembly that
                    he was hindered by the performance of solemn anniversary sacrifices. When this
                    determination was made in the case of Publius Licinius, Marcus Cornelius
                    demanded that his oath, of the like import, might be admitted as an excuse for
                    his not going into the Farther Spain. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Both
                    the praetors accordingly took an oath in the same words. Marcus Titinius and
                    Titus Fonteius, proconsuls, were ordered to remain in Spain, with authority as
                    before; and it was decreed that a reinforcement should be sent to them of three
                    thousand Roman foot, with two hundred horse; and five hundred Latin foot, with
                    three hundred horse. <pb n="1936" xml:id="p.1936"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Latin festival was celebrated on the third
                    day before the nones of May; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">5th
                        May.</note> and because, on the offering of one of the victims, the
                    magistrate of Lanuvium had not prayed for the ROMAN PEOPLE, THE QUIRITES,
                    religious scruples were felt. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the matter
                    was laid before the senate, and they referred it to the college of pontiffs, the
                    latter determined that the Latin festival had not been duly performed, and must
                    be repeated; and that the Lanuvians, on whose account they were repeated, should
                    furnish the victims. Besides the concern excited by matters of a religious
                    nature, another incident caused no small degree of uneasiness. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The consul Cneius Cornelius, as he was returning from the
                    Alban mount, fell down. And being paralysed in part of his limbs, set out for
                    the waters of Cumae, where, his disorder still increasing, he died. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> His body was conveyed to Rome to be buried, and the
                    funeral obsequies were performed with great magnificence: he was likewise a
                    pontiff. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The other consul, Quintus Petillius,
                    was ordered to hold an assembly, as soon as the auspices could be taken, for the
                    election of a consul in the room of his late colleague, and to proclaim the
                    Latin festival. Accordingly, by proclamation, he fixed the election for the
                    third day before the nones of August, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >3rd August.</note> and the Latin festival for the third before the ides of
                    the same month. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">11th August.</note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While the minds of the people were full of
                    religious fears, to add thereto, several prodigies were reported to have
                    happened; that a blazing torch was seen in the sky at Tusculum; that the temple
                    of Apollo, and many private buildings at Gabii, and a wall and gate at
                    Graviscae, were struck by lightning. The senate ordered these to be expiated as
                    the pontiffs should direct. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While the consuls
                    were detained, at first by religious ceremonies, and afterwards, one of them, by
                    the death of the other, and then by the election and the repetition of the Latin
                    festival, in the mean time Caius Claudius marched the army to Mutina, which the
                    Ligurians had taken the year before. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Before
                    three days had elapsed from the commencement of the siege he retook it, and
                    delivered it back to the colonists; on this occasion eight thousand Ligurians
                    were killed within the walls. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He immediately
                    despatched a letter to Rome, in which he not only represented this success, but
                    likewise boasted that through his good conduct and good fortune there was <pb
                        n="1937" xml:id="p.1937"/> not one enemy of the Roman people left on this
                    side the Alps; and that a large tract of land had been taken, which might be
                    distributed among many thousand men, giving each a share. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same period, Tiberius Sempronius,
                    after gaining many victories, totally subdued the people of Sardinia. Fifteen
                    thousand of the enemy were slain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> All the
                    tribes of the Sardinians, who had revolted, were brought under the dominion of
                    Rome. On those which had formerly been tributary, double taxes were imposed and
                    levied; the rest paid a contribution in corn. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When he had thus restored peace in the province, and received hostages from all
                    parts of the island, to the number of two hundred and thirty, deputies are sent
                    by him to Rome, to give information of these transactions, and to request of the
                    senate, that in consideration of those services, performed under the conduct and
                    auspices of Tiberius Sempronius, a thanksgiving might be offered to the immortal
                    gods, and permission granted him to quit the province and bring home the army
                    with him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate, having given audience to
                    the deputies in the temple of Apollo, ordered a thanksgiving for two days, and
                    that the consuls should sacrifice forty victims of the larger kinds; but
                    commanded the proconsul, Tiberius Sempronius, and his army, to continue in the
                    province for the year. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then the election for
                    filling the vacant place of a consul, which had been fixed by proclamation for
                    the third day before the nones of August, was finished in one day, and the
                    consul Quintus Petillius declared Caius Valerius Laevinus duly elected his
                    colleague, who was to assume immediately the administration of his office.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This man, having been long ambitious of
                    the government of a province, when, very seasonably for the gratification of his
                    wishes, a letter now arrived with intelligence that the Ligurians were again in
                    arms, on the nones of August <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">5th
                        August.</note> assumed the military habit; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    and ordered that, on account of this alarm, the third legion should march into
                    Gaul, and join Caius Claudius, proconsul, and that the commanders of the fleet
                    should sail with their ships to Pisae, and coast along the Ligurian shore, to
                    terrify that people by the sight of a naval power also. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The other consul, Quintus Petillius, had appointed a day
                    for his troops to assemble in the same place. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, Caius Claudius, proconsul, on hearing of the rebellion <pb n="1938"
                        xml:id="p.1938"/> in Liguria, having hastily collected some soldiers, in
                    addition to those whom he had with him at Parma, brought this army to the
                    frontiers of Liguria. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the approach of Caius Claudius, the enemy,
                    reflecting that this was the same commander who had defeated them at the river
                    Scultenna, resolving to rely on situation, rather than arms, for their defence
                    against a force with which they had so unsuccessfully struggled, took post in
                    two mountains, called Letum and Balista; and, for greater security, surrounded
                    their encampment with a wall. Some, who were too slow in removing from the low
                    grounds, were surprised and put to the sword, one thousand five hundred in
                    number. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The others kept themselves close on
                    the mountains; and retaining, in the midst of their fears, their native savage
                    disposition, vented their fury on the prey taken at Mutina. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They put their prisoners to death after shocking
                    mutilation: the cattle they butchered in the temples, rather than decently
                    sacrificed: and then (satiated with the destruction of living creatures) they
                    turned their fury against things inanimate, dashing against the walls even
                    vessels made for use rather than for show. Quintus Petillius, the consul,
                    fearing that the war might be brought to a conclusion before he arrived in the
                    province, wrote to Caius Claudius to bring the army into Gaul, saying, that he
                    would wait for him at the Long Plains. Claudius, immediately on receipt of the
                    letter, marched out of Liguria, and gave up the command of the army to the
                    consul at the Long Plains. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To the same place
                    came, in a few days after, the other consul, Caius Valerius. There having
                    divided their forces before they separated, they both together performed a
                    purification of the troops. They then cast lots for their respective routes, it
                    having been resolved that they should not assail the enemy on the same side.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was certain that Valerius cast his lot
                    auspiciously, because he was in the consecrated ground; the augurs afterwards
                    announced that there was this defect in the case of Petillius, that he himself
                    when outside the consecrated ground cast his lot into the urn, which was
                    subsequently brought into the sacred place. They then began their march in
                    different directions; Petillius pitched his camp against the ridge of Balista
                    and Letum, which joined the two together with one continued range. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> They report, that while he was here encouraging his
                    soldiers, whom he had assembled <pb n="1939" xml:id="p.1939"/> for the purpose,
                    without reflecting on the ambiguity of the word, he uttered this ominous
                    expression: <quote>This day I will have Letum.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Letum, the name of the place, in the
                        Latin language, signifies death. </note> He made his troops march up the
                    mountain in two places at the same time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    division in which he was advanced briskly: the other was repulsed by the enemy;
                    and the consul riding up thither, to remedy the disorder, rallied his troops;
                    but whilst he moves about too carelessly in the front, he was pierced through
                    with a javelin, and fell. The commanders of the enemy did not know that he was
                    killed; and the few of his own party who saw the disaster, carefully covered the
                    body from view, knowing that the victory rested on this. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The rest of the troops, horse and foot, though deprived of
                    their leader, dislodged the enemy, and took possession of the mountains. Five
                    thousand of the Ligurians were slain, and of the Roman army only fifty-two were
                    lost. Besides this evident completion of the unhappy omen, the keeper of the
                    chickens was heard to say, that there had been a defect in the auspices, and
                    that the consul was not ignorant of it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Caius
                    Valerius, <hi rend="italics"> when he was informed of the death of Quintus
                        Petillius, made the army, thus bereft of its commander, join his own; then,
                        attacking the enemy again, in their blood he offered a noble sacrifice to
                        the shade of his departed col- league. He had the honour of a triumph over
                        the Ligurians. The legion, at whose head the consul was killed, was severely
                        punished by the senate. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They determined
                        that the campaign of this year should not be counted to the entire legion,
                        and that their pay should be stopped, for not exposing themselves to the
                        enemy's weapons in defence of their commander. About this time ambassadors
                        came to Rome from the Dar- danians, who were greatly distressed by the
                        numerous army of Bastarnians, under Clondicus, mentioned above. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> These ambassadors, after describing the vast
                        multitude of the Bastarnians, their tall and huge bodies, and their daring
                        intrepidity in facing danger, added, that there was an al- liance between
                        them and Perseus, and that the Dardanians were really more afraid of him
                        than even of the Bastarnians: and therefore begged of the senate that
                        assistance should be sent them. The senate thereupon agreed, that
                        ambassadors should be sent to examine into the affairs of Macedonia; and
                        immediately a commission was given to Aulus Postu- <pb n="1940"
                            xml:id="p.1940"/> mius to go thither. They gave to him as colleagues
                        some young men, that he might have the principal direction and management of
                        the embassy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The senate then took into
                        consideration the election of magistrates for the ensuing year, on which
                        subject there was a long debate; for </hi> people skilled in the rules of
                    religion and politics affirmed, that, as the regular consuls of the year had
                    died, one by the sword, the other by sickness, the substituted consuls could not
                    with propriety hold the elections. <hi rend="italics"> An interregnum,
                        therefore, took place, and the interrex elected consuls Publius Mucius
                        Scaevola, and Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, a second time. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Then Caius Popillius Laenas, Titus Annius Luscus, Caius
                        Memmius Gallus, Caius Cluvius Saxula, Servius Cor- nelius Sulla, and Appius
                        Claudius Centho, were chosen praetors. The provinces assigned to the consuls
                        were Gaul and Liquria. Of the praetors, Cornelius Sulla obtained Sardinia,
                        Claudius Centho gained Hither Spain. There is no record of those to whom the
                        other praetorian provinces fell. This year was notorious for an epidemic,
                        which how- ever attacked cattle only. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                        Ligurians, a nation ever vanquished, yet ever rebelling, ravaged the lands
                        of Luna and Pisae; and at the same time there were alarming ru- mours of
                        disturbances in Gaul. Lepidus having easily quelled the commotions among the
                        Gauls, then marched into Liguria. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Several
                        states of this country submitted themselves to his disposal; and he,
                        supposing that they were rendered savage by the rugged mountain tops which
                        they inhabited, as the dispositions of the inhabitants of a country
                        generally resemble its natural features, by the precedent of some former
                        consuls, brought them </hi> down to the plains. Of these the Garulians,
                    Lapicinians, and Hercatians had lived on the other side of the Apennine, and the
                    Briniatians on the farther side. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the hither side of the river Audena,
                    Quintus Mucius made war on those who had wasted the lands of Luna and Pisae: and
                    having reduced them all to subjection, he took away their arms from them. On
                    account of these services, performed under the conduct and auspices of the two
                    consuls, the senate voted a thanksgiving for three days, and sacrifices of forty
                    victims. The commotions which broke out in Gaul and Liguria, at the beginning of
                    this year, were thus speedily sup- <pb n="1941" xml:id="p.1941"/> pressed,
                    without any great difficulty; but the apprehensions of the public, respecting a
                    war with Macedon, still continued. For Perseus laboured to embroil the
                    Bastarnians with the Dardanians; and the ambassadors, sent to examine into the
                    state of affairs in Macedon, returned to Rome, and brought certain information
                    that hostilities had commenced in Dardania. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At
                    the same time came envoys from king Perseus, to plead in excuse that neither had
                    the Bastarnians been invited by him, nor had they done any thing at his
                    instigation. The senate neither acquitted the king of the imputation, nor urged
                    it against him; they only ordered him to be warned to be very careful to show,
                    that he considered the treaty between him and the Romans as inviolable.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Dardanians, perceiving that the
                    Bastarnians, so far from quitting their country, as they had hoped, became daily
                    more troublesome, as they were supported by the neighbouring Thracians and
                    Scordiscians, thinking it necessary to make some effort against them, though
                    without any reasonable prospect of success, assembled together in arms from all
                    quarters, at the town that was nearest to the camp of the Bastarnians. It was
                    now winter, and they chose that season of the year, as supposing that the
                    Thracians and Scordiscians would return to their own countries. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> As soon as they heard that these were gone, and the
                    Bastarnians left by themselves, they divided their forces into two parts, that
                    one might march openly along the straight road to attack the enemy; and that the
                    other, going round through a wood, which lay out of sight, might assault them on
                    the rear. But, before these could arrive at the enemy's post, the fight
                    commenced, and the Dardanians were beaten, and pursued to the town, which was
                    about twelve miles from the Bastarnian camp. The victors immediately invested
                    the city, not doubting that, on the day following, either the enemy would
                    surrender it from fear, or they might take it by storm. Meanwhile the other body
                    of Dardanians, which had gone round, not having heard of the defeat of their
                    countrymen, <hi rend="italics">easily</hi> possessed themselves of the camp of
                    the Bastarnians, which had been left without a guard. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics"> The Bastarnians, thus deprived of all their provisions and
                        warlike stores, which were in their camp, and having no means of re- placing
                        them in a hostile country, and at that unfavourable season, resolved to
                        return to their native home. Having <pb n="1942" xml:id="p.1942"/> therefore
                        retreated to the Danube, they found it, to their great joy, covered with
                        ice, so thick as to seem capable of sustaining any weight. But when the
                        entire body of men and cattle, hastening on, and crowding together, pressed
                        on it at the same time, the ice, splitting under the immense weight,
                        suddenly parted, and being overcome and broken up, left in the middle of the
                        water the entire army which it had supported so long. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Most of them were immediately swallow- ed in the eddies
                        of the river. The fragments of the broken ice passed over many of them in
                        their attempt to swim and drown- ed them. A few out of the entire nation
                        with difficulty escaped to either bank, with their persons severely crushed.
                        About this time, Antiochus, son to Antiochus the Great, who had been for a
                        long time a hostage at Rome, came into possession of the kingdom of Syria,
                        on the death of his brother Seleucus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For
                        Seleucus, whom the Greeks call Phi- lopator, after having received the
                        kingdom of Syria, which had been greatly debilitated by the misfortunes of
                        his father, during an idle reign of twelve years never distinguished by any
                        memorable enterprise at all, called home from Rome this his younger brother,
                        sending, in his stead, his own son Demen- lius, according to the terms of
                        the treaty, which allowed the changing of the hostages from time to time.
                        Antiochus had but just reached Athens on his way, when Seleucus was
                        murdered, in consequence of a conspiracy formed by Helio- dorus, one of the
                        nobles. Eumenes and Attalus expelled him aiming at the crown, and put
                        Antiochus in possession of it, and valued it highly that they had bound him
                        to them by this so important a favour. They now began to harbour some
                        jealousy of the Romans, on account of several trifling causes of disgust.
                        Antiochus, having gained the kingdom by their aid, was received by the
                        people with such transports of joy, that they gave him the surname of
                        Epiphanes, or Rising Star, because when aliens to the royal blood were about
                        to seize the throne, he appeared like a propitious star, to assert his
                        hereditary right. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was not deficient in
                        capacity or vigour of mind to make figure in war; but he was so perverse and
                        indiscreet in the whole tenor of his con- duct and behaviour, that they soon
                        changed the surname which they had given him, and instead of Epiphanes,
                        called him Epimanes or Madman. For often having gone forth <pb n="1943"
                            xml:id="p.1943"/> from the palace without the knowledge of his servants,
                        with one or two attendants, crowned with roses, and dressed in robes
                        embroidered with gold, he used to go through the city, sometimes striking
                        those that he met with stones that he carried under his arms; sometimes, on
                        the other hand, throwing money among the mob, and shouting out, <quote>Let
                            him take to whom fortune shall give.</quote> But at another time he used
                        to go through the workshops of the goldsmiths, and engravers and other
                        artisans, arguing vainly concerning the art of each: at another time he
                        engaged in conversation in public with any of the plebeian she met: again,
                        wandering around the common taverns, he indulged in potations with
                        foreigners and strangers of the lowest grade. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> If by chance he had learned that any young men were
                        celebrating an un- timely banquet, he himself at once came upon them
                        suddenly, with a glass and a concert, revelling and wantoning, so that most
                        of them, struck with terror at the strangeness of the matter, fled away, and
                        the remainder were silent in fear. It is ascertained also that, in the
                        public baths, he used to bathe with the mob. As however there he was in the
                        habit of using the most precious unguents, they report that a plebeian one
                        day said to him: <quote>You are happy, O king: you savour of perfumes of the
                            highest value.</quote>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To whom Antiochus, delighted at his
                        words, said, <quote>I will immediately make you so happy, that you will
                            confess that you are sated:</quote> and immediately ordered a large pot
                        of most valuable unguent to be poured on his head, so that, the floor being
                        drenched with it, both the others began to fall on the slippery surface, and
                        the king himself, laughing heartily, came to the ground. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> 20. Lastly, having assumed the Roman gown instead of
                        his royal robes, he used to go about the market-place, as he had seen done
                        by the candidates for office at Rome, saluting and embracing each of the
                        plebeians; soliciting at one time for the aedileship, at another for the
                        plebeian tri- buneship, until at last he obtained the office by the
                        suffrages of the people, and then, according to the Roman </hi>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/> custom, he took his seat in an ivory chair,
                    where he heard causes, and listened to debates on the most trivial matters. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> So far was his mind from adhering to any
                    routine, for it wandered through every sort of life, that it was not ascertained
                    either by himself or any one else what was his real character. He was accustomed
                    not to speak to his <pb n="1944" xml:id="p.1944"/> friends, nor scarcely afford
                    a smile to his acquaintance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By an
                    inconsistent kind of liberality, he made himself and others subjects of
                    ridicule; for to some in the most elevated stations, and who thought highly of
                    themselves, he would give childish presents of sweetmeats, cakes, or toys;
                    others expecting nothing he enriched. Wherefore to many he appeared not to know
                    what he was doing; some said that he acted from a silly, sportive temper;
                    others, that he was evidently mad. In two great and honourable instances,
                    however, he showed a spirit truly royal, in the presents which he made to
                    several cities, and the honour he paid to the gods. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> To the inhabitants of Megalopolis, in Arcadia, he made a
                    promise to build a wall round their city, and he gave them the greater part of
                    the money requisite for the purpose. At Tegea he began to erect a magnificent
                    theatre of marble. At Cyzicum, he presented a set of golden utensils for the
                    service of one table in the Prytaneum, the state-room of the city, where such as
                    are entitled to that honour dine together. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To
                    the Rhodians he gave presents of every kind that their convenience required, but
                    none very remarkable. Of the magnificence of his notions, in every thing
                    respecting the gods, the temple of Jupiter Olympius at Athens can be a
                    sufficient testimony: being the only one in the world, the plan of which was
                    suitable to the greatness of the deity. He likewise ornamented Delos with altars
                    of extraordinary beauty, and abundance of statues. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> A magnificent temple of Jupiter Capitolinus, which he
                    promised to build at Antioch, of which not only the ceilings, but all the walls,
                    were to be covered with plates of gold, and many other edifices which he
                    intended in various places, he did not finish, as his reign was very short. He
                    surpassed his predecessors, too, in the magnificence of the public games of
                    every description; of which all the games but one were after their own custom,
                    and celebrated by an immense number of Grecian actors. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He gave a show of gladiators in the Roman manner, which at
                    first, among a people unaccustomed to such sights, caused more terror than
                    pleasure; but by frequently repeating them, and sometimes permitting the
                    combatants to go no further than wounds, at other times to fight until one was
                    killed, he rendered such kind of shows not only familiar to people's eyes, but
                    even agreeable, and kindled in most of the young men a passion for <pb n="1945"
                        xml:id="p.1945"/> arms; so much so that, although, at the beginning, he was
                    obliged to entice gladiators from Rome, by high rewards, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Crevier supplement: <p>
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> he soon found a sufficient number in
                            his own dominions willing to perform for a moderate hire. But he
                            displayed the same worthlessness and levity in exhibiting the games, as
                            in the rest of his life, so that nothing could be seen more magnificent
                            than the preparation for the games, nothing more vile or contemptible
                            than the king himself. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And when this
                            appeared often on other occasions, it was then most conspicuous in those
                            games, which, in emulation of the magnificence of those which were given
                            by Paulus in Macedon, after the conquest of Perseus, he exhi- bited at
                            immense expense, and with corresponding dishonour. To return, however,
                            to the Roman affairs, from which the mention of this king has caused us
                            to digress too far. Tibe- rius Sempronius Gracchus, after holding the
                            government of Sardinia two years, resigned it to Servius Cornelius
                            Sulla, the praetor, and, coming home to Rome, triumphed over the
                            Sardinians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> We are told that he
                            brought such a multitude of captives from that island, that from the
                            long continuance of the sale, <quote>Sardinians for sale</quote> became
                            a vulgar proverb, to denote things of little price. <milestone n="11"
                                unit="section"/> Both the consuls (Scaevola and Lepidus) triumphed
                            over the Ligurians; Lepidus over the Gauls also. Then were held the
                            elections of magistrates for the ensuing year. Spurius Postumius Albinus
                            and Quintus Mucius Scaevola were chosen consuls. In the election of
                            prae- tors, fortune involved Lucius or Cneius Cornelius Scipio, son of
                            Publius Africanus, one of the candidates, in a very invidi- ous struggle
                            with Caius Cicereius, who had been his father's secretary. <milestone
                                n="12" unit="section"/> For, after five praetors had been declared,
                            namely, Caius Cassius Longinus, Publius Furius Philus, Lucius Clau- dius
                            Asellus, Marcus Atilius Serranus, and Cneius Servilius Caepio; although
                            Scipio struggled hard to be admitted even in the last place, yet he was
                            thought to have degenerated so far from the virtues of his father, that
                            Cicereius would have been preferred by the votes of all the centuries,
                            had not the latter, with singular modesty, corrected what might be
                            considered either the fault of fortune or error of the elections.
                                <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He could not reconcile it to
                            himself, that, in a struggle in the elections, he should gain the
                            victory over the son of his patron; but im- mediately throwing off the
                            white gown, he became, from a com- id="p.1946" n="1946"/&gt; petitor
                            sure of success, the grateful friend and supporter of the interest of
                            his rival. Thus, by the help of Cicereius, Scipio obtained an honour
                            which he did not seem likely to gain from the people, and which
                            reflected greater glory on Cicereius than on himself. </p>
                        <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                        <p>
                            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The provinces assigned to the consuls
                            were Gaul and Liguria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the praetors
                            casting lots, the city jurisdiction fell to Caius Cassius Longinus, </p>
                    </note> and the foreign, to Lucius Cornelius Scipio. The province of Sardinia
                    fell to Marcus Atilius, who was ordered to sail over to Corsica with a new
                    legion, raised by the consuls, and consisting of five thousand foot and three
                    hundred horse; and while he was engaged in carrying on the war there, Cornelius
                    was continued in command, that he might hold the government of Sardinia.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To Cneius Servilius Caepio, for the
                    service of Farther Spain, and to Publius Furius Philus for that of Hither Spain,
                    the following troops were assigned to each, three thousand Roman foot with one
                    hundred and fifty horse, and five thousand Latin foot with three hundred horse.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Sicily was decreed to Lucius Claudius,
                    without any reinforcement. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls were
                    ordered to levy two more legions, of the regular numbers of foot and horse, and
                    to demand from the allies ten thousand foot and six hundred horse: but they met
                    great difficulty in making the levies; for the pestilence, which the year before
                    had fallen on the cattle, in the present year attacked the human species.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Such as were seized by it, seldom survived
                    the seventh day; those who did survive, lingered under a tedious disorder, which
                    generally turned to a quartan ague. The slaves especially perished, of whom
                    heaps lay unburied on all the roads. The necessary requisites could not be
                    procured for the funerals of those of free condition. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The bodies were consumed by putrefaction, without being
                    touched by the dogs or vultures; and it was universally observed, that during
                    that and the preceding year, while the mortality of cattle and men was so great,
                    no vultures were any where seen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of the public
                    priests, there died by this contagion, Cneius Servilius Caepio, father of the
                    praetor, a pontiff; Tiberius Sempronius Longus, son of Tiberius, decemvir of
                    religious rites; Publius Aelius Paetus, and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus,
                    augurs; Caius Mamilius Vitulus, chief curio; and Marcus Sempronius Tuditanus, a
                        <pb n="1947" xml:id="p.1947"/> pontiff. In the vacant places of pontiff
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So in the original; the name of
                        the person who was chosen in the room of <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Caepio being lost. </note> were chosen * * * * and Caius Sulpicius Galba, in
                    the room of Tuditanus. The augurs substituted were, Titus Veturius Gracchus
                    Sempronianus, in place of Gracchus; and Quintus Aelius Paetus, in place
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> of Publius Aelius. Caius Sempronius
                    Longus was made decemvir of religious rites, and Caius Scribonius Curio, chief
                    curio. When the termination of the plague was not visible, the senate voted that
                    the decemvirs should consult the Sibylline books; and, by their directions, a
                    supplication of one day was performed; and the people assembled in the forum
                    made a vow, whilst Quintus Marcius Philippus dictated the words, that <quote> if
                        the sickness and pestilence should <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> be
                        removed out of the Roman territory, they would solemnize a festival and
                        thanksgiving of two days' continuance. </quote> In the district of Veil, a
                    boy was <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> born with two heads; at Sinuessa, one
                    with a single hand; and at Oximum, a girl with teeth; in the middle of the day,
                    the sky being perfectly clear, a rainbow was seen, stretching over the temple of
                    Saturn, in the Roman forum, and three <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> suns
                    shone at once; and the following night many lights were seen gliding through the
                    air, about Lanuvium. The people of Caere affirmed that there had appeared in
                    their town a snake with a mane, having its body marked with spots like gold; and
                    it was fully proved that an ox had spoken in Campania. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the nones of June, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">7th of June.</note> the ambassadors returned from
                    Africa, who having first had an interview with king Masinissa, proceeded to
                    Carthage; but they received much more certain information respecting what had
                    taken place in Carthage from the king than from the Carthaginians themselves.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They said they had sufficient proof that
                    ambassadors had come from king Perseus, and that an audience of the senate was
                    given to them by night, in the temple of Aesculapius; and the king asserted,
                    that the Carthaginians had sent ambassadors to Macedon, which they themselves
                    did not positively deny. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate, hereupon,
                    resolved to send an embassy to Macedonia. They made choice of Caius Laelius,
                    Marcus Valerius Messala, and Sextus Digitius, who accordingly proceeded thither.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> About this time, Perseus, because some of
                        <pb n="1948" xml:id="p.1948"/> the Dolopians were refractory, and in the
                    matters in dispute were for referring the decision from the king to the Romans,
                    marched an army into their country, and reduced the whole nation under his
                    jurisdiction and dominion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thence he passed
                    through the mountains of ta, and on account of some religious scruples
                    affecting his mind, went up to Delphi, to apply to the oracle. His sudden
                    appearance in the middle of Greece caused a great alarm, not only in the
                    neighbouring states, but also caused alarming intelligence to be brought into
                    Asia to king Eumenes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He staid only three days
                    at Delphi, and then returned to his own dominions, through Phthiotis, Achaia,
                    and Thessaly, without doing the least injury or damage to those countries.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He did not think it sufficient to
                    conciliate the esteem of the several states through which his road lay; but
                    despatched either ambassadors or letters to every one of the Grecian powers,
                    requesting that they would <quote> think no more of the animosities which had
                        subsisted between them and his father; that the disputes had not been so
                        violent that they might not, and ought not, to cease with regard to himself.
                        On his part, there was no kind of obstacle to the forming of a cordial
                        friendship. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Above all, he wished particularly to find some
                    way of ingratiating himself with the Achaean nation. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This nation, and the state of Athens, solitary
                    exceptions to the whole of Greece, had carried their resentment to such a
                    length, as to prohibit the Macedonians entering their territories. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> In consequence of this, Macedonia became a place of
                    refuge for slaves running away out of Achaia; for, as the Achaeans had forbidden
                    the inhabitants of Macedon to set foot in their territories, they could not
                    presume to pass the boundaries of that kingdom. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> When Perseus observed this, he seized all the fugitives, and wrote a letter *
                    * * * * * * <quote> but that they ought to consider of the proper means of
                        preventing such elopements for the future. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When this letter was read by the praetor
                    Xenarchus, who was seeking a path to private influence with the king, the
                    greater part who were present, but especially those who, contrary to their
                    expectations, were about to receive the slaves they had lost, commended the
                    moderation and kindness with which it was written; but Callicrates, one who
                    thought that the safety of the nation depended on the treaty with Rome being
                    preserved inviolate, delivered his sentiments to <pb n="1949" xml:id="p.1949"/>
                    this effect; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>  <quote> To some of you,
                        Achaeans, the matter under consideration appears trifling and unimportant.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I think that a very great and
                        important subject is not only under consideration, but to a certain extent
                        decided. For we, who prohibited the kings of Macedonia, and all their
                        subjects, from entering our territories, and made a perpetual decree, not to
                        receive from those sovereigns either ambassadors or messengers, by whom the
                        minds of any of us might be tampered with; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        we, I say, listen to the king speaking in a manner, though absent, and what
                        is more, approve of his discourse. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Although wild beasts generally reject and shun the food laid in their way
                        for their destruction; yet we, blinded by the specious offer of an
                        insignificant favour, swallow the bait, and would, for the sake of
                        recovering a parcel of wretched slaves, of no value worth mentioning, suffer
                        our independence to be undermined and subverted. For who does not see that a
                        way is being paved to an alliance with the king, by which the treaty with
                        Rome in which all our interests are involved would be violated? <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> That there must be a war between Perseus and the
                        Romans, is not, I believe, a matter of doubt to any one, and the struggle
                        which was expected during the life of Philip, and interrupted by his death,
                        will, now that he is dead, most certainly ensue. Philip, you all know, had
                        two sons, Demetrius and Perseus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Demetrius was much superior in birth, on the mother's side, in merit,
                        capacity, and in the esteem of the Macedonian nation. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But Philip, having set up the crown as the prize of
                        hatred towards the Romans, put Demetrius to death, for no other crime than
                        having contracted a friendship with that people; and made Perseus king,
                        because he knew him to be an enemy to the Roman people almost before he
                        determined on making him king. Accordingly, what else has the present king
                        done since his father's death, than prepare for the war? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> In the first place, to the terror of all the
                        surrounding nations, he brought the Bastarnians into Dardania; where if they
                        had made a lasting settlement, Greece would have found them more troublesome
                        neighbours than Asia found the Gauls. Disappointed in that hope, he did not
                        drop his design of a war; nay, if we choose to speak the truth, he has
                        already commenced hostilities. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He subdued
                        Dolopia by force of arms; and would not listen when they wished to appeal
                        concerning their disputes to the arbitration of the Romans. <pb n="1950"
                            xml:id="p.1950"/> Then, crossing ta, that he might show himself in the
                        very centre of Greece, he went up to Delphi. To what, think you, did his
                        taking a journey so uncommon tend? He next traversed Thessaly; and as to his
                        refraining on his route from doing injury to the people whom he hated, I
                        dread his machinations the more on that very account. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> He then sent a letter to us, with the hollow show of an
                        act of kindness, and bade us to consider measures by which we may not
                        require this gift for the future; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> that
                        is, to repeal the decree by which the Macedonians are excluded from
                        Peloponnesus; to receive again ambassadors from him their king; to renew
                        intimacies contracted with his principal subjects; and, in a short time, we
                        should see Macedonian armies, with himself at their head, crossing over the
                        narrow strait from Delphi into Peloponnesus, and thus we should be blended
                        with the Macedonians, while they are arming themselves against the Romans.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> My opinion is, that we ought not to
                        resolve on any new proceeding, but to keep every thing in its present state,
                        until the question shall be reduced to a certainty, whether these our fears
                        be well or ill grounded. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> If the peace
                        between the Romans and Macedonians shall continue inviolate, then may we
                        also have a friendship and intercourse with Perseus; <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> but to think of such a measure now, appears to me both
                        premature and dangerous. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After him, Arco, brother to the praetor
                    Xenarchus, said:  <quote> Callicrates hath made the delivery of our sentiments
                        difficult both to me and to every one who differs in opinion from him;
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for after his pleading in favour of
                        the Roman alliance, alleging that it was undermined and attacked, (although
                        no one either undermines or attacks it,) he has caused that whoever dissents
                        from him must seem to argue against the cause of the Romans. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> In the first place, as if he had not been here
                        with us, but had just left the senate-house of the Roman people, or had been
                        admitted into the privy councils of kings, he knows and tells us every
                        transaction that passes in secret. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nay
                        more, he divines what would have happened if Philip had lived, why Perseus
                        became heir of the kingdom: in such a manner, what are the intentions of the
                        Macedonians, and what the thoughts of the Romans. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But we, who neither know for what cause, nor in what
                        manner, Demetrius perished, nor what Philip would have done, if he had
                        lived, ought to accommodate our resolutions to the transactions that have
                        passed <pb n="1951" xml:id="p.1951"/> in open view. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> We know that Perseus, on his coming to the throne, sent
                        ambassadors to Rome, and received the title of king from the Roman people,
                        and we hear that ambassadors came from Rome to the king, and were graciously
                        received by him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I consider that all these
                        circumstances are signs of peace, not of war; and that the Romans cannot be
                        offended, if, as we imitated their conduct in war, so we follow now their
                        example in peace. For my part, I cannot see why we alone, of all mankind,
                        wage implacable war against the kingdom of the Macedonians. Are we exposed
                        to insult by a close neighbourhood to Macedon? or are we like the Dolopians,
                        whom Perseus subdued lately, the weakest of all states? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> No; on the contrary, by the bounty of the gods, we are
                        sufficiently secured, as well by our own strength, as by the remoteness of
                        our situation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But we have as much reason
                        to apprehend ill treatment, as the Thessalians and Aetolians; have we no
                        more credit or influence with the Romans, though we were always their
                        friends and allies, than the Aetolians, who but lately were their enemies?
                        Whatever reciprocal rights the Aetolians, the Thessalians, the Epirots, in
                        short, every state in Greece, allow to subsist between them and the
                        Macedonians, let us allow the same. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Why
                        have we alone what may be termed a cursed neglect of the ties of humanity?
                        Philip may have done some act on account of which we should pass this decree
                        against him when in arms and waging war against us: <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> What has Perseus deserved, a king just seated on the
                        throne, guiltless of all injury against us, and effacing by his own kindness
                        his father's feuds? Why should we be his only enemies? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Although I might make this assertion, that so great
                        have been our obligations to the former kings of Macedon, that the ill
                        usage, suffered from a single prince of their line, if any has really been
                        suffered from Philip, * * * especially after his death. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> When a Roman fleet was lying at Cenchreae, and the
                        consul, with his army, was at Elatia, we were three days in council,
                        deliberating whether we should follow the Romans or Philip. Now, granting
                        that the fear of immediate danger from the Romans had no influence on our
                        judgments, yet there was, certainly, something that made our deliberation
                        last so long; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and that was, the connexion
                        which had long subsisted between us and the Macedonians; the distinguished
                        favours in ancient times received from their kings. Let the same <pb
                            n="1952" xml:id="p.1952"/> considerations prevail at present, not to
                        make us his singular friends, but to hinder us from becoming his singular
                        enemies. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Let us not, Callicrates, pretend
                        what is not even thought of. No one advises us to form a new alliance, or
                        sign a new treaty, by which we might inconsiderately compromise ourselves,
                        but merely that we may have the intercourse of affording and demanding
                        justice, and that we may not by excluding his subjects from our territories,
                        exclude ourselves from his dominions, and that our slaves may not have any
                        refuge to fly to. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> How does this operate
                        against the Roman treaty? Why do we give an air of importance and suspicion
                        to a matter which is trifling and open to the world? <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Why do we raise groundless alarms? Why, for the sake of
                        ingratiating ourselves still more particularly with the Romans, render
                        others odious and suspected? <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> If war shall
                        take place, even Perseus himself does not doubt our taking part with the
                        Romans. While peace continues, let animosities if they are not terminated,
                        be at least suspended. </quote>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> When those who approved of the king's letter
                    expressed their approbation of this speech, the decree was postponed, owing to
                    the indignation of the chief men that Perseus should obtain by a letter of a few
                    lines a matter which he did not even deign worthy of an embassy. Ambassadors
                    were afterwards sent by the king, when a council was held at Megalopolis;
                        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> but exertions were made by those, who
                    dreaded a rupture with Rome, that they should not be admitted to an audience. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this period the fury of the Aetolians,
                    being turned against themselves, seemed likely to cause the total extinction of
                    that nation by the massacres of the contending parties. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Then both parties, being wearied, sent ambassadors to Rome,
                    and also opened a negotiation between themselves for the restoration of concord:
                    but this was broken off by an act of barbarity, which revived their old
                    quarrels. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When a return to their country had
                    been promised to the exiles from Hypata, who were of the faction of Proxenus,
                    and the public faith had been pledged to them by Eupolemus, the chief man of the
                    state; eighty persons of distinction, whom even Eupolemus, among the rest of the
                    multitude, had gone forth to meet on their return, though they were received
                    with kind salutation, and right hands were pledged to them, were butchered on
                    entering the gate, though they implored in vain <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> the honour that <pb n="1953" xml:id="p.1953"/> had been
                    pledged, and the gods the witnesses of the transaction. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On this the war blazed out anew, with greater fury than
                    ever. Caius Valerius Laevinus, Appius Claudius Pulcher, Caius Memmius, Marcus
                    Popilius, and Lucius Canuleius, being sent as ambassadors by the senate, arrived
                    in that country. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the deputies from both
                    parties pleaded their respective causes with great energy, Proxenus appeared to
                    have greatly the advantage as well in the justice of his cause as in eloquence;
                    a few days after, he was poisoned by his wife Orthobula, who being convicted of
                    the crime, went into banishment. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same
                    madness was wasting the Cretans also; but, on the arrival of Quintus Minucius,
                    lieutenant-general, who was sent with ten ships to quiet their contentions, the
                    inhabitants had some prospect of peace; however, they only concluded a
                    suspension of arms for six months, after which the war was again renewed with
                    much greater violence. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About this time, the
                    Lycians, too, were harassed in war by the Rhodians. But the wars of foreign
                    nations among themselves, or the several methods in which they were conducted,
                    it is not my business to detail; since I have a task of more than sufficient
                    weight in writing the deeds performed by the Roman people. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Spain, the Celtiberians, (who, since their
                    reduction by Tiberius Gracchus, and their consequent surrender to him, had
                    remained quiet; when Marcus Titinius, the praetor, held the government of that
                    province,) on the arrival of Appius Claudius, resumed their arms, and commenced
                    hostilities by a sudden attack on the Roman camp. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It was nearly the first dawn when the sentinels on the
                    rampart, and the men on guard before the gates, descrying the enemy approaching
                    at a distance, shouted <quote>to arms.</quote> Appius Claudius instantly
                    displayed the signal of battle; and, after exhorting the troops, in few words,
                    ordered them to rush out by three gates at once. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> But they were opposed by the Celtiberians in the very passage; and in
                    consequence, the fight was for some time equal on both sides, as, on account of
                    the narrowness, the Romans could not all come into action in the entrance;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> then pressing forward on one another,
                    whenever it was possible, they made their way beyond the trenches, so that they
                    were able to extend their line, and form a front equal to the wings of the
                    enemy, by which they were surrounded; and now they <pb n="1954" xml:id="p.1954"
                    /> made their onset with such sudden impetuosity, that the Celtiberians could
                    not support the assault. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Before the second
                    hour, they were driven from the field; about fifteen thousand were either killed
                    or made prisoners, and thirty-two standards were taken. Their camp, also, was
                    stormed the same day, and a conclusion put to the war; for those who survived
                    the battle fled by different ways, to their several towns, and thenceforth
                    submitted quietly to the Roman government. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Flaccus and Aulus Postumius,
                    being created censors, reviewed the senate this year. Marcus Aemilius Lepidus,
                    chief pontiff, was chosen chief of the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Nine senators were expelled. The remarkable censures pronounced were on Marcus
                    Cornelius Maluginensis, who had been praetor in Spain two years before; on
                    Lucius Cornelius Scipio, who was then praetor and exercised the jurisdiction
                    between natives and foreigners; and on Cneius Fulvius, brother to the censor,
                    and, as Valerius Antias says, partner in property. The consuls, after offering
                    vows in the Capitol, set out for their provinces. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Marcus Aemilius was commissioned by the senate to suppress
                    an insurrection of the Patavians in Venetia; for their own ambassadors had given
                    information that by the violent contests of opposing factions they had broken
                    out into civil war. The ambassadors who had gone into Aetolia, to suppress
                    commotions of a similar kind, reported on their return, that the outrageous
                    temper of that nation could not be restrained. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The consul's arrival among the Patavians saved them from ruin; and having no
                    other business in the province, he returned to Rome. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The present censors were the first who contracted for
                    paving the streets of Rome with flint stones, for laying with gravel the
                    foundation of roads outside the city, and for forming raised foot-ways on the
                    sides; for building bridges in several places; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    and affording seats in the theatre to the praetors and aediles; they fixed up
                    goals in the circus, with balls on the goals for marking the number of courses
                    of the chariots; and erected iron grates, through which wild beasts might be let
                    in. They caused the Capitoline hill to be paved with flint, and erected a piazza
                    from the temple of Saturn, in the Capitol, to the council-chamber, and over that
                    a public hall. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the outside of the gate
                    Trigemina, they also paved a market-place with stones, and enclosed it with a
                    paling; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> they repaired the Aemilian portico,
                    and formed an ascent, <pb n="1955" xml:id="p.1955"/> by stairs, from the Tiber
                    to the market-place. They paved, with flint, the portico, from the same gate to
                    the Aventine, and built a court-house: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    contracted for walls to be built at Galatia and Oximum, and, after selling lots
                    of ground there, which belonged to the public, employed the money arising from
                    the sale in building shops round the forums of both places. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Fulvius Flaccus (for Postumius <hi rend="italics"
                        >declared,</hi> that, without a decree of the senate, or order of the
                    people, he would not expend any money belonging to them) agreed for building a
                    temple of Jupiter at Pisaurum; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and another at
                    Fundi; for bringing water to Pollentia; for paving the street of Pisaurum, and
                    for many various works at Sinuessa; among which were, the structure of a sewer
                    to fall into the river, the enclosure of the forum with porticoes and shops, and
                    erection of three statues of Janus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These
                    works were all contracted for by one of the censors, and gained him a high
                    degree of favour with those colonists. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Their
                    censorship was also very active and strict in the superintendence of the morals
                    of the people. Many knights were deprived of their horses. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of the year, there was a
                    thanksgiving, for one day, on account of the advantages obtained in Spain under
                    the conduct and auspices of Appius Claudius, the proconsul; and they sacrificed
                    twenty victims, of the larger kinds. There was also a supplication, for another
                    day, at the temples of Ceres, Liber, and Liberia, because a violent earthquake
                    with the destruction of many houses was announced from the Sabines. When Appius
                    Claudius came home from Spain, the senate voted that he should enter the city in
                    ovation. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The election of consuls now came on:
                    when they were held, after a violent struggle in consequence of the great number
                    of candidates, Lucius Postumius Albinus and Marcus Popilius Laenas were elected
                    consuls. Then Numerius Fabius Buteo, Marcus Matienus, Caius Cicereius, Marcus
                    Furius Crassipes, a second time, Marcus Atilius Serranus, a second time, and
                    Caius Cluvius Saxula, a second time, were chosen praetors. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> After the elections were finished, Appius Claudius Centho,
                    entering the city in ovation over the Celtiberians, conveyed to the treasury ten
                    thousand pounds' weight of silver, and five thousand of gold. Cneius Cornelius
                    was inaugurated flamen of Jupiter. In the same year a tablet was hung up in the
                    temple of mother Matuta, with this inscription: UNDER <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1956" xml:id="p.1956"/> THE COMMAND AND AUSPICES OF TIBERIUS SEMPRONIUS
                    GRAC- CHUS, CONSUL, A LEGION AND ARMY OF THE ROMAN PEOPLE SUBDUED SARDINIA; IN
                    WHICH PROVINCE ABOVE EIGHTY THOUSAND OF THE ENEMY WERE KILLED OR TAKEN. HAVING
                    EXECUTED THE BUSINESS OF THE PUBLIC WITH THE HAPPIEST SUCCESS; HAVING RECOVERED
                    THE REVENUES, AND RESTORED THEM <hi rend="italics">to the commonwealth,</hi> HE
                    BROUGHT HOME THE ARMY SAFE, UNINJURED, AND ENRICHED WITH SPOIL, AND, A SECOND
                    TIME, ENTERED THE CITY OF ROME IN TRIUMPH. IN COMME- MORATION OF WHICH EVENT HE
                    PRESENTED THIS TABLET AS AN OFFERING TO JUPITER. A map of the island of Sardinia
                    was engraved on the tablet, and pictures of the battles fought there were
                    delineated on it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Several small exhibitions of
                    gladiators were given to the public this year; the only one particularly
                    remarkable, was that of Titus Flamininus, which he gave on occasion of his
                    father's death, and it was accompanied with a donation of meat, a feast, and
                    stage-plays, and lasted four days. Yet, in the whole of this great exhibition,
                    only seventy-four men fought in three days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics"> The close of this year was rendered memorable by the
                        proposal of a new and import- ant rule, which occupied the state, since it
                        was debated with great emotion. Hitherto, as the law stood, women were as
                        equal- ly capable of receiving inheritances as men. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> From which it hap- pened that the wealth of the most
                        illustrious houses was frequent- ly transferred into other families, to the
                        great detriment, as it was generally supposed, of the state; to which it was
                        no small advantage that there should be a sufficiency of wealth to the
                        descendants of distinguished ancestors, by which they might support and do
                        honour to their nobility of birth, which otherwise would form a burden
                        rather than honour to them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Besides, since
                        with the now growing power of the empire, the riches of private persons also
                        were increasing fear was felt, lest the minds of women, being rather
                        inclined by nature to luxury, and the pursuit of a more elegant routine of
                        life, and deriving from un- bounded wealth incentives to desire, should fall
                        into immoderate expenses and luxury, and should subsequently chance to de-
                        part from the ancient sanctity of manners, so that there would be a change
                        of morals no less than of the manner of living. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> To obviate these evils, Quintus Voconius Saxa, plebeian
                        tri- bune, proposed to the people, that <quote> no person who should be
                            rated after the censorship of Aulus Postumius and Quintius <pb n="1957"
                                xml:id="p.1957"/> Fulvius should make any woman, whether married or
                            unmar- ried, his heir; also, that no woman, whether married or un-
                            married, should be capable of receiving, by inheritance, goods exceeding
                            the value of one hundred thousand sesterces. </quote>
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 885 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 8
                                <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                        </note> Voconius, also, thought it proper to provide that estates should not
                        be exhausted by the number of legacies, which some- times happened.
                        Accordingly he added a clause to his law, that no person should bequeath to
                        any person or persons pro- perty exceeding in value what was to go to the
                        immediate heirs." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This latter clause
                        readily met the general approbation; it appeared reasonable, and calculated
                        to press severely on no- body. Concerning the former clause, by which women
                        were utterly disqualified from receiving inheritances, there were many
                        doubts. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Marcus Cato put an end to all
                        hesitation, having been already, on a former occasion, a most determined
                        adversary and reprover of women, in the defence of the Oppian law, who,
                        although sixty-five years of age, with loud voice and good lungs advocated
                        this law of still greater importance, against them, inveighing, with his
                        usual asperity, against the tyranny of women, and their unsufferable
                        insolence when opulent: on the present occasion, too, he declaimed against
                        the pride and arrogance of the rich matrons, <quote> because they
                            oftentimes, after bringing a great dowry to their husband, kept back and
                            re- tained for themselves a great sum of money, and lent that money on
                            such terms afterwards to their husbands, on their asking it, that as
                            often as they were angry they immediately pressed im- portunately on
                            their husbands, as if they were strange debtors, by a reserved slave who
                            followed them and daily importuned payment. </quote> Moved by
                        indignation at this, they voted for pass- ing the law as Voconius proposed
                        it. </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
