<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 41</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="book">
                <head>Perseus and the States of Greece</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> . . . It was said that he called to arms
                        the fighting men whom his father had kept in peace, and that he was very
                        popular with them, as they were eager for plunder. The consul held a council
                        of war to discuss the Histrian campaign. Some thought it ought to be
                        undertaken at once before the enemy had time to get his forces together;
                        others considered that the senate ought first to be consulted. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The opinion in favour of prompt action prevailed.
                        From Aquileia, the consul advanced to the Timavus Lake close to the sea.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> C. Furius, one of the two naval
                        commanders, sailed there with ten ships. He and his colleague were to act
                        against the Illyrian fleet and protect the coasts of the Upper Sea with
                        twenty ships. Their joint command pivoted on Ancona; L. Cornelius had the
                        defence of the coast to the right as far as Tarentum, and C. Furius to the
                        left as far as Aquileia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The ten ships
                        under Furius had been sent to the nearest harbour on Histrian territory,
                        together with cargo ships and a large amount of supplies. The consul
                        followed them with the legions and fixed his camp about five miles from the
                        sea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A busy market soon sprang up in the
                        harbour, and all supplies were carried up from the sea to the camp. To
                        render this more secure, pickets were posted on every side of the camp.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the side facing Histria the
                        emergency cohort from Placentia was posted permanently; M. Aebutius, one of
                        the military tribunes, was ordered to take two maniples from the second
                        legion to the river bank between the camp and the sea to protect the
                        watering-parties; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> two other military
                        tribunes, L. and C. Aelius, took the third legion along the road leading to
                        Aquileia to protect the foraging and wood-cutting troops. In that direction
                        lay the camp of the Gauls about a mile distant. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> and in their chief's absence Catemelus was in command.
                        They did not number more than 3000 armed men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as the Roman army began to move
                        towards the Timavus, the Histri took up a position in concealment behind a
                        hill and followed it while on the march, carefully watching for every
                        opportunity; nothing that happened on sea or land escaped their notice.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they saw that only weak pickets
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> were posted in front of the camp and
                        that between the camp and the sea there was a crowd of unarmed traders busy
                        with their traffic and without any protection either on the land side or
                        towards the sea, they made a simultaneous attack on the pickets, the
                        Placentian cohort and the maniples of the second legion. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Their movements were at first concealed by an early
                        morning fog. As this began to disperse under the warm rays of the sun, the
                        sunshine struggling fitfully through made everything, as it generally does,
                        look larger to the beholder. In this way the Romans were deceived, as the
                        hostile army appeared larger than it really was. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The men from both the pickets fled in a great tumult to
                        the camp. The terror they spread here was greater than the alarm in which
                        they had fled, for they could not explain why they had fled, nor could they
                        give any answer to those who questioned them. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Shouts were heard from the gates, as there were no
                        outposts there to make any resistance, and the crowding together of the
                        soldiers, who were falling over each other in the fog, made it impossible to
                        know whether the enemy were inside the camp or not. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> One voice was heard amongst the cries, calling "To the
                        sea!" and this chance cry started by one individual resounded everywhere
                        throughout the camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They began to run
                        down to the sea, as though acting under orders; at first in small bodies,
                        some with arms, most of them without; then in larger numbers, till at last
                        nearly every man had gone, including the consul himself. He was quite
                        powerless to rally the fugitives; his commands, his authority, his
                        expostulations were all fruitless. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        only officer who remained was M. Licinius Strabo, a military tribune
                        attached to the second legion, who had left him with three maniples in their
                        flight. The Histri made their attack on the empty camp, and after finding no
                        armed resistance, came upon him as he was forming and encouraging his men in
                        the headquarters tent. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The fight was a
                        more stubborn one than might have been expected from the fewness of the
                        defenders, and did not come to an end until the tribune and all round him
                        had fallen. After overturning the headquarters tent and plundering
                        everything in it, the enemy went on to the quaestor's tent, the forum, and
                        the via quintana. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Here they found an
                        abundant supply of everything laid out in readiness, and in the quaestor's
                        tent couches arranged for a meal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        chieftain lay down and began to feast himself; <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> soon all the others, oblivious of any armed enemy, did
                        the same, and being unused to such good fare, loaded themselves greedily
                        with wine and food. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Things wore a very different aspect among
                        the Romans. There was confusion both on land and sea. The marines struck
                        their tents and hurriedly carried back on board the stores which had been
                        landed on the beach; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the soldiers rushed
                        in panic to the boats at the water's edge; some of the sailors, afraid of
                        their boats being overcrowded, tried to stop the crowd; others pushed their
                        boats off into deep water. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This resulted
                        in a struggle, and soon a regular fight began between the soldiers and the
                        sailors-with bloodshed on both sides-until at the consul's orders the fleet
                        was withdrawn to some distance from the land. Then he began to separate
                        those who had arms from those who were without any. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> There were hardly 1200 out of the whole number who were
                        still armed; very few of the cavalry were found to have brought away their
                        horses with them; the rest were a disorderly mob like so many sutlers and
                        camp-followers, certain to fall a prey to the enemy, if the enemy had had
                        any idea of fighting. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At last, word was
                        sent to recall the third legion and the Gaulish contingent, and the troops
                        posted round the camp began to come in determined to recover the camp and
                        remove the stain of disgrace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The military
                        tribunes of the third legion ordered the loads of wood and fodder to be
                        thrown off the baggage animals, and commanded the centurions to place the
                        older men in couples on the mules which had been relieved of their loads,
                        and the cavalry were each to take one of the younger men with them on their
                        horses. They told their men that it would be a most glorious thing for their
                        legion if, by their own valour, they recovered the camp which had been lost
                        through the faintheartedness of the second legion. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> And it easily could be recovered if the barbarians were
                        suddenly surprised in the midst of their plundering; the camp could be
                        recaptured just as it had been captured. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        His words of encouragement were listened to eagerly by the soldiers, the
                        standards rapidly went forward, and the legionaries followed without a
                        moment's delay. The first, however, to approach the rampart were the consul
                        and the troops he was bringing from the sea. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> The first tribune of the second legion, with the view of encouraging his
                        men, pointed out to them that if the barbarians had intended to hold the
                        camp by the same arms by which they had taken it, they would, first of all,
                        have followed up their enemy in his flight from his camp to the sea, and
                        then they would have stationed pickets in front of their rampart. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> They were in all probability lying sunk in wine
                        and slumber. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He thereupon ordered his standard-bearer,
                        A. Baeculonius, a man noted for his courage, to go forward with his
                        standard. Baeculonius replied that if they would follow him and his standard
                        they would help him to do so all the more quickly. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He then flung the standard with all his might over the
                        rampart and was the first to pass through the camp gate. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> On another side of the camp the two Aelii, Titus and
                        Caius, came up with the cavalry of the third legion. They were almost
                        immediately followed by the men mounted on the baggage animals, and then the
                        consul with the whole of the army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A few
                        of the Histri who had taken only a moderate amount of wine were careful to
                        escape; for the rest, sleep was prolonged into death, and the Romans
                        recovered all their property intact. save the wine and food which had been
                        consumed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even the sick who had been left
                        in the camp, finding their comrades inside the rampart, seized their arms
                        and inflicted great slaughter. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A
                        cavalryman, C. Popilius Sabellus, distinguished himself especially in this
                        way. He had been left behind with a wounded foot and he slew by far the
                        greatest number of the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As many as
                        8000 of the Histri were killed, not one prisoner was taken, rage and shame
                        made the Romans indifferent to booty. The King of the Histri, however, drunk
                        as he was, was carried off hurriedly from the table and lifted by his men on
                        to a horse and so escaped. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Two hundred and
                        thirty-seven of the victors perished; more fell in the morning rout than in
                        the recapture of the camp. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Cn. and L. Gavilius Novellus were coming
                        with supplies from Aquileia, and unaware of what had happened, very nearly
                        entered the camp while it was in the possession of the Histrians. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> They left their goods and fled back to Aquileia,
                        spreading alarm and tumult not only in that city, but in Rome itself.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Reports reached the City, true so far
                        as they told of the capture of the camp by the enemy and the flight of the
                        defenders, but rumours also filled the City to the effect that all was lost
                        and the entire army annihilated. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As usual
                        in times of tumult and alarm, an extraordinary levy was ordered in the City
                        and throughout the length and breadth of Italy. Two legions of Roman
                        citizens were called up, and from the Latin allies 10,000 infantry with a
                        complement of 500 cavalry were raised. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        consul, M. Junius, was ordered to go to Gaul and requisition from the
                        communities in that province as many soldiers as they could each supply.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was decreed that the praetor
                        Tiberius Claudius should give notice to the men of the fourth legion, the
                        5000 allied troops and the 250 cavalry to muster at Pisae, and that he
                        should be responsible for the defence of that province in the consul's
                        absence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> M. Titinius received instructions
                        to order the first legion and the same number of allied infantry to assemble
                        at Ariminum. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nero, wearing his
                        paludamentum, left for Pisae; Titinius, after sending C. Cassius, one of the
                        military tribunes, to take command of the legion at Ariminum, arrived at
                        Aquileia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There he was informed that the
                        army was safe, and at once sent a despatch to Rome to allay the tumult and
                        alarm. He then sent back the contingents which he had requisitioned in Gaul
                        and went to rejoin his colleague. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There
                        was great rejoicing in Rome at the unlooked-for news, all enrolment of
                        troops was suspended and those who had already taken the military oath were
                        released from its obligations. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The army
                        at Ariminum which had been suffering from the pestilence was disbanded and
                        sent home. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Histrians were encamped in
                        great strength not far from the consul's camp, and when they heard that the
                        other consul had arrived with a fresh army they everywhere dispersed to
                        their cities. The consuls took the legions back to Aquileia for their winter
                        quarters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Histrian disturbance had at last
                        quieted down, the senate passed a resolution that the consuls should arrange
                        which of them was to come to Rome for the election. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Two tribunes of the plebs, Licinius Nerva and C.
                        Papirius Turdus, attacked Manlius in his absence and brought forward a
                        motion that he should not retain his command after the Ides of March-the
                        consuls had already had their administrations extended for a year-in order
                        that he might be brought to trial immediately on quitting office. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Their colleague, Q. Aelius, opposed the motion
                        and after long and violent disputes prevented it from being carried.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On their return from Spain, Tiberius
                        Sempronius Gracchus and L. Postumius Albinus were received by the senate in
                        the temple of Bellona. They gave a report of their administration and asked
                        that honours should be paid to the immortal gods. News came from T.
                        Aebutius, commanding in Sardinia, of a serious disturbance in that island.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Ilienses, in conjunction with the
                        Balari, had invaded the province which was at peace, and owing to the
                        weakened condition of the army, a large number of men having been carried
                        off by the pestilence, no resistance could be offered. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Envoys from Sardinia came with the same tale; they
                        implored the senate to send assistance to the cities at all events; it was
                        too late to save the fields. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was left to the consuls to decide what
                        reply should be given to these envoys and to deal with the whole state of
                        things in Sardinia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> An equally tragic
                        story was told by the Lycians, who had come to complain of the cruel tyranny
                        of the Rhodians, under whose government they had been placed by L. Cornelius
                        Scipio. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They had been formerly under
                        Antiochus and they assured the senate that their subjection under the king
                        was glorious liberty compared with their present condition. It was not
                        political oppression only under which they were suffering, but absolute
                        slavery; they, their wives and children were the victims of violence;
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> their oppressors vented their rage on
                        their persons and their backs, their good name was besmirched and
                        dishonoured, their condition rendered detestable in order that their tyrants
                        might openly assert a legal right over them and reduce them to the status of
                        slaves bought with money. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Moved by this
                        recital, the senate gave the Lycians a letter to hand to the Rhodians,
                        intimating that it was not the pleasure of the senate that either the
                        Lycians or any other men born free should be handed over as slaves to the
                        Rhodians or any one else. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Lycians
                        possessed the same rights under the suzerainty and protection of Rhodes that
                        friendly states possessed under the suzerainty of Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The two commanders in Spain now celebrated
                        their triumph; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> first, Sempronius Gracchus
                        for his victory over the Celtiberi and their allies, and on the following
                        day L. Postumius over the Lusitanians and the adjacent tribes. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> In Gracchus' procession were borne 40,000 pounds
                        of silver, in that of Postumius 20,000. Each of the legionaries received 25
                        denarii, the centurions twice and the cavalry three times as much, and the
                        allied troops received the same. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        consul, M. Junius, came about this time to Rome for the elections.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Two tribunes of the plebs, Papirius
                        and Licinius, put a multitude of questions to him in the senate about what
                        had happened in Histria, and then they brought him before the Assembly.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul explained that he had not
                        been in that province more than eleven days and he, like them, only knew by
                        report what had happened in his absence. Then they asked "why in that case
                        A. Manlius had not come to Rome, rather than Junius, that he might explain
                        to the people of Rome why he had left the province of Gaul, which had been
                        allotted to him, for Histria. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When did the
                        senate make a decree or the Assembly an order for that war? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> 'Well,' you may say, 'granting that the war was
                        undertaken on his personal responsibility, still it was conducted with
                        courage and prudence.' On the contrary it is impossible to say whether its
                        inception is the more flagitious or its conduct the more reckless.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Two pickets were surprised by the
                        Histrians, a Roman camp was taken and what troops were in the camp were cut
                        to pieces; all the rest threw away their arms and fled in disorder to the
                        sea and the ships, the consul himself above all. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He will have to account for all this as an ordinary
                        citizen, since he will not do so as consul." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then came the elections. The new consuls
                        were C. Claudius Pulcher and Ti. Sempronius Gracchus, and the new praetors,
                        P. Aelius Tubero (for the second time), C. Quinctius Flamininus, C.
                        Numisius, L. Mummius, Cnaeus Cornelius Scipio and C. Valerius Laevinus.
                        Tubero received the civic jurisdiction, Quinctius the alien. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Sicily fell to Numisius, and Sardinia to Mummius;
                        the latter, however, owing to the magnitude of the war, was made a consular
                        province. Gaul was divided into two provinces and allotted to Scipio and
                        Laevinus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the Ides of March, when
                        Sempronius and Claudius entered upon office, the provinces of Sardinia and
                        Histria and the instigators of war in those provinces were only informally
                        discussed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the following day, the
                        Sardinian deputation, who had been referred to the new consuls, and L.
                        Minucius Thermus, who had been second <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> in
                        command with the consul Manlius in Histria, appeared before the senate, and
                        after the information they gave, the senate realised what a state of war
                        existed in those provinces. Delegates from the Latin allies, after
                        numberless appeals to the censors and the late consuls, were at length
                        admitted to an audience of the senate, and their statement made a great
                        impression. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The gist of their complaint
                        was that their citizens who were on the Roman register had migrated in great
                        numbers <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> to the City, and if this were
                        allowed it would come to pass in a very few lustra that the towns and fields
                        would be deserted and incapable of furnishing any men for the army.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Samnites and Paeligni stated that
                        4000 families had gone from them to Fregellae, but they were not diminishing
                        their contingents, nor were the Fregellans increasing theirs. The practice
                        of individuals changing their citizenship led to two kinds of fraud.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The law allowed those amongst the
                        Latin allies who chose, to become Roman citizens if they left male progeny
                        behind in the old home. This law was abused to the injury of the allies and
                        of the Roman people. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For in order to
                        avoid any male descendants being left at home, they gave their children as
                        slaves to some Roman or other, on condition that they should be manumitted,
                        and as freedmen become citizens, whilst on the other hand those who had no
                        male descendants became Roman citizens. Subsequently, even this legal
                        presence was brushed aside. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In defiance
                        of law and without any male descendants they migrated to Rome and were
                        placed on the City register. The delegates asked that this might be stopped
                        for the future, and that those who had migrated should be ordered to return
                        to their homes. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They asked further that a
                        law might be passed making it illegal for any person to adopt or manumit any
                        one with the view of changing his citizenship, and also require those who
                        had become Roman citizens by this means to renounce their citizenship. The
                        senate granted these requests. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate then decreed that the provinces
                        which were in a state of war-Sardinia and Histria-should be assigned to the
                        consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two legions were ordered to be
                        raised for Sardinia, each consisting of 5200 infantry and 300 cavalry; the
                        Latin allies were to supply 12,000 infantry and 600 cavalry. In case the
                        consul wished to take ships from the dockyard, ten quinqueremes were placed
                        at his disposal. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The same strength of
                        infantry and cavalry was decreed for Histria as for Sardinia. The consuls
                        also received instructions to despatch a force of one legion with its
                        complement of cavalry and 5000 infantry and 250 cavalry from the allies to
                        M. Titinius in Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before the consuls
                        balloted for their provinces various portents were reported. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> A stone fell from the sky into the grove of Mars
                        in the Crustumerian district; on Roman land a boy was born without all his
                        limbs, and a four-footed snake was seen; at Capua numerous buildings in the
                        forum were struck by lightning; at Puteoli two shops had been set on fire by
                        a similar stroke. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While these were being
                        reported, a wolf entered the City by the Colline Gate in broad daylight and
                        was chased till it escaped through the Esquiline Gate, amidst great
                        excitement on the part of its pursuers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In
                        consequence of these portents the consuls sacrificed full-grown victims, and
                        there were special intercessions at all the shrines for one day. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> When the religious rites had been duly performed
                        the consuls drew for their provinces. Histria fell to Claudius, Sardinia to
                        Sempronius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then, in accordance with the
                        resolution of the senate, the consul C. Claudius carried a measure in which
                        it was ordered that those of the Latin allies who themselves or whose
                        ancestors had been registered among the Latin allies during the censorship
                        of M. Claudius and T. Quinctius or subsequently, should all return to their
                        cities before November 1. The praetor L. <milestone n="10??" unit="section"
                        /> Mummius was charged to enquire into the cases of those who had not
                        returned by that date. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In addition to
                        this new law, and the consul's edict enforcing it, a resolution was passed
                        by the senate ordering that whenever any one of them was manumitted and
                        publicly declared to be free, the dictator, consul, interrex, censor or
                        praetor for the time being should put the manumitter on his oath that he was
                        not doing it for the purpose of altering his citizenship; in case he refused
                        to take the oath the senate would declare the manumission invalid.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This resolution was to guide all
                        future proceedings. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Junius and A. Manlius, the ex-consuls
                        who had been in winter quarters at Aquileia, led their army into Histria at
                        the commencement of spring. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They carried
                        their ravages far and wide, and the Histrians were animated much more by
                        indignation and rage at the loss of their property than by any certain hope
                        that they would be strong enough to meet two consular armies. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> From all the tribes their fighting men collected
                        into a hastily levied tumultuary force, and they displayed much more
                        impetuosity in beginning a battle than steadfastness in keeping it up. Four
                        thousand of them fell on the field; the rest abandoned all resistance and
                        dispersed to their cities. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From these
                        cities delegates were sent to the Roman camp to sue for peace, and on being
                        required to give hostages they sent them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        When this became known in Rome through despatches from the proconsuls, C.
                        Claudius, fearing lest this success should rob him of his province and his
                        army, went off post-haste to his province without offering the customary
                        prayers, unattended by his lictors and in the dead of night, his colleague
                        being the only one who was aware of his intention. His conduct after his
                        arrival was more ill-advised even than the way in which he had started for
                        his province. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Addressing the assembled
                        troops, he taunted Manlius with his flight from the camp, to the intense
                        annoyance of the soldiers, since it was they who began the flight, and then
                        he attacked M. Junius for associating himself with his colleague's disgrace,
                        and ended by ordering them both to quit the province. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They promised that they would obey his order as soon as
                        he had made his departure from the City in the traditional way, after the
                        customary prayers in the Capitol, and attended by his lictors in their
                        official dress. Claudius, beside himself with rage, called the official who
                        was acting as quaestor to Manlius to bring fetters, and threatened to send
                        both Manlius and Junius in chains to Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        This officer also ignored the consul's authority, and their determination
                        not to obey was strengthened by the way the army supported their commanders
                        and resented the conduct of Claudius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At
                        last the consul, overborne by the insults and jeers of individual soldiers,
                        and the ridicule (for they actually laughed at him) of the whole army,
                        returned to Aquileia in the same vessel in which he had come. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> From there he sent word to his colleague to warn
                        that portion of the new levies which had been <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> raised for service in Histria to assemble at Aquileia,
                        so that nothing might detain him in Rome or prevent him from leaving the
                        City, with due formalities, offering the customary prayers and wearing the
                        paludamentum. His colleague carried out his instructions and ordered the
                        troops to assemble at an early date at Aquileia. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Claudius almost overtook his letter. On his arrival he
                        convened the Assembly and laid before it the case of Manlius and Junius.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> His stay in Rome only lasted three
                        days, and then, in full state with lictors and paludamentum, after offering
                        up prayers in the Capitol, he departed for his province with quite as much
                        precipitancy as before. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days before his arrival Junius and
                        Manlius began a determined attack on the town of Nesactium, to which place
                        the chiefs of the Histri, with their king, Aepulo, had retired. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Claudius brought up the two newly-raised legions,
                        and after disbanding the old army with its generals, invested the town and
                        proceeded to attack it with the vineae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        There was a river flowing past the town which impeded the assailants and
                        furnished water to the Histrians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After
                        many days' work he diverted this river into a new channel, and the cutting
                        off of their water-supply as though by a miracle greatly alarmed the
                        natives. Even then they had no thought of suing for peace; they made up
                        their minds to murder their women and children, and that this horrid deed
                        might be a spectacle to the enemy, they butchered <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> them openly on the walls and then flung them down.
                        Amidst the shrieks of the women and children and the unspeakable <milestone
                            n="6??" unit="section"/> horrors of the massacre, the Romans surmounted
                        the walls and entered the town. When the king heard the terrified cries of
                        those who fled, and understood <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> from the
                        tumult that the place was taken, he stabbed himself that he might not be
                        taken alive. The rest were either killed or made prisoners. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This was followed by the storming and destruction of
                        two other towns, Mutila and Faveria. The booty, considering the poverty of
                        the natives, surpassed expectations, and the whole of it was given to the
                        soldiers; 5632 persons were sold as slaves. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> The prime instigators of the war were scourged and beheaded. The
                        extermination of these three towns and the death of the king led to peace
                        throughout Histria; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> all the tribes made
                        their submission and gave hostages. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just after the Histrian war had come to an
                        end the Ligurians began to hold councils of war. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Tiberius Claudius, who had been praetor the previous
                        year and was now acting as proconsul, was in command of Pisae with one
                        legion He reported the movement in Liguria to the <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> senate, and they decided to send his despatch on to C.
                        Claudius, for the other consul had landed in Sardinia, and they authorised
                        him to transfer his army, if he thought it advisable now that Histria was
                        quiet, to Liguria. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After receiving the
                        consul's report of his operations in Histria a two days' thanksgiving was
                        decreed. The other consul, Tiberius Sempronius, was equally successful in
                        Sardinia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He marched into the Ilian
                        country, and finding a large body of Balari had come to the assistance of
                        the Ilians, he fought a pitched battle with the two tribes. The enemy were
                        routed, put to flight and driven out of their camp, 12,000 men being killed.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul ordered all the arms to be
                        collected on the following day and thrown into one heap. He then burnt them
                        as an offering to Vulcan. The victorious army retired into winter quarters
                        in the friendly cities. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On receipt of
                        Tiberius Claudius' despatch and the instructions of the senate, Caius
                        Claudius led his legions into Liguria. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        enemy had come down into the plains and was encamped by the river Scultenna.
                        A battle took place there; 15,000 were killed and over 700 were made
                        prisoners, either on the battlefield or in the camp-for this was stormed-and
                        51 military standards taken. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Ligurians
                        who survived this slaughter fled to the mountains, and no resistance was met
                        with anywhere by the consul as he traversed the level country plundering and
                        devastating their fields. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After winning
                        victories over two nations and reducing two provinces to submission during
                        his year of office-a thing which very few have done-Claudius returned to
                        Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some portents were reported this year.
                        Near Crustumerium an osprey cut a sacred stone with its beak; <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> in Campania a heifer spoke; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> a brazen image of a cow in Syracuse was mounted by a
                        bull which had strayed from the herd. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Special intercessions were offered on the spot at Crustumerium, and the
                        heifer in Campania was to be kept at the public cost. The portent at
                        Syracuse was expiated by sacrifices to the deities who were named by the
                        haruspices. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> One of the pontiffs, M.
                        Claudius Marcellus, died this year. He had been consul and also censor.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His son, M. Marcellus, was appointed
                        pontiff in his place. Two thousand Roman citizens were settled as colonists
                        at Luna under the supervision of P. Aelius, M. Aemilius Lepidus and Cnaeus
                        Sicinius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Fifty-one and a half jugera were
                        allotted to each colonist. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The land had
                        been taken from the Ligurians; it had previously been in the possession of
                        the Etruscans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After his return to the City the consul C.
                        Claudius made his report to the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> senate
                        of his victories in Histria and Liguria, and at his request, a triumph was
                        decreed to him. Whilst still in office he celebrated a double triumph over
                        the two nations. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the procession were
                        carried 307,000 denarii and 85,702 "victoriati." To each legionary were
                        given fifteen denarii, double the amount to the centurions, and treble to
                        the cavalry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The allied troops received
                        only half as much, and by way of showing their anger, they followed the
                        victor's chariot in silence. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst the
                        new consuls were each sacrificing an ox to Jupiter on the day of their
                        entering upon office, the victim which Q. Petilius was sacrificing was
                        defective; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> there was no head to the liver
                        visible. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He reported this to the senate,
                        and they ordered him to go on sacrificing until the victim gave a favourable
                        omen. The provinces were then discussed, and the senate decreed that Pisae
                        and Liguria should be the consular provinces, and the one to whom the ballot
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> gave Pisae was ordered to return and
                        hold the elections when the time for them arrived. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> They further decreed that the consuls should raise two
                        new <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> legions and 300 cavalry with each,
                        and from the Latin allies 10,000 infantry and 600 cavalry. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Ti. Claudius retained his command till the new consul
                        arrived in his province. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While this business was being transacted
                        in the senate, Cnaeus Cornelius was called out by an apparitor, and left the
                        House. On his return he was visibly perturbed, and explained that the liver
                        of the ox which he had sacrificed had disappeared. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When the victimarius reported this to him he did not
                        believe it, and he ordered the water in which the entrails were being boiled
                        to be poured out from the cauldron. He saw every other portion of the victim
                        complete, but in some unaccountable way the liver had been consumed.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senators were much alarmed at this
                        ominous incident, and their alarm was intensified by the other consul's
                        statement that after the appearance of the defective liver he had sacrificed
                        three oxen in succession without getting any favourable indication.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate ordered them both to go on
                        sacrificing until the omens were favourable. It is said that favourable
                        omens were at last observed in the case of all the other deities, but not in
                        the case of Salus, to whom Petilius was sacrificing. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls and praetors now balloted for
                        their provinces. Pisae fell to Cnaeus Cornelius, Liguria to Petilius, the
                        City jurisdiction to L. Papirius Maso, the alien to M. Aburius. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> M. Cornelius Scipio Maluginensis had Further
                        Spain, and L. Aquilius Gallus received Sardinia. Two asked to be excused
                        from going to their provinces. M. Popilius alleged as a reason for his not
                        going to Sardinia that Gracchus was pacifying that province and that the
                        praetor T. <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Aebutius was, by direction of
                        the senate, helping him in this task. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It
                        was, he said, most inconvenient for a line of policy to be interrupted when
                        its success mainly depends upon its continuance in the same hands. During
                        the transfer of authority and the time required by the new man to learn the
                        condition <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> of affairs before taking any
                        action, many an opportunity of achieving success is lost. The senate allowed
                        his excuse. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> P. Licinius Crassus, to whom
                        Hither Spain had fallen, alleged that he was prevented by his religious
                        duties. However, he was ordered either to go or to take an oath before the
                        Assembly that he was prevented by his religious duties. When the case of P.
                        Licinius had been settled in this way, M. Cornelius Scipio asked them to
                        accept his oath also, that he might not have to go to Further Spain. These
                        two praetors both took the same oath. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> M.
                        Titinius and T. Fonteius, who were in charge of that province as proconsuls,
                        were ordered to remain in Spain with the same authority as before and
                        reinforcements were to be sent to them-3000 Roman citizens and 200 cavalry,
                        with 5000 infantry and 300 cavalry from the allies. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Latin Festival took place on March 5,
                        and something occurred to mar its celebrations; the magistrate of Lanuvium
                        omitted to pray over one of the victims for "the Roman people of the
                        Quirites." <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This irregularity was reported
                        to the senate and by them referred to the college of pontiffs. The pontiffs
                        decided that the Latin Festival not having been properly and duly celebrated
                        must be observed anew, and that the people of Lanuvium, whose fault made the
                        renewal necessary, should provide the victims. A fresh misfortune increased
                        the general uneasiness. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul Cn.
                        Cornelius, whilst returning from the Alban Mount, fell from his horse and
                        was partially crippled. He went to the Baths of Cumae, but became gradually
                        worse and died at Cumae. The body was brought to Rome and received a
                        magnificent funeral. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had also been a
                        pontiff. Orders were given to the consul Q. Petilius to hold an election-as
                        soon as he obtained favourable omens from the sacrifices-to provide him with
                        a colleague and also to proclaim the Latin Festival. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He fixed the election for the 3rd and the Latin
                        Festival for the 11th of August. </p>
                    <p> Whilst men's minds were thus filled with religious fears, fresh portents
                        were announced. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At Tusculum a burning
                        brand was seen in the sky; at Gabii the temple of Apollo and several private
                        buildings were struck by lightning, as also were the wall and one of the
                        gates at Graviscae. The senate ordered such measures to be taken as the
                        pontiffs should direct. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During this time,
                        whilst the two consuls were pre-occupied with matters of religion, and then
                        the death of one of them and the duty thrown upon the other of electing his
                        successor, and also of presiding at the Latin Festival, created further
                        delay, C. Claudius brought his army up to Mutina, which the Ligurians had
                        taken the year before. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After a three days'
                        assault he recaptured the place and restored it to the colonists; 8000
                        Ligurians were killed inside the walls. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                        promptly sent a despatch to Rome in which he gave an account of his
                        operations and boasted that owing to his good fortune and ability there was
                        no longer any enemy to Rome on this side the Alps, and that a considerable
                        quantity of land had been acquired which could be distributed amongst many
                        thousands of colonists. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After many successful actions Ti.
                        Sempronius finally subjugated Sardinia; 15,000 natives were killed and all
                        the revolting tribes were forced into submission. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Those who had before paid the tax had now to pay
                        double; the rest paid in corn. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After peace
                        was established in the province and hostages taken from all parts of the
                        island-230 in all-a deputation was sent to Rome to announce the subjection
                        of the island and to ask the senate that honours should be paid to the
                        immortal gods for the success achieved under the leadership and auspices of
                        Ti. Sempronius, and that he himself might be allowed to bring away his army
                        with him when he left the province. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        senate received the deputation with their report in the temple of Apollo and
                        decreed a two days' thanksgiving; the consuls were also ordered to offer
                        forty sacrifices of the larger victims. Ti. Sempronius was to remain in the
                        province with his army as proconsul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        election to fill the vacancy in the consulship took place on the appointed
                        day, August 3. C. Valerius Laevinus was chosen as colleague to Q. Petilius
                        and was to enter upon his consulship at once. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He had long been anxious to obtain a province and most
                        opportunely for his wishes a despatch reached Rome saying that the Ligurians
                        had begun another war. On receipt of this intelligence the senate ordered
                        his immediate departure, and he left the City, wearing the paludamentum, on
                        August 5. The third legion was ordered to join C. Claudius in Gaul and the
                        fleet commanders were instructed to proceed to Pisae, making a circuit of
                        the Ligurian littoral and creating alarm in the coastal districts.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Q. <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        Petilius had previously fixed the date for the muster of the army at Pisae.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> C. Claudius, on hearing that the
                        Ligurians were renewing hostilities, raised an emergency force in addition
                        to the troops he had with him, and marched to the frontiers of Liguria. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The enemy had not forgotten that it was C.
                        Claudius who had defeated and routed them at the Scultenna, and they
                        prepared to defend themselves against a force of which they had had so
                        unhappy an experience more by the strength of their position than by their
                        arms. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With this object they occupied two
                        mountain heights, Letum and Ballista, and enclosed them with a wall. Some
                        who were too late in getting away from their fields were caught and 1500 of
                        them perished; the rest kept to the mountains. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> But they were not too much cowed to forget their native
                        savagery, and they glutted their cruelty upon what they had taken at Mutina.
                        The prisoners were put to death amid horrible tortures; the cattle were
                        killed in their temples as an act of butchery rather than of sacrifice.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When they were satiated with the
                        slaughter of living things they turned to the destruction of inanimate
                        objects and dashed against the walls vessels of every description, though
                        made for use more than for ornament. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Q.
                        Petilius did not want the war to be brought to a close while he was absent
                        and sent written instructions to C. Claudius to come to him in Gaul with his
                        army, saying that he should expect him at the Campi Macri. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> On receiving the despatch C. Claudius left Liguria and
                        handed over his army to the consul at the Campi Macri. A few days later the
                        other consul, C. Valerius, arrived. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Here,
                        before the two armies separated, a lustration was completed for them both.
                        As the consuls had settled not to make a combined attack on the enemy, they
                        drew lots to decide in which direction each should advance. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> It was generally understood that Valerius cast his lot
                        under proper auspices. In the case of Petilius the augurs declared
                        afterwards that he had been at fault, for after the lottery had been taken
                        into the sacred enclosure he remained outside, whereas he ought to have gone
                        in himself . </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then they started for their respective
                        positions. Petilius fixed his camp fronting the twin heights of Ballista and
                        Letum, which are connected by a continuous ridge. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Writers say that whilst he was addressing words of
                        encouragement to his troops, he made the ominous prediction that he would
                        take Letum on that day; the double meaning of the word did not occur to him.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He then advanced up the mountain in
                        two divisions. The division which he personally commanded mounted with great
                        spirit, but the enemy forced the other division back, and to restore the
                        battle the consul rode forward and rallied his men. Whilst exposing himself
                        somewhat incautiously in front of the standards, he was struck by a missile
                        and fell. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The enemy were not aware of the
                        general's death, and a few of his men who had witnessed it carefully
                        concealed the body, as they felt sure that the victory turned on that.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The rest of the troops-infantry and
                        cavalry alike-drove the enemy out of his positions and took the mountain
                        heights without their general; 5000 Ligurians were killed; out of the Roman
                        army 52 fell. In addition to his ill-omened words, to which his death gave a
                        clear significance, it was gathered from what the "pullarius" said that the
                        auspices had been unfavourable and that the consul was not unaware of this. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> . . . . . . . . Those skilled in divine
                        and human law said that since <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> the two
                        duly elected consuls for the year had died, one through sickness, the other
                        by the sword, the "consul suffectus" could not rightly hold the election. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> . . . . . . . . </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> . . . On this side the Apennines there had
                        been the Garuli, the Lapicini and the Hergates; on the other side the
                        Briniates. P. Mucius made war on those who had ravaged Luna and Pisae, and
                        after completely subjugating them deprived them of their arms. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> For these successes in Gaul and Liguria under the
                        leadership and auspices of the two consuls, the senate decreed a three days'
                        thanksgiving and sacrifices of forty victims. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The disturbances in Gaul and Liguria which had broken
                        out at the beginning of the year had been quelled without any great
                        difficulty, and now the public anxiety was directed to the danger of a war
                        with Macedonia, as Perseus was trying to involve the Dardani and the
                        Bastarnae in a conflict. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The commissioners
                        who had been sent to Macedonia to investigate the position there had now
                        returned and reported that there was a state of war in Dardania. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Envoys from Perseus arrived at the same time and
                        they declared, on his behalf, that the Bastarnae had not been approached by
                        him nor had they done anything at his instigation. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The senate did not clear him from the charges brought
                        against him, nor did they press them; they only ordered a warning to be
                        given him that he must be very careful to hold sacred the treaty which he
                        could regard as existing between him and Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the Dardani found that the Bastarnae
                        were not evacuating their territory as they had hoped, but were becoming
                        every day more aggressive and were receiving assistance from their Thracian
                        neighbours and from the Scordisci, they thought that they ought to attempt
                        some active measures, however hazardous. The whole of their armed force
                        assembled at a town near the camp of the Bastarnae. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> It was winter and they chose that season on the chance
                        of the Thracians and the Scordisci going back to their own country. It fell
                        out as they expected, and when they learnt that the Bastarnae were left to
                        themselves they divided their forces; one division was to make a frontal
                        attack, the other fetching a circuit was to take the enemy in the rear.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The fighting began, however, before
                        they could get round the enemy, and the Dardani were defeated and driven
                        into a city some twelve miles distant from the camp of the Bastarnae.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The victors followed them closely and
                        invested the place, feeling pretty confident that they would capture the
                        place the next day either by surrender or by storm. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Meanwhile the other division, unaware of the disaster
                        which had overtaken their comrades, seized the camp of the Bastarnae which
                        had been left unguarded. </p>
                    <p>. . . . . . . .</p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> . . . Seated in Roman fashion on an ivory
                        chair he used to administer justice and settle the most trifling disputes.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Roaming through every phase of life,
                        he was so far from remaining constant to any one form of it, that neither he
                        himself nor any one else was at all clear as to his real character.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He did not speak to his friends; he
                        had a pleasant smile for those who were hardly known to him; he made himself
                        and others ridiculous by his misplaced liberality. To some who were of high
                        rank and set great value upon themselves he used to give childish presents
                        of cakes and toys; others who expected nothing he enriched. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Some people thought that he was at a loss to know what
                        he meant by his actions; some said he was only playing the fool; some
                        declared that he was undoubtedly mad. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In
                        two matters of great importance and redounding to his honour he showed a
                        truly kingly spirit-his munificence to cities and his care for divine
                        worship. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He promised to build a wall round
                        Megalopolis and gave the greater part of the money for it. At Tegea he began
                        the construction of a magnificent marble theatre. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> At Cyzicus he furnished vessels of gold for one table
                        in the Prytaneum, the central hall of the city, where those to whom the
                        privilege has been granted dine at the public cost. In the case of the
                        Rhodians he did not make them any single gift of surpassing value, but he
                        gave them all sorts of things to suit their various requirements. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The splendid munificence which he showed towards
                        the gods is attested by the temple of Jupiter Olympius at Athens, the only
                        one in the world which has been begun on a scale proportionate to the
                        greatness of the deity. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Delos he adorned
                        with splendid altars and a great array of statues. At Antioch he projected a
                        magnificent temple to Jupiter Capitolinus, of which not only the ceiling was
                        to be overlaid with gold, but the whole of the walls were to be covered with
                        gold leaf. Many public edifices in other places he promised to build, but
                        the shortness of his reign prevented him from fulfilling his promises.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the magnificence of public
                        exhibitions of every kind he surpassed all former monarchs; they were with
                        only one exception given by Greek performers, the one exception being a
                        gladiatorial contest exhibited in Roman fashion, which frightened the
                        spectators, who were unused to such sights, more than it pleased them.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> By frequently giving these
                        exhibitions, in which the gladiators sometimes only wounded one another, and
                        at other times fought to the death, he familiarised the eyes of his people
                        to them and they learnt to enjoy them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In
                        this way he created amongst most of the younger men a passion for arms, and
                        whilst at first he used to hire gladiators from Rome <milestone n="13??"
                            unit="section"/> at a great cost, now from his own. </p>
                    <p>. . . . . .</p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> . . . Scipio, the alien jurisdiction.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The province of Sardinia had fallen to
                        M. Atilius, but he was ordered to sail to Corsica with the new legion which
                        the consuls had raised-5000 infantry and 300 cavalry. Whilst he was engaged
                        in that war, Cornelius' command in Sardinia was extended. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> To Cnaeus Servilius in Further Spain and P. Furius
                        Philus in Hither Spain were voted 3000 Roman infantry and 150 cavalry, and
                        of Latin allied troops 5000 infantry and 300 cavalry. Lucius Claudius
                        received no reinforcements for Sicily. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                        addition to these troops the consuls were required to raise two fresh
                        legions in full strength, both of infantry and cavalry, and also 10,000
                        infantry and 600 cavalry from the Latin allies. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The work of enrolment was all the more difficult for
                        the consuls, because the pestilence which the year before had attacked the
                        cattle had now turned into an epidemic, and those who fell victims to it
                        seldom survived the seventh day; those who did survive were subject to a
                        long and tedious illness, which generally took the form of a quartidian
                        ague. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The deaths occurred chiefly amongst
                        the slaves and their unburied bodies lay scattered in all the streets, and
                        not even in the case of the free population could the funeral rites be
                        carried out decently The corpses lay untouched by dog and <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> vulture and slowly rotted away, and it was generally
                        observed that neither in this nor in the previous year had a vulture been
                        anywhere seen. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Several members of the sacerdotal colleges
                        died from the epidemic-the pontiff Cn. Servilius Caepio, father of the
                        praetor; Tiberius Sempronius Longus, a Keeper of the Sacred Books; P. Aelius
                        Paetus, the augur; Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus; C. Atellus Mamilius, the
                        chief curio; and the pontiff M. Sempronius Tuditanus. C. Sulpicius Galba was
                        elected pontiff in place of Caepio . . . in place of Tuditanus. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The new augurs were T. Veturius Gracchus
                        Sempronianus in place of Gracchus, and Q. Aelius Paetus in place of P.
                        Aelius. C. Sempronius Longus was appointed a Keeper of the Sacred Books, and
                        C. Scribonius Curio was made chief curio. As the pestilence continued
                        unabated the senate decided that the Keepers should consult the Sacred
                        Books. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In accordance with their decree
                        there were special intercessions for one day, and the people, gathered
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> together in the Forum, made a
                        solemn vow, in words dictated by Marcius Philippus, that if disease and
                        pestilence were banished from Roman soil they would keep two days as solemn
                        holy days and days of special intercession. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> In the district of Veii a boy was born with two heads; at Sinuessa a
                        child with only one hand; at Ariminum a girl was born with teeth; a rainbow
                        spanned the temple of Saturn in the Forum in broad daylight and under a
                        cloudless sky, three suns shone at the same time, and in the same night many
                        meteors glided through the sky. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                        people of Caene declared that a crested snake covered with golden spots had
                        appeared in the town, and it was generally believed that an ox had spoken in
                        the Capuan district. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commission who had gone to Carthage,
                        after interviewing Masinissa, returned on June 7. They had been more
                        accurately informed as to what was going on in Carthage by the king than by
                        the Carthaginians themselves. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was an
                        ascertained fact, so they asserted, that envoys from Perseus had gone to
                        Carthage, and that the senate there had given them audience at a nocturnal
                        session in the temple of Aesculapius. Masinissa had stated that envoys had
                        been sent from Carthage to Macedonia, and this the Carthaginians did not
                        directly deny. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman senate decided
                        that they too must send envoys to Macedonia. Three were sent-C. Laelius, M.
                        Valerius Messala, and Sextus Digitius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A
                        certain section of the Dolopes refused to obey Perseus' orders and appealed
                        from him to the Romans to settle the differences between them. He advanced
                        against them with an army and reduced the whole nation to complete
                        submission. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then he crossed Mount Oeta and
                        went up to Delphi to consult the oracle about religious matters which were
                        disquieting his mind. His sudden appearance in the middle of Greece created
                        general alarm, not only amongst the neighbouring States, but in Asia as
                        well, where information of what was happening was hurriedly sent to Eumenes.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Perseus did not stay more than three
                        days at Delphi, and passing through Phthiotis, Achaia and Thessaly, returned
                        to his kingdom without damaging or injuring the districts through which he
                        passed. Nor did he consider it sufficient to conciliate those States through
                        which his route lay; he sent either letters or envoys to the different Greek
                        peoples, asking them to dismiss from their minds the hostile feelings which
                        had existed between them and his father. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        They were not, he urged, so bitter that they could not, and ought not, to be
                        put an end to in his case. As far as he was concerned there was nothing to
                        disturb their relations or to prevent the growth of an honest and sincere
                        friendship. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With the Achaeans, especially,
                        he was anxious to find some way of ingratiating himself. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This nation and the Athenians alone out of
                        all Greece had pushed their animosity so far as to forbid the Macedonians to
                        enter their country. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Macedonia had, in
                        consequence, become a refuge for all the runaway slaves from Achaia, for as
                        the Achaeans had closed their frontiers against Macedonia, they could not
                        themselves venture into that kingdom. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When
                        Perseus got to know this, he had the runaways arrested and sent a letter . .
                        . "They, too, however, must think out the best means of preventing the
                        flight of slaves in the future." <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        letter was read at a meeting of their council by Xenophanes, their
                        captain-general, who was anxious to make private interest with the king.
                        Most of those present thought it written in a fair and generous spirit,
                        especially those who were to recover the runaway slaves whom they had given
                        up for lost. Amongst those who believed that the safety of the nation
                        depended upon their keeping their treaty with Rome intact was Callicrates.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He made the following speech to the
                        council: "Some look upon this question as of small and trifling importance;
                        I regard it as the greatest and most serious of all under discussion, and,
                        more than that, I consider that it has in one way been decided. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> For although we have excluded the kings of
                        Macedonia and the Macedonians themselves from our territories, and that
                        decree is still in force forbidding us to admit the envoys and
                        communications <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> of their kings, through
                        which the feelings of some amongst us might be wrongly influenced,
                        nevertheless, we are now listening to the king as though he were addressing
                        us whilst absent, and we are actually giving our approval to his speech.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Wild animals mostly reject and shun
                        the food which is placed to deceive them, but we in our blindness are caught
                        by the idle show of a petty boon, and in the hope of recovering some
                        miserable slaves of very little value we are allowing our own liberty to be
                        tampered with and undermined. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Who does not
                        see that a way is being sought to lead us to an alliance with the king, and
                        therefore to a breach of the treaty with Rome, with which all our interests
                        are bound up? Unless, indeed, anyone doubts that a war between Perseus and
                        the Romans is inevitable, and that what was expected during Philip's
                        lifetime and interrupted by his death will take place now that he is dead.
                        Philip, as you know, had two sons, Demetrius and Perseus. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Demetrius far surpassed his brother in birth on the
                        mother's side, in courage, in ability, in popularity with his countrymen.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But Philip had destined the crown as
                        a reward for hatred of the Romans, and he put Demetrius to death for no
                        other offence than his friendship with Rome. Perseus, he knew, would inherit
                        a war with Rome almost before he inherited the crown, and he made him king.
                        What else has he been doing since his father's death but making preparations
                        for war? In the first place he sent the Bastarnae into Dardania creating
                        universal alarm. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If they had made their
                        home in that country, Greece would have found them more troublesome
                        neighbours than the Gauls were in Asia. Though his expectations here were
                        frustrated, he did not give up all thoughts of war; rather, to say the
                        truth, he has now commenced war and subjugated the Dolopes by force of arms,
                        and refused to listen to their proposal to refer their differences to the
                        arbitration of Rome. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then he crossed
                        Mount Oeta and, in order to make a sudden appearance in the heart of Greece,
                        went up to Delphi. What do you imagine was his object in thus exercising a
                        right-of-way where none existed? Then he traversed Thessaly. His doing so
                        without inflicting injury on any of those he hated I regard with all the
                        more apprehension as an attempt to win them over. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> And now he has sent a letter to us with what looks like
                        an act of generosity, and advises us to consider how for the future we may
                        dispense with that generosity, namely, by rescinding the decree by which the
                        Macedonians are kept out of the Peloponnese. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> This, too, in order that we may once more see the
                        king's ambassadors and the renewal of hospitable relations with his chief
                        men. Before long we shall have the Macedonian armies and the king himself
                        entering the Peloponnese by way of Delphi-narrow is the strait that
                        separates us! and, finally, we shall find ourselves in the ranks of the
                        Macedonians whenever they take up arms against Rome. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> I give it as my opinion that we make no fresh decree,
                        but let everything remain just <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> as it
                        is, until it becomes absolutely certain whether these fears of mine are
                        groundless or justified. If the peace between Macedonia and Rome remains
                        unbroken, let there be friendly intercourse between us. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> For the present it seems to me premature and dangerous
                        to think of altering our policy." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He was followed by Archo, the brother of
                        Xenarchus, who spoke as follows: "Callicrates has made it difficult for me
                        and for all who disagree with him to reply. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> By taking up the defence of our alliance with Rome and asserting that it
                        is attacked and opposed when nobody is either attacking or opposing it, he
                        has made anyone who does not agree with him appear as though he were
                        speaking against the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To begin
                        with, he knows and proclaims every secret transaction, just as if instead of
                        being here amongst us he had come straight from the Roman senate-house or
                        from the king's privy council. He even divines what would have happened had
                        Philip lived; why under the circumstances Perseus was heir to the crown;
                        what preparations the Macedonians are making; what designs the Romans are
                        entertaining. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But we, who do not know the
                        cause of the circumstances of Demetrius' death, nor what Philip would have
                        done had he lived, are bound to frame our policy in accordance with open and
                        notorious facts. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "Now we know that on receiving the crown
                        Perseus was recognised as king by the Roman people; we hear that Roman
                        ambassadors visited the king and were graciously received by him. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> In my judgment, this points to peace and not to
                        war, nor can the Romans possibly be offended if, as we followed their lead
                        in war, so now we follow them as the authors of peace. I do not see why we
                        alone in all the world should wage a relentless war against the kingdom of
                        Macedonia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Are we so near it as to be open
                        to attack? Are we like the Dolopes, who are the weakest of all the nations
                        that he has subdued? No, quite the contrary. Whether it is through our own
                        strength or through the favour of heaven or owing to the distance which
                        separates us, in any case we are safe. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                        suppose we lay as open to invasion as the Thessalians and the Aetolians,
                        have we no more interest with the Romans, no stronger claim upon them than
                        the Aetolians, who were not long ago in arms against them, while we have
                        always been their friends and allies? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Whatever reciprocal rights exist between the Macedonians and the Aetolians,
                        Thessalians and Epirotes, in fact the whole of Greece, let us also enjoy.
                        Why does this abominable interference with the common rights of humanity
                        exist for us alone? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Granting that Philip
                        did something which caused us to make this decree against him when he was in
                        arms and engaged in war, what has Perseus, new to the throne, guiltless of
                        any wrong towards us, effacing by his kindness the enmity aroused against
                        his father-what has Perseus done to make us, alone of all nations, his
                        enemies? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I might also urge this point,
                        that the services which the former kings of Macedonia have rendered us have
                        been so great that the injury which Philip has done to us, however great it
                        was, should be forgotten, especially now that he is dead. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> You know that when the Roman fleet was lying at
                        Cenchreae and the consul with his army was at Elatia, we were assembled in
                        council to decide whether we should follow Philip or the Romans, and the
                        discussion lasted three days. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Even if the
                        pressure of immediate danger in no way alienated our feelings from the
                        Romans, there must have been something at least to make our deliberations so
                        lengthy, and this was our long-standing union of interests with Macedonia
                        and the great services which her kings have for many years rendered to us.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Let these same motives weigh with us
                        now, not to make us especially his friends, but to prevent us from being
                        especially his enemies. Do not let us make a presence, Callicrates, of
                        seriously discussing a proposal which nobody has brought forward. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> No one suggests that we should form fresh
                        alliances or draw up a new treaty so as to fetter ourselves with obligations
                        thoughtlessly incurred. Let there be free intercourse between us, a mutual
                        recognition of reciprocal rights; let us not, by closing our own frontiers,
                        shut ourselves off at the same time from the king's dominions; let it not be
                        possible for our runaway slaves to find shelter anywhere. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> What is there in all this that conflicts with the terms
                        of our treaty with Rome? Why do we make so much of a little matter and throw
                        suspicion upon what is simple and straightforward? Why do we raise such
                        troubles out of nothing? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Why do we make
                        others mistrusted and suspected in order that we ourselves may be free to
                        flatter the Romans? <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> If there is to be
                        war, even Perseus himself entertains no doubt as to our taking the side of
                        Rome. As long as there is peace, let all hostile feelings be suppressed,
                        even if they are not dispelled." Those who had approved of the king's letter
                        were in full agreement with this speech. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        The leaders were indignant at Perseus not thinking the matter important
                        enough for formal negotiation and making his demand in the few lines of a
                        letter. The discussion was adjourned and no decree was made. <milestone
                            n="20" unit="section"/> Subsequently envoys were sent by the king whilst
                        the council was in session at Megalopolis, and those who feared a breach
                        with Rome took steps to prevent their admission to the council. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While this was going on the Aetolians
                        turned their rage against themselves, and it seemed as though the massacres
                        on both sides would result in the total destruction of the nation.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At last both factions, weary of
                        slaughter, sent missions to Rome and approached each other in the hope of
                        re-establishing peace and concord. But these negotiations were rendered
                        fruitless by a fresh outrage which roused all the old passions. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The refugees from Hypata, comprising eighty
                        illustrious citizens, who belonged to the party of Proxenus, had been
                        assured of their restoration to their native country under the pledged word
                        of Eupolemus, the chief magistrate. As they were returning home the whole
                        population, including Eupolemus himself, came out to meet them; he gave them
                        a kind greeting and the right hand of friendship. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> But as they were entering the gates they were all put
                        to death in spite of their appeals to the gods, as witnesses of the pledges
                        given by Eupolemus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After this the war
                        blazed up more fiercely than ever. C. Valerius Laevinus, Ap. Claudius
                        Pulcher, C. Memmius, M. Popilius and L. Canuleius had been sent by the
                        senate to arbitrate between the contending parties. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The delegates from both sides appeared before them at
                        Delphi and a keen debate took place, in which Proxenus was considered to
                        have spoken by far the most convincingly and most eloquently. A few days
                        later he was poisoned by his wife Orthobula. She was convicted of the crime
                        and sent into exile. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same madness of
                        party faction was rife among the Cretans. When Q. Minucius, who had been
                        sent with ten ships to settle their disputes, arrived off the island they
                        entertained hopes of peace. There was only a six months' truce, however;
                        after that a still more bitter conflict was kindled. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The Lycians were being harassed at this time by the
                        Rhodians. But it is not worth while to narrate in detail these wars which
                        foreign nations waged with each other. The task before me is sufficiently
                        and more than sufficiently heavy of describing the doings of the Romans.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Spain the Celtiberi who, after their
                        defeat, had submitted to Ti. Gracchus, remained quiet during M. Titinius'
                        administration. On the arrival of Appius Claudius they resumed hostilities
                        and began by a sudden attack on the Roman camp. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The day had hardly dawned when the sentinels on the
                        rampart and the men on outpost duty at the gates caught sight of the enemy
                        advancing in the distance and gave the alarm. Appius Claudius hoisted the
                        signal for action and after addressing a few words to the soldiers made a
                        simultaneous sortie from three gates. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        Celtiberi met them as they emerged and for a short time the fighting was
                        equal on both sides, because owing to the confined space the Romans could
                        not all get into action. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As soon as they
                        got clear of the rampart they followed those in front of them in a compact
                        mass in order to be able to deploy into line and extend their front to the
                        same length as that of the enemy by whom they were being surrounded. Then
                        they made a sudden charge which the Celtiberi could not withstand.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In less than two hours they were
                        defeated; 15,000 were either killed or taken prisoners; 32 standards were
                        captured. The camp was stormed the same day and the war brought to an end.
                        The survivors from the battle dispersed to their various towns. After that
                        they submitted quietly to the authority of Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Q. Fulvius Flaccus and A. Postumius
                        Albinus were elected censors this year and revised the roll of the senate.
                        M. Aemilius Lepidus, the Pontifex Maximus, was chosen as leader of the
                        House. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nine names were struck off the
                        roll, the most important being those of M. Cornelius, Maluginensis, who had
                        commanded as praetor in Spain two years before, L. Cornelius Scipio, who was
                        at the time exercising the civic and alien jurisdictions, and L. Fulvius the
                        censor's brother, and according to Valerius Antias, co-proprietor with him
                        of the family estate. After the usual prayers and vows the consuls left for
                        their provinces. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> M. Aemilius was charged
                        by the senate with the task of suppressing the outbreak of the Petavines in
                        Venetia, amongst whom, as their own envoys reported, the strife of rival
                        factions had led to civil wars. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        commissioners who had gone to Aetolia to put down similar disturbances
                        brought back word that the frenzy of the nation could not be restrained. The
                        consul's arrival was the salvation of the Petavines, and as he had nothing
                        else to do in his province he returned to Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These censors were the first to make
                        contracts for paving the streets of the City with flints and the roads
                        outside with gravel, and footpaths raised at the sides, and also for the
                        construction of bridges at various points. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        They furnished the praetors and aediles with a stage, placed the barriers in
                        the Circus and provided egg-shaped balls to mark the number of laps,
                        turning-posts on the course and iron doors for the cages through which the
                        animals were sent into the arena. They also undertook the paving of the
                        ascent from the Forum to the Capitol with flint and the construction of a
                        colonnade from the temple of Saturn to the Capitol, and then on to the
                        senaculum, and beyond that to the senate-house. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The market-place outside the Porta Trigemina was paved
                        with stone slabs and enclosed by a palisading; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> they also repaired the Aemilian colonnade and made a
                        flight of stone steps on the slope leading from the Tiber. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Inside the same gate they paved the colonnade leading
                        to the Aventine with flint and made a road from the temple of Venus by the
                        Clivus Publicius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These censors also
                        signed contracts for the erection of walls at Calatia and Auximium, and the
                        money which they received from the sale of portions of the State domain was
                        spent in building shops round the forums in both these places. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Postumius gave out that without the orders of
                        the Roman senate or people he would not spend their money, so Fulvius
                        Flaccus, acting alone, built a temple to Jupiter at Pisaurum and at Fundi
                        and brought water to Placentia. He also paved a street at Pisaurum with
                        flint. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At Sinuessa he added some suburban
                        residences with aviaries, constructed sewers, enclosed the place with a
                        wall, built colonnades and shops all round the forum, setting up three
                        statues of Janus there. These works contracted for by one of the censors
                        were greatly appreciated by the members of the colony. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The censors were strict and painstaking in the
                        regulation of morals; several of the equites were deprived of their horses.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Towards the close of the year there were
                        thanksgivings for one day for the successes gained in Spain under the
                        auspices and generalship of Appius Claudius, and twenty of the larger
                        victims were offered in sacrifice. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        next day special intercessions were offered up at the temples of Ceres,
                        Liber and Libera, owing to a report which had come in of a violent
                        earthquake in the Sabine country which had laid many buildings in ruins.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On Appius Claudius' return from Spain
                        the senate decreed that he should enter the City in ovation. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The consular elections were now approaching and
                        there was keen competition owing to the large number of candidates. L.
                        Postumius Albinus and M. Popilius Laenas were elected. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The new praetors were N. Fabius Buteo, M. Matienus, C.
                        Cicereius, M. Furius Crassipes for the second time, A. Atilius Serranus for
                        the second time, and C. Cluvius Saxula also for the second time. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> When the elections were over, Ap. Claudius
                        celebrated his triumph over the Celtiberi by entering the City in ovation,
                        and he brought into the treasury 10,000 pounds of silver and 5000 pounds of
                        gold. Cnaeus Cornelius was inaugurated as Flamen Dialis. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During the year a tablet was placed in the
                        temple of Mater Matuta with this inscription: <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> "Under the auspices and command of the consul Tiberius
                        Sempronius Gracchus, the legions of the army of Rome have subjugated
                        Sardinia. In that province there have been 80,000 natives either killed or
                        made prisoners. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was most happy in his
                        administrations; he liberated the allies of Rome; he restored the revenues
                        and brought his army safely home laden with enormous booty. For the second
                        time he entered Rome in triumph. Because of this he has given this tablet as
                        an offering to Jove." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There was a
                        representation of the island and pictures of the battles on the tablet.
                        Several gladiatorial exhibitions were given this year, most of them on a
                        small scale; the one given by T. Flamininus far surpassed the rest.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the occasion of his father's death
                        he exhibited this spectacle for four days, and accompanied it with a
                        distribution of meat, a funeral feast, and scenic plays. But even in this
                        magnificent exhibition the total number of men who fought was only
                        seventy-four. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
