<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six -
                    29</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to
                                thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="1231" xml:id="p.1231"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXIX.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> In Spain, Mandonius and Indibilis, reviving hostilities, are finally
                        subdued. Scipio goes over from Syracuse to Locri; dislodges the Carthaginian
                        general; repulses Hannibal, and recovers that city. Peace made with Philip.
                        The Idaean Mother brought to Rome from Phrygia; received by Publius Scipio
                        Nasica, judged by the senate the best man in the state. Scipio passes over
                        into Africa. Syphax, having married a daughter of Hasdrubal, renounces his
                        alliance with Scipio. Masinissa, who had been expelled his kingdom by
                        Syphax, joins Scipio with two hundred horsemen; they defeat a large army
                        commanded by Hanno. Hasdrubal and Syphax approach with a most numerous
                        force. Scipio raises the siege of Utica, and fortifies a post for the
                        winter. The consul Sempronius gets the better of Hannibal in a battle near
                        Croton. dispute between Marcus Livius and Claudius Nero, censors. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> SCIPIO, after his arrival in Sicily, formed
                    his volunteers into cohorts and centuries. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of
                    these he kept about his person three hundred young men, in the bloom of their
                    age and the prime of their strength, unarmed, and not knowing for what purpose
                    they were reserved, as they were not included in the centuries, nor furnished
                    with arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then selected out of the number
                    of the youth of all Sicily three hundred horsemen, of the highest birth and
                    fortune, who were to cross over with him into Africa, appointing a day on which
                    they were to present themselves equipped and furnished with horses and arms.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This severe service, far from their native
                    land, appeared to them likely to be attended with many hardships, and great
                    dangers, both by sea and land; nor did that anxiety affect themselves alone, but
                    also their parents and relations. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the
                    appointed day arrived, they exhibited their arms and horses. Then Scipio
                    observed, <quote> that an intimation had been conveyed to him that certain of
                        the Sicilian horsemen felt a strong aversion to that service, as being
                        severe and arduous. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If there were any who
                        entertained such a feeling, that he would rather they should then confess it
                        to him, than, complaining afterwards, prove themselves slothful and <pb
                            n="1232" xml:id="p.1232"/> useless soldiers to the state. He desired
                        that they would openly avow their sentiments, for that he would hear them
                        with kindly feeling. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When one of the number took courage to
                    declare, that if he were allowed the uncontrolled exercise of his will he
                    certainly would not serve, Scipio replied to him thus: <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Since then, young man, you have not dissembled your sentiments, I will
                        furnish a substitute for you, to whom I request that you transfer your arms,
                        your horse, and other appliances of war; and, taking him hence immediately
                        to your house, train him, and take care that he is instructed in the
                        management of his horse and arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The youth accepted the terms joyfully, when
                    Scipio delivered to him one of the three hundred whom he kept unarmed. The rest,
                    seeing the horseman thus discharged without giving any offence to the general,
                    began severally to excuse themselves and receive substitutes. Thus Roman
                    horsemen were substituted for the three hundred Sicilian, without any expense to
                    the state. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Sicilians had the care of
                    instructing and training them, because the general had ordered that the man who
                    should not do so, should serve himself. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It is
                    said that this turned out to be an admirable body of cavalry, and rendered
                    effectual service to the state in many engagements. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Afterwards, inspecting the legions, he chose out of them
                    such soldiers as had served the greatest number of campaigns, particularly those
                    who had acted under Marcellus; for he considered that they were formed under the
                    best discipline, and also, from the long time in which they were engaged in the
                    siege of Syracuse, were most skilled in the assault of towns: for his thoughts
                    were now occupied with no small object, but the destruction of Carthage.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He then distributed his army through the
                    towns; ordered the Sicilian states to furnish corn, sparing that which had been
                    brought from Italy; repaired his old ships, and sent Caius Laelius with them
                    into Africa to plunder. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> His new ships he
                    hauled on shore at Panormus, that they might be kept on land during the winter,
                    as they had been hastily built of unseasoned timber. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When every thing was got in readiness for the
                    war he came to Syracuse, which had hardly yet returned to a state of
                    tranquillity, after the violent commotions of the war. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> The Greeks, demanding restitution of their property, which
                    had been granted to them by the senate, from certain persons of <pb n="1233"
                        xml:id="p.1233"/> the Italian nation, who retained possession of it in the
                    same forcible manner in which they had seized it in the war, Scipio, who deemed
                    it <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> of the first importance to preserve the
                    public faith, restored their property to the Syracusans, partly by proclamation,
                    and partly even by judgments pronounced against those who pertinaciously
                    retained their unjust acquisitions. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> This
                    measure was acceptable not only to the persons immediately concerned, but to all
                    the states of Sicily, and so much the more energetically did they give aid in
                    the war. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> During the same summer a very
                    formidable war sprang up in Spain, at the instance of Indibilis the Ilergetian,
                    from no other cause than the contempt he conceived for the other generals, in
                    consequence of his admiration of Scipio. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> He
                    considered <quote> that he was the only commander the Romans had left, the rest
                        having been slain by Hannibal. That they had, therefore, no other general
                        whom they could send into Spain after the Scipios were cut off there, and
                        that afterwards, when the war in Italy pressed upon them with increased
                        severity, he was recalled to oppose Hannibal. That, in addition to the fact
                        that the Romans had the names only of generals in Spain, their old army had
                        also been withdrawn thence. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> That all the
                        troops they had there were irresolute, as consisting of an undisciplined
                        multitude of recruits. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> That there would
                        never again occur such an opportunity for the liberation of Spain.
                            <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> That up to that time they had been
                        the slaves either of Carthaginians or Romans, and that not to one or the
                        other in turns, but sometimes to both together. <milestone n="24"
                            unit="section"/> That the Carthaginians had been driven out by the
                        Romans, and that the Romans might be driven out by the Spaniards, if they
                        would unite: so that Spain, for ever freed from a foreign yoke, might return
                        to her native customs and rites. </quote>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> By these and other observations he stirred up
                    not only his countrymen, but the Ausetanians also, a neighbouring nation, as
                    well as other states bordering on his own and their country. <milestone n="26"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, within a few days, thirty thousand foot and
                    about four thousand horse assembled in the Sedetanian territory, according to
                    the orders which had been given. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the other side, the Roman generals also,
                    Lucius Lentulus and Lucius Manlius Acidinus, lest <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> by neglecting the first beginnings of the war it should
                    increase in violence, having united their armies, and led their troops through
                    the <pb n="1234" xml:id="p.1234"/> Ausetanian territory in a peaceable manner,
                    as though it had been the territory of friends instead of enemies, came to the
                    position of the enemy, and pitched their camp at a distance of three miles from
                    theirs. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first an unsuccessful attempt was
                    made, through ambassadors, to induce them to lay down their arms; then the
                    Spanish cavalry making a sudden attack on the Roman foragers, a body of cavalry
                    was sent to support them from the Roman outposts, when a battle between the
                    cavalry took place with no memorable issue to either side. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The next day, at sun-rise, the whole force displayed their
                    line, armed and drawn out for battle, at the distance of about a mile from the
                    Roman camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Ausetanians were in the
                    centre, the right wing was occupied by the Ilergetians, the left by some
                    inconsiderable states of Spain. Between the wings and the centre they had left
                    intervals of considerable extent, through which they might send out their
                    cavalry when occasion required. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Romans
                    also, drawing up their army in their usual manner, imitated the enemy in respect
                    only of leaving themselves also intervals between the legions to afford passages
                    for their cavalry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Lentulus, however,
                    concluding that the cavalry could be employed with advantage by those only who
                    should be the first to send them against the enemy's line, thus broken by
                    intervals, ordered Servius Cornelius, a military tribune, to direct the cavalry
                    to ride at full speed into the spaces left in the enemy's line. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Lentulus himself, as the battle between the infantry was
                    somewhat unfavourable in its commencement, waited <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> only until he had brought up from the reserve into the
                    front line the thirteenth legion to support the twelfth legion, which had been
                    posted in the left wing, against the Ilergetians, and which was giving ground.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And when the battle was thus placed on an
                    equal footing in that quarter, he came to Lucius Manlius, who was exhorting the
                    troops in the foremost line, and bringing up the reserves in such places as
                    circumstances required, and told him that all was safe in the left wing, and
                    that Cornelius Servius, who had <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> been sent
                    by him for that purpose, would soon pour round the enemy a storm of cavalry.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He had scarcely uttered these words, when
                    the Roman horse, riding into the midst of the enemy, at once threw their line of
                    infantry into disorder, and closed up the passage by which the Spanish cavalry
                    were to advance. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Spaniards, therefore,
                    giving up all thoughts of fighting on <pb n="1235" xml:id="p.1235"/> horseback,
                    dismounted and fought on foot. When the Roman generals saw that the ranks of the
                    enemy were in confusion, that they were in a state of trepidation and dismay,
                    their standards moving to and fro, they exhorted and implored their men to
                    charge them while thus discomfited, and not allow them to form their line again.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So desperate was their charge that the
                    barbarians could not have withstood the shock, had not the prince Indibilis in
                    person, together with the dismounted cavalry, opposed himself to the enemy
                    before the front rank of the infantry. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> There
                    an obstinate contest continued for a considerable time; but those who fought
                    round the king, who continued his resistance though almost expiring, and who was
                    afterwards pinned to the earth by a javelin, having at length fallen,
                    overwhelmed with darts, a general flight took place; <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> and the number slain was the greater because the horsemen
                    were prevented from remounting, and because the Romans pressed impetuously upon
                    the discomfited troops; nor did they give over until they had deprived the enemy
                    of their camp. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> On that day thirteen thousand
                    Spaniards were slain, and about eight hundred captured. Of the Romans and allies
                    there fell a little more than two hundred, and those principally in the left
                    wing. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Such of the Spaniards as were beaten
                    out of their camp, or had escaped from the battle, at first dispersed themselves
                    through the country, but afterwards returned each to his own state. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They were then summoned to an assembly by
                    Mandonius, at which, after complaining bitterly of the losses they had
                    sustained, and upbraiding the instigators of the war, they resolved that
                    ambassadors should be sent with proposals to deliver up their arms and make a
                    surrender. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These, laying the blame on
                    Indibilis, the instigator of the war, and the other chiefs, most of whom had
                    fallen in the battle, and offering to deliver up their arms and surrender
                    themselves, received for answer, that their surrender would be accepted on
                    condition that they delivered up alive Mandonius and the rest of the persons who
                    had fomented the war; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but if they refused to
                    comply, that armies should be marched into the territories of the Ilergetians
                    and Ausetanians, and afterwards into those of the other states in succession.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This answer given to the ambassadors, was
                    reported to the assembly, and Mandonius and the other chiefs were there seized
                    and delivered up for punish- <pb n="1236" xml:id="p.1236"/> ment. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Peace was restored to the states of Spain, which were
                    ordered to pay double taxes that year, and furnish corn for six months, together
                    with cloaks and gowns for the army; and hostages were taken from about thirty of
                    the states. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The tumult occasioned by the rebellion in
                    Spain having been thus excited and suppressed within the space of a few days,
                    without any great disturbance, the whole terror of the war was directed against
                    Africa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Caius Laelius having arrived at Hippo
                    Regius by night, at break of day led his soldiers and mariners in regular array
                    to lay waste the country. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As all the
                    inhabitants were living unguardedly, as in a time of peace, great damage was
                    done; and messengers, flying in terror, filled Carthage with alarm, by reporting
                    that the Roman fleet and the general, Scipio, had arrived; for there was a
                    rumour that Scipio had already crossed over into Sicily. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Not knowing accurately how many ships they had seen, or how
                    large a body of troops was devastating the country, they, under the influence of
                    fear, which represented them as greater than they really were, exaggerated every
                    thing. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly, at first, terror and
                    dismay took possession of their minds, but afterwards grief, when they reflected
                    that their circumstances had undergone so great a change; that they, who lately
                    as conquerors had an army before the walls of Rome, and, after having laid
                    prostrate so many armies of the enemy, had received the surrender of all the
                    states of Italy, either by force or choice, now, the war having <milestone
                        n="11??" unit="section"/> taken an unfavourable turn, were destined to
                    behold the devastation of Africa and the siege of Carthage, without any thing
                    like the resources to enable them to bear up against those calamities which the
                    Romans possessed. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To the latter the Roman
                    commons and Latium afforded a supply of young men, which continually grew up
                    more vigorous and more numerous, in the room of so many armies destroyed, while
                    their own people, both those in the city and those in the country, were unfit
                    for military service; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> their troops consisted
                    of auxiliaries, procured by hire from the Africans, a faithless nation, and
                    veering about with every gale of fortune. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Now
                    too, with regard to the kings, Syphax was alienated from them since his
                    conference with Scipio, and Masinissa, by an open defection, had become their
                    most determined enemy. Wherever they turned their eyes there was no hope, no
                    aid. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Neither did Mago ex- <pb n="1237"
                        xml:id="p.1237"/> cite any commotion on the side of Gaul, nor join his
                    forces with those of Hannibal; while Hannibal himself was now declining both in
                    reputation and strength. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their minds, which had fallen into these
                    melancholy reflections in consequence of the intelligence they had just
                    received, were brought back by their immediate fears to deliberate how to oppose
                    the instant danger. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They resolved, that troops
                    should be hastily levied both in the city and in the country; that persons
                    should be sent to hire auxiliaries from the Africans; that the city should be
                    fortified, corn collected, weapons and arms prepared, and ships equipped and
                    sent to Hippo against the Roman fleet. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But
                    now, while engaged in these matters, news at length arrived that it was Laelius,
                    and not Scipio; that the forces which he had brought over were only what were
                    sufficient for making predatory incursions into the country, and that the
                    principal stress of the war still lay in Sicily. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Thus they were enabled to take breath, and they began to send embassies to
                    Syphax and the other petty princes, for the purpose of strengthening their
                    alliances. To Philip also ambassadors were sent, to promise him two hundred
                    talents of silver, if he would cross over into Sicily or Italy. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Ambassadors were also sent into Italy to the two generals,
                    to desire them to keep Scipio at home by terrifying the enemy in every way they
                    could. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To Mago, not only ambassadors were
                    sent, but twenty-five men of war, six thousand infantry, eight hundred horse,
                    and seven elephants, besides a large sum of money to be employed in hiring
                    auxiliaries, in order that, encouraged by these aids, he might advance his army
                    nearer to the city of Rome, and form a junction with Hannibal. Such were the
                    preparations and plans at Carthage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While
                    Laelius was employed in carrying off an immense quantity of booty from the
                    country, the inhabitants of which had no arms, and which was destitute of
                    forces, Masinissa, moved by the report of the arrival of the Roman fleet, came
                    to him attended by a small body of horse. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                    complained that <quote> Scipio had not acted with promptness in this business,
                        in that he had not already passed his army over into Africa, while the
                        Carthaginians were in consternation, and while Syphax was entangled in wars
                        with the neighbouring states, and in doubt and uncertainty as to the course
                        he should take; that if time was allowed to Syphax to adjust his own <pb
                            n="1238" xml:id="p.1238"/> affairs according to his mind, he would not
                        in any thing keep his faith with the Romans inviolate. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He requested that he would exhort and
                    stimulate Scipio not to delay. Though driven from his kingdom, he said he would
                    join him with no despicable force of foot and horse. Nor was it right, said he,
                    that Laelius should continue in Africa, for he believed that a fleet had set
                    sail from Carthage, with which, in the absence of Scipio, it would not be
                    altogether safe to engage. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this discourse Masinissa departed.
                    Laelius, the next day, sailed from Hippo with his ships loaded with booty, and
                    returning to Sicily, delivered to Scipio the injunctions of Masinissa.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> About the same time the ships which were
                    sent from Carthage to Mago touched at the country between the Albingaunian
                    Ligurians and Genoa. Mago happened to be lying here with his fleet at this time.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After hearing the message of the
                    ambassadors, directing him to collect as great a number of troops as possible,
                    he immediately held a council of the Gauls and Ligurians, for a great number of
                    both those nations were there. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He said that he
                    was sent to restore them to liberty, and, as they themselves might see, succours
                    were sent him from home; but that it depended upon them with how great forces
                    and how large an army the war for that purpose was to be carried on. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> That the Romans had two armies in the field, one in
                    Gaul and another in Etruria. That he was well informed that Spurius Lucretius
                    would form a junction with Marcus Livius, and that they on their part must arm
                    many thousands, in order to cope with two Roman generals and two armies.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Gauls replied, that they had the
                    strongest possible inclination to this, but as the Romans had one army within
                    their borders, and another in the neighbouring country of Etruria, almost within
                    sight, if it should be known that they had supported the Carthaginians with
                    auxiliaries, those would immediately invade their territories on both sides with
                    determined hostility. They requested that he would ask of the Gauls such aids as
                    they could afford in a covert manner. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    purposes of the Ligurians, they said, were unrestrained, because the Roman
                    troops were at a distance from their lands and cities; that it was fair that
                    they should arm their youth and take upon themselves a portion of the war.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Ligurians did not dissent; they only
                    requested the space of two months to make their levies. Having <pb n="1239"
                        xml:id="p.1239"/> dismissed the Gauls, Mago in the mean time secretly hired
                    soldiers through their country. Provisions also of every description were sent
                    to him privately by the Gallic states. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Livius led his army of volunteer slaves out of Etruria into Gaul, and having
                    joined Lucretius, prepared to meet Mago in case he should move from Liguria
                    nearer to the city; but intending, if the Carthaginian should keep himself quiet
                    under the angle formed by the Alps, to remain himself also in the same quarter,
                    near Ariminum. for the protection of Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the return of Caius Laelius from Africa,
                    though Scipio was goaded on by the exhortations of Masinissa; and the soldiers,
                    on seeing the booty which was taken from the enemy's country landed from the
                    whole fleet, were inflamed with the strongest desire to cross over as soon as
                    possible; this important object was interrupted by one of minor consideration,
                    namely, that of regaining the town of Locri, which at the time of the general
                    defection of Italy had itself also gone over to the Carthaginians. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The hope of accomplishing this object beamed forth
                    from a very trifling circumstance. The war was carried on in Bruttium rather in
                    a predatory than a regular manner, the Numidians having set the example, and the
                    Bruttians falling in with that practice, not more in consequence of their
                    connexion with the Carthaginians, than from their natural inclination.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At last the Romans also, who now took
                    delight in plunder by a sort of infection, made excursions into the lands of
                    their enemies so far as their leaders would permit it. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Some Locrians who had gone out of the town were surrounded
                    by them and carried off to Rhegium. Among the number of the prisoners were
                    certain artisans, who, as it happened, had been accustomed to work for the
                    Carthaginians in the city of Locri for hire. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    They were recognised by some of the Locrian nobles, who having been driven out
                    by the opposite faction, which had delivered up Locri to Hannibal, had retired
                    to Rhegium; and having answered their other questions relative to what was going
                    on at home, questions which are usually put by such as have been long absent,
                    they gave them hopes that, if ransomed and sent back, they might be able to
                    deliver up the citadel to them; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> for there they
                    resided, and among the Carthaginians they enjoyed unlimited confidence.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Accordingly, as these nobles <pb n="1240"
                        xml:id="p.1240"/> were at once tormented with a longing for their country,
                    and inflamed with a desire to be revenged on their enemies, they immediately
                    ransomed the prisoners and sent them back, after having settled the plan of
                    operation, and agreed upon the signals which were to be given at a distance and
                    observed by them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They then went themselves to
                    Scipio to Syracuse, with whom some of the exiles were; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and having, by relating to him the promises made by the
                    prisoners, inspired the consul with hopes which seemed likely to be realized,
                    Marcus Sergius and Publius Matienus, military tribunes, were sent with them, and
                    ordered to lead three thousand soldiers from Rhegium to Locri. A letter was also
                    written to Quintus Pleminius, the proprietor, with directions that he should
                    assist in the business. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The troops, setting
                    out from Rhegium and carrying with them ladders to suit the alleged height of
                    the citadel, about midnight gave a signal to those who were to betray it from
                    the place agreed upon. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The latter were ready
                    and on the watch, and having themselves also lowered down ladders made for the
                    purpose, and received the Romans as they climbed up in several places at once,
                    an attack was made upon the Carthaginian sentinels, who were fast asleep, as
                    they were not afraid of any thing of the kind before any noise was made.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their dying groans were the first sound
                    that was heard; then, awaking from their sleep, a sudden consternation and
                    confusion followed, the cause of the alarm being unknown. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> At length, one rousing another, the fact became more
                    certain, and now every one shouted <quote>To arms</quote> with all his might;
                        <quote>that the enemy were in the citadel and the sentinels slain;</quote>
                    and the Romans, who were far inferior in numbers, would have been overpowered,
                    had not a shout raised by those who were outside of the citadel rendered it
                    uncertain whence the noise proceeded, while the terror of an alarm by night
                    magnified all fears, however groundless. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginians, therefore, terrified and supposing that the citadel was already
                    filled with the enemy, gave up all thoughts of opposition and fled to the other
                    citadel; for there were two at no great distance from each other. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> The townsmen held the city, which lay between the
                    two fortresses, as the prize of the victors. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Slight engagements took place daily from the two citadels. Quintus Pleminius
                    commanded the Roman, Hamilcar the Carthaginian garrison. They augmented their
                        <pb n="1241" xml:id="p.1241"/> forces by calling in aids from the
                    neighbouring places. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> At last Hannibal himself
                    came; nor would the Romans have held out, had not the general body of the
                    Locrians, exasperated by the pride and rapacity of the Carthaginians, leaned
                    towards the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Scipio received intelligence that the
                    posture of affairs at Locri had become more critical, and that Hannibal himself
                    was approaching, lest even the garrison might be exposed to danger; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> for it was not an easy matter for it to retire
                    thence; as soon as the direction of the tide in the strait had changed, he let
                    the ships drive with the tide from Messana, having left his brother, Lucius
                    Scipio, in command there. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal also sent a
                    messenger in advance from the river Butrotus, which is not far from the town of
                    Locri, to desire his party to attack the Romans and Locrians at break of day in
                    the most vigorous manner, while he on the opposite side assaulted the town,
                    which would be unprepared for such a measure, as every one would have his
                    attention occupied with the tumult created in the other quarter. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> But when, as soon as it was light, he found that the
                    battle had commenced, he was unwilling to shut himself up in the citadel, where,
                    by his numbers, he would crowd that confined place; nor had he brought with him
                    scaling-ladders to enable him to mount the walls. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Having, however, had the baggage thrown together in a heap,
                    and displayed his line at a distance from the walls to intimidate the enemy,
                    while the scaling-ladders and other requisites for an assault were preparing, he
                    rode round the city with some Numidian horsemen, in order to observe in what
                    quarter the attack might be best made. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having
                    advanced towards the rampart, the person who happened to stand next him was
                    struck by a weapon from a scorpion; and, terrified at an accident in which he
                    had been exposed to so much danger, he retired, gave directions for sounding a
                    retreat, and fortified a camp out of the reach of weapons. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman fleet from Messana came to Locri several hours
                    before night. The troops were all landed and had entered the city before
                    sun-set. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The following day the fight began
                    from the citadel on the part of the Carthaginians, and Hannibal, having now
                    prepared ladders and all the other requisites for an assault, was coming up to
                    the walls; when, throwing open the gate, the Romans suddenly sallied out <pb
                        n="1242" xml:id="p.1242"/> upon him, Hannibal fearing nothing less than such
                    a step. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They slew as many as two hundred in
                    the attack, having taken them by surprise. The rest Hannibal withdrew into the
                    camp when he found the consul was there; and having despatched a messenger to
                    those who were in the citadel, to desire them to take measures for their own
                    safety, he decamped by night. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Those who were
                    in the citadel also, after throwing fire upon the buildings they occupied, in
                    order that the alarm thus occasioned might detain their enemy, went away with a
                    speed which resembled flight, and overtook the body of their army before night. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, seeing that the citadel was abandoned
                    by the enemy, and their camp deserted, called the Locrians to an assembly and
                    rebuked them severely for their defection. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                    inflicted punishment on the persons principally concerned, and gave their
                    effects to the leaders of the other party, in consideration of their
                    extraordinary fidelity to the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As to
                    the Locrians in general, he said that he would neither grant them any thing, nor
                    take any thing from them. They might send ambassadors to Rome, and they should
                    experience that treatment which the senate thought proper to adopt. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Of one thing, however, he said he was confident,
                    which was, that although they had deserved ill at the hands of the Romans, they
                    would be better off when subject to them, though incensed against them, than
                    they had been when in the power of their friends the Carthaginians. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Leaving Quintus Pleminius lieutenant-general, and the
                    garrison which had taken the citadel to defend the city, the general himself
                    crossed over to Messana with the forces he had brought with him. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The Locrians had been treated with such insolence and
                    cruelty by the Carthaginians since their revolt from the Romans, that they were
                    able to endure severities of an ordinary kind not only with patience but almost
                    willingness. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But indeed, so greatly did
                    Pleminius surpass Hamilcar, who had commanded the garrison, so greatly did the
                    Roman soldiers in the garrison surpass the Carthaginians in villany and
                    rapacity, that it would appear that they endeavoured to outdo each other, not in
                    arms, but in vices. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> None of all those things
                    which render the power of a superior hateful to the powerless was omitted
                    towards the inhabitants, either by the general or his soldiers. The most
                    shocking insults were committed <pb n="1243" xml:id="p.1243"/> against their own
                    persons, their children, and their wives. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For
                    their rapacity did not abstain from the spoliation even of sacred things; and
                    not only were other temples violated, but even the treasures of Proserpine,
                    which had never been touched through all ages, excepting that they were said to
                    have been carried away by Pyrrhus, who restored the spoils, together with a
                    costly offering in expiation of his sacrilege. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Therefore, as on the former occasion, the royal ships, wrecked and shattered,
                    brought nothing safe to land, except the sacred money of the goddess, which they
                    were carrying away; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> so now also, that same
                    money, by a different kind of calamity, cast a spirit of madness upon all who
                    were contaminated by this violation of the temple, and turned them against each
                    other with the fury of enemies, general against general, and soldier against
                    soldier. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Pleminius had the chief command; that part of
                    the soldiers which he had brought with him from Rhegium were under his own
                    command, the rest were under the command of the tribunes. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> One of Pleminius's men, while running away with a silver
                    cup which he had stolen from the house of a townsman, the owners pursuing him,
                    happened to meet Sergius and Matienus, the military tribunes. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The cup having been taken away from him at the order of the
                    tribunes, abuse and clamour ensued, and at last a fight arose between the
                    soldiers of Pleminius and those of the tribunes; the numbers engaged and the
                    tumult increasing at the same time, as either party was joined by their friends
                    who happened to come up at the time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the
                    soldiers of Pleminius, who had been worsted, had run to him in crowds, not
                    without loud clamouring and indignant feelings, showing their blood and wounds,
                    and repeating the reproaches which had been heaped upon him during the dispute,
                    Pleminius, fired with resentment, flung himself out of his house, ordered the
                    tribunes to be summoned and stripped, and the rods to be brought out. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> During the time which was consumed in stripping them,
                    for they made resistance, and implored their men to aid them, on a sudden the
                    soldiers, flushed with their recent victory, ran together from every quarter, as
                    if there had been a shout to arms against enemies; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and when they saw the bodies of their tribunes now mangled
                    with rods, then indeed, suddenly inflamed with much more ungovernable rage,
                    without respect, <pb n="1244" xml:id="p.1244"/> not only for the dignity of
                    their commander, but of humanity, they made an attack upon the
                    lieutenant-general, having first mutilated the lictors in a shocking manner;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> they then cruelly lacerated the
                    lieutenant-general himself, having cut him off from his party and hemmed him in,
                    and after mutilating his nose and ears left him almost lifeless. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Accounts of these occurrences arriving at Messana,
                    Scipio, a few days after, passing over to Locri in a ship with six banks of
                    oars, took cognizance of the cause of Pleminius and the tribunes. Having
                    acquitted Pleminius and left him in command of the same place, and pronounced
                    the tribunes guilty and thrown them into chains, that they might be sent to Rome
                    to the senate, he returned to Messana, and thence to Syracuse. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Pleminius, unable to restrain his resentment, for he
                    thought that the injury he had sustained had been treated negligently and too
                    lightly by Scipio, and that no one could form an estimate of the punishment
                    which ought to be inflicted in such a case, except the man who <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> had in his own person felt its atrocity, ordered
                    the tribunes to be dragged before him, and after lacerating them with every
                    punishment which the human body could endure, put them to death; and not
                    satisfied with the punishment inflicted on them while alive, cast them out
                    unburied. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The like cruelty he exercised
                    towards the Locrian nobles, whom he heard had gone to Scipio to complain of the
                    injuries he had done them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The horrid acts,
                    prompted by lust and rapacity, which he had before perpetrated upon his allies,
                    he now multiplied from resentment; thus bringing infamy and odium, not only upon
                    himself, but upon the general also. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The time of the elections was now drawing
                    near, when a letter from the consul Publius Licinius arrived at Rome, stating
                    that <quote> he himself and his army were afflicted with a severe sickness, nor
                        could they have stood their ground had not the malady attacked the enemy
                        with the same or even greater violence. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Therefore, as he could not come himself to the election, he would, with the
                        approbation of the senate, nominate Quintus Caecilius Metellus dictator, for
                        the purpose of holding the election. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That
                        it was for the interest of the state that the army of Quintus Caecilius
                        should be disbanded; for that it could not be made any use of under present
                        circumstances, for Hannibal had now withdrawn his troops into <pb n="1245"
                            xml:id="p.1245"/> winter quarters; and so violent was the malady which
                        had infected that camp, that unless it was speedily broken up, there would
                        not survive one man out of the whole army. </quote> The senate left it to
                    the consul to settle these matters, as he should deem consistent with the
                    interest of the state and his own honour. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    state was at this time suddenly occupied with a question of a religious nature,
                    in consequence of the discovery of a prediction in the Sibylline books, which
                    had been inspected on account of there having been so many showers of stones
                    this year. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It ran thus: <quote> Whensoever a
                        foreign enemy should bring war into the land of Italy, he may be driven out
                        of Italy and conquered, if the Idaean Mother should be brought from Pessinus
                        to Rome. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This prophecy, discovered by the decemviri,
                    produced the greater impression upon the senate, because ambassadors also, who
                    had carried a present to Delphi, had brought word back, that they had both
                    obtained a favourable appearance in sacrificing to the Pythian Apollo, and that
                    a response was delivered from the oracle, to the effect, that a much greater
                    victory than that from the spoils of which they now brought presents, awaited
                    the Roman people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They considered the
                    presentiment which existed in the mind of Publius Scipio, with regard to the
                    termination of the war, when he claimed Africa as his province, as corroborating
                    the same anticipation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In order, therefore,
                    that they might the more speedily put themselves in possession of victory, which
                    was portended to them by the fates, omens, and oracles, they began to think what
                    method could be adopted for conveying the goddess to Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As yet the Roman people had none of the states
                    of Asia in alliance with them. Recollecting, however, that formerly Aesculapius,
                    on account of a sickness among the people, was fetched from Greece, which was
                    not then united with them by any treaty; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    recollecting, also, that a friendship had already commenced between them and
                    king Attalus, on <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> account of the war which
                    they waged in common against Philip, and that he would do whatever he could to
                    oblige the Roman people, they resolved to send, as ambassadors to him, Marcus
                    Valerius Laevinus, who had been twice consul, and had carried on operations in
                    Greece; Marcus Caecilius Metellus, who had been praetor; Servius Sulpicius
                    Galba, who had been aedile; and two who had been quaestors, Caius Tremellius <pb
                        n="1246" xml:id="p.1246"/> Flaccus and Marcus Valerius Falto. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> To these five quinqueremes were assigned, in order
                    that, in a manner suitable to the dignity of the Roman people, they might visit
                    those lands where it was important to gain respect for the Roman name.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The ambassadors, on their way to Asia,
                    having landed at Delphi, immediately approached the oracle, inquiring what hopes
                    the deity held out to themselves and the Roman people, of accomplishing the
                    business for which they had been sent from home. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> It is said that the answer given was, <quote> that they would obtain what
                        they were seeking by means of king Attalus. When they had conveyed the
                        goddess to Rome, they must take care that the best man at Rome should
                        receive her to his hospitality. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They came to Pergamus to the king, who
                    received the ambassadors graciously, and conducted them to Pessinus in Phrygia,
                    and putting into their hands a sacred <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> stone,
                    which the inhabitants said was the mother of the gods, bid them convey it to
                    Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius Falto, who was sent in
                    advance, brought word that the goddess was on her way, and that the most
                    virtuous man in the state must be sought out, who might in due form receive and
                    entertain her. Quintus Caecilius Metellus was nominated dictator for holding the
                    elections, by the consul in Bruttium, and his army was disbanded. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Lucius Veturius Philo was made master of the horse.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The elections were held by the dictator;
                    the consuls elected were Marcus Cornelius Cethegus and Publius Sempronius
                    Tuditanus, who was absent, being engaged in his province of Greece. The praetors
                    were then elected: Titus Claudius Nero, Marcus Marcius Ralla, Lucius Scribonius
                    Libo, Marcus Pomponius Matho. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On the
                    conclusion of the elections, the dictator abdicated his office. The Roman games
                    were repeated thrice, the plebeian seven times. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> The curule aediles were Cneius and Lucius Cornelius Lentulus: Lucius had the
                    province of Spain; he was elected in his absence, and was absent while he filled
                    the office. The plebeian aediles were Titus Claudius Asellus and Marcus Junius
                    Pennus. Marcus Marcellus this year dedicated the temple of Virtue at the Porta
                    Capena, in the seventeenth year after it had been vowed by his father during his
                    first consulate at Clastidium in Gaul: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> also
                    Marcus Aemilius Regillus, flamen of Mars, died this year. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For the last two years the affairs of Greece
                    had been <pb n="1247" xml:id="p.1247"/> neglected. Accordingly, as the Aetolians
                    were deserted by the Romans, on whom alone they depended for assistance, Philip
                    compelled them to sue for and agree to a peace on whatever conditions he
                    pleased. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Had he not exerted himself to the
                    utmost in expediting this measure, he would have been overpowered, while engaged
                    in war with the Aetolians, by Publius Sempronius, the proconsul, who had been
                    sent to succeed Sulpicius in the command, with ten thousand infantry and a
                    thousand horse, together with thirty-five ships of war, a force of no small
                    importance to bring to the assistance of allies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Ere the peace was well concluded, news was brought to the king that the
                    Romans had arrived at Dyrrachium; that the Parthinians, and other bordering
                    nations, were up in arms on seeing hopes of effecting a change; and that
                    Dimallum was besieged. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans had turned
                    their efforts to that quarter instead of assisting the Aetolians, for which
                    purpose they had been sent, from resentment at the conduct of the Aetolians for
                    making peace with the king without their sanction, contrary to the league.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When Philip had received intelligence of
                    these events, lest any greater commotion should arise in the neighbouring
                    nations and states, he proceeded by forced marches to Apollonia, to which place
                    Sempronius had retired, having sent Laetorius, his lieutenant-general, with a
                    part of his forces and fifteen ships into Aetolia, to look into the state of
                    affairs, and, if he could, dissolve the peace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Philip laid waste the lands of the Apollonians, and, advancing his troops to the
                    tower, offered the Romans battle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But seeing
                    that they remained quiet, only defending the walls, and not having sufficient
                    confidence in his strength to assault the town, being desirous also of making
                    peace with the Romans if possible, as he had with the Aetolians, or at least a
                    truce, he withdrew into his own dominions, without further exciting their
                    animosity by a fresh contest. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During the same
                    time the Epirots, wearied by the long continuance of the war, having first
                    sounded the disposition of the Romans, sent ambassadors to Philip on the subject
                    of a common peace; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> affirming that they were
                    well satisfied that it might be arranged if he would come to a conference with
                    Publius Sempronius, the Roman general. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They
                    easily prevailed on him to pass into Epirus, for neither were the king's own
                    inclinations averse from this measure. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Phnice is a <pb n="1248" xml:id="p.1248"/> city of Epirus; here Philip first
                    conferred with Aeropus Dardas and Philip, praetors of the Epirots, and
                    afterwards met Publius Sempronius. Amynander, king of the Athamanians, and other
                    magistrates of the Epirots and Acarnanians, were present at the conference.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The praetor Philip spoke first, and
                    requested at once of the king and the Roman general, that they would put an end
                    to the war, and grant this boon to the Epirots. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> Publius Sempronius proposed as the conditions of the peace, that the
                    Parthinians, and Dimallum, and Bargulum, and Eugenium, should be under the
                    dominion of the Romans; that Atintania, if on sending ambassadors to Rome they
                    could prevail upon the senate to acquiesce, should be added to the dominions of
                    the Macedonian. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The peace having been agreed
                    upon on these terms, Prusias king of Bithynia, the Achaeans, the Botians, the
                    Thessalians, the Acarnanians, and the Epirots, were included in the treaty by
                    the king; by the Romans, the Ilians, king Attalus, Pleuratus, Nabis tyrant of
                    the Lacedaemonians, the Eleans, the Messenians, and Athenians. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> These conditions were committed to writing and sealed; and
                    a truce was agreed upon for two months, to allow time for ambassadors being sent
                    to Rome, that the people might order the peace upon these terms. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> All the tribes agreed in ordering it, because now
                    that the operations of the war were removed into Africa, they were desirous to
                    be relieved for the present from all other wars. The peace being concluded,
                    Publius Sempronius took his departure for Rome, to attend to the duties of his
                    consulship. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To Publius Sempronius and Marcus Cornelius,
                    the consuls in the fifteenth year of the Punic war, the provinces assigned were,
                    to Cornelius, Etruria, with the old army; to Sempronius, Bruttium, with
                    directions to levy fresh legions. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of the
                    praetors, to Marcus Marcius fell the city jurisdiction; to Lucius Scribonius
                    Libo, the foreign, together with Gaul; to Marcus Pomponius Matho, Sicily; to
                    Titus Claudius Nero, Sardinia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Publius Scipio
                    was continued in command with the army and fleet which he had under him, as was
                    also Publius Licinius, with directions to occupy Bruttium with two legions, so
                    long as the consul should deem it for the advantage of the state that he should
                    continue in the province ithw command. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Livius and Spurius Lucretius were <pb n="1249" xml:id="p.1249"/> also continued
                    in command, with the two legions with which they had protected Gaul against
                    Mago; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> also Cneius Octavius, with orders that,
                    after he had delivered up Sardinia and the legion to Titus Claudius, he should,
                    with forty ships of war, protect the sea-coast within such limits as the senate
                    should appoint. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To Marcus Pomponius, the
                    praetor in Sicily, the troops which had fought at Cannae, consisting of two
                    legions, were assigned. It was decreed, that Titus Quinctius and Caius Tubulus,
                    proprietors, should occupy, the former Tarentum, the latter Capua, as in the
                    former year, each having his old army. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With
                    respect to the command in Spain, it was submitted to the people to decide on the
                    two proconsuls to be sent into that province. All the tribes agreed in ordering
                    that the same persons, namely, Lucius Cornelius Lentulus and Lucius Manlius
                    Acidinus, should, as proconsuls, hold the command of those provinces as they had
                    the former year. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls set about making
                    the levies, both to raise new legions for Bruttium, and recruit the other
                    armies; for so were they directed by the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although Africa had not as yet been openly
                    declared a province, the senate keeping it a secret, I suppose, lest the
                    Carthaginians should get intelligence of it beforehand, nevertheless, the most
                    sanguine hopes were entertained in the city, that the enemy would be vanquished
                    that year in Africa, and that the termination of the Punic war was at hand.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This circumstance had filled the minds of
                    the people with superstitious notions, and they were strongly disposed to credit
                    and propagate accounts of prodigies, and for that reason more were reported.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was said, <quote> that two suns had
                        been seen; that it had become light for a time during the night; that at
                        Setia a meteor had been seen, extending from the east to the west; that at
                        Tarracina a gate, at Anagnia a gate and the wall in many places, had been
                        struck by lightning; that in the temple of Juno Sospita, at Lanuvium, a
                        noise had been heard, accompanied with a tremendous crash. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There was a supplication for one day for the
                    purpose of expiating these, and the nine days' sacred rite was celebrated on
                    account of a shower of stones. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In addition to
                    these cares, they had to deliberate about the reception of the Idaean Mother;
                    for besides that Marcus Valerius, one of the ambassadors who had come before the
                    rest, had brought word that she would be in Italy <pb n="1250" xml:id="p.1250"/>
                    forthwith, a recent account had arrived that she was at Tarracina. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The senate was occupied with the determination of a
                    matter of no small importance, namely, who was the most virtuous man in the
                    state. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Every one doubtless would wish for
                    himself the victory in this contest, rather than any office of command, or any
                    honours, which could be conferred by the suffrages either of the senate or the
                    people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Publius Scipio, son of Cneius who had
                    fallen in Spain, a youth not yet of the age to be quaestor, they adjudged to be
                    the best of the good men in the whole state. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Though I would willingly record it for the information of posterity, had the
                    writers who lived in the times nearest to those events mentioned by what virtues
                    of his they were induced to come to this determination, yet I will not obtrude
                    my own opinion, formed upon conjecture, relative to a matter buried in the
                    obscurity of antiquity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Publius Cornelius was
                    ordered to go to Ostia, attended by all the matrons, to meet the goddess; to
                    receive her from the ship himself, and, when landed, place her in the hands of
                    the matrons to convey her away. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After the
                    ship arrived at the mouth of the Tiber, Scipio, according to the directions
                    given him, sailed out into the open sea, and, receiving the goddess from the
                    priests, conveyed her to land. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The chief
                    matrons in the state received her, among whom the name of Claudia Quinta alone
                    is worthy of remark. Her fame, which, as it is recorded, was before that time
                    dubious, became, in consequence of her having assisted in so solemn a business,
                    illustrious for chastity among posterity. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    matrons, passing her from one to another in orderly succession, conveyed the
                    goddess into the temple of Victory, in the Palatium, on the day before the ides
                    of April, which was made a festival, while the whole city poured out to meet
                    her; and, placing censers before their doors, on the way by which she was
                    conveyed in procession, kindled frankincense, and prayed that she would enter
                    the city of Rome willingly and propitiously. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    The people in crowds carried presents to the goddess in the Palatium; a
                    lectisternium was celebrated, with games called the Megalesian. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the business of recruiting the legions in
                    the provinces was under consideration, it was suggested by certain senators that
                    now was the time, when, by the favour of the gods, their fears were removed, to
                    put a stop to certain <pb n="1251" xml:id="p.1251"/> things, however they might
                    have been tolerated in perilous circumstances. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The senators, being intent in expectation, subjoined, that the twelve Latin
                    colonies which had refused to furnish soldiers to the consuls, Quintus Fabius
                    and Quintus Fulvius, were enjoying, for now the sixth year, exemption from
                    military service, as though it had been granted to them as a mark of honour and
                    favour; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> while in the mean time their good and
                    dutiful allies, in return for their fidelity and obedience to the Roman people,
                    had been exhausted by continual levies every year. By these words the
                    recollection of the senate was renewed touching a matter which was now almost
                    obliterated, and their indignation equally excited. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, without allowing the consuls to lay any other
                    business before the senate in priority, they decreed, <quote> that the consuls
                        should summon to Rome the magistrates, and ten principal inhabitants, from
                        each of the colonies, Nepete, Sutrium, Ardea, Cales, Alba, Carseoli, Sora,
                        Suessa, Setia, Circeii, Narnia, and Interamna; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> for these were the colonies implicated in this affair;
                        and command them that each of those colonies should furnish double the
                        greatest number of foot soldiers which they had ever provided for the Roman
                        people since the enemy had been in Italy, and one hundred and twenty
                        horsemen each. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If any of them was unable
                        to make up that number of horsemen, that it should be allowed to furnish
                        three foot soldiers for every horseman deficient. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> That both the foot and horse soldiers should be chosen
                        from the wealthiest of the inhabitants, and should be sent out of Italy
                        wheresoever there was want of recruits. If any of them refused to comply, it
                        was their pleasure that the magistrates and ambassadors of such should be
                        detained; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and that, if they requested it,
                        they should not be allowed an audience of the senate till they had obeyed
                        these orders. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Moreover, that an annual tax
                        should be imposed upon them, and collected after the rate of one <hi
                            rend="italics">as</hi> for every thousand; and that a census should be
                        taken in those colonies, according to a formula appointed by the Roman
                        censors, which should be the same which was employed in the case of the
                        Roman people; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that a return should be
                        made at Rome by sworn censors of the colonies, before they retired from
                        their office. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The magistrates and principal men of these
                    colonies having been summoned to Rome, when the consuls imposed upon them the
                        <pb n="1252" xml:id="p.1252"/> contribution of men, and the management of
                    the tax, they vied with each other in making excuses, and remonstrating against
                    it. They said <quote> it was impossible that so large a number of men could be
                        raised. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That they could scarcely
                        accomplish it, if even the simple contribution only, according to the
                        established ratio, were required of them. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        They entreated and besought them that they might be allowed to appear before
                        the senate and deprecate their resolution. They had committed no crime for
                        which they deserved to be ruined; but, even if they were to be ruined,
                        neither their own crime nor the resentment of the Roman people could make
                        them furnish a greater number of soldiers than they had got. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The consuls, persisting, ordered the
                    ambassadors to remain at Rome, and the magistrates to go home to make the
                    levies; observing, that <quote> unless the amount of soldiers enjoined were
                        brought to Rome, no one would give them an audience of the senate. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> All hope of appearing before the senate, and
                    deprecating their decision, being then cut off, the levies were completed in the
                    twelve colonies without difficulty, as the number of their youth had increased
                    during their long exemption from service. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Another affair, likewise, which had been
                    passed over in silence for an almost equally long period, was laid before the
                    senate by Marcus Valerius Laevinus; who said, <quote> that equity required that
                        the monies which had been contributed by private individuals, when he and
                        Marcus Claudius were consuls, should now at length be repaid. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Nor ought any one to feel surprised that a case,
                        where the public faith was pledged, should have engaged his attention in an
                        especial manner; for, besides that the matter appertained, in some degree,
                        peculiarly to the consul of that year in which the money was contributed, he
                        was himself the author of the measure, as the treasury was drained, and the
                        people unable to pay the taxes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This suggestion was well received by the
                    senate, and, bidding the consuls to propose the question, they decreed, <quote>
                        that this money should be paid by three instalments; that the present
                        consuls should make the first payment immediately, and the third and fifth
                        consuls, from that time, the two remaining. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After this, all their other cares gave place
                    to one alone, when the sufferings of the Locrians, of which they had been
                    ignorant up to that day, were made known by the arrival of <pb n="1253"
                        xml:id="p.1253"/> their ambassadors. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor
                    was it the villany of Pleminius so much as the partiality or negligence of
                    Scipio in that affair, which excited the resentment of the people. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> While the consuls were sitting in the comitium, ten
                    ambassadors of the Locrians, covered with filth, and in mourning, and extending
                    branches of olive, the badges of suppliants, according to the Grecian custom,
                    prostrated themselves on the ground before the tribunal, with loud lamentations.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In answer to the inquiry of the consuls,
                    they said, <quote> that they were Locrians, who had suffered such things at the
                        hands of Pleminius the lieutenant-general, and the Roman soldiers, as the
                        Roman people would not wish even the Carthaginians to experience. They
                        requested that they would allow them to appear before the senate, and
                        complain of their sufferings. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An audience having been granted, the eldest of
                    them thus spoke: "I know, conscript fathers, that the importance you will attach
                    to the complaints we make before you must depend, in a very great degree, upon
                    your accurately knowing the manner in which Locri was betrayed to Hannibal, and
                    placed again under your dominion after the expulsion of his garrison. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Inasmuch as if the guilt of defection does not rest
                    upon the public, and it is made apparent that our restoration to your dominion
                    was effected, not only in concurrence with our wishes, but by our own
                    co-operation and valour, you will be the more indignant that such atrocious and
                    shameful injuries should have been inflicted upon good and faithful allies by
                    your lieutenant-general and soldiers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But I
                    think it proper that the subject of our changing sides, in both instances,
                    should be deferred to another time, on two accounts: <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> first, that it may be discussed in the presence of Publius
                    Scipio, who retook Locri, and who witnessed all our acts, both good and bad; and
                    secondly, because, whatever we are, we ought not to have suffered what we have.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> We cannot conceal, conscript fathers, that
                    when we had a Carthaginian garrison in our citadel we were exposed to many
                    sufferings, of a shocking and shameful kind, from Hamilcar, the captain of the
                    garrison, and the Numidians and Africans. But what are they compared with what
                    we endure this day? I request, conscript fathers, that you will hear without
                    offence what I am reluctant to mention. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All
                    mankind are now in a state of anxious suspense, whether they are to see you or
                    the Carthaginians lords <pb n="1254" xml:id="p.1254"/> of the world. If an
                    estimate is to be formed of the Roman and Carthaginian governments from what we
                    Locrians have suffered from the Carthaginians on the one hand, or on the other,
                    from what we are suffering, at the present time especially, from your garrison;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> there is no one who would not wish the
                    Carthaginians to be his masters rather than the Romans. And yet observe what are
                    the feelings which the Locrians have entertained towards you. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When we were suffering injuries of much less magnitude from
                    the Carthaginians, we fled for protection to your general; now we are suffering
                    more than hostile indignities from your garrison, we have carried our complaints
                    to no others than yourselves. Conscript fathers! either you will consider our
                    forlorn condition, or there is no other resource left us for which we can even
                    pray to the immortal gods. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Quintus Pleminius,
                    the lieutenant-general, was sent with a body of troops to recover Locri from the
                    Carthaginians, and was left there in command of the same as a garrison.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In this your lieutenant-general there is
                    neither any thing of a man, conscript fathers, but the figure and <milestone
                        n="11??" unit="section"/> outward appearance, (for the extremity of our
                    misery prompts me to speak freely,) nor of a Roman citizen, but the attire and
                    dress, and the sound of the Latin language. He is a pest and savage monster,
                    such as are fabled to have beset the strait by which we are separated from
                    Sicily, for the destruction of mariners. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And
                    yet if he had been content to be the only person to vent his villany, his
                        <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> lust, and rapacity upon your allies,
                    that one gulf, deep as it was, we would however have filled up by our patience.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But the case is, he has made every one of
                    your centurions and soldiers a Pleminius, so indiscriminately has he willed that
                    licentiousness and wickedness should be practised. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> All plunder, spoil, beat, wound, and slay; all defile
                    matrons, virgins, and free-born youths torn from the embraces of their parents.
                    Our city is captured daily, plundered daily. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Day and night, every place indiscriminately rings with the lamentations of women
                    and children, seized and carried away. Any one, acquainted with our sufferings,
                    might be astonished how it is that we are capable of bearing them, or that the
                    authors of them are not yet satiated with inflicting such enormous cruelties.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Neither am I able to go through with
                    them, nor is it worth your while to listen to the particulars of our sufferings.
                    I will embrace <pb n="1255" xml:id="p.1255"/> them all in a general description.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> I declare that there is not a house or a
                    man at Locri exempt from injury. I say that there cannot be found any species of
                    villany, lust, or rapacity which has not been exercised on every one capable of
                    being the object of them. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> It would be
                    difficult to determine in which case the city was visited with the more horrible
                    calamity, whether when it was captured by an enemy, or when a sanguinary tyrant
                    crushed it by violence and arms. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Every evil,
                    conscript fathers, which captured cities suffer, we have suffered, and do now as
                    much as ever suffer. All the enormities which the most cruel and savage tyrants
                    are wont to perpetrate upon their oppressed subjects, Pleminius has perpetrated
                    upon ourselves, our children, and our wives. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> There is one circumstance, however, in complaining of which particularly
                        we may be allowed to yield to our deeply-rooted sense of religion, and
                        indulge a hope that you will listen to it; and, if it shall seem good to
                        you, conscript fathers, free your state from the guilt of irreligious
                        conduct. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For we have seen with how great
                        solemnity you not only worship your own deities, but entertain even those of
                        foreign countries. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> We have a fane
                        dedicated to Proserpine, of the sanctity of which temple I imagine some
                        accounts must have reached you, during the war with Pyrrhus; <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> who, when sailing by Locri, on his return from
                        Sicily, among other horrid enormities which he committed against our state,
                        on account of our fidelity towards you, plundered also the treasures of
                        Proserpine, which had never been touched up to that day; and then, putting
                        the money on board his ships, proceeded on his journey himself by land.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> What, therefore, was the result,
                        conscript fathers? The next day his fleet was shattered by a most hideous
                        tempest, and all the ships which carried the sacred money were thrown on our
                        shores. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That most insolent king, convinced
                        by this so great disaster that there were gods, ordered all the money to be
                        collected and restored to the treasures of the goddess. However, he never
                        met with any success afterwards; but, after being driven out of Italy, he
                        died an ignoble and dishonourable death, having incautiously entered Argos
                        by night. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though your lieutenant-general
                        and military tribune had heard of these, and a thousand other circumstances,
                        which were related not for the purpose of creating increased reverence, but
                        frequently <pb n="1256" xml:id="p.1256"/> experienced by ourselves and our
                        ancestors, through the special interposition of the goddess, they had,
                        nevertheless, the audacity <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> to apply
                        their sacrilegious hands to those hallowed treasures, and pollute
                        themselves, their own families, and your soldiers, with the impious booty.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Through whom we implore you, conscript
                        fathers, by your honour, not to perform any thing in Italy or in Africa,
                        until you have expiated their guilty deed, lest they should atone for the
                        crime they have committed, not with their own blood only, but by some
                        disaster affecting their country. Although, even now, conscript fathers, the
                        resentment of the goddess does not tarry either towards your generals or
                        your soldiers. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Already have they several
                        times engaged each other in pitched battles, one party headed by Pleminius,
                        and the other by the two military tribunes. Never did they employ their
                        weapons with more fury against the Carthaginians than when encountering each
                        other; and they would have afforded Hannibal an opportunity of retaking
                        Locri, had not Scipio, whom we called in, come in time to prevent it.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But, by Hercules, is it that the
                        soldiers are impelled by frenzy, and that the influence of the goddess has
                        not shown itself in punishing the generals themselves? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Nay, herein her interposition was manifested in the
                        most conspicuous manner. The tribunes were beaten with rods by the
                        lieutenant-general. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then the
                        lieutenant-general, treacherously seized by the tribunes, besides being
                        mangled in every part of his body, had his nose and ears cut off, and was
                        left for dead. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then, recovering from his
                        wounds, he threw the tribunes into chains; beat them, tortured them with
                        every species of degrading punishment, and put them to death in a cruel
                        manner, forbidding them to be buried. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Such atonements has the goddess exacted from the despoilers of her temple;
                        nor will she cease to pursue them, with every species of vengeance, till the
                        sacred money shall have been replaced in the treasury. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Formerly, our ancestors, during a grievous war with the
                        Crotonians, because the temple was without the town, were desirous of
                        removing the money into it; but a voice was heard from the shrine, during
                        the night, commanding them to hold off their hands, for the goddess would
                        defend her own temple. As they were deterred, by religious awe, from
                        removing the treasures thence, they were desirous of surrounding the temple
                        with a wall. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The walls <pb n="1257"
                            xml:id="p.1257"/> were raised to a considerable height, when they
                        suddenly fell down in ruins. But, both now, and frequently on other
                        occasions, the goddess has either defended her own habitation and temple, or
                        has exacted heavy expiations from those who had violated it. Our injuries
                        she cannot avenge, nor can any but yourselves avenge them, conscript
                        fathers. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> To you, and to your honour, we
                        fly, as suppliants. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> It makes no
                        difference to us whether you suffer Locri to be subject to that
                        lieutenant-general and that garrison, or whether you deliver us up for
                        punishment to incensed Hannibal and the Carthaginians. We do not request
                        that you should at once believe us respecting one who is absent, and when
                        the cause has not been heard. Let him come; let him hear our charges in
                        person, and refute them himself. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> If there
                        is any enormity one man can commit against another which he has not
                        committed upon us, we do not refuse to suffer all the same cruelties over
                        again, if it is possible we can endure them, and let him be acquitted of all
                        guilt towards gods and men. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the ambassadors had thus spoken, and
                    Quintus Fabius had asked them whether they had carried those complaints to
                    Publius Scipio, they answered, <quote> that deputies were sent to him, but he
                        was occupied with the preparations for the war, and had either already
                        crossed over into Africa, or was about to do so within a few days.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That they had experienced how highly
                        the lieutenant-general was in favour with the general, when, after hearing
                        the cause between him and the tribunes, he threw the tribunes into chains,
                        while he left the lieutenant-general, who was equally or more guilty, in
                        possession of the same power as before. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The ambassadors, having been directed to
                    withdraw from the senate-house, not only Pleminius, but even Scipio, was
                    severely inveighed against by the principal men; but, above all, by Quintus
                    Fabius, who endeavoured to show, <quote> that he was born for the corruption of
                        military discipline. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was thus, </quote>
                    he said, <quote> that in Spain he almost lost more men in consequence of mutiny
                        than the war. That, after the manner of foreigners and kings, he indulged
                        the licentiousness of the soldiers, and then punished them with cruelty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then followed up his speech by a resolution
                    equally harsh: that <quote> it was his opinion, that Pleminius should be
                        conveyed to Rome in chains, and in chains plead his cause; and, if the
                        complaints of the Locrians were found- <pb n="1258" xml:id="p.1258"/> ed in
                        truth, that he should be put to death in prison, and his effects
                        confiscated. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That Publius Scipio should be
                        recalled, for having quitted his province without the permission of the
                        senate; and that the plebeian tribunes should be applied to, to propose to
                        the people the abrogation of his command. That the senate should reply to
                        the Locrians, when brought before them, that the injuries which they
                        complained of having received were neither approved of by the senate nor the
                        people of Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That they should be
                        acknowledged as worthy men, allies, and friends; that their children, their
                        wives, and whatsoever else had been taken from them, should be restored;
                        that the sum of money which had been taken from the treasures of Proserpine
                        should be collected, and twice the amount placed in the treasury. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> That an expiatory sacred rite should be
                        celebrated, first referring it to the college of pontiffs, to determine what
                        atonements should be made, to what gods, and with what victims, in
                        consequence of the sacred treasures' having been removed and violated.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That the soldiers at Locri should be
                        all transported into Sicily, and four cohorts of the allies of the Latin
                        confederacy taken to Locri for a garrison. </quote> The votes could not be
                    entirely collected that day in consequence of the warm feeling excited for and
                    against Scipio. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Besides the atrocious conduct
                    of Pleminius, and the calamities of the Locrians, much was said about the dress
                    of the general himself, as being not only not Roman, but even unsoldierlike.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was said, that <quote> he walked about
                        in the gymnasium in a cloak and slippers, and that he gave his time to light
                        books and the palaestra. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That his whole
                        staff were enjoying the delights which Syracuse afforded, with the same
                        indolence and effeminacy. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That Carthage
                        and Hannibal had dropped out of his memory; that the whole army, corrupted
                        by indulgence, like that at Sucro in Spain, or that now at Locri, was more
                        to be feared by its allies than by its enemies. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though these charges, partly true, and partly
                    containing a mixture of truth and falsehood, and therefore, probably, were urged
                    with vehemence; the opinion, however, of Quintus Metellus prevailed, who,
                    agreeing with Maximus on other points, differed from him in the case of Scipio.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>For how inconsistent would it be,</quote> said he, <quote> that the
                        person whom the state a little while ago selected as their general, though a
                        very young man, for the recovery of Spain; whom, after he had <pb n="1259"
                            xml:id="p.1259"/> taken Spain out of the hands of their enemies, they
                        elected their consul, for the purpose of putting an end to the Punic war;
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> whom they marked out with the most
                        confident anticipation as the person who would draw Hannibal out of Italy,
                        and subdue Africa; how inconsistent would it be, that this man, like another
                        Pleminius, condemned in a manner without a hearing, should suddenly be
                        recalled from his province! when the Locrians asserted that the wicked acts
                        which had been committed against them were done not even in the presence of
                        Scipio, and no other charge could be brought against him, than that he
                        spared the lieutenant-general, either from good nature or respect.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He thought it advisable, that Marcus
                        Pomponius the praetor, to whose lot the province of Sicily had fallen,
                        should go to his province within the next three days; that the consuls
                        should select out of the senate ten deputies, whomsoever they thought
                        proper, and send them with the praetor, together with two tribunes of the
                        people, and an aedile. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That the praetor,
                        assisted by this council, should take cognizance of the affair. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> If those acts of which the Locrians complained
                        were committed at the command or with the concurrence of Scipio, that they
                        should command him to quit the province. If Publius Scipio had already
                        crossed over into Africa, that the tribunes of the people and the aedile,
                        with two of the deputies, whom the praetor should judge most fit for it,
                        should proceed into Africa; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the tribunes
                        and the aedile to bring Scipio back from thence, and the deputies to take
                        the command of the army until a new general had come to it. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But if Marcus Pomponius and the ten deputies should
                        discover that those acts had been committed neither with the orders nor
                        concurrence of Publius Scipio, that Scipio should then remain with the army
                        and carry on the war as he had proposed. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A decree of the senate having passed to this
                    effect, application was made to the tribunes of the people to arrange among
                    themselves, or determine by lot, which two should go with the praetor and the
                    deputies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The advice of the college of
                    pontiffs was taken on the subject of the expiations to be made, on account of
                    the treasures in the temple of Proserpine, at Locri, having been touched,
                    violated, and carried out of it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The tribunes
                    of the people, who went with the praetor and ten deputies, were Marcus Claudius
                    Marcellus and Marcus Cincius Alimentus. To these a plebeian aedile <pb n="1260"
                        xml:id="p.1260"/> was given, whom, if Scipio, whether he was still in Sicily
                    or had now crossed over into Africa, should refuse to obey the orders of the
                    praetor, the tribunes might direct to apprehend him, and bring him home in right
                    of their most sacred authority. The plan was, to go to Locri before they went to
                    Messana. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With regard to Pleminius, there are two
                    different accounts. Some relate that, having heard what measures had been
                    adopted at Rome, as he was going into exile to Naples, he accidentally fell in
                    with Quintus Metellus, one of the deputies, by whom he was forcibly conveyed
                    back to Rhegium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Others say, that Scipio
                    himself sent a lieutenant-general with thirty of the most distinguished of the
                    cavalry to throw Quintus Pleminius into chains, and with him the principal
                    movers of the mutiny. All these, whether by the orders of Scipio before, or of
                    the praetor now, were delivered over to the Rhegians to be kept in custody.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The praetor and the deputies, going to
                    Locri, gave their attention first to the affair relating to religion, agreeably
                    to their instructions; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> for, collecting all the
                    sacred money, whether in the possession of Pleminius or the soldiers, they
                    replaced it in the treasury, together with that which they had brought with
                    them, and performed an expiatory sacred rite. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The praetor then, summoning the soldiers to an assembly, ordered them to march
                    out of the city, and pitched a camp in the plain, issuing an edict which
                    threatened severe punishment to any soldier who either had remained behind in
                    the city, or had carried out with him what did not belong to him. He gave
                    permission to the Locrians to seize whatever each of them identified as his
                    property, and demand restitution to be made of any thing which was concealed.
                    Above all, he was resolved that the free persons should be restored to the
                    Locrians without delay. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the man who did
                    not restore them should be visited with no light punishment. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He then held an assembly of the Locrians, and told them,
                    that <quote> the people and senate of Rome restored to them their liberty and
                        their laws. That if any one was desirous of bringing charges against
                        Pleminius, or any one else, he should follow them to Rhegium. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> If they were desirous of complaining, in the name
                        of their state, of Publius Scipio, as having ordered and approved of the
                        nefarious acts which had been committed at Locri against gods and men, that
                        they should send deputies to Messana, where, with the assistance <pb
                            n="1261" xml:id="p.1261"/> of his council, he would hear them. </quote>
                    The Locrians returned thanks to the praetor and deputies, and to the senate and
                    people of Rome, and said that they would go and bring their charge against
                    Pleminius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That Scipio, though he had evinced
                    too little sympathy in the injuries inflicted on their state, was such a man as
                    they would rather have their friend than their enemy; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> that they were convinced that the many and horrid acts
                    which had been committed were done neither by the orders nor with the approval
                    of Publius Scipio; that he had either placed too much confidence in Pleminius,
                    or too little in them; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that the natural
                    disposition of some men was such, that they rather were unwilling that crimes
                    should be committed, than had sufficient resolution to punish them when
                    committed. Both the praetor and his council were relieved from a burden of no
                    ordinary weight in not having to take cognizance of charges against Scipio.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Pleminius, and as many as thirty-two
                    persons with him, they condemned and sent in chains to Rome. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> They then proceeded to Scipio, that they might carry to
                    Rome a statement attested by their own observation relative to the facts which
                    had been so generally talked of, concerning the dress and indolent habits of the
                    general, and the relaxation of military discipline. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While they were on their way to Syracuse,
                    Scipio prepared to clear himself, not by words but facts. He ordered all his
                    troops to assemble there, and the fleet to be got in readiness, as though a
                    battle had been to be fought that day with the Carthaginians, by sea and land.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the day of their arrival he entertained
                    them hospitably, and on the next day presented to their view his land and naval
                    forces, not only drawn up in order, but the former performing evolutions, while
                    the fleet in the harbour itself also exhibited a mock naval fight. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The praetor and the deputies were then conducted
                    round to view the armouries, the granaries, and other preparations for the war.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And so great was the admiration excited in
                    them of each particular, and of the whole together, that they firmly believed,
                    that under the conduct of that general, and with that army, the Carthaginians
                    would be vanquished, or by none other. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                    bid him, with the blessing of the gods, cross over, and, as soon as possible,
                    realize to the Roman people the hopes they conceived on that day when all the
                    centuries concurred in naming him first consul. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Thus <pb n="1262" xml:id="p.1262"/> they set out on their return in the
                    highest spirits, as though they were about to carry to Rome tidings of a
                    victory, and not of a grand preparation for war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Pleminius, and those who were implicated in the same guilt with him, when
                    they arrived at Rome, were thrown immediately into prison. At first, when
                    brought before the people by the tribunes, they found no place in their
                    compassion, as their minds were previously engrossed by the sufferings of the
                    Locrians; but afterwards, being repeatedly brought before them, and the hatred
                    with which they were regarded subsiding, their resentment was softened.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Besides, the mutilated appearance of
                    Pleminius, and their recollections of the absent Scipio, operated in gaining
                    them favour with the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Pleminius,
                    however, died in prison, before the people had come to a determination
                    respecting him. Clodius Licinius, in the third book of his Roman history,
                    relates, that this Pleminius, during the celebration of the votive games, which
                    Africanus, in his second consulate, exhibited at Rome, made an attempt, by means
                    of certain persons whom he had corrupted by bribes, to set fire to the city in
                    several places, that he might have an opportunity of breaking out of prison, and
                    making his escape; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that afterwards, the
                    wicked plot having been discovered, he was consigned to the Tullian dungeon,
                    according to a decree of the senate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The case
                    of Scipio was considered no where but in the senate; where all the deputies and
                    tribunes, bestowing the highest commendations on the fleet, the army, and the
                    general, induced the senate to vote that he should cross over into Africa as
                    soon as possible; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and that permission should
                    be given him to select himself, out of those armies which were in Sicily, those
                    forces which he would carry with him into Africa, and those which he would leave
                    for the protection of the province. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the Romans were thus employed, the
                    Carthaginians, on their part, though they had passed an anxious winter,
                    earnestly inquiring what was going on, and terrified at the arrival of every
                    messenger, with watch-towers placed on every promontory, <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> had gained a point of no small importance for the defence
                    of Africa, in adding to their allies king Syphax, in reliance on whom chiefly
                    they believed the Romans would cross over into Africa. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, not only formed a connexion of
                    hospitality with the before-named <pb n="1263" xml:id="p.1263"/> king, when
                    Scipio and Hasdrubal happened to come to him at the same time out of Spain, but
                    mention had also been slightly made of an affinity to take place between them,
                    by the king's marrying the daughter of Hasdrubal. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, who had gone for the purpose of completing this
                    business, and fixing a time for the nuptials, for the virgin was now
                    marriageable, perceiving that the king was inflamed with desire, for the
                    Numidians are, beyond all the other barbarians, violently addicted to love, sent
                    for the virgin from Carthage, and hastened the nuptials. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Among the other proofs of joy felt upon the occasion, and
                    in order that a public connexion might be added to this private one, an oath was
                    taken in confirmation of an alliance between the Carthaginian people and the
                    king, and faith reciprocally pledged that they would have the same friends and
                    enemies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But Hasdrubal, recollecting both the
                    alliance which had been entered into by the king and Scipio, and how inconstant
                    and changeable were the minds of the barbarians, was afraid that, if Scipio were
                    to invade Africa, that marriage would prove but a slight bond of union, he
                    therefore took advantage of the Numidian while under the influence of the first
                    transports of love, and calling to his aid the caresses of the bride, prevailed
                    upon him to send ambassadors into Sicily to Scipio, and by them to warn him "not
                    to <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> cross over into Africa in reliance upon
                    his former promises. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That he was united to the
                    Carthaginians both by a marriage with a Carthaginian citizen, the daughter of
                    Hasdrubal, whom he saw entertained at his house, and likewise by a public
                    treaty. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That his first wish was that the
                    Romans would carry on the war with the Carthaginians at a distance from Africa,
                    as they had hitherto done, lest he should be compelled to interfere with their
                    disputes, and join one of the two contending parties, renouncing his alliance
                    with the other. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If Scipio should not keep
                    away from Africa, and should advance his army to Carthage, it would be incumbent
                    upon him to fight for the land of Africa, which gave him birth, and for the
                    country of his spouse, for her parent, and household gods. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassadors, sent to Scipio by the king
                    with these instructions, met him at Syracuse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio, though disappointed in an affair which was of the greatest importance
                    with regard to his operations in Africa, and in the sanguine expectations he had
                    formed from it, sent the ambassadors back <pb n="1264" xml:id="p.1264"/> into
                    Africa speedily, before their business was made <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> known, giving them letters for the king, in which he warned
                    him over and over again <quote> not to violate the laws of hospitality which
                        bound them together; the obligation of the alliance entered into with the
                        Roman people; nor make light of justice, honour, their right hands pledged,
                        and the gods the witnesses and arbitrators of compacts. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But, as the coming of the Numidians could not
                    be concealed, for they lounged about the city, and had frequently appeared at
                    the pavilion; and as, if nothing were said about the object of their visit,
                    there was danger lest the truth, from the very circumstance of its being made a
                    secret, should spontaneously spread the more; and, in consequence, the troops
                    become alarmed lest they should have to wage war at once with the king and the
                    Carthaginians, Scipio endeavoured to divert their attention from the truth by
                    preoccupying their minds with false information; and, summoning his soldiers to
                    an assembly, said, <quote> that it was not expedient to delay any longer.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That the kings, their allies, urged
                        them to cross over into Africa with all speed. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That Masinissa himself had before come to Lalius,
                        complaining that time was consumed in delays, and that now Syphax sent
                        ambassadors, expressing his astonishment on the same account, namely, what
                        could be the cause of such long delay; and requesting either that the army
                        would now at length be transported into Africa, or, if the plan was changed,
                        that he might be informed so that he might himself take measures for the
                        safety of himself and his dominions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Therefore, as every thing was now ready and prepared, and as the business
                        admitted of no further delay, he was resolved, after having removed the
                        fleet to Lilybaeum, and collected here all his forces of foot and horse,
                        with the blessing of the gods to pass over into Africa the first day the
                        ships could sail. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He sent a letter to Marcus Pomponius,
                    directing him, if he thought proper, to come to Lilybaeum, that they might
                    consult together as to what legions, in preference to any others, and how large
                    a number of soldiers, they should convey into Africa; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> he also sent round to every part of the sea-coast, with
                    directions that all the ships of burthen should be seized and collected at
                    Lilybaeum. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When all the soldiers and ships in
                    Sicily were assembled at Lilybaeum, and neither the city could contain the
                    multitude of men, nor the harbour the ships, so ardent was the desire possessed
                    by all of passing over to Africa, that they <pb n="1265" xml:id="p.1265"/> did
                    not appear as if going to wage war, but to reap the certain rewards of victory.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Particularly those who remained of the
                    soldiers who had fought at Cannae felt convinced that under Scipio, and no other
                    general, they would be enabled, by exerting themselves in the cause of the
                    state, to put an end to their ignominious service. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio was very far from feeling contempt for that
                    description of soldiers, inasmuch as he knew that the defeat sustained at Cannae
                    was not attributable to their cowardice, and that there were no soldiers in the
                    Roman army who had served so long, or were so experienced not only in the
                    various kinds of battles, but in assaulting towns also. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The legions which had fought at Cannae were the fifth and
                    sixth. After declaring that he would take these with him into Africa, he
                    inspected them man by man; and leaving those whom he considered unfit for
                    service, he substituted for them those whom he had brought from Sicily, filling
                    up those legions so that each might contain six thousand two hundred infantry
                    and three hundred horse. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The horse and foot
                    of the allies. of the Latin confederacy, he also chose out of the army of
                    Cannae. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There is a wide difference among historians as
                    to the number of men transported into Africa. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    In some I find ten thousand infantry and two hundred horse; in others, sixteen
                    thousand infantry and sixteen hundred horse. In others, again, I find it stated
                    that thirty-five thousand infantry and cavalry were put on board the fleet,
                    making the number more than one half greater. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Some have not added an account of the number; among whom, as the matter is
                    doubtful, I should rather have myself ranked. Caelius, though he abstains from
                    specifying the number, increases the impression of their multitude indefinitely.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He says, that birds fell to the ground
                    from the shout of the soldiers, and that so great a multitude went on board the
                    fleet, that it seemed as if there was not a man left in Italy or Sicily. Scipio
                    took upon himself the care of seeing that the soldiers embarked orderly and
                    without confusion. The seamen, who were made to embark first, Caius Laelius, the
                    admiral of the fleet, kept in order on board the ships. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The task of the putting on board the provisions was
                    assigned to Marcus Pomponius, the praetor. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Food for forty-five days, of which enough for fifteen was cooked, was put on
                    board. When they were all embarked, he sent boats round with directions that the
                    pilots <pb n="1266" xml:id="p.1266"/> and masters, with two soldiers from each
                    ship, should assemble in the forum to receive orders. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> After they had assembled, he first asked them whether they
                    had put on board water for the men and cattle, sufficient to last as many days
                    as the corn would. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they answered that
                    there was water on board sufficient for five and forty days' consumption, he
                    then charged the soldiers that, conducting <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    themselves submissively, and keeping quiet, they would not make any noise or
                    disturb the mariners in the execution of their duties. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> He informed them, that he himself and Lucius Scipio in the
                    right wing, with twenty ships of war, and Caius Laelius, admiral of the fleet,
                    together with Marcus Porcius Cato, who was then quaestor, with the same number
                    of ships of war in the left wing, would protect the transports. That the ships
                    of war should carry each a single light, the transports two each. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> That in the ship of the commander-in-chief there
                    would be three lights as a distinction by night. He desired the pilots to make
                    for Emporia, where the land is remarkably fertile; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and on that account the district abounds with plenty of
                    every thing, and the barbarous inhabitants are unwarlike, which is usually the
                    case where the soil is rich. It was supposed that they might, therefore, be
                    overpowered before assistance could be brought them from Carthage. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> After these commands were delivered, they were
                    ordered to return to their ships, and the next day, with the blessing of the
                    gods, on the signal being given, to set sail. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Many Roman fleets had set sail from Sicily,
                    and from that very harbour. But not only during this war, nor is that
                    surprising, (for most of the fleets went out for the purpose of getting
                    plunder,) but even in any former war, never did a fleet on setting out exhibit
                    so grand a spectacle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And yet, if the estimate
                    is to be formed with reference to the magnitude of the fleet, it must be owned
                    that two consuls with their armies had passed from thence before, and there were
                    almost as many ships of war in those fleets as the transports with which Scipio
                    was crossing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For, besides fifty men of war,
                    he conveyed his army over in four hundred transports. But what made the Romans
                    consider one war as <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> more formidable than the
                    other, the second than the first, was, that it was carried on in Italy, and that
                    so many armies had been destroyed, and their commanders slain. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The general, Scipio, also, who <pb n="1267" xml:id="p.1267"
                    /> enjoyed the highest degree of renown, partly from his brave achievements, and
                    partly from a peculiar felicity of fortune, which conducted him to the
                    acquisition of boundless glory, attracted extraordinary regard. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time, the very project of passing over into the
                    enemy's country, which had not been formed by any general before during that
                    war, had made him an object of admiration; for he had commonly declared, that he
                    passed over with the object of drawing Hannibal out of Italy, of removing the
                    seat of war into Africa, and terminating it there. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> A crowd of persons of every description had assembled in
                    the harbour to view the spectacle; not only the inhabitants of Lilybaeum, but
                    all the deputies from Sicily, who had come together out of compliment to witness
                    the departure of Scipio, and had followed Marcus Pomponius, the praetor of the
                    province. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Besides these, the legions which
                    were to be left in Sicily had come forth to do honour to their comrades on the
                    occasion; and not only did the fleet form a grand sight to those who viewed it
                    from the land, but the shore also, crowded as it was all around, afforded the
                    same to those who were sailing away. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as day appeared, silence having been
                    obtained by a herald, Scipio thus spoke from the ship of the commander-in-chief:
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Ye gods and goddesses who preside over the seas and lands, I pray and
                        entreat you, that whatever things have been, are now, or shall be performed
                        during my command, may turn out prosperously to myself, the state, and
                        commons of Rome, to the allies and the Latin confederacy, and to all who
                        follow my party and that of the Roman people, my command and auspices, by
                        land, by sea, and on rivers. That you would lend your favourable aid to all
                        those measures, and promote them happily. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        That you would bring these and me again to our homes, safe and unhurt;
                        victorious over our vanquished enemies, decorated with spoils, loaded with
                        booty, and triumphant. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That you would
                        grant us the opportunity of taking revenge upon our adversaries and foes,
                        and put it in the power of myself and the Roman people to make the
                        Carthaginian state feel those signal severities which they endeavoured to
                        inflict upon our state. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After these prayers, he threw the raw entrails
                    of a victim into the sea, according to custom, and, with the sound of a trumpet,
                    gave the signal for sailing. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Setting out with
                    a favourable wind, which blew <pb n="1268" xml:id="p.1268"/> pretty strong, they
                    were soon borne away out of sight of the land; and in the afternoon a mist came
                    over them, so that they could with difficulty prevent the ships from running
                    foul of each other. The wind abated when they got into the open sea. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The following night the same haziness prevailed; but
                    when the sun rose it was dispelled, and the wind blew stronger. They were now
                    within sight of land, and, not long after, the pilot observed to Scipio, that
                        <quote> Africa was not more than five miles off; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> that he could discern the promontory of Mercury, and
                        that if he gave orders to direct their course thither, the whole fleet would
                        presently be in harbour. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio, when the land was in sight, after
                    praying that his seeing Africa might be for the good of the state and himself,
                    gave orders to make for another place of landing, lower down. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> They were borne along by the same wind; but a mist, arising
                    nearly about the same time as on the preceding day, hid the land from them; and
                    the wind fell as the mist grew more dense. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Afterwards, the night coming on increased the confusion in every respect; they
                    therefore cast anchor, lest the ships should either run foul of each other, or
                    be driven on shore. At daybreak the wind, rising in the same quarter, dispelled
                    the mist and discovered the whole coast of Africa. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio asked what was the name of the nearest promontory,
                    and, on being told that it was called the cape of Pulcher, he observed,
                        <quote>the omen pleases me, direct your course to it.</quote> To this place
                    the fleet ran down, and all the troops were landed. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> I have adopted the accounts given by a great many Greek and
                    Latin authors, who state that the voyage was prosperous, and unattended with any
                    cause of alarm or confusion. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Caelius alone,
                    except that he does not state that the ships were sunk in the waves, says that
                    they were exposed to all the terrors of the heavens and the sea, and that at
                    last the fleet was driven by tempest from Africa to the island Aegimurus, from
                    which, with great difficulty, they got into the right course; <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> and that, the ships almost foundering, the soldiers,
                    without orders from their general, got into boats, just as if they had suffered
                    shipwreck, and escaped to land without arms, and in the utmost disorder. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The troops being landed, the Romans marked out
                    their camp on the nearest rising grounds. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By
                    this time, not only the parts bordering on the sea were filled with
                    consternation and alarm, first in consequence of the fleet being seen, and <pb
                        n="1269" xml:id="p.1269"/> afterwards from the bustle of landing, but they
                    had extended to the cities also. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For not only
                    multitudes of men, mixed with crowds of women and children, had filled up all
                    the roads in every direction, but the rustics also drove away their cattle
                    before them, so that you would say that Africa was being suddenly deserted.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the cities, indeed, they occasioned
                    much greater terror than they felt themselves. At Carthage, particularly, the
                    tumult was almost as great as if it had been captured. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> For since the time of Marcus Atilius Regulus and Lucius
                    Manlius, which was almost fifty years ago, the Carthaginians had seen no Roman
                    armament, with the exception of fleets sent for plundering, from which troops
                    had made descents upon the lands bordering on the sea, <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> and after carrying away every thing which chance threw in
                    their way, had always returned to their ships before their noise had collected
                    the peasantry. For this reason the hurry and consternation in the city was, on
                    the present occasion, the greater. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And, by
                    Hercules, they had neither an efficient army at home, nor a general, whom they
                    could oppose to their enemy. Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, was by far the first man
                    in their state in respect of birth, fame, opulence, and, at that time, also by
                    reason of an affinity with the king. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But they
                    recollected that he had been routed in several battles and driven out of Spain
                    by this very Scipio; and that therefore, as a general, he was no more a match
                    for the general of the enemy than their tumultuary army was for that of the
                    Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Therefore they shouted to arms, as if
                    Scipio were coming immediately to attack the city; the gates were hastily
                    closed, armed men placed upon the walls, guards and outposts stationed in
                    different places, and the following night was spent in watching. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The next day, five hundred horsemen, sent to the
                    coast to reconnoitre and interrupt the enemy while landing, fell in with the
                    advanced guards of the Romans; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for by this
                    time Scipio, having sent his fleet to Utica, had proceeded a short distance from
                    the sea, and occupied the nearest heights. He had also placed outposts of
                    cavalry in proper situations, and sent troops through the country to plunder. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These, engaging the body of Carthaginian
                    horse, slew a few of them in the fight, and the greater part of them as they
                    pursued them when they were flying; among whom was <pb n="1270" xml:id="p.1270"
                    /> Hanno, their captain, a young man of distinction. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio not only devastated the lands in the country round
                    him, but also took a very wealthy city of the Africans which lay nearest to him;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> where, besides other things which were
                    immediately put on board the transports and sent into Sicily, eight thousand
                    free persons and slaves were captured. But the most gratifying circumstance to
                    the Romans was, the arrival of Masinissa just at the commencement of their
                    operations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some say that he came with not
                    more than two hundred horse, but most authors say with a body of two thousand
                    cavalry. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But, as this man was by far the
                    greatest king of his age, and rendered most essential service to the Romans, it
                    seems worth while to digress a little, to give a full account of the great
                    vicissitudes of fortune he experienced in the loss and recovery of his father's
                    kingdom. While he was serving in Spain in the cause of the Carthaginians, his
                    father, named Gala, died. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The kingdom,
                    according to the custom of the Numidians, came to salces, the brother of the
                    late king, who was very aged. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Not long after,
                    salces also dying, the elder of his two sons, named Capusa, the other being
                    quite a boy, succeeded to his father's kingdom. But, as he occupied the throne
                    more by right of descent than from the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    esteem in which he was held among his countrymen, or the power he possessed,
                    there stood forth a person named Mezetulus, not unrelated by blood to the kings,
                    of a family which had always been hostile to them, and had continually contested
                    the right to the throne with those who then occupied it, with various success.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This man, having roused his countrymen to
                    arms, over whom he possessed a great influence, from the hatred felt towards the
                    kings, openly pitched his camp, and compelled the king to come into the field
                    and fight for the throne. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Capusa, with many
                    of his nobles, falling in the action, the whole nation of the Massylians came
                    under the dominion and rule of Mezetulus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He
                    abstained, however, from assuming the title of king; and, contenting himself
                    with the modest appellation of protector, gave the name of king to the boy
                    Lacumaces, a surviving branch of the royal stock. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> In the hope of an alliance with the Carthaginians, he
                    formed a matrimonial connexion with a noble Carthaginian lady, daughter of
                    Hannibal's sister, who had been lately married to the king salces; <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> and, sending ambassadors for that purpose, renewed
                    an old con- <pb n="1271" xml:id="p.1271"/> nexion of hospitality with Syphax,
                    taking all these measures with a view to obtain assistance against Masinissa. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Masinissa, hearing of the death of his uncle,
                    and afterwards that his cousin-german was slain, passed over out of Spain into
                    Mauritania. Bocchar was king of the Moors at that time. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Applying to him as a suppliant, he succeeded, by means of
                    the most humble entreaties, in obtaining from him four thousand Moors to escort
                    him on his march, since he could not procure his co-operation in the war.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> With these, after sending a messenger
                    before him to his own and his father's friends, he arrived on the frontiers of
                    the kingdom, when about five hundred Numidians came to join him. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Having, therefore, sent back the Moors to their king,
                    as had been agreed, though the numbers which joined him were much less than he
                    had anticipated, not being such as to inspire him <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> with sufficient confidence for so great an attempt, yet,
                    concluding that by action, and by making some effort, he should collect
                    sufficient strength to enable him to effect something, he threw himself in the
                    way of the young king Lacumaces, at Thapsus, as he was going to Syphax. The
                    troops which attended him having fled back to the town in consternation,
                    Masinissa took it at the first assault. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Of the
                    royal party, some who surrendered themselves he received, others he slew while
                    attempting resistance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The greater part, with
                    the young king himself, escaped during the confusion and came to Syphax, to whom
                    they intended to go at first. The fame of this success, in the commencement of
                    his operations, though of no great magnitude, brought the Numidians over to the
                    cause of Masinissa; and the veteran soldiers of Gala flocked to his standard
                    from all quarters, from the country and the towns, inviting the youth to come
                    and recover his paternal dominions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Mezetulus
                    had somewhat the advantage in the number of his soldiers, for he had himself
                    both the army with which he had conquered Capusa, and also some troops who had
                    submitted to him after the king was slain; and the young king Lacumaces had
                    brought him very large succours from Syphax. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Mezetulus had fifteen thousand infantry, and ten thousand cavalry. With these
                    Masinissa engaged in battle, though he had by no means so many horse or foot.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The valour, however, of the veteran
                    troops, and the skill of the general, who had been exercised in the war between
                    the Romans and Carthaginians, <pb n="1272" xml:id="p.1272"/> prevailed. The
                    young king, with the protector and a small body of Massylians, escaped into the
                    territories of the Carthaginians. Masinissa thus recovered his paternal
                    dominions; but, as he saw that there still remained a struggle considerably more
                    arduous with Syphax, he thought it advisable to come to a reconciliation with
                    his cousin-german. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Having, therefore, sent
                    persons to give the young king hopes, that if he put himself under the
                    protection of Masinissa, he would be held in the same honour by him as salces
                    had formerly been by Gala; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and to promise
                    Mezetulus, in addition to impunity, a faithful restitution of all his property;
                    as both of them preferred a moderate share of fortune at home to exile, he
                    brought <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> them over to his side,
                    notwithstanding the Carthaginians studiously exerted every means to prevent it. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened that Hasdrubal was with Syphax at
                    the time these things were taking place. He told the Numidian, who considered
                    that it could make very little difference to him whether the government of the
                    Massylians was in the hands of Lacumaces or Masinissa, that <quote> he was very
                        much mistaken if he supposed that Masinissa would be content with the same
                        power which his father Gala or his uncle salces enjoyed. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> That he possessed a much greater degree of spirit, and
                        a more enterprising turn of mind, than had ever existed in any one of that
                        race. That he had frequently, when in Spain, exhibited proofs to his allies,
                        as well as to his enemies, of such valour as was rarely found among men.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That both Syphax and the
                        Carthaginians, unless they smothered that rising flame, would soon find
                        themselves enveloped in a vast conflagration, when they could not help
                        themselves. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That as yet his strength was
                        feeble, and such as might easily be broken, while he was trying to keep
                        together a kingdom, which was not yet firmly cemented. </quote> By
                    continually urging and goading him on, he succeeded in inducing him to lead an
                    army to the frontiers of the Massylians, and to pitch his camp in a country for
                    which he had not only disputed verbally, but had fought battles with Gala, as
                    though it had been his own by uncontested right. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> He alleged, that <quote> if any one should attempt to dislodge him, which was
                        what he most wanted, he would have an opportunity of fighting; but, if the
                        ground were given up to him through fear, he must march into the heart of
                        the kingdom. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the Massylians would
                        either submit to his authority <pb n="1273" xml:id="p.1273"/> without a
                        contest, or would be inferior to him in arms. </quote> Syphax, impelled by
                    these arguments, made war on Masinissa, and, in the first engagement, routed and
                    put him to flight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Masinissa, with a few
                    horsemen, effected his escape from the field to a mountain called by the natives
                    Balbus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Several families, with their tents and
                    cattle, which form their wealth, followed the king; the rest of the Massylian
                    people submitted to Syphax. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The mountain,
                    which the exiles had seized, had plenty of grass and water; and, as it was well
                    adapted for feeding cattle, afforded an abundant supply of food for men who live
                    upon flesh and milk. From this place they infested all the surrounding country;
                    at first with nightly and clandestine incursions, but afterwards with open
                    depredations. The lands of the Carthaginians suffered the severest devastation,
                    because there was not only a greater quantity of booty there than among the
                    Numidians, but their plunder would be safer. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And now they did it with so much boldness and defiance, that, carrying their
                    booty down to the sea, they sold it to merchants, who brought their ships to
                    land for that very purpose; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> while a greater
                    number of Carthaginians were slain and made prisoners, than frequently happens
                    in a regular war. The Carthaginians complained bitterly of these occurrences to
                    Syphax, and urged him strongly to follow up this remnant of the war, though he
                    was himself highly incensed at them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But he
                    considered it hardly suitable to the dignity of a king to pursue a vagabond
                    robber through the mountains. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Bocchar, one of the king's generals, an
                    enterprising and active officer, was chosen for this service. Four thousand
                    infantry and two thousand cavalry were assigned him; and having been loaded with
                    promises of immense rewards if he brought back the head of Masinissa, or if,
                    which would be a source of incalculable joy, he took him alive; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> he unexpectedly attacked his party while dispersed and
                    carelessly employed, and after cutting off an immense quantity of cattle and men
                    from the troops which guarded them, drove Masinissa himself with a small body of
                    attendants to the summit of the mountain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On
                    this, considering the business as in a manner settled, he not only sent the
                    booty of cattle and the prisoners he had made to the king, but also sent back a
                    part of his forces, as being considerably more than were necessary to accomplish
                    what remained of the war; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and then pursuing
                    Maninissa, <pb n="1274" xml:id="p.1274"/> who had come down from the top of the
                    mountain with not more than five hundred foot and two hundred horse, shut him up
                    in a narrow valley, both the entrances of which he blocked up. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Here great slaughter was made of the Massylians. Masinissa,
                    with not more than fifty horsemen, disengaged himself from the defile by passing
                    through steep descents of the mountains, which were not known to his pursuers.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Bocchar, however, followed close upon him,
                    and overtaking him in the open plains near Clupea, so effectually surrounded
                    him, that he slew every one of his attendants except four horsemen. These,
                    together with Masinissa himself, who was wounded, he let slip, in a manner, out
                    of his hands during the confusion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    fugitives were in sight, and a body of horse, dispersed over the whole plain,
                    pursued the five horsemen of the enemy, some of them pushing off in an oblique
                    direction, in order to meet them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    fugitives met with a very broad river, into which they unhesitatingly plunged
                    their horses, as they were pressed by greater danger from behind, and carried
                    away by the current were borne along obliquely. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> Two of them having sunk in the rapid eddy in the sight of the enemy,
                    Masinissa himself was supposed to have perished; but he with the two remaining
                    had emerged among the bushes on the farther bank. Here Bocchar stopped his
                    pursuit, as he neither had courage to enter the river, nor believed that he now
                    had any one to pursue. Upon this he returned to the king, with the false account
                    of the death of Masinissa. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Messengers were
                    despatched to Carthage to convey this most joyful event, and all Africa rang
                    with the news of Masinissa's death; but the minds of men were variously affected
                    by it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Masinissa, while curing his wound by
                    the application of herbs, was supported for several days in a secret cave by
                    what the two horsemen procured by plunder. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As
                    soon as it was cicatrized, and he thought himself able to bear the motion, with
                    extraordinary resolution he set out to recover his kingdom; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> and collecting not more than forty horsemen during his
                    progress, when he arrived among the Massylians, where he now made himself known,
                    he produced such a sensation among them, both by reason of their former regard
                    for him, and also from the unhoped-for joy they experienced at seeing him safe
                    whom they supposed to have perished, that within a few days six thousand armed
                    foot and <pb n="1275" xml:id="p.1275"/> four thousand horse came and joined him;
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and now he not only was in possession of
                    his paternal dominions, but was also laying waste the lands of the states in
                    alliance with the Carthaginians, and the frontiers of the Massylians, the
                    dominions of Syphax. Then, having provoked Syphax to war, he took up a position
                    between Cirta and Hippo, on the tops of mountains which were conveniently
                    situated for all his purposes. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Syphax, considering this an affair of too
                    great importance to be managed by one of his generals, sent a part of his army
                    with his son Vermina, a youth, with orders to march his troops round and attack
                    the enemy in the rear, while he engaged their attention in front. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Vermina set out by night, as he was to fall upon the
                    enemy unawares; but Syphax decamped in the day-time and marched openly,
                    intending to fight a pitched battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When it
                    was thought that sufficient time had elapsed for those who were sent round to
                    have reached their destination, Syphax himself, relying upon his numbers and on
                    the ambuscade prepared on the enemy's rear, led his troops up the mountain which
                    lay before him, by a gentle acclivity which led towards the enemy. Masinissa,
                    relying chiefly on the great superiority he would have over his opponents in
                    respect of the ground, on his part also formed his troops. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The battle was furious, and for a long time doubtful;
                    Masinissa having the advantage in point of situation and the courage of his
                    troops, and Syphax in respect of his numbers, which were much the greater of the
                    two. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His numerous troops, which were divided,
                    some of them pressing upon the enemy in front, while others surrounded them on
                    the rear, gave Syphax a decisive victory; and, enclosed as they were in front
                    and rear, the enemy had not even a way to escape. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, all their troops, both horse and foot, were
                    slain and made prisoners, except about two hundred horsemen, which Masinissa
                    having collected round him in a compact body, and divided into three squadrons,
                    ordered to force their way through, first naming a place where they were to meet
                    after being separated in their flight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa himself escaped through the midst of the enemy's weapons in the
                    quarter to which he had directed his course; two of the squadrons were unable to
                    extricate themselves; one of them surrendered to the enemy through fear, the
                    other, making a more obstinate resistance, was overwhelmed with weapons and
                    annihilated. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Vermina followed Masinissa, <pb
                        n="1276" xml:id="p.1276"/> treading almost in his steps; but he eluded him
                    by continually turning out of one road into another, till at length he obliged
                    him, wearied with the hopeless task, to desist from the pursuit, and arrived at
                    the Lesser Syrtis with sixty horsemen. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Here,
                    in the country lying between the Carthaginian Emporia and the nation of the
                    Garamantians, he passed all the time till the coming of Caius Laelius and the
                    Roman fleet into Africa, with the proud consciousness of having made every
                    exertion to recover his paternal dominions. These are the circumstances which
                    incline me to the opinion, that afterwards also, when Masinissa came to Scipio,
                    he brought with him a smallish rather than a large body of cavalry to succour
                    him; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> for the large number would seem to suit
                    only with the condition of a reigning king, while the small number corresponds
                    with the circumstances of an exile. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians having lost a detachment of
                    cavalry, together with the commander, got together another body by means of a
                    new levy, and gave the command of it to Hanno, son of Hamilcar. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They frequently sent for Hasdrubal and Syphax by letters
                    and messengers, and lastly even by ambassadors, ordering Hasdrubal to bring
                    assistance to his almost besieged country, and imploring Syphax to bring relief
                    to Carthage, nay to all Africa. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At that time
                    Scipio had his camp about five miles from the city of Utica, having removed it
                    from the sea, where he had continued encamped for a few days near the fleet.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hanno, having received the body of horse,
                    which was far from being strong enough, not only to attack the enemy, but even
                    to protect the country from devastation, made it his first business to augment
                    the number of his cavalry by pressing; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and
                    though he did not despise the men of other nations, he enlisted principally from
                    the Numidians, who are by far the first horsemen in Africa. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He had now as many as four thousand horsemen, when he took
                    possession of a town named Salera, about fifteen miles from the Roman camp. When
                    Scipio was told of this, he said, <quote> What! cavalry lodging in houses during
                        the summer! <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Let them be even more in
                        number while they have such a leader. </quote> Concluding that the more
                    dilatory they were in their operations, the more active he ought to be, he sent
                    Masinissa forward with the cavalry, directing him to ride up to the gates of the
                    enemy and draw them out to battle; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and when
                    their whole force had poured out and pressed upon him with such <pb n="1277"
                        xml:id="p.1277"/> impetuosity in the contest that they could not easily be
                    withstood, then to retire by degrees, and he would himself come up and join in
                    the battle in time. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Waiting only till he
                    thought he had allowed sufficient time for the advanced party to draw out the
                    enemy, he followed with the Roman cavalry, proceeding without being seen, as he
                    was covered by some rising grounds, which lay very conveniently between him and
                    the enemy, round the windings of the road. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Masinissa, according to the plan laid down, at one time as if menacing the
                    enemy, at another as if he had been afraid, either rode up to the gates, or else
                    by retiring when his counterfeited fears had inspired them with courage, tempted
                    them to pursue him with inconsiderate ardour. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    They had not as yet all gone out, and the general was wearying himself with
                    various occupations, compelling some who were oppressed with sleep and wine to
                    take arms and bridle their horses, and preventing others from running out at all
                    the gates in scattered parties and in disorder, without keeping their ranks or
                    following their standards. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At first, those
                    who incautiously rushed out were overpowered by Masinissa; but then a greater
                    number pouring out of the gate at once in a dense body, placed the contest on an
                    equal footing; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and at last the whole of their
                    cavalry coming up and joining in the battle, they could now no longer be
                    withstood. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Masinissa, however, did not
                    receive their charge in hasty flight, but retired slowly, until he drew them to
                    the rising grounds which covered the Roman cavalry. The Roman cavalry then
                    rising up, their own strength unimpaired and their horses fresh, spread
                    themselves round Hanno and the Africans, fatigued 'with the fight and the
                    pursuit, and Masinissa, suddenly turning his horses round, came back to the
                    battle. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> About a thousand who formed the first
                    line and could not easily retreat, together with Hanno their general, were
                    surrounded and slain. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The victors pursuing
                    the rest through a space of three miles, as they fled with the most violent
                    haste, being terrified, principally on account of the death of their leader,
                    either took or slew as many as two thousand horsemen more. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> It appeared that there were not less than two hundred
                    Carthaginian horsemen among them, some of whom were distinguished by birth and
                    fortune. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened that the same day on which these
                    events <pb n="1278" xml:id="p.1278"/> occurred, the ships which had carried the
                    plunder to Sicily returned with provisions, as if divining that they came to
                    take another cargo of booty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> All the writers
                    do not vouch for the fact that two generals of the Carthaginians bearing the
                    same name were slain in the battles of the cavalry; fearing, I believe, lest the
                    same circumstance related twice should lead them into error. Caelius, indeed,
                    and Valerius, make mention of a Hanno also who was made prisoner. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio rewarded his officers and horsemen according
                    to the service they had respectively rendered, but he presented Masinissa above
                    all the rest with distinguished gifts. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Leaving
                    a strong garrison at Saleca, he set out with the rest of his army; and having
                    not only devastated the country wherever he marched, but taken some cities and
                    towns, thus spreading the terrors of war far and wide, he returned to his camp
                    on the seventh day after he set out, bringing with him an immense quantity of
                    men and cattle, and booty of every description, and sent away his ships again
                    loaded with the spoils of the enemy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then
                    giving up all expeditions of a minor kind, and predatory excursions, he directed
                    the <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> whole force of the war to the siege of
                    Utica, that he might make it for the time to come, if he took it, a position
                    from which he might set out for the execution of the rest of his designs.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At one and the same time his marines
                    attacked the city from the fleet in that part which is washed by the sea, and
                    the land forces were brought up from a rising ground which almost immediately
                    overhung the walls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He had also brought with
                    him engines and machines which had been conveyed from Sicily with the stores,
                    and fresh ones were made in the armoury, in which he had for that purpose
                    employed a number of artificers skilled in such works. The people of Utica, thus
                    beset on all sides with so formidable a force, placed all their hopes in the
                    Carthaginians, and the Carthaginians in the chance there was that Hasdrubal
                    could induce Syphax to take arms. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But all
                    their movements were made too slowly for the anxiety felt by those who were in
                    want of assistance. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, though he had
                    by levies, conducted with the utmost diligence, made up as many as thirty
                    thousand infantry and three thousand horse, yet dared not move nearer to the
                    enemy before the arrival of Syphax. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Syphax
                    came with fifty thousand foot and ten thousand horse, and, immediately <pb
                        n="1279" xml:id="p.1279"/> decamping from Carthage, took up a position not
                    far from Utica and the Roman works. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their
                    arrival produced, however, this effect, that Scipio, who had been besieging
                    Utica for forty days, during which he had tried every expedient without effect,
                    left the place without accomplishing his object; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> and as the winter was now fast approaching, fortified a
                    camp for the winter upon a promontory, which being attached to the continent by
                    a narrow isthmus, stretched out a considerable way into the sea. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> He included his naval camp also within one and the
                    same rampart. The camp for the legions being stationed on the middle of the
                    isthmus, the ships, which were drawn on land, and the mariners occupied the
                    northern shore, the cavalry a valley on the south inclining towards the other
                    shore. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Such were the transactions in Africa
                    up to the close of autumn. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Besides the corn collected from all parts of
                    the surrounding country by plunder, and the provisions imported from Italy and
                    Sicily, Cneius Octavius, propraetor, brought a vast quantity out of Sardinia
                    from Tiberius Claudius the praetor, whose province Sardinia was; and not only
                    were the granaries already built filled, but new ones were erected. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The army wanted clothing, and Octavius was instructed
                    to consult with the praetor in order to ascertain if any could be procured and
                    sent out of that province. This business was also diligently attended to. One
                    thousand two hundred gowns and twelve thousand tunics were in a short time sent.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> During the summer in which these
                    operations were carried on in Africa, Publius Sempronius, the consul, who had
                    the province of Bruttium, fought an irregular kind of battle with Hannibal in
                    the Crotonian territory while actually on march; <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> they fought with their troops drawn more in order of march than of battle.
                    The Romans were driven back, and as many as twelve hundred of the army of the
                    consul were slain in this affair, which was more a tumult than a battle.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They returned in confusion to their camp.
                    The enemy, however, dared not assault it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But,
                    during the silence of the following night, the consul marched away, and having
                    sent a messenger before him to Publius Licinius, the proconsul, to bring up his
                    legions, united his forces with his. Thus two generals and two armies returned
                    to Hannibal. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor did either party delay to
                    fight, as the forces of the consul were <pb n="1280" xml:id="p.1280"/> doubled,
                    and the Carthaginian was inspirited by recent victory. Sempronius led his
                    legions into the front line; those of Licinius were placed in reserve.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consul, in the beginning of the
                    battle, vowed a temple to Fortuna Primigenia if he routed the enemy that day,
                    and he obtained the object of that vow. The Carthaginians were routed and put to
                    flight; above four thousand armed men were slain, a little under three hundred
                    taken alive, with forty horses and eleven military standards. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal, dispirited by this adverse battle, led his troops
                    away to Croton. At the same time, in another part of Italy, Etruria, almost the
                    whole of which had espoused the interest of Mago, and had <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> conceived hopes of effecting a revolution through his
                    means, was kept in subjection by the consul Marcus Cornelius, not so much by the
                    force of his arms as the terror of his judicial proceedings. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> In the trials he had instituted there, in conformity with
                    the decree of the senate, he had shown the utmost impartiality; and many of the
                    Tuscan nobles, who had either themselves gone, or had sent others to Mago
                    respecting the revolt of their states, at first standing their trials, were
                    condemned; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but afterwards others, who, from a
                    consciousness of guilt, had gone into voluntary exile, were condemned in their
                    absence, and by thus withdrawing left their effects only, which were liable to
                    confiscation, as a pledge for their punishment. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the consuls were thus engaged in
                    different quarters, in the mean time, at Rome, the censors, Marcus Livius and
                    Caius Claudius, called over the senate roll. Quintus Fabius was again chosen
                    chief of the senate; seven were stigmatized, of whom there was not one who had
                    sat in the curule chair. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They inquired into
                    the business relating to the repair of public edifices with diligence and the
                    most scrupulous exactness. They set by contract the making of a road out of the
                    ox market to the temple of Venus, with public seats on each side of it, and a
                    temple to be built in the palatium for the great mother. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They established also a new tax out of the price of salt.
                    Salt, both at Rome, and throughout all Italy, was sold at the sixth part of an
                        <hi rend="italics">as.</hi> They contracted for the supply of it at Rome at
                    the same price, at a higher price in the country towns and markets, and at
                    different prices in different places. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They
                    felt well convinced that this tax was invented by one of the censors, out of
                    resentment to the people, <pb n="1281" xml:id="p.1281"/> because he had formerly
                    been condemned by an unjust sentence, and that in fixing the price of salt,
                    those tribes had been most burdened by whose means he had been condemned.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hence Livius derived the surname of
                    Salinator. The closing of the lustrum was later than usual, because the censors
                    sent persons through the provinces, that <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> a
                    report might be made of the number of Roman citizens in each of the armies.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Including these, the number of persons
                    returned in the census was two hundred and fourteen thousand. Caius Claudius
                    Nero closed the lustrum. They then received a census of the twelve colonies,
                    which had never been done before, the censors of the colonies themselves
                    presenting it, in order that there might appear registers among the public
                    records, stating the extent of their resources, both in respect of furnishing
                    soldiers and money. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The review of the knights
                    then began to be made, and it happened that both the censors had a horse at the
                    public expense. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they came to the Pollian
                    tribe, in which was the name of Marcus Livius, and the herald hesitated to cite
                    the censor himself, Nero said, <quote>Cite Marcus Livius;</quote> and whether it
                    was that he was actuated by the remains of an old enmity, or that he felt a
                    ridiculous pride in this ill-timed display of severity, he ordered Marcus Livius
                    to sell his horse, because he had been condemned by the sentence of the people.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In like manner, when they came to the
                    Narnian tribe, and the name of his colleague, Marcus Livius ordered Caius
                    Claudius to sell his horse, for two reasons; one, because he had given false
                    evidence against him; the other, because he had not been sincere in his
                    reconciliation with him. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thus a disgraceful
                    contest arose, in which each endeavoured to asperse the character of the other,
                    though not without detriment to his own. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On
                    the expiration of the office, when Caius Claudius had taken the oath respecting
                    the observance of the laws, and had gone up into the treasury, he gave the name
                    of his colleague among the names of those whom he left disfranchised. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Afterwards, Marcus Livius came into the treasury,
                    and excepting only the Maecian tribe, which had neither condemned him nor made
                    him consul or censor when condemned, left all the Roman people, four and thirty
                    tribes, disfranchised, because they had both condemned him when innocent, and
                    when condemned had made him consul and censor; <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> and therefore could not deny <pb n="1282" xml:id="p.1282"/> that they had
                    been guilty of a crime, either once in his condemnation, or twice at the
                    elections. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He said that the disfranchisement
                    of Caius Claudius would be included in that of the thirty-four tribes, but that
                    if he were in possession of a precedent for leaving the same person
                    disfranchised twice, he would have left his name particularly among the
                    disfranchised. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> This contest between censors,
                    endeavouring to brand each other, was highly improper, while the correction
                    applied to the inconstancy of the people was suitable to the office of a censor,
                    and worthy of the strict discipline of the times. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> As the censors were labouring under odium, Cneius Babius,
                    tribune of the people, thinking this a favourable opportunity of advancing
                    himself at their expense, summoned them both to trial before the people. This
                    proceeding was quashed by the unanimous voice of the senate, lest in future the
                    office of censor should become subject to the caprice of the people. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same summer Clampetia in Bruttium was
                    taken by the consul by storm. Consentia and Pandosia, with some other
                    inconsiderable states, submitted voluntarily. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    As the time for the elections was now drawing near, it was thought best that
                    Cornelius should be summoned to Rome from Etruria, as there was no war there.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He elected, as consuls, Cneius Servilius
                    Caepio and Caius Servilius Geminus. The election of praetors was then held.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The persons elected were, Publius
                    Cornelius Lentulus, Publius Quinctilius Varus, Publius Aelius Paetus, and
                    Publius Villius Tappulus. The last two were plebeian aediles when elected
                    praetors. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The elections finished, the consul
                    returned into Etruria to his army. The priests who died this year, and those who
                    were put in their places, were Tiberius Veturius Philo, flamen of Mars, elected
                    and <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> inaugurated in the room of Marcus
                    Aemilius Regillus, who died the year before: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    in the room of Marcus Pomponius Matho, augur and decemvir, were elected Marcus
                    Aurelius Cotta, decemvir, and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus, augur, being then a
                    very young man; an instance of very rare occurrence in the disposal of the
                    priests' offices in those times. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Golden
                    four-horsed chariots were placed this year in the Capitol by the curule aediles,
                    Caius Livius and Marcus Servilius Geminus. The Roman games were repeated during
                    two days. During two days also the plebeian games were repeated by the aediles,
                    Publius Aelius and Publius Villius. There was likewise a feast of Jupiter on
                    occasion of the games. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
