<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 28-30 - 29</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Moore" role="editor"> Frank Gardener Moore, Professor Emeritus in
                    Columbia University </editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XXVIII-XXX With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1949: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.207"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="book">
                <head>Book XXIX</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, now that he had reached Sicily,
                    assigned <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                    his volunteers to their ranks and centuries. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Three hundred of them, young men in the bloom of their youth and conspicuous for
                    their physical strength, he kept about him unarmed and ignorant of the purpose
                    for which they were being reserved without being organized in centuries or
                    furnished with arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then he chose out of the
                    number of the younger men of all Sicily three hundred horsemen, men of high rank
                    and of wealth, to cross over with him into Africa. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He appointed a day also on which they were to present
                    themselves equipped and furnished with horses and arms. Such service far from
                    home seemed to them formidable and likely to bring many hardships and great
                    dangers on land and sea. And concern on this account troubled not merely the men
                    themselves but also their parents and relations. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> When the day which had been appointed came the men displayed their arms and
                    horses. Then Scipio said reports were coming to him that some of the Sicilian
                    horsemen shrank from that service as formidable and difficult. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> If any were of that mind he preferred that they should
                    confess it to him at once, rather than complain later and prove spiritless
                    soldiers and useless for the state. Let them declare what was their mind; he
                    would give them a kindly hearing. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When one of
                    them ventured to say that <pb n="p.209"/> if he was free to choose whichever he
                    wished he did <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        205</note> not wish to serve at all, thereupon Scipio said to him:
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Accordingly, since you have not concealed what your mind is, young man,
                        I will furnish a substitute for you, and to him you shall hand over your
                        arms and horse and the other equipment for the service, and forthwith shall
                        take him away with you to your home, train him and see that he is taught
                        horsemanship and the use of arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As the man gladly accepted the terms Scipio
                    turned over to him one of the three hundred unarmed men that-he had. When the
                    others saw the horseman thus discharged with the consent of the commander, every
                    man excused himself and took a substitute. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Thus three hundred Sicilians were replaced by Roman horsemen without expense to
                    the state. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Of their training and drilling the
                    Sicilians were in charge, because the general's order was that any man who
                    failed to do so should himself serve. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A similar method of raising cavalry inexpensively was used by the Spartan
                        King Agesilāus in order to make war upon the Persian King's satrap
                        Tissaphernes near Ephesus, <date when="-0395">395 B.C.</date> ; Xenophon <hi
                            rend="italics">Hell.</hi> III. iv. 15; <hi rend="italics">Ages.</hi> I.
                        24; Plutarch <hi rend="italics">Ages. 9.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They say that this cavalry squadron proved
                    excellent and was of value to the state in many battles. </p>
                <p> Then while mustering the legions he chose out of them soldiers who had served
                    for the greatest number of campaigns, especially those who had done so under
                    Marcellus as commander, believing them to have been schooled by the best
                    training and in particular to be most skilled <milestone n="13??" unit="section"
                    /> in besieging cities in consequence of the long siege of Syracuse. For he was
                    planning nothing small, but already the destruction of Carthage. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Thereupon he distributed his army among the towns,
                    requisitioned grain from the Sicilian cities, spared the grain imported from <pb
                        n="p.211"/> Italy. He repaired the old ships, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> of the previous year at least; of. XXVIII. xlv.
                        8, where thirty war-ships are mentioned. </note> and with these <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> sent Gaius
                    Laelius to Africa for plunder. The new ships he beached at Panormus, that they
                    might winter out of the water, since they had been built in haste of green
                    timber. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Every preparation for the war having been
                    made, he came to Syracuse, which was not yet quite peaceful after the great
                    unsettlement due to the war. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The Greeks were
                    making their claims to properties granted them by the senate against certain
                    Italians who were holding on with the same use of force with which they had
                    seized the property during the war. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Evidently Laevinus' efforts to remedy abuses had not been altogether
                        successful (XXVI. xl. 1). Syracusans ( <hi rend="italics">Graeci</hi> ) had
                        often been unable to recover landed property still occupied and forcibly
                        held by Italians; of. <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> xxx. 10; xxxii. 6 (the
                        latter implying the senate's promise of compensation). </note>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Thinking it of the utmost importance to keep
                    a promise given by the state, Scipio restored their property to the Syracusans,
                    partly by <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> an edict, partly also by granting
                    hearings against those who persisted in maintaining an unlawful possession.
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> This act was acceptable not only to the
                    owners themselves but to all the communities of Sicily as well, and all the more
                    energetically did they render assistance for the war. </p>
                <p> In the same summer a great war broke out in Spain, instigated by Indibilis <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXVIII. xxiv ff. and note on xxiv.
                        3. Indibilis was prince of a north-eastern tribe, the Ilergetes; XXVI. xlix.
                        11; cf. XXVIII. xxvii. 5. </note> of the Ilergetes for no other reason than
                    because contempt for other generals sprang from admiration for Scipio.
                        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> He thought that Scipio was the one
                    general left to the Romans, the rest having been killed by Hannibal; that
                    consequently after the slaying of the Scipios they had no one else to send to
                    Spain, and had also, once the war grew more serious in Italy, summoned him to
                    face Hannibal; that, besides <pb n="p.213"/> having merely nominal commanders in
                    Spain, the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        205</note> Romans had taken away the veteran army also. <milestone n="21"
                        unit="section"/> There was nothing but confusion and an untrained mob of
                    recruits. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Never would there be such an
                    opportunity for the liberation of Spain. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Slaves they had been down to that time, either to Carthaginians or to Romans,
                    and not by turns to the one people or the other but at times to both at once.
                        <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians had been driven out by
                    the Romans; the Spaniards, if they should agree, were able to drive out the
                    Romans, so that, free from all foreign authority, Spain might return permanently
                    to its ancestral customs and usages. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> By these
                    and similar utterances he stirred up not only his own countrymen but also the
                    Ausetani, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Their territory reached
                        from the Pyrenees south-east to the Mediterranean, Gerunda being their chief
                        town (now Gerona). Cf. XXI. xxiii. 2; lxi. 8 (here and in XXXIX. lvi. 1 they
                        even approach the Ebro; not so in Casear <hi rend="italics">B.C.</hi> I. x.
                        2); XXVI. xvii. 4 (doubtful reading); XXXIV. xx. 1; below, ii. 5; iii. 3.
                    </note> a neighbouring tribe, and other peoples adjoining his territory and
                    theirs. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> And thus within a few days thirty
                    thousand infantry and about four thousand horse came together in the territory
                    of the Sedetani, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Often confused with
                        the Edetani, and north of the Ebro, but we do not know their exact location.
                        Cf. XXVIII. xxiv. 4; xxxi. 7. </note> in accordance with their instructions. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman commanders on their part, Lucius
                    Lentulus and Lucius Manlius Acidinus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cornelius Lentulus and Manlius had been praetors in 211 and <date
                            when="-0210">210 B.C.</date> respectively; XXV. xli. 12; XXVI. xxiii. 1;
                        sent to Spain <hi rend="italics">cum imperio;</hi> cf. XXVIII. xxxviii. 1;
                        styled proconsuls without having held the consulship; below, xiii. 7.
                    </note> for fear <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the war might grow more
                    serious from neglect of the first hostile acts, likewise united their armies,
                    and leading their soldiers through the Ausetanian territory with restraint on an
                    enemy's soil, as though it <pb n="p.215"/> were friendly, they reached the place
                    where their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        205</note> enemies had concentrated and pitched camp three miles away from
                    their camp. At first a vain effort was made through envoys to make them abandon
                    fighting. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then when an attack was suddenly
                    made upon Roman foragers by Spanish horse and from a Roman outpost horsemen were
                    sent to the rescue, there was a cavalry battle with no success for either side
                    worth mentioning. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At sunrise on the following
                    day, under arms and drawn up, all of them displayed their battle-line at a
                    distance of about a mile from the Roman camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The Ausetani were in the centre; of the wings the Ilergetes occupied the right,
                    unimportant Spanish tribes the left. Between the wings and the centre they had
                    made spaces broad enough to send the cavalry through when the time came.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And the Romans, having drawn up their army
                    in the customary fashion, imitated this feature only of the enemy's line, that
                    they likewise left broad spaces between the legions for the passage of cavalry.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But Lentulus thought that whichever side
                    should first send its cavalry out into the enemy's line with its gaping
                    intervals would use its cavalry to advantage. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore ordered Servius Cornelius, a tribune of the soldiers, to command
                    his cavalry to give their horses free rein through the broad openings in the
                    battle-line of the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lentulus himself,
                    after the infantry battle had begun without success, delayed only long enough to
                    bring up the thirteenth legion from the reserves into the front line to support
                    the twelfth legion, which had been placed on the left wing facing the Ilergetes
                    and was giving way. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Now that the battle was
                    evenly balanced there, he came up to Lucius Manlius, who <pb n="p.217"/> was in
                    the foremost ranks, encouraging the men <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> and bringing up reserves
                    to such positions as the case required. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He
                    informed him that all was secured on the left wing; that he had already sent
                    Servius Cornelius to surround the enemy with a whirlwind attack of cavalry. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scarcely had Lentulus said this when the
                    Roman horse, charging into the midst of the enemy, threw the infantry lines into
                    confusion and at the same time closed for the Spanish cavalry the route by which
                    they might launch their attack. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Accordingly
                    the Spaniards gave up the cavalry battle and dismounted. The Roman generals, on
                    seeing the broken ranks of the enemy, and their fright and alarm and the
                    wavering standards, exhorted and implored their soldiers to attack the
                    discouraged enemy and not allow the line to re-form. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The barbarians would have failed to withstand so impetuous
                    an attack, had not even their prince, Indibilis, exposed himself with the
                    dismounted cavalry in front of the first units of the infantry. At that point a
                    fierce battle continued for some time. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Finally, when those who kept on fighting round the prince, who resisted though
                    half-dead, but was pinned to the ground by a javelin, were overwhelmed by
                    missile weapons and fell, at that moment began a flight pell-mell. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> Greater numbers were slain because the horsemen had
                    left no room to mount their horses, and because the Romans made a spirited
                    attack upon the terrified. And they did not withdraw until they had routed the
                    enemy out of his camp as well. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Thirteen
                    thousand Spaniards were slain that day, about one thousand eight hundred
                    captured. Of the Romans and their allies little more than two <pb n="p.219"/>
                    hundred fell, mainly on the left wing. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Those
                    of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                    Spaniards who were driven out of their camp or had escaped from the battle
                    scattered at first over the country and then returned to their respective
                    communities. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then they were summoned by Mandonius to a
                    council, and there, after lamenting their heavy losses and berating those who
                    were responsible for the war, they voted that envoys should be sent to arrange
                    for a surrender of arms and a capitulation. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    When the envoys laid the blame upon Indibilis as responsible-for the war and
                    upon the rest of their leading men, most of whom, they said, had fallen in the
                    battle, and offered to deliver their arms and surrender, the answer given them
                    was: that their surrender would be accepted only in case they should deliver
                    Mandonius and the other instigators of the war alive. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> If not, the generals said they would lead their army into
                    the lands of the Ilergetes and Ausetani and the other tribes one after another.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Such was the reply given to the legates
                    and reported by them to the council. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thereupon
                    Mandonius and the other leaders were seized and handed over to be punished. For
                    the peoples of Spain peace was restored, a double tribute for that year and
                    grain for six months exacted, also cloaks and togas for the army; and hostages
                    were accepted from about thirty tribes. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thus a rebellious uprising in Spain was
                    incited and suppressed within a few days with no serious consequences, and alarm
                    was completely shifted to Africa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Gaius
                    Laelius, having reached Hippo Regius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Livy or his Roman source must have confused Hippo Diarrhytus (Bizerte) with
                        Hippo Regius (near Bone), which was ten days' journey from Carthage (so
                        Procopius <hi rend="italics">Bell.</hi> IV ( <hi rend="italics">Vand.</hi>
                        II.), iv. 26; Mela I. 33; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> V. 22; VI.
                        212). Laelius would not lay waste land claimed by Masinissa. Cf. p. 334 for
                        the real Hippo Regius. </note> by night, led out his soldiers and marines
                    under their standards at daybreak to lay the country <pb n="p.221"/> waste.
                    Since everybody was free from concern, as <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> if in peace-time, great
                    losses were inflicted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And excited messengers
                    filled Carthage with great alarm, reporting that the Roman fleet and Scipio as
                    commander-in-chief had arrived. In fact it had been previously rumoured that he
                    had already crossed over to Sicily. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lacking
                    exact information also as to how many ships the messengers had seen and how
                    large a force was laying waste the country, they exaggerated every report under
                    the stimulus of fear. Accordingly alarm and panic at first, then dejection came
                    over their spirits. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So far, they said, had
                    fortune changed that those who as victors had but lately had their own army
                    before the walls of Rome and, after laying low so many armies of the enemy, had
                    by force or by voluntary action received the surrender of all the peoples of
                    Italy, with the shifting fortune <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> of war
                    were now destined to see the devastation of Africa and a siege of Carthage, when
                    they had no such strength as the Romans had possessed to endure all that.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For them, they said, the Roman populace,
                    for them Latium had always furnished a greater and more numerous body of young
                    men growing up in place of so many armies slain. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> As for their own populace, they were unwarlike in the city,
                    unwarlike in the country. Hireling auxiliaries were being recruited from the
                    Africans, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The earlier inhabitants,
                        mostly rustics, many of them mercenary soldiers; cf. XXVIII. xiv. 4, 19; xx.
                        1, etc.; below, iv. 2. </note> a race shifting with every fickle breath of
                    hope and lacking in loyalty. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Of the kings,
                    moreover, Syphax had been alienated after his conference with Scipio, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXVIII. xviii.</note> they said, and
                    Masinissa by open defection had shown himself their bitterest enemy. Nowhere was
                    there any hope, nowhere any aid. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Mago was
                    neither setting in motion any uprising on the part of Gaul, <pb n="p.223"/> nor
                    uniting with Hannibal; and Hannibal himself <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> by this time was on the
                    decline both in repute and in strength. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the laments into which men had
                    fallen in consequence of the recent news when impending alarm roused them again
                    to deliberate how they should meet the dangers of the moment. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It was decided to hold levies speedily in city and country;
                    to send men to hire African auxiliaries; to fortify the city, to bring in grain,
                    to provide arms offensive and defensive, to equip ships and send them to Hippo
                    to face the Roman fleet. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While they were
                    already thus employed the news at last came that Laelius, not Scipio, had sailed
                    across and only sufficient forces to raid the farms; that the bulk of the main
                    army was still in Sicily. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So there was a
                    breathing spell, and they set about sending embassies to Syphax and other
                    princes, to cement an alliance. To Philip also envoys were sent to promise him
                    two hundred talents of silver, on condition that he should cross over into
                    Sicily or Italy. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Instead of doing so
                        Philip made a treaty with the Romans; below, xii. 14. For a previous effort
                        of the king to form an alliance with Carthage cf. XXIII. xxxiii. f. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Men were sent likewise to their own commanders
                    in Italy, that by every sort of alarm they should keep Scipio there. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Not only envoys were sent to Mago but twenty-five
                    war-ships, six thousand infantry, eight hundred horsemen, seven elephants, and
                    in addition a large sum of money to hire auxiliaries. Relying upon these
                    resources he was to advance nearer to the city of Rome with his army and unite
                    with Hannibal. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such were their plans and deliberations at
                    Carthage <pb n="p.225"/> when Masinissa, aroused by the report of a Roman <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> fleet,
                    came with a few horsemen to Laelius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A different account, followed by Livy in xxxiii. 9, placed Masinissa, at the
                        time of Laelius' landing, in the region of the Emporia, far away to the
                        south-east (cf. xxv. 12 and note). </note> who was carrying off a vast
                    amount of booty from territory that lacked troops and garrisons. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Masinissa complained that Scipio was conducting the
                    war without spirit in not having already transported his army to Africa, while
                    the Carthaginians were panic-stricken and Syphax was entangled in wars with
                    neighbours. He was certain, he said, that if Syphax should be given time to
                    settle his affairs to his own satisfaction, there would be no real loyalty in
                    his dealings with the Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Laelius should
                    exhort and spur Scipio on to avoid delay. For himself, although he had been
                    driven out of his kingdom, he would assist with no inconsiderable forces of
                    infantry and cavalry. Laelius also must not tarry in Africa. A fleet, he
                    believed, had sailed from Carthage, and with that fleet it was unsafe to engage
                    in the absence of Scipio. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Directly after this conversation Laelius sent
                    Masinissa away, and on the following day he weighed anchor at Hippo, his ships
                    booty-laden, and sailing back to Sicily delivered Masinissa's messages to
                    Scipio. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> About the same time the ships which had been
                    sent to Mago from Carthage came into port between Ligurian Albingaunum and
                    Genua. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For that coast and its ports
                        cf. XXVIII. xlvi. 8 ff. and notes. Here Savo (Savona), or Vada Sabat(i)a (2
                        1/2 miles farther west), is evidently meant. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In that region, as it happened, Mago had his
                    fleet at the time. On hearing the words of the envoys, who urged him to get
                    together the largest possible armies, he at once held a council of Gauls and
                    Ligurians; for great numbers of both nations were present. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And he told <pb n="p.227"/> them that he had been sent to
                    restore their liberty, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 205</note> and that forces were being sent to him from home, as they
                    themselves saw; but with what resources, with how large an army that war was to
                    be waged depended upon themselves. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There were
                    two Roman armies, he said, one in Gaul, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXVIII. ix. 1 and note.</note> the other in Etruria.
                    He was sure that Spurius Lucretius would unite with Marcus Livius; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> xlvi.
                        12 f.; below, xiii. 4. </note> that many thousands must be armed for
                    resistance to two generals, two Roman armies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Gauls said that they were entirely willing to do so, but that since they had
                    almost before their eyes one Roman camp within their borders and another in the
                    neighbouring land of Etruria, if it should become known that they had aided the
                    Carthaginian by furnishing auxiliaries, forthwith hostile armies would invade
                    their territory from both directions. From Gauls he should require such support
                    as could be given in secret. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Ligurians were
                    free to act, they said, since Roman camps were far from their land and their
                    cities; it was right that <hi rend="italics">they</hi> should arm their young
                    men and take their proper share in the war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The Ligurians did not refuse, but simply asked for two months' time to hold
                    levies. Meanwhile Mago by sending men secretly through their territory hired
                    Gauls as soldiers. Supplies also of every kind were coming to him in secret from
                    the Gallic nations. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcus Livius led his army
                    of slave-volunteers over from Etruria into Gaul and, having united with
                    Lucretius, prepared to confront Mago, should he move out of Liguria towards the
                    city; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It was safe to assume that he
                        would follow Hasdrubal's example in making for the Adriatic coast, to enter
                        Italy at Ariminum. The shorter Riviera route was never practicable until
                            <date when="-0109">109 B.C.</date> , when the Via Aurelia was extended
                        to Pisae, Genua, and Vada Sabatia; Strabo V. i. 11; cf. Mommsen <hi
                            rend="italics">C.I.L.</hi> V. p. 885. </note> but should the <pb
                        n="p.229"/> Carthaginian quietly remain in a distant region <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the broader meaning of <hi
                            rend="italics">angulus</hi> = <hi rend="italics">recessus,</hi>
                        <quote>remote region,</quote> cf. XXVIII. xii. 6; xlii. 18. </note> at the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> foot
                    of the Alps, he too would remain where he was, near Ariminum, for the defence of
                    Italy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the return of Gaius Laelius from Africa
                    Scipio was spurred on by Masinissa's encouragement, and the soldiers seeing
                    booty from the land of the enemy being brought ashore from an entire fleet, were
                    likewise fired with a desire to cross over as soon as possible. The greater
                    design, however, was interrupted by a lesser, that of recovering the city of
                    Locri, which in the rebellion of Italy had also gone over to the Carthaginians.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As Livy has twice told: in <date
                            when="-0216">216 B.C.</date> , at XXIII. xxx. 8, and more fully under
                        215 in XXIV. i. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Bright hopes of accomplishing that purpose,
                    moreover, arose from a petty circumstance. There was brigandage rather than
                    normal war operations in the country of the Bruttii, where a beginning had been
                    made by the Numidians, and the Bruttians fell in with that practice not more on
                    account of their Punic alliance than of their own nature. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Finally the Roman soldiers also from a kind of infection
                    now delighted in plunder, making raids upon the enemy's farms just as far as
                    their commanders permitted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They had
                    overpowered certain Locrians straying from the city and had carried them off to
                    Regium. In the number of these captives were some artisans who, as it happened,
                    were in the habit of plying their trade for hire among the Carthaginians in the
                    citadel of Locri. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These men were recognized by
                    leading Locrians who, on being driven out by the opposing party, which had
                    surrendered Locri to Hannibal, had retired to Regium. On being asked the
                    questions usually put by men long absent, the artisans first <pb n="p.231"/>
                    told them what was going on at home, and then <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> inspired the hope that, if
                    ransomed and sent back, they would betray the citadel to them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> It was there, they said, that they dwelt and among the
                    Carthaginians were trusted in everything. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly the leading men, being tormented by home-sickness and at the same
                    time fired with a desire for vengeance on their enemies, at once ransomed the
                    artisans and sent them back after agreeing upon a plan of action and signals for
                    the display of which in the distance they should be on the watch. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> They themselves went to Scipio at Syracuse, with whom
                    were some of the exiles. There they reported the promises of the captives and
                    inspired in the consul a hope which gave good prospect of success. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Consequently Marcus Sergius and Publius Matienus,
                    tribunes of the soldiers, were sent with them and ordered to take three thousand
                    soldiers from Regium to Locri. And a written order was sent to the propraetor
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e. legatus pro praetore,</hi> representing Scipio. Cf.
                        viii. 5; xvii. 10. </note> Quintus Pleminius to assist in carrying out the
                    project. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Setting out from Regium, carrying ladders
                    constructed for the height of the citadel as reported, about midnight they set a
                    signal <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXVIII. v. 17 and
                        note.</note> for the betrayers of the citadel from the place agreed upon.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These men were ready and alert, and after
                    they on their part also had lowered ladders made for that very purpose and at
                    several different places at the same time had admitted scaling parties, before
                    any outcry could arise came the attack upon the Carthaginian guards, who in the
                    absence of any such fear naturally were asleep. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> At first it was the groans of the dying indistinctly heard; then sudden
                    terror on awaking, and confused action, since the reason was unknown; finally
                    greater certainty as they awakened <pb n="p.233"/> one another. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> By this time every man was shouting <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> his
                    loudest <quote>To arms!</quote> that enemies were on the citadel and guards
                    being cut down. And the Romans, who were by no means equal in numbers, would
                    have been overpowered, had not an outcry raised by the men who were outside the
                    citadel made it uncertain from what quarter the sounds came, while everything
                    they imagined was intensified by the uproar in the dark. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the Carthaginians, supposing the citadel to be
                    already filled with the enemy, were terrified, gave up fighting and fled to the
                    other citadel; for there are two not far apart. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                    /> The inhabitants were holding the city, set between combatants as a prize for
                    the victors. From the two citadels came slight engagements every day. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> Quintus Pleminius commanded the Roman, Hamilcar the
                    Carthaginian garrison. Summoning reinforcements from neighbouring places they
                    kept increasing their numbers. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Finally
                    Hannibal himself was on the way, and the Romans would not have held out if the
                    mass of the Locrians, embittered by the arrogance and greed of the
                    Carthaginians, had not taken the side of the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, on being informed that the situation
                    at Locri had become more critical and that Hannibal himself was approaching, was
                    afraid to take risks for the garrison as well, since it was not easy to retire
                    from the place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly he too set out
                    from Messana, after leaving his brother Lucius Scipio there in command of the
                    garrison; and as soon as the strait shifted with the tide, he cast off with . .
                    . ships while the current favoured. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">1 I.e.</hi> the so-called <quote>descending</quote> tide,
                        running south into the Ionian Sea; XXIII. xli. 11; Strabo I. iii. 11. This
                        strait has marked tides <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> —very rare in the
                        Mediterranean. Cf. the Euripus, XXVIII. vi. 10 and note. </note> And
                    Hannibal <pb n="p.235"/> sent a messenger from the river Bulotus —it is not far
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> from
                    the city of Locri —ordering his men to engage in battle with the Romans and
                    Locrians with the utmost violence at daybreak, while, when all eyes were turned
                    in the direction of that conflict, he should himself attack the city unawares
                    from the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> rear. When he came upon the battle,
                    already begun at daybreak, he did not wish to shut himself in the citadel, where
                    he would have clogged a cramped space by his numbers, and on the other hand he
                    had not brought ladders for scaling city <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    walls. After making a pile of the soldiers' baggage and displaying his line of
                    battle at no great distance from the walls to frighten the enemy, while ladders
                    and other requisites for an assault were being prepared, he rode round the city
                    with his Numidian horsemen, to discover just where to make the <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> attack. He had approached the wall when a man who happened
                    to stand nearest to him was struck by a missile from a scorpion. Frightened away
                    by an occurrence so dangerous, he thereupon ordered the recall to be sounded and
                    fortified a camp beyond the range of <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> missiles.
                    The Roman fleet sailing from Messana reached Locri while several hours of
                    daylight <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> remained. All were landed from the
                    ships and before sunset they entered the city. </p>
                <p> On the following day a battle was begun by the Carthaginians from their citadel,
                    and Hannibal, having made ready the ladders and everything else for the assault,
                    was coming close to the walls when suddenly the Romans opened a gate and sallied
                    out against an enemy who feared anything but <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    that. In making this surprise attack they slew about two hundred. As for the
                    rest, Hannibal on <pb n="p.237"/> learning that the consul was there withdrew
                    them <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> to
                    his camp, and sending word to the men in the citadel to shift for themselves, he
                    broke camp in the night and marched <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> away. And
                    the men in the citadel set fire to the houses which they were occupying, that
                    the commotion might delay the enemy, and with a speed that resembled flight
                    overtook their own column before nightfall. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, seeing that the citadel had been
                    abandoned by the enemy and the site of the camp deserted, summoned the Locrians
                    to an assembly and stoutly upbraided them for their revolt. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He punished those who had prompted it and bestowed their
                    property upon the leaders of the other party in view of their conspicuous
                    loyalty towards the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As regards their
                    state, he said he would neither grant the Locrians anything nor take anything
                    away. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They should send envoys to Rome; and
                    whatever lot the senate thought it proper for them to have would be theirs. Even
                    though they had deserved ill of the Roman people, of this he was certain, that
                    they would be in a better position under angry Romans than they were under
                    friendly Carthaginians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Leaving Pleminius, his
                    lieutenant, to defend the city with the force which had captured the citadel,
                    Scipio crossed over to Messana with the troops with which he had come. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With such arrogance and cruelty had the
                    Locrians been treated by the Carthaginians after their revolt from the Romans
                    that they could bear minor wrongs not only calmly but almost willingly.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In actual fact, however, so far did
                    Pleminius surpass Hamilcar, commandant of the garrison, so far did the Roman
                    soldiers in the garrison surpass the Carthaginians in <pb n="p.239"/> villainy
                    and greed that they seemed to be competing <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> not in arms but in vices.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of all the things that make the power of
                    the stronger odious to the helpless man not one was overlooked by commander and
                    soldiers in dealing with the townspeople. Unutterable insults were practised
                    upon their own persons, upon their children, upon their wives. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> It goes without saying that their avarice did not refrain
                    from despoiling even sacred things. And not only were other temples desecrated,
                    but also the treasure chambers of Proserpina, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The chief divinity of Locri was Persephone, her famous
                        temple and rich treasury being just outside the walls and to the north-west.
                        Cf. xviii. 3. </note> untouched in every age except that they were said to
                    have been despoiled by Pyrrhus, who met with a signal punishment and restored
                    the plunder gained by his sacrilege. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Cf. xviii. 4-6 and notes.</note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Consequently, just as formerly the king's
                    ships, battered and wrecked, had landed nothing intact but the goddess' sacred
                    money which they were trying to carry <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> away,
                    so on this occasion also, with a different kind of disaster that same money
                    visited insanity upon all who had shared in that desecration of the temple, and
                    mutually turned commander against commander, soldier against soldier, with the
                    frenzy of enemies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The chief command belonged to Pleminius. Part
                    of the soldiers whom he had brought from Regium were under him, part under the
                    tribunes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Having stolen a silver cup from the
                    house of a citizen, a fleeing soldier of Pleminius was being pursued by the
                    owners when he chanced to meet Sergius and Matienus, tribunes of the soldiers.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By order of the tribunes the cup was taken
                    away from the man. <pb n="p.241"/> Thereupon angry words followed and shouting,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                    finally a battle between Pleminius' soldiers and those of the tribunes, while
                    numbers and rioting increased in proportion as one side or the other gained a
                    timely arrival. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The soldiers of Pleminius were
                    worsted, and when they came running to him displaying bloody wounds, not without
                    angry shouts as they reported insults that had been heaped even upon him in an
                    altercation, he was inflamed with anger, dashed out of his house, summoned the
                    tribunes and ordered them to be stripped and the rods made ready. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> While time was being taken to strip them —for they
                    resisted and called upon the soldiers to help them — suddenly soldiers, flushed
                    by their recent victory, came running from every quarter, just as if there had
                    been a call to arms against the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And
                    when they caught sight of the tribunes' backs already welted by the rods, upon
                    that they were indeed suddenly fired to a much more uncontrollable madness, and
                    after roughly handling the lictors in shameful fashion, without regard even for
                    humanity, not to say for the dignity of his rank, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Pleminius represents Scipio and has <hi rend="italics"
                            >imperium.</hi>
                    </note> they assaulted the legatus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then,
                    having separated and cut him off from his men, they slashed him as if an enemy
                    and, mutilating his nose and ears, left him almost lifeless. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These acts being reported at Messana, Scipio a
                    few days later sailed to Locri on a <hi rend="italics">hexēris.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This rare type of vessel had been
                        used in the First Punic War for the flag-ships of Regulus and Manlius;
                        Polybius I. xxvi. 11. It was the next grade above the quinquereme. Cf.
                        XXVIII. xxx. 11, note. </note> Then having heard the case of Pleminius and
                    the tribunes, he discharged Pleminius as innocent and left him in command of the
                    same place, while the tribunes were adjudged guilty and put in chains, to be
                    sent to the <pb n="p.243"/> senate at Rome; whereupon he returned to Messana
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> and
                    thence to Syracuse. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Pleminius was beside
                    himself with rage, thinking the wrong done to him had been overlooked by Scipio
                    and treated as too trivial; also that no one else was capable of naming a
                    penalty for the offence except a man who had known its barbarity by suffering.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly he ordered the tribunes to be
                    brought before him, and had them mangled by every torture which any human body
                    can endure and then put to death. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Not
                    satisfied with a penalty paid by the living either, he threw them out unburied.
                    The like cruelty was used by him against leading men of the Locrians who, he
                    learned, had gone to Publius Scipio to complain of the outrages. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Then in anger he multiplied the shameful acts which,
                    prompted previously by lust and greed, he had perpetrated upon the allies, and
                    brought infamy and odium not only upon himself but also upon his general. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The time for the elections was already at hand
                    when a letter from Publius Licinius, the consul, reached Rome, reporting that he
                    and his army were suffering from a serious malady, and that they could not have
                    held out if an equally violent or even more serious disease had not been visited
                    upon the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly, since he was
                    unable to come in person to the elections, he would name Quintus Caecilius
                    Metellus dictator to hold the elections, if the senators approved. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> It was to the interest of the state, he said, that
                    the army of Quintus Caecilius should be discharged; for at present his army had
                    nothing to do, since Hannibal had already withdrawn his troops into winter
                    quarters; and so violent a malady had befallen Caecilius' camp that, unless the
                    troops were promptly disbanded, not one man, it <pb n="p.245"/> seemed, would
                    survive. The consul was permitted <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 205</note> by the senate to do whatever he thought
                    consistent with the public interest and his own conscience. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At that time religious scruples had suddenly
                    assailed the citizens because in the Sibylline books, which were consulted on
                    account of the frequent showers of stones that year, an oracle was found that,
                    if ever a foreign foe should invade the land of <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> Italy, he could be driven out of Italy and defeated if the
                    Idaean Mother <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Kybele (Cybele), the
                        Phrygian Mother of the Gods; Preller, <hi rend="italics">Griechische
                            Mythologie</hi> 14. 643 ff.; Roscher, <hi rend="italics">Lex.</hi> II.
                        i. 1638 if., 1666 ff.; Catullus 63; Lucretius II. 600 ff.; Dio Cass. frag.
                        57. 61; Strabo XII. v. 3; Appian <hi rend="italics">Hann.</hi> 56; Cicero
                            <hi rend="italics">de Harusp. Resp.</hi> 27 f. Ovid's imaginative
                        account should be compared, <hi rend="italics">Fasti</hi> IV. 247-348 (see
                        Frazer's notes). Pessinus was near the border of Galatia (towards Phrygia),
                        ca. 80 miles south-west of Ancyra (Ankara). Cf. xi. 7, note. </note> should
                    be brought from Pessinus to Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    discovery of that oracle by the decemvirs impressed the senators all the more
                    because the ambassadors also who had carried a gift to Delphi reported that,
                    when they offered sacrifices themselves to Pythian Apollo, the omens had been
                    favourable, and that likewise from the sanctum there had come a response that a
                    much greater victory was in prospect for the Roman people than that from spoils
                    of which they were bringing gifts. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To the
                    facts supporting that same hope the senators added Publius Scipio's state of
                    mind, virtually forecasting the end of the war, in that he demanded Africa as
                    his province. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And so, that they might the
                    sooner be in possession of the victory which foreshadowed itself in oracles,
                    forecasts <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Referring mainly to
                        Scipio's confident anticipation, while <quote>oracles</quote> covers the
                        Sibylline prophecy and <quote>responses</quote> that from Delphi
                        (Gronovius). </note> and responses, they planned and discussed what should
                    be the method of transporting the goddess to Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Asia the Roman people had as yet no allied
                    states. They bore in mind, however, that Aesculapius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Cf. X. xlvii. 7; <hi rend="italics">Periocha</hi> 11;
                        Strabo <hi rend="italics">l. c.</hi> (cf. n. 1). </note> also had been
                    summoned once upon a <pb n="p.247"/> time from Greece on account of an epidemic,
                    while <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note>
                    there was as yet no treaty of alliance; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that
                    at present on account of a joint war against Philip they had already entered
                    into friendly relations with King Attalus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Thinking that he would do what he could for the sake of the Roman people, they
                    decided to send ambassadors to him. These were Marcus Valerius Laevinus, who had
                    been twice consul <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXX. xxiii. 5.
                        One list of the consuls gives Laevinus a first consulship in <date
                            when="-0220">220 B.C.</date> ; Chronogr. an. 354 in <hi rend="italics"
                            >C.I.L.</hi> I. p. 524. He may have been a <hi rend="italics"
                            >suffectus</hi> in <date when="-0208">208 B.C.</date> (end of the year,
                        both consuls being dead; XXVII. xxxiii. 7). In Livy a new man when elected
                        in <date when="-0211">211 B.C.</date> ; XXVI. xxii. 12. </note> and had held
                    a command in Greece, Marcus Caecilius Metellus, an ex-praetor, Servius Sulpicius
                    Galba, an ex-aedile, and two former quaestors, Gnaeus Tremelius Flaccus and
                    Marcus Valerius Falto. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For them they voted
                    five quinqueremes, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See XXVIII. xxx.
                        11 and note. Whatever may have been the arrangement of the oars on a
                        quinquereme, it is clear that these larger vessels were meant to impress all
                        who saw them with the <hi rend="italics">dignitas</hi> of the Roman state.
                    </note> that in keeping with the dignity of the Roman people they might visit
                    lands where the highest respect for the Roman name was to be won. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The ambassadors on the voyage to Asia made their way
                    up to Delphi and consulted the oracle, enquiring what hope of accomplishing the
                    task for which they had been sent from home it foresaw for themselves and the
                    Roman people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The response, they say, was that
                    they should gain what they sought with the help of King Attalus; that after
                    conveying the goddess to Rome they were then to make sure that the best man at
                    Rome should hospitably welcome her. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They came
                    to the king at Pergamum. He courteously received the ambassadors and, escorting
                    them to Pessĭnus in Phrygia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        region was still held by the Gallic invaders, but the temple was favoured
                        and adorned by the kings at Pergamum. That Attalus and the legati actually
                        went to Pessĭnus, about 240 miles from his capital, is very unlikely.
                    </note> presented them with the sacred stone <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Probably a meteorite, small enough to be used later as
                        the face of her statue; Arnobius VII. 49; of. VI. 11; Herodian I. 11, 1;
                        Appiaan <hi rend="italics">Hann.</hi> 56. Cp. p. 261, n. 2. </note>
                    <pb n="p.249"/> which the inhabitants said was the Mother of the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> Gods, and
                    bade them carry it away to Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Sent on in
                    advance by the ambassadors, Marcus Valerius Falto brought the news that they
                    were bringing the goddess; they must seek out the best man in the state to
                    receive her with due hospitality. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Quintus Caecilius Metellus was named, by the
                    consul who was in the land of the Bruttians, dictator for the purpose of holding
                    the elections, and Metellus' army was disbanded. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Veturius Philo was named master of the horse. The
                    elections were held by the dictator. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Cornelius Cethegus and Publius Sempronius Tuditanus were elected consuls, the
                    latter in his absence, since he had Greece as his province. Then Tiberius
                    Claudius Nero, Marcus Marcius Ralla, Lucius Scribonius Libo, Marcus Pomponius
                    Matho were elected praetors. The elections being completed, the dictator
                    abdicated his office. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Roman Games were repeated for three of
                    the days, the Plebeian Games for seven. The curule aediles were Gnaeus and
                    Lucius Cornelius Lentulus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Lucius was in
                    charge of the province of Spain; being elected in absence he was aedile in
                    absence. Tiberius Claudius Asellus and Marcus Iunius Pennus were plebeian
                    aediles. The Temple of Valour <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf.
                        Vol. VI. p. 494, note; VII. p. 312 f., notes; Platner- Ashby, <hi
                            rend="italics">Topogr. Dict.</hi> 258 f. For the younger Marcellus cf.
                        p. 288, n. 1. </note> at the Porta Capena was dedicated that year by Marcus
                    Marcellus, in the seventeenth year after it had been vowed at Clastidium in Gaul
                    by his father in his first consulship. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And
                    the flamen of Mars, Marcus Aemilius Regillus, died that year. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Greece the situation had been ignored in
                    the last two years. Consequently when the Aetolians were abandoned by the
                    Romans, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> No abandonment has been
                        previously mentioned, but neglect for many months would have the same
                        effect. </note> the one defence in <pb n="p.251"/> which they trusted,
                    Philip compelled them to sue <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 205</note> for peace and make a treaty on terms of his
                    own choosing. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Had he not used every effort to
                    bring that about promptly, he would have been surprised while still making war
                    upon the Aetolians by Publius Sempronius, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> He had been censor (XXVII. xi. 7), and already
                        proconsul in Greece before his consulship; cf. XXVIII. xxxviii. 1, note.
                    </note> the proconsul, who with ten thousand infantry and a thousand cavalry and
                    thirty-five warships had been sent as Sulpicius' successor in command and was no
                    small factor in bringing aid to the allies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Scarcely had peace been made when word came to the king that the Romans had
                    arrived at Dyrrachium, and that the Parthini and other neighbouring tribes were
                    aroused to the hope of revolution and that Dimallum <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On the Adriatic, location uncertain, but near the
                        Parthini and Dyrrhachium (Durazzo). Cf. XXXIII. xxxiv. 11; XLIII. xxi. 3;
                        Polybius II. xi. 11; III. xviii. 1, 3; VII. ix. 13 (text of a treaty between
                        Hannibal and Philip). </note> was besieged. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> To that place the Romans had turned aside from helping the Aetolians, to whom
                    they had been sent. They were angry because without Roman consent and contrary
                    to the treaty <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Of. XXVI. xxiv.
                        8-14.</note> the Aetolians had made peace with the king. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On hearing of this Philip, fearing some greater disturbance
                    might begin among neighbouring tribes and peoples, hastened by forced marches to
                    Apollonia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. Vol. VI. p. 303, n. 3;
                        305, 307; VII. p.95 fin.</note> to which Sempronius had withdrawn after
                    sending Laetorius, his lieutenant, with a part of his troops and fifteen ships
                    into Aetolia to survey the situation and, if possible, to disturb the peace.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Philip laid waste the farms of the
                    Apollonians and, moving his troops up to the city, gave the Roman an opportunity
                    to engage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as he saw that they
                    remained inactive, merely defending the walls, Philip, who had not sufficient
                    confidence in his forces to assault the city and was desirous of peace <pb
                        n="p.253"/> with the Romans also, if possible, just as with the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> Aetolians,
                    but if not, of making an armistice, retired to his own kingdom without provoking
                    any further animosities by a fresh conflict. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About the same time the Epirotes, weary of the
                    protracted war, first sounding the disposition of the Romans, sent ambassadors
                    to Philip in regard to a general peace, asserting their confidence that it
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> would be agreed upon if he should come
                    to a conference with Publius Sempronius, the Roman general. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The king was easily prevailed upon to cross over into
                    Epirus, for he himself was not disinclined to peace. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Phoenice <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In
                        Chaonia (northern Epirus), a few miles from the port of Onchesmos, opposite
                        Corcyra (Corfu); Polybius II. v. 3; Strabo VII. vii. 5. </note> is a city in
                    Epirus; there the king first conferred with Aëropus and Derdas and Philip, chief
                    magistrates of the Epirotes, and later met Publius Sempronius. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Present at the conference were Amynander, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Athamanes (in eastern Epirus, close
                        to the Pindus range; Strabo IX. v. 1) had a king, the neighbouring tribes
                        only <foreign xml:lang="greek">strathgoi/.</foreign> A peacemaker in <date
                            when="-0208">208 B.C.</date> (XXVII. xxx. 4), Amynander allowed Philip
                        to pass through his territory, and thus the Aetolians were obliged to make a
                        separate peace with Macedonia (§ 1). </note> King of the Athamanians, and in
                    addition magistrates of the Epirotes and Acarnanians. The first to speak was
                    Philip, the magistrate, begging the king and at the same time the Roman general
                    to make an end of the war and grant that favour to the Epirotes. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Publius Sempronius stated as terms of the peace that
                    the Parthini and Dimallum and Bargullum <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Small places, unknown; probably near Dimallum.</note>
                    and Eugenium <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Small places, unknown;
                        probably near Dimallum.</note> should fall to the Romans; that Atintania
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In northwestern Epirus, in the
                        upper valley of the Aōus river; XXVII. xxx. 13. Allied with Rome in the
                        Illyrian War of <date when="-0219">219 B.C.</date> , but now subject to
                        Philip. </note> should be annexed to Macedonia, if the king, sending
                    ambassadors to Rome, should obtain the senate's consent. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Peace being agreed upon on these terms, <pb n="p.255"/>
                    Prusias, King of Bithynia, the Achaeans, Boeotians, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 205</note> Thessalians, Acarnanians
                    and Epirotes were included on the king's side of the treaty; on the side of the
                    Romans, the Ilians, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As progenitors of
                        the Romans. Cf. their statement when Lucius Scipio visited Ilium in <date
                            when="-0190">190 B.C.</date> ; XXXVII. xxxvii. 1 ff.; cf. XXXVIII.
                        xxxix. 10; Herodian I. 11. 3. Early evidence for the Aeneas legend. </note>
                    King Attalus, Pleuratus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A king of
                        the Thracians; XXVI. xxiv. 9; XXVII. xxx. 13; XXVIII. v. 7. </note> Nabis,
                    tyrant of the Lacedaemonians, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> From
                        207 to <date when="-0192">192 B.C.</date> Successor of Machanidas, who fell
                        in battle three years before this; Polybius XI. xviii. Frequently mentioned
                        by Livy in subsequent books; his death XXXV. xxxv. 19. </note> also the
                    Eleans, Messenians and Athenians. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> These
                    provisions were reduced to writing and sealed, and an armistice was made for two
                    months, that meanwhile ambassadors might be sent to Rome, so that the people
                    might order peace to be made on these terms. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    And all the tribes so ordered, since, now that the war had shifted to Africa,
                    they wished for the present to be relieved of all other wars. Publius
                    Sempronius, after the peace had been made, left his province for Rome to enter
                    upon his consulship. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the consulship of Marcus Cornelius and
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    Publius Sempronius, this being the fifteenth year of the Punic war, the province
                    of Etruria was assigned by decree to Cornelius with the old army, the land of
                    the Bruttii to Sempronius, with orders to enrol new legions. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As for the praetors, the city jurisdiction fell to Marcus
                    Marcius, that over strangers and also the province of Gaul to Lucius Scribonius
                    Libo, Sicily to Marcus Pomponius Matho, Sardinia to Tiberius Claudius Nero.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Publius Scipio's command was continued for
                    one year with the army and the fleet which he then had. The same was done in the
                    case of Publius Licinius, who was to hold the Bruttian territory with two
                    legions so long as the consul should judge it to the public interest for him to
                    remain in the province with a high command. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Marcus Livius also and Spurius Lucretius had their <pb n="p.257"/> commands
                    continued, with two legions each to defend <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> Gaul against Mago.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So Gnaeus Octavius also, with the order
                    that, after turning over Sardinia and the legion to Tiberius Claudius, his duty
                    should be the defence of the sea-coast with forty war-ships within an area to be
                    defined by the senate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To Marcus Pomponius,
                    the praetor in Sicily, was assigned the army <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Frequently mentioned in these books; cf. esp. XXV. v.
                        10 and the speech following; XXIII. xxxi. 2, 4; XXIV. xviii. 9; XXVI. ii.
                        14; XXVII. ix. 4; XXVIII. x. 13; below, xxiv. 11 f. </note> from Cannae, two
                    legions. Titus Quinctius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Better known
                        as Flamininus (his cognomen). Elected consul for <date when="-0198">198
                            B.C.</date> , though he had not been aedile and in spite of his youth.
                        Cf. XXXI. xlix. 12; XXXII. vii. 8-12. His province as consul was Macedonia (
                            <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> viii. 4). In the next year he vanquished
                        Philip at Cynoscephalae, near Scotussa; XXXIII. vii-x. Cf. Polybius XVIII.
                        xxii ff.; Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">.Flamininus</hi> 7 f. </note> was to
                    have Tarentum, Gaius Hostilius Tubulus to have Capua, both as propraetors, as in
                    the preceding year, with the old garrison in each case. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As for the command in Spain, the question what two men it
                    wished to send to that province as proconsuls was brought before the people. The
                    tribes unanimously ordered that the same men, Lucius Cornelius Lentulus and
                    Lucius Manlius Acidinus should hold these provinces <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Formal organization as Hispania Citerior and Hispania
                        Ulterior did not come until seven years later, <date when="-0197">197
                            B.C.</date> , with the dividing line at the Saltus Castulonensis (Sierra
                        Morena); XXXII. xxviii. 11; XXXIII. xxi. 6 f.; xxv. 9; XXXIV. xvii. 1.
                    </note> as proconsuls, as they had done in the preceding year. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls began the conduct of a levy both for the
                    enrolment of new legions for the Bruttian territory and to fill the ranks of the
                    other armies; for so they had been ordered by the senate. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although Africa had not been openly assigned
                    as a province, while the senators kept the matter dark, I believe, for fear the
                    Carthaginians might know in advance, nevertheless the people were aroused to
                    hope that the war would be waged that year in Africa, and that the end of the
                    Punic war was at hand. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That situation had
                    filled men's <pb n="p.259"/> minds with superstitious fears and they were <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> indined
                    both to report and to believe portents. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All
                    the greater was the number of them in circulation: that two suns had been seen,
                    and that at night there had been light for a time; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Again an aurora probably, as rare in Italy; cf. XXVIII.
                        xi. 3, Fregellae; XXXII. xxix. 2, Frusino, <date when="-0197">197
                            B.C.</date> An earlier instance, <date when="-0223">223 B.C.</date> at
                        Ariminum, Zonaras VIII. xx. 4; more in Iulius Obsequens, <hi rend="italics"
                            >e.g.</hi> 44 and 70 (102 and <date when="-0042">42 B.C.</date> ), from
                        lost books of Livy. Cf. Cicero <hi rend="italics">de Div.</hi> I. 97
                        (Pease). </note> and that at Setia a meteor <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Meteors were often reported among the prodigies; XXX.
                        ii. 11; XLI. xxi. 13; XLIII. xiii. 3; XLV. xvi. 5; Cicero <hi rend="italics"
                            >de Div.</hi> (Pease) I. 18 and 97; II. 60; <hi rend="italics">N.D.</hi>
                        II. 14. </note> had been seen shooting from east to west; that at Tarracina
                    a city-gate had been struck by lightning, at Anagnia a gate and also the wall at
                    many points; that in the temple of Juno Sospita at Lanuvium a noise was heard
                    with a dreadful crash. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To expiate these there
                    was a single day of prayer, and on account of the shower of stones nine days of
                    rites <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. Vol. VII. p. 90,
                        note.</note> were observed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In addition
                    they deliberated on the reception of the Idaean Mother, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Cf. p. 244, n. 1; George F. Moore, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Hist. of Religions</hi> I. 556 f. </note> in regard to whom not only
                    had Marcus Valerius, one of the ambassadors, arriving in advance, reported that
                    she would be in Italy very soon, but also there was recent news that she was
                    already at Tarracina. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was no unimportant
                    decision that occupied the senate — the question who was the best man in the
                    state. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At any rate every man would have
                    preferred a real victory in that contest to any high commands or magistracies,
                    whether conferred by vote of the senators or of the people. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Scipio, son of the Gnaeus who had fallen in Spain,
                    was the young man not yet of an age to be quaestor, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> There was still no law fixing a minimum age —not until
                        24 years later. Cf. Vol. VI. p. 344, n. 3. In <date when="-0191">191
                            B.C.</date> this Scipio Nasica reached the consulship; XXXV. xxiv. 5;
                        XXXVI. i. 1. </note> whom they judged to be the best of good men among all
                    the <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> citizens. If writers who lived nearest in
                    time to men who <pb n="p.261"/> remembered those days had handed down by what
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    virtues the senate was led to make that judgment, I should indeed gladly hand it
                    on to posterity. But I shall not interject my own opinions, reached by
                    conjecture in a matter buried by the lapse of <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    time. Publius Cornelius was ordered to go to Ostia with all the matrons to meet
                    the goddess, and himself to receive her from the ship, and carrying her to land
                    to turn her over to the matrons to <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> carry.
                    After the ship had reached the mouth of the river Tiber, in compliance with the
                    order he sailed out into open water on a ship, received the goddess from her
                    priests <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A Phrygian man and woman,
                        Dion. Hal. II. xix. 4 f. Romans were excluded by a decree of the senate, but
                        the restriction was later removed (2nd century A.D.). Cf. XXXVII. ix. 9;
                        XXXVIII. xviii. 9. </note> and carried her to <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> land. The foremost matrons in the state, among whom the
                    name of one in particular, that of Claudia Quinta, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Her statue was later placed in the temple of the Magna
                        Mater dedicated in <date when="-0191">191 B.C.</date> , the consulship of
                        Nasica. Cf. XXXVI. xxxvi. 3 f.; Tacitus <hi rend="italics">Ann.</hi> IV. 64;
                        Val. Max. I. viii. 11. Between <date when="-0204">204 B.C.</date> and 191
                        the black stone remained in the Temple of Victory, § 14 </note> is
                    conspicuous, received her. Claudia's repute, previously not unquestioned, as
                    tradition reports it, has made her purity the more celebrated among posterity by
                    a service so <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> devout. The matrons passed the
                    goddess from hand to hand in an unbroken succession to each other, while the
                    entire city poured out to meet her. Censers had been placed before the doors
                    along the route of the bearers, and kindling their incense, people prayed that
                    gracious and benignant she might enter the city of Rome. It was to the Temple of
                    Victory, which is on the Palatine, that they carried the goddess on the day
                    before the Ides of April, and that was a holy <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    day. The people thronged to the <pb n="p.263"/> Palatine bearing gifts for the
                    goddess, and there <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        204</note> was a banquet of the gods, and games also, called the Megalesia.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Later the festival was shifted to
                            <hi rend="italics">pridie nonas,</hi> the 4th of April in place of the
                        12th. Its name came from her Megalesion at Pergamum, the temple from which
                        she was brought to Rome according to Varro <hi rend="italics">L.L.</hi> VI.
                        15. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While they were discussing the men needed to
                    recruit the legions in the provinces, certain senators suggested that, since now
                    by favour of the gods fear had at last been removed, it was time for them no
                    longer to tolerate what had been endured as best they could in critical
                    circumstances. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As the senate was alert and in
                    suspense, they added that the twelve Latin colonies <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. Vol. VII. pp. 242 f. and notes; below, § 5.</note>
                    which had refused to furnish soldiers in the consulship of Quintus Fabius and
                    Quintus Fulvius had been exempt from service for now <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> about five years, as though it were an honour and a favour
                    bestowed upon them, whereas in the meantime good and obedient allies, in return
                    for their loyalty and submission to the Roman people, had been exhausted by
                    successive levies every year. These words revived the memory of an affair almost
                    obliterated and correspondingly inflamed the anger of the senators. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly, allowing the consuls to bring up no
                    other question first, they decreed that the consuls should summon to Rome
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> the magistrates <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the two <hi rend="italics">duumviri iure
                            dicendo,</hi> two <hi rend="italics">duumviri aediles,</hi> and two
                        quaestors of each colony. The leading citizens are <hi rend="italics"
                            >decuriones,</hi> members of a local senate. </note> and ten leading
                    citizens in each case from Nepete, Sutrium, Ardea, Cales, Alba, Carsioli, Sora,
                    Suessa, Setia, Circeii, Narnia, Interamna, for these were the colonies
                    concerned; that they should order them to furnish double the maximum number of
                    infantry that each of those colonies had ever furnished to the Roman people
                    since the enemy was <pb n="p.265"/> in Italy, and also one hundred and twenty
                    horsemen <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    in each case. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If any colony should be unable
                    to make up that number of horsemen, it should be permitted to give three
                    foot-soldiers for-one horseman. Men having the largest means should be chosen
                    for infantry and cavalry and sent to any place outside of Italy where
                    supplements were needed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If any delegation
                    should refuse, it was decided that the magistrates and envoys of that colony
                    should be detained, and that if they asked for a hearing in the senate, it
                    should be refused until they had done what was required of them. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> It was further ordered that a tax of one <hi
                        rend="italics">as</hi> for each thousand be laid upon those colonies and
                    exacted, every year, and that a census be taken in those colonies on the basis
                    of a census-list <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> To such a statement
                        of property was prefixed a questionnaire to establish identity of the
                        tax-payer. Cf. Caesar's Lex Iulia municipalis 146 f. (Bruns, <hi
                            rend="italics">Fontes</hi> 7 p. 109 f.). </note> furnished by the Roman
                    censors. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They resolved also that it be the
                    same which was given to the Roman people —and <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    that it be sworn to by the censors of the colonies and brought to Rome before
                    they laid down their office. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Complied
                        with in xxxvii. 7.</note>
                </p>
                <p> In accordance with this decree of the senate the consuls summoned the
                    magistrates and leading citizens of those colonies to Rome and required of them
                    soldiers and the tax. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thereupon they outdid
                    each other in refusing and loudly protesting. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    They said that such a number of soldiers could not be made up; that even if the
                    normal number were required according to the original compact, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A quite different sense of the term <hi
                            rend="italics">formula</hi> from that in § 9. Explained in Vol. VII. p.
                        245, note. </note> they could hardly reach it. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> They begged and implored that they be permitted to go
                    before the senate and make their plea. No such offence, they said, had been
                    committed that they deserved to perish. But even if perish they must, neither
                    their crime nor the anger of the Roman people could enable them to <pb n="p.267"
                    /> furnish more soldiers than they had. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    disinclined to yield, ordered the envoys to remain at Rome, the magistrates to
                    go to their homes in order to conduct levies, adding that unless the number of
                    soldiers demanded of them was first brought to Rome, no one would give them a
                    hearing in the senate. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Thus, after their
                    hopes of appearing before the senate and of making their plea had been
                    shattered, a levy was carried out in those twelve colonies without difficulty,
                    since owing to long exemption the number of younger men had increased. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In like manner another matter which had been
                    passed over in silence for about the same length of time was broached by Marcus
                    Valerius Laevinus, who said it was proper that the sums contributed <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXVI. xxxvi, including Laevinus'
                        speech on that occasion and the generous response (§§ 11 f.). It was in
                            <date when="-0210">210 B.C.</date> , a year before the refusal of the
                        colonies named in xv. 5. </note> when he and Marcus Claudius were consuls
                    should at last be repaid to private citizens; and that no one ought to be
                    astonished that a matter in which the credit of the state-was involved should
                    especially concern himself. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For in addition to
                    the responsibility that in a way belonged peculiarly to a consul of the year in
                    which the moneys had been contributed, he had also been the first to suggest
                    such contribution, since the treasury was empty and the common people unable to
                    pay a tax. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXVI. xxxv. 4 ff.,
                        9.</note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This reminder was welcomed by the senators,
                    and bidding the consuls to introduce the measure, they decreed that the money
                    should be paid in three instalments; that the consuls who were then in office
                    should pay the first in ready money, that the consuls of the third and fifth
                    years should pay two instalments. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> biennial payments. See Vol. IX. p. 40, note (
                            <date when="-0200">200 B.C.</date> ). Final settlement, however, was not
                        made until <date when="-0196">196 B.C.</date> ; XXXIII. xlii. 3. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thereafter all other concerns yielded place to
                    a single one, when the atrocities suffered by the Locrians <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. ix, esp. §§ 11 f.</note> but up to that time unknown
                    were spread <pb n="p.269"/> abroad by the arrival of their envoys. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> And it was <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 204</note> not so much the crime of Pleminius that
                    provoked men to anger as Scipio's partiality for him or else indifference.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The ten envoys of the Locrians, in soiled
                    and neglected clothing and holding out the woollen bands of suppliants and olive
                    branches, as is the custom of the Greeks, towards the consuls seated in the
                    Comitium, fell to the ground before the tribunal as they raised a mournful
                    plaint. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In answer to the consuls' question
                    they said that they were Locrians who had suffered from Quintus Pleminius, the
                    legatus, and the Roman soldiers such things as the Roman people would not wish
                    even the Carthaginians to suffer; that they begged the consuls to give them
                    permission to go before the senate and complain of their sufferings. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A hearing in the senate being granted, the
                    eldest of them said: "I know, conscript fathers, that in determining what weight
                    is to be given to our complaints in your presence very much depends upon your
                    being well informed both as to how Locri was betrayed to Hannibal, and how by
                    driving out Hannibal's garrison it was restored to your authority. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For if it prove that no guilt for the revolt attaches
                    to our council of state, and if it be at the same time evident that we returned
                    to your authority not by our consent only but also by our effort and our
                    courage, you will be all the more indignant that good and faithful allies are
                    receiving such outrageous treatment from your legatus and his soldiers.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But in my opinion enquiry into our revolts
                    should be put off in both cases to another time for two reasons. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The first is in order that the hearing may be in the
                    presence of Publius Scipio, who recovered Locri and <pb n="p.271"/> is our
                    witness for every act, the good and the bad. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> The second reason is
                    because, whatever our character is, we nevertheless did not deserve to suffer
                    these things that we have suffered. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> We cannot
                    conceal the truth, conscript fathers, that when we had a Punic garrison in our
                    citadel we suffered many shameful outrages both at the hands of Hamilcar,
                    commandant of the garrison, and from the Numidians and Africans. But what are
                    they in comparison with the things we are suffering today? <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> With kind indulgence, conscript fathers, give ear, I pray,
                    to what I shall reluctantly say. The entire human race is now in suspense as to
                    whether it is to see you, or the Carthaginians, lords of the whole world.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If one must judge Roman and Carthaginian
                    rule from what we Locrians either have suffered from them, or are at this very
                    moment suffering from your garrison, no one would fail to prefer them rather
                    than you as his masters. And yet observe how the Locrians are disposed towards
                    you. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Although from the Carthaginians we were
                    suffering wrongs so much less serious, we sought refuge with your general.
                    Although from your garrison we are suffering acts worse than those of an enemy,
                    we have brought our complaints nowhere else than to you. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Either you will have regard for our ruin, conscript
                    fathers, or else no help remains for us to pray for even from the immortal gods. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "Quintus Pleminius was sent as legatus with a
                    military force to recover Locri from the Carthaginians, and with that same force
                    he was left there. In this legatus of yours —for the depths of misery <pb
                        n="p.273"/> embolden me to speak freely —there <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> is nothing of a <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 204</note> human being, conscript fathers, except his
                    form and outward appearance, nothing of a Roman citizen except his bearing and
                    garments and the sound of the Latin language. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    He is a pest-bringing monster, like those of which myths say that, in order to
                    destroy mariners, they once had their abode on this side and that of the strait
                    by which we are separated from Sicily. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And if
                    he were content to be the only man to practise his criminal passion and greed
                    upon your allies, we in our long-suffering should still be filling up a single
                    whirlpool however deep. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As it is, he has made
                    every centurion and every soldier of yours a Pleminius; so universal has he
                    wished licence and dishonour to be. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> They all
                    rob, plunder, beat, wound, slay. They defile matrons, maidens and free-born
                    boys, dragged from the embrace of parents. Every day our city is captured, every
                    day it is plundered. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Day and night every part
                    of it re-echoes the wailing of women and children who are being seized and
                    carried off. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Knowing that, any one would
                    wonder either how we have the patience to endure, or how those who commit such
                    outrages are not yet sated with them. Neither can I retail them all, nor is it
                    worth your while to hear each thing that we have suffered. In a general
                    statement I shall embrace everything. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Here and in the following statement one finds an obvious reminiscence of
                        Cicero <hi rend="italics">in Verr.</hi> IV. 1; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">ibid.</hi> 57. </note>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> I tell you there is not a house at Locri, not
                    a man that has not suffered a wrong. I tell you there remains no kind of crime,
                    lust, avarice that has been overlooked in the case of any possible victim.
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> It is all but impossible to decide <pb
                        n="p.275"/> which of the two is the more revolting lot for a state <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> —when the
                    enemy have captured the city in war, or when a death-dealing tyrant has
                    overpowered it by force of arms. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> All things
                    that captured cities suffer we have suffered and at this very moment are
                    suffering, conscript fathers. All the crimes that the most cruel and despotic
                    tyrants inflict upon their helpless citizens Pleminius has inflicted upon us and
                    our children and our wives. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "There is one thing in regard to which
                    conscientious scruples implanted in our minds compel us to complain in
                    particular, and at the same time we would have you, conscript fathers, give us
                    your attention and, if you approve, free your state from impiety. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For we have seen with what punctiliousness you
                    worship, not your own gods merely, but even welcome them from abroad. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy represents the speaker as actually
                        having witnessed the stately ceremonial when the Magna Mater was welcomed;
                        xiv. 5-14. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> We have in our city a sanctuary of Proserpina,
                    a temple of whose sanctity I believe some report reached you in the war with
                    Pyrrhus. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. viii. 9 f.</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When on his return from Sicily he was passing
                    Locri in his fleet, among other shameful acts which he visited upon our state
                    for its loyalty to you, he despoiled the treasury of Proserpina <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Appian <hi rend="italics">Samn.</hi> 12
                        tells the story of Pyrrhus' sacrilege. Plutarch omits it. Cf. Diodorus Sic.
                        XXVII. iv. 3; Val. Max. I. i. Ext. 1. </note> as well, which had been
                    untouched down to that time. And, that done, he put the money on shipboard,
                    setting out himself by land. What happened, conscript fathers, in consequence?
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the following day the fleet was
                    shattered by a terrible storm, and all the ships which had the sacred money on
                    board were cast upon our shores. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having at
                    last learned from this great disaster that the gods do exist, the haughtiest <pb
                        n="p.277"/> of kings ordered that all the money should be sought <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> out and
                    restored to the treasure-chambers of Proserpina. And yet never thereafter did he
                    meet with any success, and having been driven out of Italy, he rashly entered
                    Argos by night and died an inconspicuous and inglorious death. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For Pyrrhus' death v. Plutarch, <hi
                            rend="italics">Pyrrhus</hi> 34; Strabo VIII. vi. 18 (before the walls);
                        Justin XXV. 5. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Although your legatus and the tribunes had
                    heard all this and a thousand other occurrences which were repeated to them, not
                    merely to increase religious feeling but as facts repeatedly confirmed for us
                    and our ancestors by the evident intervention of the goddess, they nevertheless
                    dared to lay sacrilegious hands upon those treasure-chambers that were not to be
                    touched, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> and by that unspeakable plunder to
                    bring pollution upon themselves and their homes and upon your soldiers.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> With such men, conscript fathers, I beg of
                    you for conscience' sake not to undertake any action either in Italy or in
                    Africa until you first atone for their crime, lest for the sacrilege committed
                    they make amends not only by their own blood but also by a disaster to the
                    state. </p>
                <p> "Even now, however, the wrath of the goddess is not idle, conscript fathers, as
                    regards either your commanders or your men. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Several times already have they clashed with each other in actual battle.
                    Pleminius was in command of the one faction, of the other faction two tribunes
                    of the soldiers. They have fought each other with the sword as fiercely as
                    against the Carthaginians, and by their madness would have given Hannibal a
                    chance to regain Locri, had not Scipio forestalled that in answer to our call
                    for help. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> True, you may say, the soldiers
                    polluted by sacrilege are indeed frenzied, but the power of the goddess has not
                    been manifest in punishing the <pb n="p.279"/> commanders themselves. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> On the contrary, it is <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> there that it was most
                    evident. The tribunes were scourged by the legatus; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. above, ix. 4 ff.</note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> whereupon the legatus was isolated by a ruse
                    of the tribunes, and besides receiving wounds in every part of his body, he was
                    left half-dead after even his nose and ears had been mutilated. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Then when the legatus had recovered from his wounds
                    and the tribunes of the soldiers had been thrown into chains, then, after
                    scourging them and racking them with all the torments applied to slaves, he put
                    them to death, then forbade burial of the dead. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> "Such are the penalties the goddess has
                    exacted of those who despoil her temple, nor will she cease to drive them on by
                    every form of madness until the consecrated money has been replaced in her
                    treasury. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Our ancestors once in a serious war
                    with the Crotonians <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For Croton cf.
                        XXIV. iii. 1 ff., and for the disastrous battle at the Sagra river (near
                        Caulonia) v. Strabo VI. i. 10; Justin XX. 3. </note> desired to bring that
                    money over into the city, since the temple is outside the city. In the night a
                    voice from the sanctuary was heard: let them keep their hands off; the goddess
                    will defend her temples. Since conscientious scruples were raised against moving
                    the treasure away, they planned to surround the temple with a wall of defence.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The walls had already been raised to a
                    considerable height when suddenly they fell in ruins. But both at this time and
                    at that, and often on other occasions, the goddess has either defended her abode
                    and her temple, or else has exacted heavy penalties from those who profaned
                    them. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> To avenge wrongs done to us, however,
                    no one but you, conscript fathers, <pb n="p.281"/> has the power —and may no one
                    else have it! <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> To <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> you and your protection we
                    have come for refuge as suppliants. It makes no difference to us whether you
                    allow Locri to remain under that legatus, under that garrison, or surrender it
                    to angry Hannibal and the Carthaginians for punishment. We do not demand that
                    you at once believe us in regard to an absent defendant, his case unheard. Let
                    him come, let him hear in person, in person let him disprove. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> If there is any crime which a man can perpetrate upon human
                    beings that he has failed to commit upon us, we do not refuse to endure all the
                    same wrongs again, if that is possible for us, while he is to be acquitted of
                    every crime against gods and men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the envoys had thus spoken and Fabius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As <hi rend="italics">princeps
                            senatus</hi> he speaks first; cf. XXVII. xi. 12 and below, xxxvii. 1.
                    </note> asked them whether they had carried such complaints to Publius Scipio,
                    they replied that emissaries had been sent, but that he was occupied with
                    preparations for war and had either already crossed over to Africa, or was about
                    to do so within a few days; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and they had
                    learned what partiality for his legatus was felt by the general-in-command when,
                    after hearing the charges of Pleminius and those of the tribunes, he put the
                    tribunes in chains and, though the legatus was equally guilty or even more so,
                    left him in that command. </p>
                <p> When the envoys had been ordered to retire from the Senate House, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Curia had been inaugurated as a
                        temple, that decrees of the senate might be valid; so Varro in Gellius XIV.
                        vii. 7. Cf. XXVI. xxx. 11; xxxi. 11. </note> not Pleminius only but also
                    Scipio was savagely attacked in the speeches of leading men. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> First and foremost Quintus Fabius charged that he was by
                    nature adapted to corrupt his soldiers' discipline. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Thus even in Spain, he said, almost more soldiers had been
                    lost in a mutiny than <pb n="p.283"/> by war; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> An exaggerated statement, of course, for which <hi
                            rend="italics">prope</hi> is half-apologetic. Cf. XXVIII. xxvi. 2.
                    </note> that after the manner of a foreign tyrant he <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> gave free rein to the
                    excesses of his soldiers and was also cruel to them. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He then appended to his speech an equally ruthless
                    resolution: that it was the will of the senate that Pleminius, the legatus, be
                    brought to Rome bound and plead his cause in chains, and if the complaints of
                    the Locrians should prove true, that he be put to death in the prison and his
                    property confiscated; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that Publius Scipio,
                    having left his province without orders of the senate, be recalled, and that the
                    tribunes of the plebs be urged to bring before the people a bill to annul his
                    command; that the senate should make answer to the Locrians face to face that
                    neither the senate nor the Roman people approved of the wrongs which they
                    complained had been inflicted upon them; that they be declared good men and good
                    allies and friends; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that their children, their
                    wives and whatever else had been taken away by violence be restored to them;
                    that all the money removed from the treasure-chambers of Proserpina be sought
                    out and twice that amount be restored to her treasury; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and that expiatory rites be performed, with the provision
                    that the question be first laid before the college of pontiffs, in view of the
                    removal, opening and profanation of the sacred treasure, what expiations they
                    would order to be made, to what divinities, with what victims; that all the
                    soldiers who were at Locri be transported to Sicily; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> that four cohorts of Latin allies be brought to Locri as a
                    garrison. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Not all the senators could be asked their
                    opinion on that day owing to the heat of party feeling for <pb n="p.285"/>
                    Scipio and against Scipio. In addition to the crime <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> of Pleminius and the
                    sufferings of the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> Locrians, they kept
                    censuring even the personal appearance of the general-in-chief, as not even
                    soldierly, not to say un- Roman; that wearing a Greek mantle and sandals he
                    strolled about in the gymnasium, giving his attention to books in Greek and
                    physical exercise; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plutarch makes
                        Cato, as quaestor to Scipio, complain that the general was extravagant,
                        pampering his troops and giving too much time to palaestra and theatre; <hi
                            rend="italics">Cat. Mai.</hi> iii. 5 ff. Cf. below, p. 307 and note 2.
                        284 </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> that with equal indolence and self-indulgence
                    his entire retinue <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This would include
                        such high officers as legati, as well as friends. </note> was enjoying the
                    charms of Syracuse; that Carthage and Hannibal had been forgotten; <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> that the entire army, being spoiled by lack of
                    restraint and, like the army formerly at Sucro in Spain, like the troops now at
                    Locri, was more to be feared by allies than by the enemy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although some of these taunts were true, some
                    half-true and hence plausible, nevertheless the motion of Quintus Metellus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Of, x. 2; xi. 9 f. Consul in <date
                            when="-0206">206 B.C.</date> ; XXVIII. x. 2, 8. </note> carried the day.
                    In agreement with Maximus on the other points, he disagreed with him so far as
                    concerned Scipio, the man whom the state chose not long before, he said, in
                    spite of his youth as sole general to recover Spain; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> then, after Spain had been rewon from the enemy, elected
                    him consul to put an end to the Punic war, and counted upon him to draw Hannibal
                    out of Italy and to conquer Africa. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> How then
                    was it logical for him, as if he were a Quintus Pleminius, suddenly to be all
                    but condemned without a hearing, recalled from his province, although the
                    Locrians said that the criminal acts against them of which they complained had
                    been committed when Scipio was not even present, and nothing else could be
                    charged <pb n="p.287"/> against him than slowness to anger, or else reluctance
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> in
                    sparing his legatus? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His proposal, he said,
                    was that Marcus Pomponius, the praetor, to whom Sicily had been allotted as his
                    province, should within three days leave for the province; that the consuls
                    should choose ten legati at their discretion from the senate, to be sent with
                    the praetor, as also two tribunes of the plebs and an aedile; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A plebeian aedile (§ 11), to carry out
                        the orders of the tribunes. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that with these men as assessors the praetor
                    should conduct an examination; if the offences of which the Locrians complained
                    had been committed by the command or with the consent of Publius Scipio, they
                    should order him to retire from his province; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    if Publius Scipio should have already crossed over into Africa, the tribunes of
                    the plebs and the aedile should go to Africa with two of the legati —those
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> whom the praetor should judge most
                    competent —the tribunes and aedile to bring Scipio away, the legati to be in
                    command of the army until anew general-in-command should reach that army;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> if Marcus Pomponius-and the ten legati
                    should find that the acts had been committed neither by order of Publius Scipio
                    nor with his consent, that Scipio should remain with the army and carry on the
                    war as he had planned. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A decree of the senate
                    to this effect having been passed, the tribunes of the plebs were requested
                    either to arrange among themselves or to choose by lot which two of them should
                    go with the praetor and legati. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The matter of
                    expiation for all that in the temple of Proserpina at Locri had been touched and
                    profaned and carried away was referred to the college of pontiffs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the plebs, Marcus Claudius
                        <pb n="p.289"/> Marcellus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. xi.
                        13; XXVII. xxvi. 12; xxvii. 7. Consul in <date when="-0196">196 B.C.</date>
                        ; censor <date when="-0189">189 B.C.</date> ; XXXIII. xxiv. 1; XXXVII.
                        lviii. 2. </note> and Marcus Cincius Alimentus <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Almost certainly a brother of Lucius, the historian
                        (frequently mentioned in XXVI-XXVII). As tribune in this year he proposed
                        the Lex Cincia to limit gifts; cf. Cicero <hi rend="italics">Cat. Mai.</hi>
                        10. Livy fails to mention the law until XXXIV. iv. 9, in a speech of Cato as
                        consul, <date when="-0195">195 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> departed
                    with the praetor and ten legati. A plebeian aedile was added to their number,
                    and either in case Scipio in Sicily should fail to obey the praetor, or if he
                    should have crossed already into Africa, the tribunes were to order the aedile
                    to arrest him, and by virtue of their inviolable authority they were to bring
                    him back. It was their plan to go to Locri first and then to Messana. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But so far as Pleminius is concerned we have
                    two reports. Some authorities relate that, on hearing what had been done at
                    Rome, he was on his way into exile at Neapolis when he happened to encounter
                    Quintus Metellus, one of the legati, and that he was forcibly brought back by
                    him to Regium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Others say that Scipio himself
                    sent a legatus with thirty horsemen of the first order, to throw Quintus
                    Pleminius into chains and with him the leaders of the outbreak. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> All of them, whether by Scipio's order earlier or at this
                    time by that of the praetor, were delivered into the custody of the men of
                    Regium. </p>
                <p> The praetor and legati went to Locri and, as they had been instructed, made
                    religion their first concern. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For they sought
                    out and restored to the treasure-chambers all the sacred money, both what was in
                    the hands of Pleminius and what was in the possession of the soldiers, together
                    with what they had themselves brought with them; and they performed the rite of
                    expiation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then the praetor summoned the
                    soldiers to an assembly, ordered their units to march out of the city, and
                    assigned a site in the plain for their camp, with a threatening edict in case
                    any soldier should either remain in the <pb n="p.291"/> city or carry out with
                    him what was not his own. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 204</note> In this he stated that he gave permission to
                    the Locrians to seize any possession a man should recognize as his; and if
                    anything was not produced he should demand its restitution. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Above all, he said, he ruled that free persons should be
                    restored to the Locrians without delay; that a heavy penalty would be paid by
                    the man who did not restore them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thereupon he held an assembly of the Locrians
                    and said that the Roman people and senate restored to them their independence
                    and their own laws; that if anyone desired to bring charges against Pleminius or
                    any other man, let him follow him to Regium. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    As regarded Publius Scipio, should they wish, he said, to make complaint in the
                    name of their state, claiming that such wicked deeds as had been committed at
                    Locri against gods and men had been done by command of Publius Scipio or with
                    his consent, let them send envoys to Messana; there with his assessors he would
                    conduct the inquiry. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Locrians thanked the
                    praetor and his legati, the senate and the Roman people. They would go, they
                    said, to prefer charges against Pleminius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As
                    for Scipio, although he was not sufficiently pained by the wrongs done to their
                    state, he was such a man as they would prefer to have as their friend rather
                    than as an enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They had definitely
                    ascertained that the many unspeakable crimes had not been committed either by
                    order or consent of Publius Scipio; but either he had trusted Pleminius too much
                    and themselves too little; or else for some men it was natural to disapprove of
                    misdoing but to lack sufficient spirit to punish the misdeeds. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Both the praetor and his assessors were
                    relieved of <pb n="p.293"/> the burden —no slight one either —of a court of
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    inquiry concerning Scipio. Pleminius and with him some thirty-two men they found
                    guilty <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> at a preliminary hearing; cf. xxii. 7 ff. The
                        charge would be treason, <hi rend="italics">perduellio.</hi>
                    </note> and sent in chains to Rome. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They
                    themselves went to Scipio with the further intention to see for themselves what
                    had been common talk in regard to the dress and indolent habits of the general
                    and lax discipline of his soldiers, and to report back to Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While they were on their way to Syracuse
                    Scipio prepared tangible evidence, not words, in his defence. He ordered the
                    entire army to be concentrated there, and the fleet to be cleared for action, as
                    if on that day he must fight on land and sea with the Carthaginians. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> On the day of their arrival they were hospitably
                    entertained, and the next day he showed them his land and naval forces, not
                    merely drawn up in line, but the soldiers in manœuvres <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> It is a sham battle, as <hi rend="italics">et
                            ipsam</hi> proves. No parade here; no more than in XXVI. li. 4. </note>
                    and the fleet likewise manœuvring in mimicry of a naval battle in the harbour.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then the praetor and the legati were
                    conducted on a tour of inspection of arsenals and magazines and other equipment
                    for war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And so much was their admiration
                    aroused for particular things and for the sum total that they fully believed the
                    Carthaginian people could be defeated either by that general and army or by no
                    other, and bade <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> him with the blessing of the
                    gods to cross over, and at the first possible moment to bring to the Roman
                    people the fulfilment of the hope inspired on the day on which all the centuries
                        <pb n="p.295"/> had named him consul first. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> So happy also were they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 204</note> on leaving the city, it was if they were to
                    carry to Rome the news of a victory, not of a magnificent preparation for war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Pleminius and those who were involved in the
                    same charge, upon their arrival in Rome, were at once put in the prison. And
                    when first brought before the people by the tribunes, while men's minds were
                    already filled with the sufferings of the Locrians, they found no room left for
                    pity. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Later, as they were brought out
                    repeatedly, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A defendant charged with
                            <hi rend="italics">perduellio</hi> was brought before a <hi
                            rend="italics">contio</hi> in the Forum three times, not on successive
                        days. At the close of the third <hi rend="italics">contio</hi> the tribunes
                        pronounced judgment, repeating their demand for a penalty or changing it in
                        either direction. Then they announced a final hearing 28 days later( <hi
                            rend="italics">quarta accusatio</hi> ). On that date the case would be
                        finally decided by vote of the <hi rend="italics">comitia tribute</hi> (if a
                        fine was demanded), or of the <hi rend="italics">centuriata</hi> (if a death
                        penalty). Cf. XXVI. iii. 9 ff. (Vol. VII. pp. 13 ff. and notes p. 12);
                        Mommsen, <hi rend="italics">Staatsrecht</hi> III. 354 if. Confinement was in
                        the Career, § 7; cf. p. 296, n. 1. </note> men's anger was subsiding as
                    animosity now waned, and even Pleminius' disfigurement and the memory of the
                    absent Scipio won them support among the populace. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He died, however, in prison before his trial in the
                    assembly of the people could be completed. </p>
                <p> Clodius Licinus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A younger
                        contemporary of Livy, consul suffectus in A.D. 4. His history must have
                        begun with the end of the Second Punic War. Cf. Suet. <hi rend="italics">de
                            Gram.</hi> 20. Rare in Livy is so precise a reference to any authority.
                    </note> in the third book of his Roman History relates of this Pleminius that
                    during the votive games which Africanus was conducting at Rome in his second
                    consulship, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <date when="-0194">194 B.C.</date> ; XXXIV. xliv. 6 if., the same story
                        under a different date and with omission of the source. </note> he made an
                    attempt, with the aid of certain men whom he had bribed, to set fire to the city
                    in a number of places, in order to have a chance to break out of prison and
                    escape; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.297"/> that then, when his crime was revealed, he was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> consigned
                    to the Tullianum <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The older
                        underground chamber beneath the Carcer. Mere mention of it implies that
                        Pleminius was executed there, as is explicitly stated <hi rend="italics"
                            >l.c.</hi> xliv. 8. Cf. xix. 5; Val. Max. I. i. 21. </note> in
                    accordance with a decree of the senate. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In regard to Scipio no action was taken
                    anywhere except in the senate, in which both legati and tribunes united in
                    praise of the fleet, army and general. Consequently the senate voted that at the
                    earliest possible moment the crossing to Africa must take place, and that out of
                    the armies then in Sicily Scipio should be permitted to choose for himself what
                    forces he would transport with him to Africa, and what he would leave as a
                    garrison <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> for the province. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were in progress among the
                    Romans, the Carthaginians on their part, placing watch-towers on all the
                    promontories, had passed an anxious winter, gathering information and alarmed by
                    each fresh report. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And then, as no small
                    factor in the defence of Africa, they added an alliance of their own with King
                    Syphax, in reliance chiefly upon whom the Roman, they had believed, intended to
                    cross over to Africa. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal the son of
                    Gisgo had not merely a guest-friendship with the king, of which mention has been
                    made above <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The formal bond of a <hi
                            rend="italics">hospitium</hi> with Hasdrubal was implied in XXVIII.
                        xviii but not exactly mentioned. As for Scipio, cf. below, xxiv. 3. </note>
                    —when Scipio and Hasdrubal coming from Spain arrived, as it happened, at the
                    same time —but also the first proposal of a marriage tie was made, in which the
                    king was to marry Hasdrubal's daughter. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To
                    carry the matter through and to fix a time for the wedding, Hasdrubal went to
                    him; for the maiden was already of marriageable age. On perceiving that he was
                        <pb n="p.299"/> fired with passion —and more than all barbarians <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> the
                    Numidians are prone to sensuality —he summoned the maiden from Carthage and
                    hastened the wedding. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And in the midst of
                    congratulations on other grounds, in order that a public compact might be added
                    to the private, an alliance between the Carthaginian people and the king was
                    cemented by an oath, while a pledge was given by both sides that they would have
                    the same friends and enemies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, however, remembered not only the
                    alliance with Scipio into which the king had entered, but also how naturally
                    characterless and fickle are barbarians. He feared that if Scipio should cross
                    over to Africa this marriage would be a slender bond. Consequently while the
                    Numidian, fired by his newfound love, was in his power, with the help also of
                    the young woman's allurements, Hasdrubal prevailed upon him to send ambassadors
                    to Scipio in Sicily, and through these men he was to warn Scipio not to cross
                    over to Africa in reliance upon his previous promises. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They were to say that he was <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> linked with the Carthaginian people both by his marriage to
                    a citizen of Carthage, daughter of the Hasdrubal whom Scipio had seen received
                    as a guest in his own house, and by a public treaty as well; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> that in the first place he wished that the Romans would
                    carry on war with the Carthaginians, as they had done hitherto, far from Africa,
                    making it unnecessary for him to be involved in their conflicts and to follow
                    the arms of this side or that, rejecting alliance with the other side;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that if Scipio did not keep away from
                    Africa and moved his army up to Carthage, it would be necessary for him to fight
                    both for the land of Africa, in which he too had <pb n="p.301"/> been born, and
                    for the native city of his wife and for <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> her father and her home. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With these instructions ambassadors were sent
                    to Scipio by the king, and they met him at Syracuse. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio had lost, to be sure, an important factor for the
                    campaign in Africa and a high hope; nevertheless, sending the messengers back to
                    Africa promptly, before the matter should be widely reported, he gave them a
                    letter to the king. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In this he insistently
                    admonished him not to prove false to the claims of a guest-friendship entered
                    into with himself, nor to those of an alliance contracted with the Roman people,
                    nor to divine law, to honour, to the clasped hands, to the gods as witnesses and
                    arbiters of compacts. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the arrival of the
                    Numidians could not be kept secret, for they had roamed about the city and had
                    showed themselves at headquarters; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Formerly the palace of King Hiero II; Cicero <hi rend="italics">in
                            Verr.</hi> IV. 118; V. 80. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and if the object of their mission was passed
                    over in silence there would be danger that the facts might of themselves
                    transpire, all the more from the very attempt to conceal them, and that the fear
                    of having to fight at the same time with the king and the Carthaginians might
                    overtake the army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For that reason Scipio
                    diverted men's attention from the truth by preoccupation with false statements,
                    and summoning the soldiers to an assembly, he told them that there must be no
                    further delay; that the kings, their allies, were insisting that he cross over
                    to Africa as soon as possible. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Masinissa, he
                    said, had previously come in person to Gaius Laelius complaining because they
                    were wasting time in hesitation; and now Syphax was sending ambassadors, stating
                    that he also was at a loss to explain what was the reason for a delay so
                    protracted, and <pb n="p.303"/> demanding either that the army be at last <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    transported <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> to Africa, or, if their plans
                    had been changed, that he be informed, so that he on his part might take
                    measures for himself and his kingdom. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, since now everything had been duly fitted out and made ready and
                    the situation admitted of no further delay, Scipio said <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> it was his intention to shift his fleet to Lilybaeum and
                    concentrate there all his infantry and cavalry forces, then on the first day
                    that offered a passage to his ships to cross over with the blessing of the gods
                    to Africa. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He sent a letter to Marcus
                    Pomponius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. xx. 4, 8; xiii. 2, 6:
                        XXVIII. xlv. 12 (his mission to Delphi). </note> requesting him, if he
                    approved, to come to Lilybaeum, so that they might jointly decide which
                    particular legions to transport to Africa and how large a number of men.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He likewise sent orders round the entire
                    coastline to have all merchantmen pressed into the service and concentrated at
                    Lilybaeum. </p>
                <p> When all the soldiers and ships in Sicily had been brought together at Lilybaeum
                    and the city could not contain the multitude of men nor the harbour the ships,
                    such was the ardour of every man <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> for the
                    passage to Africa that it seemed as though they were being led, not to a war but
                    to assured rewards of victory. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Especially the
                    soldiers who were left of the army at Cannae believed that under that general
                    and no other, by active duty for the state they could bring their ignominious
                    service to an end. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Their appeals,
                        such as that in <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> vi. 2-23 (eight years before), had been of
                        no avail. They saw no service as combat troops in Sicily, not even in the
                        long siege of Syracuse. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And Scipio did not in the least scorn soldiers
                    of that kind, <pb n="p.305"/> as he knew that the disaster at Cannae had not
                    been <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    incurred by their cowardice, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Here
                        Scipio had personal knowledge, having been a tribune of the soldiers at
                        Cannae; XXII. liii. 2; Val. Max. V. vi. 7. </note> and that there were no
                    soldiers in the Roman army who were such veterans and as highly trained not only
                    in battles of different kinds but also in besieging cities. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The fifth and sixth legions were those from Cannae. Having
                    said he would transport these legions to Africa, he inspected the soldiers one
                    by one, and leaving those whom he believed to be unfit, he substituted for them
                    men whom he had brought with him from Italy, and recruited the legions to such
                    an extent that each had six thousand two hundred infantry <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">This is the maximum known for a legion.</note> and three
                    hundred cavalry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In like manner he chose
                    foot-soldiers and horse from the Latin allies out of the army which fought at
                    Cannae. </p>
                <p> XXV. As to the number of soldiers transported to Africa the authorities differ
                    by no small figure. In some I find that ten thousand infantry, two thousand two
                    hundred cavalry were embarked; in others sixteen thousand infantry, sixteen
                    hundred cavalry; in others the total is more than doubled —thirty-five thousand
                    infantry and cavalry. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some authorities have
                    not introduced the figures, and it is among these that I should myself prefer to
                    be counted in view of the uncertainty. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Coelius, while he gives no figures, nevertheless immensely increases the
                    impression of great numbers. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Another
                        example of Coelius' rhetorical exaggeration is found in xxvii. 14 f. </note>
                    He says that birds fell to the ground owing to the shouts of the soldiers, and
                    that such a multitude boarded the ships that not a human being seemed to be left
                    either in Italy or Sicily. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.307"/>
                <p> That the soldiers should board the ships in good <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> order and without
                    confusion the general took upon himself. As for the crews, Gaius Laelius, who
                    was admiral of the fleet, ordered them to go on board first, and kept them
                    there. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The duty of loading supplies was
                    assigned to Marcus Pomponius, the praetor. Rations for forty-five days —of these
                    cooked rations for fifteen days —were placed on board. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When now they had all embarked, Scipio sent ships' boats
                    round with orders that pilots and masters from all the ships and two soldiers
                    from each should assemble before the headquarters to receive commands. When they
                    were assembled he first asked them if they had put on board water for men and
                    beasts for just as many days as they had grain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> When they replied that there was water for forty-five days on board, he
                    thereupon gave orders to the soldiers to remain quiet and ensure silence in
                    proper obedience to the seamen and without interference, that these might
                    perform their duties. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> With twenty warships,
                    he said, he and Lucius Scipio <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He had
                        been with his older brother in Spain (XXVIII. iii. 2 ff.; iv. 2 ff.; xvii.
                        1) and in Sicily (above, vii. 2); consul in <date when="-0190">190
                            B.C.</date> with Laelius; XXXVI. xlv. 9. </note> on the right wing would
                    protect the transports; on the left wing the same number of war-ships and Gaius
                    Laelius, admiral of the fleet, with Marcus Porcius Cato, who was at that time
                    quaestor; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> His quaestorship in this
                        year is attested by Cicero <hi rend="italics">Cat.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">Mai.</hi> 10; <hi rend="italics">Brutus</hi> 60; not in
                            <date when="-0205">205 B.C.</date> , as Nepos <hi rend="italics"
                            >Cato</hi> i. 3. Plutarch has him return in protest from Sicily to Rome,
                        iii. 7. </note> that war-ships should have one lantern for each ship,
                    transports two for each; that on the flagship the designation at night <pb
                        n="p.309"/> would be three lanterns. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He
                    ordered the pilots to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 204</note> steer for the Emporia. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Trading centres ( <hi rend="italics">emporia)</hi>
                        along the western shore of the Gulf of Gabès (Syrtis Minor) gave this name
                        to an entire region. It extended southward from Leptis Minor (100 miles from
                        Carthage) and Thapsus. Cf. xxxiii. 9; XXXIV. lxii. 3; Polybius III. xxiii.
                        2; XXXI. xxi; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> V. 25. So public an
                        announcement of a distant beachhead forces us to suspect that Scipio really
                        intended to land near Utica, after misleading the enemy. Before the great
                        convoy reached Africa spies could easily bring to Carthage news of the
                        order. Cf. note on xxvii. 9; Gsell, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> III.
                        213; Zielinski in <hi rend="italics">Riv. di storia antica</hi> III. 74 f.
                    </note> There the soil is very fertile and for that reason the region supplies
                    everything in abundance; and the natives are unwarlike, as is usually the case
                    in a fertile country, and it seemed that they could be overpowered before aid
                    could be sent from Carthage. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> But
                        remoteness from Carthage would mean a greatly increased distance from
                        Sicily, and on the long passage south-ward Roman ships would be in constant
                        danger of attack, with few ports in which they might seek even a temporary
                        refuge. The <hi rend="italics">fertilissimus ager</hi> was little more than
                        a strip <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> —one more reason to believe that
                        no Roman general would seriously propose to launch a campaign against
                        Carthage from such a coast. </note> After he had issued these commands they
                    were ordered to return to their ships and on the following day, with the
                    blessing of the gods, to cast off at the given signal. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Many Roman fleets had sailed from Sicily and
                    out of that very harbour. Yet not only during that war was there never a sailing
                    so spectacular and no wonder, since most of the fleets had sailed out merely to
                    plunder-but there had been nothing similar even in the previous war. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And yet if one had based his comparison upon the size
                    of the fleet, more than once <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Exactly
                        twice: in <date when="-0256">256 B.C.</date> L. Manlius Vulso and M. Atilius
                        Regulus (xxviii. 5) with 330 war-ships (Polybius I. xxv. 7; xxix. 1); in
                            <date when="-0255">255 B.C.</date> M. Aemilius Paulus and Ser. Fulvius
                        Nobilior with 350, but no army, and shipwrecked on their return; <hi
                            rend="italics">ibid.</hi> xxxvi. 10 ff. </note> before had two consuls
                    with two armies made the passage, and there had been almost as many war-ships in
                    those fleets as now transports with which Scipio was crossing over. For in
                    addition to forty war-ships only, he carried his army across on about four
                    hundred transports. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But the second war was
                    made to appear to the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> Romans more terrible
                        <pb n="p.311"/> than the first both by being carried on in Italy and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> by the
                    immense losses which befell so many armies, with the death of their generals at
                    the same time. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Furthermore Scipio, whom men
                    praised as a general partly because of his brave deeds, partly because of a good
                    fortune peculiarly his own —a matter of the greatest importance to his growing
                    celebrity —had commanded attention, as had also the very thought, not hazarded
                    by any previous general in this war, of crossing the sea. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> For he had spread the report that he was making the passage
                    in order to draw Hannibal out of Italy and, shifting its scene, to bring the war
                    to an end in Africa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To see that sight there
                    had flocked to the harbour a crowd made up, not only of all the inhabitants of
                    Lilybaeum, but of all the delegations from Sicily which had arrived to show
                    their respect as an escort to Scipio, and of those that had followed the praetor
                    of the province, Marcus Pomponius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In addition
                    the legions that were being left behind in Sicily had turned out to escort their
                    fellow-soldiers. And not only was the fleet a spectacle for those who viewed it
                    from the shore, but also the whole densely crowded shore on this side and that
                    was a sight for those who were sailing. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the day dawned Scipio on his flagship,
                    after silence had been secured by a herald, prayed: <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Ye gods and goddesses who inhabit seas and lands, I pray and beseech you
                        that whatever under my authority has been done, is being done, and shall
                        henceforth be done, may prosper for me, for the Roman people and the
                        commons, for allies and Latins who by land, by sea, and by rivers follow the
                            <pb n="p.313"/> lead, authority and auspices of the Roman people <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> and of
                        myself; and that ye lend your kind aid to all those acts and make them bear
                        good fruit; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that when the foe has been
                        vanquished, ye bring the victors home with me safe and sound, adorned with
                        spoils, laden with booty, and in triumph; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        that ye grant power to punish opponents and enemies; and that ye bestow upon
                        the Roman people and upon me the power to visit upon the state of the
                        Carthaginians the fate that the people of Carthage have endeavoured to visit
                        upon our state. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Immediately after this prayer a victim was
                    slain and Scipio threw the organs raw into the sea, as is customary, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For this practice when ships were
                        setting sail with ceremony v. Cicero <hi rend="italics">N.D.</hi> III. 51
                            <hi rend="italics">fin.;</hi> cf. Servius on <hi rend="italics"
                            >Aeneid</hi> V. 238; Macrobius <hi rend="italics">Sat.</hi> III. ii. 2
                        ff. </note> and by a trumpet gave the signal to sail. A favouring wind
                    sufficiently strong quickly carried them out of sight of land. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> And after mid-day they encountered a fog, so that with
                    difficulty could they avoid collisions between the ships. In the open sea the
                    wind was gentler. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Through the following night
                    the same fog held; and when the sun was up, it was dispersed and the wind
                    increased in force. Already they were in sight of land. Not very long afterwards
                    the pilot told Scipio that Africa was not more than five miles away; that they
                    sighted the Promontory of Mercury; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This headland, now Cap Bon (Ras Adar), marks the eastern entrance to the Bay
                        of Tunis. It is 45 miles from Carthage, and is the nearest point to Sicily.
                        Cf. Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> V. 23 f.; Strabo XVII. iii, 13, 16;
                        Mela I. 34. </note> if he should order him to steer for that, the entire
                    fleet would soon be in port. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio, now that
                    the land was visible, after a prayer to the gods that <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> his sight of Africa might be a <pb n="p.315"/> blessing to
                    the state and to himself, gave orders to <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> make sail and to seek
                    another landing-place for the ships farther down. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> farther along the coast. Cf. Caesar <hi
                            rend="italics">B.G.</hi> IV. 36 <hi rend="italics">fin.</hi> He meant
                            <hi rend="italics">-inside</hi> the Bay (not towards the Emporia), there
                        being no harbour on either side of the Cape. His order to the helmsmen (at
                        Lilybaeum, xxv. 12) to steer for the Emporia was probably a ruse (cf. note
                        there); or it merely named a rendezvous in case the convoy should be
                        scattered. A complete change in his plan for the campaign could not be made
                        suddenly. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They were running before the same wind; but
                    at about the same time as on the preceding day a fog appeared cutting off the
                    sight of land, and under the weight of fog the wind dropped. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Then night added to all their uncertainties; so they cast
                    anchor, that the ships might not collide or drift onto the shore. When day
                    dawned the same wind sprang up and by dispelling the fog revealed the whole
                    African coast. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scipio inquired what the
                    nearest promontory was, and upon being told it was called Cape of the Fair God,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> of Apollo, translating Polybius' <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">ton= Kalon= a)kroth/rion</foreign> (III. xxii. 5), who
                        in the same passage has <foreign xml:lang="greek">to\ Kalo\n
                            a)kroth/rion</foreign> (xxiii. 1). Cf. <hi rend="italics"
                            >Apollinis,</hi> XXX. xxiv. 8; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H. l.c.;</hi>
                        Mela I. 34; <foreign xml:lang="greek">)Apollw/nion,</foreign> Dio Cass.
                        (Zonaras) IX. xii. 3 and Strabo XVII. <hi rend="italics">l. c.</hi> The
                        modern name is Ras Sidi Ali el Mekki. </note> he said <quote>A welcome omen!
                        steer your ships this way!</quote> There the fleet came into port and all
                    the troops were disembarked. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Inside
                        the Cape, probably near modern Porto Farina, not far from Utica; Appian <hi
                            rend="italics">Pun.</hi> 13 <hi rend="italics">fin.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That the passage was successful and free from
                    alarm and disorder I have accepted on the authority of many Greek and Latin
                    writers. Coelius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. xxv. 3. We may,
                        however, suspect a slip of Livy's memory, or an error in verification of a
                        source. See p. 316, n. 1. </note> alone describes all the terrors of weather
                    and waves —everything short of saying that the ships were overwhelmed by the
                    seas. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He relates that finally the fleet was
                    swept by the storm away from Africa to the island of Aegimurus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> North-west of the Prom. Mercurii
                        (Hermaeum) and about 30 miles north-east of Carthage, now el Djamur (also
                        called Zembra); XXX. xxiv. 9, 11 f.; Strabo II. v. 19 <hi rend="italics"
                            >fin.;</hi> VI. ii. 11 <hi rend="italics">fin.</hi> Pliny has two
                        Aegimoeroe, V. 42. </note> and that from there the proper <pb n="p.317"/>
                    course was regained with difficulty; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and that
                    as the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    ships were all but sinking the soldiers, without waiting for an order from the
                    general, made their way to the shore in small boats, as though they had been
                    shipwrecked, with no arms and in the greatest disorder. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This entire statement about storm and wreck is
                        disproved by a fragment (41) of Coelius' Book VI preserved by Nonius <hi
                            rend="italics">s.v. metari,</hi> p. 199 L. The fragment unquestionably
                        refers to this landing. Cf. H. Peter, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Rom.
                            Rell.</hi> I. 159; Gsell <hi rend="italics">op.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">cit.</hi> 212. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After landing their troops the Romans laid out
                    a camp on the nearest heights. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By this time,
                    first from the sight of the fleet, and then from the commotion produced as they
                    were disembarking, apprehension and panic had reached not only the farms near
                    the coast but even into the cities. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For it was
                    not merely the massed humanity that, interspersed with columns of women and
                    children, had filled all the roads in every direction, but cattle also driven
                    before them by the farmers, so that one would have said Africa was suddenly
                    being deserted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But even in the cities they
                    inspired greater alarm than that which they had brought with them. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Especially at Carthage the uproar was almost like
                    that of a captured city. For since the consulship of Marcus Atilius Regulus and
                    Lucius Manlius, for almost fifty years <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">In</hi> reality just 52 years (256- <date when="-0204"
                            >204 B.C.</date> ); cf. xxvi. 2, note. </note> they had seen no Roman
                    forces except only predatory fleets, by means of which descents had been made on
                    farms near the sea; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and seizing whatever
                    chance had put in their way, the men had always raced back to their ships before
                    the outcry should arouse the farmers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All the
                    greater at this time was the flight and alarm in the city. They lacked also, to
                    be sure, both a strong army at home and a general to confront the enemy.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal the son of Gisgo was far the
                    foremost man of the state in family, reputation, wealth, and at that time also
                    by reason <pb n="p.319"/> of his relationship to a king. But they recalled that
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> in a
                    number of battles in Spain he had been routed and beaten by the self-same
                    Scipio, and that the one general was no more a match for the other than was
                    their own irregular army for the Roman army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly they sounded the alarm, as if Scipio were intending forthwith to
                    attack the city. The gates were hastily closed also and armed men posted on the
                    walls, sentries and outposts stationed, while the following night no one slept.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Next day five hundred horsemen, sent to
                    the coast to reconnoitre and to break up the disembarkation, encountered Roman
                    outposts. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For already Scipio, after sending
                    the fleet towards Utica, had himself advanced not very far from the sea and
                    taken the nearest heights. He had stationed cavalry on outpost duty in suitable
                    positions and had sent others to plunder the countryside. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These horsemen, having engaged in battle with
                    the Carthaginian cavalry, slew a few in the actual engagement, many more as they
                    pursued them in flight, among the number Hanno <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Cf. xxxiv. 14 ff., where this engagement may appear to
                        be repeated with the same result for a commander of the same name, a common
                        name, however, at Carthage. But v. p. 343 and notes. </note> also, the
                    commander, a young man of rank. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Scipio not
                    only laid waste the farms all around but also captured the nearest city of the
                    Africans, quite a prosperous place. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There, in
                    addition to the other spoils which had been at once loaded on transports and
                    sent to Sicily, eight thousand free persons and slaves were taken captive. </p>
                <p> What brought the greatest joy, however, to the Romans at the beginning of the
                    campaign was the <pb n="p.321"/> arrival of Masinissa. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Some authorities relate that <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> he came with no more than
                    two hundred horsemen, the majority say with two thousand cavalry. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> But since he was far the greatest of all the kings of
                    his time and gave the greatest aid to the Roman state, it seems worth while to
                    digress a little to tell how checkered was the fortune he met with in losing and
                    recovering his father's kingdom. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        long digression (4 1/2 chapters) is probably from a lost portion of
                        Polybius, who had a personal acquaintance with Masinissa; for in his IX.
                        xxv. 4 a conversation with him is reported. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While he was serving on the side of the
                    Carthaginians in Spain his father died; Gala was his name. The kingdom came to
                    the king's brother, Oezalces, a very aged man, such being the custom among the
                    Numidians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Not long after, upon the death of
                    Oezalces also, the elder of his two sons, Capussa, succeeded to his father's
                    throne, the other son being a mere boy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                    inasmuch as he held the kingship more by customary law of his people than by
                    prestige among his countrymen or by his might, a man came forward named
                    Mazaetullus, not unconnected by blood with the royal house and member of a
                    family that had always been hostile and had contested the throne with different
                    results against the house which was then in possession. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> After rousing his countrymen, among whom he had great
                    influence because of the unpopularity of the royal family, and openly pitching
                    his camp, he compelled the king to go out into battle-line and fight for his
                    kingdom. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In that battle Capussa fell with
                    many of the leading men. The entire tribe of the Maesulii submitted to the sway
                    and authority of Mazaetullus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Nevertheless he
                    refrained from using the kingly title and, contented with the modest style of
                    guardian, he gave the royal title to the boy Lacumazes, who also belonged to the
                    royal line. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He married a noble Carthaginian
                    lady, <pb n="p.323"/> daughter of Hannibal's sister and lately wedded to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> King
                    Oezalces. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He did so in the hope of an
                    alliance with the Carthaginians, and with Syphax he renewed a guest-friendship
                    of long standing, sending envoys for the purpose. All these advantages he was
                    preparing against Masinissa. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And Masinissa having heard of the death of his
                    uncle, and then that his cousin had fallen, crossed over from Spain into
                    Mauretania, Baga being at that time king of the Mauri. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> From Baga with the most abject entreaties as a suppliant he
                    obtained four thousand Mauri as an escort on his journey, being unable to obtain
                    aid for the war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When with that escort, after
                    first sending word to his father's friends and his own, he had reached the
                    frontier of the kingdom, about five hundred Numidians joined him. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Therefore from that point he sent back the Mauri to
                    their king, as it had been agreed, and although the numbers that had joined him
                    were considerably smaller than he had hoped for, and not such that he quite
                    dared to attempt so great a venture with them, he thought that by vigorous
                    action he would also gather up the forces needed for some success. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Hence as Lacumazes, the prince, was on his way to
                    Syphax, Masinissa encountered him near Thapsus. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Unknown; probably a corruption of the name. Not to be
                        confused with the distant city famous for Julius Caesar's victory, on the
                        coast south of Hadrumetum (Sousse). </note> When the frightened column had
                    sought refuge in the city, Masinissa not only took the city by the first assault
                    but received the surrender of some of the royal escort and slew others
                    attempting resistance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The majority together
                    with the boy himself in the midst of the commotion made <pb n="p.325"/> their
                    way to Syphax, towards whom they had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 204</note> originally directed their march. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The report of this modest success at the beginning of
                    the campaign brought the Numidians over to Masinissa, and from farms and
                    villages on all sides old soldiers of Gala flocked to him; and they spurred the
                    young man on to recover the kingdom of his father. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the number of his soldiers Mazaetullus was
                    considerably superior; for not only did he himself have the army with which he
                    had defeated Capussa, and a number of men whom he had taken over after the
                    slaying of the king, but also the young Lacumazes had brought up very large
                    auxiliary forces from Syphax. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Fifteen thousand
                    infantry Mazaetullus had and ten thousand cavalry; and with these he engaged in
                    battle with Masinissa, who was far from having so great a number of infantry or
                    cavalry. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nevertheless victory was won by the
                    courage of the veteran soldiers and the sagacity of a general who had been
                    trained in the war between Roman and Carthaginian armies. The prince with his
                    guardian and a very small band of Masaesulians sought refuge in the territory of
                    Carthage. So, having recovered his father's kingdom, Masinissa, seeing that his
                    remaining conflict against Syphax would be considerably more serious, thought it
                    best to be reconciled with his cousin. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly he sent men to encourage the boy to hope that, if he should put
                    himself in the hands of Masinissa, he would be held in the same honour as
                    Oezalces had formerly been in the house of Gala. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> To Mazaetullus also they were to pledge, besides impunity,
                    the faithful restoration of all his property. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    By this means, as they preferred a modest fortune at home to exile, Masinissa
                    won <pb n="p.327"/> them both over, although the Carthaginians purposely <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> did
                    everything to prevent it. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal happened to be with Syphax <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For a previous visit, presumably at
                        Siga (west of Oran), cf. XXVIII. xvii <hi rend="italics">fin.</hi> and
                        xviii. </note> all the time that these events were in progress. And when the
                    Numidian said he believed it was of no great importance to him whether the
                    kingdom of the Maesulians was in the hands of Lacumazes or of Masinissa,
                    Hasdrubal said he was very much mistaken if he believed that Masinissa would be
                    content with what had satisfied his father Gala or his uncle Oezalces;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that he had in him a far greater gift of
                    spirit and talent than had ever been found in any man of his tribe; that often
                    in Spain he had given allies and enemies alike evidence of a courage rare among
                    men. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He added that unless Syphax and the
                    Carthaginians should put out that incipient flame, they would be consumed later
                    by a mighty conflagration when they could no longer cope with it; that
                    Masinissa's strength was still slight and frail, while he was nursing a kingdom
                    whose wounds had barely begun to heal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> By
                    insisting and goading him on Hasdrubal brought him to the point of advancing his
                    army to the frontier of the Maesulians and pitching his camp as though upon soil
                    to which he was unquestionably entitled —land concerning which he had not only
                    argued with Gala repeatedly but had contended also in arms. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> If anyone should try to drive him away he would fight a
                    regular battle, which would be greatly to his advantage. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But if Masinissa in fear should withdraw from that region
                    they must advance into the interior of the kingdom. Either the Maesulians would
                    submit without resistance to the rule of Syphax, or they would be no match for
                    him in arms. </p>
                <pb n="p.329"/>
                <p> Aroused by these words Syphax made war upon <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> Masinissa and in the first
                    engagement routed the Maesulians and put them to flight. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Masinissa with a few horsemen fled from the battle-field to
                    a mountain called Bellus by the natives. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">No Mount Bellus is known.</note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A considerable number of households followed
                    the king with their portable huts <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Thatched huts that were portable, often resembling an overturned ship, as
                        Sallust describes them; <hi rend="italics">Jug.</hi> xviii. 8. Cf. <hi
                            rend="italics">ibid.</hi> xlvi. 5; Pliny <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> V.
                        22 (carried on wagons); Vergil <hi rend="italics">Georg.</hi> III. 340.
                    </note> and their flocks, the latter being their only wealth. But the rest, the
                    mass of the Maesulians, submitted to the rule of Syphax. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The mountain which the fugitives had occupied is well
                    supplied with grass and water and being suitable for the support of cattle, it
                    was quite capable of sustaining men also who lived on flesh and milk. From it
                    they rendered all the surrounding country unsafe, first by stealthy raids in the
                    night and later by open brigandage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Most of
                    all it was Carthaginian territory that was ravaged, because there was more
                    plunder than among the Numidians, and also brigandage was safer. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> By this time they played their game so openly as to
                    bring their booty down to the sea and sell it to traders who put in with their
                    vessels for that very purpose; and more Carthaginians fell or were captured than
                    occurred often in regular warfare. </p>
                <p> The Carthaginians complained of all this to Syphax and, as he also was enraged,
                    they spurred him on to complete what was left of the war. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> But it seemed hardly becoming for a king to pursue a nomad
                    bandit in the mountains. <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One of the king's officers, Bucar, a man of
                    spirit and energy, was chosen for the purpose. Four thousand infantry and two
                    thousand cavalry were given to him; and he <pb n="p.331"/> was laden with
                    immense rewards in anticipation, if <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 204</note> he should bring back the head of Masinissa, or
                    —and this would be a joy beyond price —should capture him alive. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> While they were scattered and off their guard Bucar
                    unexpectedly attacked them, and separating the great number of cattle and men
                    from their armed escort, he drove Masinissa himself with a few of his men up to
                    the top of the mountain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then, just as though
                    the war had been already finished, he sent not only the booty in cattle and
                    captives to the king but returned his troops also, as much too many for the
                    remainder of the war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With not more than five
                    hundred foot-soldiers and two hundred horsemen he pursued Masinissa (who had
                    come down from the heights), and penned him in a gorge with both entrances
                    blocked. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There a great slaughter of the
                    Maesulians took place; but Masinissa with no more than fifty horsemen following
                    him through the unknown recesses of the mountain made his escape. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Bucar, however, kept on the trail and overtaking him
                    in an open plain near the city of Clupea <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Unknown, the name perhaps confused with that of the
                        city on Cap Bon (XXVII. xxix. 7), now Kelibia. The place meant here was
                        probably in north-western Tunisia or north-eastern Algeria. </note> so
                    overwhelmed him that he slew every one of his horsemen except four. With these
                    men, in the midst of the uproar he let the wounded Masinissa himself slip away
                    when almost in his hands. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The fugitives were
                    insight; a squadron of cavalry, scattering over the breadth of the plain, while
                    some, in order to head them off, pushed on obliquely, was pursuing five enemies.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A broad stream <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Probably the Bagradas (Medjerda), as streams of size
                        are rare in the region. </note> was the refuge of the <pb n="p.333"/>
                    fleeing; for without hesitation, under the pressure <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> of a greater fear, they
                    put their horses into it; and swept by the whirling current, they were borne
                    obliquely past the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When two of them had
                    been drowned in the swiftly whirling waters before the eyes of the enemy,
                    Masinissa himself, whom they believed to have perished, and the two remaining
                    horsemen with him made their way out among the bushes of the farther bank. That
                    was the end of pursuit for Bucar, as he did not dare enter the river and
                    believed he had no one left to pursue. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then
                    he returned to the king, falsely reporting that Masinissa had been drowned; and
                    messengers were sent to bring tidings of great joy to Carthage. And all Africa
                    was filled with the story of Masinissa's death, producing different emotions. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While Masinissa in a hidden cave was nursing
                    his wound with herbs, he lived for some days on booty brought in by the two
                    horsemen. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As soon as the wound had closed and
                    it seemed possible for him to endure jolting, with great audacity he set out to
                    reclaim his kingdom. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And after picking up not
                    more than forty horsemen as he rode along, he came among the Maesulians, openly
                    announcing now who he was; thereupon he caused a great stir, owing to their
                    old-time favour and especially to their unexpected joy because they saw a man
                    safe and sound whom they had believed to have perished. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The results were that within a few days six thousand armed
                    foot-soldiers and four thousand horsemen flocked to him, and that now he was not
                    merely in possession of his father's kingdom but was even laying waste lands of
                    allies of the Carthaginians and those of the Masaesulians, the kingdom, that is,
                    of <pb n="p.335"/> Syphax. Consequently, having provoked Syphax to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> war, he
                    established himself between Cirta <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This was Syphax' capital; XXX. xii. 3, 7 f. Given to Masinissa, <hi
                            rend="italics">ibid.</hi> xliv. 12. Formidably defended by great cliffs.
                        Later it was the city of Fronto, teacher of Marcus Aurelius. Rebuilt by
                        Constantine, whose name it still bears. Cf. Appian <hi rend="italics"
                            >Pun.</hi> 27; Strabo XVII. iii. 13. </note> and Hippo <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Hippo Regius (Bône), not the Hippo meant on p.
                        218. </note> on a mountain range that in every way was favourable. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Therefore Syphax, thinking the affair was now
                    too serious to be conducted by his officers, sent a part of the army under his
                    young son, Vermina by name, with orders to lead his column round and attack the
                    rear of the enemy, whose eyes would be upon the king himself. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Vermina, who was to make a secret attack, set out by night.
                    But Syphax broke camp and marched by day along an open road, since he intended
                    to engage in battle formation, standards against standards. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When the interval seemed to be such that the flanking party
                    might be thought to have reached their objective already, the king on his part,
                    relying both on numbers and on the ambuscade prepared in the rear, led his line
                    up along the face of the mountain over a gentle slope leading in the direction
                    of the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Masinissa also, relying chiefly
                    upon the much more favourable ground on which he was to fight, led his men out
                    into line. The battle was fierce and long indecisive, while position and the
                    courage of his soldiers aided Masinissa and numbers that were far superior
                    favoured Syphax. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That great army in its two
                    sections —since the one pressed the enemy hard in front, while the other had
                    accomplished its flanking movement in the rear —gave no uncertain victory to
                    Syphax; and there was not even a way of escape open to men enclosed both in
                    front and in the rear. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly the rest,
                    infantry and cavalry, were slain or captured; but some two hundred horsemen were
                    ordered by Masinissa to mass about him, divide into <pb n="p.337"/> three
                    troops, and so to break their way through, a <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> place being assigned in
                    advance at which they should meet after their flight in different directions.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He himself escaped in the direction he had
                    chosen through the midst of the enemies' weapons. Two of the squadrons were held
                    fast; one in fear surrendered to the enemy, while the other, offering a more
                    stubborn resistance, was overwhelmed by missiles and slain. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Vermina, who was almost at his heels, Masinissa evaded by
                    turning now into this road and now into that, and compelled him at last to
                    abandon pursuit when he was weary and had given up hope. He himself made his way
                    with sixty horsemen to the Lesser Syrtis. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    There, with the proud consciousness of having repeatedly made claim to his
                    father's kingdom, in the region between the Punic Emporia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. xxv. 12 and notes.</note> and the tribe of the
                    Garamantes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Their land, south of
                        modern Tripolitania, is now Fezzan, reaching back into the Sahara; Herodotus
                        IV. 174, 183; Strabo II. v. 33; XVII. iii. 19, 23; Pliny <hi rend="italics"
                            >N.H.</hi> V. 36; VI. 209; Mela I. 23, 45; Tacitus <hi rend="italics"
                            >Ann.</hi> III. 74. </note> he spent the whole time until the arrival in
                    Africa of Gaius Laelius and the Roman fleet. These circumstances incline me to
                    believe that Masinissa came to Scipio also later with a small force <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">In agreement with Polybius XXI. xxi.
                        2.</note> of cavalry rather than with a large one. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> For such great numbers are suited to a monarch, while my
                    small figures match the plight of an exile. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians, having lost a squadron of
                    cavalry with its commander <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the Hanno named in xxix. 1 without further
                        description than <hi rend="italics">nobilem iuvenem.</hi>
                    </note> and acquired other horse by a fresh levy, placed Hanno the son of
                    Hamilcar <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Dio Cassius
                        this Hanno was the son of Hasdrubal son of Gisgo; frag. 57. 65 f. See below,
                        p. 343, n. 2. </note> in command. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Again
                    and again they summoned Hasdrubal and Syphax by letters and messengers, finally
                    even by envoys. They bade <pb n="p.339"/> Hasdrubal bring aid to his native
                    city, now almost <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        204</note> invested; they entreated Syphax to come to the rescue of
                    Carthage, to the rescue of all Africa. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio
                    at that time had his camp near Utica, about a mile from the city, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Evidently south-west of Utica and on
                        the same long ridge. Not the same situation as that in xxxv. 7. Cf. Veith,
                            <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> 579 f. </note> having shifted it from
                    the seashore, where for a few days the camp had been established close to the
                    fleet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hanno, who had received a cavalry force
                    not strong enough even to prevent the devastation of farms, to say nothing of
                    attacking the enemy, made it his very first task to increase the number of his
                    horsemen by recruiting. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And though he did not
                    reject men from other tribes, it was nevertheless especially Numidians that he
                    hired, they being easily the foremost type of cavalry in Africa. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Already he had about four thousand horsemen when he
                    seized a city named Salaeca, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Mentioned only here and xxxv. 4. Possibly Henchir el Bey, west-south-west of
                        Utica. Appian names a large town called Locha; <hi rend="italics">Pun.</hi>
                        15. </note> some fifteen miles from the Roman camp. When this was reported
                    to Scipio, he said <quote> Cavalry summering under roofs! <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Let them be even more numerous, provided they have that
                        kind of a commander! </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thinking that the more spiritless they were
                    the less must he delay, he sent Masinissa forward with cavalry, ordering him to
                    ride up to the gates and draw the enemy out into battle. When the whole
                    multitude should have sallied out and in battle should then prove too powerful
                    for them to withstand easily, he was gradually to retire. He would himself come
                    into the battle at the right moment. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After
                    delaying only long enough to give time, as it seemed, for Masinissa, who had
                    preceded him, to draw out the enemy, Scipio followed with the <pb n="p.341"/>
                    Roman cavalry and advanced unseen under cover of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> the hills, which were most
                    conveniently placed on both sides of a winding road. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Masinissa according to plan, now as inspirer
                    of terror, now as the terror-stricken, would either ride up to the very gates,
                    or retiring would tempt them to reckless pursuit whenever his pretence of fear
                    added to the enemy's boldness. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Not yet had
                    all sallied out, and the commander was exerting himself in various ways, as he
                    compelled some men heavy with wine and sleep to take up their arms and bridle
                    their horses, and stood in the way of others, to prevent their dashing out of
                    all the gates, scattering and unformed, with no order, no standards. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> At first, as they rashly charged, Masinissa would
                    meet their attack. Later larger numbers, dashing out of a gate in a mass, had
                    made it an even combat. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Finally, when all
                    their cavalry was engaged, they could no longer be withstood. Yet Masinissa did
                    not flee in disorder, but retiring gradually would meet their attacks until he
                    drew them to the hills which concealed the Roman cavalry. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Thereupon the horsemen dashing out, themselves with
                    undiminished strength and their horses fresh, surrounded Hanno and the Africans,
                    who were exhausted by fighting and pursuit; and Masinissa, suddenly turning his
                    horses about, went into battle again. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> About a
                    thousand men who had been at the head of the column, finding retreat difficult,
                    were cut off and slain along with Hanno himself, their commander. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> As for the rest, who were terrified especially by
                    the death of their commander, the victors pursuing them in headlong flight for
                    thirty miles either captured or slew about two thousand more <pb n="p.343"/>
                    horsemen. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Among these it was well established
                    that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note>
                    there were not less than two hundred Carthaginian horsemen, some of them
                    distinguished both for wealth and noble blood. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the same day on which these events took
                    place the ships which had carried booty to Sicily happened to return with
                    supplies, as though with a presentiment that they had come for booty a second
                    time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not all the historians vouch for the
                    slaying of two Carthaginian commanders of the same name in two cavalry battles,
                    fearing, I suppose, unwittingly to tell the same story twice. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy appears to have followed a lost
                        part of Polybius. Two annalists only are mentioned (next sentence) who
                        accepted but one encounter with cavalry commanded by a Hanno. Cf. Appian <hi
                            rend="italics">l.c.</hi> 14; Dio Cass. <hi rend="italics">l.c.</hi> ( =
                        Zonaras IX. xii. 4 f.). These tell the story quite differently. Modern
                        historians are divided, some insisting that one of the battles is a doublet,
                            <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> De Sanctis III. 2. 581 f.; <hi
                            rend="italics">C.A.H.</hi> VIII. 100, n. 2. Not so Gsell, <hi
                            rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> 216, n. 4; Neumann, <hi rend="italics">Das
                            Zeitalter der punischen Kriege</hi> 522; Karstedt, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Gesch. der Karthager</hi> III. 337 f., 545. </note> Coelius and
                    Valerius, to be sure, relate that Hanno too was captured. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This is the statement of Appian also and Dio Cass.
                        (Zon.), who add ( <hi rend="italics">ll. cc.</hi> ) that the prisoner was
                        exchanged for Masinissa's own mother. So much detail seems to establish the
                        historicity of the second engagement reported. As for the first (xxix. 1),
                        something more than identity of a name (especially of a common name) is
                        needed to stamp it as necessarily fictitious. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio bestowed conspicuous rewards upon the
                    commanders and the horsemen according to the service each had rendered, and
                    above all on Masinissa. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And having posted a
                    strong garrison at Salaeca, he set out himself with the rest of the army. Laying
                    waste not merely the farms wherever he went, but storming certain cities also
                    and villages, while the alarm of the war was spread far and wide, on the seventh
                    day after his departure he returned to camp bringing a great number of men and
                    cattle and much booty of every kind; and again he sent away the ships loaded
                    down with spoils of the enemy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then, giving up
                    small raids and petty pillaging, he applied <pb n="p.345"/> all his military
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> resources to the siege of Utica, with
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> the
                    intention of having that city, if captured, as a base henceforth for all
                    remaining operations. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From the fleet marines
                    were brought up to the city on the side where it is washed by the sea, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At the north-east end of a long ridge.
                        Just beyond there was a small island on which lay the oldest quarter of the
                        city, at least 200 years older than Carthage (cf. Gades, p. 141, n. 1). The
                        Medjerda (Bagradas) has since changed its winding course far to the west,
                        and coming within less than half a mile of the ridge, has brought down
                        alluvial deposits so extensive that the ruins of Utica are now about 7 miles
                        from the nearest coast-line. Cf. Caesar <hi rend="italics">B.C.</hi> II.
                        xxiv. 1, 3; Polybius I. lxxv. 5; XV. ii. 8 (his name for the river is
                        Macaras); Strabo XVII. iii. 13 <hi rend="italics">fin.;</hi> Pliny <hi
                            rend="italics">N.H.</hi> V. 24. Appian <hi rend="italics">Pun.</hi> 75
                        errs as to the distance from Carthage, which was 27 miles ( <hi
                            rend="italics">Itin. Ant.</hi> 22). </note> and at the same time land
                    forces on the side where a height almost overhung the very walls. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Artillery and engines he had not only brought with
                    him but they had also been sent from Sicily with the supplies, and new ones were
                    being made in an arsenal where many makers of such devices had been interned for
                    the purpose. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The artisans as captives
                        had become public slaves of the Roman people. Cf. those taken at New
                        Carthage, XXVI. xlvii. 2; Polybius X. xvii. 6, 9. </note>
                </p>
                <p> For the people of Utica, completely beset by so great a force, all their hope
                    was in the Carthaginian people; for the Carthaginians it was in Hasdrubal,
                    provided he should prevail upon Syphax. But everything was moving more slowly
                    than people in need of help desired. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Although
                    Hasdrubal by most intensive recruiting had made up a <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> total of about thirty thousand infantry and three thousand
                    cavalry, it was not before the arrival of Syphax, however, that he dared to move
                    his camp nearer to the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Syphax came
                    with fifty thousand foot-soldiers and ten thousand horsemen, whereupon
                    Hasdrubal, at once moving his camp away from Carthage, established himself not
                    far from Utica and the Roman fortifications. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Their arrival had this effect at any <pb n="p.347"/> rate, that Scipio, after
                    besieging Utica for about <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 204</note> forty days to no purpose in spite of all his
                    attempts, retired from the place, having failed in his undertaking. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> And as winter was now at hand, he fortified a winter
                    camp on a promontory which is connected with the mainland by a narrow ridge, but
                    extends for a considerable distance into the sea. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Caesar describes the site, still called Castra
                        Corneli(an)a in his time and much later; <hi rend="italics">B.C.</hi> II.
                        xxiv; cf. Appian <hi rend="italics">B.C.</hi> II. 44; Pliny <hi
                            rend="italics">N.H.</hi> V. 29; Ptolemy IV. 3. It was at the north-east
                        end of a long ridge projecting into the sea (a cape Polybius calls it, XIV.
                        vi. 7), and parallel to the ridge on which lay Utica, nearly two miles
                        farther west, with a broad marsh between them. Caesar's text gives half the
                        actual distance. </note>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> By a single earthwork he enclosed the naval
                    camp as well. The camp of the legions being placed on the middle of the ridge,
                    its northern side was occupied by the beached ships and the men to man them, its
                    southern slope, descending to the other shore, by the cavalry. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Such were the events in Africa down to the end of autumn. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Besides the grain brought in on all sides from
                    ravaged farms of the whole region and supplies transported from Sicily and
                    Italy, Gnaeus Octavius, the propraetor, brought a large amount of grain sent
                    from Sardinia by Tiberius Claudius, the praetor in charge of that province.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And not only were the granaries filled
                    which had been built already, but also new granaries were built. Clothing was
                    insufficient for the army. Octavius was ordered to obtain from the praetor
                    whatever could be assembled and sent from that province. This charge also was
                    carried out without delay. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Twelve hundred
                    togas were sent in a short time and twelve thousand tunics. </p>
                <pb n="p.349"/>
                <p> In the summer in which these events occurred in <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> Africa Publius Sempronius,
                    the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> consul who had the land of the Bruttii
                    as his province, engaged with Hannibal in the territory of Croton in an
                    unorganized battle while actually on the march. They fought in columns rather
                    than in battle-line. The Romans were worsted, and in what was in fact a confused
                    struggle rather than a battle about twelve hundred of the consul's army were
                    slain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was a panic-stricken retreat to
                    the camp, and yet the enemy did not venture to attack it. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But in the silence of the following night the consul set
                    out, and after despatching a messenger to Publius Licinius, the proconsul,
                    urging him to bring up his legions, he united their forces. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Thus two generals and two armies once more confronted
                    Hannibal, and there was no delay in engaging, since doubled forces emboldened
                    the consul, as his recent victory did the Carthaginian. Sempronius led his
                    legions into the first line, while Publius Licinius' legions were posted in
                    reserve. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the battle the
                    consul vowed a temple to Fortuna Primigenia, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The temple, dedicated in <date when="-0194">194
                            B.C.</date> , stood on the Quirinal inside the Porta Collina; cf. XXXIV.
                        liii. 5 f. The worship of this goddess came from Praeneste (Palestrina). She
                        was so named as Jupiter's first-born daughter. </note> if he should rout the
                    enemy that day; and he had his wish. The Carthaginians were routed and put to
                    flight. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Over four thousand armed men were
                    slain, a little less than three hundred were captured alive, and forty horses
                    and eleven military standards taken. Discouraged by defeat, Hannibal led his
                    army back to Croton. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the same time Marcus Cornelius, the
                    consul, in <pb n="p.351"/> the north of Italy held Etruria in check not so much
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> by
                    arms as by the alarm produced by the trials, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Begun in <date when="-0206">206 B.C.</date> under M.
                        Livius Salinator for the punishment of Etruscan and Umbrian disloyalty; p.
                        43 <hi rend="italics">med.</hi> Fugitives who escaped execution suffered
                        confiscation of property (§ 12). </note> while almost the whole land was
                    inclined towards Mago and through him to the hope of a political change.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In accordance with a decree of the senate
                    he conducted these cases with no respect of persons. And at first many noble
                    Etruscans who either had gone in person to Mago or had sent others to him
                    reporting on the disloyalty of their communities, had appeared and had been
                    condemned. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Later on men who from a guilty
                    conscience went into voluntary exile, on being condemned in absence, eluded
                    bodily punishment, merely exposing their property instead to possible
                    confiscation. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Begun in <date
                            when="-0206">206 B.C.</date> under M. Livius Salinator for the
                        punishment of Etruscan and Umbrian disloyalty; p. 43 <hi rend="italics"
                            >med.</hi> Fugitives who escaped execution suffered confiscation of
                        property (§ 12). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the consuls were thus employed in
                    opposite regions, the censors Marcus Livius and Gaius Claudius at Rome meanwhile
                    publicly read the list of senators. Quintus Fabius Maximus was chosen <hi
                        rend="italics">princes</hi> for the second time. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXVII. xi. 12.</note> Seven men received their
                        <quote>mark,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">nota</hi> of
                        the censors was a mark or stigma affixed (in the revised list of citizens)
                        to the names of such men as had been degraded by the censors, who added the
                        reason in each case. Cf. XXIV. xviii. 2 ff., esp. 9. </note> but no one who
                    had occupied a curule chair. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Repairs to public
                    buildings and their roofs they enforced strictly and with the greatest fidelity.
                    They let the contract for the making of a street leading out of the Cattle
                    Market, on both sides of the spectators' stands, as far as the Temple of Venus,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Venus Obsequens. Built <date when="-0295">295
                            B.C.</date> , near the east end of the Circus Maximus, and on the side
                        toward the Aventine; X. xxxi. 9. The stands for spectators were of wood, as
                        the upper tiers of the Circus always continued to be. </note> also for the
                    erection of a Temple of the Great Mother <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For thirteen years longer she was to remain in the
                        Temple of Victory; cf. xiv. 14; XXXVI. xxxvi. 3 f. </note> on the Palatine.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They also established a new revenue from
                    the yearly production of salt. Both at Rome and throughout Italy salt was then
                    sold at one-sixth of an <hi rend="italics">as.</hi> The censors let <pb
                        n="p.353"/> contracts for the sale of salt at the same price at <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> Rome, at a
                    higher price even in market-towns and local centres, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On these petty localities v. - Vol. VI. p. 356, n. 1.
                        In the Lex Iulia municipalis ( <date when="-0045">45 B.C.</date> ) they are
                        repeatedly mentioned as the lowest grades of communities, inferior to <hi
                            rend="italics">municipia, coloniae</hi> and <hi rend="italics"
                            >praefecturae,</hi> which are implied here in <hi rend="italics"
                            >alibi,</hi> as we cannot believe that any towns however small escaped
                        the higher price. In Rome alone was the previous <quote>ceiling</quote>
                        continued. </note> and at prices which varied from place to place.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This source of revenue was generally
                    believed to have been devised by only one of the censors, who was angry with the
                    people because he had formerly been condemned by an unjust verdict; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> and that in the price of salt those tribes by whose
                    efforts he had been condemned were most heavily burdened. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> How to reconcile this statement with the status of
                        Livius' own Maecia (§ 13) as one of the rustic tribes and hence bound to pay
                        the higher price is a futile question, since the whole story bears the stamp
                        of fiction. The state owned all salt works, but they were operated by
                        contractors, who with prices raised could now pay more for their
                        concessions. This amounted to putting a tax on salt except in Rome. Cf. Dio
                        Cassius frag. 57. 70. </note> Hence the cognomen Salinator was bestowed upon
                    Livius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The ceremony of purification was completed
                    later than usual because the censors had sent men to the various provinces to
                    report the number of Roman citizens in each of the armies. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Including these, 214,000 men <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Compared with 137,108 four years before; Vol. VII. p.
                        355, n. 3. </note> were listed. Gaius Claudius Nero concluded the rite of
                    purification. Then they received the census lists of the twelve colonies <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. xv. 5 ff., esp. 10.</note> presented
                    by their own censors, as had never been done before. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The purpose was that documents, to show what was their
                    strength in the number of soldiers and what in money, might be found in the
                    public records. Then they began to take the census of the knights; and it
                    happened that both of the censors had horses from the state. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When they had reached the Pollia tribe, in which stood the
                    name of <pb n="p.355"/> Marcus Livius, and while the herald was hesitating <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> to summon
                    the censor himself, Nero said, <quote>Summon Marcus Livius!</quote> And whether
                    as still nursing their ancient quarrel, or priding himself on an ill-timed
                    display of strictness because he had been condemned by a verdict of the people,
                    he ordered Marcus Livius to sell his horse. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The horse had been bought out of an allowance ( <hi
                            rend="italics">aes equestre</hi> ) from the state, but was not public
                        property; Mommsen, <hi rend="italics">Staatsrecht</hi> III. 256, n. 3. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Likewise Marcus Livius, when they had reached
                    the Arniensis tribe and the name of his colleague, ordered Gaius Claudius to
                    sell his horse for two reasons: one because he had given false testimony <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the trial before the popular
                        assembly, cf. Vol. VII. p. 347 and note 1. </note> against Livius, the other
                    that he had not honestly been reconciled with him. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Equally shameful at the close of their censorship was their
                    contest in besmirching each the other's reputation to the detriment of his own.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When Gaius Claudius had taken the oath
                    that he had complied with the laws, upon going up into the Treasury and giving
                    the names of those whom he was leaving as mere tax-payers, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Cf. Vol. VI. p. 231. Any action taken by a censor
                        without approval of his colleague was void; Mommsen <hi rend="italics">op.
                            cit.</hi> II.3 358; cf. <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> XLV. xv. 8. </note>
                    he gave the name of his colleague. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then
                    Marcus Livius came into the Treasury, and except for the Maecia tribe, which had
                    neither condemned him nor after his condemnation voted for him either for consul
                    or for censor, he left the entire Roman people, thirty-four tribes, as mere
                    tax-payers, alleging that they had <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> both
                    condemned him, an innocent man, and after his condemnation had made him consul
                    and censor, and could not deny that they had erred either once in their verdict
                    or twice in the elections. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He said that among
                    the thirty-four tribes Gaius Claudius also would be a mere tax-payer; and that
                    if he had a precedent <pb n="p.357"/> for twice leaving the same man a mere
                    tax-payer, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        204</note> he would have left Gaius Claudius among them with express mention
                    of his name. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> A perverted contest between the
                    censors in regard to their <quote>marks</quote> ; but to the fickleness of the
                    people it was a rebuke worthy of a censor and in keeping with the earnestness of
                    those times. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Since the censors were
                    unpopular, Gnaeus Baebius, a tribune of the plebs, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Baebius Tamphilus reached the consulship in <date
                            when="-0182">182 B.C.</date> ; XXXIX. lvi. 4. </note> thinking it an
                    opportunity to advance himself at their expense, named a day for both to appear
                    before the people. That procedure was quashed by unanimity among the senators,
                    lest the censorship should be subject thereafter to the caprice of the populace. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same summer in the land of the
                    Bruttii Clampetia was taken by storm by the consul. Consentia <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Chief town of the Bruttii, modern
                        Cosenza, captured by the Carthaginians in <date when="-0216">216 B.C.</date>
                        It returned to the Romans in 213, but had changed sides once more; cf.
                        XXIII. xxx. 5; XXV. i. 2; XXX. xix. 10 (a repetition). Later an important
                        point on the great inland road, Via Popilia, from Capua to Reggio (Regium);
                            <hi rend="italics">C.I.L.</hi> X. 6950 (= I. ii, ed. 2, 638). Clampetia
                        was on the coast south-west of Consentia. </note> together with Pandosia and
                    other cities of no importance voluntarily submitted to his authority. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And since the time for elections was now at hand, it
                    was decided to summon Cornelius to Rome from Etruria, where there was no war.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He announced the election of Gnaeus
                    Servilius Caepio and Gaius Servilius Geminus as consuls. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then elections for the praetorships were held. Elected were
                    Publius Cornelius Lentulus, Publius Quinctilius Varus, Publius Aelius Paetus,
                    Publius Villius Tappulus, the last two being made praetors while they were
                    plebeian aediles. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul after the
                    elections were over returned to the army in Etruria. </p>
                <p> Priests who died that year and successors appointed <pb n="p.359"/> in their
                    places were: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Tiberius Veturius Philo, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 204</note> elected
                    and installed flamen of Mars in place of Marcus Aemilius Regillus, who had died
                    in the preceding year; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Immediately
                        correcting the opening words of the paragraph. Cf. xi. 14 for Regillus'
                        death in <date when="-0205">205 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> in succession to Marcus Pomponius Matho, augur
                    and decemvir, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Pomponius, probably
                        praetor in <date when="-0216">216 B.C.</date> , had held two priesthoods
                        concurrently, as did Otacilius in XXVII. vi. 15. </note> were elected Marcus
                    Aurelius Cotta as decemvir, Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus as augur, being a mere
                    youth, which was then a very unusual thing in the assignment of priesthoods.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A gilded four-horse chariot was set up in
                    that year on the Capitol by the curule aediles Gaius Livius and Marcus Servilius
                    Geminus. And the Roman Games were repeated for two days, as were the Plebeian
                    Games also for two days by the aediles Publius Aelius and Publius Villius; and
                    on account of the festival there was a banquet for Jupiter. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
