<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six - 9</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp> literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by </resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>

                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1849</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="book">
                <head>BOOK IX.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Titus Veturius and Spurius Postumius, with their army, surrounded by the
                        Samnites at the Caudine forks; enter into a treaty, give six hundred
                        hostages, and are sent under the yoke. The treaty declared invalid; the two
                        generals and the other sureties sent back to the Samnites, but are not
                        accepted. Not long after, Papirius Cursor obliterates this disgrace, by
                        vanquishing the Samnites, sending them under the yoke, and recover- ing the
                        hostages. Two tribes added. Appius Claudius, censor, con- structs the
                        Claudian aqueduct, and the Appian road; admits the sons of freedom into the
                        senate. Successes against the Apulians, Etruscans, Umbrians, Marsians,
                        Pelignians, Aequans, and Samnites. Mention made of Alexander the Great, who
                        flourished at this time; a compara- tive estimate of his strength, and that
                        of the Roman people, tending to show, that if he had carried his arms into
                        Italy, he would not have been as successful there as he had been in the
                        Eastern countries. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THIS year is followed by the convention of
                    Caudium, so memorable on account of the misfortune of the Romans, the consuls
                    being Titus Veturius Calvinus and Spurius Postumius. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Samnites had as their commander that year Caius
                    Pontius, son to Herennius, born of a father most highly renowned for wisdom, and
                    himself a consummate warrior and commander. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When the ambassadors, who had been sent to make restitution, returned, without
                    concluding a peace, he said, <quote> That ye may not think that no purpose has
                        been effected by this embassy, whatever degree of anger the deities of
                        heaven had conceived against us, on account of the infraction of the <pb
                            n="560" xml:id="p.560"/> treaty, has been hereby expiated. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> I am very confident, that whatever deities they
                        were, whose will it was that you should be reduced to the necessity of
                        making the restitution, which had been demanded according to the treaty, it
                        was not agreeable to them, that our atonement for the breach of treaty
                        should be so haughtily spurned by the Romans. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> For what more could possibly be done towards appeasing
                        the gods, and softening the anger of men, than we have done? <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The effects of the enemy, taken among the spoils,
                        which appeared to be our own by the right of war, we restored: the authors
                        of the war, as we could not deliver them up alive, we delivered to them
                        dead: their goods we carried to Rome, lest by retaining them, any degree of
                        guilt should remain among us. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What more,
                        Roman, do I owe to thee? what to the treaty? what to the gods, the
                        guarantees of the treaty? What umpire shall I call in to judge of your
                        resentment, and of my punishment? I decline none; neither nation nor private
                        person. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But if nothing in human law is
                        left to the weak against a stronger, I will appeal to the gods, the avengers
                        of intolerable arrogance, and will beseech them to turn their wrath against
                        those for whom neither the restoration of their own effects, nor additional
                        heaps of other men's property, can suffice; <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> whose cruelty is not satiated by the death of the guilty, by the
                        surrender of their lifeless bodies, nor by their goods accompanying the
                        surrender of the owner; who cannot be appeased otherwise than by giving them
                        our blood to drink, and our entrails to be torn. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Samnites, war is just to those for whom it is
                        necessary, and arms are clear of impiety for those who have no hope left but
                        in arms. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Wherefore, as in every human
                        undertaking, it is of the utmost importance what matter men may set about
                        with the favour, what under the displeasure of the gods, be assured that the
                        former wars ye waged in opposition to the gods more than to men; in this,
                        which is now impending, ye will act under the immediate guidance of the gods
                        themselves. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After uttering these predictions, not more
                    cheering than true, he led out the troops, and placed his camp about Caudium, as
                    much out of view as possible. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From thence he
                    sent to Calatia, where he heard that the Roman consuls were encamped, ten
                    soldiers, in the habit of shepherds, and ordered them to keep some cattle
                    feeding in several different places, at a small <pb n="561" xml:id="p.561"/>
                    distance from the Roman posts; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that, when
                    they fell in with any of their foragers, they should all agree in the same
                    story, that the legions of the Samnites were then in Apulia, that they were
                    besieging Luceria with their whole force, and very near taking it by storm.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Such a rumour had been industriously
                    spread before, and had already reached the Romans; but these prisoners increased
                    the credit of it, especially as they all concurred in the same report.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was no doubt but that the Romans
                    would carry succour to the Lucerians, as being good and faithful allies; and for
                    this further reason, lest all Apulia, through apprehension of the impending
                    danger, might go over to the enemy. The only point of deliberation was, by what
                    road they should go. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There were two roads
                    leading to Luceria, one along the coast of the upper sea, wide and open; but, as
                    it was the safer, so it was proportionably longer: the other, which was shorter,
                    through the Caudine forks. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The nature of the
                    place is this: there are two deep glens, narrow and covered with wood, connected
                    together by mountains ranging on both sides from one to the other; between these
                    lies a plain of considerable extent, enclosed in the middle, abounding in grass
                    and water, and through the middle of which the passage runs: <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> but before you can arrive at it, the first defile must be
                    passed, while the only way back is through the road by which you entered it; or
                    if in case of resolving to proceed forward, you must go by the other glen, which
                    is still more narrow and difficult. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Into this
                    plain the Romans, having marched down their troops by one of those passes
                    through the cleft of a rock, when they advanced onward to the other defile,
                    found it blocked up by trees thrown across, and a mound of huge stones lying in
                    their way. When the stratagem of the enemy now became apparent, there is seen at
                    the same time a body of troops on the eminence over the glen. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Hastening back, then, they proceed to retrace the road by
                    which they had entered; they found that also shut up by such another fence, and
                    men in arms. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then, without orders, they
                    halted; amazement took possession of their minds, and a strange kind of numbness
                    seized their limbs: they then remained a long time motionless and silent, each
                    looking to the other, as if each thought the other more capable of judging and
                    advising than himself. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After some time, when
                    they saw that the consul's pavilions were being erected, and that some <pb
                        n="562" xml:id="p.562"/> were getting ready the implements for throwing up
                    works, although they were sensible that it must appear ridiculous, the attempt
                    to raise a fortification in their present desperate condition, <milestone
                        n="13??" unit="section"/> and when almost every hope was lost, would be an
                    object of necessity, yet, not to add a fault to their misfortunes, they all,
                    without being advised or ordered by any one, set <milestone n="14??"
                        unit="section"/> earnestly to work, and enclosed a camp with a rampart,
                    close to the water, while themselves, besides that the enemy heaped insolent
                    taunts on them, seemed with melancholy to acknowledge the apparent fruitlessness
                    of their toil and labour. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The
                    lieutenants-general and tribunes, without being summoned to consultation, (for
                    there was no room for either consultation or remedy,) assembled round the
                    dejected consul; while the soldiers, crowding to the general's quarters,
                    demanded from their leaders that succour, which it was hardly in the power of
                    the immortal gods themselves to afford them. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Night came on them while lamenting their
                    situation, rather than consulting, whilst they urged expedients, each according
                    to his temper; one crying out, <quote>Let us go over those fences of the
                        roads;</quote> others, <quote> over the steeps; through the woods; any way,
                        where arms can be carried. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Let us be but
                        permitted to come to the enemy, whom we have been used to conquer now near
                        thirty years. All places will be level and plain to a Roman, fighting
                        against the perfidious Samnite. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Another would say, <quote> Whither, or by what
                        way can we go? Do we expect to remove the mountains from their foundations?
                        While these cliffs hang over us, by what road will you reach the enemy?
                        Whether armed or unarmed, brave or dastardly, we are all, without
                        distinction, captured and vanquished. The enemy will not even show us a
                        weapon, by which we might die with honour. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        He will finish the war, without moving from his seat. </quote> In such
                    discourse, thinking of neither food nor rest, the night was passed. Nor could
                    the Samnites, though in circumstances so joyous, instantly determine how to act:
                    it was therefore universally agreed, that Herennius Pontius, father of the
                    general, should be consulted by letter. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He was
                    now grown feeble through age, and had withdrawn himself, not only from all
                    military, but also from all civil occupations; yet, notwithstanding the decline
                    of his bodily strength, his mind retained its full vigour. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When he heard that the Roman armies were shut up at the
                    Caudine <pb n="563" xml:id="p.563"/> forks between the two glens, being
                    consulted by his son's messenger, he gave his opinion, that they should all be
                    immediately dismissed from thence unhurt. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On
                    this counsel being rejected, and the same messenger returning a second time, he
                    recommended that they should all, to a man, be put to death. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When these answers, so opposite to each other, like those
                    of an ambiguous oracle, were given, although his son in particular considered
                    that the powers of his father's mind, together with those of his body, had been
                    impaired by age, was yet prevailed on, by the general desire of all, to send for
                    him to consult him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The old man, we are told,
                    complied without reluctance, and was carried in a waggon to the camp, where,
                    when summoned to give his advice, he spoke in such a way as to make no
                    alteration in his opinions; he only added the reasons for them. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> That "by his first plan, which he esteemed the best,
                    he meant, by an act of extraordinary kindness, to establish perpetual peace and
                    friendship with a most powerful nation: by the other, to put off the return of
                    war to the distance of many ages, during which the Roman state, after the loss
                    of those two armies, could not easily recover its strength. A third plan there
                    was not. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When his son, and the other chiefs,
                    went on to ask him if <quote> a plan of a middle kind might not be adopted; that
                        they both should be dismissed unhurt, and, at the same time, by the right of
                        war, terms imposed on them as vanquished? </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>That, indeed,</quote> said he, <quote> is a plan of such a nature, as
                        neither procures friends nor removes enemies. Only preserve those whom ye
                        would irritate by ignominious treatment. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        The Romans are a race who know not how to sit down quiet under defeat;
                        whatever that is which the present necessity shall brand will rankle in
                        their breasts for ever, and will not suffer them to rest, until they have
                        wreaked manifold vengeance on your heads. </quote> Neither of these plans
                    was approved, and Herennius was carried home from the camp. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the Roman camp also, when many fruitless
                    efforts to force a passage had been made, and they were now destitute of every
                    means of subsistence, forced by necessity, they send ambassadors, who were first
                    to ask peace on equal terms; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> which, if they
                    did not obtain, they were to challenge the enemy to battle. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To this Pontius answered, that <quote> the war was at an
                        end; and since, even in their present vanquished <pb n="564" xml:id="p.564"
                        /> and captive state, they were not willing to acknowledge their situation,
                        he would send them under the yoke unarmed, each with a single garment; that
                        the other conditions of peace should be such as were just between the
                        conquerors and the conquered. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If their
                        troops would depart, and their colonies be withdrawn out of the territories
                        of the Samnites; for the future, the Romans and Samnites, under a treaty of
                        equality, shall live according to their own respective laws. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> On these terms he was ready to negotiate with the
                        consuls: and if any of these should not be accepted, he forbade the
                        ambassadors to come to him again. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the result of this embassy was made
                    known, such general lamentation suddenly arose, and such melancholy took
                    possession of them, that had they been told that all were to die on the spot,
                    they could not have felt deeper affliction. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    After silence continued a long time, and the consuls were not able to utter a
                    word, either in favour of a treaty so disgraceful, or against a treaty so
                    necessary; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> at length, Lucius Lentulus, who was
                    the first among the lieutenants-general, both in respect of bravery, and of the
                    public honours which he had attained, addressed them thus: <quote> Consuls, I
                        have often heard my father say, that he was the only person in the Capitol
                        who did not advise the senate to ransom the state from the Gauls with gold;
                        and these he would not concur in, because they had not been enclosed with a
                        trench and rampart by the enemy, (who were remarkably slothful with respect
                        to works and raising fortifications,) and because they might sally forth, if
                        not without great danger, yet without certain destruction. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Now if, in like manner as they had it in their power to
                        run down from the Capitol in arms against their foe, as men besieged have
                        often sallied out on the besiegers, it were possible for us to come to blows
                        with the enemy, either on equal or unequal ground, I would not be wanting in
                        the high quality of my father's spirit in stating my advice. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> I acknowledge, indeed, that death, in defence of
                        our country, is highly glorious; and I am ready, either to devote myself for
                        the Roman people and the legions, or to plunge into the midst of the enemy.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But in this spot I behold my country:
                        in this spot, the whole of the Roman legions: and unless these choose to
                        rush on death in defence of their own individual characters, what have they
                        which can be preserved by their death? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        The houses of the city, some may <pb n="565" xml:id="p.565"/> say, and the
                        walls of it, and the crowd who dwell in it, by which the city is inhabited.
                        But in fact, in case of the destruction of this army, all these are
                        betrayed, not preserved. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For who will
                        protect them? An unwarlike and unarmed multitude, shall I suppose? Yes, just
                        as they defended them against the attack of the Gauls. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Will they call to their succour an army from Veii, with
                        Camillus at its head? Here, on the spot, I repeat, are all our hopes and
                        strength; by preserving which, we preserve our country; by delivering them
                        up to death, we abandon and betray our country. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> But a surrender is shameful and ignominious. True: but
                        such ought to be our affection for our country, that we should save it by
                        our own disgrace, if necessity required, as freely as by our death.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Let therefore that indignity be
                        undergone, how great soever, and let us submit to that necessity which even
                        the gods themselves do not overcome. Go, consuls, ransom the state for arms,
                        which your ancestors ransomed with gold. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls having gone to Pontius to confer
                    with him, when he talked, in the strain of a conqueror, of a treaty, they
                    declared that such could not be concluded without an order of the people, nor
                    without the ministry of the heralds, and the other customary rites. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly the Caudine peace was not ratified by
                    settled treaty, as is commonly believed, and even asserted by Claudius, but by
                    conventional sureties. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For what occasion would
                    there be either for sureties or hostages in the former case, where the
                    ratification is performed by the imprecation, <quote> that whichever nation
                        shall give occasion to the said terms being violated, may Jupiter strike
                        that nation in like manner as the swine is struck by the heralds. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consuls, lieutenants-general, quaestors,
                    and military tribunes, became sureties; and the names of all these who became
                    sureties are extant; where, had the business been transacted by treaty, none
                    would have appeared but those of the two heralds. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On account of the necessary delay of the treaty, six
                    hundred horsemen were demanded as hostages, who were to suffer death if the
                    compact were not fulfilled; a time was then fixed for delivering up the
                    hostages, and sending away the troops disarmed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> The return of the consuls renewed the general grief in the camp, insomuch
                    that the men hardly refrained from offering violence to them, <quote>by whose
                        rashness,</quote> they said, <quote> they had been brought into such a
                        situation; and <pb n="566" xml:id="p.566"/> through whose cowardice they
                        were likely to depart with greater disgrace than they came. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They had employed no guide through the country, nor
                        scouts; but were sent on blindly, like beasts into a pitfall. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They cast looks on each other, viewed
                    earnestly the arms which they must presently surrender; while their persons
                    would be subject to the will of the enemy: figured to themselves the hostile
                    yoke, the scoffs of the conquerors, their haughty looks, and finally, thus
                    disarmed, their march through the midst of an armed foe. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> In a word, they saw with horror the miserable journey of
                    their dishonoured band through the cities of the allies; and their return into
                    their own country, to their parents, whither themselves, and their ancestors,
                    had so often come in triumph. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Observing, that
                        <quote> they alone had been conquered without a fight, without a weapon
                        thrown, without a wound; that they had not been permitted to draw their
                        swords, nor to engage the enemy. In vain had arms, in vain had strength, in
                        vain had courage been given them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While they were giving vent to such grievous
                    reflections, the fatal hour of their disgrace arrived, which was to render every
                    circumstance still more shocking in fact, than they had preconceived it in their
                    imaginations. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> First, they were ordered to go
                    out, beyond the rampart, unarmed, and with single garments; then the hostages
                    were surrendered, and carried into custody. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The lictors were next commanded to depart from the consuls, and the robes of the
                    latter were stripped off. This excited such a degree of commiseration in the
                    breasts of those very men, who a little before, pouring execrations upon them,
                    had proposed that they should be delivered <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/>
                    up and torn to pieces, that every one, forgetting his own condition, turned away
                    his eyes from that degradation of so high a dignity, as from a spectacle too
                    horrid to behold. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> First, the consuls, nearly half naked, were
                    sent under the yoke; then each officer, according to his rank, was exposed to
                    disgrace, and the legions successively. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    enemy stood on each side under arms, reviling and mocking them; swords were
                    pointed at most of them, several were wounded and some even slain, when their
                    looks, rendered too fierce by the indignity to which they were subjected, gave
                    offence to the conquerors. Thus were they led under the yoke; and what was still
                    more intolerable, under the eyes of the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="567" xml:id="p.567"/> When they had got clear of the defile, they seemed
                    as if they had been drawn up from the infernal regions, and then for the first
                    time beheld the light; yet, when they viewed the ignominious appearance of the
                    army, the light itself was more painful to them than any kind of death could
                    have been; so that although they might have arrived at Capua before night, yet,
                    uncertain with respect to the fidelity of the allies, and because shame
                    embarrassed them, in need of every thing, they threw themselves carelessly on
                    the ground, on each side of the road: which being told at Capua, just compassion
                    for their allies got the better of the arrogance natural to the Campanians.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They immediately sent to the consuls their
                    ensigns of office, the fasces and lictors; to the soldiers, arms, horses,
                    clothes, and provisions in abundance: and, on their approach to Capua, the whole
                    senate and people went out to meet them, and performed every proper office of
                    hospitality, both public and private. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the
                    courtesy, kind looks, and address of the allies, could not only not draw
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> a word from them, but it could not even
                    prevail on them to raise their eyes, or look their consoling friends in the
                    face, so completely did shame, in addition to grief, oblige them to shun the
                    conversation and society of these their friends. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Next day, when some young nobles, who had been sent from Capua, to escort
                    them on their road to the frontiers of Campania, returned, they were called into
                    the senate-house, and, in answer to the inquiries of the elder members, said,
                    that <quote> to them they seemed deeply sunk in melancholy and dejection;
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that the whole body moved on in
                        silence, almost as if dumb; the former genius of the Romans was prostrated,
                        and that their spirit had been taken from them, together with their arms.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Not one returned a salute, nor
                        returned an answer to those who greeted them; as if, through fear, they were
                        unable to utter a word; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> as if their necks
                        still carried the yoke under which they had been sent. That the Samnites had
                        obtained a victory, not only glorious, but lasting also; for they had
                        subdued, not Rome merely, as the Gauls had formerly done, but what was a
                        much more warlike achievement, the Roman courage. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When these remarks were made and attentively
                    listened to, and the almost extinction of the Roman name was lamented in this
                    assembly of faithful allies, Ofilius Calavius, son of Ovius, a man highly
                    distinguished, both by his birth and conduct, and at this time <pb n="568"
                        xml:id="p.568"/> further respectable on account of his age, is said to have
                    declared that he entertained a very different opinion in the case. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>This obstinate silence,</quote> said he, <quote> those eyes fixed on the
                        earth, —those ears deaf to all comfort, —with the shame of beholding the
                        light, —are indications of a mind calling forth, from its inmost recesses,
                        the utmost exertions of resentment. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Either he was ignorant of the temper of the Romans, or that silence would
                        shortly excite, among the Samnites, lamentable cries and groans; for that
                        the remembrance of the Caudine peace would be much more sorrowful to the
                        Samnites than to the Romans. Each side would have their own native spirit,
                        wherever they should happen to engage, but the Samnites would not, every
                        where, have the glens of Caudium. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their disaster was, by this time, well known
                    at Rome also. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At first, they heard that the
                    troops were shut up; afterwards the news of the ignominious peace caused greater
                    affliction than had been felt for their danger. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> On the report of their being surrounded, a levy of men was begun; but when it
                    was understood that the army had surrendered in so disgraceful a manner, the
                    preparations were laid aside; and immediately, without any public directions, a
                    general mourning took place, with all the various demonstrations of grief.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The shops were shut; and all business
                    ceased in the forum, spontaneously, before it was proclaimed. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Laticlaves <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In
                        the original, <hi rend="italics">lati clavi.</hi> The latus clavus was a
                        tunic, or vest, or- namented with a broad stripe of purple <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> on the fore part, worn by the senators; the knights
                        wore a similar one, only ornamented with a nar- rower stripe. Gold rings
                        were also used as badges of distinction, the common people wore iron ones.
                    </note> and gold <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> rings were laid aside: and
                    the public were in greater tribula- tion, if possible, than the army itself;
                    they were <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> not only en- raged against the
                    commanders, the advisers and sureties of the peace, but detested even the
                    unoffending soldiers, and asserted, that they ought not to be admitted
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> into the city or its habita- tions. But
                    these transports of passion were allayed by the arrival of the troops, which
                    excited compassion even in the angry; for entering into the city, not <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> like men returning into their country with
                    unexpected safety, but in the habit and with the looks of captives, late in the
                    evening; they hid themselves so closely in their houses, that, <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> for the next, and several following days, not one of them
                    could bear to come in <pb n="569" xml:id="p.569"/> sight of the forum, or of the
                    public. The consuls, shut up in private, transacted no official business, except
                    that which was <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> wrung from them by a decree of
                    the senate, to nominate a dictator to preside at the elections. They nominated
                    Quintus Fabius <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Ambustus, and as master of the
                    horse Publius Aelius Paetus. But they having been irregularly appointed, there
                    were substituted in their room, Marcus <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Aemilius Papus dictator, and Lucius Valerius Flaccus master of the horse. But
                    neither did these <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> hold the elections: and the
                    people being dissatisfied with all the magistrates of that year, an interregnum
                    ensued. The interreges were, Quintus Fabius Maximus and Marcus Valerius Corvus,
                    who elected consuls Quintus Publilius Philo, and Lucius Papirius Cursor a second
                    time; a choice universally approved, for there were no commanders at that time
                    of higher reputation. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They entered into office on the day they were
                    elected, for so it had been determined by the fathers. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When the customary decrees of the senate were passed, they
                    proposed the consideration of the Caudine peace; and Publilius, who was in
                    possession of the fasces, said, <quote>Spurius Postumius, speak:</quote> he
                    arose with just the same countenance with which he had passed under the yoke,
                    and delivered himself to this effect: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Consuls, I am well aware that I have been called up first with marked
                        ignominy, not with honour; and that I am ordered to speak, not as being a
                        senator, but as a person answerable as well for an unsuccessful war as for a
                        disgraceful peace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> However, since the
                        question propounded by you is not concerning our guilt, or our punishment;
                        waving a defence, which would not be very difficult, before men who are not
                        unacquainted with human casualties or necessities, I shall briefly state my
                        opinion on the matter in question; which opinion will testify, whether I
                        meant to spare myself or your legions, when I engaged as surety to the
                        convention, whether dishonourable or necessary: <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> by which, however, the Roman people are not bound,
                        inasmuch as it was concluded without their order; nor is any thing liable to
                        be forfeited to the Samnites, in consequence of it, except our persons.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Let us then be delivered up to them by
                        the heralds, naked, and in chains. Let us free the people of the religious
                        obligation, if we have bound them under any such; so that there may be no
                        restriction, divine or human, to prevent your entering on the war <pb
                            n="570" xml:id="p.570"/> anew, without violating either religion or
                        justice. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I am also of opinion, that the
                        consuls, in the mean time, enlist, arm, and lead out an army; but that they
                        should not enter the enemy's territories before every particular, respecting
                        the surrender of us, be regularly executed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> You, O immortal gods! I pray and beseech that, although it has not been
                        your will that Spurius Postumius and Titus Veturius, as consuls, should wage
                        war with success against the Samnites, ye may yet deem it sufficient to have
                        seen us sent under the yoke; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> to have seen
                        us bound under an infamous convention; to have seen us delivered into the
                        hands of our foes naked and shackled, taking on our own heads the whole
                        weight of the enemy's resentment. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And
                        grant, that the consuls and legions of Rome may wage war against the
                        Samnites, with the same fortune with which every war has been waged before
                        we became consuls. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On his concluding this speech, men's minds
                    were so impressed with both admiration and compassion, that now they could
                    scarce believe him to be the same Spurius Postumius who had been the author of
                    so shameful a peace; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> again lamenting, that
                    such a man was likely to undergo, among the enemy, a punishment even beyond that
                    of others, through resentment for annulling the peace. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> When all the members, extolling him with praises, expressed
                    their approbation of his sentiments, a protest was attempted for a time by
                    Lucius Livius and Quintus Maelius, tribunes of the commons, who said, that
                        <quote> the people could <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> not be
                        acquitted of the religious obligation by the consuls being given up, unless
                        all things were restored to the Samnites in the same state in which they had
                        been at Caudium; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> nor had they themselves
                        deserved any punishment, for having, by becoming sureties to the peace,
                        preserved the army of the Roman people; nor, finally, could they, being
                        sacred and inviolable, be surrendered to the enemy or treated with violence.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this Postumius replied, <quote> In the mean
                        time surrender us as unsanctified persons, which ye may do, without offence
                        to religion; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> those sacred and inviolable
                        personages, the tribunes, ye will afterwards deliver up as soon as they go
                        out of office: but, if ye listen to me, they will be first scourged with
                        rods, here in the Comitium, that they may pay this as interest for their
                        punishment being delayed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For, as to their
                        denying that the people are acquitted of the re- <pb n="571" xml:id="p.571"
                        /> ligious obligation, by our being given up, who is there so ignorant of
                        the laws of the heralds, as not to know, that those men speak in that
                        manner, that they themselves may not be surrendered, rather than because the
                        case is really so? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Still I do not deny,
                        conscript fathers, that compacts, on sureties given, are as sacred as
                        treaties, in the eyes of all who regard faith between men, with the same
                        reverence which is paid to duties respecting the gods: but I insist, that
                        without the order of the people, nothing can be ratified that is to bind the
                        people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Suppose that, out of the same
                        arrogance with which the Samnites wrung from us the convention in question,
                        they had compelled us to repeat the established form of words for the
                        surrendering of cities, would ye, tribunes, say, that the Roman people was
                        surrendered? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and, that this city, these
                        temples, and consecrated grounds, these lands and waters, were become the
                        property of the Samnites? I say no more of' the surrender, because our
                        having become sureties is the point insisted on. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Now, suppose we had become sureties that the Roman
                        people should quit this city; that they should set it on fire; that they
                        should have no magistrates, no senate, no laws; that they should, in future,
                        be ruled by kings: the gods forbid, you say. But, the enormity of the
                        articles lessens not the obligation of a compact. If there is any thing in
                        which the people can be bound, it can in all. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Nor is there any importance in another circumstance,
                        which weighs, perhaps, with some: whether a consul, a dictator, or a
                        praetor, be the surety. And this, indeed, was what even the Samnites
                        themselves proved, who were not satisfied with the security of the consuls,
                        but compelled the lieutenants-general, quaestors, and military tribunes to
                        join them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Let no one, then, demand of me,
                        why I entered into such a compact, when neither such power was vested in a
                        consul, and when I could not, either to them, insure a peace, of which I
                        could not command the ratification; or in behalf of you, who had given me no
                        powers. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Conscript fathers, none of the
                        transactions at Caudium were directed by human wisdom. The immortal gods
                        deprived of understanding both your generals and those of the enemy.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the one side we acted not with
                        sufficient caution in the war; on the other, they threw away a victory,
                        which through our folly they had obtained, while they hardly confided in the
                        places, by means of which they had conquered; <pb n="572" xml:id="p.572"/>
                        but were in haste, on any terms, to take arms out of the hands of men who
                        were born to arms. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Had their reason been
                        sound, would it have been difficult, during the time which they spent in
                        sending for old men from home to give them advice, to send ambassadors to
                        Rome, and to negotiate a peace and treaty with the senate, and with the
                        people? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It would have been a journey of
                        only three days to expeditious travellers. In the interim, matters might
                        have rested under a truce, that is, until their ambassadors should have
                        brought from Rome, either certain victory or peace. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> That would have been really a compact, on the faith of
                        sureties, for we should have become sureties by order of the people. But,
                        neither would ye have passed such an order, nor should we have pledged our
                        faith; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> nor was it right that the affair
                        should have any other issue, than, that they should be vainly mocked with a
                        dream, as it were, of greater prosperity than their minds were capable of
                        comprehending, and that the same fortune, which had entangled our army,
                        should extricate it; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> that an ineffectual
                        victory should be frustrated by a more ineffectual peace; and that a
                        convention, on the faith of a surety, should be introduced, which bound no
                        other person beside the surety. For what part had ye, conscript fathers;
                        what part had the people, in this affair? Who can call upon you? Who can
                        say, that he has been deceived by you? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        Can the enemy? Can a citizen? To the enemy ye engaged nothing. Ye ordered no
                        citizen to engage on your behalf. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Ye are
                        therefore no way concerned either with us, to whom ye gave no commission;
                        nor with the Samnites, with whom ye transacted no business. We are sureties
                        to the Samnites; debtors, sufficiently wealthy in that which is our own, in
                        that which we can offer —our bodies and our minds. On these, let them
                        exercise their cruelty; against these, let them whet their resentment and
                        their swords. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> As to what relates to the
                        tribunes, consider whether the delivering them up can be effected at the
                        present time, or if it must be deferred to another day. Meanwhile let us,
                        Titus Veturius, and the rest concerned, offer our worthless persons, as
                        atonements, for the breaking our engagements, and, by our sufferings,
                        liberate the Roman armies. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Both these arguments, and, still more, the
                    author of them, powerfully affected the senators; as they did likewise every
                    one, not excepting even the tribunes of the commons, <pb n="573" xml:id="p.573"
                    /> who declared, that they would be directed by the senate. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They then instantly resigned their office, and were
                    delivered, together with the rest, to the heralds, to be conducted to Caudium.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On passing this decree of the senate, it
                    seemed as if some new light had shone upon the state: Postumius was in every
                    mouth: they extolled him to heaven; and pronounced his conduct as equal even to
                    the devoting act of the consul Publius Decius, and to other illustrious acts.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Through his counsel, and exertions,</quote> they said, <quote> the state
                        had raised up its head from an ignominious peace. He now offered himself to
                        the enemy's rage, and to torments; and was suffering, in atonement for the
                        Roman people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> All turned their thoughts towards arms and
                    war, [and the general cry was,] <quote>When shall we be permitted with arms in
                        our hands to meet the Samnites?</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While the state glowed with resentment and
                    rancour, the levies were composed almost entirely of volunteers. New legions,
                    composed of the former soldiers, were quickly formed, and an army marched to
                    Caudium. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The heralds, who went before, on
                    coming to the gate, ordered the sureties of the peace to be stripped of their
                    clothes, and their hands to be tied behind their backs. As the apparitor, out of
                    respect to his dignity, was binding Postumius in a loose manner, <quote>Why do
                        you not,</quote> said he, <quote>draw the cord tight, that the surrender may
                        be regularly performed?</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then, when they came into the assembly of the
                    Samnites, and to the tribunal of Pontius, Aulus Cornelius Arvina, a herald,
                    pronounced these words: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Forasmuch as these men, here present, without orders from the Roman
                        people, the Quirites, entered into surety, that a treaty should be made, and
                        have thereby rendered themselves criminal; now, in order that the Roman
                        people may be freed from the crime of impiety, I here surrender these men
                        into your hands. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the herald saying thus, Postumius gave him
                    a stroke on the thigh with his knee, as forcibly as he could, and said with a
                    loud voice, that <quote> he was now a citizen of Samnium, the other a Roman
                        ambassador; that the herald had been, by him, violently ill-treated,
                        contrary to the law of nations; and that his people would therefore have the
                        more justice on their side, in waging war. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Pontius then said, <quote> Neither will I
                        accept such a surrender, nor will the Samnites deem it valid. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Spurius Postu- <pb n="574" xml:id="p.574"/> mius,
                        if you believe that there are gods, why do you not undo all that has been
                        done, or fulfil your agreement? The Samnite nation is entitled, either to
                        all the men whom it had in its power, or, instead of them, to a peace.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But why do I call on you, who, with as
                        much regard to faith as you are able to show, return yourself a prisoner
                        into the hands of the conqueror? I call on the Roman people. If they are
                        dissatisfied with the convention made at the Caudine forks, let them replace
                        the legions within the defile where they were pent up. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Let there be no deception on either side. Let all that
                        has been done pass as nothing. Let them receive again the arms which they
                        surrendered by the convention; let them return into their camp. Whatever
                        they were in possession of, the day before the conference, let them possess
                        again. Then let war and resolute counsels be adopted. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Then let the convention, and peace, be rejected. Let us
                        carry on the war in the same circumstances, and situations, in which we were
                        before peace was mentioned. Let neither the Roman people blame the
                        convention of the consuls, nor us the faith of the Roman people. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Will ye never want an excuse for not standing to
                        the compacts which ye make on being defeated? Ye gave hostages to Porsena:
                        ye clandestinely withdrew them. Ye ransomed your state from the Gauls, for
                        gold: while they were receiving the gold, they were put to the sword.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Ye concluded a peace with us, on
                        condition of our restoring your captured legions: that peace ye now annul;
                        in fine, ye always spread over your fraudulent conduct some show of right.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Do the Roman people disapprove of
                        their legions being saved by an ignominious peace? Let them have their
                        peace, and return the captured legions to the conqueror. This would be
                        conduct consistent with faith, with treaties, and with the laws of the
                        heralds. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But that you should, in
                        consequence of the convention, obtain what you desired, the safety of so
                        many of your countrymen, while I obtain not, what I stipulated for on
                        sending you back those men, a peace; is this the law which you, Aulus
                        Cornelius, which ye, heralds, prescribe to nations? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> But for my part, I neither accept those men whom ye
                        pretend to surrender, nor consider them as surrendered; nor do I hinder them
                        from returning into their own country, which stands bound under an actual
                        convention, formally entered into, carrying with them the wrath of all the
                        gods, <pb n="575" xml:id="p.575"/> whose authority is thus baffled.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Wage war, since Spurius Postumius has
                        just now struck with his knee the herald, in character of ambassador. The
                        gods are to believe that Postumius is a citizen of Samnium, not of Rome; and
                        that a Roman ambassador has been violated by a Samnite; and that therefore a
                        just war has been waged against us by you. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> That men of years, and of consular dignity, should not be ashamed to
                        exhibit such mockery of religion in the face of day! <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> And should have recourse to such shallow artifices to
                        palliate their breach of faith, unworthy even of children! Go, lictor, take
                        off the bonds from those Romans. Let no one delay them from departing when
                        they think proper. </quote> Accordingly they returned unhurt from Caudium to
                    the Roman camp, having acquitted, certainly, their own faith, and perhaps that
                    of the public. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Samnites finding that, instead of a peace
                    which flattered their pride, the war was revived, and with the utmost
                    inveteracy, not only felt, in their minds, a foreboding of all the consequences
                    which ensued, but saw them, in a manner, before their eyes. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They now, too late and in vain, applauded the plans of old
                    Pontius, by blundering between which, they had exchanged the possession of
                    victory for an uncertain peace; and having lost the opportunity of doing a
                    kindness or an injury, were now to fight against men, whom they might have
                    either put out of the way, for ever, as enemies; or engaged, for ever, as
                    friends. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And such was the change which had
                    taken place in men's minds, since the Caudine peace, even before any trial of
                    strength had shown an advantage on either side, that Postumius, by surrendering
                    himself, had acquired greater renown among the Romans, than Pontius among the
                    Samnites, by his bloodless victory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans
                    considered their being at liberty to make war, as certain victory; while the
                    Samnites supposed the Romans victorious, the moment they resumed their arms.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, the Satricans revolted to the
                    Samnites, who attacked the colony of Fregellae, by a sudden surprise in the
                    night, accompanied, as it appears, by the Satricans. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> From that time until day, their mutual fears kept both
                    parties quiet: the daylight was the signal for battle, which the Fregellans
                    contrived to maintain, for a considerable time, without loss of ground; both
                    because they fought for their religion and liberty; and <pb n="576"
                        xml:id="p.576"/> the multitude, who were unfit to bear arms, assisted them,
                    from the tops of the houses. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At length a
                    stratagem gave the advantage to the assailants; for they suffered the voice of a
                    crier to be heard proclaiming, that <quote>whoever laid down his arms might
                        retire in safety.</quote> This relaxed their eagerness in the fight, and
                    they began almost every where to throw away their arms. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A part, more determined, however, retaining their arms,
                    rushed out by the opposite gate, and their boldness brought greater safety to
                    them, than their fears, which inclined them to credulity, did to the others: for
                    the Samnites, having surrounded the latter with fires, burned them all to death,
                    while they made vain appeals to the faith of gods and men. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls having settled the provinces between them,
                    Papirius proceeded into Apulia to Luceria, where the Roman horsemen, given as
                    hostages at Caudium, were kept in custody: Publilius remained in Samnium, to
                    oppose the Caudine legions. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This proceeding
                    perplexed the minds of the Samnites: they could not safely determine either to
                    go to Luceria, lest the enemy should press on their rear; or to remain where
                    they were, lest in the mean time Luceria should be lost. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They concluded, therefore, that it would be most advisable
                    to trust to the decision of fortune, and to try the issue of a battle with
                    Publilius: accordingly they drew out their forces into the field. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Publilius was about to engage,
                    considering it proper to address his soldiers first, he ordered an assembly to
                    be summoned. But though they ran together to the general's quarters with the
                    greatest alacrity, yet so loud were their clamours, demanding the fight, that
                    none of the general's exhortations were heard: each man's own reflections on the
                    late disgrace served as an exhortation. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                    advanced there- fore to battle, urging the standard-bearers to hasten; and rest,
                    in beginning the conflict, there should be any delay, in wielding their javelins
                    and then drawing their swords, they threw away the former, as if a signal to
                    that purpose had been given, and, drawing the latter, rushed in full speed upon
                    the foe. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nothing of a general's skill was
                    displayed in forming ranks or reserves; the resentment of the troops performed
                    all, with a degree of fury little inferior to madness. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The enemy, therefore, were not only completely routed, not
                    even daring to embarrass their flight by retreating to their camp, <pb n="577"
                        xml:id="p.577"/> but dispersing, made towards Apulia in scattered parties:
                    afterwards, however, collecting their forces into one body, they reached
                    Luceria. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The same exasperation, which had
                    carried the Romans through the midst of the enemy's line, carried them forward
                    also into their camp, where greater carnage was made, and more blood spilt, than
                    even in the field, while the greater part of the spoil was destroyed in their
                    rage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The other army, with the consul
                    Papirius, had now arrived at Arpi, on the sea-coast, having passed without
                    molestation through all the countries in their way; which was owing to the
                    ill-treatment received by those people from the Samnites, and their hatred
                    towards them, rather than to any favour received from the Roman people.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For such of the Samnites as dwelt on the
                    mountains in separate villages, used to ravage the low lands, and the places on
                    the coast; and being mountaineers, and savage themselves, despised the
                    husbandmen who were of a gentler kind, and, as generally happens, resembled the
                    district they inhabited. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Now if this tract had
                    been favourably affected towards the Samnites, either the Roman army could have
                    been prevented from reaching Arpi, or, as it lay between Rome and Arpi, it might
                    have intercepted the convoys of provisions, and utterly destroyed them by the
                    consequent scarcity of all necessaries. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Even
                    as it was, when they went from thence to Luceria, both the besiegers and the
                    besieged were distressed equally by want. Every kind of supplies was brought to
                    the Romans from Arpi; but in so very scanty proportion, that the horsemen had to
                    carry corn from thence to the camp, in little bags, for the foot, who were
                    employed in the outposts, watches, and works; and sometimes falling in with the
                    enemy, they were obliged to throw the corn from off their horses, in order to
                    fight. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Before the arrival of the other consul
                    and his victorious army, both provisions had been brought in to the Samnites,
                    and reinforcements conveyed in to them from the mountains; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> but the coming of Publilius contracted all their resources;
                    for, committing the siege to the care of his colleague, and keeping himself
                    disengaged, he threw every difficulty in the way of the enemy's convoys.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> There being therefore little hope for the
                    besieged, or that they would be able much longer to endure want, the Samnites,
                    encamped at Luceria, were obliged to collect their forces from every side, and
                    come to an engagement with Papirius. <pb n="578" xml:id="p.578"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this juncture, while both parties were
                    preparing for an action, ambassadors from the Tarentines interposed, requiring
                    both Samnites and Romans to desist from war; with menaces, that <quote> if
                        either refused to agree to a cessation of hostilities, they would join their
                        arms with the other party, against them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Papirius, on hearing the purport of their
                    embassy, as if influenced by their words, answered, that he would consult his
                    colleague: he then sent for him, employing the intermediate time in the
                    necessary preparations; and when he had conferred with him on a matter, about
                    which no doubt was entertained, he made the signal for battle. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> While the consuls were employed in performing the religious
                    rites, and the other usual business preparatory to an engagement, the Tarentine
                    ambassadors put themselves in their way, expecting an answer: <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> to whom Papirius said, <quote> Tarentines, the priest
                        reports that the auspices are favourable, and that our sacrifices have been
                        attended with excellent omens: under the direction of the gods, we are
                        proceeding, as you see, to action. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then ordered the standards to move, and led
                    out the troops; thus rebuking the exorbitant arrogance of that nation, which at
                    a time when, through intestine discord and sedition, it was unequal to the
                    management of its own affairs, yet presumed to prescribe the bounds of peace and
                    war to others. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the other side, the
                    Samnites, who had neglected every preparation for fighting, either because they
                    were really desirous of peace, or it seemed their interest to pretend to be so,
                    in order to conciliate the favour of the Tarentines, when they saw, on a
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> sudden, the Romans drawn up for battle,
                    cried out, that <quote> they would continue to be directed by the Tarentines,
                        and would neither march out, nor carry their arms beyond the rampart. That
                        if deceived, they would rather endure any consequence which chance may
                        bring, than show contempt to the Tarentines, the advisers of peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls said, that <quote> they embraced
                        the omen, and prayed that the enemy might continue in the resolution of not
                        even defending their rampart. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then, dividing the forces between them, they
                    advanced to the works; and, making an assault on every side at once, while some
                    filled up the trenches, others tore down the rampart, and tumbled it into the
                    trench. All were stimulated, not only by their native courage, but by the
                    resentment which, since their disgrace, had been festering in their <pb n="579"
                        xml:id="p.579"/> breasts. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They made their
                    way into the camp; where, every one repeating, that here was not Caudium, nor
                    the forks, nor the impassable glens, where cunning haughtily triumphed over
                    error; but Roman valour, which no rampart nor trench could ward off; —they slew,
                    without distinction, those who resisted and those who fled, the armed and
                    unarmed, freemen and slaves, young and old, men and cattle. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Nor would a single animal have escaped, had not the consuls
                    given the signal for retreat; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and, by
                    commands and threats, forced out of the camp the soldiers, greedy of slaughter.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As they were highly incensed at being
                    thus interrupted in the gratification of their vengeance, a speech was
                    immediately addressed to them, assuring the soldiers, that <quote> the consuls
                        neither did nor would fall short of any one of the soldiers, in hatred
                        toward the enemy; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> on the contrary, as
                        they led the way in battle, so would they have done the same in executing
                        unbounded vengeance, had not the consideration of the six hundred horsemen,
                        who were confined as hostages in Luceria, restrained their inclinations;
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> lest total despair of pardon might
                        drive on the enemy blindly to take vengeance on them, eager to destroy them
                        before they themselves should perish. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The soldiers highly applauded this conduct,
                    and rejoiced that their resentment had been checked, and acknowledged that every
                    thing ought to be endured, rather than that the safety of so many Roman youths
                    of the first distinction should be brought into danger. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The assembly being then dismissed, a
                    consultation was held, whether they should press forward the siege of Luceria,
                    with all their forces; or, whether with one of the commanders, and his army,
                    trial should be made of the Apulians, a nation in the neighbourhood still
                    doubtful. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul Publilius set out to make
                    a circuit through Apulia, and in the one expedition either reduced by force, or
                    received into alliance on conditions, a considerable number of the states.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Papirius likewise, who had remained to
                    prosecute the siege of Luceria, soon found the event agreeable to his hopes: for
                    all the roads being blocked up through which provisions used to be conveyed from
                    Samnium, the Samnites, who were in garrison, were reduced so low by famine, that
                    they sent ambassadors to the Roman consul, proposing that he should raise the
                    siege, on receiving the horsemen who were the cause of the war. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="580" xml:id="p.580"/> To whom Papirius returned this answer, that <quote>
                        they ought to have consulted Pontius, son of Herennius, by whose advice they
                        had sent the Romans under the yoke, what treatment he thought fitting for
                        the conquered to undergo. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But since,
                        instead of offering fair terms themselves, they chose rather that they
                        should be imposed on them by their enemies, he desired them <milestone
                            n="6??" unit="section"/> to carry back orders to the troops in Luceria,
                        that they should leave within the walls their arms, baggage, beasts of
                        burthen, and all persons unfit for war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        The soldiers he would send under the yoke with single garments, retaliating
                        the disgrace formerly inflicted, not inflicting a new one. </quote> The
                    terms were not rejected. Seven thousand soldiers were sent under the yoke, and
                    an immense booty was seized in Luceria, all the standards and arms which they
                    had lost at Caudium being recovered; and, what greatly surpassed all their joy,
                    recovered the horsemen whom the Samnites had sent to Luceria to be kept as
                    pledges of the peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hardly ever did the
                    Romans gain a victory more distinguished for the sudden reverse produced in the
                    state of their affairs; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> especially if it be
                    true, as I find in some annals, that Pontius, son of Herennius, the Samnite
                    general, was sent under the yoke along with the rest, to atone for the disgrace
                    of the consuls. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I think it indeed more
                    strange that there should exist any doubt whether it was Lucius Cornelius, in
                    quality of dictator, Lucius Papirius Cursor being master of the horse, who
                    performed these achievements at Caudium, and afterwards at Luceria, as the
                    single avenger of the disgrace of the Romans, enjoying the best deserved
                    triumph, perhaps, next to that of Furius Camillus, which had ever yet been
                    obtained; or whether that honour belongs to the consuls, and particularly to
                    Papirius. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This uncertainty is followed by
                    another, whether, at the next election, 'Papirius Cursor was chosen consul a
                    third time, with Quintus Aulus Ceretanus a second time, being re-elected in
                    requital of his services at Luceria; or whether it was Lucius Papirius
                    Mugillanus, the surname being mistaken. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From henceforth, the accounts are clear, that
                    the other wars were conducted to a conclusion by the consuls. Aulius, by one
                    successful battle, entirely conquered the Forentans. The city, to which their
                    army had retreated after its defeat, surrendered on terms, hostages having been
                    demanded. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With similar success the other
                    consul conducted his operations <pb n="581" xml:id="p.581"/> against the
                    Satricans; who, though Roman citizens, had, after the misfortune at Caudium,
                    revolted to the Samnites, and received a garrison into their city. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The Satricans, however, when the Roman army
                    approached their walls, sent deputies to sue for peace, with humble entreaties;
                    to whom the consul answered harshly, that <quote> they must not come again to
                        him, unless they either put to death, or delivered up, the Samnite garrison:
                    </quote> by which terms greater terror was struck into the colonists than by the
                    arms with which they were threatened. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    deputies, accordingly, several times asking the consul, how he thought that
                    they, who were few and weak, could attempt to use force against a garrison so
                    strong and well-armed: he desired them to <quote>seek counsel from those, by
                        whose advice they had received that garrison into the city.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They then departed, and returned to their
                    countrymen, having obtained from the consul, with much difficulty, permission to
                    consult their senate on the matter, and bring back their answer to him.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two factions divided the senate; one that
                    whose leaders had been the authors of the defection from the Roman people, the
                    other consisted of the citizens who retained their loyalty; both, however,
                    showed an earnest desire, that every means should be used towards effecting an
                    accommodation with the consul for the restoration of peace. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As the Samnite garrison, being in no respect prepared for
                    holding out a siege, intended to retire the next night out of the town, one
                    party thought it sufficient to discover to the consul, at what hour, through
                    what gate, and by what road, his enemy was to march out. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The other, against whose wishes defection to the Samnites
                    had occurred, even opened one of the gates for the consul in the night, secretly
                    admitting the armed enemy into the town. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In
                    consequence of this twofold treachery, the Samnite garrison was surprised and
                    overpowered by an ambush, placed in the woody places, near the road; and, at the
                    same time, a shout was raised in the city, which was now filled with the enemy.
                    Thus, in the short space of one hour, the Samnites were put to the sword, the
                    Satricans made prisoners, and all things reduced under the power of the consul;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> who, having instituted an inquiry by
                    whose means the revolt had taken place, scourged with rods and beheaded such as
                    he found to be guilty; and then, disarming the Satricans, he placed a strong
                    garrison in the place. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On this those writers
                        <pb n="582" xml:id="p.582"/> state, that Papirius Cursor proceeded to Rome
                    to celebrate his triumph, who say, that it was under his guidance Luceria was
                    retaken, and the Samnites sent under the yoke. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> Undoubtedly, as a warrior, he was deserving of every military praise,
                    excelling not only in vigour of mind, but likewise in strength of body.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He possessed extraordinary swiftness of
                    foot, surpassing every one of his age in running, from whence came the surname
                    into his family; and he is said, either from the robustness of his frame, or
                    from much practice, to have been able to digest a very large quantity of food
                    and wine. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Never did either the foot-soldier
                    or horseman feel military service more laborious, under any general, because he
                    was of a constitution not to be overcome by fatigue. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> The 'cavalry, on some occasion, venturing to request that,
                    in consideration of their good behaviour, he would excuse them some part of
                    their business, he told them, <quote> Ye should not say that no indulgence has
                        been granted you, —I excuse you from rubbing your horses' backs when ye
                        dismount. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He supported also the authority of command,
                    in all its vigour, both among the allies and his countrymen. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> The praetor of Praeneste, through fear, had been tardy in
                    bringing forward his men from the reserve to the front: he, walking before his
                    tent, ordered him to be called, and then bade the lictor to make ready his axe,
                    on which, the Praenestine standing frightened almost to death, he said,
                        <quote>Here, lictor, cut away this stump, it is troublesome to people as
                        they walk;</quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> and, after thus alarming him with the dread
                    of the severest punishment, he imposed a fine and dismissed him. <milestone
                        n="19" unit="section"/> It is beyond doubt, that during that age, than which
                    none was ever more productive of virtuous characters, there was no man in whom
                    the Roman affairs found a more effectual support; nay, people even marked him
                    out, in their minds, as a match for Alexander the Great, in case that, having
                    completed the conquest of Asia, he should have turned his arms on Europe. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nothing can be found farther from my
                    intention, since the commencement of this history, than to digress, more than
                    necessity required, from the course of narration; and, by embellishing my work
                    with variety, to seek pleasing resting-places, as it were, for my readers, and
                    relaxation for my own mind: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> nevertheless, the
                    mention of so great a king and commander, now calls forth to public view those
                    silent reflections, <pb n="583" xml:id="p.583"/> with which it has oftentimes
                    occupied my mind; and disposes me to inquire, what would have been the
                    consequence, respecting the affairs of the Romans, if they had happened to have
                    been engaged in a war with Alexander. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    circumstances of greatest moment in war seem to be, the number and bravery of
                    the soldiers, the abilities of the commanders, and fortune, which exerts a
                    powerful sway over all human concerns, and especially over those of war.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now these particulars, to one who
                    considers them both separately and collectively, must clearly convince an
                    observer, that not only other kings and nations, but that even Alexander
                    himself, would have found the Roman empire invincible. And first to begin with
                    comparing the commanders. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I do not, indeed,
                    deny that Alexander was a captain of consummate merit; but still it renders him
                    more illustrious that he was single in command, and that he died young, while
                    his affairs were advancing in improvement, and while he had not yet experienced
                    a reverse of fortune. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For, to pass by other
                    illustrious kings and leaders, who afford exemplary instances of the decline of
                    human greatness, what was it, but length of life, which subjected Cyrus (whom
                    the Greeks, in their panegyrics, exalt so far beyond all others) to the caprice
                    of fortune? And the same was, lately, the case of Pompey the Great. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> I shall enumerate the Roman chiefs; not every one of
                    every age, but those very ones with whom, either as consuls or dictators,
                    Alexander might have been engaged: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Valerius Corvus, Caius Marcius Rutilus, Caius Sulpicius, Titus Manlius
                    Torquatus, Quintus Publilius Philo, Lucius Papirius Cursor, Quintus Fabius
                    Maximus, the two Decii, Lucius Volumnius, Manius Curius. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Then follow a number of very extraordinary men, had it so
                    happened, that he had first engaged in war with Carthage, and had come into
                    Italy at a more advanced period of life. Every one of these both possessed
                    powers of mind and a capacity equal with Alexander; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and also a regular system of military discipline had been
                    transmitted from one to another, from the first rise of the city of Rome; a
                    system now reduced into the form of an art, completely digested in a train of
                    fixed and settled principles. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> According to
                    these principles kings had carried on wars; and afterwards, the expellers of
                    those kings, the Junii and Valerii; according to these the Fabii, the Quintii,
                    the Cornelii, and so too Furius Camillus, who was an old man in the earlier
                    years of those with <pb n="584" xml:id="p.584"/> whom Alexander must have
                    fought. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Manlius Torquatus, had he met him in
                    the field, might, perhaps, have yielded to Alexander in discharging military
                    duties in battle (for these also render him no less illustrious); and so might
                    Valerius Corvus; men who were distinguished soldiers, before they became
                    commanders. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The same, too, might have been
                    the case with the Decii, who, after devoting their persons, rushed upon the
                    enemy; or of Papirius Cursor, though possessed of such powers, both of body and
                    mind. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> By the counsels of one youth, it is
                    possible the wisdom of a whole senate, not to mention individuals, might have
                    been baffled, [consisting of such members,] that he alone, who declared that
                        <quote>it consisted of kings,</quote> conceived a correct idea of a Roman
                    senate. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> But then the danger was, that with
                    more judgment than any one of those whom I have named he might choose ground for
                    an encampment, provide supplies, guard against stratagems, distinguish the
                    season for fighting, form his line of battle, or strengthen it properly with
                    reserves. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He would have owned that he was not
                    dealing with Darius, who drew after him a train of women and eunuchs; saw
                    nothing about him but gold and purple; was encumbered with the trappings of his
                    state, and should be called his prey, rather than his antagonist; whom therefore
                    he vanquished without loss of blood, and had no other merit, on the occasion,
                    than that of showing a proper spirit in despising empty show. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> The aspect of Italy would have appeared to him of a quite
                    different nature from that of India, which he traversed in the guise of a
                    reveller, at the head of a crew of drunkards, if he had seen the forests of
                    Apulia, and the mountains of Lucania, with the vestiges of the disasters of his
                    house, and where his uncle Alexander, king of Epirus, had been lately cut off. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> We are now speaking of Alexander not yet
                    intoxicated by prosperity, the seductions of which no man was less capable of
                    withstanding. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But, if he is to be judged from
                    the tenor of his conduct in the new state of his fortune, and from the new
                    disposition, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> as I may say, which he put on
                    after his successes, he would have entered Italy more like Darius than
                    Alexander; and would have brought thither an army who had forgotten Macedonia,
                    and were degenerating into the manners of the Persians. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It is painful, in speaking of so great a king, to recite
                    his ostentatious change of dress; his requiring that people should address him
                    with adulation, <pb n="585" xml:id="p.585"/> prostrating themselves on the
                    ground, a practice insupportable to the Macedonians, had they even been
                    conquered, much more so when they were victorious; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> the shocking cruelty of his punishments; his murdering his
                    friends in the midst of feasting and wine; with the folly of his fiction
                    respecting his birth. What must have been the consequence, if his love of wine
                    had daily become more intense? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> if his fierce
                    and uncontrollable anger? And as I mention not any one circumstance of which
                    there is a doubt among writers, do we consider these as no disparagements to the
                    qualifications of a commander? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But then, as is
                    frequently repeated by the silliest of the Greeks, who are fond of exalting the
                    reputation, even of the Parthians, at the expense of the Roman name, the danger
                    was that the Roman people would not have had resolution to bear up against the
                    splendour of Alexander's name, who, however, in my opinion, was not known to
                    them even by common fame; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and while, in
                    Athens, a state reduced to weakness by the Macedonian arms, which at the very
                    time saw the ruins of Thebes smoking in its neighbourhood, men had spirit enough
                    to declaim with freedom against him, as is manifest from the copies of their
                    speeches, which have been preserved; [we are to be told] that out of such a
                    number of Roman chiefs, no one would have freely uttered his sentiments.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> How great soever our idea of this man's
                    greatness may be, still it is the greatness of an individual, constituted by the
                    successes of a little more than ten years; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    and those who give it pre-eminence on account that the Roman people have been
                    defeated, though not in any entire war, yet in several battles, whereas
                    Alexander was never once unsuccessful in a single fight, do not consider that
                    they are comparing the actions of one man, and that a young man, with the
                    exploits of a nation waging wars now eight hundred years. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Can we wonder if, when on the one side more ages are
                    numbered than years on the other, fortune varied more in so long a lapse of time
                    than in the short term of thirteen years? <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The duration of Alexander's military career.</note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But why not compare the success of one
                    general with that of another? How many Roman commanders might I name who never
                    lost a battle? In the annals of the magistrates, and the records, we may run
                    over whole pages of consuls and dictators, with whose bravery, and successes
                    also, the Roman <pb n="586" xml:id="p.586"/> people never once had reason to be
                    dissatisfied. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And what renders them more
                    deserving of admiration than Alexander, or any king, is, that some of these
                    acted in the office of dictator, which lasted only ten, or it might be twenty
                    days; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> none, in a charge of longer duration
                    than the consulship of a year; their levies obstructed by plebeian tribunes;
                    often late in taking the field; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> recalled,
                    before the time, on account of elections; amidst the very busiest efforts of the
                    campaign, their year of office expired; sometimes the rashness, sometimes the
                    perverseness of a colleague, proving an impediment or detriment; and finally
                    succeeding to the unfortunate administration of a predecessor, with an army of
                    raw or ill-dis- ciplined men. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But, on the
                    other hand, kings, being not only free from every kind of impediment, but
                    masters of circumstances and seasons, control all things in subserviency to
                    their designs, themselves uncontrolled by any. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                    /> So that Alexander, unconquered, would have encountered unconquered
                    commanders; and would have had stakes of equal consequence pledged on the issue.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Nay, the hazard had been greater on his
                    side; because the Macedonians would have had but one Alexander, who was not only
                    liable, but fond of exposing himself to casualties; <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/> the Romans would have had many equal to Alexander, both in
                    renown, and in the greatness of their exploits; any one of whom might live or
                    die according to his destiny, without any material consequence to the public. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It remains that the forces be compared
                    together, with respect to their numbers, the quality of the men, and their
                    supplies of auxiliaries. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now, in the general
                    surveys of that age, there were rated two hundred and fifty thousand men; so
                    that, on every revolt of the Latin confederates, ten legions were enlisted
                    almost entirely in the city levy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It often
                    happened during those years, that four or five armies were employed at a time,
                    in Etruria, in Umbria, the Gauls also being at war, in Samnium, in Lucania.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then as to all Latium, with the Sabines,
                    and Volscians, the Aequans, and all Campania; half of Umbria, Etruria, and the
                    Picentians, the Marsians, Pelignians, Vestinians, and Apulians; to whom we may
                    add, the whole coast of the lower sea, possessed by the Greeks, from Thurii to
                    Neapolis and Cumae; and the Samnites from thence as far as Antium and Ostia: all
                    these he would have found either powerful allies to the Romans, or <pb n="587"
                        xml:id="p.587"/> deprived of power by their arms. He would have crossed the
                    sea with his veteran Macedonians, amounting to no more than thirty thousand
                    infantry and four thousand horse, these mostly Thessalians. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This was the whole of his strength. Had he brought with him
                    Persians and Indians, and those other nations, it would be dragging after him an
                    encumbrance rather than a support. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Add to
                    this, that the Romans, being at home, would have had recruits at hand:
                    Alexander, waging war in a foreign country, would have found his army worn out
                    with long service, as happened afterwards to Hannibal. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As to arms, theirs were a buckler and long spears; those of
                    the Romans, a shield, which covered the body more effectually, and a javelin, a
                    much more forcible weapon than the spear, either in throwing or striking. The
                    soldiers, on both sides, were used to steady combat, and to preserve their
                    ranks. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the Macedonian phalanx was unapt
                    for motion, and composed of similar parts throughout: the Roman line less
                    compact, consisting of several various parts, was easily divided as occasion
                    required, and as easily conjoined. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then what
                    soldier is comparable to the Roman in the throwing up of works? who better
                    calculated to endure fatigue? Alexander, if overcome in one battle, would have
                    been overcome in war. The Roman, whom Claudium, whom Cannae, did not crush, what
                    line of battle could crush? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In truth, even
                    should events have been favourable to him at first, he would have often wished
                    for the Persians, the Indians, and the effeminate tribes of Asia, as opponents;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and would have acknowledged, that his
                    wars had been waged with women, as we are told was said by Alexander, king of
                    Epirus, after receiving his mortal wound, when comparing the wars waged in Asia
                    by this very youth, with those in which himself had been engaged. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Indeed, when I reflect that, in the first Punic war,
                    a contest was maintained by the Romans with the Carthaginians, at sea, for
                    twenty-four years, I can scarcely suppose that the life of Alexander would have
                    been long enough for the finishing of one war [with either of <milestone
                        n="13??" unit="section"/> those nations]. And perhaps, as both the Punic
                    state was united to the Roman by ancient treaties, and as similar apprehensions
                    might arm against a common foe those two nations the most potent of the time in
                    arms and in men, he might have been overwhelmed in a Punic and a Roman war at
                    once. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The Romans have had experience of the
                    boasted prowess of <pb n="588" xml:id="p.588"/> the Macedonians in arms, not
                    indeed under Alexander as their general, or when their power was at the height,
                    but in the wars against Antiochus, Philip, and Perses; and not only not with any
                    losses, but not even with any danger to themselves. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Let not my assertion give offence, nor our civil wars be
                    brought into mention; never were we worsted by an enemy's cavalry, never by
                    their infantry, never in open fight, never on equal ground, much less when the
                    ground was favourable. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Our soldiers, heavy
                    laden with arms, may reasonably fear a body of cavalry, or arrows; defiles of
                    difficult passage, and places impassable to convoys. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> But they have defeated, and will defeat a thousand armies,
                    more formidable than those of Alexander and the Macedonians, provided that the
                    same love of peace and solicitude about domestic harmony, in which we now live,
                    continue permanent. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Foslius Flaccinator and Lucius Plautius
                    Venno were the next raised to the consulship. In this year ambassadors came from
                    most of the states of the Samnites to procure a renewal of the treaty;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and, after they had moved the compassion
                    of the senate, by prostrating themselves before them, on being referred to the
                    people, they found not their prayers so efficacious. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The treaty therefore, being refused, after they had
                    importuned them individually for several days, was obtained. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Teaneans likewise, and Canusians of Apulia, worn out by
                    the devastations of their country, surrendered themselves to the consul, Lucius
                    Plautius, and gave hostages. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This year
                    praefects first began to be created for Capua, and a code of laws was given to
                    that nation, by Lucius Furius the praetor; both in compliance with their own
                    request, as a remedy for the disorder of their affairs, occasioned by intestine
                    dissensions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At Rome, two additional tribes
                    were constituted, the Ufentine and Falerine. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    On the affairs of Apulia falling into decline, the Teatians of that country came
                    to the new consuls, Caius Junius Bubulcus, and Quintus Aemilius Barbula, suing
                    for an alliance; and engaging, that peace should be observed towards the Romans
                    through every part of Apulia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By pledging
                    themselves boldly for this, they obtained the grant of an alliance, not however
                    on terms of equality, but of their submitting to the dominion of the Roman
                    people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Apulia being entirely reduced, (for
                    Junius had also gained pos- session of Forentum, a town of great strength,) the
                    consuls ad- <pb n="589" xml:id="p.589"/> vanced into Lucania; there Nerulum was
                    surprised and storm- ed by the sudden advance of the consul Aemilius. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> When fame had spread abroad among the allies, how
                    firmly the affairs of Capua were settled by [the introduction of] the Roman
                    institutions, the Antians, imitating the example, presented a complaint of their
                    being without laws, and without magistrates; on which the patrons of the colony
                    itself were appointed by the senate to form a body of laws for it. Thus not only
                    the arms, but the laws, of Rome became extensively prevalent. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, Caius Junius Bubulcus and Quintus
                    Aemilius Barbula, at the conclusion of the year, delivered over the legions, not
                    to the consuls elected by themselves, who were Spurius Nautius and Marcus
                    Popillius, but to a dictator, Lucius Aemilius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    He, with Lucius Fulvius, master of the horse, having commenced to lay siege to
                    Saticula, gave occasion to the Samnites of reviving hostilities. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Hence a twofold alarm was occasioned to the Roman
                    army. On one side, the Samnites having collected a numerous force to relieve
                    their allies from the siege, pitched their camp at a small distance from that of
                    the Romans: on the other side, the Saticulans, opening suddenly their gates, ran
                    up with violent tumult to the posts of the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Afterwards, each party, relying on support from the other,
                    more than on its own strength, formed a regular attack, and pressed on the
                    Romans. The dictator, on his part, though obliged to oppose two enemies at once,
                    yet had his line secure on both sides; for he both chose a position not easily
                    surrounded, and also formed two different fronts. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> However, he directed his greater efforts against those who
                    had sallied from the town, and, without much resistance, drove them back within
                    the walls. He then turned his whole force against the Samnites: there he found
                    greater difficulty. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the victory, though
                    long delayed, was neither doubtful nor alloyed by losses. The Samnites, being
                    forced to fly into their camp, extinguished their fires at night, and marched
                    away in silence; and renouncing all hopes of relieving Saticula, sat themselves
                    down before Plistia, which was in alliance with the Romans, that they might, if
                    possible, retort equal vexation on their enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year coming to a conclusion, the war was
                    thenceforward conducted by a dictator, Quintius Fabius. The new <pb n="590"
                        xml:id="p.590"/> consuls, Lucius Papirius Cursor and Quintus Publilius
                    Philo, both a fourth time, as the former had done, remained at Rome. Fabius came
                    with a reinforcement to Saticula, to receive the army from Aemilius. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For the Samnites had not continued before Plistia;
                    but having sent for a new supply of men from home, and relying on their numbers,
                    had en- camped in the same spot as before; and, by provoking the Romans to
                    battle, endeavoured to divert them from the siege. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator, so much the more intently, pushed forward his
                    operations against the fortifications of the enemy; consider- ing that only as
                    war which was directed against the city, and showing an indifference with
                    respect to the Samnites, except that he placed guards in proper places, to
                    prevent any at- tempt on his camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The more
                    furiously did the Samnites ride up to the rampart, and allowed him no quiet.
                    When the enemy were now come up close to the gates of the camp, Quintus Aulius
                    Cerretanus, master of the horse, without con- sulting the dictator, sallied out
                    furiously at the head of all the troops of cavalry, and drove back the enemy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In this de- sultory kind of fight, fortune
                    worked up the strength of the combatants in such a manner, as to occasion an
                    extraordinary loss on both sides, and the remarkable deaths of the com- manders
                    themselves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> First, the general of the
                    Samnites, in- dignant at being repulsed, and compelled to fly from a place to
                    which he had advanced so confidently, by entreating and exhorting his horsemen,
                    renewed the battle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As he was easily
                    distinguished among the horsemen, while he urged on the fight, the Roman master
                    of the horse galloped up against him, with his spear directed, so furiously,
                    that, with one stroke, he tumbled him lifeless from his horse. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The multitude, however, were not, as is generally the case,
                    dismayed by the fall of their leader, but rather raised to fury. All who were
                    within reach darted their weapons at Aulius, who incautiously pushed for- ward
                    among the enemy's troops; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but the chief share
                    of the honour of revenging the death of the Samnite general they assigned to his
                    brother; he, urged by rage and grief, dragged down the victorious master of the
                    horse from his seat, and slew him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor were
                    the Samnites far from obtaining his body also, as he had fallen among the
                    enemies' troops: but the Romans instantly dismounted, and the Samnites were
                    obliged to do the same; and lines being thus formed suddenly, <pb n="591"
                        xml:id="p.591"/> they began a battle on foot, round the bodies of the
                    generals, in which the Romans had manifestly the advantage; and recovering the
                    body of Aulius, carried it back in triumph to the camp, with joy mixed with
                    grief. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Samnites having lost their
                    commander, and made a trial of their strength in this contest between the
                    cavalry, left Saticula, which they in vain hoped to relieve, and returned to the
                    siege of Plistia: within a few days after which, the Romans got possession of
                    Saticula by capitulation, and the Samnites of Plistia by force. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The seat of the war was then changed. The
                    legions were led away from Samnium and Apulia to Sora. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Sora had revolted to the Samnites, and put to death the
                    Roman colonists. The Roman army having arrived here first, by forced marches,
                    with the purpose of revenging <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> the murder of
                    their countrymen, and recovering possession of the colony, and the scouts who
                    were scattered about the roads bringing intelligence, one after another, that
                    the Samnites were following and were now not <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    far off, they marched to meet the enemy, and at Lautulae fought them with
                    doubtful success. Neither loss nor flight on either side, but the night
                    separated the combatants, uncertain whether they were victorious or defeated.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I find in some historians, that the Romans
                    were worsted in this battle, and that here Quintus Aulius, the master of the
                    horse, fell. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Caius Fabius, substituted master
                    of the horse in the room of Quintus Aulius, came hither with a new army from
                    Rome; and having, by messengers whom he sent forward, consulted the dictator,
                    where he should halt, at what time, and on what side he should fall upon the
                    enemy, and, being sufficiently apprized of his designs in every particular, he
                    rested in a place where he was safe from observation. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator, after having kept his men within the rampart
                    for several days after the engagement, like one besieged, rather than a
                    besieger, suddenly displayed the signal for battle; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and judging it the more efficacious method of inflaming the
                    courage of brave men, to let none have any room for hope but in himself, he kept
                    secret from the troops the arrival of the master of the horse and the new army;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and, as if there were no safety but in
                    forcing their way thence, he said, <quote> Soldiers, caught as we are in a
                        confined situation, we have no passage through which we can extricate
                        ourselves, unless we open one by a victory. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> Our post is sufficiently secured by works; <pb n="592" xml:id="p.592"/>
                        but, at the same time, untenable through scarcity of necessaries: for all
                        the country round, from which provisions could be supplied, has revolted;
                        and besides, even were the inhabitants disposed to aid us, the ground is
                        unfavourable. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I will not therefore
                        mislead you by leaving a camp here, into which ye may retreat, as on a
                        former day, without completing the victory. Works ought to be secured by
                        arms, not arms by works. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Let those keep a
                        camp, and repair to it, whose interest it is to protract the war; but let us
                        cut off from ourselves every other prospect but that of conquering.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Advance the standards against the
                        enemy; as soon as the troops shall have marched beyond the rampart, let
                        those who have it in orders burn the camp. Your losses, soldiers, shall be
                        compensated with the spoil of all the nations round who have revolted. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The soldiers advanced against the enemy with
                    spirits inflamed by the dictator's discourse, which seemed indicative of an
                    extreme necessity; and, at the same time, the very sight of the camp burning
                    behind them, though the nearest part only was set on fire, (for so the dictator
                    had ordered,) was no small incitement: <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    rushing on therefore like madmen, they disordered the enemy's battalions at the
                    very first onset; and the master of the horse, when he saw at a distance the
                    fire of the camp, which was a signal agreed on, made a seasonable attack on
                    their rear. The Samnites, thus surrounded on every side, fled different ways.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> A vast number, who had gathered into a
                    body through fear, yet from confusion incapable of acting, were surrounded and
                    cut to pieces. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The enemy's camp was taken and
                    plundered; and the soldiers being laden with the spoil, the dictator led them
                    back to the Roman camp, highly rejoiced at the success, but by no means so much
                    as at finding, contrary to their expectation, every thing there safe, except a
                    small part only, which was injured or destroyed by the fire. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They then marched back to Sora; and the new
                    consuls, Marcus Pœtelius and Caius Sulpicius, receive the army from the dictator
                    Fabius, discharging a great part of the veteran soldiers, having brought with
                    them new cohorts to supply their place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now
                    while, on account of the difficult situation of the city, no certain mode of
                    attack could be devised, and success must either be distant in time, or at a
                    desperate risk; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> a deserter from Sora came out
                    of the town privately by night, and when he had got as far as the <pb n="593"
                        xml:id="p.593"/> Roman watches, desired to be conducted instantly to the
                    con- suls: which being complied with, he made them an offer of delivering the
                    place into their hands. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he answered their
                    questions, respecting the means by which he intended to make good his promise,
                    appearing to state a project by no means idle, he persuaded them to remove the
                    Roman camp, which was almost close to the walls, to the distance of six miles;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that the consequence would be that this
                    would render the guards by day, and the watches by night, the less vigilant.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then desired that some cohorts should
                    post themselves the following night in the woody places under the town, and took
                    with himself ten chosen soldiers, through steep and almost impassable ways, into
                    the citadel, where a quantity of missive weapons had been collected, larger than
                    bore proportion to the number of men. There were stones besides, some lying at
                    random, as in all craggy places, and others heaped up designedly by the
                    townsmen, to add to the security of the place. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Having posted the Romans here, and shown them a steep and narrow path leading up
                    from the town to the citadel — <quote>From this ascent,</quote> said he, <quote>
                        even three armed men would keep off any multitude whatever. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Now ye are ten in number; and, what is more, Romans,
                        and the bravest among the Romans. The night is in your favour, which, from
                        the uncertainty it occasions, magnifies every object to people once alarmed.
                        I will immediately fill every place with terror: be ye alert in defending
                        the citadel. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then ran down in haste, crying aloud,
                        <quote>To arms, citizens, we are undone, the citadel is taken by the enemy;
                        run, defend it.</quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This he repeated, as he passed the doors of
                    the principal men, the same to all whom he met, and also to those who ran out in
                    a fright into the streets. The alarm, communicated first by one, was soon spread
                    by numbers through all the city. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    magistrates, dismayed on hearing from scouts that the citadel was full of arms
                    and armed men, whose number they multiplied, laid aside all hopes of recovering
                    it. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> All places are filled with terror: the
                    gates are broken open by persons half asleep, and for the most part unarmed,
                    through one of which the body of Roman troops, roused by the noise, burst in,
                    and slew the terrified inhabitants, who attempted to skirmish in the streets.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Sora was now taken, when, at the first
                    light, the consuls arrived, and accepted the surrender of those whom fortune had
                        <pb n="594" xml:id="p.594"/> left remaining after the flight and slaughter
                    of the night. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Of these, they conveyed in
                    chains to Rome two hundred and twenty-five, whom all men agreed in pointing out
                    as the au- thors, both of the revolt, and also of the horrid massacre of the
                    colonists. The rest they left in safety at Sora, a garrison being placed there.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> All those who were brought to Rome were
                    beaten with rods in the forum, and beheaded, to the great joy of the commons,
                    whose interest it most highly con- cerned, that the multitudes, sent to various
                    places in colonies, should be in safety. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, leaving Sora, turned their
                    warlike opera- tions against the lands and cities of the Ausonians; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> for all places had been set in commotion by the
                    coming of the Sam- nites, when the battle was fought at Lautulae: conspiracies
                    likewise had been formed in several parts of Campania; nor was Capua itself
                    clear of the charge: nay, the business spread even to Rome, and inquiries came
                    to be instituted respecting some of the principal men there. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> However, the Ausonian nation fell into the Roman power, in
                    the same manner as Sora, by their cities being betrayed: these were Ausona,
                    Minturnae, and Vescia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Certain young men, of
                    the principal families, twelve in number, having conspired to betray their
                    respective cities, came to the consuls; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> they
                    informed them that their countrymen, who had for a long time before earn- estly
                    wished for the coming of the Samnites, on hearing of the battle at Lautulae, had
                    looked on the Romans as defeated, and had assisted the Samnites with supplies of
                    young men and arms; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but that, since the
                    Samnites had been beaten out of the country, they were wavering between peace
                    and war, not shutting their gates against the Romans, lest they should thereby
                    invite an attack; yet determined to shut them if an army should approach; that
                    in that fluctuating state they might easily be overpowered by surprise.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By these men's advice the camp was moved
                    nearer; and soldiers were sent, at the same time, to each of the three towns;
                    some armed, who were to lie concealed in places near the walls; others, in the
                    garb of peace, with swords hidden under their clothes, who, on the opening of
                    the gates at the approach of day, were to enter into the cities. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> These latter began with killing the guards; at the
                    same time, a signal was made to the men in arms, to hasten up from the
                    ambuscades. Thus the gates <pb n="595" xml:id="p.595"/> were seized, and the
                    three towns taken in the same hour and by the same device. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But as the attacks were made in the absence of the
                    generals, there were no bounds to the carnage which ensued; and the nation of
                    the Ausonians, when there was scarcely any clear proof of the charge of its
                    having revolted, was utterly destroyed, as if it had supported a contest through
                    a deadly war. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this year, Luceria fell into the hands
                    of the Samnites, the Roman garrison being betrayed to the enemy. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> This matter did not long go unpunished with the
                    traitors: the Roman army was not far off, by whom the city, which lay in a
                    plain, was taken at the first onset. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    Lucerians and Samnites were to a man put to the sword; and to such a length was
                    resentment carried, that at Rome, on the senate being consulted about sending a
                    colony to Luceria, many voted for the demolition of it. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Besides, their hatred was of the bitterest kind, against a
                    people whom they had been obliged twice to subdue by arms; the great distance,
                    also, made them averse from sending away their citizens among nations so
                    ill-affected towards them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> However the
                    resolution was carried, that the colonists should be sent; and accordingly two
                    thousand five hundred were transported thither. This year, when all places were
                    becoming disaffected to the Romans, secret conspiracies were formed among the
                    leading men at Capua, as well as at other places; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> a motion concerning which being laid before the senate, the
                    matter was by no means neglected. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Inquiries
                    were decreed, and it was resolved that a dictator should be appointed to enforce
                    these inquiries. Caius Maenius was accordingly nominated, and he appointed
                    Marcus Foslius master of the horse. People's dread of that office was very
                    great, insomuch that the Calavii, Ovius and Novius, who were the heads of the
                    conspiracy, either through fear of the dictator's power, or the consciousness of
                    guilt, previous to the charge against them being laid in form before him,
                    avoided, as appeared beyond doubt, trial by a voluntary death. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> As the subject of the inquiry in Campania was thus removed,
                    the proceedings were then directed towards Rome: <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> by construing the order of the senate to have meant, that inquiry should be
                    made, not specially who at Capua, but generally who at any place had caballed or
                    conspired against the state; for that cabals, for the attaining of honours, were
                        <pb n="596" xml:id="p.596"/> contrary to the edicts of the state. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The inquiry was extended to a greater latitude, with
                    respect both to the matter, and to the kind of persons concerned, the dictator
                    scrupling not to avow, that his power of research was unlimited: <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> in consequence, some of the nobility were called to
                    account; and though they applied to the tribunes for protection, no one
                    interposed in their behalf, or to prevent the charges from being received.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On this the nobles, not those only
                    against whom the charge was levelled, but the whole body jointly insisted that
                    such an imputation lay not against the nobles, to whom the way to honours lay
                    open if not obstructed by fraud, but against the new men: <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> so that even the dictator and master of the horse, with
                    respect to that question, would appear more properly as culprits than suitable
                    inquisitors; and this they should know as soon as they went out of office.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then indeed Maenius, who was more
                    solicitous about his character than his office, advanced into the assembly and
                    spoke to this effect: <quote> Romans, both of my past life ye are all witnesses;
                        and this honourable office, which ye conferred on me, is in itself a
                        testimony of my innocence. For the dictator, proper to be chosen for holding
                        these inquiries, was not, as on many other occasions, where the exigencies
                        of the state so required, the man who was most renowned in war; but him
                        whose course of life was most remote from such cabals. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> But certain of the nobility (for what reason it is more
                        proper that ye should judge, than that I, as a magistrate, should, without
                        proof, insinuate) have laboured to stifle entirely the inquiries; <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> and then, finding their strength unequal to it,
                        rather than stand a trial have fled for refuge to the stronghold of their
                        adversaries, an appeal, and the support of the tribunes; <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> and on being there also repulsed, (so fully were they
                        persuaded that every other measure was safer than the attempt to clear
                        themselves,) have made an attack upon us; and, though in private characters,
                        have not been ashamed of instituting a criminal process against a dictator.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Now, that gods and men may perceive
                        that they, to avoid a scrutiny as to their own conduct, attempt even things
                        which are impossible, and that I willingly meet the charge, and face the
                        accusations of my enemies, I divest myself of the dictatorship. <milestone
                            n="19" unit="section"/> And, consuls, I beseech you, that, if this
                        business is put into your hands by the senate, ye will make me and Marcus
                        Foslius the first objects of your ex- <pb n="597" xml:id="p.597"/>
                        aminations; that it may be manifested that we are safe from such imputations
                        by our own innocence, not by the dignity of office. </quote>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> He then abdicated the dictatorship, as did
                    Marcus Foslius, immediately after, his office of master of the horse; and being
                    the first brought to trial before the consuls, for to them the senate had
                    committed the business, they were most honourably acquitted of all the charges
                    brought by the nobles. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Even Publilius Philo,
                    who had so often been invested with the highest honours, and had performed so
                    many eminent services, both at home and abroad, being disagreeable to the
                    nobility, was brought to trial, and acquitted. <milestone n="22" unit="section"
                    /> Nor did the inquiry continue respectable on account of the illustrious names
                    of the accused, longer than while it was new, which is usually the case; it then
                    began to descend to persons of inferior rank; and, at length, was suppressed, by
                    means of those factions and cabals against which it had been instituted. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The accounts received of these matters, but
                    more especially the hope of a revolt in Campania, for which a conspiracy had
                    been formed, recalled the Samnites, who were turning towards Apulia, back to
                    Caudium; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> so that from thence, being near, they
                    might, if any commotion should open them an opportunity, snatch Capua out of the
                    hands of the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the same place the
                    consuls repaired with a powerful army. They both held back for some time, on the
                    different sides of the defiles, the roads being dangerous to either party.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then the Samnites, making a short circuit
                    through an open tract, marched down their troops into level ground in the
                    Campanian plains, and there the hostile camps first came within view of each
                    other. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Trial of their strength in slight
                    skirmishes was made on both sides, more frequently between the horse than the
                    foot; and the Romans were no way dissatisfied either at the issue of these, or
                    at the delay by which they protracted the war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Samnite generals, on the contrary, considered that their battalions were
                    becoming weakened daily by small losses, and the general vigour abated by
                    prolonging the war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They therefore marched
                    into the field, disposing their cavalry on both wings, with orders to give more
                    heedful attention to the camp behind than to the battle; for that the line of
                    infantry would be able to provide for their own safety. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls took post, Sulpicius on the right wing,
                    Pœtelius on the left. The right wing was stretched out wider than usual, where
                    the <pb n="598" xml:id="p.598"/> Samnites also stood formed in thin ranks,
                    either with design of turning the flank of the enemy, or to avoid being
                    themselves surrounded. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On the left, besides
                    that they were formed in more compact order, an addition was made to their
                    strength, by a sudden act of the consul Pœtelius; for the subsidiary cohorts,
                    which were usually reserved for the exigencies of a tedious fight, he brought up
                    immediately to the front, and, in the first onset, pushed the enemy with the
                    whole of his force. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Samnite line of
                    infantry giving way, their cavalry advanced to support them; and as they were
                    charging in an oblique direction between the two lines, the Roman horse, coming
                    up at full speed, disordered their battalions and ranks of infantry and cavalry,
                    so as to oblige the whole line on that side to give ground. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The left wing had not only the presence of Pœtelius to
                    animate them, but that of Sulpicius likewise; who, on the shout being first
                    raised in that quarter, rode thither from his own division, which had not yet
                    engaged. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When he saw victory no longer
                    doubtful there, he returned to his own post with twelve hundred men, but found
                    the state of things there very different; the Romans driven from their ground,
                    and the victorious enemy pressing on them thus dismayed. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> However, the arrival of the consul effected a speedy change
                    in every particular; for, on the sight of their leader, the spirit of the
                    soldiers was revived, and the bravery of the men who came with him rendered them
                    more powerful aid than even their number; while the news of success in the other
                    wing, which was heard, and after seen, restored the fight. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> From this time, the Romans became victorious through the
                    whole extent of the line, and the Samnites, giving up the contest, were slain or
                    taken prisoners, except such as made their escape to Maleventum, the town which
                    is now called Beneventum. It is recorded that thirty thousand of the Samnites
                    were slain or taken. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, after this important victory, led
                    forward the legions to lay siege to Bovianum; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and there they passed the winter quarters, until Caius Pœtelius, being nominated
                    dictator, with Marcus Foslius, master of the horse, received the command of the
                    army from the new consuls, Lucius Papirius Cursor a fifth, and Caius Junius
                    Bubulcus a second time. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On hearing that the
                    citadel of Fregellae was taken by the Samnites, he left Bovianum, and proceeded
                    to Fregellae, <pb n="599" xml:id="p.599"/> whence, having recovered possession
                    of it without any contest, the Samnites abandoning it in the night, and having
                    placed a strong garrison there, he returned to Campania, directing his
                    operations principally to the recovery of Nola. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Within the walls of this place, the whole multitude of the Samnites, and the
                    inhabitants of the country about Nola, betook themselves on the approach of the
                    dictator. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having taken a view of the situation
                    of the city, in order that the approach to the fortifications may be the more
                    open, he set fire to all the buildings which stood round the walls, which were
                    very numerous; and, in a short time after, Nola was taken, either by the
                    dictator Pœtelius, or the consul Caius Junius, for both accounts are given.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Those who attribute to the consul the
                    honour of taking Nola, add, that Atina and Calatia were also taken by him, and
                    that Pœtelius was created dictator in consequence of a pestilence breaking out,
                    merely for the purpose of driving the nail. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The colonies of Suessa and Pontiae were established in this year. Suessa had
                    belonged to the Auruncians: the Volscians had occupied Pontiae, an island lying
                    within sight of their shore. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A decree of the
                    senate was also passed for conducting colonies to Interamna and Cassinum. But
                    commissioners were appointed, and colonists, to the number of four thousand,
                    were sent by the succeeding consuls, Marcus Valerius and Publius Decius. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The war with the Samnites being now nearly put
                    an end to, before the Roman senate was freed from all concern on that side, a
                    report arose of an Etrurian war; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and there was
                    not, in those times, any nation, excepting the Gauls, whose arms were more
                    dreaded, by reason both of the vicinity of their country, and of the multitude
                    of their men. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While therefore one of the
                    consuls prosecuted the remains of the war in Samnium, Publius Decius, who, being
                    attacked by a severe illness, remained at Rome, by direction of the senate,
                    nominated Caius Junius Bubulcus dictator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He,
                    as the magnitude of the affair demanded, compelled all the younger citizens to
                    enlist, and with the utmost diligence prepared arms, and the other matters which
                    the occasion required. Yet he was not so elated by the power he had collected,
                    as to think of commencing offensive operations, but prudently determined to
                    remain quiet, unless the Etrurians should become aggressors. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The plans of the Etrurians were exactly similar, <pb
                        n="600" xml:id="p.600"/> with respect to preparing for, and abstaining from,
                    war: nei- ther party went beyond their own frontiers. The censorship of Appius
                    Claudius and Caius Plautius, for this year, was remarkable; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> but the name of Appius has been handed down with more
                    celebrity to posterity, on account of his having made the road, [called after
                    him, the Appian,] and for having conveyed water into the city. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> These works he performed alone; for his colleague,
                    overwhelmed with shame by reason of the infamous and unworthy choice made of
                    senators, had abdicated his office. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Appius
                    possessing that inflexibility of temper, which, from the earliest times, had
                    been the charac- teristic of his family, held on the censorship by himself.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By direction of the same Appius, the
                    Potitian family, in which the office of priests attendant on the great altar of
                    Hercules was hereditary, instructed some of the public servants in the rites of
                    that solemnity, with the intention to delegate the same to them. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> A circumstance is recorded, wonderful to be told,
                    and one which should make people scrupulous of disturbing the established modes
                    of religious solemnities: for though there were, at that time, twelve branches
                    of the Potitian family, all grown-up persons, to the number of thirty, yet they
                    were every one, together with their offspring, cut off within the year;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> so that the name of the Potitii became
                    extinct, while the censor Appius also was, by the unrelenting wrath of the gods,
                    some years after, deprived of sight. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls of the succeeding year were, Caius
                    Junius Bubulcus a third time, and Quintus Aemilius Barbula a se- cond. In the
                    commencement of their office, they complained before the people, that, by the
                    improper choice of members of the senate, that body had been disgraced, several
                    having been passed over who were preferable to the persons chosen in; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> and they declared, that they would pay no regard to
                    such election, which had been made without distinction of right or wrong, merely
                    to gratify interest or humour: they then im- mediately called over the list of
                    the senate, in the same order which had existed before the censorship of Appius
                    Claudius and Caius Plautius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Two public
                    employments, both relating to military affairs, came this year into the disposal
                    of the peo- ple; one being an order, that sixteen of the tribunes, for four
                    legions, should be appointed by the people; whereas hitherto they had been
                    generally in the gift of the dictators and con- <pb n="601" xml:id="p.601"/>
                    suls, very few of the places being left to suffrage. This order was proposed by
                    Lucius Atilius and Caius Marcius, plebeian tribunes. Another was, that the
                    people likewise should constitute two naval commissioners, for the equipping and
                    refitting of the fleet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The person who
                    introduced this order of the people, was Marcus Decius, plebeian tribune.
                    Another transaction of this year I should pass over as trifling, did it not seem
                    to bear some relation to religion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    flute-players, taking offence because they had been prohibited by the last
                    censors from holding their repasts in the temple of Jupiter, which had been
                    customary from very early times, went off in a body to Tibur; so that there was
                    not one left in the city to play at the sacrifices. The religious tendency of
                    this affair gave uneasiness to the senate; and they sent envoys to Tibur to
                    endeavour that these men might be sent back to Rome. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Tiburtines readily promised compliance, and first,
                    calling them into the senate-house, warmly recommended to them to return to
                    Rome; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and then, when they could not be
                    prevailed on, practised on them an artifice not ill adapted to the dispositions
                    of that description of people: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> on a festival
                    day, they invited them separately to their several houses, apparently with the
                    intention of heightening the pleasure of their feasts with music, and there
                    plied them with wine, of which such people are always fond, until they laid them
                    asleep. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In this state of insensibility they
                    threw them into waggons, and carried them away to Rome: nor did they know any
                    thing of the matter, until, the waggons having been left in the forum, the light
                    surprised them, still heavily sick from the debauch. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The people then crowded about them, and, on their
                    consenting at length to stay, privilege was granted them to ramble about the
                    city in full dress, with music, and the licence which is now practised every
                    year during three days. And that licence, which we see practised at present, and
                    the right of being fed in the temple, was restored to those who played at the
                    sacrifices. These incidents occurred while the public attention was deeply
                    engaged by two most important wars. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls adjusting the provinces between
                    them, the Samnites fell by lot to Junius, the new war of Etruria to Aemilius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In Samnium the Samnites had blockaded and
                    reduced by famine Cluvia, a Roman garrison, because they had been unable to take
                    it by storm; and, after torturing with stripes, <pb n="602" xml:id="p.602"/> in
                    a shocking manner, the townsmen who surrendered, they had put them to death.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Enraged at this cruelty, Junius determined
                    to postpone every thing else to the attacking of Cluvia; and, on the first day
                    that he assaulted the walls, took it by storm, and slew all who were grown to
                    man's estate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The victorious troops were led
                    from thence to Bovianum; this was the capital of the Pentrian Samnites, by far
                    the most opulent of their cities, and the most powerful both in men and arms.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The soldiers, stimulated by the hope of
                    plunder, for their resentment was not so violent, soon made themselves masters
                    of the town: where there was less severity exercised on the enemy; but a
                    quantity of spoil was carried off, greater almost than had ever been collected
                    out of all Samnium, and the whole was liberally bestowed on the assailants.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And when neither armies, camps, or cities
                    could now withstand the vast superiority of the Romans in arms; the attention of
                    all the leading men in Samnium became intent on this, that an opportunity should
                    be sought for some stratagem, if by any chance the army, proceeding with
                    incautious eagerness for plunder, could be caught in a snare and overpowered.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Peasants who deserted and some prisoners
                    (some thrown in their way by accident, some purposely) reporting to the consul a
                    statement in which they concurred, and one which was at the same time true, that
                    a vast quantity of cattle had been driven together into a defile of difficult
                    access, prevailed on them to lead thither the legions lightly accoutred for
                    plunder. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Here a very numerous army of the
                    enemy had posted themselves, secretly, at all the passes; and, as soon as they
                    saw that the Romans had got into the defile, they rose up suddenly, with great
                    clamour and tumult, and attacked them unawares. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> At first an event so unexpected caused some confusion, while they were taking
                    their arms, and throwing the baggage into the centre; but, as fast as each had
                    freed himself from his burden and fitted himself with arms, they assembled about
                    the standards, from every side; and all, from the long course of their service,
                    knowing their particular ranks, the line was formed of its own accord without
                    any directions. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consul, riding up to the
                    place where the fight was most warm, leaped from his horse, and called <quote>
                        Jupiter, Mars, and the other gods to witness, that he had come into that
                        place, not in pursuit of any glory to <pb n="603" xml:id="p.603"/> himself,
                        but of booty for his soldiers; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> nor could
                        any other fault be charged on him, than too great a solicitude to enrich his
                        soldiers at the expense of the enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        From that disgrace nothing could extricate him but the valour of the troops:
                        let them only join unanimously in a vigorous attack against a foe, already
                        vanquished in the field, beaten out of their camps, and stripped of their
                        towns, and now trying their last hope by the contrivance of an ambuscade,
                        placing their reliance on the ground they occupied, not on their arms.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But what ground was now
                        unsurmountable to Roman valour? </quote> The citadel of Fregellae, and that
                    of Sora, were called to their remembrance, with many other places where
                    difficulties from situation had been surmounted. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Animated by these exhortations, the soldiers, regardless of
                    all difficulties, advanced against the line of the enemy, posted above them; and
                    here there was some fatigue whilst the army was climbing the steep. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> But as soon as the first battalions got footing in
                    the plain, on the summit, and the troops perceived that they now stood on equal
                    ground, the dismay was instantly turned on the plotters; who, dispersing and
                    casting away their arms, attempted, by flight, to recover the same
                    lurking-places in which they had lately concealed themselves. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> But the difficulties of the ground, which had been intended
                    for the enemy, now entangled them in the snares of their own contrivance.
                    Accordingly very few found means to escape; twenty thousand men were slain, and
                    the victorious Romans hastened in several parties to secure the booty of cattle,
                    spontaneously thrown in their way by the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While such was the situation of affairs in
                    Samnium, all the states of Etruria, except the Arretians, had taken arms, and
                    vigorously commenced hostilities, by laying siege to Sutrium; which city, being
                    in alliance with the Romans, served as a barrier against Etruria. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Thither the other consul, Aemilius, came with an army
                    to deliver the allies from the siege. On the arrival of the Romans, the Sutrians
                    conveyed a plentiful supply of provisions into their camp, which was pitched
                    before the city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Etrurians spent the first
                    day in deliberating whether they should expedite or protract the war. On the day
                    following, when the speedier plan pleased the leaders in preference to the
                    safer, as soon as the sun rose the signal for battle was displayed, and the
                    troops marched out to <pb n="604" xml:id="p.604"/> the field; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> which being reported to the consul, he instantly commanded
                    notice to be given, that they should dine, and after taking refreshment, then
                    appear under arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The order was obeyed; and
                    the consul, seeing them armed and in readiness, ordered the standards to be
                    carried forth beyond the rampart, and drew up his men at a small distance from
                    the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Both parties stood a long time with
                    fixed attention, each waiting for the shout and fight to begin on the opposite
                    side; and the sun had passed the meridian before a weapon was thrown by either
                    side. Then, rather than leave the place without something being done, the shout
                    was given by the Etrurians, the trumpets sounded, and the battalions advanced.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With no less alertness do the Romans
                    commence the fight: both rushed to the fight with violent animosity; the enemy
                    were superior in numbers, the Romans in valour. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> The battle being doubtful, carries off great numbers on both sides,
                    particularly the men of greatest courage; nor did victory declare itself, until
                    the second line of the Romans came up fresh to the front, in the place of the
                    first, who were much fatigued. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Etrurians,
                    because their front line was not supported by any fresh reserves, fell all
                    before and round the standards, and in no battle whatever would there have been
                    seen less disposition <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> to run, or a greater
                    effusion of human blood, had not the night sheltered the Etrurians, who were
                    resolutely determined on death; so that the victors, not the vanquished, were
                    the first who desisted from fighting. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After
                    sunset the signal for retreat was given, and both parties retired in the night
                    to their camps. During the remainder of the year, nothing memorable was effected
                    at Sutrium; for, of the enemy's army, the whole first line had been cut off in
                    one battle, the reserves only being left, who were scarce sufficient to guard
                    the camp; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and, among the Romans, so numerous
                    were the wounds, that more wounded men died after the battle than had fallen in
                    the field. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius, consul for the ensuing year,
                    succeeded to the command of the army at Sutrium; the colleague given to him was
                    Caius Marcius Rutilus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the one side, Fabius
                    brought with him a reinforcement from Rome, and on the other, a new army had
                    been sent for, and came from home, to the Etrurians. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Many years had now passed without any disputes between the
                    patrician magistrates and plebeian tribunes, <pb n="605" xml:id="p.605"/> when a
                    contest took its rise from that family, which seemed raised by fate as
                    antagonists to the tribunes and commons of those times; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Appius Claudius, being censor, when the eighteen months had
                    expired, which was the time limited by the Aemilian law for the duration of the
                    censorship, although his colleague Caius Plautius had already resigned his
                    office, could not be prevailed on, by any means, to give up his. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> There was a tribune of the commons, Publius
                    Sempronius; he undertook to enforce a legal process for terminating the
                    censorship within the lawful time, which was not more popular than just, nor
                    more pleasing to the people generally than to every man of character in the
                    city. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After he frequently appealed to the
                    Aemilian law, and bestowed commendations on Mamercus Aemilius, who, in his
                    dictatorship, had been the author of it, for having contracted, within the space
                    of a year and six months, the censorship, which formerly had lasted five years,
                    and was a power <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> which, in consequence of its
                    long continuance, often became tyrannical, he proceeded thus: <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Tell me, Appius Claudius, in what manner you would have acted, had you
                        been censor, at the time when Caius Furius and Marcus Geganius were censors?
                    </quote> Appius insisted, that <quote> the tribune's question was irrelevant to
                        his case. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For, although the Aemilian law
                        might bind those censors, during whose magistracy it was passed, —because
                        the people made that law after they had become censors; and whatever order
                        is the last passed by the people, that is held to be the law, and valid: —
                        yet neither he, nor any of those who had been created censors subsequent to
                        the passing of that law, could be bound by it. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Appius urged such frivolous arguments as
                    these, which carried no conviction whatever, the other said, <quote> Behold,
                        Romans, the offspring of that Appius, who being created decemvir for one
                        year, created himself for a second; and who, during a third, without being
                        created even by himself or by any other, held on the fasces and the
                        government though a private individual; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        nor ceased to continue in office, until the government itself, ill acquired,
                        ill administered, and ill retained, overwhelmed him in ruin. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> This is the same family, Romans, by whose
                        violence and injustice ye were compelled to banish yourselves from your
                        native city, and seize on the Sacred mount; <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> the same, against which ye pro- <pb n="606" xml:id="p.606"/> vided for
                        yourselves the protection of tribunes; the same, on account of which two
                        armies of you took post on the Aventine; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        the same, which violently opposed the laws against usury, and always the
                        agrarian laws; the same, which broke through the right of intermarriage
                        between the patricians and the commons; the same, which shut up the road to
                        curule offices against the commons: this is a name, more hostile to your
                        liberty by far, than that of the Tarquins. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        I pray you, Appius Claudius, though this is now the hundredth year since the
                        dictatorship of Mamercus Aemilius, though there have been so many men of the
                        highest characters and abilities censors, did none of these ever read the
                        twelve tables? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> none of them know, that,
                        whatever was the last order of the people, that was law? Nay, certainly they
                        all knew it; and they therefore obeyed the Aemilian law, rather than the old
                        one, under which the censors had been at first created; because it was the
                        last order; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and because, when two laws are
                        contradictory, the new always repeals the old. Do you mean to say, Appius,
                        that the people are not bound by the Aemilian law? <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Or, that the people are bound, and you alone exempted?
                        The Aemilian law bound those violent censors, Caius Furius and Marcus
                        Geganius, who showed what mischief that office might do in the state; when,
                        out of resentment for the limitation of their power, they disfranchised
                        Mamercus Aemilius, the first man of the age, either in war or peace.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It bound all the censors
                        thenceforward, during the space of a hundred years. It binds Caius Plautius
                        your colleague, created under the same auspices, with the same privileges.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Did not the people create him with
                        the fullest privileges with which any censor ever was created? Or is yours
                        an excepted case, in which this peculiarity and singularity takes place?
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Shall the person, whom you create
                        king of the sacrifices, laying hold of the style of sovereignty, say, that
                        he was created with the fullest privileges with which any king was ever
                        created at Rome? Who then, do you think, would be content with a
                        dictatorship of six months? who, with the office of interrex for five days?
                        Whom would you, with confidence, create dictator, for the purpose of driving
                        the nail, or of exhibiting games? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> How
                        foolish, how stupid, do ye think, those must appear in this man's eyes, who,
                        after performing most important services, abdicated the dictatorship within
                        the twentieth day; or who, <pb n="607" xml:id="p.607"/> being irregularly
                        created, resigned their office? Why should I bring instances from antiquity?
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Lately, within these last ten years,
                        Caius Maenius, dictator, having enforced inquiries, with more strictness
                        than consisted with the safety of some powerful men, a charge was thrown out
                        by his enemies, that he himself was infected with the very crime against
                        which his inquiries were directed; —now Maenius, I say, in order that he
                        might, in a private capacity, meet the imputation, abdicated the
                        dictatorship. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I expect not such
                        moderation in you; you will not degenerate from your family, of all others
                        the most imperious and assuming; nor resign your office a day, nor even an
                        hour, before you are forced to it. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Be it
                        so: but then let no one exceed the time limited. It is enough to add a day,
                        or a month, to the censorship. But Appius says, I will hold the censorship,
                        and hold it alone, three years and six months longer than is allowed by the
                        Aemilian law. Surely this is like kingly power. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Or will you fill up the vacancy with another colleague,
                        a proceeding not allowable, even in the case of the death of a censor?
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> You are not satisfied that, as if a
                        religious censor, you have degraded a most ancient solemnity, and the only
                        one instituted by the very deity to whom it is performed, from priests of
                        that rite who were of the highest rank to the ministry of mere servants.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> [You are not satisfied that] a
                        family, more ancient than the origin of this city, and sanctified by an
                        intercourse of hospitality with the immortal gods, has, by means of you and
                            <milestone n="20??" unit="section"/> your censorship, been utterly
                        extirpated, with all its branches, within the space of a year, unless you
                        involve the whole commonwealth in horrid guilt, which my mind feels a horror
                        even to contemplate. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> This city was taken
                        in that lustrum in which Lucius Papirius Cursor, on the death of his
                        colleague Julius, the censor, rather than resign his office, substituted
                        Marcus Cornelius Maluginensis. Yet how much more moderate was his ambition,
                        Appius, than yours! Lucius Papirius neither held the censorship alone, nor
                        beyond the time prescribed by law. But still he found no one who would
                        follow his example; all succeeding censors, in case of the death of a
                        colleague, abdicated the office. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> As for
                        you, neither the expiration of the time of your censorship, nor the
                        resignation of your colleague, nor law, nor shame restrains you. You make
                        fortitude to consist in arrogance, in boldness, in a contempt of gods and
                        men. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                        <pb n="608" xml:id="p.608"/> Appius Claudius, in consideration of the
                        dignity and respect due to that office which you have borne, I should be
                        sorry, not only to offer you personal violence, but even to address you in
                        language too severe. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> With respect to what
                        I have hitherto said, your pride and obstinacy forced me to speak. And now,
                        unless you pay obedience to the Aemilian law, I shall order you to be led to
                        prison. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> Nor, since a rule has been
                        established by our ancestors, that in the election of censors, unless two
                        shall obtain the legal number of suffrages, neither shall be returned, but
                        the election deferred, —will I suffer you, who could not singly be created
                        censor, to hold the censorship without a colleague. </quote> Having spoken
                    to this effect, he ordered the censor to be seized, and borne to prison.
                        <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> But, although six of the tribunes
                    approved of the proceeding of their colleague, three gave their support to
                    Appius, on his appealing to them, and he held the censorship alone, to the great
                    disgust of all ranks of men. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While such was the state of affairs at Rome,
                    the Etrurians had laid siege to Sutrium, and the consul Fabius, as he was
                    marching along the foot of the mountains, with a design to succour the allies,
                    and attempt the enemy's works, if it were by any means practicable, was met by
                    their army prepared for battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As the
                    wide-extended plain below showed the greatness of their force, the consul, in
                    order to remedy his deficiency in point of number, by advantage of the ground,
                    changed the direction of his route a little towards the hills, where the way was
                    rugged and covered with stones, and then formed his troops, facing the enemy.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Etrurians, thinking of nothing but
                    their numbers, on which alone they depended, commence the fight with such haste
                    and eagerness, that, in order to come the sooner to a close engagement, they
                    threw <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> away their javelins, drew their
                    swords, rushing against the enemy. On the other side, the Romans poured down on
                    them, sometimes javelins, and sometimes stones, which the place abundantly
                    supplied; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> so that whilst the blows on their
                    shields and helmets confused even those whom they did not <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> wound, (it was neither an easy matter to come to close
                    quarters, nor had they missive weapons with which to fight at a distance,) when
                    there was nothing now to protect them whilst standing and exposed to the blows,
                    some even giving way, and the whole line wavering and unsteady, <pb n="609"
                        xml:id="p.609"/> the spearmen and the first rank, renewing the shout, rush
                    on them with drawn swords. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This attack the
                    Etrurians could not withstand, but, facing about, fled precipitately towards
                    their camp; when the Roman cavalry, getting before them by galloping obliquely
                    across the plain, threw themselves in the way of their flight, on which they
                    quitted the road, and bent their course to the mountains. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> From thence, in a body, almost without arms, and
                    debilitated with wounds, they made their way into the Ciminian forest. The
                    Romans, having slain many thousands of the Etrurians, and taken thirty-eight
                    military standards, took also possession of their camp, together with a vast
                    quantity of spoil. They then began to consider of pursuing the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Ciminian forest was in those days deemed
                    as impassable and frightful as the German forests have been in latter times; not
                    even any trader having ever attempted to pass it. Hardly any, besides the
                    general himself, showed boldness enough to enter it; the others had not the
                    remembrance of the disaster at Caudium effaced from their mind. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> On this, of those who were present, Marcus Fabius, the
                    consul's brother, (some say Caeso, others Caius Claudius, born of the same
                    mother with the consul,) undertook to go and explore the country, and to bring
                    them in a short time an account of every particular. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Being educated at Caere, where he had friends, he was
                    perfectly acquainted with the Etrurian language. I have seen it affirmed, that,
                    in those times, the Roman youth were commonly instructed in the Etrurian
                    learning, as they are now in the Greek: but it is more probable, that there was
                    something very extraordinary in the person who acted so daringly a counterfeit
                    part, and mixed among the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is said,
                    that his only attendant was a slave, who had been bred up with him, and who was
                    therefore not ignorant of the same language. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    They received no further instructions at their departure, than a summary
                    description of the country through which they were to pass; to this was added
                    the names of the principal men in the several states, to prevent their being at
                    a loss in conversation, and from being discovered by making some mistake. They
                    set out in the dress of shepherds, armed with rustic weapons, bills, and two
                    short javelins each. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But neither their
                    speaking the language of the country, nor the fashion of their dress <pb n="610"
                        xml:id="p.610"/> and arms, concealed them so effectually, as the incredible
                    circumstance of a stranger's passing the Ciminian forest. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They are said to have penetrated as far as the Camertian
                    district of the Umbrians: there the Romans ventured to own who they were, and
                    being introduced to the senate, treated with them, in the name of the consul,
                    about an alliance and friendship; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and after
                    being entertained with courteous hospitality, were desired to acquaint the
                    Romans, that if they came into those countries, there should be provisions in
                    readiness for the troops sufficient for thirty days, and that they should find
                    the youth of the Camertian Umbrians prepared in arms to obey their commands.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When this information was brought to the
                    consul, he sent forward the baggage at the first watch, ordering the legions to
                    march in the rear of it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He himself staid
                    behind with the cavalry, and next day, as soon as light appeared, rode up to the
                    posts of the enemy, which had been stationed on the outside of the forest; and,
                    when he had detained them there for a sufficient length of time, he retired to
                    his camp, and marching out by the opposite gate, overtook the main body of the
                    army before night. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At the first light, on the
                    following day, he had gained the summit of Mount Ciminius, from whence having a
                    view of the opulent plains of Etruria, he let loose his soldiers upon them.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When a vast booty had been driven off,
                    some tumultuary cohorts of Etrurian peasants, hastily collected by the principal
                    inhabitants of the district, met the Romans; but in such disorderly array, that
                    these rescuers of the prey were near becoming wholly a prey themselves.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These being slain or put to flight, and
                    the country laid waste to a great extent, the Romans returned to their camp
                    victorious, and enriched with plenty of every kind. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> It happened that, in the mean time, five deputies, with two
                    plebeian tribunes, had come hither, to charge Fabius, in the name of the senate,
                    not to attempt to pass the Ciminian forest. These, rejoicing that they had
                    arrived too late to prevent the expedition, returned to Rome with the news of
                    its success. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this expedition of the consul, the war,
                    instead of being brought nearer to a conclusion, was only spread to a wider
                    extent: for all the tract adjacent to the foot of Mount Ciminius had felt his
                    devastations; and, out of the indignation conceived thereat, had roused to arms,
                    not only the states <pb n="611" xml:id="p.611"/> of Etruria, but the
                    neighbouring parts of Umbria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They came
                    therefore to Sutrium, with such a numerous army as they had never before brought
                    into the field; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and not only ventured to
                    encamp on the outside of the wood, but through their earnest desire of coming to
                    an engagement as soon as possible, marched down the plains to offer battle. The
                    troops, being marshalled, stood at first, for some time, on their own ground,
                    having left a space sufficient for the Romans to draw up, opposite to them;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but perceiving that the enemy declined
                    fighting, they advanced to the rampart; where, when they observed that even the
                    advanced guards had retired within the works, a shout at once was raised around
                    their generals, that they should order provisions for that day to be brought
                    down to them: <quote> for they were resolved to remain there under arms; and
                        either in the night, or, at all events, at the dawn of day, to attack the
                        enemy's camp. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman troops, though not less eager for
                    action, were restrained by the commands of the general. About the tenth hour,
                    the consul ordered his men a repast; and gave directions that they should be
                    ready in arms, at whatever time of the day or night he should give the signal.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then addressed a few words to them;
                    spoke in high terms of the wars of the Samnites, and disparagingly of the
                    Etrurians, who <quote>were not,</quote> he said, <quote> as an enemy to be
                        compared with other enemies, nor as a numerous force, with others in point
                        of numbers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Besides, he had an engine at
                        work, as they should find in due time; at present it was of importance to
                        keep it secret. </quote> By these hints he intimated that the enemy was
                    circumvented in order to raise the courage of his men, damped by the superiority
                    of the enemy's force; and, from their not having fortified the post where they
                    lay, the insinuation of a stratagem formed against them seemed the more
                    credible. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After refreshing themselves, they
                    consigned themselves to rest, and being roused without noise, about the fourth
                    watch, took arms. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Axes are distributed among
                    the servants following the army, to tear down the rampart and fill up the
                    trench. The line was formed within the works, and some chosen cohorts posted
                    close to the gates. Then, a little before day, which in sum- mer nights is the
                    time of the profoundest sleep, the signal being given, the rampart was levelled,
                    and the troops rushing forth, fell upon the enemy, who were every where
                    stretched <pb n="612" xml:id="p.612"/> at their length. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Some were put to death before they could stir; others half
                    asleep, in their beds; the greatest part, while they ran in confusion to arms;
                    few, in short, had time afforded them to arm themselves; and these, who followed
                    no particular leader, nor orders, were quickly routed by the Romans and pursued
                    by the Roman horse. They fled different ways; to the camp and to the woods. The
                    latter afforded the safer refuge; for the former, being situated in a plain, was
                    taken the same day. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The gold and silver was
                    ordered to be brought to the consul; the rest of the spoil was given to the
                    soldiers. On that day, sixty thousand of the enemy were slain or taken. Some
                    affirm, that this famous battle was fought on the farther side of the Ciminian
                    forest, at Perusia; and that the public had been under great dread, lest the
                    army might be enclosed in such a dangerous pass, and overpowered by a general
                    combination of the Etrurians and Umbrians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    But on whatever spot it was fought, it is certain that the Roman power
                    prevailed; and, in consequence thereof, ambassadors from Perusia, Cortona, and
                    Arretium, which were then among the principal states of Etruria, soliciting a
                    peace and alliance with the Romans, obtained a truce for thirty years. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these transactions in Etruria, the
                    other consul, Caius Marcius Rutilus, took Allifae by storm from the Samnites;
                    and many of their forts, and smaller towns, were either destroyed by his arms,
                    or surrendered without being injured. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> About
                    the same time also, the Roman fleet, having sailed to Campania, under Publius
                    Cornelius, to whom the senate had given the command on the sea-coast, put into
                    Pompeii. Immediately on landing, the soldiers of the fleet set out to ravage the
                    country about Nuceria: and after they had quickly laid waste the parts which lay
                    nearest, and whence they could have returned to the ships with safety, they were
                    allured by the temptation of plunder, as it often happens, to advance too far,
                    and thereby roused the enemy against them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    While they rambled about the country, they met no opposition, though they might
                    have been cut off to a man; but as they were returning, in a careless manner,
                    the peasants overtook them, not far from the ships, stripped them of the booty,
                    and even slew a great part of them. Those who escaped were driven in confusion
                    to the ships. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As Fabius' having marched
                    through the Ciminian forest had occasioned violent apprehensions at Rome, <pb
                        n="613" xml:id="p.613"/> so it had excited joy in proportion among the enemy
                    in Samnium: they talked of the Roman army being pent up, and surrounded; and of
                    the Caudine forks, as a model of their defeat. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Those people,</quote> they said, <quote> ever greedy after further
                        acquisitions, were now brought into inextricable difficulties, hemmed in,
                        not more effectually by the arms of their enemy, than by the disadvantage of
                        the ground. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Their joy was even mingled with a degree of
                    envy, because fortune, as they thought, had transferred the glory of finishing
                    the Roman war, from the Samnites to the Etrurians: <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> they hastened, therefore, with their whole collected force,
                    to crush the consul Caius Marcius; resolving, if he did not give them an
                    opportunity of fighting, to proceed, through the territories of the Marsians and
                    Sabines, into Etruria. The consul met them, and a battle was fought with great
                    fury on both sides, but without a decisive issue. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Although both parties suffered severely, yet the discredit
                    of defeat fell on the Romans, because several of equestrian rank, some military
                    tribunes, with one lieutenant-general, had fallen; and, what was more remarkable
                    than all, the consul himself was wounded. On account of this event, exaggerated
                    by report as is usual, the senate became greatly alarmed, so that they resolved
                    on having a dictator nominated. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> No one
                    entertained a doubt that the nomination would light on Papirius Cursor, who was
                    then universally deemed to possess the greatest abilities as a commander: but
                    they could not be certain, either that a message might be conveyed with safety
                    into Samnium, where all was in a state of hostility, or that the consul Marcius
                    was alive. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The other consul, Fabius, was at
                    enmity with Papirius, on his own account; and lest this resentment might prove
                    an obstacle to the public good, the senate voted that deputies of consular rank
                    should be sent to <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> him, who, uniting their
                    own influence to that of government, might prevail on him to drop, for the sake
                    of his country, all remembrance of private animosities. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> When the deputies, having come to Fabius, delivered to him
                    the decree of the senate, adding such arguments as were suitable to their
                    instructions, the consul, casting his eyes towards the ground, retired in
                    silence, leaving them in uncertainty what part he intended to act. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Then, in the silent time of the night, according to
                    the established custom, he nominated Lucius Papirius dictator. When the deputies
                    returned him <pb n="614" xml:id="p.614"/> thanks, for so very meritoriously
                    subduing his passion, he still persevered in obstinate silence, and dismissed
                    them without any answer, or mention of what he had done: a proof that he felt an
                    extraordinary degree of resentment, which had been suppressed within his breast.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Papirius appointed Caius Junius Bubulcus
                    master of the horse; and, as he was proceeding in an assembly of the Curiae
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">comitia
                            curiata,</hi> or assemblies of the curie, alone had the power of
                        conferring military command; no magistrate, therefore, could assume the
                        command without the previous order of their assembly. In time, this came to
                        be a mere matter of form; yet the practice always continued to be observed.
                    </note> to get an order passed respecting the command of the army, an unlucky
                    omen <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> obliged him to adjourn it; for the Curia
                    which was to vote first, happened to be the Faucian, remarkably distinguished
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> by two disasters, the taking of the city,
                    and the Caudine peace; the same Curia having voted first in those years in which
                    the said events are found. Licinius Macer supposes this Curia ominous, also, on
                    account of a third misfortune, that which was experienced at the Cremera. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next day the dictator, taking the auspices
                    anew, obtained the order, and, marching out at the head of the legions, lately
                    raised on the alarm occasioned by the army passing the Ciminian forest, came to
                    Longula; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> where having received the old troops
                    of the consul Marcius, he led on his forces to battle; nor did the enemy seem to
                    decline the combat. However, they stood drawn up for battle and under arms,
                    until night came on; neither side choosing to begin the fray. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> After this, they continued a considerable time encamped
                    near each other, without coming to action; neither diffident of their own
                    strength, nor despising the adversary. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Meanwhile matters went on actively in Etruria; for a decisive battle was fought
                    with the Umbrians, in which the enemy was routed, but lost not many men, for
                    they did not maintain the fight with the vigour with which they began it.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Besides this the Etrurians, having raised
                    an army under the sanctions of the devoting law, each man choosing another, came
                    to an engagement at the Cape of Vadimon, with more numerous forces, and, at the
                    same time, with greater spirit than they had ever shown before. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The battle was fought with such animosity that no javelins
                    were thrown by either party: swords alone were made use <pb n="615"
                        xml:id="p.615"/> of; and the fury of the combatants was still higher
                    inflamed by the long-continued contest; so that it appeared to the Romans as if
                    they were disputing, not with Etrurians, whom they had so often conquered, but
                    with a new race. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Not the semblance of giving
                    ground appeared in any part; the first lines fell; and lest the standards should
                    be exposed, without defence, the second lines were formed in their place.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At length, even the men forming the last
                    reserves were called into action; and to such an extremity of difficulty and
                    danger had they come, that the Roman cavalry dismounted, and pressed forward,
                    through heaps of arms and bodies, to the front ranks of the infantry. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> These starting up a new army, as it were, among men
                    now exhausted, disordered the battalions of the Etrurians; and the rest, weak as
                    their condition was, seconding their assault, broke at last through the enemy's
                    ranks. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Their obstinacy then began to give
                    way: some companies quitted their posts, and, as soon as they once turned their
                    backs, betook themselves to more decided flight. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> That day first broke the strength of the Etrurians, now
                    grown exuberant through a long course of prosperity; all the flower of their men
                    were cut off in the field, and in the same assault their camp was seized and
                    sacked. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Equal danger, and an issue equally glorious,
                    soon after attended the war with the Samnites; who, besides their many
                    preparations for the field, made their army to glitter with new decorations of
                    their armour. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Their troops were in two
                    divisions, one of which had their shields embossed with gold, the other with
                    silver. The shape of the shield was this; broad at the middle to cover the
                    breast and shoulders, the summit being flat, sloping off gradually so as to
                    become pointed below, that it might be wielded with ease; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> a loose coat of mail also served as a protection for the
                    breast, and the left leg was covered with a greave; their helmets were adorned
                    with plumes, to add to the appearance of their stature. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The golden-armed soldiers wore tunics of various colours;
                    the silver-armed, of white linen. To the latter the right wing was assigned; the
                    former took post on the left. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans had
                    been apprized of these splendid accoutrements, and had been taught by their
                    commanders, that <quote> a soldier ought to be rough; not decorated with gold
                        and silver, but placing his confidence in his sword. That matters of this
                        kind were in <pb n="616" xml:id="p.616"/> reality spoil rather than armour;
                        glittering before action, but soon becoming disfigured amid blood and
                        wounds. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the brightest ornament of a
                        soldier was valour; that all those trinkets would follow victory, and that
                        those rich enemies would be valuable prizes to the conquerors, however poor. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cursor, having animated his men with these
                    observations, led them on to battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He took
                    post himself on the right wing, he gave the command of the left to the master of
                    the horse. As soon as they engaged, the struggle between the two armies became
                    desperate, while it was no less so between the dictator and the master of the
                    horse, on which wing victory should first show itself. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> It happened that Junius first, with the left wing, made the
                    right of the enemy give way; this consisted of men devoted after the custom of
                    Samnites, and on that account distinguished by white garments and armour of
                    equal whiteness. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Junius, saying <quote>he
                        would sacrifice these to Pluto,</quote> pressed forward, disordered their
                    ranks, and made an evident impression on their line: which being perceived by
                    the dictator, he exclaimed, <quote> Shall the victory begin <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> on the left wing, and shall the right, the dictator's
                        own troops, only second the arms of others, and not claim the greatest share
                        of the victory? </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This spurred on the soldiers: nor did the
                    cavalry yield to the infantry in bravery, nor the ardour of lieutenants-general
                    to that of the commanders. Marcius Valerius from the right wing, and Publius
                    Decius from the left, both men of consular rank, rode off to the cavalry, posted
                    on the extremities of the line, and, exhorting them to join in putting in for a
                    share of the honour, charged the enemy on the flanks. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> When the addition of this new alarm assailed the enemies'
                    troops on both sides, and the Roman legions, having renewed the shout to
                    confound the enemy, rushed on, they began to fly. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> And now the plains were quickly filled with heaps of bodies
                    and splendid armour. At first, their camp received the dismayed Samnites; but
                    they did not long retain even the possession of that: before night it was taken,
                    plundered, and burnt. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The dictator triumphed,
                    in pursuance of a decree of the senate; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> and
                    the most splendid spectacle by far, of any in his procession, was the captured
                    arms: so magnificent were they deemed, that the shields, adorned with gold, were
                    distributed among the owners of the silver shops, to serve as embellishments to
                    the forum. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Hence, it is said, arose the
                    custom of the forum <pb n="617" xml:id="p.617"/> being decorated by the aediles,
                    when the grand processions are made, on occasion of the great games. The Romans,
                    indeed, converted these extraordinary arms to the honour of the gods: <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> but the Campanians, out of pride, and in hatred of
                    the Samnites, gave them as ornaments to their gladiators, who used to be
                    exhibited as a show at their feasts, and whom they distinguished by the name of
                    Samnites. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> During this year, the consul Fabius
                    fought with the remnants of the Etrurians at Perusia, which city also had
                    violated the truce, and gained an easy and decisive victory. <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> He would have taken the town itself; (for he marched up to
                    the walls,) had not deputies come out and capitulated. Having placed a garrison
                    at Perusia, and sent on before him to the Roman senate the embassies of Etruria,
                    who solicited friendship, the consul rode into the city in triumph, for
                    successes more important than those of the dictator. <milestone n="21"
                        unit="section"/> Besides, a great share of the honour of reducing the
                    Samnites was attributed to the lieutenants-general, Publius Decius and Marcius
                    Valerius: whom, at the next election, the people, with universal consent,
                    declared the one consul, the other praetor. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To Fabius, in consideration of his
                    extraordinary merit in the conquest of Etruria, the consulship was continued.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Decius was appointed his colleague.
                    Valerius was created Praetor a fourth time. The consuls divided the provinces
                    between them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Etruria fell to Decius, Samnium
                    to Fabius. The latter, having marched to Nuceria, rejected the application of
                    the people of Alfaterna, who then sued for peace, because they had not accepted
                    it when offered, and by force of arms compelled them to surrender. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> A battle was fought with the Samnites; the enemy were
                    overcome without much difficulty: nor would the memory of that engagement have
                    been preserved, except that in it the Marsians first appeared in arms against
                    the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Pelignians, imitating the
                    defection of the Marsians, met the same fate. The other consul, Decius, was
                    likewise very successful in his operations: through terror he compelled the
                    Tarquinians to supply his army with corn, and to sue for a truce for forty
                    years. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He took several forts from the
                    Volsinians by assault, some of which he demolished, that they might not serve as
                    receptacles to the enemy, and by extending his operations through every quarter,
                    diffused such a dread of his arms, that the whole <pb n="618" xml:id="p.618"/>
                    Etrurian nation sued to the consul for an alliance: this they did not obtain;
                    but a truce for a year was granted them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    pay of the Roman army for that year was furnished by the enemy; and two tunics
                    for each soldier were exacted from them: this was the purchase of the truce.'
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The tranquillity now established in
                    Etruria was interrupted by a sudden insurrection of the Umbrians, a nation which
                    had suffered no injury from the war, except what inconvenience the country had
                    felt in the passing of the army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These, by
                    calling into the field all their own young men, and forcing a great part of the
                    Etrurians to resume their arms, made up such a numerous force, that speaking of
                    themselves with ostentatious vanity, and of the Romans with contempt, they
                    boasted that they would leave Decius behind in Etruria, and march away to
                    besiege Rome; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> which design of theirs being
                    reported to the consul Decius, he removed by long marches from Etruria towards
                    their city, and sat down in the district of Pupinia, in readiness to act
                    according to the intelligence received of the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was the insurrection of the Umbrians slighted at Rome:
                    their very threats excited tears among the people, who had experienced, in the
                    calamities suffered from the Gauls, how insecure a city they inhabited.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Deputies were therefore despatched to the
                    consul Fabius with directions, that, if he had any respite from the war of the
                    Samnites, he should with all haste lead his army into Umbria. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The consul obeyed the order, and by forced marches
                    proceeded to Mevania, where the forces of the Umbrians then lay. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> The unexpected arrival of the consul, whom they had
                    believed to be sufficiently employed in Samnium, far distant from their country,
                    so thoroughly affrighted the Umbrians, that several advised retiring to their
                    fortified towns; others, the discontinuing the war. However, one district,
                    called by themselves Materina, prevailed on the rest not only to retain their
                    arms, but to come to an immediate engagement. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    They fell upon Fabius while he was fortifying his camp. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> When the consul saw them rushing impetuously towards his
                    rampart, he called off his men from the work, and drew them up in the best
                    manner which the nature of the place and the time allowed; encouraging them by
                    displaying, in honourable and just terms, the glory which they had acquired, as
                    well in Etruria as in Samnium, he bade them finish this insignificant appendage
                        <pb n="619" xml:id="p.619"/> to the Etrurian war, and take vengeance for the
                    impious expressions in which these people had threatened to attack the city of
                    Rome. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Such was the alacrity of the soldiers
                    on hearing this, that, raising the shout spontaneously, they interrupted the
                    general's discourse, and, without waiting for orders, advanced, with the sound
                    of all the trumpets and cornets, in full speed against the enemy. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> They made their attack not as on men, or at least
                    men in arms, but, what must appear wonderful in the relation, began by snatching
                    the standards out of the hands which held them; and then, the standard-bearers
                    themselves were dragged to the consul, and the armed soldiers transferred from
                    the one line to the other; and wherever resistance was any where made, the
                    business was performed, not so much with swords, as with their shields, with the
                    bosses of which, and thrusts of their elbows, they bore down the foe. <milestone
                        n="19" unit="section"/> The prisoners were more numerous than the slain, and
                    through the whole line the Umbrians called on each other, with one voice, to lay
                    down their arms. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Thus a surrender was made in
                    the midst of action, by the first promoters of the war; and on the next and
                    following days, the other states of the Umbrians also surrendered. The
                    Ocriculans were admitted to a treaty of friendship on giving security. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius, successful in a war allotted to
                    another, led back his army into his own province. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And as, in the preceding year, the people had, in
                    consideration of his services so successfully performed, re-elected him to the
                    consulship, so now the senate, from the same motive, notwithstanding a warm
                    opposition made by Appius, prolonged his command for the year following, in
                    which Appius Claudius and Lucius Volumnius were consuls. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In some annals I find, that Appius, still holding the
                    office of censor, declared himself a candidate for the consulship, and that his
                    election was stopped by a protest of Lucius Furius, plebeian tribune, until he
                    resigned the censorship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After his election to
                    the consulship, the new war with the Sallentine enemies being decreed to his
                    colleague, he remained at Rome, with design to increase his interest by city
                    intrigues, since the means of procuring honour in war were placed in the hands
                    of others. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Volumnius had no reason to be
                    dissatisfied with his province: he fought many battles with good success, and
                    took several cities by assault. He was <pb n="620" xml:id="p.620"/> liberal in
                    his donations of the spoil; and this munificence, engaging in itself, he
                    enhanced by his courteous demeanour, by which conduct he inspired his soldiers
                    with ardour to meet both toil and danger. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Quintus Fabius, proconsul, fought a pitched battle with the armies of the
                    Samnites, near the city of Allifae. The victory was complete. The enemy were
                    driven from the field, and pursued to their camp; nor would they have kept
                    possession of that, had not the day been almost spent. It was invested, however,
                    before night, and guarded until day, lest any should slip away. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Next morning, while it was scarcely clear day, they
                    proposed to capitulate, and it was agreed, that such as were natives of Samnium
                    should be dismissed with single garments. All these were sent under the yoke.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> No precaution was taken in favour of the
                    allies of the Samnites: they were sold by auction, to the number of seven
                    thousand. Those who declared themselves subjects of the Hernicians, were kept by
                    themselves under a guard. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> All these Fabius
                    sent to Rome to the senate; and, after being examined, whether it was in
                    consequence of a public order, or as volunteers, that they had carried arms on
                    the side of the Samnites against the Romans, they were distributed among the
                    states of the Latins to be held in custody; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    and it was ordered, that the new consuls, Publius Cornelius Arvina and Quintus
                    Marcius Tremulus, who by this time had been elected, should lay that affair
                    entire before the senate: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> this gave such
                    offence to the Hernicians, that, at a meeting of all the states, assembled by
                    the Anagnians, in the circus called the Maritime, the whole nation of the
                    Hernicians, excepting the Alatrians, Ferentines, and Verulans, declared war
                    against the Roman people. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Samnium also, in consequence of the
                    departure of Fabius, new commotions arose. Calatia and Sora, and the Roman
                    garrisons stationed there, were taken, and extreme cruelty was exercised towards
                    the captive soldiers: Publius Cornelius was therefore sent thither with an army.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The command against the new enemy (for by
                    this time an order had passed for declaring war against the Anagnians, and the
                    rest of the Hernicians) was decreed to Marcius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> These, in the beginning, secured all the passes between the camps of the
                    consuls, in such a manner, that no messenger, however expert, could make his way
                    from one to the other; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and each <pb n="621"
                        xml:id="p.621"/> consul spent several days in absolute uncertainty regarding
                    every matter and in anxious suspense concerning the state of the other.
                    Apprehensions for their safety spread even to Rome; so that all the younger
                    citizens were compelled to enlist, and two regular armies were raised, to answer
                    sudden emergencies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The conduct of the
                    Hernicians during the progress of the war afterwards, showed nothing suitable to
                    the present alarm, or to the ancient renown of that nation. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Without ever venturing any effort worth mentioning, being
                    stripped of three different camps within a few days, they stipulated for a truce
                    of thirty days, during which they might send to Rome, to the senate, on the
                    terms of furnishing two months' pay, and corn, and a tunic to every soldier.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were referred back to Marcius by the
                    senate, whom by a decree they empowered to determine regarding the Hernicians,
                    and he accepted their submission. Meanwhile, in Samnium, the other consul,
                    though superior in strength, was very much embarrassed by the nature of his
                    situation; the enemy had blocked up all the roads, and seized on the passable
                    defiles, so that no provisions could be conveyed; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> nor could the consul, though he daily drew out his troops
                    and offered battle, allure them to an engagement. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> It was evident, that neither could the Samnites support an
                    immediate contest, nor the Romans a delay of action. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The approach of Marcius, who, after he had subdued the
                    Hernicians, hastened to the succour of his colleague, put it out of the enemy's
                    power any longer to avoid fighting: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for they,
                    who had not deemed themselves a match in the field, even for one of the armies,
                    could not surely suppose that if they should allow the two consular armies to
                    unite, they could have any hope remaining: they made an attack therefore on
                    Marcius, as he was approaching in the irregular order of march. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> The baggage was hastily thrown together in the
                    centre, and the line formed as well as the time permitted. First the shout which
                    reached the standing camp of Cornelius, then the dust observed at a distance,
                    excited a bustle in the camp of the other consul. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Ordering his men instantly to take arms, and leading them
                    out to the field with the utmost haste, he charged the flank of the enemy's
                    line, which had enough to do in the other dispute, at the same time <milestone
                        n="14??" unit="section"/> exclaiming, that <quote> it would be the height of
                        infamy if they suffered Marcius's army to monopolize the honour of both
                        victories, and did not assert <pb n="622" xml:id="p.622"/> their claim to
                        the glory of their own war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He bore down all before him, and pushed
                    forward, through the midst of the enemy's line, to their camp, which, being left
                    without a guard, he took and set on fire; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    which when the soldiers of Marcius saw in flames, and the enemy observed it on
                    looking about, a general flight immediately took place among the Samnites. But
                    they could not effect an escape in any direction; in every quarter they met
                    death. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> After a slaughter of thirty thousand
                    men, the consuls had now given the signal for retreat; and were collecting, into
                    one body, their several forces, who were employed in mutual congratulations,
                    when some new cohorts of the enemy, which had been levied for a reinforcement,
                    being seen at a distance, occasioned a renewal of the carnage. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> On these the conquerors rushed, without any order of the
                    consuls, or signal received, crying out, that they would make these Samnites pay
                    dearly for their introduction to service. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls indulged the ardour of the legions, well knowing that the raw troops of
                    the enemy, mixed with veterans dispirited by defeat, would be incapable even of
                    attempting a contest. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Nor were they wrong in
                    their judgment: all the forces of the Samnites, old and new, fled to the nearest
                    mountains. These the Roman army also ascended, so that no situation afforded
                    safety to the vanquished; they were beaten off, even from the summits which they
                    had seized. And now they all, with one voice, supplicated for a suspension of
                    arms. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> On which, being ordered to furnish corn
                    for three months, pay for a year, and a tunic to each of the soldiers, they sent
                    deputies to the senate to sue for peace. Cornelius was left in Samnium.
                        <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Marcius returned into the city, in
                    triumph over the Hernicians; and a decree was passed for erecting to him, in the
                    forum, an equestrian statue, which was placed before the temple of Castor.
                        <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> To three states of the Hernicians, (the
                    Alatrians, Verulans, and Ferentines,) their own laws were restored, because they
                    preferred these to the being made citizens of Rome; and they were permitted to
                    intermarry with each other, a privilege which they alone of the Hernicians, for
                    a long time after, enjoyed. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> To the Anagnians,
                    and the others, who had made war on the Romans, was granted the freedom of the
                    state, without the right of voting; public assemblies, and intermarriages, were
                    not allowed them, and their magistrates were prohibited from acting except in
                    the ministration of public worship. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="623" xml:id="p.623"/> During this year, Caius Junius Bubulcus, censor,
                    contracted for the building of a temple to Health, which he had vowed during his
                    consulate in the war with the Samnites. By the same person, and his colleague,
                    Marcus Valerius Maximus, roads were made through the fields at the public
                    expense. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> During the same year the treaty with
                    the Carthaginians was renewed a third time, and ample presents made to their
                    ambassadors who came on that business. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year had a dictator in office, Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio, with Publius Decius Mus, master of the horse. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> By these the election of consuls was held, being the
                    purpose for which they had been created, because neither of the consuls could be
                    absent from the armies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls elected
                    were Lucius Postumius and Titus Minucius; whom Piso places next after Quintus
                    Fabius and Publius Decius, omitting the two years in which I have set down
                    Claudius with Volumnius, and Cornelius with Marcius, as consuls. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Whether this happened through a lapse of memory in
                    digesting his annals, or whether he purposely passed over those two consulates
                    as deeming the accounts of them false, cannot be ascertained. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> During this year the Samnites made incursions into the
                    district of Stellae in the Campanian territory. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Both the consuls were therefore sent into Samnium, and proceeded to different
                    regions, Postumius to Tifernum, Minucius to Bovianum. The first engagement
                    happened at Tifernum, under the command of Postumius. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Some say, that the Samnites were completely defeated, and
                    twenty thousand of them made prisoners. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Others, that the army separated without victory on either side; and that
                    Postumius, counterfeiting fear, withdrew his forces privately by night, and
                    marched away to the mountains; whither the enemy also followed, and took
                    possession of a strong-hold two miles distant. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, having created a belief that he had come thither for the sake of a
                    safe post, and a fruitful spot, (and such it really was,) secured his camp with
                    strong works. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Furnishing it with magazines of
                    every thing useful, he left a strong guard to defend it; and at the third watch,
                    led away the legions lightly accoutred, by the shortest road which he could
                    take, to join his colleague, who lay opposite to his foe. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> There, by advice of Postumius, Minucius came to an
                    engagement with the enemy; and when the fight had continued doubtful through a
                    great part of the day, Postumius, <pb n="624" xml:id="p.624"/> with his fresh
                    legions, made an unexpected attack on the enemy's line, spent by this time with
                    fatigue: <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> thus, weariness and wounds having
                    rendered them incapable even of flying, they were cut off to a man, and
                    twenty-one standards taken. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Romans then
                    proceeded to Postumius's station, where the two victorious armies falling upon
                    the enemy, already dismayed by the news of what had passed, routed and dispersed
                    them: twenty-six military standards were taken here, and the Samnite general,
                    Statius Gellius, with a great number of other prisoners, and both the camps were
                    taken. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Next day Bovianum was besieged, and
                    soon after taken. Both the consuls were honoured with a triumph, with high
                    applause of their excellent conduct. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Some
                    writers say, that the consul Minucius was brought back to the camp grievously
                    wounded, and that he died there; that Marcus Fulvius was substituted consul in
                    his place, and that it was he who, being sent to command Minucius's army, took
                    Bovianum. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> During the same year, Sora,
                    Arpinum, and Censennia were recovered from the Samnites. The great statue of
                    Hercules was erected in the Capitol, and dedicated. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the succeeding consulate of Publius
                    Sulpicius Saverrio and Publius Sempronius Sophus, the Samnites, desirous either
                    of a termination or a suspension of hostilities, sent ambassadors to Rome to
                    treat of peace; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> to whose submissive
                    solicitations this answer was returned, that, <quote> had not the Samnites
                        frequently solicited peace, at times when they were actually preparing for
                        war, their present application might, perhaps, in the course of negotiating,
                        have produced the desired effect. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But now,
                        since words had hitherto proved vain, people's conduct must be guided by
                        facts: that Publius Sempronius the consul would shortly be in Samnium with
                        an army: that he could not be deceived in judging whether their dispositions
                        inclined to peace or war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He would bring
                        the senate certain information respecting every particular, and their
                        ambassadors might follow the consul on his return from Samnium. </quote>
                    When the Roman army accordingly marched through all parts of Samnium, which was
                    in a state of peace, provisions being liberally supplied, a renewal of the old
                    treaty was, this year, granted to the Samnites. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The Roman arms were then turned against the Aequans, their old enemies, but
                    who had, for many years past, remained quiet, under the guise of a treacherous
                    peace; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="625" xml:id="p.625"/> because, while the Hernicians were in a state of
                    prosperity, these had, in conjunction with them, frequently sent aid to the
                    Samnites; and after the Hernicians were subdued, almost the whole nation,
                    without dissembling that they acted by public authority, had revolted to the
                    enemy; and when, after the conclusion of the treaty with the Samnites at Rome,
                    ambassadors were sent to demand satisfaction, they said, that <quote> this was
                        only a trial made of them, on the expectation that they would through fear
                        suffer themselves to be made Roman citizens. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> But how much that condition was to be wished for they had been taught by
                        the Hernicians; who, when they had the option, preferred their own laws to
                        the freedom of the Roman state. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To people
                        who wished for liberty to choose what they judged preferable, the necessity
                        of becoming Roman citizens would have the nature of a punishment. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In resentment of these declarations, uttered
                    publicly in their assemblies, the Roman people ordered war to be made on the
                    Aequans; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and, in prosecution of this new
                    undertaking, both the consuls marched from the city, and sat down at the
                    distance of four miles from the camp of the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The troops of the Aequans, like tumultuary recruits, in
                    consequence of their having passed such a number of years without waging war on
                    their own account, were all in disorder and confusion, without established
                    officers and without command. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some advised to
                    give battle, others to defend the camp; the greater part were influenced by
                    concern for the devastation of their lands, likely to take place, and the
                    consequent destruction of their cities, left with weak garrisons. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Among a variety of propositions, one, however, was
                    heard which, abandoning all concern for the public interest, tended to transfer
                    every man's attention to the care of his private concerns. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> It recommended that, at the first watch, they should depart
                    from the camp by different roads, so as to carry all their effects into the
                    cities, and to secure them by the strength of the fortifications; this they all
                    approved with universal assent. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When the
                    enemy were now dispersed through the country, the Romans, at the first dawn,
                    marched out to the field, and drew up in order of battle; but no one coming to
                    oppose them, they advanced in a brisk pace to the enemy's camp. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> But when they perceived neither guards before the
                    gates, nor soldiers on the ramparts, nor the usual bustle of a camp, —surprised
                    at the extra- <pb n="626" xml:id="p.626"/> ordinary silence, they halted in
                    apprehension of some stratagem. At length, passing over the rampart, and finding
                    the whole deserted, they proceeded to search out the tracks of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But these, as they scattered themselves
                    to every quarter, occasioned perplexity at first. Afterwards discovering their
                    design by means of scouts, they attacked their cities, one after another, and
                    within the space of fifty days took, entirely by force, forty-one towns, most of
                    which were razed and burnt, and the race of the Aequans almost extirpated.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> A triumph was granted over the Aequans.
                    The Marrucinians, Marsians, Pelignians, and Ferentans, warned by the example of
                    their disasters, sent deputies to Rome to solicit peace and friendship; and
                    these states, on their submissive applications, were admitted into alliance. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year, Cneius Flavius, son of
                    Cneius, grandson of a freed man, a notary, in low circumstances originally, but
                    artful and eloquent, was appointed curule aedile. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> I find in some annals, that, being in attendance on the
                    aediles, and seeing that he was voted aedile by the prerogative tribe, but that
                    his name would not be received, because he acted as a notary, he threw down his
                    tablet, and took an oath, that he would not, for the future, follow that
                    business. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But Licinius Macer contends, that he
                    had dropped the employment of notary a considerable time before, having already
                    been a tribune, and twice a triumvir, once for regulating the nightly watch, and
                    another time for conducting a colony. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> However,
                    of this there is no dispute, that against the nobles, who threw contempt on the
                    meanness of his condition, he contended with much firmness. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He made public the rules of proceeding in judicial causes,
                    hitherto shut up in the closets of the pontiffs; and hung up to public view,
                    round the forum, the calendar on white tablets, that all might know when
                    business could be transacted in the courts. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To
                    the great displeasure of the nobles, he performed the dedication of the temple
                    of Concord, in the area of Vulcan's temple; and the chief pontiff, Cornelius
                    Barbatus, was compelled by the united instances of the people, to dictate to him
                    the form of words, although he affirmed, that, consistently with the practice of
                    antiquity, no other than a consul, or commander-in-chief, could dedicate a
                    temple. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This occasioned a law to be proposed
                    to the people, by direction of the senate, that no person should <pb n="627"
                        xml:id="p.627"/> dedicate a temple, or an altar, without an order from the
                    senate, or from a majority of the plebeian tribunes. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The incident which I am about to mention would be trivial
                    in itself, were it not an instance of the freedom assumed by plebeians in
                    opposition to the pride of the nobles. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                    Flavius had come to make a visit to his colleague, who was sick, and when, by an
                    arrangement between some young nobles who were sitting there, they did not rise
                    on his entrance, he ordered his curule chair to be brought thither, and from his
                    honourable seat of office enjoyed the sight of his enemies tortured with envy.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> However, a low faction, which had
                    gathered strength during the censorship of Appius Claudius, had made Flavius an
                    aedile; for he was the first who degraded the senate, by electing into it the
                    immediate descendants of freed men; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and when
                    no one allowed that election as valid, and when he had not acquired in the
                    senate-house that influence in the city which he had been aiming at, by
                    distributing men of the meanest order among all the several <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> tribes, he thus corrupted the assemblies both of the forum
                    and of the field of Mars; and so much indignation did the election of Flavius
                    excite, that most of the nobles laid aside their gold rings and bracelets in
                    consequence of it. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> From that time the state
                    was split into two parties. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The uncorrupted
                    part of the people, who favoured and supported the good, held one side; the
                    faction of the rabble, the other; until Quintus Fabius and Publius Decius were
                    made censors; and Fabius, both for the sake of concord, and at the same time to
                    prevent the elections remaining in the hands of the lowest of the people, purged
                    the rest of the tribes of all the rabble of the forum, and threw it into four,
                    and called them city tribes. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> And this
                    procedure, we are told, gave such universal satisfaction, that, by this
                    regulation in the orders of the state, he obtained the surname of Maximus, which
                    he had not obtained by his many victories. The annual review of the knights, on
                    the ides of July, is also said to have been instituted by him. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
