<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab urbe condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 8-10 - 9</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books VIII-X With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1926: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="book">
                <head>Book IX</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/> IN the following year came the Caudine Peace,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 321</note> the
                    notorious sequel of a disaster to the Roman arms. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>Titus</name> Veturius Calvinus and Spurius Postumius were consuls. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the second time, having held the
                        office together thirteen years before. </note>
                    <name>The</name> Samnites had that year for their general Gaius Pontius, whose
                    father Herennius far excelled them all in wisdom, while the son was their
                    foremost warrior and captain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> the envoys who had been dispatched to make restitution returned
                    without having achieved a peace, Pontius said: <quote>
                        <reg>you</reg> must not think that this embassy has been of no avail:
                        whatever divine resentment we incurred by breaking the treaty <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified">The reference is to events described
                            at viii. xxxvii. 3.</note> has been appeased. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>well</reg> do I know that whatever gods desired that we might be
                        compelled to restore the spoils which had been demanded again of us in
                        accordance with the treaty did not desire that our expiation of the treaty
                        should be so scornfully rejected by the Romans. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>for</reg> what more could have been done to mollify the gods and to
                        placate men than we have done? <name>The</name> goods of the enemy which we
                        had taken as booty, and regarded as our own by the laws of war, we restored
                        to them; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the authors of the war, whom we
                        could not surrender living, we surrendered dead; their possessions —that no
                        guilt might remain with us from touching them —we carried to Rome.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>what</reg> more do I owe to you, Romans, or to the treaty, or to the
                        gods, its witnesses? <reg>whom</reg> can I proffer as umpire betwixt <pb
                            n="p.165"/> your anger and my punishment? <reg>i</reg> refuse no nation,
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 321</note>
                        no private citizen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>but</reg> if, in dealing with the mighty, the weak are left no human
                        rights, yet will I seek protection of the gods, who visit retribution on
                        intolerable pride, and will beseech them that they tum their anger against
                        those who are not content with the restitution of their own possessions, nor
                        the heaping up in addition of <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> other
                        men's; whose rage is not sated with the death of the guilty, nor with the
                        surrender of their lifeless bodies, nor with the master's goods going with
                        that surrender —unless we yield them our blood to drink and our flesh to
                        rend. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        <name>Samnites</name> , that war is just which is necessary, and righteous
                        are their arms to whom, save only in arms, no hope is left. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>since</reg> , therefore, it is of the utmost moment in the affairs of
                        men whether what they undertake be pleasing in the sight of Heaven or
                        whether it be offensive, be well assured that you waged your former war
                        rather against gods than men, but that you will wage this war now
                        threatening with the gods themselves for your leaders. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>having</reg> pronounced these words, as prophetic as they were encouraging,
                    he led his army out and encamped with all possible secrecy in the vicinity of
                    Caudium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>thence</reg> he dispatched in the direction of Calatia, where he heard that
                    the Roman consuls were already in camp, ten soldiers in the guise of shepherds,
                    with orders to graze their flocks —dispersed one here another there —at no great
                    distance from the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> encountering pillagers, they were all to tell one story; namely,
                    that the Samnite levies were in Apulia, where they were laying siege with all
                    their forces to Luceria, and were on the <pb n="p.167"/> point of taking it by
                    assault. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> rumour, which <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 321</note> had designedly been given out before, had
                    already come to the ears of the Romans, but the prisoners strengthened their
                    belief in it, especially since they all gave the same account. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans did not hesitate about helping the Lucerini, their good
                    and faithful allies, and preventing Apulia at the same time from a general
                    defection in the face of instant peril: the only subject of deliberation was by
                    what route they should march. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> were two roads to Luceria. <reg>one</reg> skirted the Adriatic,
                    and though open and unobstructed, was long almost in proportion to its safety.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> other led through the Caudine Forks, and was shorter, but this
                    is the nature of the place: two deep defiles, narrow and wooded, are connected
                    by an unbroken range of mountains on either hand; shut in between them lies a
                    rather extensive plain, grassy and well —watered, with the road running through
                    the middle of it; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but before you come to it,
                    you must enter the first defile, and afterwards either retrace the steps by
                    which you made your way into the place, or else —should you go forward —pass out
                    by another ravine, which is even narrower and more difficult. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>into</reg> this plain the Romans debouched from the rocky gorge of one of
                    the two passes; and advancing forthwith to the other pass, found it blocked with
                    a barrier of felled trees and huge boulders. <name>The</name> enemy's stratagem
                    now stood revealed, and indeed a body of troops was descried at the head of the
                    defile. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans thereupon hastened back to regain the road by which they
                    had come, but found that this was likewise closed with its own <pb n="p.169"/>
                    barricade and armed men. <reg>at</reg> this they came to a <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 321</note> halt, without any command,
                    and a stupor came over the minds of all, and a strange kind of numbness over
                    their bodies; and looking at one another —for <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    every man supposed his neighbour more capable of thinking and planning than
                    himself —they stood for a long time motionless and silent. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>afterwards</reg> , when they saw the tents of the consuls going up and some
                    of the men getting out entrenching tools, although they perceived that in their
                    desperate plight, deprived of every hope, it would be ridiculous for them to
                    entrench <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> themselves, nevertheless, that
                    they might not add a fault to their misfortunes, they fell to digging —each for
                    himself with no encouragement or command from anyone —and fortified a camp close
                    to the water; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> meanwhile not only did their
                    enemies insolently scoff at them, but they jested themselves, with pathetic
                    candour, at the futility of their works and the pains they took. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> dejected consuls did not even call a council, for the situation
                    admitted neither of discussion nor of help, but the lieutenants and tribunes
                    assembled of their own accord, and the soldiers, turning to the headquarters
                    tent, called on their generals for help, which the immortal gods could scarce
                    have given them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>night</reg> came, and found them not so much consulting as lamenting, while
                    each murmured as his nature prompted him. <quote>
                        <reg>let</reg> us force the barriers of the road, </quote> said one, <quote>
                        let us scale the mountains, penetrate the forests, go wherever we can carry
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> arms, if only we may come at the
                        enemy, whom we have now been conquering for close upon thirty years <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified">The speaker disregards the interval
                            of peace (341-328).</note> ; any field will be smooth and level to a <pb
                            n="p.171"/> Roman who fights against a treacherous Samnite! </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 321</note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Another would ask: <quote>
                        <reg>where</reg> or by what way can we go? <reg>do</reg> we think to remove
                        the mountains from their seat? <reg>so</reg> long as these ridges tower over
                        you, how shall you come at the enemy? <reg>armed</reg> and unarmed, the
                        brave and the cowardly, we are all alike captured and beaten men.
                            <name>The</name> foe will not even draw his sword on us, that we may die
                        with honour; he will end the war by sitting still. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>with</reg> such —like exchange of talk the night wore on, neither was there
                    any thought of food or sleep. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>even</reg> the Samnites were at a loss what course to follow in such happy
                    circumstances; and accordingly they agreed unanimously to dispatch a letter to
                    Herennius Pontius, the father of their general, asking his advice. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> man, bowed down with years, had already withdrawn not only from
                    military but even from civic duties; yet, despite his bodily infirmity, his mind
                    and judgment retained their vigour. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> he learned that the Roman armies had been hemmed in between two
                    defiles at the Caudine Forks, and was asked by his son's messenger for his
                    opinion, he advised that they should all be dismissed unscathed, at the earliest
                    possible moment. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> policy having been rejected, and the messenger returning a
                    second time to seek his counsel, he recommended that all, to the last man, be
                    slain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>having</reg> received these answers, as inconsistent as the riddling
                    responses of an oracle, the younger Pontius was among the first to conclude that
                    his father's mind had now given way along with his failing body, but yielded to
                    the general desire and sent for him to advise with them in person. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> old man made no objection; he was <pb n="p.173"/> brought to
                    the camp in a waggon —so the story <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 321</note> runs —and being invited to join the council of
                    war, spoke to such purpose as merely, without changing his opinion, to add
                    thereto his reasons: If, he said, they adopted his first proposal —which
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> he held to be the best —they would
                    establish lasting peace and friendship with a very powerful people by conferring
                    an enormous benefit upon them; by adopting the other plan they would postpone
                    the war for many generations, in which time the Roman State, having lost two
                    armies, would not easily regain its strength; there was no third plan.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> his son and the other leading men pressed him to say what would
                    happen if they took a middle course, and while letting them go unhurt imposed
                    terms upon them by the rights of war, as upon the vanquished, <quote>
                        <reg>that</reg> , </quote> he answered, <quote> is in sooth a policy that
                        neither wins men friends nor rids them of their enemies. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>spare</reg> , if you will, those whom you have stung to anger with
                        humiliation; the Roman race is one that knows not how to be still under
                        defeat. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>whatever</reg> shame you brand them with in their present necessity,
                        the wound will ever rankle in their bosoms, nor will it suffer them to rest
                        until they have exacted many times as heavy a penalty of you. </quote>
                    <reg>neither</reg> proposal was accepted, and Herennius was carried home from
                    the camp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> the other camp the Romans, finding themselves now, after many
                    fruitless efforts to break out, in want of everything, were reduced to the
                    necessity of sending envoys; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> who were first to
                    treat for an equal peace, and, if peace could not be had, to provoke the enemy
                    to fight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>to</reg> them Pontius made answer, that the war was <pb n="p.175"/> already
                    fought and won; and since they knew <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 321</note> not how to admit their plight, even when
                    beaten and made prisoners, he intended to send them unarmed and with a single
                    garment each under the yoke; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> in all else the
                    peace should be one of equal terms to the vanquished and the victors; for if the
                    Romans would evacuate the Samnite territory and withdraw their colonies, Romans
                    and Samnites should thenceforward live by their own laws in an equal alliance.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> these terms he was ready to conclude a treaty with the consuls; if
                    they were any of them unacceptable, he forbade the envoys to return to him.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> the upshot of this embassy was made known to the Romans, they
                    all straightway fell to groaning, and so overcome were they with sorrow that it
                    seemed as though they <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> could not possibly
                    take it more to heart if they should be told that they must all die in that
                    place. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>finally</reg> , after a long silence —for the consuls were incapable of
                    uttering a word, either for a treaty so disgraceful or against a treaty so
                    necessary — <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Lucius Lentulus, at that time
                    first of the lieutenants both for his valour and his dignities, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He had been consul <date when="-0328"
                            >328 B.C.</date> (viii. xxii. 8). His descendants assumed the surname of
                        Caudini and a P. Cornelius Caudinus is mentioned at XXVI. xlviii. 9 and a L.
                        Cornelius Caudinus at xxvii. xxi. 9. </note> spoke as follows: <quote>
                        <reg>consuls</reg> , I have often heard my father say that on the Capitol he
                        was the only man who would not have the senate ransom the City from the
                        Gauls with gold, since their enemies, who were most indolent besiegers, had
                        not shut them in with trench and rampart, and they were able to make a
                        sortie, if not without great danger, yet without certain destruction.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>but</reg> if, in like manner as they had it in their power to run down
                        from the Capitol, sword in hand, against their enemy, even as the besieged
                        have often sallied out against the besiegers, <pb n="p.177"/> so we were
                        able, whether on favourable ground or <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 321</note> no, only to come to
                        grips with our antagonist, I should not lack my father's spirit in advising
                        you. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>i</reg> do indeed confess that it is glorious to die for one's country,
                        and I am ready to devote myself for the Roman People and the legions, or to
                        throw myself into the midst of the enemy; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        but it is here I see my country, here all the legions Rome possesses, and
                        unless they would rush on death to please themselves, what have they to save
                        by dying? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> 'The roof —trees of the City,'
                        someone may say, 'and its walls, and the multitude by whom it is inhabited.'
                            <reg>nay</reg> , not so! <reg>for</reg> all these are betrayed, not
                        saved, if this army is wiped out! <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>for</reg> who shall preserve them? <name>The</name> unwarlike, unarmed
                        rabble? <reg>ay</reg> , even as it preserved them from the onset of the
                        Gauls! <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>or</reg> will they pray perhaps that an army may be sent from Veii, and
                        a Camillus to command it? <reg>here</reg> are all our hopes and our
                        resources, which if we save we save our country; whereas if we give these up
                        to die, we abandon our country and betray it. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> ' But surrender is shameful and humiliating.'
                            <reg>true</reg> , but our country is so dear that we would save it by
                        enduring shame, as we would, if need were, by our death. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>let</reg> us submit then to that indignity, however great, and obey
                        necessity, to which even gods are not superior. <reg>go</reg> , consuls, at
                        the cost of arms redeem the City which your sires paid gold to redeem.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls then went to confer with Pontius. <name>The</name>
                    victor proposed a treaty, but they declared that a treaty could not be made
                    without the authorization of the people, nor without fetials and the rest of the
                    customary ceremonial. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>consequently</reg> the Caudine <pb n="p.179"/> Peace was not entered into
                    by means of a treaty, as <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 321</note> people in general believe and as Claudius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Q. Claudius Quadrigarius (Introduction,
                        Vol. I. p. xxx).</note> actually states, but by a guarantee. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>
                            <name>The</name>
                            <hi rend="italics">sponsio</hi> was a verbal engagement or pledge made
                            by those in authority (the generals and, if required, their officers) in
                            answer to a formal question from the other party. </quote>
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> —Anderson. </note>
                    <reg>for</reg> what need would there have been for guarantors or for hostages in
                    a treaty, where the agreement is concluded with a prayer that the nation
                    responsible for any departure from the recited terms may be smitten by Jupiter
                    even as the swine is smitten by the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> fetials?
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See I. xxiv. 8.</note>
                    <name>The</name> guarantors were the consuls, the lieutenants, the quaestors,
                    and the tribunes of the soldiers, and the names of all who gave the guarantee
                    are extant, whereas, if the agreement had been entered into as in making a
                    treaty, none would be preserved except those of the two <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> fetials; and because of the inevitable postponement of the
                    treaty, hostages were also required to the number of six hundred knights, whose
                    lives were to be forfeit if the Romans should fail to keep the <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> terms. <reg>a</reg> time was then set for the delivery of
                    the hostages and the dismissal of the army without their arms. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>fresh</reg> lamentations broke out in the camp when the consuls returned;
                    and the men could hardly keep from laying violent hands on those through whose
                    rashness they had been led into that place, and through whose cowardice they
                    were now to depart more shamefully than they had <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> come. <reg>they</reg> bethought them how they had been unprovided either with
                    guides or with patrols, but had been driven blindly, like wild beasts, into a
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> trap. <reg>they</reg> looked at one
                    another; they gazed on the arms that they must presently surrender, on the right
                    hands that would be helpless and the bodies that would be at the mercy of the
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> foe. <reg>they</reg> pictured to their
                    mind's eye the hostile yoke, the victor's taunts, <pb n="p.181"/> and fleering
                    countenance; and how they must pass <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 321</note> unarmed between the ranks of their armed
                    enemies, and then wend their wretched way, a pitiful band, through the cities of
                    their allies; and finally the return to their own city and their parents,
                    whither they themselves and their ancestors had often returned in <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> triumph. <reg>they</reg> alone had been defeated
                    without a wound, without a weapon, without a battle; to them it had not been
                    granted to draw the sword, nor to join in combat with the enemy; on them in vain
                    had arms, in vain had strength, in vain had bravery been <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> bestowed. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>as</reg> they uttered these complaints, the fateful hour of their
                    humiliation came, an hour destined to transcend all anticipations in the
                    bitterness of its <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> reality. <reg>to</reg>
                    begin with, they were ordered to pass outside the rampart, clad in their tunics
                    and unarmed, and the hostages were at once handed over and led off into
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> custody. <reg>next</reg> , the lictors
                    were commanded to forsake the consuls, who then were stripped of their generals'
                    cloaks, —a thing which inspired such compassion in those very men who a little
                    while before had cursed them and had declared that they deserved <milestone
                        n="14??" unit="section"/> to be given up and put to torture, that every man,
                    forgetting his own evil case, averted his eyes from that degradation of so
                    majestic an office, as from a spectacle of horror. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>first</reg> the consuls, little better than half —naked, were sent under
                    the yoke, then their subordinates were humbled, each in the order of his rank;
                    and then, one after another, the several legions. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> enemy under arms stood on either side, reviling them and
                    mocking them; many they actually threatened with the sword, and some, whose <pb
                        n="p.183"/> resentment of the outrage showing too plainly in their <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 321</note> faces gave
                    their conquerors offence, they wounded or slew outright. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>thus</reg> they were sent under the yoke, and, what was almost harder to
                    bear, while their enemies looked on. <reg>on</reg> emerging from the pass,
                    although they seemed like men raised from the dead, who beheld for the first
                    time the light of day, yet the very light itself, which allowed them to see that
                    dismal throng, was gloomier than any death. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> so, although it was in their power to have made Capua before
                    nightfall, yet, questioning the loyalty of their allies, and withheld also by
                    shame, they threw themselves upon the ground along the roadside, not far from
                    the city, with nothing to supply their wants. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> tidings of this were brought to Capua, a feeling of pity,
                    natural to allies, overcame the ingrained arrogance of the Campanians.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>ungrudgingly</reg> , without an instant's hesitation, they dispatched the
                    insignia of their office to the consuls, together with arms, horses, clothing,
                    and provisions, for the men; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and as they drew
                    near Capua, the whole senate and people going forth to meet them used towards
                    them all the rites of hospitality and every public and private courtesy.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>yet</reg> the kindness of their allies and their friendly looks and words
                    were so far from drawing the Romans into talk that they could not even be got to
                    raise their eyes or look their friends and comforters in the face; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> so constrained were they by a kind of humiliation
                    —over and above their grief —to <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> avoid the
                    speech and assemblages of men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> the following day, when the young nobles sent from Capua to attend
                    them to the borders of Campania had returned, and were called into the <pb
                        n="p.185"/> senatehouse and questioned by the elders, they reported <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 321</note> that they
                    had seemed to be much more sorrowful and dejected than before: their column had
                    marched on in silence and almost as though dumb; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> the old Roman spirit was quite dashed; they had lost their
                    courage with their arms; being saluted, they returned not the salutation; they
                    responded to no questions; not a man of them had been able to open his mouth for
                    shame, as if they still bore on their necks the yoke under which they had been
                    sent; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> the Samnites had won not only a famous
                    but a lasting victory, for they had conquered, not Rome —as the Gauls had done
                    before —but a thing which demanded far greater prowess —the Roman valour and
                    independence. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>such</reg> were the opinions that were spoken <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note> and listened to, and the
                    Roman name had well —nigh <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> been given up for
                    lost in the council of Rome's faithful allies, when Aulus Calavius, son of
                    Ovius, a man of famous birth and achievements and at that time venerable also
                    for his age, asserted that the case was very different: <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> that obstinate silence, those eyes fixed on the ground and
                    ears deaf to every consolation, that shame at looking on the light, were signs,
                    he argued, of bosoms bursting with passionate resentment; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> either he knew nothing of the Roman character, or that
                    silence was destined ere long to draw from the Samnites cries and groans of
                    anguish, and the Caudine Peace to become a far more bitter memory to Samnites
                    than to Romans; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> for each people would have its
                    own native spirit wherever they might encounter, but the Samnites would not
                    everywhere have a Caudine Pass. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>by</reg> this time Rome, too, had heard of her shameful <pb n="p.187"/>
                    calamity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> first news was that the army was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note> entrapped; then came a
                    gloomier report, more by reason of the disgraceful peace than because of the
                    peril. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> the rumour of a blockade they had begun to hold a levy; but they
                    afterwards gave over their measures for relief, when they learned that there had
                    been so infamous a capitulation, and immediately, without official sanction of
                    any sort, betook themselves with one mind to every form of mourning. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> booths round about the Forum were shut up, and ere proclamation
                    could be made, all business was suspended; tunics with the broad stripe of
                    purple were discarded, as were golden rings. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">latus clavus,</hi> a broad
                        (purple) stripe in the tunic, marked the senator. <reg>both</reg> senators
                        and knights wore golden rings, though these later became the distinguishing
                        badge of the knights. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> citizens were almost more dejected than the army; and not only
                    were they enraged against their generals and those who had favoured and
                    guaranteed the peace, but they even visited their hate upon the innocent
                    soldiers and proposed to exclude them from the City and from their homes.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> this flurry of resentment was dispelled by the arrival of the
                    army, which even angry men could not but pity. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> they came not like men returning in safety to their homes, after
                    all hope of them had been abandoned; but entering the City late in the day, with
                    the bearing and looks of prisoners, they slipped away every man to his own
                    house, and on the next and the succeeding days not one of them would look into
                    the Forum or the streets. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls shut themselves up in their houses and would transact
                    no public business, except that they were forced by a senatorial decree to name
                    a dictator to preside at the election. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> designated Quintus Fabius Ambustus, with Publius Aelius Paetus
                    to be master of the horse. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>a</reg> flaw in their appointment occasioned the substitution in their <pb
                        n="p.189"/> room of Marcus Aemilius Papus, as dictator, and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note> Lucius
                    Valerius Flaccus, as master of the horse. <reg>however</reg> , even they did not
                    hold an election; and because the people were dissatisfied with all the
                    magistrates of that year, the state reverted to an interregnum. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> interreges were Quintus Fabius Maximus and Marcus Valerius
                    Corvus. <name>The</name> latter announced the election to the consulship of
                    Quintus Publilius Philo (for the third time) and Lucius Papirius Cursor (for the
                    second) with the unmistakable approval of the citizens, for there were at that
                    time no leaders more distinguished. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> the day of their election —for so the Fathers had ordained —they
                    entered upon the duties of their magistracy, and having disposed of the routine
                    resolutions, raised the question of the Caudine Peace. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>Publilius</name> had the fasces, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > The <hi rend="italics">fasces</hi> (bundles of rods, symbolic of supreme
                        authority) were borne by the lictors in alternate attendance on the two
                        consuls. <name>The</name> elder had them first. </note> and called on
                    Spurius Postumius to speak. <reg>having</reg> risen to his feet, he said, with
                    the same expression on his countenance as when he had been sent <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> under the yoke, <quote>
                        <reg>i</reg> am not ignorant, consuls, that I have been called on first and
                        bidden to speak because of my disgrace, and not to honour me; not as a
                        senator, but as one charged with the guilt not only of an unlucky war but of
                        a shameful peace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>however</reg> , you have not raised the question of our wrongdoing or
                        our punishment; I will therefore attempt no defence —though it should be no
                        difficult cause to plead before judges not unacquainted with the fortunes of
                        men and their necessities —but will briefly formulate a motion concerning
                        the subject you have asked us to consider. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>my</reg> motion will bear witness whether it was myself or your legions
                        that I spared, when I bound myself by a base, or, perhaps, <pb n="p.191"/> a
                        necessary pledge, —by which, however, the Roman <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note> People is not held,
                        since it was given without the people's authorization; nor by its terms is
                        aught but our own persons due to the Samnites. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>let</reg> us be given up, I propose, by the fetials, stripped and
                        bound; let us release the people from their religious obligation, if in any
                        such we have involved them, that no obstacle, divine or human, may block the
                        way to a just and righteous renewal of the war. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>meantime</reg> I move that the consuls enroll an army and arm it and
                        lead it forth, yet without crossing the borders of the enemy, until all the
                        ceremonies incident to our surrender shall have been completed. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>do</reg> you, immortal gods, I beseech and pray you, if you were not
                        pleased that the consuls Spurius Postumius and Titus Veturius should
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> wage a successful war with the
                        Samnites, yet deem it enough to have seen us sent beneath the yoke, to have
                        seen us bound by an infamous agreement, to behold. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> us, naked and in bonds, delivered to the enemy,
                        receiving on our own heads all the resentment of our foes; and vouchsafe to
                        the new consuls and the Roman legions so to wage war with the Samnites, as,
                        until our consulship, all Rome's wars were waged. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> he had finished speaking, such a thrill of astonishment, and at
                    the same time of pity for the man, ran through the senate, that at first men
                    could hardly believe it was the same Spurius Postumius who had been the author
                    of a peace so shameful; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and presently they
                    were all compassion, to think that such a man should suffer what would be no
                    ordinary punishment at the hands of enemies enraged by the rupture of the peace.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>as</reg> they <pb n="p.193"/> were all crossing over to support his motion,
                    with <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note>
                    nothing but praises for his heroism, Lucius Livius and Quintus Maelius, tribunes
                    of the plebs, endeavoured for a moment to interpose their veto. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> people, they said, could not be freed from their obligation by
                    surrendering <hi rend="italics">them,</hi> unless every advantage which the
                    Samnites had possessed at Caudium were restored to them; <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> moreover, they had merited no punishment for having
                    preserved by their pledge of peace the army of the Roman People; nor, finally,
                    seeing that they were sacrosanct, could they be surrendered to the enemy or
                    violated. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livius and Maelius are
                        apparently thought of as having been among the guarantors and as having
                        afterwards been elected plebeian tribunes. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>then</reg> said Postumius: " <reg>meanwhile</reg> , surrender us, who are
                    unconsecrate, as you may do without offence to Heaven; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> afterwards you shall surrender also those sacrosanct ones,
                    when once they have retired from their magistracy; but, if you should listen to
                    me, before surrendering them you would have them scourged here in the Comitium,
                    that they might receive in advance this extra punishment, by way of interest.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> when they deny that the people can be freed of their obligation
                    by surrendering us, who is so unacquainted with the fetial law as not to be
                    aware that they say this, more that they may not be surrendered than because the
                    case is so? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> yet, Conscript Fathers, I do not dispute the fact that guarantees
                    as well as treaties are sacred in the eyes of those who cherish honour among men
                    on an equal footing with obligations due to the gods; but I deny that without
                    the people's authorization any sanction can be given which shall be binding on
                    the people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>what</reg> ! If the Samnites with that same arrogance with which they
                    extorted this capitulation from us had <pb n="p.195"/> compelled us to pronounce
                    the solemn form of words <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 320</note> of those who surrender cities, would you tribunes assert
                    that the Roman People had been surrendered, and that this City, with its
                    temples, its holy places, its bounds and waters, was become the property of the
                    Samnites? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> enough of <hi rend="italics">surrender;</hi> we are talking of a
                        <hi rend="italics">guarantee.</hi>
                    <reg>how</reg> , pray, if we had guaranteed that the Roman People should forsake
                    this City? that they should burn it? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that it
                    should cease to have magistrates, a senate, laws? that it should be subject to
                    the rule of kings? ' The gods forbid!' you say. <reg>and</reg> yet the
                    unworthiness of the conditions cannot lessen the force of a guarantee; if there
                    is anything for which the people can be bound, it can be bound for everything.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>nor</reg> does it matter, either, as some are perhaps inclined to think,
                    whether consul or dictator or praetor have given the guarantee. <reg>and</reg>
                    this the very Samnites themselves deemed to be true, for not content with the
                    guarantee of consuls, they obliged the lieutenants, the quaestors, and the
                    tribunes of the soldiers to add theirs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        <reg>and</reg> let no man now demand of me why I gave this guarantee, seeing
                        that a consul has no right so to do and that I could not pledge them a peace
                        which was not <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> mine to grant, nor in
                        your behalf, who had given me no mandate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>there</reg> was nothing done at Caudium, Conscript Fathers, by man's
                        wisdom: the immortal gods deprived of understanding both your commanders and
                        the enemy's. We, on our part, took no sufficient precautions in the war:
                        while, as for them, they threw away their ill —got victory by their ill
                        —guided conduct, for they hardly trusted the very ground that had given them
                            <pb n="p.197"/> their conquest, in their haste to deprive of arms, on
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note>
                        any terms, men born to the use of arms. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>why</reg> , had they had their wits about them, would it have been
                        hard, while summoning old men from home for consultation, to dispatch envoys
                        to Rome? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> to treat with senate and with
                        people for a peace and covenant? <reg>it</reg> was only three days' journey
                        to those who travel light; meantime hostilities would have been suspended,
                        until their envoys should return from Rome with either certain victory or a
                        peace. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Victory, in case the Roman
                            People declined to accept terms for the ransom of their army; peace, if
                            they acceded to those terms. </note>
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>then</reg> , and then only, would there have been a guarantee in which
                        our pledge was backed by the mandate of the people. <reg>but</reg> neither
                        would you have voted one, nor should we have given it; <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> nor was it Heaven's will that the affair should have
                        any other ending, but that they should be beguiled with a dream too joyful
                        for their comprehension, and that our army should be extricated by the same
                        fortune which had entrapped it; that their idle victory should evaporate in
                        a yet idler peace, and a guarantee be proffered that should bind none but
                        the guarantor. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>for</reg> what negotiation, Conscript Fathers, has there been with you
                        or with the Roman People? <reg>who</reg> can appeal to you, who can say that
                        he has been deceived by you? <reg>can</reg> the enemy, can a fellow
                        —citizen? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>you</reg> have pledged nothing to the enemy, you have given no
                        authority to make a pledge to any fellow —citizen. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>you</reg> have therefore naught to do with us, to whom you gave no
                        mandate, or with the Samnites, with whom you have had no dealings.
                            <name>The</name> Samnites have in us guarantors who are responsible and
                        quite competent, so far as concerns what belongs to ourselves and what we
                        are able to deliver, namely, our persons and our lives; against these let
                            <pb n="p.199"/> them storm, against these direct their swords, against
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note>
                        these make sharp their anger. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>as</reg> for the tribunes, you must determine whether their surrender
                        can take place at once or had better be deferred; meantime, Titus Veturius,
                        let us, and you others, offer these caitiff heads of ours in satisfaction of
                        our pledge, and by our suffering liberate the Roman arms. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>both</reg> the cause itself and the speaker greatly stirred the Conscript
                    Fathers and the others present, including even the tribunes of the plebs, who
                    declared that they would obey the senate, and having forthwith <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> resigned their office were delivered over to the
                    fetials to be led with the rest to Caudium. <reg>when</reg> the senate had acted
                    on this motion, it somehow seemed as though day had dawned upon the State.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Postumius</name> was on all men's lips; they extolled him to the skies,
                    and compared his conduct to the devotion of Publius Decius, the consul, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">viii. ix. 4 f.</note> and to other
                    glorious deeds. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> state, they said, had emerged —thanks to his wisdom and his
                    services —from a slavish peace; he was freely giving himself up to the tortures
                    of a resentful foe, that he might make expiation for the Roman People.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>men</reg> thought of nothing but war and arms. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>would</reg> ever the hour come, they asked, when they might encounter the
                    Samnites, sword in hand? </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>in</reg> a city ablaze with wrath and hate, the levy was almost wholly made
                    up with volunteers. <name>The</name> same soldiers were enrolled into new
                    legions, and the army marched on Caudium. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>before</reg> them went the fetials, who, when they had come to the gate,
                    bade the guarantors of peace be stripped and their hands be bound behind their
                    backs. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>as</reg> the officer, awed by the dignity of Postumius, would have left him
                    loosely <pb n="p.201"/> bound, <quote>
                        <reg>nay</reg> , draw the thong tight, </quote> he exclaimed, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note>
                    <quote>that the surrender may be duly carried out.</quote>
                    <reg>then</reg> , on arriving at the assembly of the Samnites and the tribune of
                    Pontius, Aulus Cornelius Arvina the fetial <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the <hi rend="italics">pater patratus,</hi> see
                        i. xxiv. 6. </note> spoke as follows: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "
                        <reg>whereas</reg> these men, unbidden by the Roman People of the Quirites,
                    have guaranteed that a treaty should be ratified, and by so doing have committed
                    an injury; to the end that the Roman People may be absolved of heinous guilt, I
                    deliver up these men to you. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>as</reg> the fetial spoke these words, Postumius thrust his knee into the
                    other's thigh, with all the force he could summon up, and proclaimed in a loud
                    voice that he was a Samnite citizen, who had maltreated the envoy in violation
                    of the law of nations, whereby the Romans would make war with the better right. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>then</reg> said Pontius, "I will not receive this surrender, nor will the
                    Samnites hold it valid. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> you, Spurius Postumius, if you believe in the existence of the
                    gods, why not either reject the whole negotiation or abide by your agreement?
                        <name>The</name> Samnite People is entitled to all whom it had in its power,
                    or to peace in place of them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> why do I appeal to you, who yield yourself a prisoner as
                    honourably as you can? <reg>i</reg> appeal to the Roman People; if they repent
                    them of the pledge that was given at the Caudine Forks, let them replace their
                    legions in the defile where they were surrounded. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>let</reg> no one deceive anybody; let as though it had not happened; let
                    them resume the arms they laid down in accordance with the compact; let them go
                    back to their camp; whatever they had on the day before the conference, let them
                    have again; <hi rend="italics">then</hi> let them vote for war and warlike
                    measures, <hi rend="italics">then</hi> let <pb n="p.203"/> them reject the
                    guarantee and the peace! <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>let</reg> us <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        320</note> fight it out in those circumstances, and in those positions,
                    which were ours before peace was mentioned; let the Roman People not blame the
                    pledge given by the consuls, nor let us blame the honour of the Roman People.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>will</reg> you never, when you have been beaten, lack excuses for not
                    holding to your covenants? <reg>you</reg> gave hostages to Porsinna —and
                    withdrew them by a trick. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">An allusion
                        to the Cloelia episode, II. xiii. 6-11.</note>
                    <reg>you</reg> ransomed your City from the Gauls with gold —and cut them down as
                    they were receiving the gold. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> V.
                        xlviii <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> —xlix. </note>
                    <reg>you</reg> pledged us peace, on condition that we gave you back your
                    captured legions —and you nullify the peace. <reg>and</reg> always you contrive
                    to give the fraud some colour of <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> legality.
                        <reg>does</reg> the Roman People not approve the preservation of its legions
                    by a disgraceful peace? <reg>let</reg> it keep its peace, and give back the
                    captured legions to the victor; that would be conduct worthy of its promise, its
                    covenants, its fetial <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> ceremonies.
                        <reg>that</reg> you, on your side, should have what you aimed at in your
                    compact, the safety of these many citizens, but that I should not have the peace
                    I stipulated for, when I released them, —is this the judgment which you, Aulus
                    Cornelius, and you, fetials, render to the nations? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        <reg>as</reg> for me, I will none of these whom you pretend to be
                        surrendering, nor do I deem them to be surrendered, neither do I stand in
                        the way of their returning, despite the wrath of all the gods, whose
                        divinity they have made a mock, to the City which is committed by their
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> guarantee. <reg>aye</reg> , go to
                        war, since Spurius Postumius has just now jostled the envoy with his knee!
                            <reg>so</reg> shall the gods believe that Postumius is a Samnite —not a
                        Roman —citizen, <pb n="p.205"/> and that a Roman envoy has been maltreated
                        by a <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note>
                        Samnite, and that you, in consequence of this, have justly made war on
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> us! <reg>does</reg> it not shame you
                        to bring forth into the light of day these mockeries of religion, and, old
                        men and consulars as you are, to devise such quibbles to evade your promise
                        as were scarce worthy of <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> children?
                            <reg>go</reg> , lictor, strike their fetters from the Romans; let no man
                        hinder them from departing when they list. </quote>
                    <reg>and</reg> the guarantors, released it may be from the nation's pledge, but
                    at all events from their own, returned from Caudium, inviolate, to the Roman
                    camp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> Samnites now perceived that instead of their domineering peace
                    they were confronted with the renewal of a most bitter war, and not only
                    imagined but almost saw all the consequences which afterwards proceeded from it.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>too</reg> late and all in vain did they praise the alternative policies
                    suggested by the aged Pontius, between which they had fallen, and exchanged a
                    victory already in their possession for an uncertain peace; they had let slip
                    the opportunity both of doing good and of doing harm, and were going to fight
                    with men whom they might permanently have removed from their path, as enemies,
                    or have made their permanent friends. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> though there had so far been no battle since the Caudine Peace to
                    give an advantage to either side, yet such a change of feeling had come about
                    that Postumius enjoyed more fame among the Romans for his surrender than did
                    Pontius among the Samnites for his bloodless victory; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and while the Romans regarded their being able to make war
                    as certain victory, the Samnites felt that the Romans had at one and the same
                    moment renewed the war and won it. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.207"/>
                <p>
                    <reg>meanwhile</reg> the Satricans revolted to the Samnites, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note> and the
                    colony of Fregellae, in a surprise attack by the Samnites —accompanied, it would
                    seem, by people from Satricum —was seized during the night. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>mutual</reg> fear then caused both sides to remain quiet until the morning,
                    when the light ushered in a battle which for a long time was equally sustained
                    —for the townsfolk were fighting for their hearths and altars and a throng of
                    those unfit for arms gave them assistance from the housetops, —still, <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> the people of Fregellae held their own, until
                    presently a ruse decided the victory; for they permitted a herald to be heard,
                    who promised safety to any who laid down his arms. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> hope of this relaxed the tension of their courage and on every
                    side they began throwing their arms away. <name>The</name> more determined
                    portion of them retained their weapons and burst out by the opposite gate, and
                    their boldness stood them in better stead than did their too credulous timidity
                    the others; for these the Samnites compassed about with fire, and, despite their
                    appeals to Heaven and to the promise of their captors, burnt them alive. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls having divided the provinces between them, Papirius
                    took his way into Apulia towards Luceria, where the Roman knights given up at
                    Caudium for hostages were being guarded, while Publilius stopped behind in
                    Samnium to oppose the Caudine legions. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> plan distracted the minds of the Samnites, since they neither
                    dared move towards Luceria, lest they should bring the enemy down upon their
                    rear, nor remain where they were, for fear that Luceria would meanwhile be lost.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> best course seemed to be to entrust their cause to <pb
                        n="p.209"/> Fortune and fight it out with Publilius. <reg>they</reg>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note>
                    accordingly formed up in line of battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>Publilius</name> the consul was ready to engage them, but thinking it best
                    to encourage his soldiers first, he bade summon them to an assembly.
                        <reg>but</reg> though they came running to the praetorium with vast
                    alacrity, yet the outcry of those who demanded battle was so loud that the
                    general's exhortation could not be heard; still, every man's own heart,
                    remembering the late humiliation, was there to exhort him. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>so</reg> they went forward into battle, urging on their standard —bearers;
                    and, that there might be no delay in coming to grips while they were discharging
                    their javelins and drawing their swords, they threw away their javelins, as if a
                    signal had been given them, and, sword <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> in
                    hand, pushed forward at the double against the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>no</reg> tactical skill was there employed in ranging centuries or
                    reserves: the wrath of the soldiers swept everything along in its mad rush.
                        <reg>and</reg> so not only were the Samnites routed, but not daring to
                    interrupt their flight even at their camp, they dispersed and struck out for
                    Apulia; yet they afterwards rallied again and came to Luceria in one body.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> same fury that took the Romans through their enemy's battle
                    —line, carried them also into his camp. <reg>there</reg> was more bloodshed and
                    carnage there than in the battle, and the greater part of the booty was
                    destroyed in anger. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> other army, under the consul Papirius, marching along the coast
                    as far as Arpi, had found all peaceably disposed, more because of the wrongs
                    done by the Samnites and the hatred they had engendered than owing to any favour
                    shown by the <pb n="p.211"/> Roman People. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> the Samnites, who in those <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note> days dwelt in villages
                    among the mountains, used to ravage the regions of the plain and coast,
                    despising their cultivators, who were of a softer character, and one that —as
                    often happens —resembled their country, while they themselves were rude
                    highlanders. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>if</reg> this district had been faithful to the Samnites, it would either
                    have been impossible for a Roman army to have got as far as Arpi, or the utterly
                    barren nature of the intervening country would have destroyed them, cut off as
                    they would have been from their supplies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>even</reg> as it was, when they had proceeded to the vicinity of Luceria,
                    besiegers and besieged suffered alike from scarcity of food: everything was
                    carried up from Arpi for the Romans, but so precarious were their supplies, that
                    while the foot —soldiers were busy with outpost —duty, guard —mounting,
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and entrenching, the cavalry brought up
                    corn for them from Arpi in leather pouches, and, now and then, encountering the
                    enemy, were forced to throw off the corn from their horses and fight; the
                    besieged, until the arrival of the other consul with his victorious army, had
                    got in their provisions —and auxiliary forces too —from the mountains of the
                    Samnites. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> coming of Publilius tightened up the lines; for, turning the
                    siege over to his colleague, he was free to range the country —side, where he
                    made things difficult for the supply —trains of the enemy. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Samnites, therefore, who were encamped about Luceria, in
                    despair of being able to endure the scarcity, if the siege continued, were
                    obliged to gather up their forces from every quarter and give battle to
                    Papirius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> this juncture, while both sides were <pb n="p.213"/> making ready
                    for the struggle, came ambassadors <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 320</note> from Tarentum, admonishing both Samnites and
                    Romans to desist from war. <reg>whichever</reg> party should oppose the
                    cessation of hostilities, against that they proposed to fight in behalf of the
                    other. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>after</reg> listening to these envoys, Papirius, as though moved by what
                    they said, replied that he would consult his colleague. <reg>having</reg> sent
                    for Publilius, he employed every moment of the interval in making his
                    preparations, and when he had conferred with him about a matter which admitted
                    of no doubt, displayed the battle —signal. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> a red flag hung out in front of the general's
                        tent. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls were busy with matters pertaining to gods and to men,
                    as they are wont to to be on the eve of an engagement, when the envoys from
                    Tarentum approached them to receive their answer; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> to whom Papirius replied, <quote>
                        <name>Tarentines</name> , the keeper of the chickens reports that the signs
                        are favourable; the sacrifice too has been exceedingly auspicious; <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Two kinds of divination are alluded
                            to: (1) by observing the feeding of the sacred chickens, (2) by
                            inspecting the entrails of a victim. </note> as you see, the gods are
                        with us at our going into action. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> then commanded to advance the standards, and marshalled his
                    troops, with exclamations on the folly of a nation which, powerless to manage
                    its own affairs, because of domestic strife and discord, presumed to lay down
                    the limits of peace and war for others. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Samnites, on their side, having dismissed from their minds
                    every anxiety regarding the war, either because they sincerely wished for peace,
                    or because it was expedient for them to pretend that they wished it, in order to
                    gain the support of the Tarentines, when they beheld <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> the Romans suddenly arrayed for battle, cried out that they
                    would abide by the will of the Tarentines and would neither take the field nor
                    advance beyond the rampart; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> they had <pb
                        n="p.215"/> been deceived, but they chose rather to endure <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 320</note> whatever
                    Fortune might have in store for them than be thought to have spurned the
                    peaceful advice of the Tarentines. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls declared that they embraced the omen, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The omen lay in the Samnites' expressed
                        purpose to offer no resistance. </note> praying that the enemy might be so
                    minded as not even to defend his rampart. <reg>they</reg> themselves, dividing
                    their troops between them, marched up to the earthworks of the Samnites, and
                    attacked them at once from every side. <reg>some</reg> began to fill the
                    trenches, others to pull up the palings and fling them into the trenches;
                    besides their native courage they were goaded on by anger at the disgrace that
                    rankled in their hearts. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>forcing</reg> their way into the camp, while every man repeated that here
                    were no Forks, no Caudium, no trackless passes, where guile had arrogantly
                    triumphed over error, but Roman manhood, which neither rampart nor trenches
                    could keep out, they cut down without distinction those who resisted and those
                    who fled, the armed and the unarmed, slaves and <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> freemen, adults and children, men and beasts; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> nor would anything living have survived, had not the
                    consuls bade sound the recall and expelled the bloodthirsty soldiers from the
                    enemy's camp with commands and threats. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> men were incensed at the interruption of their sweet revenge,
                    and accordingly the consuls at once addressed them and explained that they had
                    neither yielded nor meant to yield to any of the soldiers in hatred of the
                    enemy; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> on the contrary, they would have led
                    the way, as in war, so in the exaction of endless vengeance, had their
                    indignation not been checked by thoughts of the six hundred knights who were
                    being held as hostages in Luceria; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> but they
                    feared that the enemy, if they despaired of <pb n="p.217"/> quarter, might be
                    driven blindly to put their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 320</note> prisoners to death, choosing to slay before
                    they were slain themselves. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <name>These</name> arguments the men applauded, and rejoiced that their wrath
                    had been restrained; they confessed that it was better that they should suffer
                    anything than betray the lives of so many distinguished young Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> assembly was dismissed, and a council of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note> war was held to determine
                    whether they should press the siege with all their forces, or should employ one
                    army and its general to test the dispositions of the Apulians around them —a
                    people whose sympathies were still in doubt. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consul Publilius set out on a march through Apulia and in a
                    single expedition either subjugated, or by granting terms, received into
                    alliance, a goodly number of states. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Papirius</name> , too, who had remained behind at Luceria to conduct the
                    siege, soon found the outcome answerable to his hopes; for all the roads by
                    which supplies were wont to be brought in from Samnium were blocked, and the
                    Samnite garrison were reduced by hunger to send a deputation to the Roman consul
                    with an offer to release the horsemen who were the cause of the war, on
                    condition that he would raise the siege. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Papirius</name> replied that they ought to have gone to Pontius, the son
                    of Herennius, at whose instance they had sent the Romans under the yoke, to find
                    out what the vanquished deserved to suffer; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    however, since they preferred that their enemies should decide on a just penalty
                    for them, rather than propose one for themselves, he bade them take word to
                    Luceria that they should leave their arms, packs, sumpter animals, and all the
                    noncombatants, within the walls; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the soldiers
                    he <pb n="p.219"/> intended to send under the yoke, clad only in their <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note> tunics,
                    inflicting on them no new disgrace, but requiting that which had first been put
                    upon the Romans. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> made no objection, and seven thousand men were sent under the
                    yoke. <reg>huge</reg> spoils were captured in Luceria, and all the standards and
                    arms which had been lost at Caudium were retaken, and, to cap the climax of
                    their joy, the horsemen were recovered whom the Samnites had assigned, as
                    pledges of peace, to be guarded at Luceria. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> is scarce any other Roman victory more glorious for its sudden
                    reversal of fortune, especially if it is true, as I find in certain annals, that
                    Pontius the son of Herennius, the Samnite general —in —chief, was sent with the
                    rest under the yoke, to expiate the humiliation of the consuls. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>be</reg> that as it may, I am not greatly surprised that there should be
                    some doubt as to the general of the enemy who was surrendered and disgraced; the
                    amazing thing is the uncertainty whether it was Lucius Cornelius, as dictator
                    —with Lucius Papirius Cursor, as master of the horse —who <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> won these victories at Caudium and subsequently at Luceria,
                    and, because of the signal vengeance that he exacted for Rome's shame, enjoyed a
                    triumph which I should be inclined to rate as the best —deserved of all down to
                    that time, next after that of Furius Camillus; or whether that honour belongs to
                    the consuls —and particularly to Papirius. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> doubt is attended with another —whether at the ensuing election
                    Papirius Cursor was retained in office in recognition of his victory at Luceria,
                    being returned for a third time to the consulship, together with Quintus Aulius
                    Cerretanus —then chosen for the second time —or <pb n="p.221"/> whether it was
                    Lucius Papirius Mugillanus, and the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 319</note> mistake was a matter of the surname. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> is agreed that from this point onwards the war was brought to a
                    conclusion by the consuls. <name>Aulius</name> finished in one successful battle
                    the campaign against the Ferentani, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Their town has been conjecturally identified with Horace's <quote>low —lying
                            Forentum,</quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>odes</reg> , </hi> III. iv. 16. </note> and having exacted
                    hostages, received the surrender of the city itself, in which their defeated
                    army had taken <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> refuge. <reg>with</reg> no less
                    good fortune the other consul overcame the Satricans, who —though Roman citizens
                    —had revolted, after the Caudine misfortune, to the Samnites, of whom they had
                    admitted a garrison into their <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> city.
                        <reg>for</reg> when the Roman army had drawn near the walls of Satricum, the
                    townspeople sent ambassadors to sue humbly for peace; but the consul returned
                    them a harsh answer: that unless they put to death the Samnite garrison or
                    delivered it up, they must come back to him no more —a saying which struck more
                    terror into their hearts than the threatened <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    assault. <reg>and</reg> so the envoys persisted in demanding of the consul how
                    he supposed that they, being few and weak, could force so strong and well —armed
                    a <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> garrison. <reg>but</reg> he bade them seek
                    advice from those same men at whose instigation they had received the garrison
                    into their city; and after they had with no small difficulty persuaded him to
                    suffer them to consult their senate in the matter and report to him its
                    decision, they went back to their <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> people.
                        <reg>two</reg> factions kept the senate divided: one of these had for
                    leaders the men who had inspired the revolt from Rome, the other was composed of
                    loyal citizens; both, however, were equally anxious to accommodate the consul,
                    so that they might be granted <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> peace.
                        <reg>one</reg> party, seeing that the Samnite garrison was <pb n="p.223"/>
                    intending to escape on the following night —for they had <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note> made no preparations for
                    enduring a siege —deemed it sufficient to let the consul know at what hour and
                    by what gate the enemy meant to leave, and what road he planned to <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> take. <name>The</name> others, who had opposed going
                    over to the Samnites, that same night also opened a gate to the consul, and
                    without letting the Samnites know, admitted his soldiers into the <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> city. <reg>in</reg> consequence of this double
                    betrayal, the Samnite garrison was surprised and overpowered by an ambush laid
                    in the woods about their road, while a shout went up in the city, which was
                    filled with enemies. <reg>thus</reg> , in one crowded hour, the Samnites were
                    slain and the Satricans captured, and all things brought under the power of the
                    consul; who conducted an investigation, and, having ascertained who were
                    responsible for the defection, had the guilty parties scourged and <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> beheaded; after which he imposed a strong garrison
                    upon the Satricans and deprived them of their arms. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Papirius</name> Cursor then departed for Rome to celebrate his triumph, as
                    those writers state who name him as the commander who recovered Luceria and sent
                    the Samnites under the <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> yoke. <reg>no</reg>
                    question, he was a man deserving of all praise as a soldier, excelling, as he
                    did, not only in the vigour of his spirit, but in physical strength.
                        <reg>he</reg> possessed remarkable fleetness of foot, which was even the
                    source of his <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> surname. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Cursor</name>
                        </hi> means <quote>runner,</quote> but the name seems really to have been an
                        inheritance in the present case, for at chap. xxxiv. §20 we read of it as
                        belonging to the grandfather of our Papirius. </note>
                    <reg>it</reg> is said that he vanquished all his mates at running, whether owing
                    to the <pb n="p.225"/> strength of his legs or to much exercise; that he <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note> had also
                    the greatest capacity for food and <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> wine; and
                    that no general was harder on his men, whether horse or foot, for his own
                    constitution could never be overcome by <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> toil.
                        <reg>it</reg> is related how his cavalrymen ventured once to ask him if in
                    view of their good conduct he would not excuse them from some portion of their
                    duties; to whom he answered, <quote>
                        <reg>that</reg> you may not say that I have excused you nothing, I freely
                        excuse you from the duty of rubbing your backs when you <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> dismount. </quote>
                    <reg>and</reg> the man possessed a power of command which was equally effective
                    with citizens and allies. <reg>a</reg> Praenestine praetor had, through
                    timidity, been somewhat slow in bringing his men up from the supports to the
                    fighting <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> line. <name>Papirius</name> strolled
                    over to the praetor's tent and having bidden them call him out, commanded a
                    lictor to prepare his <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> axe. <reg>hearing</reg>
                    this the praetor stood aghast, but Papirius said to the lictor, <quote>
                        <reg>come</reg> , cut out this root; it is a nuisance to those who walk. </quote>
                    <reg>he</reg> then fined the man and let him go, half —dead with the fear of
                    capital <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> punishment. <reg>there</reg> can be
                    no doubt that in his generation, than which none was ever more fruitful of great
                    qualities, there was no single man who did more to uphold the Roman State.
                        <reg>indeed</reg> people regard him as one who might have been a match in
                    generalship for Alexander the Great, if the latter, after subjugating Asia, had
                    turned his arms against Europe. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>nothing</reg> can be thought to have been more remote from my intention,
                    since I first set about this task, than to depart unduly from the order of
                    events, and to aim, by the introduction of ornamental digressions, at providing
                    as it were agreeable <pb n="p.227"/> bypaths for the reader, and mental
                    relaxation for <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        319</note> myself. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>nevertheless</reg> the mention of so great a prince and captain evokes
                    certain thoughts which I have often silently pondered in my mind, and disposes
                    me to enquire how the Roman State would have fared in a war with Alexander.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Professor Anderson argues that
                        the following digression (chap. xvii. § 3 through chap. xix) was a youthful
                        exercise in rhetoric written when Livy was a boy and later inserted here
                        without revision, but with the addition of an introductory section (§§ 1,
                        2). See his edition, <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>app</reg> . </hi> III, and <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>transactions</reg> of the American Philological Association, </hi>
                        XXXIX. (1908), pp. 94-99. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> appears that in war the factors of chief importance are the
                    numbers and valour of the soldiers, the abilities of the commanders, and
                    Fortune, which, powerful in all the affairs of men, is especially so in war.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>These</name> factors, whether viewed separately or conjointly, afford a
                    ready assurance, that, even as against other princes and nations, so also
                    against this one the might of Rome would have proved invincible. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>first</reg> of all —to begin by comparing commanders —I do not deny that
                    Alexander was a remarkable general; still, his fame was enhanced by the fact
                    that he was a sole commander, and the further fact that he died young, in the
                    flood —tide of success, when as yet he had experienced no other lot. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>not</reg> to speak of other distinguished kings and generals, illustrious
                    proofs of human vicissitude, what else was it but length of days that exposed
                    Cyrus, whom the Greeks exalt so high in their panegyrics, to the fickleness of
                    Fortune? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> the same thing was lately seen in the case of Pompey the Great.
                        <reg>need</reg> I repeat the names of the Roman generals, not all nor of
                    every age, but those very ones with whom, as consuls or as dictators, Alexander
                    would have had to fight —Marcus <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Valerius
                    Corvus, Gaius Marcius Rutulus, Gaius Sulpicius, Titus Manlius Torquatus, Quintus
                    Publilius Philo, Lucius Papirius Cursor, Quintus Fabius Maximus, <pb n="p.229"/>
                    the two Decii, Lucius Volumnius, Manius Curius? <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>after</reg> these come some extraordinary men, if he had turned his
                    attention to war with Carthage first and later with Rome, and had crossed into
                    Italy when somewhat old. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>any</reg> one of these was as highly endowed with courage and talents as
                    was Alexander; and military training, handed down from the very beginning of the
                    City, had taken on the character of a profession, built up on comprehensive
                    principles. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>so</reg> the kings had warred; so after them the expellers of the kings,
                    the Junii and the Valerii, and so in succession the Fabii, Quinctii, Cornelii,
                    and Furius Camillus, whom in his old age those had seen, as youths, who would
                    have had to fight with Alexander. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> in the performance of a soldier's work in battle —for which
                    Alexander was no less distinguished —Manlius Torquatus or Valerius Corvus would,
                    forsooth, have yielded to him, had they met him in a hand —to —hand encounter,
                    famous though they were as soldiers before ever they won renown as captains!
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Decii, of course, would have yielded to him, who hurled their
                    devoted bodies upon the foe! <name>Papirius</name> Cursor would have yielded,
                    with that wondrous strength of body and of spirit! <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> counsels of a single youth would no doubt have got the better
                    of that senate —not to speak of individual members —which was called an assembly
                    of kings by him who before all others had a true conception of the Roman Senate!
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cineas, the ambassador of King
                        Pyrrhus. <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>cf</reg> . </hi>
                        <reg>plut</reg> . <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Pyrrhus</name> , </hi> xix. </note>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> I suppose there was the danger that Alexander would display more
                    skill than any of these whom I have named, in selecting a place for a camp, in
                    organizing his service of supply, in guarding against ambuscades, in choosing a
                    time for battle, in <pb n="p.231"/> marshalling his troops, in providing strong
                    reserves! <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        319</note>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> would have said it was no Darius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Darius III, defeated by Alexander in the battle of
                        Arbela, <date when="-0331">331 B.C.</date>
                    </note> whom he had to deal with, trailing women and eunuchs after him, and
                    weighed down with the gold and purple trappings of his station. <reg>him</reg>
                    he found a booty rather than an enemy, and conquered without bloodshed, merely
                    by daring to despise vain shows. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>far</reg> different from India, through which he progressed at the head of
                    a rout of drunken revellers, would Italy have appeared to him, as he gazed on
                    the passes of Apulia and the Lucanian mountains, and the still fresh traces of
                    that family disaster wherein his uncle, King Alexander of Epirus, had lost his
                    life. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">VIII. xxiv.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> we are speaking of an Alexander not yet overwhelmed with
                    prosperity, which none has ever been less able to bear. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> viewing him in the light of his new fortune and of the new
                    character —if I may use the expression —which <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    he had assumed as conqueror, he would evidently have come to Italy more like
                    Darius than like Alexander, at the head of an army that had forgotten Macedonia
                    and was already adopting the degenerate customs of the Persians. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>i</reg> am loath, in writing of so great a prince, to remind the reader of
                    the ostentatious alteration in his dress, and of his desire that men should
                    prostrate themselves in adulation, a thing which even conquered Macedonians
                    would have found oppressive, much more then those who had been victorious;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> of his cruel punishments and the murder of
                    his friends as they drank and feasted; of the boastful lie about his origin.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Philotas was examined under
                        torture and confessed participation in a plot against Alexander's life.
                            <reg>he</reg> implicated also his father Parmenio, the general, and both
                        were executed. <reg>clitus</reg> , who had saved Alexander's life at the
                        Granicus, was killed by him at a banquet in a fit of drunken rage.
                            <name>The</name> last clause alludes to Alexander's claim that Zeus, not
                        Philip, was his father. </note>
                    <reg>what</reg> if his love of wine had <pb n="p.233"/> every day grown
                    stronger? and his truculent and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 319</note> fiery anger? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>i</reg> mention only things which historians regard as certain.
                        <reg>can</reg> we deem such vices to be no detraction from a general's good
                    qualities? <reg>but</reg> there was forsooth the danger —as the silliest of the
                    Greeks, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is supposed to refer to
                        Timagenes, an historian of a notoriously anti-Roman bias. </note> who exalt
                    the reputation even of the Parthians against the Romans, are fond of alleging
                    —that <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the Roman People would have been unable
                    to withstand the majesty of Alexander's name, though I think that they had not
                    so much as heard of him; and that out of all the Roman nobles not one would have
                    dared to lift up his voice against him, although in Athens, a city crushed by
                    the arms of Macedonia, at the very moment when men had before their eyes the
                    reeking ruins of the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> neighbouring Thebes,
                    they dared inveigh against him freely, as witness the records of their speeches.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> An allusion, more rhetorical than
                        exact, to the famous Philippics of Demosthenes, the latest of which was
                        probably delivered some six years before the destruction of Thebes in <date
                            when="-0335">335 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>however</reg> imposing the greatness of the man may appear to us, still
                    this greatness will be that of one man only, and the fruits of little more than
                    ten years of success. <reg>those</reg> who magnify it for this reason, that the
                    Roman People, albeit never in any war, have yet suffered defeat in a number of
                    battles, whereas Alexander's fortune was never aught but prosperous in any
                    battle, fail to perceive that they are comparing the achievements of a man —and
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> a young man too —with those of a people
                    that was now in its four hundredth year of warfare. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>should</reg> it occasion us surprise if, seeing that upon the one side are
                    counted more generations than are years <pb n="p.235"/> upon the other, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> If we reckon the <hi rend="italics"
                            >saeculum</hi> or <quote>generation</quote> at thirtythree years, the
                        Rome of Alexander's time would have endured a little over thirteen <hi
                            rend="italics">saecula.</hi>
                        <name>Livy</name> says that people are really comparing these thirteen
                        generations with the thirteen years of Alexander's (effective) life, <hi
                            rend="italics">i.e.</hi> his reign (336- <date when="-0323">323
                            B.C.</date> ). </note> fortune should have varied more <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note> in that
                    long time than in a life of thirteen years? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>why</reg> not compare a man's fortune with a man's, and a general's with a
                    general's? How many Roman generals could I name who never suffered a reverse in
                    battle! <reg>in</reg> our annals and lists of magistrates you may run through
                    pages of consuls and dictators of whom it never on any day repented the Roman
                    People, whether of their generalship or fortune. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> what makes them more wonderful than Alexander or any king is
                    this: some were dictators of ten or twenty days, and none held the consulship
                    above a year; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> their levies were obstructed by
                    the tribunes of the plebs; they were late in going to war, and were called back
                    early to conduct elections; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> in the midst of
                    their undertakings the year rolled round; now the rashness, now the frowardness
                    of a colleague occasioned them losses or difficulties; they succeeded to affairs
                    which others had mismanaged, they received an army of raw recruits, or one badly
                    disciplined. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>now</reg> consider kings: not only are they free from all impediments, but
                    they are lords of time and circumstance, and in their counsels carry all things
                    with them, instead of following in their train. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>so</reg> then, an undefeated Alexander would have warred against undefeated
                    generals, and would have brought the same pledges of Fortune to the crisis.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>nay</reg> , he would have run a greater risk than they, inasmuch as the
                    Macedonians would have had but a single Alexander, not only exposed to many
                    dangers, but <pb n="p.237"/> incurring them voluntarily, while there would have
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note> been
                        <milestone n="19??" unit="section"/> many Romans a match for Alexander,
                    whether for glory or for the greatness of their deeds, of whom each several one
                    would have lived and died as his own fate commanded, without endangering the
                    State. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> remains to compare the forces on both sides, whether for numbers,
                    or types of soldiers, or size of their contingents of auxiliaries. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> quinquennial enumerations of that period put the population at
                    250,000. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the last census which
                        Livy had recorded ( <date when="-0459">459 B.C.</date> ) were enrolled
                        117,321 persons (III. xxiv. 10). Livy seems to have consulted the records of
                        the censors, at least occasionally. </note> And so at the time when all the
                    Latin allies were in revolt <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Or
                        possibly: at every revolt of the Latin allies.</note> it was the custom to
                    enroll ten legions, by a levy which was virtually limited to the City.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> those years frequently four and five armies at a time would take
                    the field, in Etruria, in Umbria (where they also fought the Gauls), in Samnium,
                    and in Lucania. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>later</reg> on Alexander would have found all Latium, with the Sabines, the
                    Volsci and the Aequi, all Campania, and a portion of Umbria and Etruria, the
                    Picentes and the Marsi and Paeligni, the Vestini and the Apulians, together with
                    the whole coast of the Lower Sea, held by the Greeks, from Thurii as far as
                    Naples and Cumae, and thence all the way to Antium and Ostia —all these, I say,
                    he would have found either powerful friends of the Romans or their defeated
                    enemies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> himself would have crossed the sea with veteran Macedonians to the
                    number of not more than thirty thousand foot and four thousand horse —mostly
                    Thessalians —for this was his main strength. <reg>if</reg> to these he had added
                    Persians and Indians and other nations, he would have found them a greater
                    burden to have dragged about than a help. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.239"/>
                <p>
                    <reg>add</reg> to this, that the Romans would have had recruits <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 319</note> ready to
                    call upon, but Alexander, <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> as happened
                    afterwards to Hannibal, would have found his army wear away, while he warred in
                    a foreign land. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>his</reg> men would have been armed with targets and spears: <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">sarisa</hi> was
                        a pike 21 feet long. </note> the Romans with an oblong shield, affording
                    more protection to the body, and the Roman javelin, which strikes, on being
                    thrown, with a much harder impact than the lance. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">hasta</hi> was ordinarily used
                        as a pike or lance, but was sometimes thrown, by means of a thong. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>both</reg> armies were formed of heavy troops, keeping to their ranks; but
                    their phalanx was immobile and consisted of soldiers of a single type; the Roman
                    line was opener and comprised more separate units; it was easy to divide,
                    wherever necessary, and easy to unite. <reg>moreover</reg> , what soldier can
                    match the Roman in entrenching? <reg>who</reg> is better at enduring toil?
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Alexander</name> would, if beaten in a single battle, have been beaten in
                    the war; but what battle could have overthrown the Romans, whom Caudium could
                    not overthrow, nor Cannae? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>nay</reg> , many a time —however prosperous the outset of his enterprise
                    might have been —would he have wished for Indians and Persians and unwarlike
                    Asiatics, and would have owned that he had before made war upon women, as
                    Alexander, King of Epirus, is reported to have said, <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> when mortally wounded, contrasting the type of war waged by
                    this very youth in Asia, with that which had fallen to his own share. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Aulus Gellius, xvii. xxi. 33, says that
                        Alexander, as he was setting sail for Italy, remarked that he was going to
                        the Romans, as it were to the men's quarters ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >andronitin</hi> ); whereas the Macedonian had gone to the Persians, as
                        to the quarters of the women ( <hi rend="italics">gynaeconitin).</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>indeed</reg> when I remember that we contended against the Carthaginians on
                    the seas for <pb n="p.241"/> four —andtwenty years, I think that the whole life
                    of Alexander <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        319</note> would hardly have sufficed for this single war; and perchance,
                    inasmuch as the Punic State had been by ancient treaties leagued with the Roman,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The earliest treaty was said to
                        have been made in <date when="-0509">509 B.C.</date> (Livy does not mention
                        it, but Polybius does, at III. xxii.); and another in 348. See vii. xxvii.
                        2, and note. </note> and the two cities most powerful in men and arms might
                    well have made common cause against the foe whom both dreaded, he had been
                    crushed beneath the simultaneous attacks of Rome and Carthage. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans have been at war with the Macedonians —not, to be sure,
                    when Alexander led them or their prosperity was unimpaired, but against
                    Antiochus, Philippus, and Perses —and not only without ever suffering defeat,
                    but even without incurring any danger. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>proud</reg> word I would not speak, but never —and may civil wars be
                    silent! — never have we been beaten by infantry, never in open battle, never on
                    even, or at all events on favourable ground: <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    cavalry and arrows, impassable defiles, regions that afford no road to convoys,
                    may well occasion fear in heavy —armed troops. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>a</reg> thousand battle —arrays more formidable than those of Alexander and
                    the Macedonians have the Romans beaten off —and shall do —if only our present
                    love of domestic peace endure and our concern to maintain concord. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>Marcus</name> Polius Flaccina and Lucius Plautius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 318-317</note> Venox were the next
                    consuls. <reg>in</reg> that year came ambassadors from many Samnite states to
                    seek a renewal of the treaty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>prostrating</reg> themselves before the senate, they aroused the pity of
                    that order, but on being referred to the people found their prayers by no means
                    so efficacious. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>accordingly</reg> they were refused the treaty, but after some days spent
                    in importuning individual citizens, they <pb n="p.243"/> succeeded in obtaining
                    a two years' truce. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> Apulia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 318-317</note> likewise, the Teanenses and Canusini, exhausted by the
                    devastation of their lands, gave hostages to Lucius Plautius the consul and made
                    submission. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> the same year praefects began to be elected and sent out to Capua,
                    after Lucius Furius, the praetor, had given them laws —both <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> steps being taken at the instance of the Capuans
                    themselves, as a remedy for the distress occasioned by internal discord.
                        <reg>at</reg> Rome two tribes were added, the Ufentina and the Falerna.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Making the number now thirty
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> —one. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>when</reg> affairs had once taken a tum in Apulia, the Apulian Teates <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>teate</reg>
                        </hi> was in reality only another name for <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>teanum</reg> . </hi>
                        <name>Livy</name> has been drawing upon two authorities, and their use of
                        different names for the same people has led him to make two episodes out of
                        one. </note> also came to the new consuls, Gaius Junius Bubulcus and Quintus
                    Aemilius Barbula, to sue for a treaty, engaging to insure the Roman People peace
                    throughout <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Apulia. <reg>by</reg> this bold
                    pledge they prevailed so far as to obtain a treaty —not, however, on equal
                    terms, but such as made them subject to the <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Romans. <reg>after</reg> Apulia had been thoroughly subdued —for Forentum, a
                    strong town, had also fallen into the hands of Junius —the campaign was extended
                    to the Lucanians, from whom, on the sudden arrival of Aemilius the consul,
                    Nerulum was taken by <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> assault. <reg>and</reg>
                    once it had been noised abroad amongst the allies how the affairs of Capua were
                    firmly established by Roman discipline, the Antiates, too, complained that they
                    were living without fixed statutes and without magistrates, and the senate
                    designated the colony's own patrons to draw up laws for it. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Prominent Romans were often invited to
                        act in a semiofficial relation of protectorship to Italian or even to
                        foreign towns. </note>
                    <reg>not</reg> Roman arms alone but also Roman law began to exert a widespread
                    influence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls Gaius Junius Bubulcus and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 316</note> Quintus Aemilius Barbula
                    gave over their legions, at <pb n="p.245"/> the conclusion of the year, not to
                    Spurius Nautius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        316</note> and Marcus Popilius, the consuls at whose election they had
                    presided, but to a dictator —Lucius Aemilius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> latter, with Lucius Fulvius, his master of the horse, laid
                    siege to Saticula, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Saticula was
                        probably on the border between Campania and Samnium, and possibly occupied
                        the same site as the modern S. Agata dei Goti. </note> and by so doing
                    afforded the Samnites a pretext for renewing the war. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans were thus threatened in two quarters: on the one side
                    the Samnites, with a large army which they had mustered to relieve their
                    besieged allies, were encamped at no great distance from the Roman camp; on the
                    other side the Saticulani suddenly threw their gates wide open and charged pell
                    —mell against the outposts of the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>both</reg> hostile armies —each relying rather on the other's help than on
                    any strength of its own —then pressed home their attack, in what soon developed
                    into a general engagement. <reg>but</reg> the dictator, despite the twofold
                    struggle, was protected on both fronts, since he had chosen a position that was
                    difficult to tum, and made his maniples face opposite ways. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>however</reg> , he attacked the sallying party with the greater fury, and,
                    encountering no very sharp resistance, drove them back into the town.
                        <reg>he</reg> then directed his entire line against the Samnites. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> was more resistance here, but though the victory was slow in
                    coming yet it was neither dubious nor partial. <name>The</name> Samnites fled in
                    disorder to their camp, and in the night, putting out their fires, they silently
                    stole away, and relinquishing all hope of saving Saticula, themselves laid siege
                    to Plistica, an ally of Rome, that they might pay the enemy out in their own
                    coin. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> the year had come round, the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 315</note> conduct of the war passed
                    without a break into the <pb n="p.247"/> hands of the dictator Quintus Fabius.
                        <name>The</name> new <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 315</note> consuls, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The men
                        whose names are by so strange an oversight omitted here were L. Papirius
                        Cursor and Q. Publilius Philo, each of whom had thrice held the office.
                    </note> as their predecessors had done, remained in Rome; Fabius took new forces
                    to replace the old, and proceeded to Saticula, to receive the army from
                    Aemilius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> the Samnites had not continued before Plistica, but, summoning
                    fresh troops from home and confiding in their numbers, had pitched their camp on
                    the same spot as before, and were trying to provoke the Romans into giving
                    battle, in the endeavour to divert them from the siege. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> but intensified the dictator's concentration on the enemy's
                    walls, for he deemed the war to consist solely in the attack upon the city, and
                    treated the Samnites with much indifference, save only that he posted out
                    —guards to prevent their making any inroad upon his camp. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> this only made the Samnites the more audacious, and riding again
                    and again up to the rampart, they gave no respite to the Romans. <reg>and</reg>
                    now the enemy were almost in the gateway of the camp, when Quintus Aulius
                    Cerretanus, the master of the horse, without consulting the dictator, sallied
                    out with all his squadrons in a furious charge and drove them off. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> this juncture —though in a type of battle by no means marked by
                    obstinacy — Fortune so used her powers as to bring extraordinary losses on both
                    sides, and on the commanders themselves distinguished deaths. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Samnite general first, indignant at being routed and put to
                    flight from a position he had so boldly occupied, prevailed with his troopers by
                    entreaties and encouragement to renew the conflict; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> against whom, conspicuous amongst his followers as he urged
                    them into battle, the Roman master of the horse rode such a tilt with levelled
                    lance as at one lunge unhorsed and killed <pb n="p.249"/> him. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>yet</reg> the rank and file were not more dismayed <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 315</note> by their leader's death
                    —though it often happens so —than they were angered; and as Aulius rode
                    recklessly on through the enemy's squadrons, all those about him darted their
                    javelins at him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the glory of avenging the Samnite general was given by Heaven in
                    largest measure to his brother, who, wild with grief and rage, dragged down the
                    victorious Roman from his seat and slew him. <reg>indeed</reg> the Samnites
                    almost got possession of the body, which had fallen in the midst of their
                    troops. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the Romans at once dismounted, and the Samnites were forced to do
                    the same; and hurriedly forming up their lines, they began a battle on foot
                    around the bodies of their generals, in which the Romans had easily the better.
                        <reg>so</reg> they rescued the body of Aulius, which they bore back
                    victoriously to their camp, with mingled feelings of sorrow and satisfaction.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Samnites, having lost their commander, and having tried what
                    they could do in a cavalry engagement, gave up Saticula, which they felt was
                    holding out in vain, and returned to the siege of Plistica. <reg>within</reg> a
                    few days' time Saticula had surrendered to the Romans and the Samnites had
                    carried Plistica by assault. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> seat of war was now shifted, and the legions were transferred
                    from Samnium and Apulia to Sora, which had gone over to the Samnites, after
                    putting to death the Roman colonists. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Roman army, by a series of forced marches, undertaken to avenge
                    their slaughtered fellow —citizens and regain the colony, came first upon the
                    ground. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the scouts who had scattered out along the roads reported one
                    after the other that the Samnite legions <pb n="p.251"/> were following and were
                    already close at hand. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 315</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>whereupon</reg> the Romans marched to meet the enemy, and an indecisive
                    battle was fought near Lautulae. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> was not the losses nor the rout of either army that put a stop to
                    the engagement, but darkness, which left them uncertain if they had lost or won.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>i</reg> find in some authorities <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Whom Diodorus follows (xix. lxxii.).</note> that the Romans were defeated
                    in this battle, and that it was here that the master of the horse, Quintus
                    Aulius, lost his life. <reg>to</reg> fill out the term of Aulius they appointed
                    Gaius Fabius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Fasti</name> Capitolini </hi> give his name in full as C. Fabius
                        M. f. N. n. Ambustus, which makes him a brother of the dictator. </note> who
                    marched from Rome with a fresh army. <reg>sending</reg> messengers on ahead to
                    the dictator, he consulted him as to where he should halt, and when, and from
                    what quarter, attack the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> being accurately informed regarding every detail of the dictator's
                    plans, he halted where his army could lie concealed. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> some days after the battle the dictator had kept his soldiers
                    within their works, more like one besieged than a besieger. <reg>then</reg> ,
                    suddenly, he displayed the battle —signal, and thinking it more efficacious for
                    quickening the courage of brave men to leave none of them any hope but in
                    himself, he concealed from his troops the arrival <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> of the master of the horse and his new army, and, as though
                    their only salvation lay in cutting their way through, <quote>
                        <reg>soldiers</reg> , </quote> he said, <quote> we are trapped and have no
                        way of escape save such as victory shall open to us. <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> down the valley of the Liris, through the
                            Samnite army, for the other way was blocked by the town of Sora. </note>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>our</reg> standing camp is sufficiently protected by its rampart, but
                        for lack of provisions is untenable; for every place round about us from
                        which supplies could be brought up has revolted, and even if men wished to
                        help us, the character of the country is against it. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>i</reg> will therefore not beguile you by leaving the camp standing
                        here for you to <pb n="p.253"/> make a refuge, if you fail of victory, as on
                        the former <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            315</note> occasion. <reg>entrenchments</reg> should be secured by arms,
                        not arms by entrenchments. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>let</reg> those have a camp, and retire to it, who have time to prolong
                        the war: as for us, let us shut out all regard for everything but victory.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>forward</reg> against the enemy! <reg>when</reg> the column is outside
                        the rampart, let those who have been ordered to do so fire the camp!
                            <reg>your</reg> losses, men, shall be made good with the spoils of all
                        the revolted peoples round about! </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>inflamed</reg> by the dictator's speech, which pointed to the direst
                    necessity, the soldiers advanced upon the foe; and the mere sight of their
                    blazing camp as they glanced back, though only the nearest tents were set afire
                    — for so the dictator had commanded —was no small whet to their resentment.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> so, charging like madmen, they threw the enemy's ranks into
                    confusion at the first assault; and in the nick of time the master of the horse,
                    who had seen far away the burning camp —which was the signal they had agreed
                    upon —assaulted the enemy from behind. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>being</reg> thus hemmed in, the Samnites fled, as each best might, in
                    different directions; a vast throng huddled up together, in their terror, and
                    blocking each other's way in the confusion, were cut down where they stood.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> enemy's camp was seized and plundered, and the soldiers, laden
                    with the spoils, were led back by the dictator to the Roman camp, rejoicing not
                    so greatly in their victory as because, contrary to their expectation, they
                    found all safe there, except for a trifling part that had been damaged by the
                    flames. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans then returned to Sora; and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 314</note> new consuls, Marcus
                    Poetelius and Gaius Sulpicius, <pb n="p.255"/> took over the army from Fabius
                    the dictator, dismissing <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 314</note> a great part of the veteran troops and bringing in new
                    cohorts to replace them. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The legions
                        had been three years in the field, although some of the soldiers, who had
                        been enlisted to replace those killed or disabled, had not served so long.
                            <name>These</name> latter were retained with the colours and the others
                        were discharged. <name>The</name> word <quote>cohorts</quote> is
                        anachronistic; Livy had perhaps forgotten that the organization by cohorts
                        dated only from the time of Marius. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the city lay in a troublesome position, where the Romans could
                    devise no very certain way of getting at it, and it seemed that victory would
                    either be long in coming, or fraught with fearful risks; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> when a Soran deserter stole out of the town, and picking
                    his way to the Roman sentinels, bade them bring him immediately to the consuls.
                        <reg>arrived</reg> in their presence, he offered to betray the city.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> being questioned how he could accomplish it, he satisfied his
                    interrogators that his plan was not unfeasible, and induced them to withdraw the
                    Roman camp —which was almost in contact with the city walls —to a distance of
                    six miles from the town; for so, he said, the sentinels would be less vigilant
                    in guarding the place, whether by night or day. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> himself on the following night, having directed certain cohorts to
                    seek cover in the woods below the town, took with him ten picked men, whom he
                    conducted over steep and almost impassable ground up to the citadel. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Apparently conceived of as merely an
                        unfortified and (for the time being) unoccupied height. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>here</reg> he had brought together a quantity of missiles out of all
                    proportion to the number of men, besides which there were stones —both those
                    which happened to be lying there, as is usual in rough country, and those which
                    the townsmen had piled up on purpose, for the better protection of the place. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> this height he posted the Romans, and, indicating to them a steep
                    and narrow path which led up from the town to the citadel, lie said, <quote>
                        <reg>from</reg> an ascent like this three men would be enough to keep back a
                        multitude, however numerous: you are not <pb n="p.257"/> only ten, but
                        Romans, and of Romans the very <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 314</note> bravest. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>you</reg> will have the advantage of position and of night, which makes
                        everything loom greater in the eyes of frightened men, because of the
                        obscurity. <reg>as</reg> for me, I will presently strike terror into every
                        heart: do you hold the citadel and watch. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> then ran down, making all the noise he could, as he cried <quote>
                        <reg>to</reg> arms! </quote> and <quote>
                        <reg>help</reg> , help, my countrymen! <name>The</name> citadel has been
                        taken by the enemy! <reg>defend</reg> us! </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <name>These</name> words he shouted as he knocked at the doors of the great, the
                    same to all he met, the same to those who rushed out terrified into the streets.
                        <name>The</name> panic begun by one man was spread by numbers through all
                    the city. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>quaking</reg> with fear, the magistrates dispatched scouts to investigate,
                    and on hearing that armed men, in exaggerated numbers, held the citadel,
                    relinquished all hope of regaining it. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> city was thronged with fugitives, and men who were hardly yet
                    awake and most of them unarmed, began battering down the gates.
                        <reg>through</reg> one of them rushed in the band of Romans, who had started
                    up on hearing the outcry, and now running through the streets, cut down the
                    frightened townsfolk. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Sora</name> was already taken, when the consuls arrived at early dawn, and
                    received the surrender of such as Fortune had spared in the rout and slaughter
                    of the night. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>of</reg> these, two hundred and twenty —five, who were designated on all
                    hands as the authors of the revolt and the hideous massacre of the colonists,
                    they sent to Rome in chains; the rest they left unharmed in Sora, only setting a
                    garrison over them. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>all</reg> those who were taken to Rome were scourged and beheaded in the
                    Forum, to the great joy of the commons, whom it most <pb n="p.259"/> nearly
                    concerned that the people who were sent out <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 314</note> here and there to colonies
                    should in every case be protected. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls on leaving Sora conducted a campaign against the lands
                    and cities of the Ausones. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Ausones is
                        the Greek name for the Aurunci.</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> everything had been disturbed by the coming of the Samnites, when
                    the battle was fought at Lautulae, and conspiracies had been formed all about
                    Campania. <reg>even</reg> Capua itself did not escape accusation; nay, the
                    investigation actually led to Rome and to some of the prominent men there.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the Ausones were brought into subjection by the betrayal of their
                    cities, as had happened in the case of Sora. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>from</reg> Ausona, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Site
                        unknown.</note> from Minturnae, and from Vescia, twelve young nobles, having
                    conspired to betray their cities, came to the consuls, and explained to them
                    that their countrymen, after long looking forward to the coming of the Samnites,
                    had no sooner heard of the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> battle at
                    Lautulae than they had concluded the Romans vanquished and had aided the
                    Samnites with men and arms; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that since the
                    expulsion of the Samnites from that region, they had been living in an uncertain
                    kind of peace, not closing their gates upon the Romans, lest to do so should
                    invite attack, but determined none the less to close them in case an army should
                    approach; and that in that wavering state of mind they could be surprised and
                    overcome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>by</reg> their advice the camp was moved up nearer and soldiers were
                    simultaneously sent round to the three towns. <reg>some</reg> of these, in
                    armour, were to lie in ambush in places near the walls, while others, wearing
                    the toga and concealing swords under their dress, were to enter the cities, a
                    little before day, by the open gates. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.261"/>
                    <name>These</name> latter fell upon the watchmen, at the same <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 314</note> time
                    making a signal to their fellows in armour to rush in from their ambuscade.
                        <reg>thus</reg> the gates were captured, and three towns were taken in one
                    hour and by one device. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> because the leaders were not present when the attack was made,
                    there was no limit to the slaughter, and the Ausonian nation was wiped out
                    —though it was not quite clear that it was guilty of defection —exactly as if it
                    had contended in an internecine war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> the same year Luceria, betraying its Roman garrison to the enemy,
                    passed into the possession of the Samnites; but the traitors did not long go
                    unpunished for their deed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>not</reg> far away there was a Roman army, which captured the city
                    —situated as it was in a plain —at the first attack. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Lucerini and Samnites were shown no quarter, and resentment ran
                    so high that even in Rome, when the senate was debating the dispatch of
                    colonists to Luceria, there were many who voted to destroy the town. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>besides</reg> men's hate, which was very bitter against those whom they had
                    twice subdued, there was also the remoteness of the place, which made them
                    shrink from condemning fellow —citizens to an exile so far from home and
                    surrounded by such hostile tribes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>however</reg> , the proposal to send colonists prevailed, and twenty —five
                    hundred were sent. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>in</reg> that year also of general disloyalty to the Romans, there were
                    secret conspiracies of the nobles, even at Capua. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> With this sentence Livy resumes the narrative begun in
                        Chap. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> their being reported to the senate, the danger was by no means
                    minimized, but tribunals of enquiry were voted and it was determined to appoint
                    a dictator to conduct the <pb n="p.263"/> investigations. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>Gaius</name> Maenius was nominated, and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 314</note> named Marcus Folius master
                    of the horse. <name>Great</name> was the terror inspired by that magistracy; and
                    so, whether from fear or a guilty conscience, the Calavii, Ovius and Novius, who
                    had headed the conspiracy, before informations could be lodged against them with
                    the dictator, avoided trial by a death which was undoubtedly self —inflicted. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>after</reg> that, the field of enquiry at Capua having been exhausted, the
                    proceedings were transferred to Rome, on the theory that the senate had ordered
                    an investigation, not of specified individuals in Capua, but, in general, of all
                    who had anywhere combined or conspired against the State; and that cabals for
                    obtaining magistracies had been made against the common weal. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> enquiry began to take a wider range, in respect both of charges
                    and of persons, and the dictator was nothing loath that there should be no limit
                    to the jurisdiction of his court. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>certain</reg> nobles were accordingly impeached, and on appealing to the
                    tribunes found none to help them by stopping the informations. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> nobles then declared —not those alone at whom the charge was
                    levelled, but all of them conjointly —that this accusation did not lie against
                    the nobility, to whom, unless fraudulently obstructed, the road to office lay
                    wide open, but rather against upstart politicians; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> that in fact the dictator and the master of the horse
                    themselves were fitter to be tried on such a charge than to act as judges, and
                    they would find this to be so the moment they resigned their places. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>then</reg> indeed Maenius, more mindful now of his reputation than of his
                    authority, came forward and addressed the assembly. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        <reg>you</reg> are all of you, </quote> he <pb n="p.265"/> said, <quote>
                        <name>Quirites</name> , aware of my past life, and this very <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 314</note> office
                        which has been conferred upon me is witness to my innocence; for it was
                        necessary to select as dictator for the administration of judicial
                        investigations, not the most distinguished soldier —as has often been done
                        at other times, when some crisis in the state required it —but the man who
                        had lived a life most aloof from these cabals. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/>
                        <reg>but</reg> since certain noblemen —for what cause it is better that you
                        should form your own opinion than that I as magistrate should affirm
                        anything not fully ascertained —have in the first place striven with might
                        and main to defeat these very investigations; <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> and then, finding themselves not strong enough to
                        escape pleading their cause in court, have sought refuge, patricians though
                        they are, in the safeguards of their adversaries —the appeal, I mean, and
                        the help of the tribunes; — <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> and since at
                        last, repulsed in that quarter, they have fallen upon us —so much safer does
                        any course appear to them than to try to vindicate their innocence and have
                        not blushed, though private citizens, to demand the impeachment of a
                        dictator; <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> —in order that all gods and men
                        may know that they are attempting even impossibilities to avoid accounting
                        for their lives, whereas I am ready to face their charge and to offer myself
                        to my enemies to be tried, I hereby resign the dictator's authority.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        <reg>you</reg> , consuls, I beseech, if the task shall be devolved upon you
                        by the senate, that you begin your investigations with me and with Marcus
                        Folius here, that it may be seen that we are safe from these accusations by
                        reason of our innocence, not by reason of the awe inspired by our office. </quote>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> then resigned as dictator, and so at once did Folius as master of
                    the horse. <reg>they</reg> were <pb n="p.267"/> the first to go to trial before
                    the consuls —for to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        314</note> these the senate had given the matter in charge — and, against
                    the testimony of the nobles, were gloriously acquitted. <milestone n="21"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>Publilius</name> Philo, too, after all his famous achievements at home and
                    in war, and after having repeatedly held the highest offices, had incurred the
                    hate of the nobility, and was brought to trial and acquitted. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In <date when="-0339">339 B.C.</date>
                        <name>Philo</name> had proposed three democratic laws, which won him the
                        enmity of the patricians. <reg>see</reg> viii. xii. 14-16. </note>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the inquisition, as often happens, had the vigour to deal with
                    illustrious defendants no longer than while its novelty lasted; after that it
                    began to descend to the baser sort, until it was finally put down by the cabals
                    and factions which it had been instituted to oppose. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> rumour of these events, and still more the hope of a Campanian
                    insurrection, which had been the aim of the conspirators, recalled the Samnites
                    from Apulia, on which their attention had been fixed, to Caudium; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> in the hope that, being there so near, they might, if
                    any disturbance should afford the opportunity, seize Capua from the Romans; and
                    to Caudium came the consuls, with a powerful force. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>both</reg> armies at first held back, each on its own side of the pass, for
                    either would have been at a disadvantage in advancing against the other.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>then</reg> the Samnites made a short detour over open ground, and brought
                    their army down to the plain, where the hostile forces were, for the first time,
                    encamped in sight of one another. <reg>some</reg> skirmishing followed, in which
                    both sides made trial more often of their cavalry than their foot. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans were not dissatisfied either with the outcome of these
                    brushes or with the delays by which the campaign was protracted. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>to</reg> the Samnite leaders, on the contrary, it appeared that <pb
                        n="p.269"/> their forces were daily diminishing with petty <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 314</note> losses,
                    and were wasting away with the prolongation of the war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> accordingly made ready for a general engagement, dividing their
                    cavalry between the wings, with orders to pay more attention to the camp, to
                    prevent any attack upon it, than to the battle; for the infantry would
                    sufficiently safeguard the line. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>of</reg> the consuls, Sulpicius took up his post on the right wing,
                    Poetelius on the left. <name>The</name> formation on the right was spread out
                    over a considerable distance, and on that wing the Samnites, too, were drawn up
                    in ranks of little depth, either meaning to tum the Romans' flank, or to keep
                    their own from being turned. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> troops on the left, besides being drawn up in closer order, had
                    received an accession to their strength from a plan conceived on the spur of the
                    moment by Poetelius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> those subsidiary cohorts which were wont to be kept fresh in
                    reserve, to meet the chance needs of a long engagement, he sent immediately into
                    the fighting line; and by using all his strength at once, he forced the enemy
                    back at the first assault. <reg>as</reg> the Samnite infantry wavered, their
                    cavalry moved up to support them. <reg>but</reg> while they came obliquely
                    onward, in the interval between the armies, the Roman cavalry charged them at
                    the gallop, confounding the ranks and the formations of horse and foot, until
                    they had routed the entire army at that point. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Samnite right. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> that wing Sulpicius was present, as well as Poetelius, to animate
                    the soldiers, for when the shouting arose upon the left, he had ridden over
                    there, leaving his own men, who were not yet come to grips with <pb n="p.271"/>
                    the enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> perceiving his colleague's victory <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 314</note> to be safe, he left him
                    and rode off with twelve hundred men to his own wing. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> he found affairs in a different posture; the Romans had been
                    driven out of their position, and the victorious enemy were charging their
                    disordered ranks. <reg>but</reg> all was quickly changed by the arrival of the
                    consul. <reg>for</reg> the sight of their general revived the spirits of the
                    soldiers, and the brave men who followed him were a greater succour than their
                    numbers indicated; and the tidings of their comrades' victory, which they soon
                    saw for themselves, restored the battle. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>presently</reg> the Romans had begun to conquer all along the line, while
                    the Samnites, giving up the struggle, were massacred or made prisoners, except
                    those who fled to Maleventum, the city which is now called Beneventum. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The city, which was a Greek colony, was
                        called <foreign xml:lang="greek">Malovei/s,</foreign> which meant <quote>
                            <reg>sheeptown</reg>
                        </quote> (or, perhaps, <quote>
                            <reg>appletown</reg>
                        </quote> ). The Romans corrupted the accusative case, <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">Malove/nta,</foreign> to <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Maleventum</name> , </hi> which they regarded as derived from <hi
                            rend="italics">male</hi> and <hi rend="italics">,venire,</hi> and then,
                        to avoid the omen, changed it to <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Beneventum</name>
                        </hi> when they planted a colony there, <date when="-0268">268 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                    <reg>tradition</reg> avers that some thirty thousand Samnites were slain or
                    captured. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls, who had won a brilliant <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 313</note> victory, at once marched
                    away to lay siege <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> to Bovianum, where they
                    remained in winter quarters, until the new consuls, Lucius Papirius Cursor (for
                    the fifth time) and Gaius Junius Bubulcus (for the second) appointed Gaius
                    Poetelius dictator, who, with Marcus Folius as master of horse, took over the
                    command. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Poetelius</name> , hearing that the citadel of Fregellae was captured by
                    the Samnites, raised the siege of Bovianum and proceeded to Fregellae.
                        <reg>having</reg> got possession of the place without a struggle —for the
                    Samnites fled from it in the night —he installed a strong garrison there, and
                    leaving Fregellae, marched back into Campania, for the purpose, chiefly, of
                    winning back Nola by force of <pb n="p.273"/> arms. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>within</reg> its walls, as the dictator drew near, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 313</note> the whole Samnite
                    population and the Nolani of the country —side had taken refuge. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>after</reg> examining the position of the city, the dictator, in order to
                    open up approaches to the walls, caused all the buildings round them —and the
                    tract was densely inhabited —to be burnt. <reg>not</reg> very long after this
                    Nola was captured, whether by Poetelius the dictator or the consul Gaius Junius
                    —for the story is told both ways. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>those</reg> who ascribe the honour of capturing Nola to the consul, add
                    that Atina and Calatia were won by the same man, but that Poetelius was made
                    dictator on the outbreak of a pestilence, that lie might drive the nail. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the practice of driving a nail in
                        the wall of the shrine of Minerva in the great temple of Jupiter on the
                        Capitol, see vii. iii. <reg>but</reg> the writers referred to in the present
                        passage are probably mistaken, as the <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Fasti</name> Capitolini </hi> say that Poetelius was made dictator
                            <hi rend="italics">rei gerundae causa.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>colonies</reg> were planted in that same year at Suessa and Pontiae.
                        <name>Suessa</name> had belonged to the Aurunci; Volscians had inhabited
                    Pontiae, an island which lay within sight of their own coast. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> senate also passed a resolution that a colony be sent out to
                    Interamna Sucasina, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So called (or
                        sometimes Lirenas) to distinguish it from two other towns called Interamna
                        —a name which is derived from the two streams (in this case the Casinus and
                        the Liris) at whose confluence the town was situated. </note> but it was
                    left for the next consuls, Marcus Valerius and Publius Decius, to appoint the
                    three commissioners and send out four thousand settlers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> war with the Samnites was practically <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 312</note> ended, but the Roman
                    senators had not yet ceased to be concerned about it, when the rumour of an
                    Etruscan war sprang up. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> those days there was no other race —setting apart the risings of
                    the Gauls <pb n="p.275"/> —whose arms were more dreaded, not only because <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 312</note> their
                    territory lay so near, but also because of their <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> numbers. <reg>accordingly</reg> , while the other consul was in Samnium,
                    dispatching the last remnants of the war, Publius Decius, who was very sick and
                    had stopped behind in Rome, in pursuance of a senatorial resolution named Gaius
                    Sulpicius Longus dictator, who appointed Gaius Junius Bubulcus to be his master
                    of the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> horse. <name>Sulpicius</name> , as the
                    gravity of the circumstances required, administered the oath to all those of
                    military age, and made ready arms and whatever else the situation called for,
                    with the utmost assiduity. <reg>yet</reg> he was not so carried away with these
                    great preparations as to plan for an offensive war, clearly intending to remain
                    inactive, unless the Etruscans should first take the <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> field. <reg>but</reg> the Etruscans followed the same
                    policy, preparing for war but preventing it from breaking out.
                        <reg>neither</reg> side went beyond their own frontiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>noteworthy</reg> , too, in that year was the censorship of Appius Claudius
                    and Gaius Plautius; but the name of Appius was of happier memory with succeeding
                    generations, because he built a road, and conveyed a stream of water into the
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> City. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The road was the Via Appia, which ran from Rome to
                        Capua, and was later extended to Beneventum and, finally, to Brundisium.
                            <name>The</name> aqueduct brought water from a point between seven and
                        eight miles out, on the road to Gabii, and supplied the Circus Maximus and
                        other low —lying parts of the City. </note>
                    <name>These</name> undertakings he carried out by himself, since his colleague
                    had resigned, overcome with shame at the disgraceful and invidious manner in
                    which Appius revised the list <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> of senators; and
                    Appius, exhibiting the obstinacy which had marked his family from the earliest
                    days, exercised the <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> censorship alone.
                        <reg>it</reg> was Appius, too, by whose warranty the Potitian clan, with
                    whom the priesthood of Hercules at the Ara Maxima <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> An ancient altar erected in honour of Hercules.
                            <name>The</name> origin of the cult is described at I. vii. 3-15.
                    </note> was hereditary, taught the ritual of that sacrifice to public slaves,
                        <pb n="p.277"/> in order to devolve the service <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> upon them. <reg>tradition</reg>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 312</note> relates
                    that after this a strange thing happened, and one that might well give men pause
                    ere they disturb the established order of religious ceremonies. <reg>for</reg>
                    whereas at that time there were twelve families of the Potitii, and grown men to
                    the number of thirty, within the year they had perished, every man, and the
                    stock had <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> become extinct; and not only did
                    the name of the Potitii die out, but even the censor, by the unforgetting ire of
                    the gods, was a few years later stricken blind. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> so the consuls of the following year, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 311</note> Gaius Junius Bubulcus (for
                    the third time) and Quintus Aemilius Barbula (for the second), complained to the
                    people, at the outset of their administration, that the senatorial order had
                    been depraved by the improper choice of members, in which better men had been
                    passed over than some that had been appointed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> then gave notice that they should ignore that list, which had
                    been drawn up with no distinction of right and wrong, in a spirit of favouritism
                    and caprice; and proceeded to call the roll of the senate in the order which had
                    been in use before Appius Claudius and Gaius Plautius were censors. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> that year, also, two commands —both military —began to be
                    conferred by the people; for it was enacted, first, that sixteen tribunes of the
                    soldiers should be chosen by popular vote for the four legions, whereas
                    previously these places had been for the most part in the gift of dictators and
                    consuls, very few being left to popular suffrage <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For an instance of the popular election of <hi
                            rend="italics">tribuni militum</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> vii. v. 9. he plan adopted in 311 seems to have
                        given the people the right to elect four of the six tribunes assigned to
                        each legion, or sixteen in all. <reg>soon</reg> after Livy wrote these words
                        another change was made and the emperor thenceforth appointed all military
                        tribunes. </note> ; secondly, that the people should likewise elect two
                    naval commissioners to have charge of equipping and refitting the fleet.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> former of <pb n="p.279"/> these measures was proposed by the
                    tribunes of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        311</note> plebs Lucius Atilius and Gaius Marcius; the latter by Marcus
                    Decius, another tribune of the plebs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>i</reg> should omit, as an incident hardly worth narrating, a little thing
                    that happened in that same year, but that it seemed to concern religion.
                        <name>The</name> flute —players, angry at having been forbidden by the last
                    censors to hold their feast, according to old custom, in the temple of Jupiter,
                    went off to Tibur in a body, so that there was no one in the City to pipe at
                    sacrifices. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>troubled</reg> by the religious aspect of the case, the senate dispatched
                    representatives to the Tiburtines, requesting them to use their best endeavours
                    to restore these men to Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Tiburtines courteously undertook to do so; and sending for the
                    pipers to their senate —house, urged them to return. <reg>when</reg> they found
                    it impossible to persuade them, they employed a ruse, not ill —adapted to the
                    nature of the men. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> a holiday various citizens invited parties of the pipers to their
                    houses, on the pretext of celebrating the feast with music. <reg>there</reg>
                    they plied them with wine, which people of that profession are generally greedy
                    of, until they got them stupefied. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> this condition they threw them, fast asleep, into waggons and
                    carried them away to Rome; nor did the pipers perceive what had taken place
                    until daylight found them —still suffering from the debauch —in the waggons,
                    which had been left standing in the Forum. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> people then flocked about them and prevailed with them to
                    remain. <reg>they</reg> were permitted on three days in every year to roam the
                    City in festal robes, making music and enjoying the licence that is now
                    customary, and to such <pb n="p.281"/> as should play at sacrifices was given
                    again the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        311</note> privilege of banqueting in the temple. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The story of the secession of the flute —players is
                        found also in Ovid, <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Fasti</name> , </hi> vi. 651 ff., and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>quaestiones</reg> Romanae, </hi> 55. The three days (the so —called
                            <quote>lesser Quinquatrus</quote> ) were June 13th, 14th, 15th, and were
                        a festival peculiar to the guild of pipers. </note>
                    <name>These</name> incidents occurred while men were preoccupied with two mighty
                    wars. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls divided the commands between them: to Junius the lot
                    assigned the Samnites, to Aemilius the new war with Etruria. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> Samnium the Roman garrison at Cluviae, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The site of Cluviae is not known.</note> which had
                    defended itself successfully against assault, was starved into submission.
                        <name>The</name> Samnites, having scourged their prisoners in brutal
                    fashion, put them to death, although they had surrendered. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>incensed</reg> by this act of cruelty, Junius felt that nothing should take
                    precedence over an attack on Cluviae. <reg>he</reg> carried the place by storm
                    on the day he arrived before it, and slew all the grown —up males. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>from</reg> there he led his victorious army to Bovianum. <reg>this</reg>
                    was the capital of the Pentrian Samnites, a very wealthy city and very rich in
                    arms and men. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>against</reg> this town the soldiers were not so exasperated, but the hope
                    of plunder spurred them on to capture it. <reg>and</reg> so there was less
                    severity shown to the enemy, but there was almost more booty carried out than
                    was ever collected from all the rest of Samnium, and the whole of it was
                    generously made over to the soldiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> the conquering arms of the Romans might now no longer be
                    withstood by any embattled host or camp or city, the leaders of the Samnites all
                    eagerly directed their attention to the seeking out a place for an ambush, on
                    the chance that the army might somehow be permitted to disperse for plundering,
                    and so be surprised and surrounded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>certain</reg> rustic deserters and prisoners, some falling into the
                    consul's hands by accident and some on purpose, <pb n="p.283"/> by giving all
                    the same account —and a true one, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 311</note> too —of enormous flocks that had been brought
                    together in an inaccessible mountain meadow, persuaded him to lead thither his
                    legions in light marching order to seize the booty. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> a great army of the enemy had secretly beset the ways, and
                    seeing that the Romans had entered the pass, rose up suddenly with much din and
                    shouting and fell upon them unawares. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> first the unexpectedness of the attack occasioned some
                    trepidation, while the soldiers were putting on their armour and piling their
                    packs in the midst. <reg>afterwards</reg> , when everyone had got rid of his
                    encumbrance and had armed himself, they began to assemble from every side about
                    their standards. <reg>in</reg> the course of a long training in the army they
                    had become familiar with their places, and formed a line of their own accord,
                    without anyone's direction. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consul, riding up to the place where the fighting was most
                    critical, leaped down from his horse, and called on Jupiter and Mars and the
                    other gods to witness that he had come there seeking no glory for himself, but
                    only booty for his soldiers: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> his sole fault,
                    he said, was a too great desire to enrich his men; from this disgrace nothing
                    could save him but their courage. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>only</reg> let them all unite in singleness of purpose to assail an enemy
                    conquered in battle, stripped of his camp, deprived of his cities, and pinning
                    his last hopes to the treachery of an ambuscade, were his trust was in his
                    position, not in arms. <reg>but</reg> what position was there now, he demanded,
                    too strong for Roman valour to overwhelm? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> reminded them of Fregellae's citadel and Sora's, and all the
                    places where they had triumphed over disadvantage of ground. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.285"/>
                <p>
                    <reg>roused</reg> by these words, the soldiers disregarded <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 311</note> every obstacle and
                    advanced against the battle —line which their enemies had formed above them.
                        <reg>there</reg> was a little hard fighting there, while the column was
                    mounting the slope; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> but as soon as the
                    foremost companies had reached the plateau at the top, and the soldiers
                    perceived that their line was now established on level ground, the panic was
                    straightway turned upon the waylayers, who fled, dispersing and throwing down
                    their arms, in search of those very lurking —places where a little while before
                    they had concealed themselves. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the ground which they had sought out for the difficulties it
                    presented to an enemy caught the Samnites themselves in a trap of their own
                    devising. <reg>and</reg> so, very few were able to get off; about twenty
                    thousand men were slain; and the victorious Romans struck out this way and that
                    to collect the booty of cattle which the enemy had thrown in their way. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Fasti</name> Capitolini </hi> record that Junius triumphed over
                        the Samnites on August 5th ( <hi rend="italics">C.I. L.,</hi> I2, p. 45).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>while</reg> these events were taking place in Samnium, all the peoples of
                    Etruria, except the Arretini, had already armed, and beginning with the siege of
                    Sutrium, a city in alliance with the Romans, and forming as it were the key to
                    Etruria, had set on foot a tremendous war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>thither</reg> the other consul, Aemilius, came with an army, to relieve the
                    blockade of the allies. <reg>as</reg> the Romans came up, the Sutrini obligingly
                    brought provisions to their camp, which was formed before the city. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Etruscans spent the first day in deliberating whether to
                    accelerate the war or to draw it out. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> the following day, their generals having decided on the swifter
                    plan in preference to the safer, the <pb n="p.287"/> signal for battle was
                    displayed at sunrise and their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 311</note> men in fighting array marched out upon the
                    field. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> this was reported to the consul, he at once commanded the word
                    to be passed round that the men should breakfast, and having recruited their
                    strength with food, should then arm. <name>The</name> order was obeyed; and the
                    consul, seeing them equipped and ready, bade advance the standards beyond the
                    rampart, and drew up his troops a little way off from the enemy. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> some time both sides stood fast, observing one another closely,
                    each waiting for the other to give a cheer and begin to fight, and the sun had
                    begun his downward course in the heavens ere a missile was hurled on either
                    side. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>then</reg> the Etruscans, that they might not withdraw without
                    accomplishing their purpose, set up a shout, and with sound of trumpets advanced
                    their ensigns. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans were equally prompt to begin the battle.
                        <name>The</name> two armies rushed together with great fury, the enemy
                    having a superiority in numbers, the Romans in bravery. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>Victory</name> hung in the balance and many perished on both sides,
                    including all the bravest, and the event was not decided until the Roman second
                    line came up with undiminished vigour to relieve their exhausted comrades in the
                    first; and the Etruscans, whose fighting line was supported by no fresh
                    reserves, all fell in front of their standards and around them. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> would never in any battle have been more bloodshed or less
                    running away, but when the Etruscans were resolved to die, the darkness shielded
                    them, so that the victors gave over fighting before the vanquished. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> sun had set when the recall was sounded, and in the night both
                    armies retired to their camps. </p>
                <pb n="p.289"/>
                <p>
                    <reg>thereafter</reg> there was nothing done that year at <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 311</note> Sutrium worth recording.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> enemy had lost their whole first line in a single engagement,
                    and had only their reserves remaining, who barely sufficed to garrison their
                    camp; whilst the Romans had so many wounded that more died of their hurts after
                    the battle than had fallen on the field. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>Quintus</name> Fabius, consul in the following <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> year, took over the
                    campaign at Sutrium. <reg>for</reg> colleague he was given Gaius Marcius
                    Rutulus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Fabius</name> brought up replacements from Rome, and a new army came from
                    Etruria to reinforce the enemy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> a great many years now there had been no contests between the
                    patrician magistrates and the tribunes, when a dispute —arose through that
                    family which was fated, as it seemed, to wrangle with the tribunes and with the
                    plebs. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Appius</name> Claudius the censor, on the expiration of the eighteen
                    months which had been fixed by the Aemilian law <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <date when="-0434">434 B.C.</date> (iv. xxiv. 5). </note> as the limit of
                    the censorship, although his colleague Gaius Plautius had abdicated, could
                    himself by no compulsion be prevailed upon to do likewise. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> was Publius Sempronius, a tribune of the people, who commenced an
                    action to confine the censorship to its legal limits —an action no less just
                    than popular, and as welcome to every aristocrat as to the common people.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>having</reg> repeatedly read out the Aemilian law, and praised its author,
                    Mamercus Aemilius the dictator, for confining the censorship —which had until
                    then been tenable for five years and was proving despotic by reason of the long
                    continuance of its authority —within <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the space
                    of a year and a half, he said, <quote>
                        <reg>come</reg> , tell us, Appius Claudius, what <pb n="p.291"/> you would
                        have done had you been censor at the <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> time when Gaius Furius
                        and Marcus Geganius were censors. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Appius</name> replied that the tribune's question had no particular
                    bearing upon his own case; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> for even though the
                    Aemilian law had bound those censors in whose term of office it had been passed,
                    because the people had enacted the law after their election to the censorship
                    and their latest enactment was always the effective law, yet neither himself nor
                    any one of those who had been chosen censors subsequently to the passage of that
                    law could have been bound by it. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Appius held that, whereas the election of Furius and Geganius for a period
                        of five years had been set aside by the Aemilian law, which was then the
                        latest enactment on the subject and so replaced any earlier one,
                        nevertheless all those who were elected subsequently derived their powers
                        from still later enactments, by which in its tum the Aemilian law was
                        superseded. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>while</reg> Appius raised these quibbles, but found no one to support him, <quote>
                        <reg>behold</reg> , Quirites, </quote> said Sempronius, "the descendant of
                    that Appius, who having been elected decemvir for one year, himself declared his
                    own election for a second year, and in the third, although a private citizen,
                    with neither his own nor another's warrant of election, retained <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> the fasces and authority, and relinquished not his
                    hold on the magistracy until he was overwhelmed by his ill —gotten, ill
                    —administered, and ill —continued powers. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For the story of the Decemvir, see III. xxxiii
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> —lviii. </note>
                    <reg>it</reg> was this same family, Quirites, under compulsion of whose violence
                    and abuse you banished yourselves from your native City and occupied the Sacred
                    Mount <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">II. xxxii. 2.</note> ; the same
                    against which <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> you provided yourselves with
                    the help of tribunes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">II. xxxiii.
                        1-3.</note> ; the same, because of which two armies of you encamped upon the
                    Aventine <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">III. l.13, and li. 10.</note>
                    ; the same that has ever attacked the laws restricting usury and throwing open
                    the public <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> lands. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">II. xxix. 9; xliv. 1; Ixi. 1; vi. xl. 11.</note>
                    <reg>this</reg> same <pb n="p.293"/> family broke off marriages between
                    patricians and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        310</note> plebeians <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">IV. i.
                        vi.</note> ; this same family blocked the path of the plebeians to curule
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> offices. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> IV. vi. 7. </note>
                    <reg>it</reg> is a name that is far more hostile to your liberty than that of
                    the Tarquinii. <reg>so</reg> , Appius Claudius! <reg>though</reg> it is now a
                    hundred years since Mamercus Aemilius was dictator, and in that time we have had
                    all these censors, high —born and valiant men, has never one of them inspected
                    the Twelve <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Tables? <reg>has</reg> none of them
                    known that the law was that which the people had last enacted? <reg>nay</reg> ,
                    all of them knew it; and they obeyed the Aemilian law in preference to that
                    ancient ordinance which governed the first elections of censors, precisely
                    because it was the latest which the people had enacted, and <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> because in a conflict of two laws the old is ever
                    superseded by the new. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> " <reg>or</reg> will this be your contention,
                    Appius, that the people is not bound by the Aemilian law? <reg>or</reg> that the
                    people is bound, but that you alone are exempt? <name>The</name> Aemilian law
                    bound those violent censors Gaius Furius and Marcus Geganius, who showed what
                    mischief that magistracy could accomplish in the state, when, in their rage at
                    the abridgment of their powers, they reduced Mamercus Aemilius, the foremost man
                    of his time in war and peace, to the lowest class of <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> citizens; it bound all the censors who succeeded them, for
                    the period of a hundred years; it binds Gaius Plautius, your colleague, who was
                    given the office under the same auspices and with the same rights as <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> yourself. <reg>or</reg> did the people not make
                    Plautius censor as one who had been elected with the fullest rights?
                        <reg>are</reg> you the sole exception in whose case this holds, as a unique
                    and peculiar <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.295"/> privilege? <reg>whom</reg> , pray, could men elect as king <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> for
                    sacrifice? <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">I. ii. 1-2</note>
                    <reg>he</reg> will seize on the title of sovereignty, and assert that he has
                    been chosen as one elected with fullest rights to be king at Rome.
                        <reg>who</reg> , think you, will be content with six months as dictator; who
                    with five days as <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> interrex? <reg>whom</reg>
                    would you be so rash as to make dictator for the purpose of driving the nail or
                    celebrating games? <reg>how</reg> dull and lumpish must those men seem to
                    Appius, who after accomplishing great feats resigned the post of dictator within
                    twenty days, or laid down the reins of office because of a flaw in their
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> election! <reg>why</reg> should I cite
                    antiquity? <reg>recently</reg> , within these ten years, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy has himself put the dictatorship of Maenius in the
                        year 314. He is probably following another annalist here whose account (like
                        that of the <hi rend="italics">
                            <name>Fasti</name> Capitolini </hi> ) assigned it to 320. </note> Gaius
                    Maenius the dictator, for conducting an inquisition with more severity than was
                    safe for certain great men, was accused by his ill —wishers of being tainted
                    with that very felony which he was searching out, and abdicated the
                    dictatorship, that he might face the charge as a private <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> citizen. <reg>far</reg> be it from me to require such self
                    —denial of you! <reg>fall</reg> not away from the most imperious and proud of
                    families; quit not your magistracy one day, one hour, sooner than you must; only
                    see that you overstep not the appointed <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    limit. <reg>is</reg> it enough to add a day, or a month, to his censorship?
                        <reg>three</reg> years,' quoth he, and six months beyond the time permitted
                    by the Aemilian law will I administer the censorship, and administer it alone.'
                        <reg>surely</reg> this begins to look like <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                    /> monarchy! </p>
                <p> " <reg>or</reg> will you substitute a colleague for the other, though even in a
                    dead man's place such substitution is forbidden by <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> religion? <reg>you</reg> are not satisfied forsooth with
                    having in your scrupulous exercise of a censor's powers diverted the service of
                    our most <pb n="p.297"/> ancient cult, the only one inaugurated by the god <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> himself in
                    whose honour it is observed, from the priesthood of the most exalted nobles to
                    the ministry of <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> slaves; it was not enough
                    that a family more ancient than the beginnings of this City, and sanctified by
                    the entertainment of the immortal gods, should through you and your censorship
                    be within a year uprooted and <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> destroyed; no,
                    you must needs involve the entire state in such heinous guilt <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The guilt of unlawfully prolonging his
                        censorship.</note> as even to name is an omen that fills my mind with
                        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> dread. <name>The</name> city was captured
                    in that lustrum when, on the death of his colleague Gaius Julius, Lucius
                    Papirius Cursor, to avoid having to vacate his office, caused Marcus Cornelius
                    Maluginensis to be substituted in the room of the dead man. <reg>and</reg> how
                    much more moderate, Appius, was his ambition than <milestone n="22"
                        unit="section"/> yours! <name>The</name> censorship of Lucius Papirius was
                    neither a sole one nor one prolonged beyond the legally established term; yet he
                    found none to follow his example; all succeeding censors have abdicated on the
                    death of a colleague. <reg>but</reg> you neither the expiration of your time
                    restrains nor the fact that your colleague has resigned, nor the law, nor a
                    sense of decency: you reckon worth in terms of pride, of recklessness, of
                    contempt for gods and <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> men. </p>
                <p>
                    <quote>
                        <reg>for</reg> my own part, Appius Claudius, when I think of the dignity of
                        that office you have held and the reverence attaching to it, I could wish
                        that I might spare you not only personal violence but even an ungentle
                            <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> word; but your stubbornness and pride
                        have compelled me to say what I have so far said, and unless you obey the
                        Aemilian law, I shall order you to <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                        prison; nor, seeing that our forefathers have ordained that in the election
                        of censors, if either fall <pb n="p.299"/> short of the legal vote, <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> No one was held to be elected
                            unless he had received the votes of an absolute majority of the
                            centuries. </note> the election shall be put off <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> and the other not be
                        declared elected, will I now suffer you, who cannot be elected as sole
                        censor, to administer the censorship alone. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>having</reg> uttered these and similar remonstrances, he ordered the censor
                    to be arrested and carried off to prison. <reg>six</reg> tribunes approved the
                    action of their colleague: three protected Appius on his appeal, and, greatly to
                    the indignation of all classes, he continued as sole censor. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>during</reg> the progress of this affair in Rome, the Etruscans were
                    already laying siege to Sutrium; and the consul Fabius, leading his army along
                    the foot of the mountains to relieve the allies, and, if in any way practicable,
                    to attack the works of the besiegers, encountered the enemy drawn up in line of
                    battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> plain spreading out below him revealed to the consul their
                    exceeding strength; and in order to make up for his own deficiency in numbers by
                    the advantage of position, he altered slightly his line of march, so as to mount
                    the hills —which were rough and covered with stones —and there turned and faced
                    the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Etruscans, forgetting everything but their numbers, in which
                    alone they trusted, entered the combat with such haste and eagerness that they
                    cast away their missiles in order to come the sooner to close quarters, and
                    drawing their swords rushed at the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans, on the contrary, fell to pelting them, now with
                    javelins and now with stones, of which latter the ground itself provided a good
                    supply; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and even such of the Etruscans as were
                    not wounded were confused by the blows that rattled down on their helms and
                    shields. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> was no easy matter to get close enough <pb n="p.301"/> for
                    fighting hand to hand, and they had no javelins <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> for long —range work.
                        <reg>there</reg> they stood, exposed to missiles, with no adequate cover of
                    any sort, and as some of them gave ground and the line began to waver and be
                    unsteady, the Roman first and second lines, giving a fresh cheer, charged them,
                    sword in hand. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>their</reg> onset was too much for the Etruscans, who faced about and fled
                    headlong towards their camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the Roman cavalry, riding obliquely across the plain, presented
                    themselves in front of the fugitives, who then abandoned the attempt to reach
                    their camp and sought the mountains; from which they made their way in a body,
                    unarmed and suffering from their wounds, to the Ciminian Forest.
                        <name>The</name> Romans, having slain many thousand Etruscans and captured
                    eight —and —thirty standards, took possession also of the enemy's camp, with a
                    very large booty. <reg>they</reg> then began to consider the feasibility of a
                    pursuit. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> those days the Ciminian Forest was more impassable and appalling
                    than were lately the wooded defiles of Germany, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy is probably thinking of the German campaigns of
                        Caesar in 55 and 53, and of Agrippa in <date when="-0038">38 B.C.</date>
                    </note> and no one —not even a trader —had up to that time visited it.
                        <reg>to</reg> enter it was a thing that hardly anyone but the general
                    himself was bold enough to do: with all the rest the recollection of the Caudine
                    Forks was still too vivid. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>then</reg> one of those present, the consul's brother Marcus Fabius, —some
                    say that it was Caeso Fabius, others Gaius Claudius, a son of the same mother as
                    the consul —offered to explore and return in a short time with definite
                    information about everything. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> had been educated at Caere in the house of family friends, and
                    from this circumstance was learned in Etruscan writings and knew the Etruscan
                        <pb n="p.303"/> language well. <reg>i</reg> have authority for believing
                    that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> in
                    that age Roman boys were regularly wont to be schooled in Etruscan literature,
                    as nowadays they are trained in Greek; but it seems more probable that this man
                    possessed some exceptional qualification to induce him to venture amongst
                    enemies in so daring a disguise. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> is said that his only companion was a slave, brought up with him,
                    and hence acquainted, like his master, with the language. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> set out, after acquiring no more than a summary knowledge of the
                    nature of the region they must enter and the names of the chief men in those
                    tribes, to save them from being detected in conversation by boggling at any well
                    —known fact. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> went dressed as shepherds and armed with rustic weapons, namely
                    billhooks and a brace of javelins apiece. <reg>but</reg> neither their
                    familiarity with the tongue nor the fashion of their dress and weapons was so
                    great a protection to them as the fact that it was repugnant to belief that any
                    stranger would enter the Ciminian defiles. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> are said to have penetrated as far as Camerinum in Umbria, where
                    the Roman, having ventured to tell who they were, was introduced into the
                    senate, and treated with them in the consul's name for friendship and an
                    alliance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>having</reg> then been hospitably entertained, lie was bidden to carry word
                    back to the Romans that thirty days' provisions for their army would be waiting
                    for them, if they came into that region, and that the young men of the Umbrian
                    Camertes would be armed and ready to obey their orders. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> their success being made known to the consul, he sent the baggage
                    ahead, in the first watch, and directed the legions to follow the baggage.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg>
                    <pb n="p.305"/> himself stopped behind with the cavalry, and at <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> dawn of
                    the following day made a demonstration against the enemy's outposts, which had
                    been stationed at the entrance to the pass. <reg>having</reg> kept the enemy in
                    play for a sufficient time, he retired within his camp, and emerging from it by
                    the opposite gate overtook the column before night. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>next</reg> day, with the first rays of light, he was on the crest of the
                    Ciminian mountain and, looking thence over the rich ploughlands of Etruria, sent
                    his soldiers to plunder. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Romans had already brought away out enormous booty when certain
                    improvised bands of Etruscan peasants, called together in hot haste by the chief
                    men of that country, encountered them, but with so little discipline that in
                    seeking to regain the spoils they had nearly been made a spoil themselves.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>having</reg> slain or driven off these men and wasted the country far and
                    wide, the Romans returned to their camp, victorious and enriched with all manner
                    of supplies. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> , as it happened, they found five legates, with two tribunes of
                    the plebs, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The tribunes were added to
                        the embassy that they might, if necessary, compel obedience to the senate by
                        the exercise of their sacrosanct authority. <reg>this</reg> was an unusual
                        procedure, as the powers of the tribunes were held to extend no further than
                        one mile from the City. </note> who had come to order Fabius in the name of
                    the senate not to cross the Ciminian Forest. <reg>rejoicing</reg> that they had
                    come too late to be able to hinder the campaign, they returned to Rome with
                    tidings of victory. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> expedition of the consul's, instead of putting an end to the
                    war, only gave it a wider range. <reg>for</reg> the district lying about the
                    base of Mount Ciminius had felt the devastation, and had aroused not only
                    Etruria to resentment but the neighbouring parts of Umbria also. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>so</reg> an army came to Sutrium that was larger than any they had raised
                    before; and not only did they move forward their camp, out of the woods, but
                    even, in their <pb n="p.307"/> eagerness for combat, came down into the plain at
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> the
                    earliest opportunity in battle formation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> first, after forming up, they stood still in their positions,
                    having left their enemies room to draw up opposite. <reg>then</reg> , finding
                    the Romans in no haste to engage them, they advanced up to the rampart.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> they saw that even the outguards had retired within the works,
                    they began shouting to their generals, to have their rations for the day sent
                    out to them from the camp; they would wait under arms, they said, and either
                    that night, or at daybreak at the latest, attack the enemy's stockade.
                        <name>The</name> Roman army was every whit as restless, but was restrained
                    by the general's authority. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> was about the tenth hour of the day <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Perhaps about six o'clock.</note> when the consul bade
                    the soldiers sup, and commanded them to be armed and ready at whatever hour of
                    the day or night he might give the signal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> a brief address he magnified the Samnite wars and belittled the
                    Etruscans: there was no comparison, he said, between the two enemies, or between
                    their numbers; moreover, he had an additional weapon in concealment; they should
                    know about it when the time came; until then it must remain a secret. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>by</reg> these obscure hints he sought to engender a belief that the enemy
                    were being betrayed, in order to revive the spirits of his men, which were
                    damped by the numbers of their enemies; and the fact that the Etruscans had
                    thrown up no breastworks where they lay lent colour to the insinuation. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>refreshed</reg> with food, the soldiers gave themselves up to sleep, and at
                    about the fourth watch were awakened without noise and put on their armour.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>mattocks</reg> were issued to the soldiers' servants, that they might <pb
                        n="p.309"/> level the rampart and fill up the trenches. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> line <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 310</note> was drawn up inside the fortifications, and selected
                    cohorts were posted at the exits. <reg>then</reg> , on the signal being given a
                    little before dawn, which on summer nights is the time of deepest sleep, the
                    rampart was thrown down, and the Romans, rushing out in battle —formation, fell
                    upon their enemies, who were lying all about the field. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>some</reg> were slain without even stirring in their sleep, some were but
                    half awake, the greatest number were reaching in terror for their weapons.
                        <reg>only</reg> a few were given time to arm themselves; and even these,
                    with no definite standard to follow and no leader, the Romans routed and chased
                    from the field. <reg>some</reg> made for the camp and others for the mountains,
                    as they fled this way and that. <name>The</name> forests afforded the surer
                    refuge; for the camp, being situated in the plain, was captured the same day.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>orders</reg> were issued that all gold and silver be brought to the consul;
                    the rest of the booty went to the soldiers. <reg>on</reg> that day the enemy
                    lost sixty thousand slain or captured. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>some</reg> historians relate that this famous battle was fought on the
                    other side of the Ciminian Forest, near Perusia, and that Rome was in a panic
                    lest the army should be surrounded and cut off in that dangerous defile by the
                    Tuscans and Umbrians rising up on every hand. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> , wherever it was fought, the Romans were the victors.
                        <reg>and</reg> so from Perusia and Cortona and Arretium, which at that time
                    might be the chief cities of the nations of Etruria, ambassadors came to Rome to
                    sue for peace and an alliance. <reg>they</reg> obtained a truce for thirty
                    years. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>while</reg> these things were going on in Etruria, the other consul, Gaius
                    Marcius Rutulus, <pb n="p.311"/> captured Allifae from the Samnites by assault.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At viii. xxv. 4, Livy mentioned
                        the acquisition of Allifae, but has nowhere spoken of its recapture by the
                        Samnites. </note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note>
                    <reg>many</reg> forts and villages besides were either wiped out in the course
                    of hostilities or came intact into the hands of the <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>at</reg> about this time a Roman fleet, commanded by Publius Cornelius,
                    whom the senate had placed in charge of the coast, sailed for Campania and put
                    into Pompeii. <reg>from</reg> there the sailors and rowers set out to pillage
                    the territory of Nuceria. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Diod. (XIX.
                        lxv.) tells us that Nuceria (formerly an ally of Rome) had revolted to the
                        Samnites. </note>
                    <reg>having</reg> quickly ravaged the nearest fields, from which they might have
                    returned in safety to their ships, they were lured on, as often happens, by the
                    love of booty, and going too far abroad aroused the <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> enemy. <reg>while</reg> they roamed through the fields,
                    nobody interfered with them, though they might have been utterly annihilated;
                    but as they came trooping back, without a thought of danger, the country —folk
                    overtook them not far from the ships, stripped them of their plunder, and even
                    slew a part of them; those who escaped the massacre were driven, a disordered
                    rabble, to their <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> ships. </p>
                <p>
                    <name>Great</name> as had been the fears excited in Rome when Quintus Fabius
                    marched through the Ciminian Forest, the rejoicings that took place in Samnium
                    amongst the enemy were no less on their hearing a report that the Roman army was
                    intercepted and <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> besieged. <reg>they</reg>
                    recalled the Caudine Forks as showing what the disaster would be <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> like; with the same temerity, they said, a race that
                    was ever reaching out for what lay beyond had been led into pathless forests and
                    there hemmed in, more by the difficulties of the ground than by the arms of
                    their <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> enemy. <reg>soon</reg> their joy began
                    to be mixed with a kind of envy, that Fortune should have transferred the glory
                        <pb n="p.313"/> of the Roman war from Samnites to <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Etruscans. <reg>so</reg>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> they
                    hastened to bring all their strength to bear upon crushing Gaius Marcius, the
                    consul; and resolved, if Marcius should avoid an encounter, to march forthwith
                    into Etruria, through the countries of the Marsi and the Sabines.
                        <name>The</name> consul met them, and the battle was fiercely contested on
                    both sides, but without a decision being reached. <reg>yet</reg> , doubtful
                    though it was which side had suffered most, the report gained ground that the
                    Romans had been worsted: they had lost certain members of the equestrian order,
                    certain military tribunes, and one lieutenant, and —most conspicuous of their
                    misfortunes —the consul himself was <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> wounded. </p>
                <p>
                    <name>These</name> reverses as usual were further exaggerated in the telling,
                    and the senate in great dismay determined on the appointment of a <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> dictator. <reg>nobody</reg> could doubt that
                    Papirius Cursor, who was regarded as the foremost soldier of his time, would be
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> designated. <reg>but</reg> the senators
                    were not certain that a messenger could be got through in safety to Samnium,
                    where all was hostile, nor that the consul Marcius was alive. <name>The</name>
                    other consul, Fabius, had a private grudge against <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Papirius; and lest this enmity might hinder the general
                    welfare, the senate decided to send a deputation of former consuls, in the hope
                    that their personal influence, when added to the wishes of the government, might
                    induce him to forget those quarrels for the good of the <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> country. <name>The</name> ambassadors went to Fabius and
                    delivered the resolution of the senate, with a discourse that suited their
                    instructions. <name>The</name> consul, his eyes fixed on the ground, retired
                    without a word, leaving the ambassadors uncertain what he proposed to <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> do. <reg>then</reg> in the <pb n="p.315"/> silence
                    of the night, as the custom is, he appointed <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> Lucius Papirius dictator.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The consul rose and took the
                        auspices after midnight because it was less likely that anything unlucky
                        would then be said or done —in the absence of bystanders —to vitiate the
                        ceremony. </note>
                    <reg>when</reg> the envoys thanked him for nobly conquering his feelings, he
                    continued obstinately silent, and dismissed them without making any reply or
                    alluding to what he had done, so that it was clearly seen what agony his great
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> heart was suppressing. </p>
                <p>
                    <name>Papirius</name> named Gaius Junius Bubulcus master of the horse.
                        <reg>when</reg> he began to lay before the curiate assembly <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Under the kings the curiate assembly
                        had been the only formal assembly of the people ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >cf.</hi> I. xiii. 6 for the origin of the <hi rend="italics"
                            >curiae</hi> ), but in the time of the republic its functions had
                        largely passed to the centuriate assembly. <reg>it</reg> was, however, still
                        called upon to ratify the election of new magistrates by passing a <hi
                            rend="italics">lex ciuriata de imperio,</hi> and retained certain other
                        ceremonial duties. </note> a law confirming his authority, the proceedings
                    were cut short by an evil omen, the first vote to be counted being that of the
                    ward called Faucia, notorious for two calamities, the capture of the City and
                    the Caudine Peace, which had both been incurred in years when this same curia
                    had the right of <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> the first return. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">This was determined each time by
                        lot.</note>
                    <name>Licinius</name> Macer makes this ward unlucky also for a third disaster
                    —that of the Cremera. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <date when="-0477">477 B.C.</date> (Book II, chap. 1.). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>next</reg> day the dictator sought the auspices afresh and carried the law
                    through. <reg>then</reg> , setting out with the legions which had recently been
                    recruited on account of <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the fear occasioned
                    by the army's march through the Ciminian Forest, he came to the vicinity of
                    Longula, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Longula was a Volscian town,
                        but was situated not far from the Samnite border. <reg>it</reg> is not
                        necessary to assume, with Weissenborn-Mueller, that Livy is referring to an
                        otherwise unknown Longula in Samnium. </note> and taking over from Marcius
                    the consul his veteran troops, marched out and offered battle, which the enemy
                    on their part seemed willing to accept. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> while the two armies stood armed and ready for the conflict,
                    which neither cared to begin, night overtook them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> some time after that they remained quietly in the camps <pb
                        n="p.317"/> they had established near one another, neither lacking <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> confidence
                    in themselves nor yet making light of their adversaries. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>meanwhile</reg> the Etruscans, employing a <hi rend="italics"> lex sacrata,
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> One who violated the <hi
                                rend="italics">lex sacrata</hi> was forfeited to the gods.
                                <reg>see</reg> chap. xl. § 9, IV. xxvi. 3, xxxvi. xxxviii. 1, and
                            especially x. xxxviii. 3 ff. </note>
                    </hi> had raised an army in which each man had chosen his comrade, and joined
                    battle, with greater forces, and at the same time with greater valour, than ever
                    before. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> field was contested with such rivalry of rage that neither side
                    discharged a missile. <name>The</name> battle began with swords, and, furious at
                    the outset, waxed hotter as the struggle continued, for the victory was long
                    undecided. <reg>it</reg> seemed as though the Romans were contending, not with
                    the so oft defeated Etruscans, but with some new race. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>no</reg> sign of flight was visible in any quarter. <reg>as</reg> the front
                    —rankers fell, the second line moved up to replace the first, that the standards
                    might not want defenders. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>after</reg> that the last reserves were called upon; and to such extremity
                    of distress and danger did the Romans come that their cavalry dismounted, and
                    made their way over arms and over bodies to the front ranks of the infantry.
                        <reg>like</reg> a fresh line springing up amongst the exhausted combatants,
                    they wrought havoc in the companies of the Etruscans. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>then</reg> the rest of the soldiers, following up their charge, despite of
                    weariness, at last broke through the enemy's ranks. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> this their stubbornness began to be overcome, and certain
                    companies to face about; and when these had once turned tail, the rest likewise
                    took to flight. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>that</reg>
                    <pb n="p.319"/> day for the first time broke the might of the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 310</note> Etruscans,
                    which had long flourished in prosperity. <reg>their</reg> strength was cut off
                    in the battle, and their camp was taken and plundered in the same attack. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> war in Samnium, immediately afterwards, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 308</note> was attended with equal
                    danger and an equally glorious conclusion. <name>The</name> enemy, besides their
                    other warlike preparations, had made their battle —line to glitter with new and
                    splendid arms. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> were two corps: the shields of the one were inlaid with gold,
                    of the other with silver. <name>The</name> shape of the shield was this: the
                    upper part, where it protected the breast and shoulders, was rather broad, with
                    a level top; below it was somewhat tapering, to make it easier to handle.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> wore a sponge <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Weissenborn-Mueller think a breastplate resembling a sponge in appearance is
                        intended. <name>The</name> translator follows Professor Anderson in taking
                        the expression literally, of a corslet made of sponge. </note> to protect
                    the breast, and the left leg was covered with a greave. <reg>their</reg> helmets
                    were crested, to make their stature appear greater. <name>The</name> tunics of
                    the gilded warriors were parti —coloured; those of the silvern ones were linen
                    of a dazzling white. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> latter had silver sheaths and silver baldrics: the former
                    gilded sheaths and golden baldrics, and their horses had gold —embroidered
                    saddle —cloths. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> right wing was assigned to these: the others took up their post
                    on the left. <name>The</name> Romans had already learned of these splendid
                    accoutrements, and their generals had taught them that a soldier should be rough
                    to look on, not adorned with gold and silver but putting his trust in iron and
                    in courage: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> indeed those other things were
                    more truly spoil than arms, shining bright before a battle, but losing their
                    beauty in the midst of blood and wounds; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    manhood they said, <pb n="p.321"/> was the adornment of a soldier; all those
                    other <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 305</note>
                    things went with the victory, and a rich enemy was the prize of the victor,
                    however poor. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>whilst</reg> his men were animated by these words, Cursor led them into
                    battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> took up his own post on the right, and committed the left to the
                    master of the horse. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>from</reg> the moment of encountering, there was a mighty struggle with the
                    enemy, and a struggle no less sharp between the dictator and the master of the
                    horse, to decide which wing was to inaugurate the victory. <reg>it</reg> so
                    happened that Junius was the first to make an impression on the Samnites.
                        <reg>with</reg> the Roman left he faced the enemy's right, where they had
                    consecrated themselves, as their custom was, and for that reason were
                    resplendent in white coats and equally white armour. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>declaring</reg> that he offered up these men in sacrifice to Orcus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Orcus —the Greek Pluto —was god of the
                        dead.</note> ,Junius charged, threw their ranks into disorder, and clearly
                    made their <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> line recoil. <reg>when</reg> the
                    dictator saw this, he cried, <quote>
                        <reg>shall</reg> the victory begin upon the left? <reg>shall</reg> the
                        right, the dictator's division, follow the attack of others?
                            <reg>shall</reg> it not carry off the honours of <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> the victory? </quote>
                    <reg>this</reg> fired the soldiers with new energy; nor did the cavalry display
                    less valour than the foot, or the lieutenants less enthusiasm than the generals.
                        <name>Marcus</name> Valerius on the right and Publius Decius on the left,
                    both men of consular rank, rode out to the cavalry, which was posted on the
                    wings, and, exhorting them to join with themselves in seizing a share of glory,
                    charged obliquely against the <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> enemy's flanks.
                        <reg>thus</reg> a new and appalling danger enveloped their line on either
                    side, and when the Roman legions, observing the terror of the Samnites, pressed
                    forward with <pb n="p.323"/> redoubled shouts, the enemy began <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> to flee. <name>The</name>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 308</note> fields
                    were soon heaped with slain and with glittering armour. <reg>at</reg> first the
                    frightened Samnites found a refuge in their camp, but presently even that had to
                    be abandoned, and ere nightfall it had been taken, sacked, and set on fire. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> dictator, as decreed by the senate, celebrated a triumph, in
                    which by far the finest show was afforded by the <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> captured armour. <reg>so</reg> magnificent was its
                    appearance that the shields inlaid with gold were divided up amongst the owners
                    of the moneychangers' booths, to be used in decking out the Forum. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It was forty years later when the
                        Romans began to coin silver for themselves; but there would be much coined
                        silver in circulation by this time from Etruria and Magna Graecia, to
                        furnish employment for money —changers ( <hi rend="italics">argentarii</hi>
                        ). </note>
                    <reg>from</reg> this is said to have come the custom of the aediles adorning the
                    Forum whenever the <hi rend="italics">tensae,</hi> or covered chariots of the
                    gods, were <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> conducted through it. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A <hi rend="italics">tensa</hi> is
                        figured in Stuart Jones, <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>companion</reg> to Roman </hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>history</reg> , </hi> P1. xlix. <reg>it</reg> was used to carry the
                        images of the Capitoline gods in solemn procession to the Circus, at the
                        time of the <hi rend="italics">ludi circenses.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <reg>so</reg> the Romans made use of the splendid armour of their enemies to do
                    honour to the gods; while the Campanians, in consequence of their pride and in
                    hatred of the Samnites, equipped after this fashion the gladiators who furnished
                    them entertainment at their feasts, and bestowed on them the <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> name of Samnites. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > The Romans seem to have obtained from Capua the idea of gladiators (Livy,
                            <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>per</reg> . </hi> XVI.), and the <quote>
                            <name>Samnite</name>
                        </quote> was always one of the standard types. <name>The</name> sentence is
                        usually taken as implying that the Capuans had been present as allies of the
                        Romans in the battle. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>in</reg> the same year the consul Fabius fought a battle with the remnants
                    of the Etruscan forces near Perusia —which, together with other cities, had
                    broken the truce <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Chap, xxxvii. §
                        12.</note> —and gained an easy <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> and
                    decisive victory. <reg>he</reg> would have taken the town itself —for after the
                    battle he marched up to the walls —had not ambassadors come out and <milestone
                        n="20" unit="section"/> surrendered the place. <reg>having</reg> placed a
                    garrison in Perusia and having sent <pb n="p.325"/> on before him to the senate
                    in Rome the Etruscan <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 308</note> deputations which had come to him seeking friendship, the
                    consul was borne in <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/> triumph into the City,
                    after gaining a success more brilliant even than the dictator's; indeed the
                    glory of conquering the Samnites was largely diverted upon the lieutenants,
                    Publius Decius and Marcus Valerius, of whom, at the next election, the people
                    with great enthusiasm made the one consul and the other praetor. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> recognition of his remarkable conquest of Etruria, Fabius was
                    continued in the consulship, and was given Decius for his colleague. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Valerius</name> was for the fourth time chosen praetor. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls cast lots for the commands, Etruria falling to Decius
                    and Samnium to Fabius. <name>The</name> latter marched against Nuceria
                    Alfaterna, and rejecting that city's overtures of peace because its people had
                    declined it when it was offered them, laid siege to the place and forced it to
                    surrender. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>a</reg> battle was fought with the Samnites, in which the enemy were
                    defeated without much difficulty, nor would the engagement have been remembered
                    but for the fact that it was the first time that the Marsi had made war against
                    the Romans. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Marsi, though of
                        Samnite stock, had hitherto bee on good terms with the Romans. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Paeligni imitated the defection of the Marsi, and met with the
                    same fate. </p>
                <p>
                    <name>Decius</name> , the other consul, was also successful in war. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> he had frightened the Tarquinienses into furnishing corn for the
                    army and seeking a truce for forty years, he captured by storm a number of
                    strongholds belonging to the people of Volsinii. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>some</reg> of these he dismantled, lest they should serve as a refuge for
                    the enemy, and by devastating far and wide he made himself so feared that all
                    who <pb n="p.327"/> bore the Etruscan name begged the consul to grant <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 308</note> them a
                    treaty. <reg>this</reg> privilege they were denied, but a truce for a year was
                    granted them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> were required to furnish the Roman army with a year's pay and
                    two tunics for each soldier; such was the price they paid for a truce. </p>
                <p>
                    <name>The</name> tranquillity which now obtained in Etruria was disturbed by a
                    sudden revolt of the Umbrians, a people which had escaped all the distress of
                    war, except that an army had passed through their territory. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Livy has not mentioned this
                        before.</note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>calling</reg> up all their fighting men, and inducing great part of the
                    Etruscans to rebel, they mustered so large an army, that they boasted, with much
                    glorifying of themselves and fleering at the Romans, that they would leave
                    Decius behind them in Etruria and march off to the assault of Rome. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> this purpose of theirs was reported to the consul Decius, he
                    hastened by forced marches from Etruria towards the City, and encamped in the
                    fields belonging to Pupinia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> South of
                        the Anio not far from Gabii. <reg>see</reg> xxvi. ix. 12. </note> eagerly
                    waiting for word of their approach. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> Rome no one made light of an Umbrian invasion. <reg>their</reg>
                    very threats had excited fear in those who had learnt from the Gallic disaster
                    how unsafe was the City they inhabited. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>accordingly</reg> envoys were dispatched to carry word to Fabius the
                    consul, that if there were any slackening in the Samnite war he should with all
                    speed lead his army into Umbria. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consul obeyed the order, and advanced by long marches to
                    Mevania, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In the neighbourhood of
                        Perugia and Assisi.</note> where the forces of the Umbrians at that time
                    lay. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> sudden arrival of the consul, whom they had believed to have
                    his hands full with another war in Samnium, a long way from Umbria, so dismayed
                    the Umbrians that some were for falling back on their <pb n="p.329"/> fortified
                    cities, and others for giving up the war; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 308</note> but one canton —which
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> they themselves call Materina —not only
                    kept the rest to their arms, but brought them to an immediate engagement.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Fabius</name> was entrenching his camp when they attacked him.
                        <reg>as</reg> soon as he saw them rushing madly upon his ramparts, he
                    recalled the soldiers from their work and drew them up, as time and the nature
                    of the ground permitted, and encouraging them with a true relation of the
                    honours they had won, some in Etruria and some in Samnium, bade them end this
                    trivial sequel to the Etruscan war, and revenge upon the foe his impious threat
                    that he would assault the City of Rome. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    <name>These</name> words were received by the soldiers with such alacrity that
                    the speech of the general was interrupted by a spontaneous cheer.
                        <reg>then</reg> , before the command could be given, they hurled themselves
                    —to the blare of horns and trumpets —with the wildest abandon against the enemy.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> fought not as though their opponents had been men and armed; but
                    —marvellous to relate -began with tearing the standards out of the bearers'
                    hands, and then fell to dragging the bearers themselves before the consul and to
                    bringing armed men over from the other line to their own; wherever they met with
                    resistance, they did their work more with shields than with swords, swinging
                    them from the shoulder and knocking down their enemies with the bosses.
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> slain were outnumbered by the prisoners, and all along the
                    battle line one cry was heard: that they should lay down their arms. <milestone
                        n="20" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>and</reg> so, while the battle was still going on, the surrender was made,
                    by the men who had first advocated war. <reg>on</reg> the next and on succeeding
                        <pb n="p.331"/> days the other peoples of Umbria also capitulated: <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 308</note> the men of
                    Ocriculum were received into friendship under a stipulation. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>Fabius</name> , having won a war assigned by lot <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 307-306</note> to another man, led
                    his army back to his own province. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>just</reg> as in the preceding year the people had rewarded his successful
                    campaign by re —electing him to the consulship, so now the senate continued him
                    in command for the year to follow. <name>The</name> new consuls were Appius
                    Claudius and Lucius Volumnius, the former of whom had strongly opposed the
                    resolution. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The senate had a grudge
                        against Appius (see chap. xxx. § 1 f.), and so prolonged,
                        unconstitutionally, the command of Fabius, and gave the other war to
                        Volumnius. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>i</reg> find in certain annals that Appius sought the consulship when
                    censor, and that Lucius Furius, a tribune of the plebs, refused to let him stand
                    until he should have resigned the censorship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> election over, his colleague was decreed the command in the new
                    war —with the Sallentini —and Appius remained in Rome, to strengthen his power
                    by civil arts, since the means of acquiring repute in war remained with others. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Volumnius</name> had no cause to regret his assignment. <reg>he</reg>
                    engaged in many successful battles and took several hostile towns by assault.
                        <reg>generous</reg> in his distribution of the spoil, he enhanced the effect
                    of a liberality which was pleasing in itself by his friendly bearing —traits
                    which had made his soldiers eager for toil and danger. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> proconsul Quintus Fabius fought near the city Allifae a pitched
                    battle with the army of the Samnites. <name>The</name> result was anything but
                    doubtful, for the enemy were routed and driven into their camp; and they could
                    not have held the camp had there not been very little daylight left. <pb
                        n="p.333"/>
                    <reg>even</reg> so they were invested before dark, and guards <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 307-306</note> were
                    posted in the night to prevent anyone's escaping. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>next</reg> day, before it was well light, they began to surrender.
                        <name>The</name> Samnites among them bargained to be dismissed in their
                    tunics; all these were sent under the yoke. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> allies of the Samnites were protected by no guarantee, and were
                    sold into slavery, to the number of seven thousand. <reg>those</reg> who gave
                    themselves out for Hernic citizens were detained apart in custody, and Fabius
                    sent them all to the senate in Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> an enquiry was held as to whether they had been conscripted or
                    had fought voluntarily for the Samnites against the Romans; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> after which they were parcelled out amongst the Latins to
                    be guarded, and a resolution was passed directing the new consuls, Publius
                    Cornelius Arvina and Quintus Marcius Tremulus —for these men had been elected
                    —to refer the matter to the senate for fresh action. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>this</reg> the Hernici resented. <name>The</name> people of Anagnia
                    assembled a council of all the states in the circus which they call the Maritime
                    Circus, and all of the Hernic name, excepting the inhabitants of Aletrium,
                    Ferentinum and Verulae, declared war on the Roman People. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Hernici had been at peace with the Romans ever
                        since their subjugation in <date when="-0358">358 B.C.</date> (VII. xv. 9).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> Samnium, too, the departure of Fabius was the cause of fresh
                    disturbances. <name>Calatia</name> and Sora with their Roman garrisons were
                    taken by assault, and the captured soldiers were treated with shameful rigour.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Calatia was mentioned in chap.
                        ii. § 2 as a Samnite town, and its capture by the Romans in <date
                            when="-0314">314 B.C.</date> is noted in chap. xxviii. § 6. Sora, on the
                        borders of the Hernici, was taken in the same year (chap. xxiv. § 14). </note>
                    <reg>accordingly</reg> Publius Cornelius was dispatched in that direction with
                    an army. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> new enemies —for by this time war had been declared on the men
                    of Anagnia and the other Hernici —were allotted to Marcius. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> the outset of the campaign the enemy were so successful in <pb
                        n="p.335"/> seizing all the strategic points between the camps <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 307-306</note> of the
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> consuls, that not even a nimble courier
                    could get through, and for some days the consuls were kept in uncertainty
                    regarding everything and could only speculate about one another's state.
                        <reg>fears</reg> for their safety even extended to Rome, where all of
                    military age were given the oath and two full armies were enlisted, to meet any
                    sudden emergencies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>but</reg> the war with the Hernici by no means answered to the present
                    panic or to the nation's old renown. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> ventured nothing to speak of at any point, and having lost three
                    camps in the space of a few days they bargained for a thirty days' truce, to
                    enable them to send envoys to the senate in Rome, and delivered up two months'
                    pay and corn, and a tunic for every soldier. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> senate sent them back to Marcius, having passed a resolution
                    empowering him to deal with the Hernici as he saw fit. <reg>he</reg> received,
                    their submission on terms of unconditional surrender. </p>
                <p>
                    <reg>in</reg> Samnium the other consul was also stronger than the enemy, but was
                    more embarrassed by the character of the ground. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> enemy had blockaded all the roads and seized the practicable
                    passes, to prevent supplies being brought up anywhere. <reg>but</reg> though the
                    consul offered battle daily, he could not entice them to fight. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>it</reg> was quite apparent that the Samnites would not accept an immediate
                    engagement, nor the Romans endure any prolongation of the war. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> arrival of Marcius, who, having subdued the Hernici, made haste
                    to come to the assistance of his colleague, deprived the enemy of any power to
                    delay the struggle. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>for</reg> since they had not considered themselves equal to a <pb n="p.337"
                    /> battle with even one army, and believed that, once <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 307-306</note> they had suffered two
                    consular armies to unite, there would be no hope for them, they made an attack
                    on Marcius as he was approaching in loose marching older. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>hastily</reg> throwing down their packs in the midst, the Romans formed up
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> in a hollow square, as the words <hi
                            rend="italics">in medium</hi> show. </note> as well as time permitted.
                        <name>The</name> shouting was the first thing that was noticed in the camp
                    of Cornelius. <reg>then</reg> , far off, a cloud of dust was descried, and
                    caused a commotion in the camp. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consul ordered his men to arm, and leading them quickly out
                    into line attacked the enemy in the flank, when their hands were full with
                    another struggle, crying out that it would be a burning shame if they <milestone
                        n="14??" unit="section"/> let the other army win both victories, and failed
                    to claim for themselves the glory of their own campaign. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>bursting</reg> through at the point where he had charged, he advanced
                    through the enemy's line, and capturing their camp, which was empty of
                    defenders, set fire to it. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>when</reg> the soldiers of Marcius saw the blaze, and the enemy, looking
                    over their shoulders, saw it too, the flight of the Samnites soon became
                    general; but at every point death blocked the way, and there was no escaping
                    anywhere. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>thirty</reg> thousand of the enemy had already fallen, and the consuls had
                    sounded the recall and were proceeding to assemble their forces in one body,
                    amid the mutual congratulations and rejoicings of the men, when suddenly some
                    new cohorts of the Samnites, which had been levied as reliefs, were made out in
                    the distance, and occasioned a renewal of the slaughter. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> victors rushed upon them, without orders from the consuls or
                    receiving any <pb n="p.339"/> signal, exclaiming that the Samnites must begin
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 307-306</note>
                    their soldiering with a bitter lesson. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls indulged the ardour of the legions, being well aware
                    that the enemy's recruits, in the midst of routed veterans, would scarce be
                    equal to so much as an attempt at fighting. <reg>they</reg> were not mistaken.
                        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>all</reg> the forces of the Samnites, old and new, broke and fled to the
                    nearest mountains, up which the Romans too advanced in pursuit of them.
                        <name>The</name> conquered could find no refuge anywhere that afforded
                    safety, but were driven pell —mell from the ridges where they had made a stand.
                        <reg>and</reg> now with one voice they all begged for peace. <milestone
                        n="21" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>they</reg> were required to furnish corn for three months, with a year's
                    pay and a tunic for each Roman soldier, and envoys were then dispatched to the
                    senate to sue for terms. </p>
                <p>
                    <name>Cornelius</name> was left in Samnium. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Marcius</name> returned to the City, which he entered in a triumph over
                    the Hernici. <name>An</name> equestrian statue in the Forum was decreed him and
                    was erected in front of the temple of Castor. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The temple of Castor and Pollux had been vowed at the
                        battle of Lake Regillus, <date when="-0299">299 B.C.</date> , and dedicated
                        fifteen years later (II. xx. 12, and xlii. 5). </note>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>to</reg> the three Hernic peoples of Aletrium, Verulae, and Ferentinum
                    their own laws were restored, because they preferred them to Roman citizenship,
                    and they were given the right to intermarry with each other —a privilege which
                    for some time they were the only Hernici to enjoy. <milestone n="24"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> people of Anagnia and such others as had borne arms against the
                    Romans were admitted to citizenship without the right of voting. <reg>they</reg>
                    were prohibited from holding councils and from intermarrying, and were allowed
                    no magistrates save those who had charge of religious rites. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> the same year the censor Gaius Junius <pb n="p.341"/> Bubulcus let
                    the contract for the temple of Safety, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >On the Quirinal.</note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 307-306</note>
                    which he had vowed, while consul, during the Samnite war. <reg>he</reg> and his
                    colleague, Marcus Valerius Maximus, built roads through the countryside at the
                    public <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> costs. <reg>in</reg> this year also
                    the treaty with the Carthaginians was renewed for the third time, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> VII. Xxvii. 2 and note. <hi
                            rend="italics">
                            <reg>per</reg> , </hi> xiii., which speaks of <hi rend="italics"
                            >fourth</hi> treaty, would be in agreement with the present passage.
                    </note> and their ambassadors, who had come for the purpose of arranging it,
                    were treated with courtesy and given presents. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <name>The</name> same year had a dictator in the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 305</note> person of Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio, the master of the horse being Publius Decius Mus. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <name>These</name> men held a consular election —for to this end they had been
                    appointed, since neither consul had been able to leave the seat of war.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consuls chosen were Lucius Postumius and Tiberius Minucius.
                        <name>Piso</name>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Lucius Calpurnius Piso Frugi, the
                        annalist, <hi rend="italics">cos.</hi>
                        <date when="-0133">133 B.C.</date>
                    </note> makes these men follow Quintus Fabius and Publius Decius, omitting the
                    two years in which we have placed the consulship of Claudius and Volumnius and
                    that of Cornelius and Marcius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>whether</reg> in the redaction of his annals he forgot them, or omitted two
                    sets of consuls purposely, as not authentic, is uncertain. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> that year also the Samnites made forays upon the Campus Stellatis
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was a tract forming part of
                        the Ager Falernus, later celebrated for its choice wine. </note> in
                    Campania. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>both</reg> consuls were accordingly dispatched into Samnium in different
                    directions, Postumius marching on Tifernum, and Minucius on Bovianum.
                        <name>The</name> fighting began at Tifernum, where Postumius commanded.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>some</reg> relate that the Samnites were decisively beaten and that twenty
                    thousand prisoners were taken; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> others that the
                    armies quitted the field on even terms, and that Postumius, feigning fear, in
                    the night withdrew his <pb n="p.343"/> forces secretly to the mountains, where
                    the enemy <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        305</note> followed him and themselves entrenched a camp, at a distance of
                    two miles from his. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> consul, that it might appear to have been his object to gain a
                    position at once secure and abounding in supplies, — and such indeed it was
                    —having <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> fortified his camp and equipped it
                    with all manner of useful things, left in it a strong garrison, and in the third
                    watch led his legions in light marching order by the most direct route to his
                    colleague, who likewise lay in camp, facing another army. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> , at the instigation of Postumius, Minucius gave battle to the
                    enemy; and when the doubtful struggle had been prolonged until late in the
                    afternoon, Postumius with his fresh legions fell unexpectedly upon the now jaded
                    forces of their opponents. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Samnites, debarred by their weariness and wounds even from
                    flight, were utterly annihilated, and the Romans, having taken twenty —one
                    standards, set out for the camp of Postumius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>there</reg> the two victorious armies assailed the enemy, already dismayed
                    by the tidings of the other battle, and overwhelmingly routed them, capturing
                    six —and —twenty standards, the commander of the Samnites —Statius Gellius —and
                    many other prisoners, besides both camps. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>on</reg> the following day they began the siege of the city of Bovianum,
                    and on its capture, which quickly ensued, the consuls crowned their glorious
                    achievements with a triumph. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>some</reg> writers state that Minucius the consul was severely wounded and
                    expired after being carried back to his camp. <reg>they</reg> add that Marcus
                    Fulvius was made consul suffect in his place, and that it was he who, being sent
                    out to the army of Minucius, captured Bovianum. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.345"/>
                <p>
                    <reg>in</reg> that year Sora, Arpinum, and Cesennia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Site unknown.</note> were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 305</note> won back from the
                    Samnites. <name>The</name> great statue of Hercules was set up and dedicated on
                    the Capitol. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps to appease the
                        god for the indignity mentioned in chap. xxix. § 9. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> the consulship of Publius Sulpicius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 304</note> Saverrio and Publius
                    Sempronius Sophus, the Samnites, whether seeking to end or only to postpone
                    hostilities, sent envoys to Rome to treat for peace. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>to</reg> their humble supplications the answer was returned, that if the
                    Samnites had not frequently sought peace while preparing for war, a treaty could
                    have been arranged by mutual discussion: as it was, since words had hitherto
                    proved of no effect, the Romans must needs take their stand on facts. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Publius</name> Sempronius, the consul, would shortly be in Samnium with an
                    army; he was one whom they would be unable to deceive as to whether their hearts
                    inclined to peace or war; after a thorough investigation he would report his
                    findings to the senate; and on his leaving Samnium their envoys might attend
                    him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> Roman army marched all over Samnium; the people were peaceable
                    and furnished the army liberally with supplies; accordingly their ancient treaty
                    was in that year restored again to the Samnites. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In <date when="-0354">354 B.C.</date> the Samnites' had
                        sought and obtained a treaty with the Romans, upon what terms is not known,
                        but they were doubtless liberal (vii. xix. 4) </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> arms of Rome were then directed against the Aequi, who had been
                    her enemies of old, but for many years past had remained quiet, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Since <date when="-0388">388
                            B.C.</date> (vi. iv. 8). </note> under colour of a peace which they
                    observed but treacherously. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> reason for making war on them was as follows: before the
                    overthrow of the Hernici they had repeatedly joined with them in sending
                    assistance to the Samnites, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Chap.
                        xlii. § 8, where, however, the Aequi are not specified. </note> and after
                    the subjugation of the Hernici, almost the entire nation had gone over to the
                    enemy, without attempting to disguise their policy; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.347"/> and when fetials had applied to them for reparation, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 304</note> after the
                    adoption of the Samnite treaty at Rome, they had persistently asserted that the
                    Romans were attempting under threats of war to intimidate them into becoming
                    Roman citizens; and how little that was a thing to be desired had <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> been shown, they said, by the Hernici, since those
                    who had been permitted to do so had chosen their own laws in preference to Roman
                    citizenship, while those who had not been given an option were to have
                    citizenship thrust upon them as a punishment. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>cf</reg> . </hi> chap. xliii. 23 f. for the two groups. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>because</reg> of such expressions, publicly uttered in their assemblies,
                    the Roman People decreed that war should be made upon the Aequi. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>both</reg> consuls set out for the new seat of operations, and took up a
                    position four miles from the enemy's camp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <name>The</name> army of the Aequi, who for many years had made no war on their
                    own account, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> while Aequians had volunteered for service in
                        other armies, they had engaged in no war as a nation —at any rate with Rome
                        —since <date when="-0388">388 B.C.</date> (vi. iv. 8). </note> like a
                    hastily levied militia, under no definite commanders and subject to no supreme
                    authority, were in a state of panic. <reg>some</reg> were for offering battle,
                    others for defending <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> the camp.
                        <name>The</name> consideration that affected most of them was the
                    devastation which their farms would suffer and the subsequent destruction of
                    their cities, which they had left <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    inadequately garrisoned. <reg>and</reg> so when a proposal was heard —amongst
                    many others —which disregarded the common welfare and made every one think of
                    his own interest, to wit, that in the first watch they should leave the camp,
                    and going their several ways, <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> carry off all
                    their possessions from the fields and defend their cities by means of their
                    walls, they all with loud acclaim adopted it. <name>The</name> enemy were
                    scattered over the countryside when at break of day the Romans came <pb
                        n="p.349"/> out and formed in order of battle, and encountering <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 304</note> nobody,
                    advanced at a quick pace towards the <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Aequian
                    camp. <reg>but</reg> not perceiving any outposts before the gates or anybody on
                    the rampart, and missing the usual noises of a camp, they were troubled by the
                    unaccustomed silence, and apprehending an <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    ambush, halted. <reg>later</reg> , when they had scaled the rampart and found
                    everything deserted, they attempted to follow the enemy by his tracks; but the
                    tracks, which led in all directions —as they would when an army had dispersed
                    —at first <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> bewildered them.
                        <reg>afterwards</reg> they found out through their scouts what the enemy
                    designed to do; and attacking his cities in succession, one after another, they
                    captured thirty —one of them within fifty days, in every instance by assault.
                        <reg>of</reg> these the greater number were dismantled and burnt, and the
                    Aequian name was almost <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> blotted out.
                        <reg>a</reg> triumph was celebrated over the Aequi; and warned by the
                    example of their downfall, the Marrucini, Marsi, Paeligni, and Frentani sent
                    ambassadors to Rome to sue for peace and friendship. <name>These</name> nations,
                    at their request, were granted a treaty of alliance. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <reg>in</reg> the same year a government clerk, Gnaeus Flavius, the son of
                    Gnaeus, was curule aedile. <reg>born</reg> in humble circumstances —his father
                    being a freedman —he was, for the rest, a man of shrewdness and eloquence.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>i</reg> find in certain annals that being in attendance upon the aediles,
                    and perceiving that the tribes were supporting him for aedile, but that his name
                    was thrown out because he was acting as a recorder, he put away his tablet and
                    took an oath that he would keep no record. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The tribes were beginning to enter their votes in
                        favour of Flavius, but the aedile presiding at the election refused to admit
                        his candidacy, on the score that as an apparitor, a paid civil servant, he
                        might not hold a magistracy. <name>Flavius</name> thereupon renounced his
                        position as secretary and declined to serve as such at the election.
                            <reg>with</reg> Livy's narrative in this chap. <hi rend="italics"
                            >cf.</hi>
                        <reg>plin</reg> . <hi rend="italics">N. H.</hi> xxxiii. i. 17-19, and
                        Gellius, vii. (vi) 9, who quotes Piso as his authority, and uses language so
                        much like Livy's as to suggest that this annalist was Livy's source also. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.351"/> Licinius Macer alleges that he had ceased some time <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 304</note> before to
                    act as secretary, having been already a tribune, and on two occasions a
                    triumvir, once on the commission which had charge of the night —watch, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These were commonly called <hi
                            rend="italics">tresviri capitales,</hi> and were police commissioners,
                        who besides the duty referred to in the text, were charged with assisting
                        the magistrates who had criminal jurisdiction, and particularly with
                        executing sentences of death. <name>Liv</name> . <hi rend="italics">
                            <reg>per</reg> . </hi> xi. would indicate that the office was not
                        introduced until about <date when="-0289">289 B.C.</date>
                    </note> and again on one appointed to found a colony. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <reg>at</reg> all events there is no difference of opinion about the
                    stubbornness of his contention with the nobles, who despised his lowly birth.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> published the formulae of the civil law, which had been filed away
                    in the secret archives of the pontiffs, and posted up the calendar on white
                    notice —boards about the Forum, that men might know when they could bring an
                    action. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>he</reg> dedicated a temple of Concord in the precinct of Vulcan, greatly
                    to the resentment of the nobles; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and Cornelius
                    Barbatus, the chief pontiff, was forced by the unanimous wishes of the people to
                    dictate the form of words to him, though he asserted that by custom of the
                    elders none but a consul or commanding general might dedicate a temple.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>so</reg> , in accordance with a senatorial resolution, a measure was
                    enacted by the people providing that no one should dedicate a temple or an altar
                    without the authorization of the senate or a majority of the tribunes of the
                    plebs. —I will relate an incident, of no importance in itself, which may serve
                    to show how the plebs asserted their liberties against the arrogance of the
                    nobles. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Flavius</name> had come to make a call upon a colleague who was sick, and
                    the young nobles who were sitting by his bed with one consent omitted to rise on
                    his entering; whereupon he ordered his curule chair to be fetched in, and from
                    his official seat gazed at his adversaries, who were choking with resentment.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <reg>now</reg> Flavius had been elected aedile by the faction of the market
                    —place, <pb n="p.353"/> which had become powerful in consequence of the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 304</note> censorship
                    of Appius Claudius. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <name>Claudius</name> had been the first to debase the senate by the appointment
                    of the sons of freedmen, and afterwards, when no one allowed the validity of his
                    selection, and he had failed to gain the influence in the senate —house
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> which had been his object, he had
                    distributed the humble denizens of the City amongst all the tribes, and had thus
                    corrupted the Forum and the Campus Martius. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The centuriate comitia met in the Campus Martius, the
                        tribal comitia in the Forum. <reg>membership</reg> in the formen assembly
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> —now for the first time imparted to
                        the tradesmen and artisans who were not freeholders —implied also member
                        ship in the latter. <name>The</name> result of this reform was to extend the
                        franchise to a large class of citizens, many of whom were men of substance. </note>
                    <reg>and</reg> so great was the indignation over the election of Flavius that
                    many of the nobles laid aside their golden rings <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> and medals. <reg>from</reg> that time the citizens were
                    divided into two parties; the men of integrity, who favoured and cherished right
                    principles, tended one way, the rabble of the marketplace another; until Quintus
                    Fabius and Publius Decius became censors, and Fabius, partly for the sake of
                    harmony, partly that the elections might not be in the hands of the basest of
                    the people, culled out all the market —place mob and cast them into four tribes,
                    to which he gave the name <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> of Urban.
                        <name>The</name> arrangement, they say, was so gratefully received, that by
                    this regulation of the orders he purchased the surname of the Great, which not
                    all his victories had been able to procure him. <reg>it</reg> was Fabius too, so
                    it is said, who instituted the parade of the knights on the fifteenth of July. </p>
                <pb n="p.355"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
