<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to forty-five -
                    40</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">William A. McDevitte, Sen. Class. Mod. Ex. Schol.
                    A.B.T.C.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title> History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to the end,
                                with the epitomes and fragments of the lost books </title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>William A. McDevitte</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="1854" xml:id="p.1854"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XL.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> When Philip had ordered the children of those whom he had put to death, to
                        be sought after as hostages, Theoxena, fearing the king's passion for her
                        own children and those of her sister, who were still quite young, brought
                        forward swords and a cup in which there was poison, and persuaded them to
                        escape, by putting an end to their existence, the mockery that awaited them;
                        after administering which advice, she in company with her husband plunged
                        headlong from the ship into the sea. The quarrels between Perseus and
                        Demetrius, the sons of Philip, king of Macedon, are related; arid how that
                        Demetrius was first assailed by accusations invented through his brother's
                        guile, and among the rest, an impeachment for parricide and aspiring to the
                        throne, and at last, since he was the friend of the Roman people, cut off by
                        poison; and the king- dom of Macedon, on the death of Philip, fell to
                        Perseus. It contains likewise the exploits successfully achieved by very
                        many commanders in Liguria, and against the Celtiberians in Spain. Under the
                        Janiculum, in the field of L. Petillius, the secretary, the books of Numa
                        Pompilius were found by the labourers of the field, enclosed in a stone
                        chest, written in both Latin and Greek characters; in which, when the
                        praetor, to whom they had been brought, had read very many things calculated
                        to overthrow the present system of religion, he swore to the senate that
                        their being read and preserved would be detrimental to the state. And by a
                        decree of the senate they were burned in the Comitium. The colony of Aquilia
                        was planted. Philip, worn out by the pangs of conscience, because,
                        influenced by the false information of his other son Perseus, he had by
                        poison removed from life's scene his son Demetrius, both resolved on the
                        punishment of Perseus and desired to leave his friend Antigonus, rather than
                        him, as his successor. But, whilst forming this project, he was hurried off
                        by death. Perseus received the kingdom. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> AT the commencement of the next year, the
                    consuls and praetors determined the provinces by lot. For the consuls there was
                    no province to be decreed, except Liguria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    city jurisdiction fell to Marcus Ogulnius Gallus; that among foreigners, to
                    Marcus Valerius; of the Spains, the Hither, to Marcus Fulvius Flaccus; the
                    Farther, to Publius Manlius; Sicily, to Lucius Caecilius Denter; and Sardinia,
                    to Caius Terentius Istra. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls were
                    ordered to hold levies, for <pb n="1855" xml:id="p.1855"/> Quintus Fabius had
                    written from Liguria, that the Apuani seemed inclined to a renewal of
                    hostilities, and that it was to be feared that they would make an irruption into
                    the district of Pisae. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From the Spains, also,
                    they received intelligence that the Hither province was in arms; that the war
                    still continued with the Celtiberians: that, in the Farther province, because
                    the praetor had been for a long time indisposed, military discipline was relaxed
                    by intemperance and inactivity. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For these
                    reasons it was decreed that new armies should be raised; four legions for
                    Liguria, that each might contain five thousand two hundred foot, and three
                    hundred horse, and to these same were added, fifteen thousand foot and eight
                    hundred horse of the Latin allies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These were
                    to complete the two consular armies. They were ordered, also, to enrol seven
                    thousand foot and four hundred horse, of the allies and Latins, and to send them
                    into Gaul to Marcus Marcellus, whose command was prolonged on the expiration of
                    his consulship. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were ordered to be
                    levied, of Roman citizens, four thousand infantry and two hundred cavalry, and
                    of the allies, seven thousand infantry with three hundred cavalry, which should
                    be also led into both Spains. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And to Quintus
                    Fabius Labeo, with the army which he had in Liguria, was the command prolonged
                    for a year. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The spring of this year was remarkable for
                    storms. On the day before the feast of Pales, a tremendous hurricane arose about
                    mid-day, and made havoc in many places, both sacred and common. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It threw down the brazen statues in the Capitol; tore away
                    a gate from the temple of Luna, which is on the Aventine, and fastened it to the
                    back parts of the temple of Ceres; overturned other statues in the Circus
                    Maximus, together with the pillars on which they stood; tore off several cupolas
                    from the roofs of temples, and scattered them in an unseemly manner. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> This storm was converted into a prodigy, and the
                    aruspices ordered it to be attended to. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the
                    same time expiation was made, because it had been reported that a three-footed
                    mule was born at Reate, and that the temple of Apollo, at Formiae and at Caieta,
                    was struck with lightning. On account of these prodigies, a sacrifice of twenty
                    larger victims was offered, and there was a supplication of one day's
                    continuance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> About the same time information
                    was obtained from a letter of Aulus Terentius, the <pb n="1856" xml:id="p.1856"
                    /> propraetor, that Publius Sempronius, after being sick for more than a year,
                    had died in the Farther province: on this account the praetors were ordered to
                    set out sooner for Spain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The foreign
                    embassies were then brought before the senate; and first, those of the kings
                    Eumenes and Pharnaces, and of the Rhodians, complaining of the sufferings of the
                    inhabitants of Sinope. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There came also, about
                    the same time, the ambassadors of Philip, the Achaeans, and Lacedaemonians.
                    Answers were given to these, after Marcius, who had been sent to inspect the
                    affairs of Greece and Macedonia, had first received an audience. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> To the Asiatic kings and the Rhodians, they answered,
                    that the senate would send ambassadors to examine into those matters. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcius had increased their anxiety respecting
                    Philip; for, he acknowledged that the latter had acquiesced with the will of the
                    senate in such a manner, as to render it very evident, that he would conform to
                    it no longer than necessity obliged him; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> nor
                    was it difficult to see, that he intended to renew hostilities, and that every
                    thing which he then said and did had a tendency that way. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Now, in the first place, he removed almost the whole body
                    of the citizens, with their families, from the maritime cities, into Emathia,
                    which is its modern name, it was formerly called Paeonia; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> he gave up those cities to be inhabited by Thracians, and
                    other barbarians, thinking that this kind of people would prove more faithful to
                    him in case of a war with Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This
                    proceeding caused great discontent over all Macedonia; and of those who, with
                    their wives and children, left their dwellings, few concealed their grief in
                    silence; and, their hatred overcoming their fear, imprecations against the king
                    were heard, as they proceeded along in groups. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    His mind, rendered savage by these things, entertained suspicions of all men,
                    places, and seasons; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> at last he began to
                    confess openly, that he had nothing sufficiently safe without seizing and
                    confining the sons of those whom he had destroyed, and sending them out of the
                    world at different times. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This cruelty, horrible in itself, the
                    calamities of one particular family rendered still more so. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Philip had, many years before, put to death Herodicus, a
                    Thessalian of distinction; and afterwards his sons-in-law. His daughters were
                    left widows, having each a little son. The names of the women <pb n="1857"
                        xml:id="p.1857"/> were Theoxena and Archo. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Theoxena, though courted by many, rejected every offer of marriage. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Archo married a certain Poris, by far the first of
                    the Aenean nation; and, after bearing him many children, died, leaving them all
                    quite young. Theoxena then, in order that her sister's children might be
                    educated under her own inspection, married Poris, <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> and as if she herself had borne them all, treated her own
                    and her sister's sons with the same affectionate care. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When she heard of the king's order for seizing the children
                    of the persons who had been put to death, supposing that they were destined to
                    afford sport not only to the king's lust, but to that of his guards, she formed
                    in her mind a horrid project, and had the hardiness to declare, that she would
                    kill them <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> all with her own hand, rather than
                    they should come into the power of Philip. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Poris, abhorring the mention of such a dreadful deed, told her that he would
                    carry them away to Athens, to some faithful friends, and would himself accompany
                    them in their flight. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They all went from
                    Thessalonica to Aenea, to a stated sacrifice, which they offer yearly, with
                    great solemnity, in honour of Aeneas, the founder of the nation. Having spent
                    the day there, in the anniversary feast, about the third watch, when all were
                    asleep, they embarked in a vessel ready prepared by Poris, as if intending to
                    return to Thessalonica; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but their design was
                    to cross over to Eubœa. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> However, daylight
                    surprised them at a small distance from the land, struggling in vain against a
                    contrary wind, and the king's officers, who commanded the garrison of the port,
                    despatched an armed bark to bring back their ship, with a strict injunction not
                    to return without it. When they were now drawing nigh, Poris was intently
                    occupied in animating the rowers and sailors, and, at times, raising his hands
                    towards heaven, supplicated the gods to assist him. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Meanwhile, the woman, with desperate fury recurring to the
                    shocking design which she had long premeditated, dissolves some poison, and
                    produces swords; then, placing the cup in their view, and unsheathing the
                    swords, she says, <quote> Death is our only refuge. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> These paths lead thither, by whichever of them each
                        one's inclination leads them to adopt, let them escape the tyranny of the
                        king. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Come then, dear youths, let those
                        of you who are the elder, first take the sword; or, if a slower death is
                        your choice, drain the cup. </quote> At the same time the enemy was fast <pb
                        n="1858" xml:id="p.1858"/> approaching, and she, who urged them to despatch
                    themselves, was urgent; the young men, having put an end to their lives, some by
                    the one and some by the other fatal expedient, were thrown expiring into the
                    sea. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then, embracing her husband and
                    companion in death, she plunged into the deep. The king's officers then took
                    possession of the ship, deserted by its owners. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The barbarity connected with this deed added
                    fresh fuel to the flame of public resentment kindled against the king, insomuch
                    that most people uttered imprecations on himself and his children; which curses
                    being in a short time heard by all the gods, caused him to vent his cruelty on
                    his own blood relations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For Perseus, when he
                    perceived that the popularity and high reputation of his brother Demetrius among
                    the Macedonian people, and interest among the Romans, increased more and more
                    every day, and that no hope was left him of obtaining the crown save by the
                    instrumentality of some wicked device, bent all his thoughts to that one object.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But not thinking himself alone strong
                    enough even for the dastardly project, which he meditated in his effeminate
                    mind, he began to tamper with each of his father's friends by dark suggestions.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At first, several of these showed an
                    appearance of rejecting with scorn any such overtures, because they entertained
                    higher expectations from Demetrius. Afterwards Philip's animosity to the Romans
                    increased every day, which Perseus fomented; but Demetrius, with all his might,
                    opposed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Foreseeing the fatal doom of the
                    youth, who heeded not a brother's guile, and thinking that they must lend their
                    assistance to the accomplishment of what was likely to take place, and cherish
                    the hopes of the more powerful, they united themselves to Perseus. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> They defer the execution of other measures till their
                    proper season; for the present, it seems good that the king should by every
                    strenuous exertion be inflamed against the Romans, and urged to form resolutions
                    for war, to which he had already of his own accord turned his attention.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the same time, in order that Demetrius
                    might be a greater object of suspicion every day, they used deliberately to
                    prolong the conversations even to the use of insulting language towards the
                    Romans; thereupon, when some depreciating their manners and institutions, some
                    their military achievements, some the appearance of the city itself, unadorned
                        <pb n="1859" xml:id="p.1859"/> either by public or private structures;
                    others spoke scornfully of some particular individuals among their principal
                    men. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On these occasions, the young prince
                    unwary, both out of affection for the Roman nation, and opposition to his
                    brother, by maintaining their cause in all things, rendered himself an object of
                    suspicion to his father, and a fit subject for their accusations. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> His father therefore kept him a stranger to all his
                    designs respecting the Romans; he was entirely devoted to Perseus, and held with
                    him, daily and nightly, deliberations on that subject. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The envoys had returned whom he happened to have sent to
                    the Bastarnians, to solicit aid, and brought with them from thence young men of
                    distinction, and some of royal extraction; one of whom promised his sister in
                    marriage to Philip's son, and the connexion with that nation raised the king's
                    spirits. Hereupon Perseus said, <quote> What does that avail? <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> There is by no means as much protection afforded by
                        foreign aid, as there is danger arising from domestic treachery. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> I am unwilling to call him traitor, but a spy we
                        certainly have in our bosom, and although the Romans have restored to us his
                        body, since he was a hostage at Rome, yet they still possess his heart. The
                        faces of almost all the Macedonians are turned towards him, and they think
                        they are to have no other king but him whom the Romans would give them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> By such discourses the old man's mind,
                    distempered in itself, was stimulated to passion, and these imputations he
                        <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> received deeper in his mind, than
                    appeared from his countenance. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened to be the time of the purification
                    of the army; which ceremony is thus performed: —The head and fore part of a dog
                    cut through the middle is laid at the right side of the way, and the hinder part
                    with the entrails at the left. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Between the
                    parts of the victim, thus divided, the forces are led under arms. In the front
                    of the van, are carried the remarkable suits of armour of all the kings of
                    Macedon, from the remotest origin; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> next
                    follows the king himself, with his children; then the royal cohort and body
                    guards, and the remaining body of the Macedonians close the rear. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The two young sons of the king attend by his side;
                    Perseus being now in his thirtieth year, Demetrius five years younger; the
                    former in the full strength of manhood, the latter in its bloom; the mature
                    offspring of a fortunate <pb n="1860" xml:id="p.1860"/> parent, if his mind had
                    been influenced by reason. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The custom was,
                    that when the purificatory sacrifice was finished, the army should perform their
                    evolutions, and the two lines divided on both sides should engage in a mock
                    fight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The young princes were appointed
                    commanders in this mock engagement; but it was not the mere representation of a
                    battle, for they engaged as if they were fighting for the throne: many wounds
                    were given with stakes, nor was any thing but the steel wanting to give it the
                    form of a regular battle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The party which was
                    under the command of Demetrius, was far superior. While Perseus was vexed
                    thereat, his considerate friends rejoiced; and said, that that very circumstance
                    would afford grounds for impeaching the youth. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Each of the princes gave an entertainment that
                    day to his comrades, who had exercised under his command. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Perseus being invited to supper by Demetrius, refused; kind
                    hospitality and youthful merriment led both to excess in wine. Thereupon mention
                    was made of the mock engagement, and numerous remarks were thrown out against
                    the antagonists in such a manner as not to spare even the leaders themselves.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To learn these expressions, a spy was sent
                    from among the guests of Perseus; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but not
                    conducting himself with sufficient caution, he was detected by some young men
                    who happened to come out of the banqueting-room, and severely beaten. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Demetrius, knowing nothing of this matter, said,
                        <quote> Why do we not go to my brother, join with him in merriment, and by
                        our frankness and gaiety assuage his resentment, if any, arising from the
                        engagement, as yet remains? </quote> All with one accord cried out that they
                    would attend him, except those who were afraid of the immediate revenge of the
                    spy that had been beaten by them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When
                    Demetrius pressed these also, they concealed swords under their clothes, with
                    which they might defend themselves if any violence should be offered. In the
                    case of domestic discord, nothing that is concealed can remain so. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Both houses were full of spies and traitors. An
                    informer ran on before to Perseus, and told him, that four young men, armed with
                    swords, were coming with Demetrius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Though the
                    reason was evident, (for he had heard that his guest had been beaten by them,)
                    yet, for the purpose of blackening the matter, he ordered his gate to be locked,
                    and from the upper part of the house and the windows facing the street, he
                    drives away the <pb n="1861" xml:id="p.1861"/> revellers, as if they were come
                    to murder him, from the entrance to the gate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Demetrius flushed with wine, having for a little exclaimed loudly at his being
                    shut out, returns home to his own feast entirely ignorant of the meaning of the
                    whole proceeding. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next day, Perseus, as soon as an opportunity
                    of seeing his father was afforded him, entered the palace, and with looks
                    expressive of disquietude stood silent in the presence of his sire, but at some
                    distance. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of whom when his father inquired
                        <quote>if all was well, and what was the cause of that sadness?</quote> he
                    answers, <quote> Know that it is by the sufferance of another that your son
                        survives. We are now attacked by my brother with no secret treachery; he
                        came by night to my house, with armed men to take away my life, and it was
                        by shut doors, and the protection afforded by the walls, that I was saved
                        from his fury. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he had inspired into his father a horror
                    mixed with wonder, he adds, <quote>If you can listen to me, I shall cause you to
                        understand the affair as an evident truth.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But Philip replied that he would hear him, and
                    ordered Demetrius to be instantly summoned. He then sent for two friends of
                    advanced age, Lysimachus and Onomastus, (who never interfered in the juvenile
                    disputes of the brothers, and were of late rare visitors in the palace,) that he
                    might have their assistance in counsel. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While
                    his friends are coming he walked about by himself, secretly revolving many
                    things in his mind; his son still standing at a distance. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> On being told that they had arrived, he retired with his
                    two friends, and the same number of his life-guards, into an inner apartment; he
                    permitted each of his sons to bring in three persons unarmed. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Here, having taken his seat, he says, <quote> I, the most
                        unhappy of fathers, sit here as judge between my two sons, the accuser and
                        the accused of the crime of fratricide; about to find, in my nearest of
                        relations, the foul stain either of falsehood or a commission of crime.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For a long time, indeed, I have
                        apprehended an impending storm, after I perceived your mutual looks, which
                        showed no sign of brotherly affection, and after I had overheard some
                        expressions. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But I sometimes cherished the
                        hope that your passions would subside, and that your suspicions could be
                        removed; that even enemies lay down their arms and form a treaty, and that
                            <pb n="1862" xml:id="p.1862"/> the private disputes of many have been
                        ended; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and I trusted that the remembrance
                        of your fraternal relationship would at some time or other occur to you, and
                        of the simplicity and intimacy that subsisted between you in your boyish
                        days; and finally, of my instructions, which, I fear, I have fruitlessly
                        poured into deaf ears. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> How often have I,
                        in your hearing, mentioned, with abhorrence, examples of the disagreements
                        of brothers, and recounted the dreadful consequences of them, by which
                        themselves, their offspring, their houses, and their kingdoms, have been
                        utterly ruined. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> I have represented, on
                        the other hand, more laudable examples; also the social intercourse between
                        the two kings of the Lacedaemonians, beneficial to themselves and to their
                        country for many ages; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and that this same
                        state, after the custom of each one arbitrarily seizing on absolute power
                        prevailed, was quite overturned. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then,
                        that these brothers, Eumenes and Attalus, raised their dominions (from so
                        small circumstances, that they were almost ashamed of the title of king) to
                        an equality with mine, or with those of Antiochus, or indeed of any monarch
                        of this age, and by nothing else than by brotherly concord. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Nor did I decline showing you examples even from
                        among the Romans that I had either seen or heard; as of Titus and Lucius
                        Quintius, who carried on the war against me; the two Scipios, Publius and
                        Lucius, who vanquished Antiochus; and their father and uncle, the lasting
                        harmony of whose life even death could not dissolve. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> But neither could the wickedness of the former,
                        attended by an issue suitable to their crimes, deter you from your foolish
                        quarrels; nor could the sound judgment and good fortune of the latter bend
                        you to wisdom. While I am alive and in health, you have both in your hopes
                        and wicked desires laid hold on my inheritance. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> You wish me to live just so long as that, surviving
                        one, I should, by my death, make the other king without a competitor.
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> You cannot endure to have either
                        brother or father. You have no sense of affection, no religion, your
                        insatiable passion for regal sway alone has supplied the place of all other
                        feelings. Come, then, pollute your father's ears, contend with mutual
                        accusations, as you soon will with the sword; speak openly either whatever
                        truth you can, or are pleased to invent. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        My ears are now opened, which henceforward will be shut against <pb n="1863"
                            xml:id="p.1863"/> all secret charges of one against the other. </quote>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> When with fu- rious passion he had uttered
                    these words, tears gushed from the whole assembly and a sorrowful silence long
                    prevailed. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At length Perseus spoke to this effect: "I
                    ought then, it seems, to have opened my gate in the night, and admitted those
                    armed revellers, and held out my throat to their swords; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> since nothing less than the perpetration of the deed can
                    gain belief, and since I, who have been assailed by secret treachery, am
                    accosted in the same language as a robber and an assassin might expect.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is not without reason, that those
                    people say that you have but one son, Demetrius; and that I am supposititious,
                    and born of a concubine; for if I held in your breast the rank of a son, or the
                    affection due to one, you would wreak your anger not on me, who complain of
                    discovered treachery, but on him who was the author of it; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> nor would my life be so worthless in your eyes, that you
                    should neither be moved by the danger which I have already undergone, nor by
                    that to which I must be exposed in future, if punishment be not inflicted on the
                    assassins. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If, therefore, it be our doom to
                    die secretly let us be silent, only offering prayers to the gods that the
                    wickedness commenced with me may terminate in me, and that you be not aimed at
                    through my side. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But if, as nature itself
                    suggests to those encompassed with perils in a desert place, to implore
                    assistance even from men whom they had never seen, so I, on seeing a sword drawn
                    against me, may be allowed to raise my voice. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    I beseech you then, by your own person, by the name of father, (and you long
                    know which of us reveres that title most,) that you may hear me in the same
                    manner as you would if, roused by cries and lamentations by night, you had come
                    up, when I was crying for help, and in the dead of night had found Demetrius,
                    with armed men, in the porch of my house. What I should, at that time, and in
                    that case, have exclaimed with terror, I now, next day, lay before you in form
                    of a complaint. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Brother, it is long since you
                    and I lived together on the terms of mutual hospitality; you certainly wish to
                    be king; this my expectation, my age, opposes, the law of nations opposes, the
                    ancient practice of Macedon opposes, and moreover the judgment of my father
                    opposes. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These you can surmount by no other
                    means than by shedding my blood. You are making every scheme and every attempt.
                    Hitherto, <pb n="1864" xml:id="p.1864"/> either my care or fortune has prevented
                    the fratricide you intended to commit. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Yesterday, on occasion of the purification, the military exercise and mock
                    representation of a fight, you almost rendered it a bloody battle; nor was I
                    saved from death by any other means than by suffering myself and my party to be
                    overcome. Pretending brotherly sport, you wanted to drag me from a hostile fight
                    to your house to supper. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Father, do you think
                    that I, to whom they came in arms, that they might drink with me, would have
                    supped there with unarmed guests. Do you think that I would have been in no
                    danger from their swords by night, when they almost killed me with stakes, of
                    which you were a spectator. Why, Demetrius, did you come at that time of night;
                    why an enemy come to a person provoked; why with young men in arms? <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> I did not venture to trust myself with you as a
                    guest, and shall I admit you as a reveller, coming with armed men? Father, if
                    the gate had been open, you would be preparing my funeral at this moment, in
                    which you are hearing my complaint. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I do not,
                    as an accuser, urge any thing for the purpose of accusation; nor by collecting
                    doubtful circumstances, in a train of artful arguments. For what can he say?
                    Does he deny that he came to my gate with a large party, or that there were
                    armed men with him? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Send for the persons,
                    whom I will name; they who dared to do this, might dare to do any thing;
                    nevertheless, they will not dare to deny it. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    If I brought before you any who had been caught within my doors in arms, you
                    would consider this an evident proof; consider those who confess in the same
                    light as if actually caught in the fact. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Curse now thirst for dominion. Call up the
                    furies, the avengers of the wrongs of brothers; but, father, let not your curses
                    be undiscriminating. Separate and distinguish the assassin, and him by treachery
                    assailed, and charge the guilty head. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Let him,
                    who intended to kill a brother, feel the wrath of the gods, of his father; and
                    let him, who was to have perished by a brother's wickedness, find refuge in his
                    father's compassion and justice. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For where
                    else shall I seek refuge, who cannot find safety in the solemn purification of
                    your army, in the exercise of the troops, in my own house, in a feast, nor in
                    the night, which nature's bounty granted to mankind for a season of repose.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If I go to my brother, according to his
                    invitation, <pb n="1865" xml:id="p.1865"/> I must die. If I admit my brother to
                    a party of pleasure within my own gates, I must die. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Neither by going, nor by staying, do I escape secret
                    treachery. Whither then shall I betake me? Father, I have courted nothing save
                    the gods and thee. I have not the Romans, to whom I may fly. They seek my
                    destruction, because I grieve at the injuries which they have done you; because
                    I resent your being deprived of so many cities, so many nations, and, lately, of
                    the coast of Thrace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They have no hope that
                    Macedonia will ever be their property, while either you or I am safe. If a
                    brother's wickedness shall have carried off me, and old age thee, or if even
                    this should not be waited for, they know that both the king and kingdom of
                    Macedonia will become theirs. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If the Romans
                    had left you any thing beyond the limits of Macedon, I would suppose that even
                    that had been left me as a shelter. But I have protection enough in the
                    Macedonians. You were an eye-witness yesterday of the attack made on me by the
                    soldiers. What did they want, but the steel? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    And what they wanted, in the day, my brother's guests took to themselves in the
                    night. Why need I mention the greater part of the nobles, who have placed all
                    their hopes of honour and fortune in the Romans, and in him who is all-powerful
                    with the Romans? Nor, in truth, do they prefer him merely to me, his elder
                    brother, but, they want little of preferring him to yourself, his king and
                    father. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For, he is the person out of regard to
                    whom the senate remitted to you the intended punishment, who now screens you
                    from the Roman arms; who thinks it fit that your advanced age should be under
                    obligation to, and dependent on, his youth. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Him the Romans, him the cities freed from thy jurisdiction, and him the
                    Macedonians, rejoicing at the peace with Rome, defend; but for me, father, what
                    hope or protection have I any where except in thee? </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> What do you suppose to be the intention of the letter lately sent to you
                        by Titus Quintius, in which he not only says, that you acted wisely for your
                        own interest in sending Demetrius to Rome, but also advises you to send him
                        back again, with a greater number of ambassadors, and nobles of Macedonia?
                        Titus Quintius is now his counsellor, and master, in every thing. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Having renounced you his father, he has
                        substituted him in your place. There in preference to all other places their
                        secret plans are concocted. When he desires <pb n="1866" xml:id="p.1866"/>
                        you to send greater numbers, and the chief men of Macedon, they are seeking
                        assistants in their schemes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For those who
                        go from this place unchanged and uncorrupted, and impressed with the idea
                        that they had Philip as their king, return from thence tainted —infected by
                        Roman blandishments. Demetrius alone is every thing to them. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> They give him the title of king already, even in
                        his father's life-time. If I express my indignation at these things, you
                        must forthwith understand that the crime of thirsting for dominion has been
                        laid to my charge; not only by others, father, but even by you. But this
                        charge, if made against both, I do not admit; for whom do I remove from his
                        place, that I may succeed in his room? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> My
                        father alone is before me; and that he may long be so, I entreat the gods.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I his survivor, (and may I be so only
                        on these terms, if, by my desert, he shall wish me to be so,) shall receive
                        the inheritance of his kingdom, provided my father shall bequeath it to me.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He covets rule, and covets it with
                        criminal passion, since he hastily overleaps the order of age, of nature, of
                        the Macedonian custom, and of the laws of nations. An elder brother stands
                        in his way, to whom by right, and by the wish of his father, the kingdom
                        belongs. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Let him be carried off: I shall
                        not be the first that acquired a kingdom by spilling a brother's blood. My
                        father, being old, and forlorn from being bereaved of his son, will rather
                        fear for himself, than revenge his son's death. The Romans will rejoice,
                        they will approve, they will defend the deed. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Father, these prospects are uncertain, but they are not
                        groundless. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For the matter stands thus:
                        you can repel from me the fatal danger, by inflicting punishment on those
                        who have taken up arms to kill me; if success attend the daring deed, you
                        the very same shall not be able to avenge my death. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Perseus concluded his speech, the eyes of
                    all present were turned to Demetrius, as if he were going to reply immediately.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then, when it was evident to all that,
                    bathed in tears, he was unable to speak, silence for a long time reigned: at
                    length necessity itself, inasmuch as they called on him to speak, overcame his
                    grief, and he began thus: "Father, all the aids which heretofore have been the
                    privilege of the accused, my accuser has preoccupied. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> By his tears, counterfeited for the purpose of working
                    another's ruin, he has caused my unfeigned tears to be suspected by you.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Although, ever since I <pb n="1867"
                        xml:id="p.1867"/> returned from Rome, he, by holding secret consultations
                    with his confederates, labours night and day to insnare me, yet nevertheless he
                    represents me in the character, not only of a conspirator, but of an open
                    assassin and murderer. He terrifies you with his danger, in order to hasten,
                    through your means, the ruin of an innocent brother. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He asserts, that he has a place of refuge no where in the
                    world, that I may have no remaining hope even in thee. Circumvented, destitute,
                    and helpless as I am, he loads me with odium arising from foreign favour, which
                    proves detrimental rather than advantageous. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Then how, accuser-like, has he blended that which was the crime of this night
                    with other invectives against my conduct, that he might, by representing the
                    tenor of the rest of my life, throw a colour of guilt both on the late
                    transaction, the true nature of which you shall soon understand; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and that he might support the other groundless
                    insinuations respecting my views, wishes, and designs, by this latter,
                    fictitious, fabricated story. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He had, at the
                    same time, this design, that his accusation might appear to be sudden and by no
                    means premeditated, as if occasioned by sudden fright and disturbance of this
                    night. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But, Perseus, if I were a traitor
                    against my father and his government; if I had formed plans with the Romans, or
                    with other enemies of my father, the tale of last night ought not to have been
                    waited for; I ought to have been long ago brought to answer for my treason.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And if the former charge apart from the
                    latter were unfounded, and tended to discover your hatred towards me, rather
                    than my guilt, it ought on the present day also to be either omitted or
                    postponed to some future period; in order that it might clearly appear, whether
                    I plotted against you; or you, with indeed a strange and singular kind of
                    hatred, against me. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> However, I will, as well
                    as I am able in my present unforeseen perturbation of mind, distinguish those
                    matters which you have confounded; and I will unveil the plot of the preceding
                    evening, whether mine or yours. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Perseus
                    wishes it to be believed, that I had formed a design to take his life, with the
                    view, forsooth, that having removed <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> the
                    elder brother, on whom by the law of nations, by the custom of Macedonia, and
                    likewise by your judgment, as he says, the kingdom was to devolve, I, the
                    younger, should succeed in the room of him whom I had slain. What, then, can be
                    the meaning of that other part of his speech, where he <pb n="1868"
                        xml:id="p.1868"/> says that the Romans were courted by me, and from my
                    reliance on them that I conceived hopes of the crown? <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> For, if I believed that the Romans possessed such
                    influence, that they could appoint whomsoever they pleased king of Macedon, and
                    if I had such confidence in my interest with them, what need was there of
                    fratricide? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Could it be my wish to wear a
                    diadem stained with a brother's blood, or to become execrable and odious in the
                    eyes of those very people, with whom whatever interest I may happen to have, has
                    been procured by zeal, or at least affected integrity of conduct? <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> unless you believe that Titus Quintius, by whose
                    power and advice you allege I am at present governed, though he lives in such
                    cordial affection with his own brother, would recommend to me to murder mine?
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> He has united for me, not only the favour
                    of the Romans, but the opinions of the Macedonians, and the concurring
                    sentiments almost of all the gods and men, by reason of all which he cannot
                    believe that he would prove equal to me in the competition. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> Yet the same man accuses me of having (though I was
                    inferior to him in every mode of proceeding) had recourse to an act of
                    wickedness as my last resource. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Do you wish
                    that the formula of the judicial inquiry should be to this effect, that
                    whichever feared lest the other should seem more worthy of the throne, shall be
                        <milestone n="20??" unit="section"/> deemed guilty of designing his
                    brother's destruction? </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "But let us examine the process of this
                    accusation, in whatever manner it has been fabricated. He has arraigned me of
                    attempting his life, by several methods; and all these modes of attack he has
                    crowded into the space of one day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I intended
                    to kill him by day when we engaged after the purification, and, if it seems good
                    to the gods, even on the day of purification. I intended, when I invited him to
                    supper, to take him off by poison of course. I intended, when some armed persons
                    followed me to join his party in their conviviality, to kill him with the sword.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> You see what sort of opportunities were
                    chosen for this murder; those of sport, feasting, and revelling. What? on what
                    sort of a day! On the day in which the army was purified; in which, after the
                    royal armour of all the former kings of Macedon was carried in procession
                    between the divided victim, when we two only rode along with you, father, at
                    your sides, and the body of the Macedonian troops followed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Now, even supposing that I <pb n="1869" xml:id="p.1869"/>
                    had formerly been guilty of some crime requiring expiation, could I, after being
                    purified and expiated in this sacred solemnity, at the very time especially when
                    I was looking at the victim laid on each side of our road, revolved in my mind
                    fratricide, poisons and swords prepared against the feast? With what other
                    sacred rites could I afterwards atone for the guilt of a mind, contaminated with
                    every kind of villany? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But whilst his
                    understanding, blinded by a desire for accusing, wishes to render every thing an
                    object of suspicion, it confounds one thing with another. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> For if I intended to take you off by poison at supper, what
                    could be more incongruous with my design, than to provoke you to rage by an
                    obstinate contest and engagement, that you might have reason to refuse, as you
                    did, my invitation to supper? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But when, in
                    your anger, you had refused, whether ought I to have taken pains to pacify you,
                    that I might find another opportunity, since I had got the poison ready, or
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> to pass over, as it were, from that
                    design to another, namely, that of killing you with the sword, and on that same
                    day, under pretence of feasting with you? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If I
                    thought that you declined supping with me, through fear for your life, how could
                    I suppose that you would not, through the same fear, have declined drinking with
                    me also. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Father, I have no cause to blush, that on a
                    festival day, among companions of my own age, I should have indulged too freely
                    in wine; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and I wish you would also inquire
                    with what cheerfulness and mirth yesterday's entertainment, at my house, was
                    rendered festive, that joy also (perhaps a blamable one) increasing it, our
                    party not having been worsted in the fight. This my present misfortune, and my
                    fears, have effectual dissipated the fumes of the liquor; but, if these had not
                    intervened, we, the conspirators, would have been now lying fast asleep.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If, Perseus, I designed to storm your
                    house, and <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> after the house had been taken to
                    kill the owner, ought I not to have refrained from wine for that one day, and to
                    have kept my soldiers sober? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And that I should
                    not be the only one to defend my cause with excessive candour, my brother
                    himself also, not in the least inclined to malice or suspicion, says, I know
                    nothing more, I charge them with nothing more, than that they came in arms to
                    drink with me. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If I should ask, From what
                    source have you become acquainted with that very circumstance? you must
                    necessarily acknowledge, either <pb n="1870" xml:id="p.1870"/> that my house was
                    full of your spies; or that my companions took arms so openly, as that every one
                    could see them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Lest he should seem either on
                    a prior occasion to have made any investigation, or now to adduce arguments for
                    the purpose of convicting, he desired you to inquire of the persons whom he
                    would name, whether they had swords, in order that, as it were, in a doubtful
                    case, when you had investigated into that which they themselves confessed, they
                    might be deemed convicted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Why do you not
                    rather desire inquiry to be made after this, whether they carried swords for the
                    purpose of killing you; whether by my direction and knowledge? this you wish to
                    be believed, and not that which they confess, and what is, indeed, notorious,
                    they say they carried them for the purpose of defending themselves. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Whether they acted right or wrong, let them account
                    for their own conduct. My cause, which is no way affected by this act, do not
                    blend with it. Explain whether we intended to attack you openly, or secretly. If
                    openly, why had we not all swords? why had no one a sword except those who had
                    beaten your spy? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If privately, what was the
                    arrangement of our plan? Were four to remain, in order to fall on you in your
                    sleep, when the banquet broke up, and I your guest had departed? <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> How would they have escaped detection, as being
                    strangers, and belonging to me; and, above all, being liable to suspicion,
                    because they had been in a quarrel a little before? But how were they to have
                    escaped after having killed you? Could your house have been taken and stormed by
                    two swords? </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Why not rather, having dropped that fable of last night, recur to what
                        really grieves you, what kindles your envy? Say, —Why, Demetrius, is mention
                        made any where of your mounting the throne? <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Why do you appear, to some, a more worthy successor to your father's
                        dignity than I? Why do you disturb with doubt and anxiety my hopes, which
                        would be certain if you were not in being? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        These are the thoughts of Perseus, though he does not express them; these
                        make that man my enemy, these create my accuser; these fill your house,
                        these your kingdom, with accusations and suspicions. But, father, as I ought
                        not now either to hope for the crown, or perhaps ever to contend for it,
                        because I am the younger brother, and because you wish that I should yield
                        to the elder; so neither ought I at any former time, or at the present, to
                        act <pb n="1871" xml:id="p.1871"/> in such a manner as to appear undeserving
                        of you my father, and of all. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For I should
                        attain that by my own vices, not by yielding to him on whose side is law
                        both human and divine, not by moderation. You upbraid me with the Romans;
                        and what ought to be deemed an honour, you convert into a crime. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> I did not request, that I should either be
                        delivered a hostage to the Romans, or sent as an ambassador to Rome. Being
                        commissioned by you, I did not refuse to go. On both occasions, I conducted
                        myself in such a manner, as to be no disgrace to you, to your kingdom, or to
                        the Macedonian nation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You, therefore,
                        father, have been the cause of my friendship with the Romans. As long as
                        peace shall subsist between you and them, so long will I also continue in
                        friendship with them; but, if war should arise, I, the same who have been
                        there a hostage, and no unprofitable ambassador in my father's behalf, will
                        be their most determined enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor do I,
                        this day, require that the favour of the Romans should be any advantage to
                        me; I only entreat that it be not detrimental. It neither commenced in war,
                        nor is it reserved for war. I have been a pledge of peace; and, to procure a
                        continuance of peace, I was sent ambassador. Let neither be esteemed an
                        honour or a crime. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Father, if I have been
                        guilty of any undutiful behaviour towards you, or any criminal behaviour
                        towards my brother, I beg to be freed from no punishment. If I be innocent,
                        let me not, I beseech you, be destroyed by envy when I cannot by crime. My
                        brother's accusation, this day, is not the first that he has brought against
                        me; but it is the first made openly, and owing to no offence given him by
                        me. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If my father were angry with me, it
                        would become you, the elder brother, to intercede for the younger, you to
                        obtain pardon for his youth, and you for his error; but in the very person
                        from whom I ought to receive protection, in him I meet my ruin. From a feast
                        and revelry I have been hurried, almost half asleep, to plead my cause on a
                        charge of fratricide. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Without advocates,
                        without patrons, I am compelled to plead my own cause. If I were to speak
                        for another, I would have taken time to study and compose a speech; though,
                        what else would I endanger than that of my reputation for abilities. But,
                        before I knew why I had been summoned, I heard you, in a paroxysm of
                        passion, ordering me to account for my conduct, and my brother accusing me.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He employed against <pb n="1872"
                            xml:id="p.1872"/> me a speech long before prepared and studied; I had
                        only the time in which the accusations were recited, for hearing what were
                        the impeachments. During that short space, whether should I listen to my
                        accuser, or study a defence? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Thunder-struck by the sudden and unthought-of calamity, I was scarcely
                        capable of understanding what was alleged against me, much less of being
                        sufficiently aware what defence I should make. What hope indeed could I
                        have, if I had not my father as judge, with whom, though I am outstripped by
                        an elder brother in affection, yet surely, when accused, I ought not to be
                        outstripped in his compassion. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For my
                        prayer is, that you would save me, for my sake, and for your own; he
                        demands, that, for his security, you should put me to death. What do you
                        think will he do, when you shall have delivered the kingdom into his hands,
                        who even now thinks it reasonable that he should be gratified with my blood? </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> While he was uttering these words, tears
                    interrupted his breath and voice at the same time. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Philip, having sent them away, and conferred a short time
                    with his friends, declared, that <quote> he could not from a single hour's
                        discussion give a formulary judgment on the cause between them, but by a
                        scrutiny into the conduct and manners of both, and a close observation of
                        their words and actions, on occasions great and small. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> That it appeared clearly to all, that the
                    charge relating to the preceding night was effectually refuted; but that
                    Demetrius' favour with the Romans had been an object of suspicion, as being too
                    great. These, as it were, the seeds of the Macedonian war which was to be waged
                    with Perseus, in particular, were sown, when Philip was still alive. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Both the consuls set out into Liguria, which
                    at that time was the only consular province. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A
                    supplication for one day was decreed because prosperity had attended their
                    affairs in that quarter. About two thousand Ligurians came to the extreme
                    borders of the Gallic province, where Marcellus lay encamped, requesting him to
                    receive their submission. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Marcellus, having
                    ordered the Ligurians to wait in the same place, consulted the senate through
                    the medium of a letter. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate ordered
                    Marcus Ogulnius, praetor, to write back to Marcellus, that "it would have been
                    more proper for the consuls, whose province it was, than for them, to decide
                    what might tend to the interest of the republic; <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> that in this case <pb n="1873" xml:id="p.1873"/> too it was their pleasure,
                    if he should receive the surrender of the Ligurians, that their arms should not
                    be taken from them when admitted to a surrender, and that the senate thought
                    proper that the Ligurians should be sent to the consul. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The praetors arrived at the same time in Spain; Publius
                    Manlius in the Farther province, which he had governed in his former
                    praetorship, and Quintus Fulvius Flaccus in the Hither one, and he received the
                    command of the army from Terentius; for the Farther province, by the death of
                    the propraetor, Publius Sempronius, had been without a governor. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians attacked Fulvius Flaccus while
                    besieging a town of the Spaniards, called Urbicua. Many severe actions were
                    fought there, and many of the Roman soldiers killed and wounded. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> They were vanquished by Fulvius' perseverance,
                    because he could by no force be diverted from the siege; the Celtiberians,
                    wearied out with so many battles, retired. The city, having lost their
                    assistance, was within a few days taken and sacked; the praetor bestowed the
                    booty on the soldiers. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Fulvius having taken
                    this town, and Publius Manlius having only gathered together his army, which had
                    been scattered, without having achieved any other memorable action, led their
                    armies into winter quarters. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These were the
                    transactions of that summer in Spain. Terentius, who had come home from that
                    province, entered the city in ovation. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He
                    carried in the procession nine thousand three hundred and twenty pounds' weight
                    of silver, eighty pounds' weight of gold, and two golden crowns of the weight of
                    sixty-seven pounds. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year the Romans were arbitrators
                    on the spot in a dispute, subsisting between the people of Carthage and king
                    Masinissa, about a tract of ground. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This
                    ground Gala, father of Masinissa, had taken from the Carthaginians. Syphax had
                    expelled Gala, and afterwards, from respect to Hasdrubal, his father-in-law, had
                    made a present of it to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In
                    this year, Masinissa had expelled the Carthaginians. This matter was debated
                    before the Romans with no less mental ardour than they had contended for it with
                    the sword, even in the field of battle. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginians claimed the ground first, as having been the property of their
                    ancestors; and next, because it had come to them from Syphax. Masinissa urged,
                    that <quote> he had retaken possession of it as part of his father's kingdom,
                        and held it under the law <pb n="1874" xml:id="p.1874"/> of nations; and
                        that he had the advantage, both in the merits of his cause and in the
                        present possession. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That, in this
                        discussion, he had no other fear, than lest the moderation of the Romans
                        might operate to his loss, whilst they dreaded the appearance of any
                        partiality to a king who was their friend and ally, in prejudice to the
                        common enemy of him and them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The deputies did not alter the right of
                    possession, but referred the cause entire to the senate at Rome. There was
                    nothing done afterwards in Liguria. The inhabitants, at first, retired into
                    pathless forests; and afterwards, disbanding their army, separated in every
                    direction among the villages and forts. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls, too, wished to disband their forces, and consulted the senators on this
                    matter. They ordered that one of them should discharge his troops, and come to
                    Rome to elect magistrates for the year; and that the other, with his legions,
                    should pass the winter at Pisae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A report
                    prevailed, that the transalpine Gauls were arming their young men, and it was
                    not known on what quarter of Italy that multitude would pour itself. The consuls
                    settled the matter between them, —that Cneius Baebius should go home to the
                    elections, because his brother, Marcus Baebius, was a candidate for the
                    consulship. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The assembly for the election of consuls was
                    held, and Publius Cornelius Cethegus and Marcus Baebius Tamphilus were chosen.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The praetors were afterwards elected,
                    Quintus Fabius Maximus, Quintus Fabius Buteo, Tiberius Claudius Nero, Quintus
                    Petillius Spurinus, Marcus Pinarius Posca, and Lucius Duronius. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When the magistrates entered into office, the provinces
                    fell to these by lot in the following order: to the consuls, Liguria; to the
                    praetors, Quintus Petillius, the city, and Quintus Fabius Maximus, the foreign
                    jurisdiction; to Quintus Fabius Buteo, Gaul; to Tiberius Claudius Nero, Sicily;
                    to Marcus Pinarius, Sardinia; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and to Lucius
                    Duronius, Apulia, to which was annexed Istria also, because information was
                    received at Tarentum and Brundusium, that the lands bordering on the sea were
                    infested by robberies committed by foreign piratical ships. The Massilians made
                    the same complaint, with regard to the ships of the Ligurians. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The armies were then voted, to the consuls four Roman
                    legions (each consisting of five thousand two hundred foot and three hundred
                    horse); and fifteen thousand foot and <pb n="1875" xml:id="p.1875"/> eight
                    hundred horse of the allies and Latins. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the
                    Spains, the old praetors were continued in command, with the armies which they
                    then had; and as an augmentation, there were voted for them, three thousand
                    Roman citizens with two hundred horse, and six thousand foot and three hundred
                    horse of the Latin confederates. Nor was the business of the fleet neglected.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls were ordered to constitute
                    duumvirs for conducting that department; by whom, twenty ships which they had
                    launched were to be manned with Roman citizens who had been in servitude; with
                    this proviso only, that free-born officers should command them. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The duty of guarding the coast was so arranged between the
                    duumvirs, each of whom had the command of ten ships, that the promontory of
                    Minerva formed the point of division between them': one was to defend the part
                    on the right, as far as Marseilles; the other, that on the left, extending to
                    the town of Barium. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Many horrid prodigies were seen at Rome this
                    year, and reported from abroad. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It rained
                    blood in the courts of the temples of Vulcan and Concord, and the priests
                    reported that spears moved, and that the image of Juno Sospita at Lanuvium shed
                    tears. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was a pestilence in the country,
                    in the market towns and market-places: and so violent was it in the city, that
                    Libitina could scarcely supply the requisites for burying the dead. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> These prodigies, and the mortality, alarmed the
                    senate so much, that they ordered the consuls to sacrifice to such gods as they
                    thought proper, victims of the larger kinds, and likewise the decemvirs to
                    consult the books. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Pursuant to their
                    direction, a supplication for one day was proclaimed, to be performed at every
                    shrine in Rome. On the authority of these same, both the senate voted, and the
                    consuls announced, that there should be a supplication and holidays for three
                    days throughout the whole of Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    pestilence raged with so great fury, that when, in consequence of the revolt of
                    the Corsicans, and a war raised in Sardinia by the Iliensians, it seemed good,
                    that, from among the Latin allies, eight thousand foot and three hundred horse
                    should be raised, whom Marcus Pinarius the praetor should convey with him into
                    Sardinia; —the <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> consuls returned a
                    representation, that so great a number of men had died, and so many were sick,
                    in every place, that the number of soldiers could not be made up. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The praetor was ordered to take from Cneius Baebius,
                    proconsul, <pb n="1876" xml:id="p.1876"/> who was in winter quarters at Pisae,
                    as many soldiers as would make up the deficiency, and transport them from thence
                    to Sardinia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To Lucius Duronius the praetor,
                    to whose lot Apulia had fallen, was given in addition the charge of making
                    inquiry concerning the Bacchanalians; for some remaining seeds of the evils,
                    formerly excited by those people, had shown themselves there the year before.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The inquiries were rather commenced under
                    the praetor, Lucius Pupius, than brought to any issue; the senate therefore
                    ordered the new praetor to cut up that evil by the roots, lest it might spread
                    again more extensively. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consuls, also, by
                    direction of the senate, proposed to the people certain laws concerning
                    canvassing for elections. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They next introduced the embassies to
                    audience. And first, those of the kings, Eumenes and Ariarathes the Cappadocian;
                    and Pharnaces of Pontus. No further answer was given to these, than that the
                    senate would send persons to examine, and decide their disputes. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Ambassadors from the Lacedaemonian exiles, and from
                    the Achaeans, were next brought in. Hopes were given to the exiles, that the
                    senate would write to the Achaeans that they should be restored. The Achaeans
                    gave an account, to the satisfaction of the senate, of the recovery of Messene,
                    and the settlement of affairs there. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From
                    Philip, king of Macedonia, came two ambassadors also, —Philocles and Appelles;
                    not on any business with the senate, but rather to pry into and inquire
                    concerning the correspondence with the Romans, of which Perseus had accused
                    Demetrius, and, particularly, into that with Titus Quintius, concerning the
                    kingdom, to the prejudice of his brother. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    king had employed these men, believing them unbiassed and inclined in favour of
                    neither party; but they were accomplices and agents of Perseus, in his
                    treacherous designs against his brother. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Demetrius, ignorant of all except the villanous scheme of his brother which had
                    lately broke out, at first neither utterly despaired, nor yet entertained much
                    hope of being reconciled with his father; but afterwards he trusted less and
                    less every day to Philip's affection, having observed that an audience with him
                    was prevented by his brother. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Wherefore, not
                    to increase the suspicions he laboured under, he used extreme circumspection in
                    all his words and actions, and carefully avoided all <pb n="1877"
                        xml:id="p.1877"/> mention of, and communication with, the Romans; to such a
                    degree as to wish that they should not write, as he knew that his father's mind
                    was principally exasperated by charges of this nature. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, lest his troops should be enervated by
                    inactivity, and, at the same time, to avert all suspicion of his harbouring any
                    design of a war with Rome, ordered his army to assemble at Stobi, in Paeonia;
                    and thence he led it on into Maedica. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had
                    been seized with an earnest desire of ascending to the summit of Mount Haemus,
                    for he gave credit to a vulgar opinion, that from thence could be seen at once
                    the Pontic and Adriatic Seas, the river Danube, and the Alps; and he thought
                    that the having a view of all those places, would be of no small consequence
                    towards forming his plans of a war with Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    On inquiry, from people acquainted with the country, respecting the ascent to
                    Mount Haemus, when it was ascertained from them all, that there was no way by
                    which an army could <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> go up it, but that there
                    was access for a small party, lightly accoutred, that he might soothe with
                    familiar discourse his younger son, whom he had determined not to take with him,
                    he first asked his opinion, <quote> whether, as the difficulty of the journey
                        was represented to be so great, he ought to persist in his design, or not? </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He added, that, if he should resolve to
                    proceed, he could not forget the caution of Antigonus, respecting undertakings
                    of that kind; who being tossed about by a violent storm, when he had all his
                    family in the same ship with him, was said to have advised his sons to remember,
                    and hand down to their children, this maxim: <quote> never to have the hardihood
                        to rush into danger themselves, and their whole family together. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He would therefore attend to this warning, and
                    not expose his two sons at once to the chance of those perils, which were
                    represented to lie in his way; and as he meant to take his elder son with him,
                    he would send back the younger into Macedon, as a reserve to his hopes, and as
                    guardian of the kingdom." <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It did not escape
                    Demetrius that he was sent out of the way, that he might not be present at their
                    deliberations, when, in view of those places, they should consult which were the
                    shortest roads to the Adriatic Sea and to Italy, and what was the general plan
                    to be pursued in the war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was obliged
                    however not only to obey his father on the occasion, but to express <pb n="1878"
                        xml:id="p.1878"/> his approbation of the measure, lest a reluctant obedience
                    might beget suspicion. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In order that his
                    journey into Macedonia might be safe, Didas, one of the king's general officers,
                    and governor of Paeonia, was ordered to escort him with a small party of men.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Perseus took this man, as well as most of
                    his father's friends, into the conspiracy to ruin his brother, from the time
                    that it became plain to every one, from the tendency of the king's feelings, to
                    which of the two the inheritance of the throne should come; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> and Perseus charged him on this occasion, to insinuate
                    himself by every kind of obsequiousness into the most familiar communication
                    with Demetrius, so as to draw from him all his secrets, and to pry into his
                    hidden thoughts. The prince, therefore, set out with a guard more dangerous to
                    him than if he had gone alone. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip marched first into Maedica, then
                    crossing the deserts that lie between Maedica and Haemus, at length, at his
                    seventh encampment, he reached the foot of the mountain. There he halted one
                    day, to make choice of those who were to accompany him, and on the next
                    proceeded on his journey. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At first, while they
                    ascended the lower parts of the hills, the fatigue was moderate; but as they
                    advanced upwards, they found the ground more thickly covered with woods, and
                    many places impassable. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They then came to a
                    part of the way so shaded by the thickness of the trees, and the branches so
                    interwoven with each other, that the sky could scarcely be seen; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> but when they drew near to the top, what is rarely
                    seen in other places, the whole tract was covered with so thick a fog, that they
                    were impeded no less than if they were journeying by night. At last, on the
                    third day, they arrived at the summit. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On
                    coming down they did not discountenance the vulgar opinion, more, I suppose,
                    lest the folly of the journey should be exposed to derision, than that it was
                    there possible to see those seas, and mountains, and rivers, so widely distant
                    from each other. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were all greatly
                    fatigued by the difficulty of the way; and chiefly the king himself, in
                    proportion as he was less fitted for exertion, owing to his advanced age.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After sacrificing to Jupiter and the sun,
                    on two altars which he consecrated on the spot, he descended in two days, though
                    the ascent had cost him three; for he was particularly afraid of the night cold,
                    which even at the rising of the dog-star was like the cold of winter. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1879" xml:id="p.1879"/> After struggling with numerous hardships during
                    those days, he found his camp in a condition not more pleasing, for as it lay in
                    a country enclosed on all sides by deserts, there was extreme want. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> He halted therefore but one day, to refresh those
                    whom he had taken with him, and then hastened away into the country of the
                    Dentheletians, with a rapid march close resembling flight. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> These were allies, but the Macedonians, on account of their
                    own necessities, plundered their country, as if it belonged to an enemy;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for they first pillaged the country
                    houses, and afterwards ravaged several villages, overwhelming the king with
                    shame, when he heard the cries of his allies, calling in vain on the gods who
                    witnessed their league, and on himself by name. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> Having carried off corn from hence, he marched back into Maedica, and laid
                    siege to a town called Petra. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He pitched his
                    camp in a plain, and sent his son Perseus with a small party to attack the city
                    from the higher ground. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The townsmen, when
                    danger pressed them on all sides, gave hostages, and for the present surrendered
                    themselves; but as soon as the army retired, regardless of the hostages, they
                    deserted the city, and fled into fastnesses and mountains. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Philip returned to Macedon, after having exhausted his
                    troops by every kind of fatigue, without effecting any purpose, and with his
                    suspicions of his son augmented through the treachery of the governor Didas. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This man being sent, as before mentioned, to
                    escort Demetrius, had, by flattering discourses, and even expressing his own
                    indignation at the treatment shown him, imposed on the open temper of the youth,
                    who was too much off his guard, and justly incensed against his relations; and
                    by a voluntary offer of his assistance in all his measures, and giving a solemn
                    assurance of fidelity, he elicited his secrets. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Demetrius was meditating flight to Rome; and the governor of Paeonia appeared
                    to him to have been sent by the kindness of the gods to aid him in his design;
                    —through whose province he supposed he might make his escape. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This scheme was immediately betrayed to his brother, and,
                    by his direction, discovered to his father. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A
                    letter was brought the king while he was besieging Petra; and in consequence of
                    it, Herodotus, who was the most intimate friend of Demetrius, was taken into
                    custody, and an order was given that Demetrius himself should be guarded,
                    without his perceiving it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These occurrences,
                    added <pb n="1880" xml:id="p.1880"/> to what had passed before, made the king's
                    arrival in Macedon a sad one. The present charges had an effect on him; yet he
                    resolved to wait the return of those whom he had sent to Rome, to procure
                    intelligence of every particular. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After he had
                    passed several months under this uneasiness and anxiety, the ambassadors, who
                    had preconcerted before they left Macedon, what information they should bring
                    home from Rome, at last arrived; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> who, in
                    addition to other grounds of accusation, produced to the king a forged letter,
                    sealed with a counterfeit seal of Titus Quintius. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> In this letter was a kind of interceding apology, that if
                    the young prince, misled by the ambition of reigning, had offered some
                    propositions to him on the subject, yet he was sure that <quote> Demetrius would
                        never attempt any thing against his relations; and that he himself was not
                        such an individual as to appear capable of giving an undutiful advice. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This letter confirmed the charges made by
                    Perseus: Herodotus was, therefore, immediately put to the rack, which he endured
                    a long time, and died under the torture, without giving information of any sort. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus now brought before his father a second
                    formal accusation against Demetrius. His preparations for flight through Paeonia
                    were alleged against him, and his having bribed certain persons to accompany him
                    on the journey; but the forged letter of Titus Quintius pressed hardest on him.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was, however, no severe sentence
                    pronounced openly, in order that he might be put to death in secrecy, which they
                    considered a preferable course: nor was this done through regard for himself,
                    but lest the inflicting punishment on him might unmask designs against the
                    Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The king himself having occasion to go
                    from Thessalonica to Demetrias, sent Demetrius, with the same attendant Didas,
                    to Astraeum in Paeonia, and Perseus to Amphipolis, to receive hostages from the
                    Thracians, and <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> is said, on parting with
                    Didas, to have given him directions to put his son to death. A sacrifice was
                    either intended or counterfeited by Didas, and Demetrius, being invited to be
                    present at the solemnity, came from Astraeum to Heraclea. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> It is said that poison was administered to him in that
                    supper. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The moment he had swallowed the
                    draught, he was conscious of its deadly properties; and being quickly after
                    seized with violent pains, left the banquet, <pb n="1881" xml:id="p.1881"/> and
                    retired to a chamber, where he continued for some time in agony, complaining of
                    the cruelty of his father, inveighing against the fratricide of Perseus, and the
                    villany of Didas. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then one Thyrsis of Stubera,
                    and one Alexander of Berœa, were sent in, who, covering his head and mouth with
                    blankets, suffocated him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In this manner
                    perished that innocent youth, since in his case his enemies were not even
                    content with a common kind of murder. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these matters were passing in Macedon,
                    Lucius Aemilius Paullus, being, on the expiration of his consulate, continued in
                    command, led his army at the commencement of spring into the country of the
                    Ingaunian Ligurians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had no sooner pitched
                    his camp in the enemy's territory, than ambassadors came to him under pretext of
                    suing for peace, but in reality as spies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When
                    Paullus declared that he would enter into no treaty whatever, unless they first
                    surrendered; to this they did not object, but said that it would require time to
                    procure the consent of such a rude kind of people. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> When, for that purpose, a suspension of arms for ten days
                    was granted, then they further requested that his men might not go beyond the
                    mountains for wood or forage, for that was the part of their lands which they
                    had under tillage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After they obtained this
                    request, they collected all their forces behind those mountains, which they had
                    prevented the Romans from approaching; and on a sudden, with a vast multitude,
                    assaulted every gate of his camp at once. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    During that whole day, they prosecuted the attack with such vigour, that Paullus
                    had not time to march out of the camp, nor room to draw out his troops: crowding
                    together at the gates, they defended their camp by blocking up the passage,
                    rather than by fighting. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the enemy had
                    retired a little before sun-set, the general despatched two horsemen to Pisae,
                    to Cneius Baebius, proconsul, with a letter, requesting him to come with all
                    speed to his relief, as he was besieged in the midst of a truce. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Baebius had given up his army to Marcus Pinarius, the
                    praetor, who was going into Sardinia, but he informed the senate by letter that
                    Lucius Aemilius was besieged by the Ligurians, and <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> also wrote to Marcus Claudius Marcellus, whose province lay
                    the nearest, that, if he thought proper, he should march his army out of Gaul
                    into Liguria, and relieve Lucius Aemilius from the blockade. These <pb n="1882"
                        xml:id="p.1882"/> succours would have come too late. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The Ligurians returned next day to the attack of the camp.
                    Aemilius, although he was aware that they would come, and although he could have
                    drawn out his army to meet them, yet kept his men within the lines, in order
                    that he might protract the business until such time as Baebius should come with
                    his army from Pisae. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Baebius's letter caused a great alarm at Rome,
                    and it was <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> increased by this circumstance,
                    that, in a few days after, Marcellus coming to Rome, having given up the command
                    of the army to Fabius, banished all hope of a possibility of the forces, then in
                    Gaul, being removed into Liguria; for hostilities had commenced with the
                    Istrians, who obstructed the settlement of the colony of Aquileia; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> and, as Fabius had led his army thither, he could not
                    quit that country now that the war was begun. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    There was but one hope of relief, and even that too slow for the exigency of the
                    time, —this was, that the consuls might hasten their march into that province,
                    and the senators earnestly pressed them to do so. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls declared that they would not set out until the
                    levies were completed, and that no indolence in them, but the violence of the
                    epidemic sickness, was the cause of their being so long in finishing the levy.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However, they could not withstand the
                    united wishes of the whole senate, in urging them to depart in the military
                    habit, and to proclaim a day to the troops which they had enlisted, on which
                    they should assemble at Pisae. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Authority was
                    given them to enlist hasty levies on their march, wherever they should go, and
                    take them with them. Orders were likewise issued to the praetors, Quintus
                    Petillius and Quintus Fabius, that Petillius should raise two tumultuary legions
                    of Roman citizens, and compel every person under fifty years of age to enlist;
                    and that Fabius should demand from the Latin allies, fifteen thousand foot and
                    eight hundred horse. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Two commanders were
                    appointed to the fleet, Caius Matienus and Caius Lucretius, and ships were put
                    in readiness for them. An order was given Matienus, whose station was at the
                    Gallic bay, to steer his squadron, with all expedition, to the coast of Liguria,
                    and to try if he could be of any service to Lucius Aemilius and his army. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aemilius, when no aid appeared in any quarter,
                    believing that his couriers had been intercepted, resolved to <pb n="1883"
                        xml:id="p.1883"/> wait no longer, but to make a trial of fortune by himself;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and for this purpose, before the coming of
                    the enemy, who now made their attacks with less briskness and vigour, he drew up
                    his troops at the four gates, that, on a signal being given, they might sally
                    out from all sides at once. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To four
                    independent cohorts of auxiliaries, he added two others, and gave the command to
                    Marcus Valerius, lieutenant-general, with orders to make his sally by the
                    praetorian gate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the right gate of the
                    first cohort he formed the spearmen of the first legion, placing the first-rank
                    men of the same legion in reserve: Marcus Servilius and Lucius Sulpicius,
                    military tribunes, had the command of these. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The third legion was drawn up opposite to the left gate of the first cohort,
                    with this difference only, that here the first-rank men were posted in front,
                    and the spearmen in reserve. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Sextus Julius
                    Caesar and Lucius Aurelius Cotta, military tribunes, had the command of this
                    legion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Flaccus,
                    lieutenant-general, with the right wing of the allies, was posted at the
                    quaestorian gate: and two cohorts, with the veterans of the two legions, were
                    ordered to stay within to guard the camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    general himself went round by all the gates, haranguing the troops, and excited
                    the wrath of the soldiers by all the incentives that he could use; at one time
                    declaiming against the treachery of the enemy, who after <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> suing for peace, and obtaining a truce, had come during the
                    very time of that truce, in violation of the law of nations, to attack his camp;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> at another, setting before them what a
                    shame it was that a Roman army should be besieged by Ligurians, people more
                    properly styled robbers than a regular enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>With what face,</quote> continued he, <quote> if you make your way hence
                        by the assistance of others, and not by your own valour, will any of you
                        meet, I do not say those soldiers that conquered Hannibal, or Philip, or
                        Antiochus, the greatest kings and generals of the present age, but those who
                        often drove those very Ligurians before them, flying like cattle through
                        pathless forests, and put them to the sword? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> What the Spaniards, the Gauls, the Macedonians, or
                        Carthaginians, never dared to attempt, a Ligurian enemy dares: <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> he marches up to the trenches of a Roman camp,
                        unexpectedly besieges and assaults it; although, formerly, we, searching
                        carefully the recesses of the forests, were with difficulty able to find
                        them lurking in their hiding-places. </quote> This was <pb n="1884"
                        xml:id="p.1884"/> answered by a general clamour, <quote> that it was no
                        fault of the soldiers, as no one had given them the order to sally forth.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Let him but give the order, and he
                        should soon be convinced, that both the Romans and the Ligurians were the
                        same that ever they were. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There were two camps of the Ligurians on the
                    hither side of the mountains, from which, on the former days, they had marched
                    forward at sun-rise, all in order and regular array. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> On this day they did not take arms until they had made a
                    full meal of food and wine; and then they came out in loose order, and
                    regardless of their ranks, as they expected, with certainty, that the enemy
                    would not venture out beyond the rampart. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As
                    they were approaching in this disorderly manner, the shout being raised by every
                    one in the camp at once, even by the suttlers and servants, the Romans rushed
                    out by all the gates at the same time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This
                    event was so entirely unexpected by the Ligurians, that they were confounded no
                    less than if they had been caught in an ambush. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> For a short time, some appearance of a fight was maintained, and then
                    followed a hasty flight, and a general slaughter of the fugitives. When the
                    signal was given to the cavalry to mount their horses, and not to suffer any to
                    escape, they were all driven in a confused flight to their camps, and soon
                    beaten out of them also. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Above fifteen
                    thousand of the Ligurians were killed, and two thousand five hundred taken. In
                    three days after, the whole state of the Ingaunian Ligurians gave hostages, and
                    surrendered. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The masters and crews of the
                    ships, which had been employed in piracies, were carefully sought for, and
                    thrown into prison; and thirty-two ships of that description were taken by Caius
                    Matienus, one of the two on the Ligurian coast. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Lucius Aurelius Cotta, and Caius Sulpicius Gallus, were sent to Rome to
                    announce these transactions and bring a letter to the senate, and at the same
                    time to request that, as the business of the province was finished, Lucius
                    Aemilius might have permission to leave it, and to bring away his troops and
                    disband them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Both requests were granted by
                    the senate, and a supplication was decreed, at all the shrines, for three days;
                    the praetors Petillius and Fabius received orders, the former to discharge the
                    city legions, the latter to excuse the allies and Latins from the levies, and
                    that the city praetor should write <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> to the
                    consuls, that the <pb n="1885" xml:id="p.1885"/> senate thought proper that the
                    occasional soldiers, enlisted on account of the sudden alarm, should be
                    immediately discharged. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The colony of Gravisca was established this
                    year in a district of Etruria, formerly taken from the Tarquinians, and five
                    acres of land were given to each settler. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    commissioners who conducted it were Caius Calpurnius Piso, Publius Claudius
                    Pulcher, and Caius Terentius Istra. The year was rendered remarkable by a
                    drought, and a scarcity of the productions of the earth. It is handed down on
                    record, that during the space of six months no rain fell. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In the same year, some workmen in the farm of Lucius
                    Petillius, a notary, at the foot of the Janiculum, digging the ground deeper
                    than usual, discovered two stone chests, about eight feet long and four broad,
                    the covers of which were soldered with lead. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Both the chests had inscriptions in Greek and Latin letters, one signifying that
                    therein was buried Numa Pompilius, son of Pompo, and king of the Romans; the
                    other, that therein were contained the books of Numa Pompilius. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> When the owner of the ground had, by the advice of his
                    friends, opened these chests, the one which, according to its inscription,
                    contained the body of the king, was found perfectly empty, without any trace of
                    a human body or of any thing else having ever been in it; the whole being
                    consumed by the decay of such a number of years. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> In the other were found two bundles, tied round with waxed cords, and each
                    containing seven books, not only entire, but apparently quite fresh. Seven were
                    in Latin, and related to the pontifical law; and seven in Greek, containing the
                    doctrines of philosophy, such as might have been known in that age. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias adds, that they contained the
                    doctrines of Pythagoras, supporting, by this plausible fiction, the credit
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> of the vulgar opinion, that Numa had
                    been a disciple of Pythagoras. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The books were
                    read, first, by Petillius's friends, who were present at the discovery.
                    Afterwards, when they became publicly spoken of in consequence of many others
                    reading them, Quintus Petillius, the city praetor, having a desire to read those
                    books, borrowed them from Lucius Petillius, with whom he was familiarly
                    acquainted, in consequence of Quintus Petillius having, when <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> quaestor, made him a notary, and chosen him as one of ten.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On reading the principal heads of the
                    contents, he perceived <pb n="1886" xml:id="p.1886"/> that most of them had a
                    tendency to undermine the established system of religious doctrines, and,
                    thereupon, he told Lucius Petillius, that <quote> he was determined to throw
                        those books into the fire; but before he did so, he gave him leave, if he
                        thought he had any right or appeal to demand the restitution of them, to
                        make the trial, which he might do and preserve his favour. </quote> The
                    notary applied to the plebeian tribunes, and the tribunes referred the matter to
                    the senate. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The praetor declared, that he was
                    ready to make oath that those books ought not to be read or preserved; and the
                    senate decreed, that <quote> the praetor's having offered his oath ought to be
                        deemed sufficient evidence that those books should, without delay, be burned
                            <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> in the comitium, and that such a
                        price should be paid to the owner as might be judged reasonable by the
                        praetor, Quintus Petillius, and the majority of the plebeian tribunes.
                    </quote> The notary did not receive the money. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> The books, however, were burned in the comitium, in the view of the people,
                    the fire being made by the public servants, whose duty it was to assist at
                    sacrifices. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A formidable war broke out this summer in the
                    Hither Spain, where the Celtiberians assembled such a force as they had hardly
                    ever brought into the field before, amounting to no less than thirty-five
                    thousand men. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Flaccus was
                    governor of this province, who, because he heard that the Celtiberians were
                    arming their young men, drew together all the succours he could procure from the
                    allies. But he was by no means equal to the enemy in point of numbers.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Early in spring, he marched his army into
                    Carpetania, and fixed his camp close to the town of Aebura, in which he posted a
                    small garrison. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In a few days after, the
                    Celtiberians pitched their camp at the foot of a hill, about two miles from that
                    place. When the Roman praetor was informed of their approach, he detached his
                    brother, Marcus Fulvius, with two troops of the allied horse, to the enemy's
                    post, to take a view of them; ordering him to advance as near as possible to
                    their rampart, so as to form a judgment of the size of the camp; and not to
                    engage in fight, but to retreat if he should see the enemy's cavalry coming out.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He acted according to his instructions,
                    and for several days there was nothing further done than these two troops
                    showing themselves, and then retreating when the enemy's cavalry sallied from
                    their tents. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At length, <pb n="1887"
                        xml:id="p.1887"/> the Celtiberians came out, with their entire force of
                    horse and foot together, and drawing up in a line, posted themselves about
                    midway between the two camps. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The whole plain
                    was level, and convenient for fighting, and here the Spaniards stood waiting for
                    their enemy. The Roman general kept his men within the rampart during four
                    successive days, while the others constantly drew up theirs, and formed in the
                    same place. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> No motion was made by the Romans;
                    and from that time the Celtiberians, because they had not an opportunity of
                    engaging, remained quiet in their camp; their cavalry only advanced as
                    out-posts, to be ready in case of any movement being made by Fulvius. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Both parties went for wood and forage behind their
                    own camps, neither interrupting the other. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Roman praetor thought that, by his
                    inactivity for so many days, he had created in the Celtiberians a firm
                    persuasion that he would not be first in any movement, he ordered Lucius
                    Acilius, with the left wing of allies and six thousand provincial auxiliaries,
                    to make the circuit of a mountain behind the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    enemy, and as soon as he should hear the shout, to pour down from them on their
                    camp. This party, to avoid being seen, set out in the night. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> At the dawn of day Flaccus sent Caius Scribonius, a
                    praefect of the allies, with the allied cavalry of the left wing, to the enemy's
                    rampart; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> when the Celtiberians, observing that
                    they approached nearer, and were also more numerous than usual, all their
                    cavalry poured forth from the camp, and at the same time the signal is given to
                    the infantry to sally forth. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Scribonius,
                    according to his instructions, no sooner heard the neighing of the enemy's
                    cavalry than he wheeled about and retreated to the camp, on which they pursued
                    with the more violence. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> First the cavalry, and
                    in a short time the line of infantry, came up, confidently expecting that they
                    should be able to assault the camp before night, and they were five hundred
                    paces, not more, from the rampart. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Flaccus,
                    therefore, thinking that they were now drawn far enough from their camp, to
                    hinder them from giving it any succour, as he had his troops already formed
                    within the works, burst out from three sides at once; and at the same time
                    raised the shout, not only to inspire ardour for the fight, but also that the
                    party on the mountain might hear it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor did
                    these make any delay, but, according <pb n="1888" xml:id="p.1888"/> to their
                    orders, poured down on the camp, where five thousand men, not more, were left to
                    guard it, and when the smallness of their numbers, the <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> multitude of the assailants, and the unexpectedness of the
                    affair, had struck terror into them, the camp was taken almost without a
                    struggle. Acilius set fire to that part of the camp which was most exposed to
                    the view of the combatants. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians in the rear of their own line
                    first observed the flames, and the news spread quickly through the whole army,
                    that the camp was lost, and was even then completely in a blaze, which filled
                    them with dismay, while it gave fresh spirits to the Romans; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> for now the shouts of victory raised by their friends
                    struck their ear, and the enemies' camp appeared all on fire. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The Celtiberians hesitated for some time, uncertain how to
                    act, but when they considered that, in case of a defeat, they had no place of
                    refuge, and that their only hope now lay in their arms, they renewed the combat
                    afresh, with greater obstinacy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their centre
                    was pressed hard by the fifth legion; but their men advanced with more
                    confidence against the left wing, where they saw that the Romans had posted the
                    provincial auxiliaries, troops of their own kind. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The left wing of the Romans was now near being defeated,
                    had not the seventh legion come to its support. At the same time, the troops
                    left in garrison at Aebura came up during the heat of the battle, and Acilius
                    closed on the enemy's rear. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thus surrounded,
                    the Celtiberians were, for a long time, cut off in great numbers, and at last
                    the survivors betook themselves to flight in every direction. The cavalry, in
                    two divisions, were sent in pursuit, and made great havoc. There were killed, of
                    the enemy, on that day, twenty-three thousand, and four thousand seven hundred
                    were taken, with more than five hundred horses, and eighty-eight military
                    ensigns. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The victory was great, but not
                    obtained without loss of blood. There fell, of the two Roman legions, a few more
                    than two hundred men; of the Latin confederates, eight hundred and thirty; and
                    of foreign auxiliaries, about two thousand four hundred. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The praetor led back his victorious troops to their tents:
                    Acilius was ordered to remain in the camp which he had taken. Next day the
                    spoils of the enemy were collected, and those whose bravery had been remarkable
                    were presented with gifts in a public assembly. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The wounded were then conveyed into the town
                    of <pb n="1889" xml:id="p.1889"/> Aebura, and the legions marched through
                    Carpetania, against Contrebia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The garrison
                    there, on being invested, sent for succours to the Celtiberians; but these were
                    long in coming, not because they were unwilling to give assistance, but that
                    after they had begun their march the roads were rendered impassable, and the
                    rivers swelled by continued rains, so that their countrymen, despairing of
                    assistance, capitulated. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Flaccus also, being
                    compelled by the same severe weather, brought his whole army into the city.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians, who were on their march,
                    having heard nothing of the capitulation, when the rains abated at last, passed
                    the rivers, and came to Contrebia. When they saw no camp before the town,
                    supposing either that it was removed to the other side, or that the enemy had
                    retired, they came up towards the walls in careless disorder. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans made a sally against them from two gates, and
                    attacking them in confusion completely routed them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The same circumstance that disabled them from standing
                    their ground and maintaining a fight, — their not having come in one body, or in
                    a regular disposition, round their standards, —proved favourable to many in
                    making their escape: for they scattered themselves widely over the whole plain,
                    so that the Romans could no where enclose any considerable body of them.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> However, there were about twelve thousand
                    killed, and more than five thousand taken, with four hundred horses, and
                    sixty-two military standards. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The stragglers,
                    flying homewards, turned back another body of Celtiberians, whom they met on the
                    road, by informing them of the surrender of Contrebia, and their own defeat;
                    whereupon they all immediately dispersed, and made the best of their way to
                    their several villages and forts. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Flaccus,
                    leaving Contrebia, led his legions through Celtiberia ravaging the country; he
                    stormed many forts until at length the greatest part of the Celtiberians
                    surrendered. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the transactions of that year in
                    Hither Spain. In the Farther province, Manlius fought several successful battles
                    with the Lusitanians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the same year the
                    Latin colony of Aquileia was established in the Gallic territory. Three thousand
                    foot soldiers received each fifty acres, centurions a hundred, horsemen a
                    hundred and forty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The three commissioners who
                    conducted the settlement were Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica, Caius Flaminius
                    and Lucius <pb n="1890" xml:id="p.1890"/> Manlius Acidinus. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Two temples were dedicated this year, one to Venus Erycina,
                    at the Colline gate; Lucius Porcius Licinius, duumvir, son of Lucius, dedicated
                    it. This temple had been vowed, during the Ligurian war, by Lucius Porcius, the
                    consul. The other to Piety, in the herb-market. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Manius Acilius Glabrio, the duumvir, dedicated this temple; he erected a
                    gilded statue of his father Glabrio, the first of the kind that ever was seen in
                    Italy. This was the person who vowed the temple, on the day whereon he gained
                    the decisive victory over <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> king Antiochus, at
                    Thermopylae, and who, likewise, had contracted for its being built, in pursuance
                    of a decree of the senate. At the same time when these temples were consecrated,
                    Lucius Aemilius Paullus, the proconsul, triumphed over the Ingaunian Ligurians.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He carried in the procession twenty-five
                    golden crowns, but no other article of either gold or silver. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Many Ligurian chiefs were led captives before his chariot,
                    and he distributed to each of his soldiers three hundred <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 19 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> The arrival of ambassadors from the Ligurians, begging that a perpetual
                    peace might be established, enhanced the reputation of this triumph, <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> and they asserted, that <quote> the Ligurians had
                        come to a resolution never again to take arms, on any occasion, except when
                        commanded by the Roman people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This answer was given to the Ligurians, by
                    Quintus Fabius, the praetor, by order of the senate, that <quote> such kind of
                        language was not new with the Ligurians; but it concerned chiefly their own
                        interest that their disposition should be new, and conformable to their
                        language. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They must go to the consuls,
                        and perform whatever was commanded by them; for the senate would never
                        believe, from any other than the consuls, that the Ligurians were really and
                        sincerely disposed to peace. </quote> Peace however was made with that
                    people. In Corsica, a battle was fought against the inhabitants. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> The praetor, Marcus Pinarius, slew in the field
                    about two thousand of them; by which loss they were compelled to give hostages,
                    and a hundred thousand pounds of wax. The army was then carried over into
                    Sardinia, and some successful battles were fought against the Iliensians, a
                    nation, even at the present day, not in every particular friendly to us.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In this year a hundred hostages were
                    restored to the Carthaginians, <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> and the
                    Roman people enabled them to live in peace, not only among themselves, <pb
                        n="1891" xml:id="p.1891"/> but also with Masinissa, who at that time with an
                    armed force held possession of the land in dispute. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls had nothing to do in their
                    province. Marcus Baebius, being summoned home to Rome to preside at the
                    elections, created consuls Aulus Postumius Albinus Luscus and Caius Calpurnius
                    Piso. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus,
                    Lucius Postumius Albinus, Publius Cornelius Mammula, Titus Minucius Molliculus,
                    Aulus Hostilius Mancinus, and Caius Maenius were made praetors. All these
                    entered into office on the ides of March. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In
                    the beginning of this year, in which Aulus Postumius Albinus and Caius
                    Calpurnius Piso were consuls, Lucius Minucius, lieutenant-general, and two
                    military tribunes, Titus Maenius and Lucius Terentius Massilicta, who had come
                    from Hither Spain from Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, were introduced to an audience
                    of the senate by Aulus Postumius the consul. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    These, after informing the senate of the two victories gained, of the submission
                    of Celtiberia, and of the conclusion of the business of the province, and that
                    there was no occasion either to send pay, as usual, or corn to the army for that
                    year, requested, first, that <quote> on account of these successes a
                        thanksgiving should be performed to the immortal gods; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> and, then, that leave should be given to Quintus
                        Fulvius, on his quitting the province, to bring home from it the army which
                        had served under him and many former praetors, with much bravery. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> They represented, that this measure, besides the
                        propriety of it, was in some degree necessary, for the troops were so
                        obstinately bent on it, that it did not seem possible to keep them longer in
                        the province; but, if they were not disbanded, they would either leave it
                        without orders, or, if any one would attempt to detain them by compulsion,
                        would break out into a dangerous mutiny. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate ordered, that Liguria should be the
                    province of both the consuls. The praetors then cast lots for theirs. The city
                    jurisdiction fell to Aulus Hostilius; the foreign, to Titus Minucius; Sicily, to
                    Publius Cornelius; Sardinia, to Caius Maenius; Farther Spain, to Lucius
                    Postumius; and Hither Spain, to Tiberius Sempronius. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> As this last was to succeed Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, and
                    wished that the province might not be stripped of the veteran troops, he spoke
                    thus: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Quintus Minucius, I demand of you, since you assert, in your report,
                        that your province is subdued, do you <pb n="1892" xml:id="p.1892"/> think,
                        that the Celtiberians will always faithfully observe the treaty, so that the
                        province may be kept in obedience without an army? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> If you cannot give us any assurance of, or undertake to
                        answer for, the fidelity of the barbarians, but think that, at all events,
                        there must be an army maintained there, I pray you, <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> whether would you recommend to the senate to send a
                        reinforcement into Spain, in order that those soldiers only who have served
                        out their time may be discharged, and the recruits mixed with the veterans?
                        or to withdraw the veteran legions, and enlist new ones, and send them in
                        their place? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and this, although the
                        contempt entertained for such new recruits might rouse barbarians of more
                        pacific tempers to a renewal of war? would it be a matter easier said than
                        done, to reduce to complete subjection a province naturally fierce, and
                        constantly renewing the war? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A few
                        states, as I am informed, who were awed, more than the rest, by the nearness
                        of our winter quarters, have submitted to our authority and dominion, while
                        those more remote are in arms. This being the case, conscript fathers, I now
                        give notice before-hand, that, with the army at present there, I will
                        undertake to execute the business of the republic; <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> but, if Flaccus bring those legions home with him, I
                        will choose some quiet part of the country for winter quarters, and will not
                        expose raw soldiers to an enemy so remarkably ferocious. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To these questions, which he had been asked,
                    the lieutenant-general answered, that <quote> neither he nor any other could
                        possibly divine what were the sentiments of the Celtiberians, or what they
                        would be in future; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> therefore he could not
                        deny that it would be proper to send an army among a barbarous people, who,
                        though reduced to a state of quiet, were not yet sufficiently inured to
                        subjection; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but whether a new army or a
                        veteran one might be requisite, rested with him to decide who could
                        ascertain with what sincerity the Celtiberians would observe the peace; and
                        who, at the same time, had assurance that the troops would remain quiet, if
                        kept longer in the province. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If a
                        conjecture were to be formed of their intentions, either from their
                        conversations with each other, or from the expressions with which they
                        interrupted the general's harangues, they had openly and loudly declared,
                        that they would either keep their commander in the province, or come home
                        with him to Italy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This dis- <pb n="1893" xml:id="p.1893"/>
                    cussion, between the praetor and the lieutenant-general, was suspended by the
                    consuls introducing other matters; for they thought it right, that their own
                    provinces might be adjusted before they deliberated concerning the army of the
                    praetor. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> An army entirely new was decreed to
                    the consuls: two Roman legions to each, with their proportion of cavalry; and of
                    the Latin allies, the usual number of fifteen thousand foot and eight hundred
                    horse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With these forces, they were directed
                    to make war on the Apuan Ligurians. Publius Cornelius and Marcus Baebius were
                    continued in command, and ordered to hold the government of the provinces until
                    the consuls should arrive. They were ordered then to disband their troops, and
                    return to Rome. Then they deliberated concerning the army under Tiberius
                    Sempronius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls were ordered to enlist
                    for him a new legion of five thousand two hundred foot and four hundred horse;
                    and also a thousand Roman foot and five hundred horse; and to command the allies
                    of Latium to furnish seven thousand foot and three hundred horse. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> With this army it was determined that Sempronius
                    should go into Hither Spain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Permission was
                    granted to Quintus Fulvius, with respect to all those soldiers, whether Romans
                    or allies, who had been transported into Spain previous to the consulate of
                    Spurius Postumius and Quintus Marcius; and likewise to such as, after the
                    junction of the reinforcements, should be found in the two legions, above the
                    number of ten thousand four hundred foot and six hundred horse; <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> and in the Latin auxiliaries above twelve thousand
                    foot and six hundred horse, who had behaved with courage under Quintus Fulvius
                    in the two battles with the Celtiberians, —these, if he thought proper, he might
                    bring home. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thanksgivings were also decreed,
                    because he had managed the republic successfully; and the rest of the praetors
                    sent into their provinces. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius
                    Buteo had his command in Gaul. It was resolved that eight legions should be
                    employed this year, besides the veteran army then in Liguria, which expected to
                    be speedily disbanded; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and that very army was
                    made up with difficulty, in consequence of the pestilence which continued, for
                    the third year, to depopulate the city of Rome and all Italy, </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tiberius Minucius, the praetor, died of this
                    malady; and soon after, Caius Calpurnius, the consul; also many illus- <pb
                        n="1894" xml:id="p.1894"/> trious men of all ranks; so that at last this
                    calamity began to be considered as a prodigy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Caius Servilius, chief pontiff, was ordered to find out proper atonements for
                    the wrath of the gods; the decemvirs to inspect the books, and the consul to vow
                    offerings, and to present gilded statues, to Apollo, Aesculapius, and Health;
                    which he vowed and gave. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The decemvirs
                    proclaimed, on account of the sickness, a supplication of two days in the city,
                    and in all the market-towns and villages; all persons above the age of twelve
                    years offered the supplication, with garlands on their heads, and holding
                    laurels in their hands. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There had, also, crept
                    into people's minds a suspicion of human villany in regard to it, whereupon
                    Caius Claudius, the proctor, who had been substituted in the room of Tiberius
                    Minucius, was commissioned by a decree of the senate, to make inquisition
                    concerning acts of poisoning committed in the city, or within ten miles of it;
                    and Caius Maenius was ordered to do the same, before he passed over to his
                    province, Sardinia, in the market-towns and villages beyond the tenth stone.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The death of the consul was most
                    suspected. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was reported that he had been
                    murdered by his wife, Quarta Hostilia; and when her son, Quintus Fulvius
                    Flaccus, was proclaimed consul in the room of his stepfather, the death of Piso
                    began to excite much more suspicion; for witnesses appeared, who testified,
                    that, after Albinus and Piso were declared consuls, in which election Flaccus
                    had suffered a disappointment, his mother upbraided him with being refused the
                    consulship a third time, and then desired him to make ready to stand candidate
                    again, saying, <quote>she would take such measures that within two months he
                        should be made consul.</quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This expression verified by the event, which
                    was but too real, joined to many other evidences of the same tendency, appeared
                    such strong proof, that Hostilia was condemned. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> In the spring of this year, the levies detained the new consuls at Rome;
                    while the death of one of them, and the holding of the assembly to substitute
                    another in his place, occasioned still further delays. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> In the mean time Publius Cornelius and Marcus Baebius, who,
                    in their consulate, had done nothing worth mention, led their troops into the
                    country of the Apuan Ligurians. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Ligurians, who did not expect an attack
                    before the arrival of the consuls in the province, were surprised, and <pb
                        n="1895" xml:id="p.1895"/> surrendered to the number of twelve thousand men.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Corne- lius and Baebius, having consulted
                    the senate by letter, determined to bring them down from their mountains into a
                    plain country, so far from home, that they should have no hope of a return; for
                    they were convinced, that before this was done no end could be put to the war in
                    Liguria. There was a tract of land in Samnium, the public property of the Roman
                    people, formerly occupied by the Taurasinians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When they intended to transplant the Apuan Ligurians to this country, they
                    published an order, that this people should quit the mountains, with their wives
                    and children, and bring all their effects along with them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Ligurians made, by their ambassadors, many humble
                    supplications that they might not be compelled to relinquish their native home,
                    the soil in which they were born, and the tombs of their forefathers. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> They promised to give up their arms, and deliver
                    hostages. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After they failed in all their
                    solicitations, and were destitute of strength for the maintenance of a war, they
                    obeyed the order. Forty thousand men, of free condition, with their women and
                    children, were transplanted at the expense of the public, and a hundred and
                    fifty thousand sesterces <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1210 <hi
                            rend="italics">l.</hi> 19 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 9 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> were given them, to provide necessaries for their new habitations.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cornelius and Baebius, who removed them,
                    were commissioned to divide and apportion the lands; but, at their own request,
                    the senate appointed five other commissioners, by whose advice they should act.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they had finished this business, and
                    brought home their veteran soldiers to Rome, a triumph was decreed them by the
                    senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These were the first who ever
                    triumphed without having fought an enemy. Hostages only were led before their
                    chariots; for there appeared not, in their triumphs, either spoils to be
                    carried, or prisoners to be led captives, or money to be distributed to the
                    soldiers. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year Fulvius Flaccus, the
                    proconsul in Spain, as his successor did not come to the province at the usual
                    time, having drawn out the troops from their winter quarters, proceeded to lay
                    waste the farther part of Celtiberia, whose inhabitants had not come in to make
                    submission. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But by this proceeding he rather
                    provoked than terrified the spirits of the barbarians; so that, having collected
                    secretly a body of forces, they beset the Manlian pass, through which <pb
                        n="1896" xml:id="p.1896"/> they knew, with certainty, that the Roman army
                    would march. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Gracchus had commissioned his
                    colleague, Lucius Postumius Albinus, who was going to the Farther Spain, to
                    desire Quintus Fulvius to bring his forces to Tarraco, where he intended to
                    discharge the veterans, to distribute the reinforcements among the respective
                    corps, and reorganize the entire army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The day
                    also was mentioned to Flaccus, and that not very distant, on which his successor
                    would arrive. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When tidings of this new
                    arrangement had compelled Flaccus to drop the business which he had undertaken,
                    and to lead away the troops in haste out of Celtiberia, the barbarians,
                    unacquainted with the reason, and supposing that he had discovered their revolt
                    and secret assembling of an army, and that he was retreating through fear, beset
                    the pass with the greater determination. When the Roman army entered this
                    defile, at the dawn of day, immediately the enemy starting up attacked it at two
                    sides at once. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And when Flaccus saw this, he
                    put down the confusion arising among <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the
                    soldiers by giving orders through the centurions that every man should keep his
                    post, in the order of march, and make ready his arms; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> then collecting the baggage and beasts of burden, into one
                    spot, partly by himself, partly by the help of the lieutenants-general, and
                    military tribunes, he formed his troops as the time and place required, without
                    any confusion. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He put them in mind, that they
                    were to engage with men <quote> who had been twice reduced to submission; that
                        guilt and perfidy, not valour or courage, were their only accessions. That
                        these people had put it in their power to make their return to their country
                        which otherwise would have been ignoble, glorious and splendid; for they
                        would now carry home their swords red from the slaughter, and spoils
                        dropping blood. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The time did not allow more to be said, as
                    the enemy were rapidly advancing upon them; the extremities of the wings were
                    already engaged, and quickly after the entire lines. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle was furious in every part, but the
                    success various. The two legions fought with extraordinary bravery, nor were the
                    two cohorts of the allies remiss; but the foreign auxiliaries were hard pressed,
                    by men armed like themselves, and rather a better description of soldiers;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> nor were they able to maintain their
                    ground. The Celtiberians, as soon as they perceived that, in a regular
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> line, and in fair fighting, they were no
                    match for the legions, made a charge against them, <pb n="1897" xml:id="p.1897"
                    /> in the form of a wedge, in which sort of attack they excel so much, that on
                    whatever part they direct their assault they cannot be withstood. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> On this occasion, too, the legions were disordered,
                    and the line was almost broken. When Flaccus observed this disorder, he rode up
                    to the legionary cavalry, asking them, <quote>Have we any support in you? Is the
                        whole army to be lost?</quote> Whereupon they called to him from all sides,
                    to <quote>tell them what he wished to be done; and that it should be instantly
                        attempted.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Cavalry of the two legions, double your troops,</quote> he replied,
                        <quote> and charge the wedge, which is attacking our soldiers; you will make
                        a more violent charge, if you spur your horses without bridles against the
                        foe. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This expedient is recorded to have
                        been often employed by the Roman cavalry with great advantage. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They obeyed his orders, and taking off the
                    bits of the bridle, they spurred in full career through that body twice, forward
                    and backward, breaking their spears to pieces, and making great havoc of the
                    enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians, on this dispersion of
                    their wedge, on which had been their whole reliance, were quite dismayed, and
                    almost giving over the fight, looked about for ways to escape. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> And now, when the allied horse saw this brilliant exploit
                    of the Roman cavalry, they were so inflamed by the example of their bravery,
                    that without waiting for orders, they made a charge on the enemy, while they
                    were in confusion. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then truly all the
                    Celtiberians scatter and fly, and the Roman general, when he saw their backs,
                    vowed a temple to Equestrian Fortune, and games in honour of Jupiter supremely
                    good and great. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The fugitives, dispersing,
                    were pursued with much slaughter, through the whole length of the pass.
                    Seventeen thousand of the enemy are recorded to have been killed on this
                    occasion, and more than four thousand taken, with two hundred and seventy-seven
                    military standards, and near one thousand one hundred horses. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The victorious army pitched no camp on that day. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> This victory, however, was not gained without loss;
                    four hundred and seventy-two Roman soldiers, one thousand and nineteen of the
                    allies and Latins, and besides these three thousand of the auxiliaries perished.
                    The victorious army, having thus reasserted their former renown, finished their
                    march to Tarraco. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The praetor, Tiberius
                    Sempronius, who had arrived two days before, came out to meet Fulvius on the
                    road, and congratulated <pb n="1898" xml:id="p.1898"/> him on the important
                    services which he had rendered to the commonwealth. They then, with perfect
                    unanimity, settled what soldiers they should discharge, and what they should
                    retain; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and Fulvius, embarking the disbanded
                    soldiers in the fleet, set sail for Rome, while Sempronius led the legions into
                    Celtiberia. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Both the consuls led their armies into
                    Liguria, but on different sides. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Postumius,
                    with the first and third legions, invested the mountains of Balista and
                    Suismontium; and, by securing the narrow passes leading thereto with guards, cut
                    off all supplies of provisions; and by want of every thing he reduced them to an
                    entire obedience. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fulvius, with the second and
                    fourth legions, marched from Pisae against the Apuan Ligurians; and having
                    received the submission of that part of them which inhabited the banks of the
                    river Macra, he put them, to the number of seven thousand men, on board ships,
                    and sent them along the Etrurian coast to Neapolis, from whence they were
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> conducted into Samnium, and lands were
                    assigned to them among their countrymen. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    vineyards of the Ligurians of the mountains were cut down and their corn burnt
                    by Aulus Postumius, until, compelled by all the calamities of war, they
                    surrendered and delivered up their arms. From thence Postumius proceeded, by
                    sea, to visit the coast of the Ingaunian and Intemelian tribes. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Before these consuls joined the army which had been ordered
                    to meet at Pisae, Aulus Postumius, and a <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    brother of Quintus Fulvius, Marcus Fulvius Nobilior, had the command of it.
                    Fulvius was military tribune of the second legion. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He in his months <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        As there were six tribunes in each legion, they took the command of it in
                        turn, each holding it for two months. </note> of command disbanded the
                    legion, after obliging the <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> centurions to
                    swear, that they would carry the money in their hands to the treasury, and
                    deliver it to the quaestors. When this was announced to Aulus at Placentia, to
                    which place he happened to have made an excursion, he set out with some light
                    horsemen, in quest of the disbanded men; and such <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> as he could overtake, he sharply rebuked and brought back
                    to Pisae, and then apprised the consul of the whole matter. When he laid the
                    business before the senate, a decree was passed that Marcus Fulvius should be
                    banished into that part of Spain beyond New Carthage; and a letter was given him
                    by the consul, <pb n="1899" xml:id="p.1899"/> to be carried into Farther Spain,
                    to Publius Manlius. The soldiers were ordered to return to their standards; and
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> it was decreed, that, as a mark of
                    disgrace, that' legion should, for that year, receive but half a year's pay. The
                    consul was likewise ordered to sell the person and property of every soldier who
                    should not return to the army. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year Lucius Duronius, who had been
                    praetor the year before, returned with ten ships from Illyricum to Brun- dusium,
                    and leaving the fleet in that harbour, came to Rome, and in giving a recital of
                    the services which he had performed in his province, he threw the blame of all
                    the piracies committed by sea, on Gentius, king of Illyricum, as their undoubted
                    cause. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>From his kingdom,</quote> he said, <quote> came all the ships that had
                        ravaged the coast of the Hadriatic; that he had sent ambassadors on the
                        subject, but they were not even allowed an audience of the king. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some time before this, ambassadors had come to
                    Rome from Gentius, who said, that <quote> when the Romans came for the purpose
                        of holding a conference with the king, he happened to be sick in a remote
                        part of his dominions; and that Gentius requested of the senate, not to give
                        credit to the forged charges which his enemies had made against him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Duronius added, that injuries were offered to
                    many Roman citizens and Latin allies, in Gentius's dominions; some of whom he
                    held in confinement in Corcyra. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was their
                    pleasure that all these should be brought to Rome; that the praetor, Caius
                    Claudius, should inquire into that business; and that until this were done, no
                    answer should be given to king Gentius, or his ambassadors. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Among many others whom the pestilence of this year cut off,
                    several priests also died. Lucius Valerius Flaccus, a pontiff, died of it; and
                    in his room was substituted Quintus Fabius Labeo. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Manlius, who had lately come home from the Farther
                    Spain, and was triumvir of religious feasts, died also; Quintus Fulvius, son of
                    Marcus, then a mere youth, succeeded him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    appointing of a king of the sacrifices in the room of Cneius Cornelius
                    Dolabella, gave rise to a dispute between Caius Servilius, chief pontiff, and
                    Lucius Cornelius Dolabella, naval duumvir; whom the pontiff ordered to resign
                    his office, to the end that he might inaugurate him; and on the duumvir's
                    refusing to do this, a fine was therefore imposed on him by the pontiff; and
                    when the latter appealed, they contended about the affair <pb n="1900"
                        xml:id="p.1900"/> before the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After
                    a majority of the tribes, being called in, had ordered that the duumvir should
                    comply with <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the requisition of the pontiff,
                    and that if he would resign his commission the fine should be remitted, an
                    unfavourable omen from the heavens intervened, which broke off the proceedings
                    of the assembly. After this the pontiffs were prevented by religious scruples
                    from inaugurating Dolabella. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They consecrated
                    Publius Claelius Siculus, who had been installed in the second place. Towards
                    the end of the year, Caius Servilius Geminus, the chief pontiff, also died; the
                    same was decemvir of religious affairs. In his room, as pontiff, Quintus Fulvius
                    Flaccus was nominated by the college; but Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, was elected
                    chief pontiff, though many illustrious men sought that office; and Quintus
                    Marcius Philippus was appointed to the office of the same, as decemvir of
                    religious affairs. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Spurius Postumius Albinus,
                    an augur, died; and the augurs elected into his place Publius Scipio, son of
                    Africanus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On the request of the people of
                    Cumae that year, leave was granted them to use the Latin language in their
                    public business, and that their auctioneers should have a right to use the Latin
                    language in selling. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To the Pisans, offering ground for the
                    establishment of a Latin colony, thanks were returned by the senate, and
                    triumvirs were appointed to conduct that business; these were Quintus Fabius
                    Buteo, Marcus Pompilius Laenas, and Publius Pompilius Laenas. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> A letter was brought from Caius Maenius, the praetor, (to
                    whom, after that the province of Sardinia had fallen to his lot, orders were
                    given to make inquisition concerning sorceries, in places more than ten miles
                    distant from the city,) the purport of which was, <quote> that he had already
                        passed sentence on three thousand people; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        and that still, in consequence of fresh discoveries, the business of the
                        inquisition increased so much on his hands, that he must either drop the
                        prosecution of the inquiries, or give up the province. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Flaccus returned to Rome from
                    Spain, with a high reputation for his military exploits; and while he waited
                    without the city in expectation of a triumph, was elected consul with Lucius
                    Manlius Acidinus. And after a few days, he rode through the city in triumph,
                    accompanied by the soldiers whom he had brought with him. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He carried in the procession a hundred and twenty-four
                    golden crowns, <pb n="1901" xml:id="p.1901"/> together with thirty-one pounds'
                    weight of gold, and of coined Oscan silver a hundred and seventy-three thousand
                    two hundred pieces. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 5592 <hi
                            rend="italics">l.</hi> 17 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He gave out of the booty to each of the
                    soldiers, fifty denariuses; double that sum to a centurion; triple it to a
                    horseman; and the same sums to the Latin allies, with double pay to all.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This year, for the first time, a law was
                    proposed by Lucius Villius, plebeian tribune, ascertaining at what ages men
                    might sue for, and hold each office in the state. Hence the surname Annalis was
                    given to his family. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Four praetors were elected, after a lapse of
                    many years, by the Baebian law, which enacted that four should be elected every
                    alternate year; and the persons appointed were Cneius Cornelius Scipio, Caius
                    Valerius Lavinus, Quintus Mucius Scaevola, and Publius Mucius Scaevola, sons of
                    Quintus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To the consuls, Quintus Fulvius and
                    Lucius Manlius, was decreed the same province as to the preceding ones, and the
                    same number of forces, infantry, cavalry, citizens, and allies. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In the two Spains, Tiberius Sempronius and Lucius Postumius
                    were continued in command, with the same armies which they then had; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> and to recruit their numbers, the consuls were
                    ordered to enlist, of Romans three thousand foot and three hundred horse, and of
                    the Latin allies, five thousand foot and four hundred horse. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Mucius Scaevola obtained by lot the city
                    jurisdiction, and likewise the business of the inquisitions concerning sorcery,
                    in the city, and within ten miles of it; Cneius Scipio, the foreign
                    jurisdiction; Quintus Mucius Scaevola, Sicily; and Caius Valerius Laevinus,
                    Sardinia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul, Quintus Fulvius, before
                    he meddled with any of the public business, declared that <quote> he intended to
                        acquit both himself and the state of the obligation of fulfilling the vows
                        which he had made; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that on the day of his
                        last battle with the Celtiberians, he had vowed to <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> perform games in honour of Jupiter supremely good and
                        great, and to build a temple to Equestrian Fortune; and that by the
                        Spaniards a contribution of money had been made for these purposes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A vote was passed that the games should be
                    performed, and that duumvirs should be appointed to contract for the building of
                    the temple. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> With regard to the expenses, a
                    limitation was fixed, that <quote> no greater sum should be expended on the
                        games than that which had been voted to Fulvius Nobilior, when he <pb
                            n="1902" xml:id="p.1902"/> exhibited games on the conclusion of the
                        Aetolian war; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and that the consul should
                        not, on account of these games, send for, collect, or receive, or do any
                        thing contrary to the decree of the senate passed concerning games in the
                        consulate of Lucius Aemilius and Cneius Baebius. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The senate qualified their vote in this
                    manner, on account of the lavish expense occasioned by the games of Tiberius
                    Sempronius, the aedile, which had been burthensome not only to Italy and the
                    Latin allies, but even to the provinces abroad. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The winter of that year was rendered severe by
                    falls of snow and storms of every kind; those kinds of trees which are
                    susceptible of injury from cold, were all blighted; and it continued at that
                    time somewhat longer than on other occasions. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore a tempest coming on suddenly, and with intolerable violence, shortly
                    after, interrupted the Latin festivals on the mount; and they were celebrated
                    afterwards, pursuant to an order of the pontiffs. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The same storm also threw down many statues in the Capitol,
                    disfigured very many buildings by lightning, as the temple of Jupiter at
                    Tarracina, the white temple at Capua, and a Roman gate; and in some places the
                    battlements of the wall were overthrown. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Among
                    the rest of these prodigies, an account was received from Reate, that a
                    three-footed mule had been foaled there. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On
                    account of those portents, the decemvirs, having been ordered to consult the
                    books, declared to what gods, and with how many victims, sacrifices should be
                    performed; and that on account of very many places being disfigured by
                    lightning, a supplication of one day should be performed at the temple of
                    Jupiter. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then the votive games of the consul
                    Quintus Fulvius were exhibited with great magnificence, during ten days.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Soon after was held the election of
                    censors. Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, chief pontiff, and Marcus Fulvius Nobilior,
                    who had triumphed over the Aetolians, were chosen. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Apparent hostilities existed between these men, which were
                    frequently displayed in many violent disputes, both in the senate and in the
                    assemblies of the people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the election
                    was ended, the censors, according to ancient custom, seated themselves in curule
                    chairs in the Campus Martius, near the altar of Mars; whither in a few minutes
                    came the principal senators, accompanied by the body of the citizens, of whom
                    Quintus Caecilius Metellus spoke as follows: — <pb n="1903" xml:id="p.1903"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Censors, we are not unmindful that you have been just now, by the whole
                        body of the Roman people, set over our morals; and that we ought to be
                        admonished and ruled by you, not you by us. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Nevertheless, that should be pointed out, which in you may either give
                        offence to all good men, or at least what they would wish to be altered.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When we look at you separately, Marcus
                        Aemilius, Marcus Fulvius, we know not, in the whole state, any one person
                        whom, if we were called back again to vote, we could wish to be preferred to
                        you; but when we behold you both together, we cannot avoid fearing that you
                        are but ill associated; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and that the
                        public may not reap as much advantage from your being exceedingly pleasing
                        to every one of us, as injury, from your being displeasing one to another.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You have for many years past harboured
                        an enmity, violent in its degree, and detrimental to yourselves; and it is
                        to be feared, that from this day forward it may prove more detrimental to us
                        and to the state, than it has been to you. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        As to the reasons why we fear this, many observations which might be made
                        occur to yourselves; had you not happened to be implacable they would have
                        engrossed your senses. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These feuds we all
                        beseech you to terminate this day, in that sacred place, and to suffer those
                        whom the Roman people have united by their suffrages, to be united by us,
                        through this re-establishment of friendship also. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> May you, with unanimity and harmony, choose the senate,
                        review the knights, hold the census, and close the lustrum, as truly and
                        sincerely as you would wish that to happen which you express in the words,
                        used in almost all your prayers, 'that this affair may prove good and
                        prosperous to me and my colleague:' <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and
                        cause us men also to believe that you really desire that which you entreat
                        of the gods. Titus Tatius and Romulus, after they had engaged in battle as
                        public enemies, in the midst of the forum of this city, reigned there with
                        unanimity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Not only quarrels, but wars,
                        are ended; and from deadly foes men frequently become faithful allies, nay,
                        sometimes, even fellow-citizens. The Albans, after the demolition of Alba,
                        were brought over to Rome: the Latins, the Sabines, were admitted into the
                        number of citizens. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It is a common
                        saying, and, because founded in truth, has become a proverb, that
                        'friendships ought to be immortal, but enmities mortal. </quote> '
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A roar of approbation burst forth: and
                        <pb n="1904" xml:id="p.1904"/> presently after, the voices of every one
                    present, joining in the same request, interrupted his speech. Then Aemilius,
                    besides other complaints, represented, that through Marcus Fulvius he had been
                    twice deprived of the consulship, which seemed sure. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> On the other hand, Fulvius complained that he had always
                    been assailed by Aemilius, and that security had been given for him, which was
                    attended with great disgrace. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Nevertheless,
                    each of them intimated that if the other would wish, he was ready to submit to
                    the direction of such a number of the most respectable members of the state; and
                    all present urgently repeating their request, they mutually pledged their right
                    hands, and their honour, to dismiss in reality and forget all animosity. Then
                    the whole assembly expressing the highest applause of their behaviour, they were
                    escorted to the Capitol. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Both the attention
                    paid to such a matter by the persons of the first consequence, and the
                    compliance of the censors, were most warmly approved and commended by the
                    senate. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The censors then demanded that a sum
                    of money should be assigned to them, which they might expend in public works;
                    and the customs of one year were accordingly decreed to them. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year the propraetors in Spain,
                    Lucius Postumius and Tiberius Sempronius, settled between them, that Albinus
                    should march through Lusitania, against the Vaccae- ans, and thence return into
                    Celtiberia, and Gracchus penetrate into the remotest parts of that province, if
                    the commotions there were more dangerous. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    First, having made an unexpected assault on the city of Munda, by night, he took
                    it by storm; then, after having received hostages and placed a garrison, he
                    proceeded to attack their forts and ravage the country with fire, until he
                    arrived at another very strong city, (the Celtiberians call it <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> Certima,) there, when he was already advancing his
                    works, deputies came out from the town, whose speech partook of all the
                    simplicity of the earliest times, not dissembling their wishes to continue the
                    war, if they had strength to support it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> —For
                    they requested permission to go into the camp of the Celtiberians, and procure
                    assistance from them; and said, that "if they did not obtain it they would then
                    deliberate apart from them. By the permission of Gracchus they went; and in a
                    few days after brought with them ten other ambassadors. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> It was mid-day. The first thing that they asked of the
                    praetor was, that he would order some <pb n="1905" xml:id="p.1905"/> drink to be
                    given them. After drinking off the first cups, they asked a second time, causing
                    thereby loud laughter from those present, at minds so unpolished, and ignorant
                    of all civilization. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The eldest of them then
                    says, <quote>We have been sent by our nation to ask, on what do you rely that
                        you attack us?</quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To this question Gracchus answered, that
                        <quote> he came relying on an excellent army; which if they chose to see, in
                        order to carry back more certain information to their friends, he would give
                        them an opportunity; </quote> and he orders the military tribunes to draw
                    up, in array, all the forces both horse and foot, and make them go through their
                    exercise in arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After this sight, the
                    ambassadors, being dismissed, deterred their people from attempting to succour
                    the besieged city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the townsmen had from
                    the towers raised fires, (which was the signal agreed upon,) to no purpose, and
                    had been disappointed in their only hope of relief, they capitulated. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> A contribution of two million four hundred thousand
                    sesterces <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 19,375 <hi rend="italics"
                            >l.</hi>
                    </note> was imposed on them; and they were ordered to furnish forty horsemen of
                    the highest rank among them, not under the denomination of hostages, for they
                    were ordered to serve as soldiers, but in reality to be pledges for their
                    fidelity. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From thence Gracchus now marched to the city
                    of Alce, where lay the camp of the Celtiberians, from which the ambassadors had
                    lately come. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he had harassed them for
                    some days with skirmishes, by sending his light troops to charge their advanced
                    guards, he made attacks more important every day, in order to entice them all
                    out of their intrenchments. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As soon as he
                    perceived that his object had been effected, he gives orders to the praefects of
                    the auxiliaries, that after a short contest they should suddenly turn their
                    backs, as if they were overpowered by numbers, and fly with all haste to the
                    camp: in the mean time he himself drew up all his forces in order, within the
                    rampart, at all the gates. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> No long time had
                    intervened, when he saw a body of his own troops flying back, according to the
                    preconcerted plan, and the barbarians following in a disorderly pursuit.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He had his army drawn up within the trench
                    in readiness for this very opportunity. He therefore delayed only so long as to
                    allow his own men to retreat into the camp by a free passage; then, raising the
                    shout, he rushed forth from all the <pb n="1906" xml:id="p.1906"/> gates at the
                    same time. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The enemy did not sustain the
                    unexpected shock. They who came to assault his camp could not defend even their
                    own. For they were instantly routed, put to flight, driven in a panic within
                    their trenches; and at last beaten out of them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> On that day nine thousand of the enemy were killed, and three hundred and
                    twenty taken, with a hundred and twelve horses and thirty-seven military
                    ensigns. Of the Roman army there fell a hundred and nine. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this battle, Gracchus led the legions to
                    ravage Celtiberia. And when he was carrying and driving off all things from
                    every quarter, some states voluntarily, others through fear, submitted to his
                    yoke; within a few days he received the submission of a hundred and three towns;
                    he got immense booty. He then marched back to Alce, whence he came, and set
                    about besieging that city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The townsmen
                    withstood the first assault of the enemy; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> as
                    soon as they found themselves attacked, not only by arms but by works also,
                    having despaired of any protection in the city, they all retired to the citadel.
                    And then at last they sent envoys, and surrendered themselves, and every thing
                    belonging to them, to the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Great
                    plunder was obtained from this. Many prisoners of distinction fell into his
                    power, among whom were two sons and a daughter of Thurrus. This chieftain, who
                    governed those tribes, was by far the most powerful of all the Spaniards.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On hearing the disasters of his countrymen
                    he sent persons to request protection for himself when coming to the camp to
                    Gracchus, and he came. And he first asked him, <quote>Whether the lives of
                        himself and his subjects would be spared?</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the praetor answered that they would; he
                    asked again, <quote>Whether it would be allowed him to bear arms on the side of
                        the Romans?</quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To this too Gracchus assenting, he said,
                        <quote> I will follow you then against my old allies, since they have not
                        thought proper to pay any regard to me. </quote> From that time he united
                    himself to the Romans, and by his brave and faithful exertions he in many places
                    advanced the Roman interest. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this, Ergavia, a celebrated and powerful
                    city, terrified by the disasters of the surrounding states, opened its gates to
                    the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There are some writers who say,
                    that this submission of the towns was not made with sincerity that, from
                    whatever district he might have led the legions, <pb n="1907" xml:id="p.1907"/>
                    hostilities were there renewed forthwith; and that he afterwards fought, near
                    Mount Caunus, a pitched battle with the Celtiberians, from break of day to the
                    sixth hour; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that many fell on both sides, and
                    that the Romans did not perform any feat, from which you might believe that they
                    were not vanquished, excepting that, next day, they offered battle to the enemy
                    remaining in their intrenchments: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that they
                    employed that whole day in collecting the spoils, on the third day they fought
                    again a more desperate battle, then there was no doubt that the Celtiberians
                    were at last completely defeated, and their camp taken and plundered. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Twenty-two thousand of the enemy were killed on that
                    day, more than three hundred taken, and almost an equal number of horses, and
                    seventy-two military standards. This put an end to the war: the Celtiberians
                    concluded a sincere peace, and did not waver in their allegiance as before.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They say also, that during the same summer
                    Lucius Postumius fought twice with success in the Farther Spain against the
                    Vaccaeans, killed thirty-five thousand of the enemy, and took their camp.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It is however more probable, that he came
                    into the province too late to succeed well in that summer. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The censors inspected the senate with sincere
                    unanimity. Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, the censor, who was likewise chief pontiff,
                    was chosen head of the senate; three were expelled from that body. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Lepidus restored some who were rejected by his
                    colleague. They completed these works with the money which had been assigned,
                    and divided between them: —Lepidus built a mole at Tarracina, an unpopular work,
                    because he had estates there, and brought into the account of the public
                    expenditure what ought to have been done at his own expense. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He contracted for the building of a theatre and stage near
                    the temple of Apollo, the whitening of the temple of Jupiter in the Capitol, and
                    the columns around it; he also removed from those columns the statues that stood
                    unseemingly before them, and took down from them the shields and military
                    ensigns of all sorts hung thereon. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Fulvius made contracts for works more numerous and of more use; a haven on the
                    Tiber, and piers for a bridge across it; on which piers Publius Scipio Africanus
                    and Lucius Mummius, who were the censors, many years after, bargained for the
                    erection of arches; a court of justice behind the new bankers' houses, and a
                    fish-market sur- <pb n="1908" xml:id="p.1908"/> rounded with shops, which he
                    sold to private persons; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> also a forum and
                    portico, on the outside of the gate Trigemina; another portico behind the
                    dock-yard, and one at the temple of Hercules; also a temple of Apollo Medicus,
                    behind that of Hope, on the bank of the Tiber. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They had besides, some of the money undivided, and out of this they jointly
                    agreed to pay for water being brought, and arches being made; but Marcus
                    Licinius Crassus hindered this work, for he would not suffer it to be brought
                    through his grounds. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They also established
                    many port duties and customs, and took care that very many public chapels, which
                    had been occupied by private individuals, should be public and consecrated, and
                    open to the people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They likewise made an
                    alteration in the mode of voting; for, through all the regions, they divided the
                    tribes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In consequence of which
                        regulation, all those of each tribe, who <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        were of the same rank and occupation, voted together. </note> according to
                    the different ranks, conditions, and callings of men. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One of the censors, Marcus Aemilius,
                    petitioned the senate, that a sum of money should be voted for the celebration
                    of games, in honour of the dedication of the temples of Imperial Juno and Diana,
                    which he had vowed eight years before, when employed in the Ligurian war. They
                    accordingly voted twenty thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> . <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 64 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He dedicated those temples each in the
                    Flaminian circus; and celebrated theatrical games for three days after the
                    dedication of the temple of Juno, and for two after that of Diana, and each day
                    in the circus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He also dedicated a temple to
                    the deities of the sea <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Neptune,
                        Thetis, and Glaucus.</note> in the field of Mars, which Lucius Aemilius
                    Regillus had vowed eleven years before this, in a naval engagement against the
                    commanders of king Antiochus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Over the gate of
                    the temple was hung up a tablet with this inscription: <quote> This temple was
                        vowed by Lucius Aemilius, the son of Marcus Aemilius, on coming forth from a
                        battle which he fought for the purpose of establishing peace, in which he
                        concluded a mighty war and subdued kings, —because <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> under his auspices, command, and successful gene-
                        ralship, the fleet of king Antiochus, under the very eyes of Antiochus
                        himself and his entire army, cavalry and elephants, was conquered, thrown
                        into confusion, shattered, and put to flight, on the eleventh day before the
                        calends of January; and there on that day thirteen ships of war with all
                        their crews <pb n="1909" xml:id="p.1909"/> were taken. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> When that battle was fought, king Antiochus and his
                        dominions * * * * * * * <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Here are
                            given, in the original, some lines, as the inscription; but so corrupted
                            and so defective, as to be utterly unintelligible. Gronovius endeavours,
                            in vain, to explain them; Crevier gives the matter up. </note>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On this account he vowed a temple to the
                        titular gods of the sea. </quote> In the same manner a tablet was placed
                    over the gate of the temple of Jupiter, on the Capitol. </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Two days after the censors had inspected the
                    senate, the consul Quintus Fulvius marched against the Ligurians; and having
                    with his army crossed over pathless mountains and woody valleys, he fought a
                    pitched battle <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> with the enemy, and not only
                    defeated them in the field, but took their camp the same day. Three thousand two
                    hundred of the enemy, and all that tract of Liguria, surrendered. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The consul brought down all those who surrendered
                    into the low-lands, and posted guards on the mountains. His letters from that
                    province quickly reached Rome, and thanksgivings for three days were voted on
                    account of his successes. The praetors, during these thanksgivings, celebrated
                    divine worship by sacrificing forty victims of the larger kind. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> By the other consul, Lucius Manlius, nothing worth
                    recording was done in Liguria. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Transalpine
                    Gauls, to the number of three thousand, coming over into Italy, without offering
                    to commit hostilities on any one, petitioned the consul and senate for some
                    land, that they might live as peaceable subjects, under the government of the
                    Roman people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the senate ordered them to
                    quit Italy, and enjoined the consul Quintus Fulvius to search after and punish
                    those who had been the first to advise them to cross the Alps. </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year died Philip, king of the
                    Macedonians, being worn out with old age, and grief occasioned by his son's
                    death. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He spent the winter at Demetrias, in
                    great anguish of mind, occasioned both by regret for his son and contrition for
                    his own cruelty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His other son also disquieted
                    his mind, who, both in his own opinion and that of others, was undoubtedly king.
                    The eyes of all were turned to him, and his own old age was desolate. Some only
                    waiting for his death, while others did not even wait for that event. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> By which circumstance he was still more distressed,
                    and with him Antigonus, son of Echecrates, named after his uncle Antigonus, who
                    had <pb n="1910" xml:id="p.1910"/> been guardian to Philip, a man of royal
                    dignity, and famed also for a remarkable battle which he fought against
                    Cleomenes the Lacedaemonian. The Greeks called him the Guardian, to distinguish
                    him from the other princes of that surname. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">They called him also Euergetes, and Soter.</note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His nephew Antigonus, of all the friends whom
                    Philip had honoured with his favours, alone remained uncorrupted; and this
                    faithful attachment to him had made Perseus, who had been in no wise his friend,
                    become now his most inveterate enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He,
                    foreseeing in his mind with what danger to himself the inheritance of the
                    kingdom would fall to Demetrius, as soon as he perceived the king's mind to
                    waver, and that he sometimes sighed with regret for the loss of his son;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> at one time by listening, and at another
                    by making mention of the deed, as being rashly done, he himself was at hand,
                    adding his complaint to the frequent lamentations of the king; —and, as the
                    truth usually affords many traces of itself, he assisted with the most zealous
                    diligence, in order that the whole might be brought to light as speedily as
                    possible. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of the agents employed in that
                    business, those who were most generally supposed guilty, were Apelles and
                    Philocles, who had gone ambassadors to Rome, and had brought the letter under
                    the name of Flamininus, which had proved so ruinous to Demetrius. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> They generally murmured in the palace, that it was a
                    forgery, falsified by the secretary, and that the seal was counterfeited. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But while this thing was rather a matter of
                    suspicion than of certainty, Antigonus accidentally met Xychus, whom he seized
                    and brought to the palace; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> then leaving him in
                    custody of guards, Antigonus went on to the apartment of Philip, to whom he
                    said, <quote> I think I understood from many conversations, that you would value
                        it highly, if you could ascertain the whole truth respecting your sons,
                        which of the two was assailed by the other's deceit and secret machinations.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Xychus, the only man in the world who
                        can unravel this mystery, is now in your power. I met him by accident, and I
                        have brought him to the palace; order him to be called into your presence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On being brought in, he at. first denied; but
                    with such irresolution, as showed that by a slight application to his fears he
                    would become a ready informer. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He did not
                    withstand the sight of the executioner <pb n="1911" xml:id="p.1911"/> and the
                    instruments of torture, but disclosed the whole process of the villany of the
                    ambassadors, and his own services therein. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Persons were instantly despatched to seize the ambassadors, and they apprehended
                    by surprise Philocles, who was present, but Apelles, who had been sent in
                    pursuit of a person called Chaerea, having heard of the information given by
                    Xychus, went over into Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With respect to
                    Philocles, no certain account has been published: some say, that for a time he
                    boldly denied all knowledge of the matter; but that when Xychus was confronted
                    with him, he persisted no longer; others, that he even suffered the rack without
                    confessing. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Philip's grief was renewed and
                    doubled; and he felt his unhappiness, with regard to his children, press the
                    heavier on him, because one of them was not. </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Perseus was told that all was discovered,
                    he was too powerful to think that flight was necessary. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He only took care to keep out of the way, intending to
                    guard himself, in the mean time, during the remainder of Philip's life, from the
                    flame, as it were, of his burning resentment; who, having lost hopes of
                    subjecting the person of Perseus to punishment, meditated on this, as the last
                    resource, that he would not, besides impunity, enjoy the reward of his
                    wickedness also. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Therefore he addresses
                    himself to Antigonus, to whom he was obliged for the discovery of the
                    fratricide; and whom he supposed the Macedonians, considering the fresh renown
                    of his uncle Antigonus, would neither be ashamed nor displeased at having for
                    their king. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Antigonus,</quote> says he, <quote> since I have been brought into such a
                        situation that the being childless, a state which other parents reckon a
                        curse, ought to be wished for by me, I am resolved to transfer to you the
                        kingdom which I received from your uncle, and which his faithful and
                        resolute guardianship not only preserved for me, but even enlarged.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You are the only friend I have, whom I
                        can judge worthy of the throne; and, if I had not one such, I should wish it
                        to perish and become extinct, rather than be a prize to the treacherous
                        villany of Perseus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I shall think
                        Demetrius recalled from the dead, and restored to me, if I can leave you
                        substituted in his room, who alone have wept for his innocent death, and for
                        my unhappy error. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After this discourse he did not fail to
                    advance him by conferring on him honours of every kind; and, as Perseus was
                    absent in Thrace, he went <pb n="1912" xml:id="p.1912"/> round the cities of
                    Macedon, and recommended Antigonus to the chief men; and, had his life been
                    prolonged, there is no doubt but that he would have left him in possession of
                    the throne. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After leaving Demetrias, he staid
                    a very long time at Thessalonica; and when he had gone thence to Amphipolis, he
                    was there seized with a severe sickness. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Yet
                    it was evident that it was a disorder of the mind rather than of the body, and
                    that, owing to his anxieties and want of sleep, for apparitions and phantoms of
                    his innocent murdered son ever and anon disquieted him, he breathed his last
                    uttering awful imprecations on the other. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Nevertheless Antigonus might have been first acquainted with the death of the
                    king, had it not been immediately divulged. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Calligenes, the physician, who had the charge of his treatment, not expecting
                    the king's death, sent to Perseus, on the first appearance of desperate
                    symptoms, messengers who had been previously stationed at different places; and
                    till his arrival he concealed the death of the king from all but those who were
                    in the palace. </p>
                <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus therefore surprised them all, when not
                    expecting, and totally ignorant of, his arrival, and seized on the throne, which
                    was obtained by wickedness. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The demise of
                    Philip happened very seasonably for the purpose of gaining time and collecting
                    strength for the support of a war: for, in a few days after, the nation of the
                    Bastarnians, in consequence of long solicitation, set out from their own abodes,
                    with a large force of infantry and cavalry, and crossed the Danube. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Antigonus and Cotto (the latter was a Bastarnian of
                    distinction, and Antigonus had been sent, much against his will, with this same
                    Cotto, as ambassador, to persuade his countrymen to take arms) went forward, to
                    carry intelligence of this to the king; but at a small distance from Amphipolis
                    a rumour, and then authentic information, acquainted them with the king's death;
                    which event disconcerted the whole arrangement of their plan. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It had been arranged in this manner; — Philip was to
                    procure for the Bastarnians a safe passage through Thrace, and supplies of
                    provisions. In order to be able to effect this, he had courted the chieftains in
                    that country by presents, having pledged his faith that the Bastarnians should
                    march through it in a peaceable body. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was
                    proposed to exterminate the nation of the Dardanians, and to establish
                    settlements for the Bastarnians in their country: <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1913" xml:id="p.1913"/> from which measure a double advantage would
                    accrue, if both the Dardanians, a nation ever hostile to Macedonia, and
                    anxiously looking to the unfortunate periods of its kings, would be removed out
                    of the way; and the Bastarnians, having left their wives and children in
                    Dardania, might be sent to ravage Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That
                    the road to the Adriatic Sea and Italy was through the country of the
                    Scordiscians, and that the army could not be led by any other way; that the
                    Scordiscians would readily grant a passage to the Bastarnians, for they would
                    have no dislike to people resembling themselves in language and manners, and
                    would probably join them in an expedition, when they saw that they were on their
                    way to the plunder of a most opulent nation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The remaining plans were accommodated to every kind of event that might take
                    place; for if the Bastarnians would be cut off by the Romans, still the removal
                    of the Dardanians, and the booty to be gained from the remains of the former,
                    and the full possession of Dardania, would prove a consolation; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> or if they should be successful, then, while the Romans
                    would be employed in the Bastarnian war, he might recover what he had lost in
                    Greece. Such had been the designs of Philip. </p>
                <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Bastarnians commenced their march in a
                    peaceable array, relying on the word of Cotto and Antigonus. But, not long after
                    the report of Philip's death, neither the Thracians were easily dealt with, nor
                    would the Bastarnians be content with what they could purchase; nor could they
                    be kept in a body, so as not to go out of the road. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> In consequence, injuries were committed on both sides; and,
                    from the daily multiplication of these, war at last burst forth. When at last
                    the Thracians were unable to withstand the great strength and numbers of the
                    enemy, having deserted their towns in the plains, they betook themselves to a
                    high mountain (they <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> call it Donuca). When
                    the Bastarnians wished to come up, such a tempest there discomfited them, when
                    in vain approaching the summit of the mountain, as, we are told, destroyed the
                    Gauls, when plundering Delphi. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were not
                    only overwhelmed with a deluge of rain, followed by prodigious thick showers of
                    hail, accompanied by tremendous noises in the sky, thunder, and lightning which
                    dazzled their sight; but the thunderbolts, also, fell so frequently on all
                    sides, that their bodies seemed to be aimed at: <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> and not only the soldiers, but their officers also, <pb n="1914"
                        xml:id="p.1914"/> being struck by them, fell. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When therefore, in hasty flight, they, rushing on blindly,
                    were scattered, and tumbling over very high rocks, and the Thracians also
                    attacked them when already in dismay, they themselves then said, that the gods
                    were the cause of the flight, and that the sky was falling on them. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When, being dispersed by the storm, as by a
                    shipwreck, they had returned (most of them half armed) to the camp whence they
                    had set out, they then began to consider what they should do; on which a
                    disagreement ensued, some advising to return home, and others to advance to
                    Dardania. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About thirty thousand men, under the
                    command of Clondicus, arrived at that place; the rest marched back, by the same
                    road through which they came, to the country beyond the Danube. Perseus, having
                    got possession of the kingdom, ordered Antigonus to be put to death; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> and, until he could settle his affairs on a firm
                    foundation, sent ambassadors to Rome, to renew the treaty concluded by his
                    father, and to request the senate to give him the title of king. These were the
                    transactions of that year in Macedon. </p>
                <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One of the consuls, Quintus Fulvius, triumphed
                    over the Ligurians; which triumph, it was agreed, was granted rather to the
                    greatness of his influence, than to that of his exploits. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He carried in the procession a vast quantity of arms, taken
                    from the enemy, but no money; yet he distributed to each soldier three hundred
                        <hi rend="italics">asses,</hi> double that sum to a centurion, triple it to
                    a horseman. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was nothing in this triumph
                    more remarkable, than that it happened to be celebrated on the same day of the
                    year on which he had triumphed, after his praetorship, the year before.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the triumph he proclaimed the
                    assembly of election, in which were chosen consuls, Marcus Junius Brutus, and
                    Aulus Manlius Vulso. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Afterwards, a storm
                    interrupted the election of praetors, though three had been already elected; but
                    on the following day, the fourth before the ides of March, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The eleventh of March.</note> the other three were
                    elected, Marcus Titinius Curvus, Tiberius Claudius Nero, and Titus Fonteius
                    Capito. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman games were renewed by the
                    curule aediles, Cneius Servilius Caepio, and Appius Claudius Centho, on account
                    of the prodigies which had occurred. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the
                    public forum, where a lectisternium was being celebrated, there was an
                    earthquake, and the heads of the gods who were on the couches turned away their
                    faces, and the cloak and <pb n="1915" xml:id="p.1915"/> robes placed on Jupiter
                    fell off. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was also construed as a prodigy,
                    that the mice gnawed the olives on the table. For the expiation of these,
                    nothing more was done than repeating the celebration of the games. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
