<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 40</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="book">
                <head>Perseus and Demetrius</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the following year the
                        consuls and praetors balloted for their provinces. Liguria was the only
                        consular province and was assigned to both consuls. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The result of the ballot gave the civic jurisdiction to
                        M. Ogulnius Gallus, the alien jurisdiction to M. Valerius, Hither Spain to
                        Q. Fulvius Flaccus, Further Spain to P. Manlius, Sicily to L. Caecilius
                        Denter, and Sardinia to C. Terentius Istra. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> The consuls received instructions to levy troops. Q. Fabius had written
                        from Liguria to say that the Apuani were contemplating a renewal of
                        hostilities and there was danger of their making an irruption into the
                        territory of Pisae. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the Spanish
                        provinces too there was trouble: the senate knew that Hither Spain was in
                        arms and that fighting was going on with the Celtiberi; in Further Spain,
                        owing to the long-continued illness of the praetor, military discipline was
                        relaxed by luxury and idleness. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Under
                        these circumstances they decided that fresh armies should be raised: four
                        legions for Liguria each numbering 5200 infantry and 200 cavalry, with the
                        addition of 15,000 infantry and 800 cavalry drawn from the Latin allies.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These were to form the two consular
                        armies. The consuls were further instructed to call up 7000 infantry and 400
                        cavalry as an allied contingent and despatch them to M. Marcellus, whose
                        command in Gaul had been extended at the close of his consulship. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> For the two Spanish provinces a force of 4000
                        Roman infantry and 200 cavalry, together with 7000 infantry and 300 cavalry
                        from the Latin allies, was to be raised. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Q. Fabius Labeo had his command in Liguria extended, and he was to retain
                        the army which he had. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The spring of that year was a stormy one.
                        On the eve of the Parilia, about the middle of the day a terrible storm of
                        wind and rain burst and wrecked many sacred and ordinary buildings.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It blew down the bronze statues on the
                        Capitol, it carried off the door from the temple of Luna on the Aventine and
                        dashed it against the walls behind the temple of Ceres. Other statues were
                        overturned in the Circus Maximus together with their pedestals. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Several sculptures were broken off from the roofs
                        of the temples and ruthlessly shattered. This storm was in consequence
                        regarded as a portent, and the augurs were bidden to direct the necessary
                        expiation for it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A further expiation was
                        demanded in consequence of intelligence brought to Rome of the birth of a
                        mule at Reate with only three feet, and a report from Formiae that the
                        temple of Apollo at Caieta had been struck by lightning. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> In consequence of these portents twenty full-grown
                        victims were sacrificed and special intercessions offered for one day. From
                        a despatch sent by A. Terentius it was ascertained that P. Sempronius, after
                        more than a year's illness, had died in Further Spain. The praetors were
                        ordered to start for Spain as soon as possible. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Legations from overseas were admitted to an audience of
                        the senate. First came those from Eumenes, Pharnaces and the Rhodians. The
                        latter complained of the disaster which had overtaken Sinope. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Envoys from Philip and from the Achaeans and
                        Lacedaemonians went to Rome at the same time. After hearing Marcius, who had
                        been sent to ascertain the state of affairs in Greece and Macedonia, the
                        senate gave their reply. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The two
                        sovereigns and the Rhodians were informed that the senate would send a
                        commission to look into those matters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcius had increased the senate's
                        apprehensions about Philip. He admitted that Philip had carried out the
                        measures insisted upon by the senate, but in such a way that he would
                        obviously continue to do so no longer than he was compelled. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> There was little doubt that he would recommence
                        war, and all his words and actions pointed in that direction. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> He transferred almost the entire population from
                        the maritime cities to the district now called Emathia, formerly known as
                        Paeonia, and had handed over those cities to the Thracians and other
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> barbarians for their residence,
                        thinking that these races could be more safely depended upon in case of a
                        war with Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This action called forth
                        loud protests throughout Macedonia; few of those who with their wives and
                        children were abandoning their homes bore their grief in silence. Everywhere
                        amongst the crowds of emigrants were heard curses on the king; their anger
                        got the better of their fears. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Furious at
                        all this, Philip began to suspect all persons, places and seasons alike, and
                        at last openly avowed that he could only be secure <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> when he had the children of those whom he had put to
                        death arrested and in safe keeping. Then he could put them out of the way
                        from time to time. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This brutality, hideous as it was, was
                        rendered still more so by the sufferings of one particular family.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Herodicus, a leading man in Thessaly,
                        had been put to death by Philip many years ago; afterwards he put his
                        sons-in-law to death and his two widowed daughters, Theoxena and Archo, were
                        left each with one little son. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Theoxena
                        had several offers of marriage but declined them all. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Archo married a man called Poris who held quite the
                        first place among the Aenianes. She bore him several children but died
                        whilst they were still small. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In order
                        that her sister's children might be brought up under her own care, Theoxena
                        married Poris and took as much care of her sister's sons as she did of her
                        own. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When she heard of the king's edict
                        about arresting the children of those whom he had put to death, she felt
                        sure that the boys would fall victims to the king's lust and even to the
                        passions of his guards. She formed a terrible design and dared to say that
                        she would rather kill them with her own hand than let them fall into
                        Philip's power. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Poris was horrified at the
                        mere mention of such a deed, and said that he would send <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> them away to some trustworthy friends in Athens and
                        that he would accompany them in their flight. They went from Thessalonica to
                        Aenia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A festival was being held there at
                        the time, which was celebrated with great pomp every four years in honour of
                        Aeneas, the founder of the city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After
                        spending the day in the customary feasting they waited till the third watch,
                        when all were asleep, and went on board a ship which Poris had in readiness,
                        ostensibly to return to Thessalonica, but really to sail across to Euboea.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While, however, they were vainly
                        trying to make headway against a contrary wind, they were surprised by
                        daylight not far from land, and the king's troops who were on guard at the
                        harbour sent an armed boat to seize the ship, with strict orders not to
                        return without her. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Poris, meanwhile, was
                        doing his utmost to urge on the rowers and sailors, lifting up his hands
                        from time to time to heaven and imploring the gods to help him. His wife, a
                        woman of indomitable spirit, fell back on the purpose she had long ago
                        formed, and mixing some poison, placed the cup where it could be seen,
                        together with some naked swords. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> "Death,"
                        she said, "alone can free us. Here are two ways of meeting it, choose each
                        of you which you will, as the escape from the king's tyranny. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Come, my boys, you who are the older be the
                        first to grasp the sword, or if you would have a more lingering death, drink
                        off the poison." On the one hand were the enemy close to them, on the other
                        the insistent mother urging them to die. Some chose the one death, some the
                        other, and whilst still half-alive they were thrown from the ship.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then the mother herself, flinging her
                        arms round her husband, sprang with him into the sea. The king's troops took
                        possession of a deserted ship. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The horror of this deed fanned afresh the
                        flames of hatred against the king. Curses were everywhere heaped upon him
                        and upon his children, and the dire imprecations soon reached the ears of
                        all the gods, so that they drove him into murderous cruelty against his own
                        flesh and blood. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Perseus saw that his
                        brother Demetrius was growing more every day in popularity and influence
                        with the mass of his nation and in favour with the Romans, and he felt that
                        no hope remained to him of winning the crown except through the perpetration
                        of a crime, and to its accomplishment he now devoted all his thoughts.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He did not think himself strong enough
                        to carry out the purpose which he was hatching in his weak and unmanly mind,
                        and he began to sound his father's friends one by one, dropping dark and
                        dubious hints in his talks with them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some
                        of them made it appear at first as though they rejected anything of the
                        kind, because they hoped more from Demetrius. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But as Philip's bitterness against the Romans, which
                        Perseus encouraged and Demetrius did his utmost to check, became more
                        pronounced every day, they foresaw the ruin of the youth who was taking no
                        precautions against his brother's intrigues. So they at last decided to help
                        on what must inevitably happen and advance the hopes of the stronger by
                        taking the side of Perseus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They left
                        other measures to be carried out at a fitting time, for the present they
                        determined to use all their endeavours to inflame the king against the
                        Romans and induce him to expedite the warlike plans which he was already
                        contemplating. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To aggravate the suspicions
                        against Demetrius, they used to bring up the subject of the Romans in their
                        conversations with him. Some would run down their national character and
                        institutions, others spoke lightly of their military achievements, others
                        scoffed at the appearance of the City, its lack of adornment in both public
                        and private buildings, whilst others, again, spoke contemptuously of
                        different public men. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The young man,
                        thrown off his guard by his devotion to the name of Rome and his opposition
                        to his brother, defended them in every way, and thus made himself an object
                        of suspicion to his father and laid himself open to charges of disloyalty.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The result was that his father
                        excluded him from all consultations on matters relating to Rome and took
                        Perseus entirely into his confidence, discussing these subjects with him day
                        and night. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The envoys whom he had sent to the
                        Bastarnae to summon assistance had returned and brought back with them some
                        young nobles, amongst them some of royal blood. One of these promised to
                        give his sister in marriage to Philip's son, and the king was quite elated
                        at the prospect of an alliance with that nation. Perseus, on this, said to
                        him, "What advantage is there in that? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Little protection will there be in foreign support, compared with the danger
                        of domestic treason. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> We have in our midst
                        a spy, I do not want to call him a traitor; ever since he was a hostage in
                        Rome, the Romans possess his heart and soul, though they have given us back
                        his body. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The eyes of almost all
                        Macedonia are turned towards him; they are fully persuaded that they will
                        have none else as king but the one whom the Romans give them." The
                        distempered mind of the old king was made still more uneasy by these words,
                            <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> which he took more seriously than
                        appeared from his looks. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened to be the time for the
                        lustration of the army. The following is a description of the ceremony. The
                        body of a bitch was divided in the middle, the forepart with the head was
                        placed on the right side of the road and the hinder part with the entrails
                        on the left, and the troops marched between them. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> In front of the column were borne the insignia of all
                        the kings of Macedonia from its remotest origin; then followed the king and
                        his children; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> next to them the king's own
                        cohort and his bodyguard, the Macedonian phalanx bringing up the rear.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The two princes rode on either side of
                        their father; Perseus was now thirty years old and Demetrius five years his
                        junior, the former in the prime of manhood, the latter in the flower of
                        youth. The father would have been fortunate in his maturer offspring if only
                        he had been wise and sensible. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the
                        purificatory rite was completed it was the custom for the army to go through
                        maneuvers and after being formed into two divisions to engage in a
                        sham-fight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The two princes were appointed
                        to command in this mimic contest, but there was no make-believe about the
                        fighting, it looked like a struggle for the crown, so fiercely did they
                        engage. Many wounds were caused by their staves and nothing was wanting but
                        swords to give the actual appearance of war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The division which Demetrius commanded was by far the better one. Perseus
                        was intensely annoyed, but his wiser friends were delighted. That
                        circumstance in itself, they said, would afford grounds for incriminating
                        the young man. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Demetrius invited Perseus to supper at the
                        close of the day, but he refused to go, and each of them gave a banquet to
                        those who had been their comrades in the sham-fight. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The lavish hospitality, as befitted the festal day, and
                        the high spirits of youth led both parties to drink freely. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Then they began to talk about the battle and jokes were
                        made at the expense of their opponents, not even their leaders being exempt.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A spy was sent from Perseus' party to
                        listen to this conversation, but as he behaved somewhat incautiously he was
                        caught by some youths who happened to be leaving the banquet-room and
                        soundly cudgelled. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Demetrius knew nothing
                        of this and he asked his companions, "If my brother is still in an angry
                        mood after the battle, why should we not go to him as boon companions and
                        appease him by our open-hearted merriment?" All of them, except those who
                        were afraid of prompt retaliation for thrashing the spy, called out that
                        they would go. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Demetrius made those also
                        go with him, and they concealed swords under their garments to defend
                        themselves in case of attack. Nothing could possibly be kept secret in this
                        family quarrel, both their houses were full of spies and traitors.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> An informer ran to Perseus and told
                        him that four young men who were wearing concealed swords were coming with
                        Demetrius. Although he must have known the reason, for he had heard that one
                        of his guests had been thrashed by them, he made the affair look <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> as black as possible by ordering the door to be
                        bolted, and going to the upper part of the house, where the windows looked
                        down on the road, he kept the revellers from approaching the door, as though
                        they were coming to murder him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Demetrius
                        was under the influence of wine, and finding himself shut out protested
                        loudly for some time and then returned to the banquet-room, not knowing in
                        the least what it all meant. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as he could get an opportunity of
                        seeing his father the next day, Perseus entered the palace with a perturbed
                        expression and stood in silence at some distance from his father. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> "Are you well?" asked Philip. "Why that gloomy
                        countenance?" "Let me tell you," he replied, "that it is more than I hoped
                        for to be alive now. It is no longer by secret plots that my brother is
                        seeking my life; he came to my house at night with an armed band to kill me.
                        Only by barring the doors could I shelter myself from his fury behind the
                        walls of the house." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After thus
                        astonishing and alarming his father, he went on, "Yes, and if you can give
                        me a hearing I will make you see the whole thing clearly." <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Philip said that he would certainly hear him and sent
                        orders for Demetrius to be summoned at once. He also sent for two of his
                        older friends who had nothing to do with the quarrel between the brothers,
                        and did not often visit the palace-Lysimachus and Onomastus. He wished to
                        have them present at the council. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst
                        waiting for them he walked up and down deep in thought, his son standing
                        some distance away. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they were
                        announced he withdrew with them and two of his life-guards into an inner
                        room, and allowed each of his sons to bring three companions unarmed.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After taking his seat he began: "Here
                        I, a most unhappy father, am sitting as judge between my two sons, one
                        accusing the other of fratricide, and I have to find my own children guilty
                        of either a false accusation or a confession of criminal intent. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> I have for some time been dreading the imminence
                        of this storm as I watched the way you looked at one another with an
                        expression of anything but brotherly love, and listened to some of your
                        language. Sometimes I have ventured to hope that your anger was dying down
                        and that suspicions could be cleared up. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Even hostile nations have laid down their arms and made treaties of peace,
                        and many men have put an end to their private quarrels. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> I fancied that some day you might remember your
                        relationship to one another, the unreserved intimacy of your boyish days and
                        the teaching which I have given you, which has, I fear, fallen on deaf ears.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> How often have I told you of my
                        detestation of fraternal quarrels and the dreadful results they lead to, how
                        often they have ruined families and houses and kingdoms! I have also placed
                        before you happier examples on the other side; <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> the perfectly friendly relations between the two kings
                        of Sparta, which had for long centuries been such a safeguard to themselves
                        and their country; but as soon as the fashion came in of each trying to
                        secure despotic power for himself, that State was destroyed. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Look at those two monarchs, Eumenes and Attalus,
                        who from such <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> small beginnings that
                        they shrank from the title of king have now become the peers of Antiochus
                        and myself, and this is due to nothing so much as the brotherly concord that
                        existed between them. I even drew examples from the Romans which had fallen
                        under my own observation or which I had heard of: the two Quinctii, Titus
                        and Lucius; the two Scipios, Publius and Lucius, who conquered Antiochus;
                        their father and their uncle whose lifelong harmony was cemented by death.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> And yet the bad examples which I
                        first mentioned and the evil results of their evil conduct could not deter
                        you from your insane quarrels, nor could the good character and the good
                        fortune of the others turn you to a sound and healthy state of mind.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> While I am yet alive and drawing
                        vital breath you have in your criminal ambition decided to whom the crown
                        will pass. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> You wish me to live just long
                        enough to survive one of you, and then by my death make the other the
                        unquestioned king. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> You cannot bear that
                        either your father or your brother should live. You have no affection, no
                        conscience; an insatiable desire for the crown alone has supplanted
                        everything else in your hearts. Go on, then, grieve and shock your father's
                        ears, fight out your differences with mutual recriminations as you will soon
                        do with the sword; speak out openly whatever you can truly allege or find
                        pleasure in inventing. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> My ears are open
                        to you now, henceforth they will be closed to any secret charges which you
                        may make against each other." <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> He uttered
                        these last words in very angry tones and all present burst into tears; there
                        was a long and sorrowful silence. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then Perseus began: "You think, then, that
                        I ought to have opened the door and admitted the armed revellers and
                        presented my throat to the sword, and beset as I am with plots and
                        treachery, I have to listen to the same language that is addressed to
                        thieves and foot-pads. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It is not for
                        nothing that those people say that Demetrius is your only son, whilst they
                        call me supposititious and base-born. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They
                        speak to some purpose, for if I possessed in your eyes the rank, the
                        affection due to a son, you would not vent your anger on me when I complain
                        of the plot that has been frustrated, but <milestone n="4??" unit="section"
                        /> on him who contrived it, nor would you hold my life so cheap as not to be
                        moved by past dangers or by future dangers, should the plotters escape with
                        impunity. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If I am to die without uttering
                        a protest, I would be silent except for a prayer to the gods that the
                        villainy which began with me may end with me, and that my deathblow may not
                        strike you. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But if, whilst I see the sword
                        drawn against me, I may be permitted to make my voice heard, then, just as
                        Nature herself prompts those who are surrounded by dangers, with no friend
                        near, to appeal for help to men they have never seen, so I beseech you by
                        the sacred name of father-and you have long felt which of us <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> holds that name most sacred-to grant me the
                        same hearing as you would have done had you been awakened by a cry of alarm
                        at night and gone at my call for help, and actually seen Demetrius with his
                        armed comrades in my vestibule. What would have been my cry of alarm at the
                        actual moment of danger, last night, I am today making the subject of my
                        complaint. </p>
                    <p> "Brother, for a long time we have not lived together as table-companions.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> You, in any case, want to be king.
                        This hope of yours is baffled by my seniority, by the right of primogeniture
                        universally recognised, by the time-honoured usage of the Macedonians. You
                        cannot surmount these barriers except through my blood. You are trying every
                        device, every expedient. Hitherto, either my watchfulness or my good luck
                        has stood in the way of your becoming a fratricide. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Yesterday, on the occasion of the propitiatory
                        sacrifice, the maneuvers and the sham-fight, you made the fight all but a
                        fatal one, and nothing averted my death but the fact that I allowed my men
                        and myself to be defeated. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> From that
                        hostile encounter you wanted to inveigle me to your banquet, as though it
                        had been merely brotherly sport. Do you believe, father, that it would have
                        been amongst unarmed guests that I should have banqueted, when they came in
                        arms to banquet with me? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Do you believe
                        that I was in no danger from their swords at night, after they had almost
                        killed me with their staves whilst you were looking on? Why, Demetrius, do
                        you come at that hour of the night, why do you come as an enemy to one who
                        is in an angry mood, why do you come accompanied by youths with hidden
                        swords? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> I did not dare to trust myself to
                        you even as a guest, am I to admit you when you come with an armed band? Had
                        my door been open, you, my father, would now be arranging my funeral
                        obsequies instead of listening to my complaints. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> "I am not trumping up charges as a prosecutor, nor am I
                        arguing upon questionable evidence. Surely he does not deny that he came to
                        my door with a large crowd, or that he was accompanied by men with concealed
                        swords. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Send for the men whose names I
                        give you. Those who have dared so far will go to any lengths, they will not,
                        however, venture upon a denial. If I had caught them in my vestibule with
                        their swords and brought them to you, you would have regarded it as a clear
                        case; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> take their confession as equivalent
                        to their being caught in the act. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Now invoke curses on the eager longing
                        for your crown, awake the furies that avenge a brother's blood, but do not,
                        my father, let your execrations fall blindly. Discern, distinguish between
                        the plotter and the victim of his plots, and let them fall on the guilty
                        head. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Let him who intended to kill his
                        brother feel the wrath of his father's gods, let him who was to perish
                        through a brother's crime find shelter in his father's justice and
                        compassion. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For where else can I find
                        refuge, when there is no safety either in the ceremonial purification of the
                        army, or in house, or banquet, or in night, nature's boon to mortals for
                        repose? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If I had accepted my brother's
                        invitation it would have been my death, if I had admitted my brother inside
                        my doors it would have been my death. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I do
                        not escape his murderous designs whether I go or stay. I have sought favour
                        from none, save the gods and you, my father; I have not the Romans to flee
                        to. They are seeking my ruin because I grieve over your wrongs, because I
                        resent your being deprived of so many cities, so many subject nations, and
                        now' of the coastline of Thrace. When neither you nor I are any longer safe
                        they hope that Macedonia will be theirs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        If my brother's murderous hand carries me off, if old age carries you off,
                        or even if they do not wait for that, they know that the king and realm of
                        Macedonia will be at their disposal. If the Romans had left you anything
                        beyond the borders of Macedonia, I could even believe that it was left as a
                        harbour of refuge for me. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "But, you say, I have sufficient
                        protection in the Macedonians. You saw how the soldiers attacked me
                        yesterday. What was lacking except a sword? What was lacking in the daytime
                        my brother's guests furnished themselves with at night. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Why should I speak about the majority of our leading
                        men who have placed all their hopes of fortune and power on the Romans and
                        on the man who is all-powerful with the Romans? They are not only setting
                        that fellow above me, but very soon they will set him above you, his father
                        and his king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was out of kindness to
                        him that the Romans remitted the penalty they were going to impose on you;
                        he it is who protects you from the arms of Rome, who thinks it right that
                        you at your age should be at the mercy of his youth. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> On his side stand the Romans, on his side are all the
                        cities which have been liberated from your rule, on his side are the
                        Macedonians who are happy while there is peace with Rome. Whom have I to
                        trust to but my father, what hope or security is there elsewhere? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "What do you suppose is the meaning of
                        that letter which has just been sent to you by T. Quinctius, in which he
                        says that you acted wisely in your own interest by sending Demetrius to
                        Rome, and urges you to send him again with a more numerous embassage
                        including the foremost men in Macedonia? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        T. Quinctius is now his adviser and director in everything; he has renounced
                        you, his father, and put him in your place. With him all the secret plans
                        are arranged beforehand; he is looking out for men to help him in carrying
                        out those plans when he bids you send more of the Macedonian leaders with
                        him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They will go from here loyal and
                        true, believing that they have a king in Philip, they will come back tainted
                        and poisoned with Roman blandishments. Demetrius is everything to the
                        Romans, they are already addressing him as king while his father is alive.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If I show indignation at all this, I
                        have forthwith to listen to charges of seeking the crown not only from
                        others but even from you, my father. But if the accusation rests between us,
                        I, for my part, repudiate it. For whom am I displacing that I may step into
                        his place? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> My father alone is before me,
                        and I pray Heaven that he may long be so. If I survive him-and may this be
                        so only if my deserts make him wish it-I shall receive the heritage of the
                        crown if my father delivers it to me. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That
                        youth is coveting the crown, and coveting it with criminal intent. He is
                        eager to forestall the order laid down by age, by nature, by the usage of
                        the Macedonians, by the law of nations. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        'My elder brother,' he says to himself, 'to whom by right and even by my
                        father's wish the crown belongs, stands in my way; let him be removed. I
                        shall not be the first who has sought a kingdom at the cost of a brother's
                        blood. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> My father, an old man, without the
                        support of his elder son will be too much afraid for himself to think of
                        avenging his son's death. The Romans will be glad, they will approve of my
                        act and defend it.' <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These are uncertain
                        hopes, but not groundless. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For this is
                        how matters stand, my father; you can repel the danger which menaces my life
                        by punishing those who have taken up the sword to slay me; if their criminal
                        purpose is achieved, you will not have the power to avenge my death." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Perseus had finished, all present
                        looked at Demetrius, expecting him to reply at once. There was a long
                        silence and everybody saw that he was bathed in tears and unable to speak.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At length they told him that he must
                        speak, and he was compelled to stifle his grief. So he began: "Everything,
                        my father, on which those who are accused could rely for their defence has
                        been prejudiced by my accuser. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tears
                        which he feigned for the purpose of effecting another's ruin have made you
                        suspect the reality of mine. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Ever since my
                        return from Rome he has been hatching secret plots against me day and night
                        with his confederates, and now he deliberately fastens on me the character
                        not only of an intriguer but even of an open assassin. He alarms you with
                        the bugbear of his own danger in order that through you he may hasten the
                        destruction of his unoffending brother. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He
                        says that there is no place of refuge for him in the whole world in order
                        that I may have no hope of safety with you. Beset by foes, deserted by
                        friends, destitute of all resources, he loads me with the odium aroused by
                        the favour shown to me by foreigners, which hurts me more than it benefits.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> How like a common prosecutor has he
                        acted in mixing up his account of last night's events with a bitter attack
                        upon the rest of my life so that he put that <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> incident, which you will see in its true colours, in a
                        suspicious light, by representing the tenor of my life as other than what it
                        is, and bolstering up that false and scandalous description of my hopes and
                        wishes and designs by this fictitious and hollow evidence. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> And at the same time he tried to make his accusations
                        appear as though they were uttered without preparation, on the spur of the
                        moment, called forth forsooth by the alarm and tumult of the night.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But, Perseus, if I were a traitor to
                        my father and the realm, if I were scheming with the Romans or with any of
                        my father's enemies, you ought not to have waited for this trumped-up story
                        of last night's doings, you ought to have accused me of treachery before
                        this. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If that accusation as distinct from
                        this one was without any foundation and a proof of your bad feeling towards
                        me, rather than of my guilt, surely it ought to be passed over today and
                        deferred till another occasion, so that the question which of us in a spirit
                        of unheard-of hatred has been intriguing against the other might be decided
                        on its merits. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At all events, so far as I
                        am able to do so in this sudden bewilderment, I shall separate what you have
                        confused together, and <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> unveil last
                        night's plot, to show whether you or I were the author of it. </p>
                    <p> "He wants to make it appear that I formed a design against his life in
                        order, forsooth, that <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> after the removal
                        of the elder brother, to whom by a universally acknowledged right, by the
                        usage of the Macedonians and by your decision, as he says, the future crown
                        belongs, I, the younger son, could step into the place of him whom I had
                        killed. What then is the meaning of that part of his speech in which he says
                        that I curried favour with the Romans and hoped through my reliance on them
                        to come to the throne? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> For if I believed
                        that the Romans possessed so much influence that they could impose upon the
                        Macedonians whom <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> they would as king,
                        and if I trusted so much to my interest with them, what need was there for
                        me to kill my brother? Was it that I might wear a crown stained with a
                        brother's blood? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> That I might be
                        execrated and hated by the very men whose favour I have won by a
                        straightforwardness, either sincere or at least assumed, if indeed I have
                        won it? Perhaps you imagine that T. Quinctius, by whose virtuous counsels
                        you say that I am ruled, has instigated me to be my brother's murderer,
                        though he himself lives in such close affection with his own brother.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Perseus has brought together in what
                        he said not only my favourable position with the Romans but also the
                        sentiments of the Macedonians and the all but unanimous judgment of gods and
                        men, and owing to all these advantages he professes to believe that he is no
                        match for me. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> And yet, as though in
                        everything else I were inferior to him, he maintains that I have betaken
                        myself to crime as my last hope. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Do you
                        want the issue of the trial to take this form: 'Whichever of the two feared
                        that the other might be thought more worthy of the crown, let him be judged
                        to have <milestone n="20??" unit="section"/> formed the design of crushing
                        his brother?' </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Now in whatever way these charges have
                        been fabricated, let us examine the order in which they stand. He said that
                        numerous attempts had been made against his life, and he has brought all the
                        methods employed within the limits of a single day. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> I wanted, he says, to kill him in broad daylight after
                        the lustration when we were engaged in the mimic battle, actually, good
                        heavens! on the very day of the lustration! Then I wanted to take him,
                        forsooth, by poison, after inviting him to supper. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Then I wanted to go with a band of revellers armed with
                        hidden swords and kill him with cold steel. You notice what occasions he has
                        selected for the murder-sports, a banquet, a wine party? Why, what was the
                        character of the day? A day on which the army was purified, on which they
                        marched between the two halves of the victim, with the royal arms of all the
                        kings of Macedonia borne before them, we two alone in front by the side of
                        you, my father, and the Macedonian phalanx following. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Even though I had previously committed some sin which
                        required expiation, could I, after being purified and absolved in this
                        solemn rite, especially whilst gazing upon the victim which lay on either
                        side our path-could I then be revolving in my mind thoughts of murder,
                        poison, swords? With what other rites could I then have cleansed a mind
                        steeped in uttermost guilt? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But in his
                        blind eagerness to launch accusations and throw suspicion on everything I
                        did, he has made one thing contradict another. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> For if I intended to take you off by poison during the
                        banquet, what could have less served my purpose than to rouse your anger by
                        an obstinately contested fight so as to give you just cause for refusing my
                        invitation? After your angry refusal what should I have done? <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Was I to make it my business to appease your
                        wrath so as to have another opportunity, now that I had prepared the poison,
                        or should I have, so to speak, leaped from that <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> plan to another, and in the guise of a boon companion
                        killed you with the sword, and all on the same day? <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> If I had supposed that you kept clear of my supper
                        party for fear of your life, how could I possibly have failed to suppose
                        that the same fear would keep you from the drinking bout which followed?
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "There is nothing to blush for, father, in
                        my having taken wine with my comrades somewhat freely on such a festal day.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I wish you would find out with what
                        fun and merriment we kept up the banquet at my house last night, and how
                        delighted we were-perhaps improperly-at our side not being the worst in the
                        youthful assault-at-arms. My unhappiness and my fears have quite shaken off
                        the effects of the wine; had these circumstances not arisen, we dangerous
                        plotters should now all be lying fast asleep. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> If I had been going to attack your house, and after
                        getting possession of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> it kill the owner,
                        should I not have kept myself and my soldiers from wine for one day at
                        least? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And that I may not be alone in
                        taking this simple and ingenuous line of defence, my brother, by no means a
                        suspicious person, says: 'I know of nothing more, I can bring no further
                        proof than his having come to my house with a sword.' If I were to ask
                        'whence do you know even this much?' <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> you
                        would have to confess either that my house was filled with your spies, or
                        that my comrades took their swords so openly that everybody saw them.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And to take away all appearance of his
                        having made previous enquiries, or of his proving me a criminal, now he
                        wants you to ask those whose names he has given whether they had swords, as
                        though there were any doubt about it. Then after being questioned as to a
                        fact they all admitted, they were to be treated as persons found guilty
                        after trial. Why do you not ask that this question be put to them: 'Did you
                        take your swords for the purpose of murdering him?' <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This is what you want to have made clear, and not the
                        other point which is openly admitted. But they say that they took their
                        swords for their own protection. Whether they did this rightly or wrongly is
                        their affair, they must answer for their own action. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> My case is in no way affected by what they did, do not
                        mix up the two things together. Or else explain whether we were going to
                        attack you secretly or openly. If openly, why did we not all carry swords?
                        Why did nobody take one besides those who had given your spy a thrashing?
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If secretly, what sort of a plan had
                        we formed? After the party had broken up and I had left the table and four,
                        as you say, remained behind <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> for the
                        purpose of attacking you when asleep, how could they have escaped, being as
                        they were strangers belonging to my party, and, above all, objects of
                        suspicion since they had been fighting not long before? How, too, could they
                        have got away after murdering you? Could your house have been stormed and
                        taken with four swords? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Why do you not drop this story of what
                        happened last night and come back to your real grievance which supplies the
                        fuel to your jealousy? 'Why, Demetrius, are people talking everywhere about
                        your being king? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Why do you appear in some
                        people's eyes to be a more worthy successor to your father's position than
                        myself? Why do you cloud with doubt and anxiety those hopes which, if you
                        did not exist, would be assured?' <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So
                        Perseus thinks, if he does not speak his thoughts. It is this that makes him
                        my enemy, my accuser, it is this that floods your palace and your realm with
                        slander and suspicion. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But, my father, as
                        I am bound in duty not to hope for the crown nor, perhaps, ever to dispute
                        it, since I am the younger and it is your wish that I should give place to
                        the elder, so have I felt it my duty in the past and so I feel it today,
                        never to show myself unworthy of you, my father, or unworthy of all my
                        nation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For that would be caused by my
                        faults, not by modestly giving way to him who has right and justice on his
                        side. You bring up the Romans against me and turn into a crime what ought to
                        be a source of pride. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I never asked to be
                        handed over to the Romans as a hostage, or to be sent as an envoy to Rome,
                        but when sent by you I did not refuse to go. On both occasions I so
                        conducted myself that neither you nor your sovereignty nor the whole of
                        Macedonia could be ashamed of me. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So you,
                        my father, were the cause of my friendship with the Romans; as long as peace
                        exists between you and them I too shall stand in favour with them. If war
                        breaks out I, who have been a hostage and a not unsuccessful representative
                        of my father, shall be their most determined foe. I do not claim today that
                        my interest with the Romans shall help me, but I do pray that it may not
                        injure me. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It did not begin in a time of
                        war nor is it reserved for a time of war. I was a pledge of peace, I was
                        sent as an envoy to maintain the peace: neither of these should be put down
                        to my credit or to my fault. If I have been guilty of undutiful conduct
                        towards you, my father, or criminal designs against my brother, I am
                        prepared to undergo any punishment. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If I
                        am innocent, I beg that I may not fall a victim to envy and malice, since I
                        cannot suffer for any crime. </p>
                    <p> "My brother is not accusing me for the first time today, but it is the first
                        time he is doing so openly, though I have done nothing to deserve it.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If my father were angry with me it
                        would be your duty, as the elder brother, to intercede for the younger to
                        obtain pardon for my offence in consideration of my youth. Where I ought to
                        find protection, I find a determination to destroy me. I have been dragged
                        away whilst only half-awake from a banquet and a wine party to answer a
                        charge of fratricide. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Without advocates,
                        without defending counsel, I am compelled to plead for myself. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Had I to plead for another I should have taken
                        time to think out and arrange my speech, and what else would be at stake but
                        my reputation as a skilful pleader? Unaware of the reason for being
                        summoned, I found you in an angry mood, ordering me to defend myself, and my
                        brother making accusations against me. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He
                        delivered a carefully prepared and thought-out speech against me; I had only
                        such time as he took to make his accusations in which to learn what the
                        matter at issue was. What was I to do in those few moments, listen to my
                        accuser or think out my defence? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Thunderstruck by a danger so sudden and so unlooked for, I could with
                        difficulty understand the charges brought against me, still less could I see
                        the right way of defending myself against them. What hope would there be for
                        me if I had not my father as my judge? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> If
                        my brother has a greater share of his affection, I, who have to defend
                        myself, ought at all events not to have a less share of his compassion. I am
                        praying you to preserve me in your own interest as well as mine; he demands
                        that you shall put me to death for his own security. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> What do you think he will do to me when you have left
                        your crown to him, if even now he thinks it right that my life should be
                        sacrificed for him?" </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tears and sobs prevented him from saying
                        more. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Philip ordered them to withdraw, and
                        after a short consultation with his friends gave his decision. He would not,
                        he said, base his judgment of their case upon what they had said, or upon an
                        hour's discussion, but upon an investigation into the life and character of
                        each and a close observation of their language and behaviour on all
                        occasions, important and unimportant alike. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Everybody saw from this that whilst the charges arising out of the last
                        night's proceedings were easily disposed of, Demetrius' excessive
                        friendliness with the Romans had aroused suspicion. These incidents which
                        occurred during Philip's lifetime became, so to speak, the seeds of the
                        Macedonian war, which was fought mainly against Philip. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Both the consuls left for Liguria, which
                        was the only consular province, and on account of their successes there
                        thanksgivings were ordered for one day. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        About 2000 Ligurians came to the extreme frontier of Gaul where Marcellus
                        was encamped, begging him to accept their surrender. Marcellus told them to
                        stay where they were and wait till he had communicated with the senate.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate instructed the praetor, M.
                        Ogulnius, to inform Marcellus by letter that the consuls whose province it
                        was were better able to decide than they were what course would be most in
                        the interests of the State. At the same time, if Marcellus accepted the
                        surrender of the Ligurians, the senate did not wish their arms to be taken
                        from them and thought it right that they should be sent to the consul.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The praetors took up their respective
                        commands at the same time. P. Manlius went to Further Spain, which he had
                        administered in his former praetorship; Q. Fulvius Flaccus proceeded to
                        Hither Spain and took over the army from A. Terentius, for owing to the
                        death of P. Sempronius, Further Spain had been without a magistrate.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Whilst Fulvius Flaccus was besieging a
                        Spanish town called Urbicua he was attacked by the Celtiberians. Many fierce
                        actions took place, and there were severe losses in killed and wounded
                        amongst the Romans. No display of force could draw Fulvius away from the
                        siege, and his perseverance finally conquered. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Exhausted by so many battles the Celtiberi retired, and
                        the city, now that assistance was withdrawn, was taken in a few days and
                        sacked. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The praetor gave the booty to the
                        soldiers. Beyond this capture Fulvius did nothing worth recording, nor did
                        P. Manlius, beyond concentrating his scattered forces. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> They withdrew their armies into winter quarters. Such
                        was the record of that summer in Spain. Terentius, after giving up his
                        command there, entered the City in ovation. He brought home 9320 pounds of
                        silver, 82 pounds of gold and seven golden crowns weighing 60 pounds. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the year a commission went from
                        Rome to arbitrate between the Carthaginian government and King Masinissa on
                        a claim to certain territory. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Masinissa's
                        father, Gala, had taken it from the Carthaginians, Syphax had expelled Gala
                        from it, and out of complaisance to his father-in-law Hasdrubal had made a
                        present of it to the Carthaginians, and this year Masinissa had expelled the
                        Carthaginians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The matter was contested as
                        hotly in argument as it had been with the sword, and came before the Romans
                        for decision, who investigated it on the spot. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Masinissa said that he had recovered the territory as
                        part of his ancestral dominions and held it by the universally acknowledged
                        right of inheritance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His case was the
                        stronger of the two, both by title and by actual possession. The only thing
                        he feared was that he might be at a disadvantage should the Romans shrink
                        from appearing to favour a monarch who was their friend and ally at the cost
                        of a people who were enemies to him and them alike. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The commissioners decided nothing as to the right of
                        possession and referred the whole question to the senate. Nothing further
                        took place in Liguria. The Gauls retreated into the pathless forests and
                        then dispersed to their villages and forts. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The consuls also wanted to disband their army, and consulted the senate
                        about doing so. The senate ordered one of them to disband his army and
                        proceed to Rome to elect the magistrates for the next year; the other was to
                        winter with his legions at Pisae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There
                        were rumours that the transalpine Gauls were arming and it was uncertain
                        into what part of Italy they might descend, so the consuls arranged that Cn.
                        Baebius should go to hold the elections, as his brother Marcus was a
                        candidate. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The new consuls were M. Baebius Tamphilus
                        and P. Cornelius Lentulus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Liguria was
                        assigned as their province. The assignment of provinces to the new praetors
                        was as follows: The civic jurisdiction fell to Q. Petilius, the alien to Q.
                        Fabius Maximus; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Gaul to Q. Fabius Buteo;
                        Sicily to Tiberius Claudius Nero; Sardinia to M. Pinarius; Apulia to L.
                        Duronius, who was also to command in Histria, because news was received from
                        Tarentum and Brundisium that the fields on the coast were being plundered by
                        pirates from overseas. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The same complaint
                        was made by Marseilles about the ships of the Ligurians. The military
                        requirements were then determined. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Four
                        legions were assigned to the consuls, each consisting of 5200 Roman infantry
                        and 300 cavalry, and also 15,000 infantry to be drawn from the Latin allies
                        and 800 cavalry. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The former praetors
                        remained in Spain with the armies they had, and reinforcements were sent to
                        them of 3000 Roman citizens and 200 cavalry, together with 6000 allied
                        infantry and 300 cavalry. Naval affairs were not lost sight of. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls appointed two officers to man twenty
                        ships with crews of Roman citizens who had the status of freedmen, the
                        officers alone being freeborn citizens. These two officers were responsible
                        for the defence of the coast, each commanding ten ships, and their spheres
                        of action were separated by the promontory of Minerva, which formed the
                        centre of the defence; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the operations of
                        the one extending from that point westward to Marseilles; those of the
                        other, south and east as far as Barium. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Many dreadful portents were witnessed in
                        Rome this year and reported from outlying districts. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> In the precincts of the temple of Vulcan and Concord
                        there was a rain of blood, and the pontiffs announced that the spears had
                        been shaken and the image of Juno Sospita at Lanuvium had shed tears.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So severe an epidemic broke out in the
                        market-towns and country districts that Libitina was hardly able to supply
                        the materials for the funerals. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Greatly
                        alarmed by these portents and by the ravages of the pestilence, the senate
                        decreed that the consuls should sacrifice full-grown victims to whatever
                        deities they thought proper, and that the Sacred Books should be consulted.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Keepers of these Books decreed
                        that special intercession should be offered at all the shrines for a whole
                        day. They also advised that intercessions and suspension of work for three
                        days should be observed throughout Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The senate approved and the consuls published an edict ordering the
                        observance. Owing to a revolt in Corsica and hostilities on the part of the
                        Ilians in Sardinia it had been decided to call up 8000 Latin and allied
                        infantry and 300 cavalry for the praetor M. Pinarius to take with him to
                        Sardinia, but such was the extent and deadly <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> nature of the pestilence that the consuls reported the
                        number could not be made up owing to the great mortality and wide-spread
                        sickness. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The praetor was ordered to take
                        what he wanted from C. Baebius, who was wintering in Pisae, and to sail from
                        there to Sardinia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The praetor L.
                        Duronius, to whom the province of Apulia had fallen, was further charged
                        with an investigation into the Bacchanalia, some remains of which had come
                        to light the previous year, seeds as it were sown by the earlier mischief.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> L. Pupius, the former praetor, had
                        begun an inquiry but it had not been brought to a definite issue. The senate
                        sent orders to the new praetor to cut the evil out and prevent it from
                        spreading. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Acting on the authority of the
                        senate, the consuls brought before the people a measure dealing with
                        bribery. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some deputations were introduced to the
                        senate. The first to be received were those from Eumenes, Ariarathes of
                        Cappadocia and Pharnaces, King of Pontus. They were simply informed that
                        commissions would be sent to examine and settle the conflicting claims.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These were followed by envoys from the
                        Lacedaemonian refugees and the Achaeans; the refugees were led to hope that
                        the senate would order the Achaeans to repatriate them. The Achaeans
                        explained to the satisfaction of the House the recovery of Messene and the
                        settlement which had been made there. Two envoys also arrived from Philip of
                        Macedonia-Philocles and Apelles. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were
                        not sent with the view of obtaining anything from the senate, but simply to
                        watch what was going on and to find out what those conversations were which
                        Perseus had accused Demetrius of holding with the Romans, and in particular
                        those with T. Quinctius, about the succession to the throne in opposition to
                        his brother. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king had sent these men
                        as being impartial and not biassed in favour of either, but they, too, were
                        agents and accomplices in Perseus' treachery against his brother. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Demetrius, ignorant of all the intrigues against
                        him save what he had learnt from the recent outbreak of his brother's
                        malice, was neither very sanguine nor altogether hopeless of a
                        reconciliation with his father, but he gradually felt less confidence in his
                        father's feelings towards him as he observed his brother constantly at his
                        ear. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To avoid grounds for further
                        suspicion he was circumspect in all he said and did, and he took particular
                        care to abstain from any mention of the Romans or any intercourse with them.
                        He would not even have them write to him, because he saw that his father was
                        particularly exasperated by this charge being brought against him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To prevent his soldiers from becoming
                        demoralised through inaction, and at the same time to remove any suspicion
                        of his meditating a war with Rome, Philip ordered his army to assemble at
                        Stobi in Paeonia, and from there he led them into Maedica. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He had been seized with a great desire to ascend the
                        crest of Mt. Haemus, as he shared the common belief that the Pontus and the
                        Hadriatic, the Hister and the Alps could all be seen from that point, and he
                        believed that this prospect before his eyes would in no small measure serve
                        to guide his plans in a war with Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                        questioned those who knew the country about the ascent of Haemus, and all
                        agreed that was impossible for an army, and extremely difficult even for a
                        small lightly equipped force. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His younger
                        son he had decided not to take with him, and in order to lessen his
                        disappointment, he engaged in familiar conversation with him and asked him,
                        after putting before him the difficulties of the march, whether he thought
                        he ought to go on or abandon the enterprise. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> If, however, he went on, he said, he could not forget the example of
                        Antigonus, who, whilst tossing about in a violent storm and all his family
                        in the ship with him, is reported to have given his children a precept for
                        themselves to remember and to hand on to posterity, namely, that no one
                        should expose himself to danger when accompanied by the whole of his family.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Mindful of that precept Philip said
                        that he would not expose both his sons to the chances of accident in what he
                        proposed to do, and as he was taking his older son with him, he should send
                        his younger son back to Macedonia as the stay of his hopes and the guardian
                        of his kingdom. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Demetrius was quite aware
                        that the reason for his being sent back was that he might not be present at
                        the council of war when Philip consulted his staff, whilst the various
                        localities were lying in view, as to the quickest route to the Hadriatic,
                        and the future conduct of the war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was
                        bound not only to obey his father's order but to show his approval of it,
                        lest a reluctant compliance might arouse suspicions. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> To guarantee the safety of his journey to Macedonia,
                        Didas, one of the royal officers who was governor of Paeonia, received
                        orders to escort him with a small force. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        This man, also, Perseus had drawn into the conspiracy against his brother,
                        as he had most of his father's friends, after it had become clear to
                        everyone to which of the two sons the king's sympathies pointed as the heir
                        to the throne. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Didas' instructions were
                        for the time being to insinuate himself by every kind of obsequiousness into
                        Demetrius' confidence and intimacy so as to be able to draw out all his
                        secrets and ascertain his hidden sentiments. So Demetrius departed amidst
                        greater danger from his escort than if he had travelled alone. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip's first objective was Maedica. From
                        there he marched across the desolate country between Maedica and the Haemus,
                        and in seven days reached the foot of the mountain range. Here he remained
                        encamped for one day to select those whom he was to take with him, and the
                        next day resumed his march. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The first part
                        of the ascent did not involve much labour, but as they gained higher ground
                        the country became more wooded and overgrown; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> and one part of their route was so dark that, owing to
                        the density of the foliage and the interlacing of the branches, the sky was
                        hardly visible. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As they approached the
                        crest, everything was veiled in cloud, an uncommon occurrence at great
                        altitudes, and so dense that they found marching as difficult as at night.
                        At last on the third day they reached the summit. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After their descent they said nothing to contradict the
                        popular belief; more, I suspect, to prevent the futility of their march from
                        becoming a subject of ridicule than because the widely separated seas and
                        mountains and rivers could really be seen from one spot. They were all
                        distressed by the hardships of the march, the king most of all, owing to his
                        age. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He raised two altars there to Jupiter
                        and the Sun, on which he offered sacrifices, and then commenced the descent,
                        which occupied two days, the ascent having taken three. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He was afraid of the cold nights, which, though it was
                        the dog-days, were like the cold in winter. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After all the difficulties he had had to
                        contend against during those five days, he found things just as cheerless in
                        his camp, where they were destitute of everything. This was inevitable in a
                        district surrounded on all sides by uninhabited country. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> After one day in camp to rest the men whom he had taken
                        with him, he hastened into the Dentheletic country at a speed which
                        resembled a flight. This people were his allies, but owing to lack of food
                        the Macedonians plundered them as though they were on enemy soil. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Not content with robbing the homesteads, they
                        devastated some of the villages, <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> and it
                        was with feelings of deep shame that the king heard his allies making
                        fruitless appeals to the gods who watch over treaties and invoking his help
                        and protection. Carrying off a supply of corn he returned to Maedica and
                        made an attempt on a city called Petra. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        He fixed his camp on a plain which extended to the city and sent Perseus
                        with a small force to approach the place from higher ground. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> With danger threatening them from all sides the
                        townsmen gave hostages and surrendered the place for the time being, but as
                            <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> soon as the army had withdrawn they
                        forgot all about the hostages, deserted their city and fled to their
                        mountain strongholds. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Philip returned to
                        Macedonia with his men worn out to no purpose by labours and hardships
                        innumerable, and with his mind filled with suspicions of his son through the
                        cunning and treachery of Didas. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This man, as I stated above, was sent to
                        escort Demetrius. The young prince was incautious and angry, not without
                        reason, at the way his relations treated him. Didas humoured him and
                        pretended to be indignant on his account, and offered, unsolicited, to
                        assist him in every way, and gave him his word of honour to be true to him.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In this way he succeeded in eliciting
                        his secret thoughts. Demetrius was meditating flight to the Romans and hoped
                        to get away safely across Paeonia. That the governor of this province should
                        further his project he regarded as a boon from heaven. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> This design was at once betrayed to his brother, and on
                        his advice communicated to his father. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A
                        letter was sent to Philip while he was besieging Petra. On this, Heliodorus,
                        the leading man amongst the friends of Demetrius, was flung into prison and
                        orders were given to keep a secret watch on Demetrius. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> This more than anything else made the king's journey to
                        Macedonia a very melancholy one. This new charge disturbed him greatly, but
                        he felt that he ought to await the return of those who had been sent to find
                        out everything in Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For some months he
                        remained in suspense; at length his envoys returned after having settled
                        beforehand in Macedonia what report they should bring back from Rome.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In addition to all their other
                        treachery, they handed to the king a forged letter sealed with a counterfeit
                        of T. Quinctius' seal. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The letter
                        deprecated any harsh judgment of Demetrius, and stated that whatever
                        communication the young prince in his eagerness for the crown had had with
                        him, T. Quinctius, he was certain that he would do nothing to injure any of
                        his relatives, nor was the writer a man who could be thought to countenance
                        any unfilial conduct. This letter made Perseus' accusations appear more
                        credible. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Heliodorus was at once submitted
                        to torture and died without implicating anyone. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus made fresh accusations against
                        Demetrius to his father. He alleged the preparations for his flight and the
                        bribery of some who were to accompany him. The forged letter purporting to
                        come from T. Quinctius, he said, was the strongest proof of his guilt.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> No pronouncement was, however, made as
                        to the infliction of any severe punishment, the intention was rather that he
                        should be put to death secretly, not through any anxiety felt about him, but
                        that Philip's designs against the Romans might not be revealed by a public
                        sentence of death. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Philip was marching
                        from Thessalonica to Demetrias, and he sent Demetrius, still accompanied by
                        Didas, to Astraeum in Paeonia, and Perseus to Amphipolis, to receive the
                        Thracian hostages. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is said that as
                        Didas was departing, Philip gave him instructions about putting his son to
                        death. Didas arranged a sacrifice or else pretended to do so, and Demetrius
                        was invited to the sacrificial banquet and went to Heraclea for the purpose.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It is said that poison was given to
                        him at the banquet, and that as soon as he drank the goblet he became aware
                        of it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Very soon he was in great
                        suffering., and he left the table and retired to his room. There he lay in
                        agony exclaiming against his father's cruelty, and accusing his brother and
                        Didas of murdering him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then one Thyrsis
                        of Stubera and a Beroean named Alexander entered the room, threw the
                        bed-clothes over his head and suffocated him. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In this way the unoffending youth was killed, as his
                        enemies were not content with only one way of putting him to death. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these occurrences in Macedonia, L.
                        Aemilius Paulus, whose command had been extended on the expiry of his
                        consulship, marched against the Ingauni in Liguria. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as he had encamped on the enemy's territory,
                        envoys came to him ostensibly to sue for peace, but really as spies. Paulus
                        told them that he only made terms with those who surrendered. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> They did not definitely reject his conditions,
                        but explained that they would require time to induce their people, a rustic
                        population, to submit. An armistice for ten days was granted them.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then they asked that his soldiers
                        might be forbidden to cross the mountains to gather fodder and wood-that
                        cultivated part of the country formed part of their territory. They gained
                        his consent to this also, and at once concentrated an enormous host behind
                        those very mountains from which they were keeping their enemies away.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A fierce attack was made on the Roman
                        camp, all the gates being assaulted at once, and they kept up the attack
                        with the utmost violence during the whole day. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans had no room for advancing against them, no
                        sufficient ground for forming their battle-line. Massed in close order at
                        the gates they defended the camp more by forming a barrier than by actual
                        fighting. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At sunset the enemy withdrew and
                        Paulus sent two troopers to the proconsul at Pisae with a despatch informing
                        him that his camp was invested in breach of the armistice, and asking him to
                        come to his assistance as soon as possible. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> Baebius had handed over his army to the praetor M. Pinarius, who was on
                        his way to Sardinia; however, he wrote to inform the senate that L. Aemilius
                        was blockaded in his camp by the Ligurians, and he also <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> wrote to M. Claudius Marcellus, whose province
                        adjoined, that if he thought it wise he should transfer his army from Gaul
                        to Liguria and relieve L. Aemilius from investment. This assistance would
                        have been long in coming. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The following
                        day the Ligurians renewed their attack on the camp. Though L. Aemilius knew
                        that they would come, and though he could have led out his men in line of
                        battle, he kept them within their rampart in order that he might delay a
                        battle till such time as Baebius could come with his army from Pisae. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Baebius' despatch created considerable
                        alarm in Rome, which was increased by the arrival of Marcellus a few days
                        later. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had handed over his army to
                        Fabius, and he told the senate that there was no hope of the army in Gaul
                        being transferred to Liguria because it was engaged with the Histri, who
                        were trying to prevent the formation of the colony at Aquileia. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Fabius, he explained, had marched thither, and
                        could not retrace his steps now that war had begun. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> There was one chance of sending help, though that would
                        be later than the emergency demanded, namely, if the consuls hastened their
                        departure for the province. All the senators were loud in their demand that
                        they should go. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls declared that
                        they would not go until the enrolment of troops was completed, and it was
                        not through remissness on their part but through the violence of the
                        epidemic that the completion was delayed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        They were unable, however, to hold out against the unanimous determination
                        of the senate, and left the City wearing the paludamentum, having appointed
                        a day for the men whom they had enrolled to assemble at Pisae. The consuls
                        were empowered to raise men indiscriminately as they went on, and take them
                        with them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The praetors Q. Petilius and Q.
                        Fabius received orders to raise fresh troops; Petilius to enrol two
                        emergency legions of Roman citizens and to require all under fifty years of
                        age to take the military oath; Fabius to demand from the Latin allies 15,000
                        infantry and 800 cavalry. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> C. Matienus and
                        C. Lucretius were appointed to the naval command and ships were fitted out
                        for them. Matienus, who was to command it in the Gulf of Gaul, was also
                        ordered to bring his fleet as soon as possible down to the coast of Liguria
                        in case it could be of any assistance to L. Aemilius and his army. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As there were no signs of assistance
                        coming anywhere, Aemilius supposed that his mounted messengers had been
                        intercepted, and felt that he ought not any longer to delay trying what
                        Fortune had in store for him single-handed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> The enemy's attacks showed less spirit and force, and before their next
                        assault he drew up his army at the four gates in order that on the signal
                        being given they might make a simultaneous sortie on all sides. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> To the four praetorian cohorts he added two
                        others with M. Valerius, one of his staff officers, in command, and gave
                        them orders to sally from the praetorian gate. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> At the southern gate he posted the hastati of the first
                        legion; the principes of this legion being in reserve. M. Servilius and L.
                        Sulpicius, both military tribunes, were in command of these. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The third legion was similarly drawn up at the
                        north gate, with this difference that the principes formed the front, the
                        hastati the reserve. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The military tribunes
                        Sextius Julius Caesar and L. Aurelius Cotta were in command of this legion.
                        Q. Fulvius Flaccus, a staff officer, was posted with the right division of
                        allied troops at the quaestorian gate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Two
                        cohorts and the triarii of the two legions were ordered to remain and guard
                        the camp. The general visited all the gates to harangue his men and whet
                        their rage against the enemy by everything that could exasperate them.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He spoke bitterly of the treachery of
                        the enemy who, after suing for peace and being allowed a suspension of arms,
                        had come <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> to attack the camp while the
                        armistice was actually in force, in violation of all international law. He
                        pointed out what a disgrace it was for a Roman army to be hemmed in by
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> Ligurians, who could be more truly
                        described as a horde of robbers than as a regular enemy. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> "If," he continued, "you get out of this with the help
                        of others, and not by your own courage, with what face will any of you
                        meet-I do not say the soldiers who defeated Hannibal, Philip or Antiochus,
                        the greatest generals and monarchs of our time, but-those who have so often
                        pursued and cut to pieces these very Ligurians as they fled like frightened
                        cattle through their pathless forests? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        What the Spaniards, the Gauls, the Macedonians, the Carthaginians did not
                        dare to do, this the Ligurian is doing today; he comes up to the Roman
                        rampart and actually surrounds and attacks our camp. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> And yet, formerly, it was hard to discover him after a
                        close search as he lurked in his trackless hiding-places!" His words were
                        met by a unanimous shout of approval from the soldiers. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> It was no fault of theirs, they said; no one had given
                        the signal for a sortie; let him give the signal now, he would soon learn
                        that the Romans and the Ligurians were the same that they had always been.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The two camps of the Ligurians were on the
                        near side of the mountain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During the
                        first days they all used to march out of their camps at sunrise in proper
                        formation; afterwards they did not take up arms unless they had been gorged
                        with food and wine; they left their camps without any order, scattered about
                        the field, feeling confident that their enemy would not advance outside his
                        rampart. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whilst they were coming up in
                        this disorderly fashion, the battle-shout was suddenly raised by every one
                        in the camp, camp-followers and sutlers alike, and the Romans dashed out
                        from all the gates. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So little did the
                        Ligurians expect this that they were thrown into as much confusion as if
                        they had fallen into an ambush. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For a few
                        moments there was some appearance of a battle, then there was a wild flight
                        and slaughter of the fugitives in all directions. The signal was given to
                        the cavalry to mount their horses and allow no one to escape; the enemy were
                        all driven headlong into their camp and then driven out of it. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Over 15,000 Ligurians were killed that day and
                        2500 taken prisoners. Three days afterwards the entire tribe of the Ingauni
                        made their submission and gave hostages. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Search was made for the pilots and sailors who had been in the pirate ships,
                        and they were all placed under guard. Thirty-two of these ships were
                        captured by Matienus off the coast of Liguria. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> L. Aurelius Cotta and C. Sulpicius Gallus were sent to
                        Rome to report what had happened and also to request that L. Aemilius,
                        having brought his province into order, might be permitted to leave and
                        bring away his soldiers with him and then disband them. Both requests were
                        granted by the senate and thanksgivings at all the shrines were ordered for
                        three days. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Petilius was ordered to
                        disband the citizen legions, and Fabius received orders to suspend the
                        enrolment of Latin and allied troops. The City praetor was also ordered by
                        the senate to write to the consuls and inform them that the senate thought
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> it right that the men which had
                        been hastily raised to meet the emergency should be disbanded as soon as
                        possible. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A colony was settled this year at Gravisca
                        in Etruria on territory which had formerly been taken from the Tarquinii.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Five jugera were given to each man;
                        the supervisors of the settlement were C. Calpurnius Piso, P. Claudius
                        Pulcher and C Terentius Istra. The year was marked by a drought and failure
                        of the crops. It is recorded that no rain fell for six months. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> During this year while labourers were digging at
                        some depth on land belonging to L. Petilius, a scrivener who lived at the
                        foot of the Janiculum, two stone chests were discovered about eight feet
                        long and four wide, the lids being fastened down with lead. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Each bore an inscription in Latin and Greek; one
                        stating that Numa Pompilius, son of Pompo and king of the Romans, was buried
                        there, and the other saying that it contained his books. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> When the owner at the suggestion of his friends had
                        opened them, the one which bore the inscription of the buried king was found
                        to be empty, with no vestige of a human body or of anything else, so
                        completely had everything disappeared after such a lapse of time. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> In the other there were two bundles tied round
                        with cords steeped in wax, each containing seven books, not only intact but
                        to all appearance new. There were seven in Latin on pontifical law, and
                        seven in Greek dealing with the study of philosophy so far as was possible
                        in that age. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias says further
                        that they were Pythagorean books, thus shaping his belief to the common
                        opinion that Numa was <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> a disciple of
                        Pythagoras, and trying to give probability to a fiction. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The books were first examined by the
                        friends who were present. As the number of those who read them grew, and
                        they became widely known, Q. Petilius, the City praetor, was anxious to read
                        them and took them from Lucius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They were
                        on very friendly terms; when Q. Petilius was quaestor he had given Lucius
                        Petilius a place on the decury. After perusing the most important passages
                        he perceived that most of them would lead to the break-up of the national
                        religion. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Lucius promised that he would
                        throw the books into the fire, but before doing so said that he should like
                        to find out, if allowed to do so, whether he could reclaim them either by
                        the right of possession or by the authority of the tribunes of the plebs,
                        without, however, disturbing his friendly relations with the praetor. The
                        scrivener approached the tribunes, and the tribunes left the matter for the
                        senate to deal with. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The praetor stated
                        that he was ready to declare on oath that the books ought not to be
                        preserved. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The senate held the praetor's
                        asseveration to be sufficient, and that the books ought to be burnt as soon
                        as possible in the comitium. Whatever sum the praetor and the majority of
                        the tribunes thought a fair price for the books was to be paid to the owner.
                        The scrivener refused to accept it. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                        books were burnt in the comitium in the sight of the people in a fire made
                        by the victimarii. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A serious war broke out this summer in
                        Hither Spain. The Celtiberi had got together as many as 35,000 men; hardly
                        ever before had they raised so large a force. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Q. Fulvius Flaccus was in charge of the province. On
                        hearing that the Celtiberi were arming their fighting men, he had drawn from
                        the friendly tribes all the troops he could, but he was very inferior to the
                        enemy in numbers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the first days of
                        spring he led his army into Carpetania and fixed his camp near the town of
                        Aebura, a small detachment being sent to occupy the town. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> A few days afterwards the Celtiberi encamped at the
                        foot of a hill about two miles distant. When the Roman praetor became aware
                        of their proximity, he sent his brother Marcus with two squadrons of native
                        cavalry to reconnoitre the enemy's camp. His instructions were to approach
                        as closely as possible to the rampart so as to get some idea of the size of
                        the camp, but if he saw the enemy's cavalry coming, he was to retire without
                        fighting. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These instructions he carried
                        out. For some days nothing took place beyond the appearance of these two
                        squadrons, and they were always withdrawn after the enemy's cavalry had
                        emerged from their camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At last the
                        Celtiberi issued from their camp with the whole of their infantry and
                        cavalry, and formed up in line of battle midway between the two camps and
                        remained stationary. The ground was level and well adapted for a battle.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There the Spaniards stood in
                        expectancy, whilst the Roman general kept his men within their rampart. For
                        four successive days the enemy took their stand in battle-order on the same
                        spot, but the Romans made no move. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After
                        this the Celtiberi rested in their camp as they had no opportunity of
                        fighting; the cavalry alone rode out and took station as advanced pickets,
                        in case of any movement on the part of their enemy. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Both sides went out to collect fodder and wood in the
                        rear of their camps, neither of them interfering with the other. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Roman praetor had satisfied
                        himself that after so many days' inaction the enemy would not expect him to
                        take the initiative, he ordered L. Acilius to take the division of allied
                        troops and 6000 native auxiliaries, and make a circuit round the mountain
                        which lay behind the enemy's camp. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he
                        heard the battle-shout he was to charge down on their camp. They started in
                        the night to escape observation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At
                        daybreak Flaccus sent C. Scribonius, the commander of the allied troops,
                        with his "select" cavalry up to the enemy's rampart. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When the Celtiberi saw them approaching more closely
                        and in greater strength than they had usually done, the whole of their
                        cavalry streamed out from the camp and the signal was given for the infantry
                        also to advance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Scribonius, acting on his
                        instructions, no sooner heard the clatter of the advancing cavalry than he
                        turned his horses' heads and made for his camp. The enemy followed in hot
                        haste. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> First their cavalry came up and
                        soon after the infantry, never doubting but that they would that day capture
                        the Roman camp. They were not now more than half a mile from the rampart.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as Flaccus considered that
                        they were sufficiently drawn off from guarding their own camp he sallied
                        forth from his camp, his army which had previously been drawn up inside the
                        rampart being formed into three separate corps. The battle-shout was raised
                        not only to stimulate the ardour of the combatants but also to reach the
                        ears of those who were amongst the hills. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Without a moment's delay these charged down, as they had been ordered, on
                        the enemy's camp, where not more than 5000 men were left on guard.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The strength of the assailants
                        compared with their own scanty numbers and the suddenness of the attack so
                        appalled them that the camp was taken with little or no resistance. When it
                        was captured Acilius set fire to that part of it which could be best seen
                        from the field of battle. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Celtiberi who were in the rear were
                        the first to catch sight of the flames; then word ran through the whole line
                        that the camp was lost and was burning furiously. This increased the dismay
                        of the enemy and the courage of the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> On the one hand there were the cheers of their victorious comrades, on
                        the other the sight of the hostile camp in flames. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The Celtiberi were for a few moments uncertain what to
                        do, but as there was no shelter for them if they <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> were defeated, and their only hope lay in keeping up
                        the struggle, they recommenced the fight with greater determination.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their centre was being closely pressed
                        by the fifth legion, but they advanced with more confidence against the
                        Roman left where they saw that their own countrymen were posted, and it
                        would have been repulsed had not the seventh legion come up in support. The
                        troops left to hold Aebura appeared in the middle of the battle and Acilius
                        was in the enemy's rear. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Between the two
                        the Celtiberi were being cut to pieces; the survivors fled in all
                        directions. The cavalry were sent after them in two divisions and caused
                        great slaughter among them. As many as 23,000 men were killed that day, and
                        4700 were made prisoners; 500 horses and 88 military standards were
                        captured. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was a great victory, but not
                        a bloodless one. Out of the two legions rather more than 200 Roman soldiers
                        fell, 830 out of the Latin allies, and 2400 out of the native auxiliaries.
                        The praetor led his victorious army back to camp. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Acilius was ordered to remain in the camp he had
                        captured. The following day the spoils were collected, and those who had
                        shown conspicuous bravery were rewarded in the presence of the whole army.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The wounded were carried into Aebura and
                        the legions marched through Carpetania to Contrebia. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When this city was invested, the townspeople sent to
                        the Celtiberi for assistance. This was delayed, not through any reluctance
                        on the part of the Celtiberi, but because they could not make their way over
                        the roads which were rendered impassable and the rivers which were flooded
                        by incessant rain. Despairing of any help from their countrymen, the
                        inhabitants surrendered. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Flaccus found
                        himself compelled by the terrible storms to move his entire army into the
                        city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Celtiberi, meanwhile, had
                        started from home in ignorance of the surrender, and as soon as the rain
                        stopped they succeeded at last in crossing the rivers and arrived before
                        Contrebia. They saw no camp outside the walls, and concluding that it had
                        been transferred elsewhere, or else that the enemy had withdrawn, they
                        approached the town without taking precautions or keeping any proper
                        formation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans made a sortie from
                        two gates, and attacking them whilst in disorder, routed them. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The very thing that made resistance impossible,
                        namely, their not marching in one body, or keeping with their standards,
                        really helped the majority to escape, for the fugitives dispersed all over
                        the field and the Romans could nowhere intercept any considerable number
                        together. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, the killed
                        amounted to 12,000 and the prisoners to more than 5000; 400 horses and 62
                        standards were also secured. The scattered fugitives made their way to their
                        homes, and meeting another body of Celtiberi who were going to Contrebia,
                        stopped them by informing them of the surrender of the place and of their
                        own defeat. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All promptly dispersed to
                        their forts and villages. Leaving Contrebia Flaccus led the legions through
                        Celtiberia, ravaging the country as he marched and storming many of the
                        forts until the greater part of the nation came in to make their surrender.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such were the incidents this year in
                        Hither Spain. In Further Spain the praetor Manlius fought several successful
                        actions with the Lusitanians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aquileia, a city situated on land
                        belonging to the Gauls, received this year a body of Latin colonists;
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> 3000 infantry soldiers were settled
                        there, and each man was allotted 50 jugera, the centurions 100, and the
                        cavalry men 140. The supervisors of the settlement were P. Cornelius Scipio
                        Nasica, C. Flaminius and L. Manlius Acidinus. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Two temples were dedicated during the year, one to
                        Venus Erycina, by the Porta Collina-this <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                        temple had been vowed by L. Porcius in the Ligurian war and was dedicated by
                        his son-the other, the temple of Pietas in the Forum Olitorium. Manius
                        Acilius Glabrio dedicated this temple and set up a gilt statue of his father
                        Glabrio, the first gilded statue to be set up in Italy. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He had himself vowed this temple on the day of his
                        battle with Antiochus at Thermopylae and had also contracted for the
                        building of it in accordance with a resolution of the senate. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> At the time of the dedication of these temples L.
                        Aemilius Paulus celebrated his triumph over the Ingauni. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Twenty-five golden crowns were borne in the procession;
                        there was no other gold or silver in the triumph. Many Ligurian chiefs
                        walked as prisoners before his chariot. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To
                        each soldier he gave as his share of the booty 300 ases. His triumph was
                        notable for the presence of Ligurian envoys who had come to pray for a
                        perpetual peace. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So thoroughly had he made
                        that people understand that they must never again take up arms except at the
                        bidding of Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> By order of the senate
                        the praetor informed them in answer to their request that this was no new
                        petition on the part of the Ligurians, there must be a new spirit and temper
                        corresponding to it, and this rested above all with themselves. They must go
                        to the consuls and carry out whatever they ordered. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The senate would not believe that the Ligurians meant
                        honestly and sincerely to keep the peace on any one's word but the consuls'.
                        Peace was established with them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In
                        Corsica there was fighting with the natives, M. Pinarius slew 2000 of them
                        in battle. Through this defeat they were driven to give hostages and also
                        100,000 pounds of wax. Pinarius took his army to Sardinia and fought
                        successful actions with the Ilienses, a tribe which to this day is not
                        thoroughly pacified. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In the course of
                        this year the hundred hostages were restored to the <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> Carthaginians and the Roman people brought about peace
                        not only on their side, but also on the side of Masinissa, who was in
                        forcible occupation of the disputed territory. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls' province remained quiet. M.
                        Baebius was recalled to Rome to conduct the elections. A. Postumius Albinus
                        Luscus and C. Calpurnius Piso were the new consuls. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The praetors elected were Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus,
                        L. Postumius Albinus, P. Cornelius Mammula, Ti. Minucius Molliculus, A.
                        Hostilius Mancinus and C. Maenius. All these magistrates entered upon office
                        on the Ides of March. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the beginning of
                        his year of office A. Postumius introduced to the senate L. Minucius, a
                        staff officer, and two military tribunes, T. Maenius and L. Terentius
                        Massiliota, who had come from Q. Fulvius Flaccus in Hither Spain. They gave
                        a report of the two victorious battles, the surrender of the Celtiberi and
                        the establishment of order throughout the province, and told the senate that
                        there was no <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> need of the pay which was
                        usually sent nor of any supply of corn to the army for that year. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> They then requested that honour might be paid to
                        the immortal gods for these successes and that Q. Fulvius should be allowed
                        to bring back on his departure from Spain the army whose courage had been of
                        such service to him and to many praetors before him. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> This was not only due to them, but it was all but
                        inevitable, for the soldiers were in such a determined mood that it appeared
                        impossible to keep them any longer in the province, and if they were not
                        disbanded, they were prepared to leave without orders, or if they were kept
                        back by a strong hand, would break out into a dangerous mutiny. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate ordered the consuls to take
                        Liguria as their province. Then the praetors balloted for their provinces.
                        Hither Spain fell to Tiberius Sempronius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        As he was to succeed Q. Fulvius he did not want the province to be robbed of
                        the veteran army and accordingly made the following speech in the senate:
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "I ask you, L. Minucius, since you
                        report that the province is in a settled state, whether it is your belief
                        that the Celtiberi will always keep their word so that this province can be
                        held without the presence of an army? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If
                        you can neither assure yourself nor give us any guarantee of their remaining
                        permanently at peace, and still hold that in any case an army must be kept
                        there, would <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> you advise the senate to
                        send such reinforcements as will only allow the time-expired soldiers to be
                        released, the recruits being incorporated in the old army, or would you say
                        that the veteran legions should be withdrawn and fresh ones enrolled and
                        sent there, when the contempt felt for these raw recruits might possibly
                        excite even the less aggressive barbarians to resume hostilities? <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> To say that you have pacified and settled a
                        province whose inhabitants are naturally warlike and aggressive may be
                        easier than to do it. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> According to what I
                        hear only a few communities, mainly those where we have made our winter
                        quarters, have submitted to our authority; those further off are in arms.
                        Under these circumstances, senators, I declare at the outset that I am ready
                        to take the government of the province with the army which is there now.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> If Flaccus brings his legions with
                        him, I shall select for my winter quarters places already pacified, and
                        shall not expose my new soldiers to a most fierce enemy." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In reply to these questions Minucius said
                        that neither he nor any one else could possibly divine what the intentions
                        of the Celtiberi were at the time or what they might be in the future.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He could not therefore deny that it
                        might be better for an army to be sent even to those of the natives who had
                        been reduced to submission but were not accustomed to our rule. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> But whether there was need of the old army or of
                        a new one was for him to say who was in a position to know how far the
                        Celtiberi would keep the peace, and who had also definitely ascertained
                        whether the soldiers would take it quietly if they were retained in the
                        province. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If their sentiments were to be
                        inferred from what they say to one another, or from their exclamations when
                        their commander addresses them on parade, then it ought to be known that
                        they had openly and loudly declared that they <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> would either keep their general in the province or else
                        go back with him to Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This discussion
                        was interrupted by the consuls, who gave it as their opinion that the right
                        and proper course was for their province to be provided for before the
                        question of a praetor's army was raised. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A
                        whole new army was decreed for the consuls; two Roman legions for each with
                        their full complement of cavalry and the usual proportion of Latin and
                        allied troops, namely 15,000 infantry and 800 cavalry. With this army they
                        were commissioned to make war on the Apuani in Liguria. P. Cornelius and M.
                        Baebius were ordered to retain their commands until the consuls arrived,
                        then after disbanding their army they were to return to Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the question of the army for Tiberius
                        Sempronius was settled. The consuls were ordered to enrol for him a fresh
                        legion of 5200 infantry and 400 cavalry and an additional force of 1000
                        infantry and 50 cavalry. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They were also to
                        require the Latin allies to furnish 7000 infantry and 300 cavalry. Such was
                        the army with which it was decided that Tiberius Sempronius should go to
                        Hither Spain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Q. Flaccus received
                        permission to bring away with him, if he thought fit, those soldiers,
                        whether Roman citizens or allies, who had been transferred to Spain previous
                        to the consulship of Spurius Postumius and Q. Marcius. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> When by the addition of the reinforcements the two
                        legions had been raised above their normal strength, namely 14,000 infantry
                        and 600 cavalry, Flaccus was at liberty to bring away all in excess of that
                        number whose bravery had been of such service to Flaccus in his two
                        successful actions against the Celtiberi. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Thanksgivings were also decreed for his good services to the State. The
                        other praetors were then sent off to their provinces; Q. Fabius Buteo was
                        continued in his command in Gaul. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It was
                        decided that there should be only eight legions for that year besides the
                        old army in Liguria who were expecting their discharge shortly. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Even that force was with difficulty made up
                        owing to the pestilence which had for three years been devastating Rome and
                        Italy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="48??" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The death of the praetor Tiberius Minucius
                        and not long after that of the consul C. Calpurnius, followed by those of
                        many distinguished men of all ranks, came to be regarded as a portent.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> C. Servilius, the Pontifex Maximus,
                        was instructed to search in the pontifical rolls for the method of appeasing
                        the wrath of the gods, and the Keepers of the Sacred Books were to examine
                        their Sibylline Books. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul was
                        ordered to vow and offer gilded statues to Apollo, Aesculapius and Salus.
                        The Keepers of the Sacred Books proclaimed special intercessions for two
                        days in the City, and in all market-towns and places of public resort.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All who were above twelve years of age
                        took part in the intercessions, wearing wreaths of bay and carrying branches
                        of it in their hands. Men began to suspect that this was the work of
                        criminals, and the senate ordered investigations to be made into some cases
                        of alleged poisoning. C. Claudius was charged with this enquiry in the City
                        and within a radius of ten miles from it; C. Maenius was to undertake it in
                        the market-towns and places of public resort outside that limit, before he
                        sailed for his province of Sardinia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        death of the consul aroused the strongest suspicion. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He is said to have been murdered by his wife, Quarta
                        Hostilia. When her son Q. Fulvius Flaccus was declared consul in place of
                        his step-father, the death of Piso aroused much greater misgivings.
                        Witnesses came forward who asserted that after Albinus and Piso had been
                        declared consuls, Flaccus having been defeated in the election was
                        reproached by his mother for having failed three times in his candidature
                        for the consulship, and she went on to say that she was getting ready to
                        canvass and would manage in less than two months to have him made consul.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Amongst much other evidence bearing on
                        the case this utterance of hers, which was only too truly confirmed by what
                        followed, did most to secure her condemnation. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> While the consuls were detained in Rome by the
                        enrolment of fresh troops and matters were still further delayed by the
                        death of one of them, and the holding of an election to choose his
                        successor, P. Cornelius and M. Baebius, who during their consulship
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> had done nothing of any importance,
                        now, at the beginning of spring, led their armies against the Apuani. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This Ligurian tribe, who had not expected
                        that war would begin before the arrival of the new consuls, were taken
                        wholly by surprise, and after a crushing defeat surrendered <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> to the number of 12,000. After consulting the
                        senate by letter, Cornelius and Baebius decided to remove them from their
                        mountains into some open and level country far from their homes, so that
                        there could be no hope of return; for they did not see any other end of the
                        Ligurian wars. There was some land in Samnium, forming part of the State
                        domain, which had belonged to Taurania. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The consuls wished to settle the Ligurians in this district, and they issued
                        an order for them to come down from Anidus and their mountain homes with
                        their wives and children and take all their property with them. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The Ligurians made frequent appeals through their
                        envoys, begging that they might not be compelled to abandon their household
                        gods, the homes in which they <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> had been
                        born and the burial-places of their forefathers, and promising to surrender
                        their arms and give hostages. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they
                        found all their appeals fruitless, and knew that they were not strong enough
                        for war, they obeyed the consuls' edict. As many as 40,000 freemen with
                        their wives and children were transported at the expense of the government;
                        150,000 silver denarii were allowed them to procure necessaries for their
                        new homes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cornelius and Baebius were also
                        authorised to distribute and assign the land; they asked, however, that five
                        assessors might be appointed to assist them, and the senate appointed them.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After finishing this business they
                        brought their army of veterans to Rome, and the senate decreed a triumph for
                        them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These men were the very first to
                        enjoy a triumph without having been engaged in a war. Only victims for
                        sacrifice were led before the chariot; there were no prisoners, no spoils,
                        nothing to distribute amongst the soldiers. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As his successor was somewhat late in
                        reaching Spain, Fulvius Flaccus led out his army from winter quarters and
                        began to devastate the more distant parts of Celtiberia, where the
                        inhabitants had not come in to surrender. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        By this action he irritated the natives more than he intimidated them, and
                        secretly collecting a force they beset the Manlian Pass, through which they
                        were tolerably certain that the Romans would march. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Gracchus had instructed his colleague, L. Postumius
                        Albinus, who was on his way to Further Spain, to inform Q. Fulvius that he
                        was to bring his army to Tarraco, where he intended to disband the old
                        soldiers, incorporate the reinforcements into the various corps and
                        reorganise the whole army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fulvius was
                        also informed of the date of his successor's arrival which was close at
                        hand. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This information compelled Flaccus
                        to abandon his projected operations and withdraw his army hastily from
                        Celtiberia. The barbarians, ignorant of the true reason, and imagining that
                        he had become aware of their rising and secret gathering in arms and was
                        afraid of them, invested the pass all the more closely. When the Roman
                        column entered the pass, the enemy rushed down upon it from both sides.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as Flaccus saw this, he
                        allayed the first symptoms of tumult in the column by giving the order
                        through the centurions for every <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> man to
                        stand where he was and get his weapons ready. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The packs of the baggage animals were piled up in one
                        place, and partly by his own exertions, partly through his officers, he got
                        the whole force into such fighting order as the time and place required.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He reminded his men that they had to
                        deal with those who had twice made their submission and who were impelled by
                        treachery, not by true courage. His soldiers, he told them, would have
                        returned home without distinguishing themselves; the enemy had given them
                        the chance of a glorious and memorable homecoming. They would carry in
                        triumph through Rome swords reddened with the slaughter of their foes and
                        spoils dripping with their blood. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Time
                        did not allow him to say more; the enemy were upon them and fighting was
                        already begun at the outermost points. Then the two lines closed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle was everywhere a desperate one,
                        but with changing fortunes. The legionaries fought splendidly, nor did the
                        two divisions of allied troops offer a less vigorous resistance. The native
                        auxiliaries confronted by men similarly armed, but somewhat better fighters,
                        could not hold their ground. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the
                        Celtiberi found that their regular order of battle made them no <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> match for the legions, they bore down upon them
                        in wedge-formation, a maneuver which gives them such weight that in whatever
                        direction they carry their attack it cannot be withstood. Even the legions
                        were now thrown into disorder and the Roman line was all but broken.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fulvius, seeing this, galloped up to
                        the legionary cavalry and shouted: "Unless you can come to the rescue it
                        will be all over with this army." "Say," they shouted in reply, "what you
                        want done, we shall not be slack in carrying out your orders." <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He replied: "Close up your squadrons, cavalry of
                        the two legions, and let your horses go where the enemy wedge is pressing
                        our men. Your charge will have all the greater force if you make it on
                        unbitted horses." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> (We have heard that
                        Roman cavalry have often done that and covered themselves with glory.)
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They removed the horses' bits and
                        charged the wedge in both directions, first forward and then back again,
                        inflicting great slaughter upon the enemy and shivering all their spears.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the wedge on which all their
                        hopes rested was broken up, the Celtiberi so completely lost heart that they
                        gave up almost any attempt at fighting and began to look about for means of
                        escape. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the auxiliary cavalry saw the
                        notable feat of the Roman horse they, too, fired by the courage of the
                        others, and without waiting for orders, spurred their horses against the
                        enemy who was now thoroughly shaken. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This
                        proved decisive; the Celtiberi fled precipitately in all directions, and the
                        Roman commander, watching them as they turned their backs, vowed a temple to
                        Fortuna Equestris and the celebration of solemn Games to Jupiter Optimus
                        Maximus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Celtiberi, scattered in
                        flight, were cut to pieces all through the pass. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> It is asserted that 17,000 of the enemy were killed on
                        that day, and more than 4000 taken alive, together with 277 military
                        standards and nearly 600 horses. The victorious army remained encamped in
                        the pass. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The victory was not without
                        loss; 472 Roman soldiers, 1019 soldiers of the allies and 3000 native
                        auxiliaries perished on the field. With its former glory thus renewed the
                        victorious army marched to Tarraco. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        Tiberius Sempronius, who had landed two days before, went to meet Fulvius
                        and congratulated him upon his successful conduct of affairs. They were
                        quite at one as to which soldiers they should release and which retain.
                        After releasing the time-expired men from their military oath, Fulvius
                        embarked with them for Italy. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Sempronius
                        led the legions into Celtiberia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The two consuls advanced against the
                        Ligurians by different routes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Postumius
                        with the first and third legions closed round the mountains of Ballista and
                        Suismontium, and posted detachments to block the passes. By thus cutting off
                        their supplies and reducing them to complete destitution, he brought them to
                        terms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fulvius moved out from Pisae with
                        the second and fourth legions, and marched against those of the Apuani who
                        dwelt round the Macra, and after receiving their surrender placed some 7000
                        of them on board ship and sailing along the Etruscan coast landed them at
                        Neapolis. From there they were transported to Samnium, and land was assigned
                        to them amongst their own countrymen. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        Ligurians who dwelt in the mountains had their vineyards cut <milestone
                            n="5??" unit="section"/> down and their corn crops burnt by A.
                        Postumius, until after suffering all the miseries of war they were compelled
                        to submit and give up their arms. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From
                        there Postumius sailed on a tour of inspection along the coast occupied by
                        the Ingauni and Intemelii. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Before the new
                        consuls joined the army which was to assemble at Pisae, A. Postumius
                        remained in command. M. Fulvius Nobilior, brother of Q. Fulvius, who was a
                        military tribune in the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> second legion,
                        during his two months of office, disbanded the legion, having first exacted
                        an oath from the centurions that they would carry the unexpended soldiers'
                        pay back to the quaestors who had charge of the treasury. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as Aulus heard of this at Placentia, where he
                        happened to be at the time, he followed the disbanded soldiers, and those
                        whom he caught he sternly rebuked and took them back to Pisae, and sent word
                        to the consul about the others. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        consul laid the matter before the senate, and they passed a resolution that
                        M. Fulvius should be relegated to a part of Spain beyond New Carthage, and a
                        letter was handed to him by the consul to be given to P. Manlius in Further
                        Spain. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The soldiers were ordered to
                        rejoin their standards; and in the case of any soldier who did not return to
                        the army, the consul received orders to sell him as a slave and all his
                        goods. In consequence of their disgraceful conduct, it was decreed that this
                        legion should only receive half the year's pay. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> L. Duronius, who had been commanding as
                        praetor in Illyria, returned this year to Brundisium. In giving his report
                        of what he had done, he unhesitatingly threw all the responsibility for the
                        piracy on Gentius, the King of Illyria; it was from his dominions that all
                        the ships had sailed which had ravaged the shores of the Hadriatic.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He stated, further, that he sent
                        envoys to the king to deal with the matter, but they had had no opportunity
                        of meeting him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A deputation from Gentius
                        went to Rome and explained that at the time when the Romans went to meet the
                        king he happened to be lying ill in the most distant part of his kingdom.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He asked the senate not to accept the
                        trumped-up charges against him which his enemies had made. In reply to this,
                        Duronius further stated that injuries had been inflicted on many Roman
                        citizens and Latin allies in his dominions, and it was reported that Roman
                        citizens were being detained in Corcyra. The senate decided that they should
                        all be brought to Rome and that the praetor C. Claudius should investigate
                        their case. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Till then no reply should be
                        given to Gentius or to his envoys. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Amongst the many who were carried off by
                        the epidemic this year were some of the priests. The pontiff L. Valerius
                        Flaccus died, and Q. Fabius Labeo was appointed in his place; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> P. Manlius, who had lately returned from Further
                        Spain, one of the three superintendents of the sacrificial banquets, fell a
                        victim, and Quinctus the son of M. Fulvius was appointed in his place, quite
                        a young man at the time. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The filling of
                        the vacancy caused by the death of Cneius Cornelius Dolabella, the rex
                        sacrificulus, led to a dispute between the Pontifex Maximus C. Servilius and
                        L. Cornelius Dolabella, one of the two directors of naval affairs. The
                        pontiff required him to resign his post in order that he might inaugurate
                        him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On his refusing to do so, the pontiff
                        imposed a fine upon him, and on his appeal the question of the fine was
                        argued before the Assembly. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When several
                        of the tribes had declared by their votes that the naval director should
                        comply with the pontiff's requirement, and that if he resigned his post the
                        fine should be remitted, a thunderstorm interrupted the proceedings.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The pontiffs were thus prevented on
                        religious grounds from appointing Dolabella, and they inaugurated P.
                        Claelius Siculus, who had the next largest number of votes. At the close of
                        the year the Pontifex Maximus died. C. Servilius Geminus was not only
                        Pontifex Maximus, but also one of the Keepers of the Sacred Books.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Q. Fulvius Flaccus was co-opted by
                        the college as one of the pontiffs, and M. Aemilius Lepidus was made
                        Pontifex Maximus in place of Geminus from among many distinguished
                        competitors. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In his place Q. Marcius
                        Philippus was chosen as a Keeper of the Sacred Books. The augur Sp.
                        Postumius also died and the other augurs co-opted P. Scipio the son of
                        Africanus to fill the vacancy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the year the people of Cuma sent a
                        request to be allowed to use Latin as the language of law and commerce.
                        Pisae offered land for the foundation of a Latin colony and was thanked by
                        the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The supervisors of the
                        settlement were Q. Fabius Buteo and the two Popillii Laenates, Marcus and
                        Publius. C. Maenius, to whom Sardinia had been allotted, had also been
                        charged with the investigation of the cases of poisoning which had occurred
                        beyond the ten-mile radius from the City. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        A letter was received from him stating that he had sentenced 3000 offenders,
                        and that the accumulating evidence was widening the scope of his enquiry;
                        either he would have to give up the task or resign his province. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Q. Fulvius Flaccus returned to Rome with a great
                        reputation after his work in Spain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While
                        he was still outside the City waiting for his triumph he was elected consul,
                        together with L. Manlius Acidinus, and a few days later he entered the City
                        in triumph with the soldiers he had brought with him. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> In the procession there were carried 124 golden crowns,
                        31 pounds of gold and 173,200 pieces of Oscan coinage. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> To each of the legionaries he gave from the sale of the
                        booty 50 denarii, double the amount to the centurions and treble to the
                        cavalry, and the same amount to the men of the Latin allies. All were alike
                        granted double pay. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A law was passed for the first time this
                        year fixing the age at which men could be candidates for or hold a
                        magistracy. It was introduced by L. Vilius, a tribune of the plebs, and from
                        this his family received the cognomen of Annalis. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> After many years had elapsed, four praetors were
                        elected this year under the Baebian Law, which laid down the rule that four
                        praetors should be elected in alternate years. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Those elected were Cnaeus Cornelius Scipio, C. Valerius
                        Laevinus, and two sons of M. Scaevola, Quinctius and Publius. The new
                        consuls had the same province assigned to them as their predecessors, and
                        the same number of Roman and allied infantry and cavalry. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In the two Spains, Ti. Sempronius and L. Postumius had
                        their commands extended and retained their armies. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> To reinforce them the consuls were instructed to enrol
                        3000 Roman infantry and 300 cavalry, and 5000 infantry and 400 cavalry from
                        the Latins and allies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> P. Mucius Scaevola
                        received the civic jurisdiction and was also charged with the investigation
                        into the poisoning cases in the City and within ten miles of it. Cn.
                        Cornelius Scipio had the alien jurisdiction; Q. Mucius Scaevola, Sicily; and
                        C. Valerius Laevinus, Sardinia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Before Q.
                        Fulvius commenced his duties as consul he said that he wished to discharge
                        the State from the obligation of his vows. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        He had on the day of his last battle with the Celtiberi vowed Games to
                        Jupiter Optimus Maximus and also a temple to Fortuna Equestris, and he had
                        collected money from the Spaniards for this purpose. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> A decree was made that the Games should be celebrated
                        and that two commissioners should be appointed to see to the construction of
                        the temple. A limit was fixed for the expenditure on the Games. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> It was not to exceed the sum which had been
                        decreed for the celebration of the Games after the Aetolian war by Fulvius
                        Nobilior, and the consul was forbidden to requisition or levy or accept or
                        do anything in respect of these Games in contravention of the resolution
                        passed by the senate during the consulship of L. Aemilius and Cn. Baebius.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The senate made their decree in this
                        form in consequence of the extravagant cost incurred in the Games exhibited
                        by <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> Ti. Sempronius in his capacity of
                        aedile, a cost which proved burdensome not only to Italy and the Latin
                        allies, but to the provinces abroad as well. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The winter was a severe one owing to snow
                        and storms of every description. The trees which were exposed to the icy
                        winds were all blasted, and the cold season lasted longer than usual.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One result of this was that the Latin
                        Festival was broken up by a terrible storm which burst suddenly upon the
                        Alban Mount, and the pontiffs ordered it to be celebrated afresh. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The same storm flung down some statues on the
                        Capitol and several localities were disfigured by lightning, amongst them
                        the temple of Jupiter in Terracina, the Alban temple at Capua and one of the
                        gates of Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In some places the
                        battlements were dislodged from the walls. Amongst these ominous occurrences
                        it was reported from Reate that a mule had been foaled with only three feet.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Keepers were ordered to consult
                        the Sacred Books, and they announced what deities were to be propitiated and
                        what victims were to be offered, and they also enjoined special
                        intercessions for one day. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After this the
                        Games which Q. Fulvius had vowed were exhibited on a grand scale for ten
                        days. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Next came the election of censors.
                        The new censors were M. Aemilius Lepidus, Pontifex Maximus, and M. Fulvius
                        Nobilior, who had celebrated his triumph over the Aetolians. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Between these two distinguished men there was a
                        feud which had often caused many violent quarrels between them in the senate
                        and before the Assembly. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the election
                        was over the censors took their seats, according to ancient custom, in
                        curule chairs at the altar of Mars in the Campus Martius. Suddenly the
                        leaders of the senate appeared, accompanied by a large body of citizens, and
                        Q. Caecilius Metellus addressed them in the following terms: </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "We have not forgotten, censors, that you
                        have just been chosen by the universal voice of the Roman people to
                        superintend our morals, and that we must be admonished and regulated by you,
                        not you by us. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> We are, however, bound to
                        point out what it is in you that gives offence to all good citizens, or at
                        all events what they would prefer to see changed. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When we contemplate you each by himself, M. Aemilius
                        and M. Fulvius, we feel that we have no one amongst the citizens today whom,
                        if we were recalled to the polling booths, we should wish to take precedence
                        of you. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when we behold you both
                        together we cannot help fearing that you are ill-suited for each other, and
                        that the unanimous vote in your favour will not benefit the commonwealth so
                        much as the entire absence of unanimity between yourselves will injure it.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For many years you have been
                        cherishing violent and bitter feelings against each other, and the danger is
                        that these may prove more disastrous to us and to the commonwealth than to
                        you. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Many considerations might be alleged,
                        unless you are deaf to all remonstrance, as to the causes of your mutual
                        hostility. We all of us with one voice implore you to put an end to these
                        quarrels on this day and on this hallowed ground; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> we ask that the men whom the Roman people have
                        associated together by their vote may through us be reconciled to one
                        another. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Choose the senate, revise the
                        equities, close the lustrum with one mind, one judgment, so that when you
                        repeat the formula of almost all the prayers: <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> 'May this prove to be a good and blessed thing for me
                        and my colleague,' you may in all sincerity desire and bring it about that
                        it shall so prove, so that what you have prayed for from the gods, we men
                        may believe you really wish for. In the very City where they met in hostile
                        encounter, Titus Tatius and Romulus reigned peacefully side by side.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Not only private quarrels, but even
                        wars are put an end to; deadly enemies generally prove the most faithful
                        allies; sometimes they even become fellow-citizens. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> When Alba was destroyed, the Albans were transferred to
                        Rome; the Latins and the Sabines have been admitted to our franchise. That
                        common saying: 'Friendships ought to be immortal, enmities mortal,' has
                        passed into a proverb because it is true." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Murmurs of approval were heard and then
                        the voices of all present, as though it were the voice of one making the
                        same request, drowned the speaker. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Hereupon Aemilius, amongst other things, complained that he had been twice
                        rejected by M. Fulvius as a candidate for the consulship when he was certain
                        to win it. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Fulvius, on the other hand,
                        protested that he had been constantly receiving provocation from Aemilius
                        and had undergone the humiliation of having to give security. They each,
                        however, signified that if the other was willing, he would bow to the
                        authority of such an influential body. As all present pressed their demand,
                        the censors grasped each other's hands and gave their word to dismiss all
                        angry feelings and put an end to their quarrel. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> They were then conducted to the Capitol amidst
                        universal applause, and the trouble which their leaders had taken over the
                        matter and the yielding temper of the censors received the approbation and
                        praise of the senate. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The censors asked
                        for a grant of money to spend on public works, and one year's revenue was
                        assigned to them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The propraetors in Spain agreed upon a
                        common plan of operation; Albinus was to march through Lusitania against the
                        Vaccaei, and if the Celtiberian war became more serious he was to return
                        thither; Gracchus, meantime, was to penetrate to the further borders of
                        Celtiberia. Making a nocturnal attack on the city of Munda, he took it at
                        the first assault. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After taking hostages
                        and placing a garrison to hold the place, he marched on, storming the forts
                        and burning the crops, till he came to another city of exceptional strength
                        called by the natives Certima. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was
                        already bringing up his engines against the walls when a deputation arrived
                        from the town. Their words betrayed a primitive simplicity; they made no
                        concealment of their intention to continue the struggle if they had the
                        strength. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They requested permission to
                        visit the Celtiberian camp and ask for help; if it were refused them they
                        would take counsel among themselves. Gracchus gave them permission, and in a
                        few days they returned, bringing with them ten more envoys. It was at the
                        hour of noon, and the first request they made to the praetor was that he
                        would order something to be given them to drink. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After emptying the cups they asked for more, and the
                        bystanders burst into peals of laughter at such boorishness and utter want
                        of manners. Then the oldest amongst them spoke: "We have been sent," he
                        said, "by our nation to enquire on what it is that you rely in carrying your
                        arms against us." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Gracchus told them that
                        he relied upon his splendid army, and if they wanted to see it for
                        themselves so that they might carry back a fuller account of it, he would
                        give them the opportunity of doing so. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                        then sent word to the military tribunes to order the whole of the force,
                        horse and foot, to equip themselves completely and practice their maneuvers
                        under arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After this exhibition the
                        envoys were sent home, and they dissuaded their countrymen from sending any
                        succour to the besieged city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The townsmen
                        kindled fires on their watch towers, but when they found that it was in
                        vain, and that their only hope of assistance had failed them, they
                        surrendered. A war indemnity of 2,400,000 sesterces was levied upon them.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They had also to give up forty youths
                        who were in their cavalry and belonged to their noblest families, not under
                        the name of hostages, for they were to serve in the Roman army, but as a
                        matter of fact they were pledges of the fidelity of their countrymen. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From there he advanced to the city of
                        Alce, where the camp from which the envoys had come was located. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> For some days he confined himself to annoying the
                        enemy by sending skirmishers against his advanced posts, but every day he
                        sent them out in stronger force in order to draw the full strength of the
                        enemy outside his lines. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he saw that
                        he had gained his object, he ordered the commanders of the native
                        auxiliaries to offer a slight resistance and then turn back in hasty flight
                        to their camp, as though they were overborne by numbers. He in the meanwhile
                        drew up his men at every one of the gates of the camp. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> No long time had elapsed when he saw his men flying
                        back in a body with the enemy following in disorderly pursuit. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Up to this point he kept his men within their
                        rampart, and now, only waiting till the fugitives could find shelter within
                        the camp, the battle-shout was raised and the Romans burst forth from all
                        the gates simultaneously. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The enemy could
                        not stand against this unlooked-for attack. They had come up to storm the
                        Roman camp; now they could not even defend their own. Routed, put to flight,
                        driven in a panic inside their rampart, they at last lost their camp.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were 9000 men killed that day,
                        320 taken prisoners, 112 horses and 37 military standards were captured. Out
                        of the Roman army 109 fell. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From the battlefield Gracchus led the
                        legions further into Celtiberia, which he ravaged and plundered. When the
                        natives saw him carrying off their property and driving away their cattle,
                        some of the tribes bowed their necks to the yoke voluntarily, others through
                        fear, and within a few days he accepted the surrender of a hundred and three
                        towns and secured an enormous amount of booty. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Then he marched back to Alce and commenced the siege of
                        that place. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first the townsmen
                        withstood the assaults, but when they found themselves attacked by
                        siege-engines as well as by arms, they lost confidence in the protection of
                        their walls and retired in a body to their citadel. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Finally they sent envoys to place themselves and all
                        their property at the disposal of the Romans. A large amount of booty was
                        seized here. Many of their nobles were taken, amongst them the two sons and
                        the daughter of Thurrus. This man was the chief of these tribes and by far
                        the most powerful man in Spain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On hearing
                        of the disaster to his countrymen he sent to ask for a safe-conduct while he
                        visited Gracchus in his camp. When he arrived his first question was whether
                        he and his family would be allowed to live. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> On the praetor replying that his life would be safe, he asked, further,
                        whether he would be allowed to fight on the side of the Romans. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Gracchus granted that request also, and then he
                        said: "I will follow you against my old allies." From that time he followed
                        the Romans, and on many occasions his gallant and faithful services were
                        helpful to the Roman cause. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On this, Ergavica, a powerful and
                        influential city, alarmed at the disasters which had befallen her
                        neighbours, opened her gates to the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Some authorities assert that these surrenders were not made in good
                        faith, and wherever Gracchus withdrew his legions, hostilities were at once
                        renewed; also that he fought a great battle with the Celtiberi at Mt.
                        Chaunus, lasting from dawn till mid-day, and many fell on both sides.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> You would not suppose from this that
                        the Romans achieved any great success beyond the fact that they challenged
                        the enemy who kept within his lines, and also spent the whole day in
                        collecting the spoils. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They assert,
                        further, that on the third day a still bigger battle was fought, and now at
                        last the Celtiberi suffered a decisive defeat; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> their camp was taken and plundered, 22,000 of the enemy
                        were killed, more than 300 taken prisoners, and about the same number of
                        horses and 72 military standards were taken. This finished the war and a
                        real, not an insincere peace, as before, was made. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> According to these authors, L. Postumius fought with
                        great success against the Vaccaei in Further Spain this summer, killing
                        35,000 of the enemy and getting possession of their camp. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> It would be nearer the truth to say that he arrived in
                        his province too late in the summer to undertake a campaign. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Aemilius Lepidus, Pontifex Maximus and
                        Censor, was himself chosen as leader of the House. Lepidus kept some on the
                        roll whom his colleague had left out. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        sums which had been granted to them for constructive works were employed as
                        follows. Lepidus constructed a breakwater at Terracina, an unpopular
                        proceeding because he had estates there and was charging to the public
                        account what should have been his private expenditure. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He contracted for the building of an auditorium and
                        stage at the temple of Apollo, and the polishing with chalk of the temple of
                        Jupiter on the Capitol and the columns round it. He also removed the statues
                        from the front of the columns which blocked the view and took away all the
                        shields and military standards which had been fastened to them. M. Fulvius
                        undertook more numerous and more useful works. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He constructed a wharf on the Tiber and piles for a
                        bridge on which some years later the censors P. Scipio Africanus and L.
                        Mummius erected arches. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He built a
                        court-house behind the new bankers' establishments, a fish-market surrounded
                        by shops, a market-square and colonnade outside the Porta Trigemina, and
                        other colonnades behind the docks, at the fane of Hercules, behind the
                        temple of Hope by the Tiber, and one at the temple of Apollo Medicus.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Besides the sums allotted to each they
                        had a certain amount to use in common, and this they devoted to the
                        construction of an aqueduct on arches. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> M.
                        Licinius Crassus threw difficulties in the way of this work, as he would not
                        allow it to be carried through his land. Various tolls were also initiated
                        by them, and they fixed rents for the use of the State lands. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Many chapels and public buildings had been taken
                        possession of by private individuals; the censors made it their care that
                        these should preserve their sacred character and be accessible to the
                        public. The method of voting was revised by them, and through all the
                        "regions" they classified the tribes according to their status, their
                        circumstances, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> and their sources of
                        income. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="52" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One of the censors, M. Aemilius, asked the
                        senate for a sum of money to be decreed for the Games on the occasion of the
                        dedication of Queen Juno and Diana, which he had vowed eight years
                        previously, during the Ligurian war. A sum of 20,000 ases was granted.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He dedicated the temples which both
                        stood in the Circus Flaminius, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> and
                        exhibited scenic Games for three days after the dedication of the temple of
                        Juno, and for two days after the dedication of the temple of Diana. He also
                        dedicated a temple to the Lares Permarini in the Campus Martius. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> This temple had been vowed by L. Aemilius
                        Regillus eleven years previously, during the naval action against the
                        commanders of King Antiochus. Above the folding-doors of the temple a tablet
                        was affixed with this inscription: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "When
                        Lucius the son of Marcus Aemilius went out to battle to put an end to a
                        great war and to subdue kings . . . The chief cause of obtaining peace . . .
                        under his auspicious command and fortunate leadership the fleet of
                        Antiochus, ever before invincible, was defeated, shattered and put to flight
                        between Ephesus, Samos and Chios, before the very eyes of Antiochus and of
                        his whole army, his cavalry and elephants. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        On that day forty-two ships of war were captured there, with all their
                        crews; and after that battle had been fought, King Antiochus and his realm .
                        . . Wherefore, because of this action he vowed a temple to the Lares
                        Permarini." <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A similar tablet is fixed
                        above the doors of the temple of Jupiter on the Capitol. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="53" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Two days after the censors had finished
                        revising the roll of the senate the consul Q. Fulvius set out for Liguria.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After traversing with his army
                        pathless mountains and ravines and forests, he fought a pitched battle with
                        the enemy, and not only defeated him but seized his camp the same day; 3200
                        of the enemy and the whole of that district made their surrender. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The consul brought them down into the plains and
                        posted detachments to hold the mountains. Despatches were quickly sent to
                        Rome and a three days' thanksgiving was decreed, the praetors sacrificing
                        full-grown victims. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nothing worth
                        recording was done in Liguria by the other consul L. Manlius. Three thousand
                        men belonging to the transalpine Gauls crossed the Alps into Italy without
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> doing any injury, and asked the
                        consuls and senate for a grant of land, that they might live quietly under
                        the sovereignty of Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate
                        ordered them to quit Italy, and Q. Fulvius was instructed to seek out and
                        take action against the prime instigators of this movement across the Alps.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="54" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the course of this year Philip king of
                        the Macedonians died, worn out with old age and grief at the death of his
                        son. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He passed the winter at Demetrias,
                        full of poignant regret at the death of his son and of remorse for his own
                        cruelty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His feelings were still further
                        embittered by the conduct of his other son, who, in his own opinion and in
                        that of others, was undoubtedly king, for all eyes were turned towards him,
                        and also by the desertion of his friends in his old age, some waiting for
                        his death, others not even waiting for it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        This was a greater source of anxiety to him as it was to Antigonus the son
                        of Echecrates, who bore the name of his paternal uncle, Antigonus. The uncle
                        had been Philip's guardian, a man of kingly dignity, distinguished, too, for
                        his conduct in the famous battle against Cleomenes the Lacedaemonian.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This man's nephew, Antigonus, out of
                        all those whom Philip had honoured with his friendship, alone remained
                        uncorrupted, and this loyalty made Perseus, who had never been friendly to
                        him, his bitterest enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He foresaw the
                        danger in which he would be involved by the heritage of the crown descending
                        to Perseus, and as <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> soon as he saw the
                        king's feelings changing, and heard him deploring the loss of his son, he
                        used sometimes to be a silent listener; at others he would lead the king to
                        speak of the incident as unpremeditated, and in this way often showed active
                        sympathy with his grief. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And as truth
                        usually gives signs of its presence, so it was here, and he followed up the
                        traces to the utmost of his power so that everything might be the sooner
                        brought to light. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Suspicion attached
                        mainly to Apelles and Philocles as the authors of the crime; they were the
                        men who had gone in the character of envoys to Rome, and had brought back
                        the letter forged in the name of Flamininus which had proved so fatal to
                        Demetrius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="55" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was commonly said in the palace that
                        the letter was a forgery concocted by one of the secretaries and sealed with
                        a counterfeit seal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whilst, however, there
                        was as yet no clear evidence, only suspicion, Xychus happened to meet
                        Antigonus, who had him promptly arrested and conveyed to the palace.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Leaving him there under guard he went
                        in to Philip and said to the king: "I think I have understood from my many
                        conversations with you that you would value very highly the opportunity of
                        learning the whole truth about your sons, which of them was the victim of
                        the cunning and treachery of the other. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The one man in the whole world who can unravel the knot, namely Xychus, is
                        in your hands. I met him by chance and had him brought to the palace; order
                        him to be summoned." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When brought in he at
                        first denied everything, but with such hesitancy that a moderate appeal to
                        his fears would obviously make him a ready informer. The sight of the
                        executioner with his scourge was too much for him, and he explained in full
                        detail the villainy of the two envoys and the way he had acted as their
                        tool. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Men were at once despatched to
                        arrest them. Philocles was seized on the spot; Apelles, who had been in
                        pursuit of a certain Chaereas, on learning that Xychus was turned informer,
                        sailed for Italy. The fate of Philocles is not certain. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> According to some writers he, at first, stoutly denied;
                        afterwards, confronted with Xychus, he no longer held out. Others say that
                        even when put to the torture he still maintained his innocence. Philip's
                        grief and distress were awakened afresh. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        He considered that the unhappiness caused by his children was made more
                        painful by the survival of the one than by the death of the other. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="56" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On being informed that everything had been
                        disclosed, Perseus, whilst feeling himself strong enough to avoid the
                        necessity of flight, took care, nevertheless, to keep well out of the way,
                        and prepared to protect himself from the flames of his father's wrath, as
                        long as he was alive. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Philip, hopeless of
                        being able to inflict punishment on the person of his son, made it his aim
                        to prevent him, whilst escaping punishment, from enjoying the rewards of his
                        wickedness as well. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly he
                        summoned Antigonus, to whom he was under such obligations for the detection
                        of the fratricide, and who he thought, owing to the glory recently won by
                        his uncle, Antigonus, might be one whom the Macedonians would not be ashamed
                        of or disappointed in as their king. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        "Antigonus," he began, "now that my condition is such that the childlessness
                        which other fathers regard as a curse I am compelled to regard as a thing to
                        be wished for, I have resolved to leave to you the kingdom which your
                        gallant uncle not only defended but augmented by his fidelity and
                        watchfulness. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You are the only one I have
                        whom I judge worthy of the crown; if I had no one I would rather have my
                        kingdom perish and disappear than that Perseus should have it as the prize
                        of treachery and murder. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I should feel
                        that Demetrius had been recalled from the tomb, if I could leave you to take
                        his place, you who have shed tears over the death of an innocent victim and
                        wept at my terrible mistake." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From this time he was continually
                        advancing him from one honour to another. Whilst Perseus was away in Thrace,
                        Philip made a progress through the cities of Macedonia, and recommended
                        Antigonus to their leading men, and had he lived longer he would undoubtedly
                        have left him in actual possession of the crown. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Leaving Demetrias, he stopped for a considerable time
                        at Thessalonica. From there he travelled to Amphipolis, and here he became
                        seriously ill. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But he was more sick in
                        mind than in body. He was a prey to gloomy fears and sleeplessness; again
                        and again the form and shade of his innocent murdered son threw him into
                        violent agitation. He died whilst invoking terrible curses on the other one.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Antigonus could, however, have been
                        warned, had he been at hand, or had the king's death been openly announced
                        in the palace. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Calligenes, the head
                        physician, did not anticipate it so soon. When the case became hopeless he
                        sent the news as had been mutually agreed, to Perseus by a relay of
                        messengers and concealed the fact from all outside the palace pending his
                        arrival. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="57" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus took them all by surprise; they
                        were unaware of what had happened and were not in the least expecting him.
                        He seized the throne which he had gained by crime. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The death of Philip occurred very opportunely as
                        regarded the postponement of hostilities and the concentration of the
                        resources for war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A few days later the
                        tribe of the Bastarnae, after repeated invitations, left their homes and
                        crossed the Hister with a large body of infantry and cavalry. Antigonus and
                        Cotto-a Bastarnian noble-went in advance to inform the king. Antigonus had
                        previously been sent with this same Cotto to induce the Bastarnae to move.
                        Not far from Amphipolis they heard a report, and soon afterwards were met by
                        messengers who announced the king's death. This completely upset their
                        plans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It had been settled that Philip
                        would afford the Bastarnae a safe passage through Thrace and supply them
                        with provisions. To ensure this he had bribed the chiefs in the districts to
                        be traversed and had pledged his word that the Bastarnae would pass through
                        peacefully. It was intended to exterminate the Dardani and to make a home
                        for the Bastarnae in their territory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        There was to be a double advantage in this; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> the Dardani, who had always been bitter enemies to Macedonia, and ready
                        to fall on her in times of misfortune, would be put out of the way, and the
                        Bastarnae could leave their wives and children in Dardania and be sent on to
                        devastate Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The way to the Hadriatic
                        and to Italy lay through the Scordisci; that was the only practicable route
                        for an army, and the Scordisci were expected to grant a passage to the
                        Bastarnae without any difficulty, for neither in speech nor habits were they
                        dissimilar, and it was hoped that they would unite forces with them when
                        they saw that they were going to secure the plunder of a very wealthy
                        nation. Thus Philip's plans were adapted to either alternative. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> If the Bastarnae were defeated by the Romans, the
                        extermination of the Dardani, the plunder of what remained of the Bastarnae,
                        and the unchallenged possession of Dardania would be some consolation to
                        him; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> if on the other hand they met with
                        success and the Romans were recalled to a war with the Bastarnae, he would
                        win back what he had lost in Greece. Such were Philip's schemes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="58" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the outset the Bastarnae marched in
                        peaceable and orderly fashion. But after Cotto and Antigonus had left them
                        and the news of Philip's death arrived a few days later, the Thracians began
                        to make difficulties about providing a market. Unable to buy what they
                        needed, the Bastarnae could not be kept in their ranks nor prevented from
                        straggling. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This led to acts of violence
                        on both sides, and as these became daily more aggressive, war broke out. In
                        the end the Thracians, finding themselves unable to withstand the numbers
                        and the fierceness of their assailants, left their villages in the plains
                        and retired to a mountain of immense height called Donuca. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> While the Bastarnae were preparing to follow them, a
                        storm similar to that which is said to have destroyed the Gauls while
                        plundering Delphi burst upon them as they were nearing the summit.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were overwhelmed by a deluge of
                        rain, followed by a heavy hailstorm accompanied with the crashing of thunder
                        peals and blinding flashes of lightning. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The lightning played everywhere round them; it seemed as though it were
                        aimed at the men; not only the common soldiers but their chiefs were struck
                        down. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As they floundered and fell in blind
                        headlong flight amongst the beetling cliffs, they were closely pursued by
                        the Thracians; but they said to themselves that the gods were causing their
                        flight and the heavens were falling on them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Scattered by the storm like shipwrecked sailors, they at last reached
                        their camp, most having lost their arms, and then began to deliberate as to
                        what they were to do. Opinions were divided; some were for returning home,
                        others wanted to invade Dardania. About 30,000 men, led by Clondicus,
                        succeeded in reaching Dardania; the rest of the host retraced their steps
                        and made their way into the inland district of Apollonia. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> After gaining possession of the crown, Perseus ordered
                        Antigonus to be put to death. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Whilst he
                        was strengthening himself on the throne, he sent an embassy to Rome to renew
                        the friendship which had existed in his father's time and to request the
                        senate to recognise him as king. These were the events of the year in
                        Macedonia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="59" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Q. Fulvius celebrated his triumph over the
                        Ligurians, but it was generally believed that this triumph was granted to
                        him more on personal grounds than because of the importance of his
                        victories. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had a large amount of enemy
                        arms carried in the procession, but no considerable sum of money. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> However, he distributed 300 ases to each of the
                        legionaries, twice as much to each centurion, and three times as much to
                        each of the cavalry. The most striking thing about this triumph was that he
                        happened to celebrate it on the same day as his triumph the preceding year
                        after his praetorship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Immediately after
                        his triumph he fixed the day for the elections. The new consuls were M.
                        Junius Brutus and A. Manlius Vulso. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Three
                        of the praetors had been elected when a storm interrupted the proceedings.
                        The next day the remaining three were elected, namely, M. Titinius Curvus,
                        Ti. Claudius Nero, and T. Fonteius Capitol The Roman Games were exhibited
                        afresh by the curule aediles Cnaeus Servilius Caepio and Appius Claudius
                        Cento in consequence of some portents which had occurred. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> There was an earthquake. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst a lectisternium was going on in the public
                        shrines the deities on their couches turned away their heads from the
                        offerings set before them, and the coverlet with the covers of the dishes
                        set before Jupiter fell from the table. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        The olives were nibbled by mice before they were placed before the gods, and
                        this was regarded as a portent. Nothing beyond the repetition of the Games
                        was done in the way of expiating these portents. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
