<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 23-25 - 23</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Moore" role="editor"> Frank Gardener Moore, Professor Emeritus in
                    Columbia University </editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XXIII-XXV With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1940: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.3"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="book">
                <head>Book XXIII</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> AFTER the battle of Cannae and the capture and
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note>
                    plunder of the camps, Hannibal had moved at once out of Apulia into Samnium,
                    being invited into the land of the Hirpini by Statius Trebius, who promised that
                    he would turn over Compsa to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Trebius was
                    a Compsan of high rank among his people, but opposed by the party of the Mopsii,
                    a family made powerful by the favour of the Romans. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> After the news of the battle of Cannae, and when the coming
                    of Hannibal had been made known by utterances of Trebius, since the Mopsii had
                    left the city, it was handed over to the Carthaginians without resistance and a
                    garrison admitted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There Hannibal left all his
                    booty and the baggage, divided his army, and ordered Mago either to take over
                    such cities of that region as were deserting the Romans or to compel them to
                    desert in case they refused. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He himself made
                    his way through the Campanian region to the Lower Sea, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the Tuscan Sea; cf. xxxviii. 1. </note>
                    intending to attack Neapolis, that he might have a seaport. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> On entering the territory of the <pb n="p.5"/> Neapolitans,
                    he stationed some of the Numidians in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 216</note> ambush, wherever he conveniently could (and
                    most of the roads are deep-cut and the turnings concealed). Other Numidians he
                    ordered to ride up to the gates, making a display of the booty they were driving
                    along before them from the farms. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Against
                    these men, because they seemed to be few in number and disorganized, a troop of
                    cavalry made a sally, but being drawn into the ambush by the enemy's purposely
                    retreating, it was overpowered. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And not a: man
                    would have escaped if the proximity of the sea and the sight of vessels, chiefly
                    of fishermen, not far from the shore had not given those who could swim a way of
                    escape. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> However a number of young nobles were
                    captured or slain in that battle, among them, Hegeas, a cavalry commander, who
                    fell as he rashly pursued the retreating. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    From besieging the city the Carthaginian was deterred by the sight of walls such
                    as by no means invited an attacker. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal then directed his march to Capua,
                    which was pampered by its long-continued prosperity and the favour of fortune,
                    but, along with the general corruption, especially from the licence of the
                    common people, who enjoyed an unlimited freedom. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> As for the senate, Pacuvius Calavius, a noble who was at the same time of the
                    people's party, but had gained his influence by base arts, had made it
                    subservient both to himself and to the common people. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He, being in their highest office, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> He was called <hi rend="italics">medix tuticus;</hi>
                        cf. xxxv. 13. For the defeat of Faminius at the Trasumennus cf. XXII. iv ff.
                    </note> as is happened, in the year of the defeat at Lake Trasumennus, thought
                    that the commons, long hostile to the senate, would use the opportunity of a
                    revolution and dare to commit a great crime, namely, if Hannibal should come
                    into the region with his victorious army, they would slay <pb n="p.7"/> the
                    senators and hand over Capua to the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 216</note> Carthaginians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> A bad man, but not utterly abandoned, he preferred to dominate a state still
                    intact rather than one that had been wrecked, yet believed that none was intact
                    if deprived of its deliberative body. He accordingly entered upon a scheme to
                    save the senate and at the same time to make it submissive to himself and to the
                    commons. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Summoning the senate he began by
                    saying that, unless it should prove necessary, a plan to revolt from the Romans
                    would by no means have his approval, since he had <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> children by a daughter of Appius Claudius and had given a
                    daughter in marriage to Marcus Livius at Rome. But, he went on to say, something
                    much more serious and more to be dreaded was impending; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> for the common people were not aiming to rid the state of
                    the senate by a revolt, but by the massacre of the senate wished to hand over
                    the republic, left helpless, to Hannibal and the Carthaginians. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> From that danger he could free them if they should leave it
                    to him, and, forgetting civil conflicts, trust him. When, overcome by fear, they
                    unanimously left matters to him, <quote>I will shut you up,</quote> he said,
                        <quote> in the Senate House and, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> just as
                        if I were myself a sharer in the crime intended, by approving plans which it
                        would be vain for me to oppose, I will find a way to save you. For this
                        accept a pledge, as you yourselves desire. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having given the pledge he went out, ordered
                    the Senate House to be closed and left a guard before the entrance, that no one
                    might be able to enter the Senate House or leave it without his order. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then calling the people to an assembly he
                    said: <quote> You have often desired, Campanians, to have the power to exact
                        punishment from a base and <pb n="p.9"/> odious senate. That power you have,
                        not by <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            216</note> riotously storming, with great danger to yourselves, the
                        houses of individuals who defend them with garrisons of clients and slaves,
                        but you have the power secure and unrestricted. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> As they are shut up there, every man of them, in the
                        Senate House, seize them, left alone, unarmed! <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> And do nothing in haste or at haphazard. I will give
                        you the right to decide their fate in each separate case, so that each shall
                        pay the penalty he has deserved. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But above
                        all things you should vent your wrath with due regard to the conviction that
                        your safety and advantage are worth more than wrath. For it is these
                        senators that you hate, I think; it is not your wish to have no senate at
                        all. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In fact you must either have a king
                        —save the mark! —or else a senate, the only deliberative body in a free
                        state. And so you have two things to do at the same time —to do away with
                        the old senate, and to choose a new one. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I
                        will order the senators to be called one by one and will consult you as to
                        their fate. Whatever is your opinion in each case shall be done, but before
                        punishment is inflicted on the guilty one you will choose in his place a
                        brave and active man as a new senator. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then sat down, and after the names had been
                    placed in the urn, he ordered the first name drawn by lot to be called and the
                    man himself to be led out of the Senate House. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    On hearing the name every man shouted his loudest, that he was a bad man and
                    base and deserved punishment. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Upon that
                    Pacuvius said: <quote> I see what your verdict is in this man's case; therefore
                        in place of a bad man and base nominate a good and just senator. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At first there was silence from their
                    inability to suggest a better man. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then when
                    someone, <pb n="p.11"/> overcoming his timidity, named a man, at once there was
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> a
                    much louder outcry, some saying they did not know him, others taunting him, now
                    with shameful conduct, now with low rank and sordid poverty and the disreputable
                    nature of his trade or business. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> All the more
                    was this done in the case of the second and third senator called. So it was
                    clear that people were dissatisfied with the man himself, but had no one to put
                    in his place. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For nothing was gained by once
                    more naming the same men, who had been named only to be reviled. And the rest
                    were much lower in rank and less known than those who first came to mind.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Accordingly men slipped away, saying that
                    the most familiar evil is the most endurable, and bidding Pacuvius release the
                    senate from confinement. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In this way Pacuvius, having made the senate
                    much more subservient to himself than to the common people by saving their
                    lives, ruled without arms, as all now gave way to him. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Thereafter the senators, forgetting their rank and freedom,
                    flattered the common people, greeted them, invited them graciously, entertained
                    them at well appointed feasts; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> invariably
                    undertook cases, appeared as counsel, or as jurors gave a verdict, only for that
                    side which was the more popular and better suited to win favour with the
                    populace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Moreover, nothing was done in the
                    senate otherwise than if a meeting of the common people was being held there.
                    The state had always been inclined to luxury, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Capua, prospering by its varied industries established
                        by the Etruscans, was already noted for its wealth and a luxury greater than
                        that of Croton and Sybaris; Polybius VII. i. 1 and III. xci. 6; Cicero <hi
                            rend="italics">Leg. Agr.</hi> II. 95; cf. Strabo V. iv. 3. </note> not
                    only from defects in character, but also from the abundant opportunity for
                    indulgences and the beguilement of all the charms of sea and land. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> But at that time, thanks to the servility of the
                    leading men and the <pb n="p.13"/> licence of the common people, they were so
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note>
                    unrestrained that no limit was set to passion or to expense. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> To their contempt for laws, the magistrates, the senate,
                    there was now added, after the defeat at Cannae, their disparagement of the
                    Roman power also, for which there used to be some respect. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> All that held them back from at once revolting was that the
                    long-established right of intermarriage had united many distinguished and
                    powerful families with the Romans, and that, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    although a considerable number were serving on the Roman side, the strongest
                    bond was the three hundred horsemen, noblest of the Campanians, who had been
                    chosen to garrison Sicilian cities by the Romans and sent thither. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As belonging to the most prominent
                        families and dispersed among the cities of Sicily, they were in effect
                        hostages. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their parents and relatives with difficulty
                    carried their point, that representatives should be sent to the Roman consul. </p>
                <p> These men found the consul not yet departed for Canusium, but with a few
                    half-armed men at Venusia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Immediately after the battle of Cannae; XXII. xlix. 14; liv. 1 and 6.
                    </note> exciting the utmost pity in good allies, but contempt in the haughty and
                    faithless, such as were the Campanians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And
                    the consul increased the contempt for his situation and for himself by
                    needlessly uncovering and laying bare the disaster. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> For when the delegation had reported that the senate and
                    the Campanian people were distressed that any reverse had befallen the Romans,
                    and were promising everything that might be needed for the war, he said:
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> You, Campanians, have observed the customary manner of speaking to
                        allies, in bidding me requisition whatever is needed for the war, rather
                        than spoken conformably to the present state of our fortunes. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/>
                        <pb n="p.15"/> For what has been left to us at Cannae, so that, as if <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> we had
                        something, we may wish what is lacking to be made up by the allies? Are we
                        to requisition infantry from you, as though we had cavalry? Are we to say
                        that money is lacking, as if that alone were lacking? Nothing has fortune
                        left us, even to supplement. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Legions,
                        cavalry, arms, standards, horses and men, money and supplies have vanished
                        either in the battle or in the loss of two camps the next day. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> And so you, Campanians, have not to help us in
                        war, but almost to undertake the war in our stead. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Recall how, when your ancestors were once confined in
                        alarm within their walls, dreading not only the Samnite enemy but also the
                        Sidicinian, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On the contrary, it
                            was by aiding the Sidicinians against the Samnites that the Campanians
                            became involved in the 1st Samnite War, <date when="-0343">343
                                B.C.</date> ; VII. xxix. </note> we took them under our protection
                        and defended them at Saticula. Also how with varying fortunes we endured for
                        almost a hundred years <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Really
                            seventy-one years. More rhetorical exaggeration in <hi rend="italics"
                                >propter vos,</hi> and especially in the following sentence. </note>
                        the war begun with the Samnites on your account. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Add to this that upon your submission we gave you a
                        fair treaty and your own laws, and finally —and before the disaster at
                        Cannae this was certainly the greatest privilege —our citizenship to a large
                        number of you and shared it with you. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A
                        share, then, Campanians, you should believe you have in this disaster which
                        has befallen us, and should think that you must defend the country in which
                        you have a share. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Not with the Samnite or
                        Etruscan is the struggle to have the power which has been wrested from us
                        nevertheless remain in Italy. A Carthaginian enemy, not even of African
                        origin, is dragging after him from the farthest limits of the world, from
                        the strait of Ocean and the Pillars of Hercules, soldiers who <pb n="p.17"/>
                        are unacquainted with any civilized laws and <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> organization and, one
                        may almost add, language too. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So
                            Polybius had said of Hannibal's polyglot troops, <foreign
                                xml:lang="greek">,</foreign> XI. xix. 4. </note>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Ruthless and barbarous by nature and
                        custom, these men have been further barbarized by the general himself, in
                        making bridges and embankments of piled up human bodies, and by teaching
                        them —horrible even to relate —to feed upon the bodies of men. <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy makes Varro repeat exaggerated
                            statements about Hannibal; cf. Appian <hi rend="italics">Hann.</hi> 28. </note>
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> To see and have as our masters men who
                        fatten upon these unspeakable feasts, men whom it is a crime even to touch,
                        and to get our law from Africa and Carthage, and to allow Italy to be a
                        province of the Numidians and the Mauri —who, if merely born in Italy, would
                        not find that abominable? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> It will be a
                        glorious thing, Campanians, if the Roman power, brought low by disaster,
                        shall have been maintained and restored by your loyalty and your resources.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Thirty thousand foot-soldiers and
                        four thousand horsemen can be enrolled from Campania, I believe. Moreover
                        you have sufficient money and grain. If you have a loyalty to match your
                        prosperity Hannibal will not be aware of his victory, nor the Romans of
                        their defeat. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this speech of the consul the legates
                    were dismissed, and on their way home Vibius Virrius, one of them, said the time
                    had come when the Campanians could not only recover the territory formerly taken
                    from them unjustly by the Romans, but could also gain authority over Italy. For
                    they would make a treaty with Hannibal on their own terms. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And there would be no doubt that, when Hannibal, upon the
                    completion of the war, retired as victor to Africa and removed his army,
                    authority over Italy would be left to the Campanians. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Having agreed unanimously with these words of Virrius, they
                        <pb n="p.19"/> made such a report of their embassy that the Roman <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> name
                    seemed to all to have been blotted out. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Not so to Calavius' son; viii. 3 and 11.</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At once the populace and most of the senate
                    were aiming to revolt. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But action was
                    postponed for a few days by the weighty advice of the older men. Finally the
                    view of the majority prevailed, that the same legates who had gone to the Roman
                    consul should be sent to Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before they
                    went to him and' before the plan to revolt was settled upon, I find in some of
                    the annals that legates were sent to Rome by the Campanians with the demand
                    that, if they wished' them to aid the Roman state, one of the consuls should be
                    a Campanian; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cicero mentions this
                        demand of Capua; <hi rend="italics">Leg. Agr.</hi> II. 95. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that resentment was aroused and the legates
                    were ordered to be removed from the Senate House, and that a lictor was sent to
                    lead them out of the city and bid them lodge that night outside of Roman
                    territory. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Because there was once a
                    suspiciously similar demand made by the Latins, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> That one of the consuls should be from Latium, <date
                            when="-0340">340 B.C.</date> , VIII. v. 5 and 7 (the threat of Manlius
                        mentioned below, xxii. 7). </note> and Coelius and other historians had not
                    without reason omitted the matter, I have been afraid to set this down as
                    established. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The legates came to Hannibal and made an
                    alliance with him on these terms: that no general or magistrate of the
                    Carthaginians should have any authority over a Campanian citizen, and that no
                    Campanian citizen should be a soldier or perform any service against his will;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that Capua should have its own laws, its
                    own magistrates; that the Carthaginian should give the Campanians three hundred
                    of the Roman captives of their own choosing, with whom there should be an
                    exchange of the Campanian <pb n="p.21"/> horsemen who were serving in Sicily.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Such were the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> terms. In addition to what
                    was agreed upon the Campanians perpetrated these misdeeds: the populace suddenly
                    seized prefects of the allies and other Roman citizens, some of them employed in
                    a military duty, some engaged in private business, and with the pretence of
                    guarding them ordered them all to be confined in the baths, that there they
                    might die a terrible death, being suffocated by the extreme heat. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Such conduct and the sending of an embassy to
                    the Carthaginian had been opposed to the utmost by Decius Magius, a man who
                    lacked nothing for the attainment of the highest authority except sanity on the
                    part of the citizens. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But when he heard that a
                    garrison was being sent by Hannibal, recalling the haughty rule of Pyrrhus and
                    the wretched servitude of the Tarentines as warning examples, he at first openly
                    protested that the garrison should not be admitted; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> then, after it had been admitted, either that it should be
                    driven out, or, if they wished to atone for their evil action in having revolted
                    from their oldest allies and men of the same blood by a brave and notable act,
                    that they should slay the Punic garrison and return to their Roman allegiance.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When this was reported to Hannibal (for it
                    was not done in secret), he first sent men to summon Magius to him at the camp.
                    Then when the latter replied with spirit that he would not go, for Hannibal had
                    no authority over a Campanian citizen, the Carthaginian was enraged and ordered
                    the man to be seized and brought before him in chains. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Later, fearing that in the use of force some commotion, and
                    in view of the excitement some unpremeditated conflict, might occur, he first
                    sent word to Marius Blossius, the <pb n="p.23"/> Campanian magistrate, that he
                    would be in Capua the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 216</note> next day, and then he set out from the camp with a small
                    escort. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marius, calling an assembly, ordered
                    them to go out to meet Hannibal <hi rend="italics">en masse</hi> with wives and
                    children. This was done by all not only obediently but also eagerly, owing to
                    the enthusiasm of the crowd as well and the desire to go and see a general
                    already famous for so many victories. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Decius
                    Magius neither went out to meet him nor remained in seclusion, by doing which he
                    might show some fear due to conscience. He strolled idly in the market-place
                    with his son and a few clients, although the whole city was astir to welcome and
                    to see the Carthaginian. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hannibal entered the
                    city and at once demanded a session of the senate, and then when the leading
                    Campanians begged him not to do any serious business that day, and that he
                    should <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> himself cheerfully and willingly
                    honour the day gladdened by his coming, though he was naturally hot-tempered,
                    still in order not to deny them anything at the start, he spent a large part of
                    the day in seeing the city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He lodged at the house of the Ninnii Celeres,
                    the brothers Sthenius and Pacuvius, men distinguished for their rank and wealth.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To that house Pacuvius Calavius, of whom
                    mention has been made above, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Chapters
                        ii-iv.</note> leader of the party which had drawn the state to the side of
                    the Carthaginians, came bringing his young son. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> He had got him away from the company of Decius Magius, with whom the son in
                    the most confident spirit had stood up for the Roman alliance against a treaty
                    with Carthage. And neither the decision of the state for the other side nor his
                    father's high position had dislodged him from his opinion. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Such was the young man to whom his father, rather <pb
                        n="p.25"/> by pleading than by excusing, reconciled Hannibal, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> and he,
                    prevailed upon by the father's prayers and tears, even ordered that the son
                    should be invited <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> with the father to a
                    dinner at which he was to have the company of no Campanian except his hosts and
                    Vibellius Taurea, a distinguished soldier. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They began feasting by daylight, and the banquet was not according to
                    Carthaginian custom or military regimen, but provided with all that tempts
                    indulgence, as it was to be expected in a city, and a house as well, of wealth
                    and luxury. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Calavius the son was the only one
                    who could not be prevailed upon to drink either by the invitation of the owners
                    or even, now and then, of Hannibal. He himself pleaded ill health as an excuse,
                    while his father alleged distress of mind also, at which one could not wonder.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About sunset the son followed the elder
                    Calavius coming out from the feast, and when they had reached a secluded spot
                    —it <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> was a garden in the rear of the house —he
                    said: <quote> I propose a plan, father, by which we may not only gain pardon
                        from the Romans for our offence in having revolted to Hannibal, but as
                        Campanians may be in a position of much greater respect and favour than we
                        should ever have been otherwise. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the astonished father asked what that
                    plan was, the son throwing his toga off his shoulder bared his side girt with a
                    sword. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Presently,</quote> he said, <quote> I will ratify a treaty with the
                        Romans by the blood of Hannibal. I wished you to know that in advance, in
                        case you should prefer not to be there when the deed is being done. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the old man saw and heard that, he was
                    beside himself with fear, as if he were already present at the execution of the
                    plan of which he was <pb n="p.27"/> being told, and said: <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> I pray and implore you, my <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 216</note> son, by all the rights which link children
                        to their parents, not to do and suffer all that is unutterable before the
                        eyes of your father. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is but a few hours
                        since, with an oath by all the gods that exist and joining our right hands
                        to his, we pledged our honour. Was it with the intention, as soon as we left
                        the conference, to arm against him the hands hallowed by our plighted faith?
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From the hospitable board, to which
                        you were invited by Hannibal with but two other Campanians, do you rise with
                        the intention of staining that very board with the blood of a guest?
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Was I able as a father to reconcile
                        Hannibal with my son, and can not reconcile my son with Hannibal? But
                        assuming that there is nothing hallowed, no honour, no scruple, no filial
                        devotion, dare to do unspeakable things, if they do not bring destruction to
                        us as well as guilt. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Single-handed will
                        you attack Hannibal? What of that crowd, so many free men and slaves? What
                        of all men's eyes fixed upon one man? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What
                        of so many sword-hands? Will they be paralysed in the moment of that mad
                        deed? Will you withstand Hannibal's own countenance, which armed forces have
                        been unable to withstand, which the Roman people dreads? Supposing that help
                        from others is lacking, will you bring yourself to strike <hi rend="italics"
                            >me,</hi> when I interpose my body in place of Hannibal's? And yet it is
                        through my breast that you will have to attack him and run him through.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But allow yourself to be dissuaded
                        here, rather than overpowered there. Let my prayers prove effectual with
                        you, as they have proved this day for you. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Seeing the young man in tears he threw his
                    arms about his waist, and repeatedly kissing him he did <pb n="p.29"/> not
                    desist from entreaties until he had prevailed upon <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> him to put down his sword
                    and give his pledge that he would do no such crime. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Then the young man said: <quote> As for me, I will pay my
                        father the debt of devotion which I owe to my country. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> For you I am sorry, for you will have to meet the
                        charge of thrice betraying your country, once when you took part in the
                        revolt from the Romans, a second time when you advised peace with Hannibal,
                        a third time today when you are an obstacle and a hindrance to restoring
                        Capua to the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Do you, my country,
                        take back the sword with which I had armed myself in your defence and
                        entered this stronghold of the enemy; for my father wrests it from me. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Having thus spoken, he threw the sword over
                    the garden wall into a street, and, that his conduct might not be open to
                    suspicion, himself returned to the banquet. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following day a full session of the
                    senate was given to Hannibal. There his speech was at the outset very genial and
                    kindly, thanking the Campanians for having preferred his friendship to a Roman
                    alliance. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And among his other magnificent
                    assurances he promised them that Capua should soon be the capital of all Italy,
                    and that from it the Roman people along with the rest of the nations should
                    derive its law. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He said that <hi
                        rend="italics">one</hi> man had no part in friendship with Carthage and the
                    treaty made with himself, namely Magius Decius, a man who ought neither to be a
                    Campanian nor to be so called; he demanded that the man be surrendered to him,
                    and that in his own presence his case be brought up and a decree of the senate
                    framed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All voted for that proposal, although
                    it seemed to many of them that the man did not deserve that misfortune; also <pb
                        n="p.31"/> that the right of liberty was being infringed by a first <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> act that
                    was not insignificant. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Leaving the Senate
                    House Hannibal took his seat on the tribune of the magistrates and ordered the
                    arrest of Decius Magius, and that he be placed at his feet and make his defence.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While with undaunted spirit Magius was
                    saying that by the terms of the treaty he could not be compelled to do that,
                    chains were put upon him and he was ordered to be led to the camp with a lictor
                    following. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So long as they led him with bare
                    head, he kept haranguing as he went, shouting to the crowd all about him:
                        <quote> You have the freedom you wanted, Campanians. Through the middle of
                        the market-place, in broad daylight, before your eyes, I, who am second to
                        no one of the Campanians, am being hurried away in chains to my death.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> What deed of greater violence could be
                        done if Capua had been taken? Go to meet Hannibal, decorate your city and
                        make the day of his coming a holiday, —that you may witness this triumph
                        over your fellow-citizen. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As he was thus shouting and the populace
                    seemed to be aroused, his head was covered and they were ordered to drag him
                    more swiftly outside the gate. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus he was
                    led into the camp, at once put on shipboard and consigned to Carthage, for fear,
                    if there should be some outbreak at Capua in consequence of the shameful act,
                    the senate also might regret having surrendered a leading man, and, when an
                    embassy was sent to demand his return, Hannibal either must offend his new
                    allies by refusing their first request, or by granting it be obliged to keep at
                    Capua a fomenter of insurrection and riots. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A
                    storm carried the ship to Cyrenae, which was then subject to kings. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> of Egypt. Ptolemy IV Philopator was then
                        reigning; XXIV. xxvi. 1. </note> On fleeing for refuge to the statue of <pb
                        n="p.33"/> King Ptolemy there, Magius was carried under guard <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> to Ptolemy
                    at Alexandria. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And having informed him that
                    he had been bound by Hannibal contrary to his treaty rights, he was freed from
                    his chains and allowed to return to Rome or to Capua, as he might prefer.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Magius said that Capua was unsafe for
                    him, and on the other hand, at a time when there was a war between the Romans
                    and the Campanians, Rome would be the abode of a deserter rather than of a
                    guest; that he had no wish to live elsewhere than in the land of a king in whom
                    he found the giver and defender of his freedom. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were going on, Quintus
                    Fabius Pictor <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He had been sent to
                        Delphi after the battle of Cannae; XXII. lvii. 5. His history, written in
                        Greek, was one of Livy's sources. </note> returned to Rome from his embassy
                    to Delphi and read from a manuscript the response of the oracle. In it were
                    indicated the gods and goddesses to whom offerings should be made, and in what
                    manner. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It continued: <quote> If you do thus,
                        Romans, your situation will be better and easier, and your state will go on
                        more in accordance with your desire, and the Roman people will have the
                        victory in the war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When you have
                        successfully administered and preserved your state, from the gains made you
                        shall send a gift to Pythian Apollo and do honour to him out of the booty,
                        the profits and the spoils. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> You shall keep
                        yourselves from exulting. </quote> After reading these words translated from
                    the Greek verses, he went on to say that, on coming out of the oracle, he had at
                    once made offerings to all those divinities with incense and wine; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> also that he had been bidden by the high-priest of
                    the temple, just as he had come to the oracle and also conducted the rite while
                    wearing a garland of laurel, so also to wear the garland when he boarded the
                    ship, and not to lay <pb n="p.35"/> it aside until he should reach Rome.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Further, that <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> he had carried out with
                    the utmost scrupulosity and care all the instructions given him, and had then
                    laid the wreath upon the altar of Apollo at Rome. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The senate decreed that at the first opportunity those
                    rites should be duly observed with prayers. </p>
                <p> While these things were happening at Rome and in Italy, Mago, the son of
                    Hamilcar, had come to Carthage to report the victory at Cannae. He had not been
                    sent by his brother directly from the battle, but had been detained for some
                    time in taking over the Bruttian states which were revolting. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy possibly mentioned others besides
                        the Bruttii. In i. 4 Mago is in Samnium for the same purpose. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accorded a hearing in the senate, he set forth
                    the achievements of his brother in Italy: that he had fought pitched battles
                    with six high commanders, of whom four were consuls, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Five consuls had been defeated by Hannibal: Scipio
                        (Ticinus), Sempronius (Trebia), Flaminius (Trasumennus) Paulus and Varro
                        (Cannae). As Scipio was the wounded consul of §9, it must be Sempronius who
                        is here omitted. Yet elsewhere much is made of the battle of the Trebia
                        (xviii. 7; xlv. 6). A copyist may have written <hi rend="italics"
                            >viimperatoribus</hi> instead of <hi rend="italics"
                            >viiimperatoribus.</hi> That done, the change of <hi rend="italics"
                            >v</hi> to <hi rend="italics">iv</hi> (same line and §9) would be an
                        effort to make the figures tally. </note> and two a dictator and a master of
                    the horse, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Fabius Maximus, the
                        Cunctator, and Minucius Rufus. Both are included among the defeated generals
                        in spite of what is said in regard to the dictator in §10. </note> in all
                    with six consular armies; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that he had slain
                    over 200,000 of the enemy and captured over 50,000; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Exaggerated figures in both cases.</note> that of the
                    four consuls he had slain two; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Flaminius and Aemilius Paulus.</note> of the other two one had fled
                    wounded, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Scipio at the Ticinus.</note>
                    the other with barely fifty men, after losing his entire army; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Terentius Varro.</note> that the master
                    of the horse, whose power is that of a consul, had been routed and put to
                    flight; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that the dictator was accounted an
                    extraordinary general because he never ventured into battle-line; <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> that the Bruttians and Apulians and some of the
                    Samnites and Lucanians had revolted to the Carthaginians; that <pb n="p.37"/>
                    Capua, which was the capital not only of Campania, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> but, since the blow
                    inflicted upon the Roman state by the battle of Cannae, of Italy also, had
                    surrendered to Hannibal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For these victories,
                    so many and so great, it was proper, he said, that gratitude be expressed and
                    felt toward the immortal gods. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then in evidence of such successes he ordered
                    the golden rings to be poured out at the entrance of the Senate House. And so
                    great was the heap of them that, when measured, they filled, as some historians
                    assert, three pecks and a half. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The prevailing
                    report, and nearer the truth, is that there was not more than one peck. Then,
                    that it might be proof of a greater calamity, he added in explanation that no
                    one but a knight, and even of the knights only those of the higher class, wore
                    that token. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The main point of his speech was
                    that the nearer Hannibal came to realizing his hope of ending the war, the more
                    necessary it was to help him by every means. For his campaigning was far from
                    home, in the midst of the enemy's country. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A
                    large amount of grain and money was being consumed, he said, and though so many
                    battles had destroyed the enemy's armies, still they had considerably diminished
                    the forces of the victor as well. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Therefore
                    they must send reinforcements, they must send money to pay them and grain to
                    soldiers who had deserved so well of the Carthaginian nation. </p>
                <p> After these words of Mago, while all were rejoicing, Himilco, a man of the Barca
                    party, thought it an opportunity to rebuke Hanno. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Tell me, Hanno,</quote> he-said, <quote> is it still to be regretted that
                        we undertook a war against the Romans? Order the surrender of Hannibal!
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the midst of such successes forbid
                        the <pb n="p.39"/> rendering of thanks to the immortal gods! Let us <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> listen
                        to a Roman senator in the Carthaginian 'Senate House. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thereupon Hanno said: <quote> I should have
                        remained silent to-day, members of the senate, for fear of saying something
                        which in the universal rejoicing would bring less joy to you. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> As it is, when a senator asks me whether it is
                        still a matter of regret that we entered upon a war against the Romans, if I
                        were to remain silent I should be thought either haughty or subservient, of
                        which the one marks a man forgetful of another's independence, the other a
                        man who forgets his own. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I should like to
                        say in reply to Himilco, </quote> he said, <quote> that I have not ceased to
                        regret the war, and will not cease to accuse your invincible commander until
                        I shall see the war ended on some sufferable terms; nor will anything else
                        than a new peace end my longing for the old peace. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> And so those facts which Mago has just boastfully
                        reported already give joy to Himilco and the other minions of Hannibal, and
                            <hi rend="italics">may</hi> give joy to me, since successes in war, if
                        we are willing to make use of our good fortune, will give us a more
                        favourable peace. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> I mean that if we let
                        slip this moment, when we may be considered as giving, rather than
                        receiving, a peace, I fear that this joy also of ours may run to excess and
                        come to nothing. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As in the last
                            years of the 1st Punic War.</note>
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But even now what is it worth? ' I have
                        slain armies of the enemy. Send me soldiers! ' What else would you ask for
                        if you had been defeated? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> ' I have
                        captured two camps of the enemy,' full of booty and supplies, of course. '
                        Give me grain and money! <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> ' What else
                        would you beg if you had been despoiled, if you had lost your camp? And, not
                        to have all the amazement to myself —for it is right and proper for me too,
                        having <pb n="p.41"/> answered Himilco, to turn questioner, —I <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> should like <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> either Himilco or Mago
                        to answer, in the first place, whether any state among the Latins has
                        revolted to us, although the battle of Cannae meant the utter destruction of
                        the Roman power, and it is known that all Italy is in revolt; in the second
                        place, whether any man out of the thirty-five tribes has deserted to
                        Hannibal. </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> On Mago's negative answer to both Hanno said:
                    "Accordingly there remains, to be sure, a very great number of the enemy. But
                    what spirit, what hope that multitude has, I should like to know.' <milestone
                        n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As Mago said he did not know, <quote>Nothing
                        is easier to know,</quote> said Hanno. <quote> Have the Romans sent any
                        emissaries to Hannibal suing for peace? Has it been reported to you that
                        even any mention of peace has been made at Rome? </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The answer to this also being negative,
                        <quote>Therefore,</quote> he said, <quote> we have the war intact, as truly
                        as we had on the day on which Hannibal crossed into Italy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> How often victory shifted in the previous Punic War
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <quote>Roman War</quote> would seem to us better suited to a speaker
                            addressing Carthaginians. Livy here prefers the Roman standpoint.
                        </note> very many of us are alive to remember. Never have our fortunes
                        seemed more favourable on land and sea than they were before the consulship
                        of Gaius Lutatius and Aulus Postumius. But in the consulship of Lutatius and
                        Postumius we were utterly defeated off the Aegates Islands. <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It was this defeat which brought
                            the previous war to an end, <date when="-0241">241 B.C.</date>
                        </note>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And if now also-may the gods avert the
                        omen! —fortune shall shift to any extent, do you hope that at the time of
                        our defeat we shall have a peace which no one gives us now when we are
                        victorious? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For myself, if some one is
                        about to bring up the question either of offering peace to the enemy or of
                        accepting it, I know what opinion to express. But if you are raising the
                        question of Mago's demands, I do not think it to the <pb n="p.43"/> point to
                        send those things to victors, and I think it <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> much less necessary to
                        send them to men who are deluding us with a hope unfounded and empty.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Not many were moved by Hanno's speech. For the
                    feud with the Barca family made his advice less weighty, and then minds filled
                    with the joy of the moment would not listen to anything which made their
                    rejoicing less well-founded. And they thought that, if they were willing to add
                    a little to their efforts, the war would soon be finished. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the senate with great unanimity decreed that
                    four thousand Numidians should be sent to Hannibal as a reinforcement; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Infantry are not mentioned as to be
                        sent from Carthage. Mercenaries were to be engaged in Spain and sent thence
                        to Hannibal. </note> also forty elephants and . . . silver talents.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And . . . was sent in advance to Spain
                    with Mago, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In fact Mago is still at
                        Carthage in xxxii. 5.</note> for the purpose of hiring twenty thousand
                    infantry and four thousand horse, to reinforce the armies that were in Italy and
                    those in Spain. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But, as usual in prosperous times, these
                    measures were carried out without spirit and in leisurely fashion, while the
                    Romans, in addition to their inborn activity, were prevented by misfortune also
                    from delaying. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That is, the consul was not
                    found wanting in anything which it was his to do, and the dictator, Marcus
                    Junius Pera, after performing the religious rites, proposed to the people
                    according to custom a bill allowing him to be mounted. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The dictator, as commander of the infantry, was by
                        tradition unmounted. Special permission could be obtained from the people,
                        as here, or from the senate, as Plutarch has it in <hi rend="italics"
                            >Fabius</hi> iv. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And then, in addition to the two city legions
                    which had been enrolled by the consuls at the beginning of the year, and the
                    levy of slaves, also the cohorts raised from the Picene and Gallic districts, he
                    stooped <pb n="p.45"/> to that last defence of a state almost despaired of,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> when
                    honour yields to necessity: namely, he issued an edict that, if any men who had
                    committed a capital offence, or were in chains as judgment debtors, should
                    become soldiers under him, he would order their release from punishment or debt.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Six thousand such men he armed with Gallic
                    spoils which had been carried in the triumph of Gaius Flaminius, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He triumphed over the Gauls in the Po
                        valley in <date when="-0223">223 B.C.</date>
                    </note> and thus set out from the city with twenty-five thousand armed men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal, after gaining possession of Capua
                    and vainly trying, partly by hope, partly by fear, to work for the second time
                    upon the feelings of the Neapolitans, led his army over into the territory of
                    Nola. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Though this was not at first with
                    hostile intent, since he did not despair of a voluntary surrender, still he was
                    ready, if they baulked his hope, to omit none of the things which they might
                    suffer or fear to suffer. The senate and especially its leading members stood
                    loyally by the alliance with Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the
                    common people, as usual, were all for a change of government and for Hannibal;
                    and they called to mind the fear of devastation of their lands and the many
                    hardships and indignities they must suffer in case of a siege. And men were not
                    lacking to propose revolt. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly the
                    senators, now obsessed by the fear that, if they should move openly, there could
                    be no resisting the excited crowd, found a way to postpone the evil by
                    pretending agreement. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For they pretend that
                    they favour revolt to Hannibal, but that there is no agreement as to the terms
                    on which they may go over to a new alliance and friendship. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Thus gaining time, they send emissaries in haste to the
                    Roman praetor, Marcellus Claudius, who <pb n="p.47"/> was at Casilinum <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Marcellus had been sent to Canusium
                        directly after the battle of Cannae to take command (XXII. lvii. 1), and is
                        now near Capua. </note> with his army, and inform him in <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> what
                    danger the Nolan state is placed; that its territory is in the hands of Hannibal
                    and the Carthaginians, and that the city will be so at once, if help be not
                    given; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that the senate, by conceding to the
                    common people that they would revolt whenever the people wished, had prevented
                    their making haste to revolt. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Marcellus,
                    after warmly praising the men of Nola, bade them postpone matters by the same
                    pretence until his arrival; in the meantime to conceal the dealings they had had
                    with him and all hope of Roman aid. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He
                    himself went from Casilinum to Caiatia, and thence, after crossing the river
                    Volturnus, made his way to Nola through the territory of Saticula and that of
                    Trebia, above Suessula and through the mountains. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This wide detour into mountain country was in order to
                        avoid meeting Hannibal. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Upon the arrival of the Roman praetor the
                    Carthaginian left the territory of Nola and came down to the sea near Neapolis,
                    desiring to gain possession of a coast town to which ships might have a safe
                    passage from Africa. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But on learning that
                    Neapolis was held by a Roman prefect —it was Marcus Junius Silanus, who had been
                    called in by the Neapolitans themselves —he turned aside from Neapolis also, as
                    he had from Nola, and made for Nuceria. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He had
                    besieged that city for some time, often attacking, often attempting in vain to
                    win over the populace, and at another time the leading citizens, when at last by
                    starving them he gained their surrender, stipulating that they leave unarmed and
                    with one garment only. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And then, as from the
                    beginning he had wished to be thought merciful to all Italians except the
                    Romans, he promised rewards and honours to any who remained and would serve
                    under <pb n="p.49"/> him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And yet he did not
                    hold anyone by that hope. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 216</note> They all dispersed, wherever hospitality or
                    impulse happened to carry them, among the cities of Campania, especially Nola
                    and Neapolis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A group of some thirty senators,
                    and as it chanced all the most prominent, came to Capua, and being refused
                    admission because they had closed their gates to Hannibal, went to Cumae. At
                    Nuceria the booty was given to the soldiers, the city sacked and burned. </p>
                <p> As for Nola, Marcellus held it not more by confidence in his force than by the
                    good-will of the leading citizens. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He was
                    apprehensive of the common people and above all of Lucius Bantius, who was
                    impelled by the consciousness of an attempted revolt and by fear of the Roman
                    praetor, now to betray his native city, now, if fortune should not favour him in
                    that, to desert. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was a young man of spirit
                    and at that time almost the best-known horseman among the allies. He had been
                    found half-dead at Cannae in a pile of the slain; and Hannibal, after nursing
                    him kindly, had sent him home, even adding gifts. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Out of gratitude for that service Bantius had wished to put
                    the state of Nola under the authority and rule of the Carthaginian. And the
                    praetor saw that he was troubled and tormented by his desire for a revolution.
                    But since he had either to be restrained by punishment or else won over by
                    kindness, Marcellus preferred rather to gain for himself a brave and energetic
                    ally than merely to take such a man away from the enemy, and <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> summoning him addressed him kindly. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> It was easy, he said, to judge that he had among his
                    countrymen many who envied him, and this from the fact that no citizen of Nola
                    had told the speaker how many were his <pb n="p.51"/> brilliant feats of arms.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But to a man who had served <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> in the
                    Roman camp his bravery could not be unknown. Many who had been in the service
                    with Bantius were telling the speaker what a man he was, and what dangers he had
                    incurred for the safety and honour of the Roman people, and how often;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> also how at the battle of Cannae he had
                    not ceased fighting until, almost lifeless, he had been overwhelmed by the mass
                    of men, horses and arms that fell upon him. <quote>And so,</quote> he said,
                        <quote> all honour to your courage! <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Under
                        me you will have every advancement and every reward, and the more constantly
                        you are with me, the more you will feel that it is a distinction and an
                        advantage to you. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The youth was delighted with the promises,
                    and Marcellus gave him a fine horse and ordered the quaestor to pay him five
                    hundred denarii. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These silver coins
                        at that time bore the image of Diana (of Victory not long after) driving a
                        two-horse chariot ( <hi rend="italics">biga</hi> ). </note> The lictors were
                    bidden to allow him access to the commander whenever he wished. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this kindliness on the part of Marcellus
                    the high spirit of the young man was so tempered that thereafter none of the
                    allies more bravely and loyally aided the Roman cause. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> While Hannibal was at the gates —for he again
                    moved his camp from Nuceria to Nola —and <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the
                    common people of Nola were making fresh plans to revolt, Marcellus, upon the
                    arrival of the enemy, withdrew within the walls, not fearing for his camp, but
                    lest he give the great number who were impatient for it an opportunity to betray
                    the city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then on both sides they began to
                    form their battle-lines, the Romans before the walls of Nola, the Carthaginians
                    in front of their camp. Thereupon there were small engagements with varying
                    results in the space between the city and the camp, since the commanders <pb
                        n="p.53"/> wished neither to forbid small numbers who rashly <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> challenged
                    the enemy, nor to give the signal for a general engagement. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> During this daily guard-duty of the two armies leading
                    citizens of Nola reported to Marcellus that conferences between the common
                    people and the Carthaginians were taking place by night; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and that it had been settled that, when the Roman force
                    should be outside the gates and in line, they would plunder their baggage-train
                    and their packs, then close the gates and take possession of the walls, so that,
                    having the control of their affairs and the city in their own hands, they would
                    then admit the Carthaginian instead of the Roman. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> This being reported to Marcellus, he warmly praised the
                    senators of Nola and resolved to try the fortune of battle before there should
                    be any movement in the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the three
                    gates facing the enemy he drew up his army in three sections. He ordered the
                    baggage to bring up the rear, the camp-servants and sutlers and incapacitated
                    soldiers to carry stakes. At the middle gate he posted the pick of the
                    legionaries with the Roman cavalry, at the two gates to right and left the
                    recruits, light-armed and cavalry of the allies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> The men of Nola were forbidden to approach the walls and gates, and the
                    forces to be used as reserves were assigned to the baggage, in order to prevent
                    an attack upon it while the legions were fighting. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> In this formation they were standing inside the gates. </p>
                <p> Hannibal, who remained in battle-line under the standards until late in the day,
                    as he had done for several days, at first wondered that the Roman army did not
                    come out of the gate and that there was not one armed man on the walls.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then, supposing <pb n="p.55"/> the
                    conferences to have been betrayed, and that <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> inaction was the result of
                    fear, he sent part of his soldiers back to the camp, with orders to bring up in
                    haste to the front line all the equipment for besieging the city. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> He was quite confident that, if he should press the
                    hesitating, the common people would stir up some outbreak in the city. While
                    they were scattering to their several duties and hastening to the first
                    standards, and the line was advancing to the walls, the gate suddenly opened and
                    Marcellus ordered the trumpets to be sounded and a shout raised; that infantry
                    at first, and then cavalry should sally out against the enemy with all the dash
                    possible. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They had carried sufficient panic
                    and confusion into the centre, when Publius Valerius Flaccus and Gaius Aurelius,
                    his lieutenants, sallied out of the two gates on this side and that, to attack
                    the enemy's wings. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Sutlers and camp-servants
                    raised another shout, as did the rest of the crowd stationed to guard the
                    baggage so that the shouting gave the sudden impression of a very large army to
                    the Carthaginians, who particularly despised their small numbers. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> I should hardly venture to assert, what some have
                    affirmed, that 2800 of the enemy were slain, while not more than 500 of the
                    Romans were lost. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But whether the victory was
                    on such a scale or less, a very great thing, I rather think the greatest in that
                    war, was accomplished that day. For not to be defeated by Hannibal was a more
                    difficult thing than it was later to defeat him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now that Hannibal had lost hope of gaining
                    Nola and had retired to Acerrae, Marcellus at once closed the gates, stationed
                    guards to prevent anyone from leaving, and carried on in the forum an <pb
                        n="p.57"/> investigation of those who had been in secret <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note>
                    conferences with the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Over seventy
                    having been condemned as traitors, he beheaded them and ordered that their
                    possessions should be public property of the Roman people. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> And setting out with his whole army, after turning over the
                    government to the senate, he pitched camp and established himself above
                    Suessula. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian first tried to
                    entice Acerrae into a voluntary surrender; then, seeing them steadfast, prepared
                    to blockade and attack them. But the men of Acerrae had more courage than
                    resources. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly they gave up hope of
                    defending the city, and when they saw that their walls were being encircled,
                    before the enemy's works should be made continuous, they slipped away in the
                    dead of night through the gaps in the earthworks and through neglected
                    guard-posts. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Making their way along the roads
                    and where there were none, just as prudence or chance guided the wanderer, they
                    fled for refuge to those cities of Campania of which it was known that they had
                    not changed sides. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After plundering and burning Acerrae, when
                    word had come from Casilinum that the Roman dictator and fresh legions were
                    being summoned, Hannibal led his army to Casilinum, in order to prevent any
                    uprising at Capua also, while the enemy's camp was so near. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Casilinum was at that time held by five hundred
                    Praenestines, with a few Romans and Latins, whom the news of the disaster at
                    Cannae had brought thither. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As the levy at
                    Praeneste was not completed at the proper date, they had been late in setting
                    out from home, and had reached Casilinum before the news of the defeat. And
                    joined by others, Romans and allies, they set out from Casilinum and, as <pb
                        n="p.59"/> they were proceeding in a fairly large column, the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> report of
                    the battle of Cannae turned them back again to Casilinum. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> There, being suspected by the Campanians and apprehensive,
                    they spent some days in alternately guarding against plots and hatching them.
                    When credibly informed that the revolt of Capua and Hannibal's entry were being
                    negotiated, they slew townspeople in the night and seized that part of the city
                    which is on this side <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The right
                        (north) bank of the river.</note> of the Volturnus —for it is divided by
                    that river; and this was the garrison the Romans had at Casilinum. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> It was joined by a cohort from Perusia, four hundred
                    and sixty men, who had been driven to Casilinum by the same news as the
                    Praenestines a few days before. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And there
                    were quite enough men to defend so small a walled city, bounded on one side by
                    the river. But the lack of grain made it seem that there were even too many men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, being now not far away, sent his
                    Gaetulians ahead under a prefect named Isalcas.. And he ordered him, if there
                    should be an opportunity for a conference, at first by kind words to entice them
                    to open the gates and admit a garrison; but if they persisted in their
                    obstinacy, to use force and see if at some point he could make his way into the
                    city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they approached the walls, because
                    of the stillness they thought them deserted. And the barbarian, supposing the
                    garrison had withdrawn in alarm, was preparing to force the gates and break open
                    the bars, when suddenly <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> the gates were
                    opened and the two cohorts, drawn up inside for that very purpose, sallied out
                    with a mighty uproar, and wrought havoc among the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The first troops being thus beaten back, Maharbal, who had
                    been <pb n="p.61"/> sent with a larger number of picked men, was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> likewise
                    unable to withstand the sally of the cohorts. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Finally Hannibal pitched his camp directly before the walls and prepared to
                    assault the small city and small garrison with the greatest violence and with
                    all his forces. And while he was pressing the attack, the walls being completely
                    encircled by his men, he lost a considerable number, the most active at that,
                    being hit by missiles from the wall and the towers. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When they actually sallied out once, he almost cut off
                    their retreat by sending a column of elephants <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The elephants sent by order of the Carthaginian senate
                        (xiii. 7) must have arrived. Of those he had brought from Spain only one
                        reached Central Italy (XXII. ii. 10). </note> against them, and drove them
                    in alarm into the city, after a good number, for so small a force, had been
                    slain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> More would have fallen if night had not
                    interrupted the battle. On the next day all were fired to make the assault,
                    especially after a mural crown of gold <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > Awarded to the first man to scale the wall of a city; Polybius VI. xxxix.
                        5; Livy XXVI. xlviii. 5; Gellius V. vi. 16 and 19. </note> was displayed to
                    them, and the general himself kept making their spiritless attack upon a fort on
                    level <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> ground a reproach to the captors of
                    Saguntum, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXI. xv.</note>
                    reminding them singly and collectively of Cannae and Trasumennus and Trebia.
                    Then they began to push forward their sheds also and mines. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> And to meet the different attempts made by the enemy no
                    kind of activity, no ingenuity, proved lacking to the allies of the Romans. They
                    set up defences to meet the sheds; by transverse mines they intercepted the
                    enemy's mines; they forestalled his attempts both visible and invisible, until
                    shame helped to divert Hannibal from his undertaking. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> And after fortifying his camp and posting a small garrison,
                    that the attempt might not appear to have been abandoned, he retired into
                    winter-quarters at Capua. </p>
                <p> There he kept under roofs for the greater part of <pb n="p.63"/> the winter
                    troops that had been hardened long and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 216</note> repeatedly against all human hardships, but
                    had no experience or familiarity with comforts. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> And so those whom no severe hardship had conquered were ruined by excess of
                    comfort and immoderate pleasures and the more completely ruined the more eagerly
                    they in their inexperience had plunged into them. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> For sleep and wine, and feasts and harlots, and baths and
                    idleness, which habit made daily more seductive, so weakened their bodies and
                    spirits that it was their past victories rather than their present strength
                    which thereafter protected them; and this was regarded among the military
                    experts as a more serious failure in their commander than that he had not led
                    his men from the field of Cannae forthwith to the city of Rome. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> For that delay could be regarded as having merely
                    retarded the victory, this mistake as having robbed him of the power to win.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And so in fact, just as if he were
                    setting out from Capua with a different army, not a trace of the old-time morale
                    survived. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For they came back most of them
                    ensnared by harlots, and also as soon as they began to be quartered in tents,
                    and the march and other tasks of the soldier followed, they would give out both
                    in body and in spirit after the manner of recruits. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> And afterwards through the whole season of summer camps a
                    great many kept slipping away from their standards without furloughs; and
                    deserters had no hiding-places other than Capua. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For the effect of wintering at Capua cf. xlv. 4 (the
                        famous epigram, as if from the lips of Marcellus), and <hi rend="italics"
                            >ib.</hi> 6 (Hannibal's words, as Livy imagined them). Strabo confirms,
                        Polybius denies (V. iv. 13; XI. xix. 3 respectively). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But when winter was now growing mild, Hannibal
                    led his troops out of winter quarters and returned to Casilinum. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> There, although they had been making no more attacks,
                    an uninterrupted <pb n="p.65"/> blockade had nevertheless brought townspeople
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> and
                    garrison to extreme want. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman camp was
                    commanded by Tiberius Sempronius, since the dictator had gone to Rome to take
                    new auspices. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> If the auspices were
                        alleged to be defective, the commander returned to Rome to take them again;
                        VIII. xxx. 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcellus, who was likewise eager to bring aid
                    to the besieged, was held back both by a flood of the river Volturnus and by
                    entreaties of the men of Nola and Acerrae, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The city had not been entirely destroyed (xvii. 7), and
                        part of the population must have returned. </note> who feared the Campanians
                    if the Roman garrison should withdraw. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Gracchus, merely remaining near Casilinum, because it was the dictator's order
                    that he take no action in his absence, made no move, although facts which would
                    easily pass all endurance were being reported from Casilinum. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> For it was established that some, unable to endure hunger,
                    had thrown themselves from the wall, and that men stood unarmed on the walls
                    exposing unprotected bodies to wounds from missile weapons. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Gracchus, though indignant at this, did not dare to engage
                    the enemy without the dictator's order, and saw that, if he should try openly to
                    carry in grain, he must fight. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As there was
                    also no hope of carrying it in secretly, he filled many huge jars with spelt
                    brought from the farms all around, and sent word to the magistrate at Casilinum
                    that they should catch up the jars which the river was bringing down. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> In the following night, while all were intent upon
                    the river and the hope aroused by the Roman messenger, the jars set adrift in
                    midstream floated down, and the grain was evenly divided among them all. This
                    was done the next day also and the third day. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It was night when they were set adrift and when they arrived. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> In that way they escaped the notice of the enemy's guards.
                    After that the stream, now swifter than usual because of incessant rains, forced
                        <pb n="p.67"/> the jars by a cross current to the bank guarded by <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> the enemy.
                    There, caught among the willows growing on the banks, they were seen and it was
                    reported to Hannibal. And thereafter by a closer watch they saw to it that
                    nothing sent down the Volturnus to the city should escape notice. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Hannibal had a chain across the river
                        according to Frontinus <hi rend="italics">Strat.</hi> III. xiv. 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> However nuts which were poured out from the
                    Roman camp, as they floated down the middle of the river to Casilinum, were
                    caught by wattled hurdles. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Finally they reached such a pitch of distress
                    that they tried, after softening them by hot water, to chew thongs and the hides
                    stripped off of shields; and they did not abstain from rats and other animals,
                    and dug out every kind of plant and root from the bank beneath the wall.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And when the enemy had ploughed up all
                    the grassy ground outside the wall, the garrison sowed turnips, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was to impress Hannibal with their
                        confidence that their supplies would hold out for months, and that they did
                        not need the grass and herbs of which he had deprived them; Frontinus III.
                        xv. 3; Strabo V. iv. 10. </note> so that Hannibal exclaimed <quote>Am I to
                        sit before Casilinum until those seeds come up?</quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> And the man who had never before listened to
                    any terms now at last allowed them to treat with him in regard to ransoming the
                    free men. Seven-twelfths of a pound of gold was agreed upon as the price per
                    man. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Nearly four times the ransom
                        demanded for an ally (200 denarii) after the battle of Cannae; XXII. lii. 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> On receiving his promise they surrendered.
                    They were kept in chains until all the gold was paid, then with strict regard
                    for his promise they were released. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> This is
                    the more correct version than that they were slain by a charge of cavalry as
                    they departed. The majority were Praenestines. Of the five hundred and seventy
                    who were in the garrison sword and starvation carried off less than half. The
                    rest returned safe to Praeneste with their commander Marcus Anicius, who had <pb
                        n="p.69"/> formerly been a clerk. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> As
                    evidence there formerly <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 216</note> stood in the forum of Praeneste a statue of the man,
                    wearing a cuirass and draped in a toga, with his head covered. It had an
                    inscription on a bronze plate, stating that Marcus Anicius had paid his vow on
                    behalf of the soldiers who were in the garrison at Casilinum. The same
                    inscription was placed beneath three images of gods set up in the Temple of
                    Fortune. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The town of Casilinum was restored to the
                    Campanians and defended by a garrison of seven hundred men from the army of
                    Hannibal, that the Romans might not attack it when the Carthaginian should
                    withdraw. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To the Praenestine soldiers the
                    Roman senate voted double pay and exemption from service for five years. Though
                    rewarded for their courage with the gift of Roman citizenship, they made no
                    change. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> they did not accept. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As to the fate of the Perusians the report is
                    less clear, since no light has been thrown upon it either by any record of their
                    own or by a decree of the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the same time the Petelini, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Petelia, not far north of Croton, was
                        an exception to the statement that all the Bruttians had gone over to the
                        Carthaginians; XXII. lxi. 12. </note> who alone among the Bruttians had
                    remained in the friendship of Rome, were being attacked not only by the
                    Carthaginians, who were holding the region, but also by the rest of the
                    Bruttians for not making common cause with them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Unable to withstand these dangers, the Petelini sent legates to Rome to ask
                    for a garrison. The prayers of the legates and their tears —for when ordered to
                    shift for themselves they gave way to tearful complaints before the entrance of
                    the Senate House —stirred great compassion among senators and people. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> And when consulted a second time by Marcus Aemilius,
                    a praetor, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably elected in place
                        of Postumius, who fell in Gaul (xxiv. 11). </note> the senators, after
                    surveying all the resources of the empire, were <pb n="p.71"/> compelled to
                    admit that they themselves no longer <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 216</note> had any means to protect distant allies. They
                    ordered them to return home, and having fulfilled their obligation to the last,
                    to shift for themselves for the future as best the situation permitted.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When this outcome of the embassy was
                    reported at Petelia, such dejection and fear unexpectedly seized their senate
                    that some proposed to flee, each taking any possible road, and to <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> abandon the city, while others, since they had been
                    deserted by their old allies, proposed to join the rest of the Bruttians and
                    through them to surrender to Hannibal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But
                    those who thought nothing should be done hastily or rashly, and that they should
                    deliberate again, prevailed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the matter
                    was brought up in less excitement the following day, the optimates carried their
                    point, that they should bring in everything from the farms and strengthen the
                    city and the walls. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The siege lasted
                        eleven months, and at the last they were subsisting on hides, bark, twigs,
                        etc.; xxx. 1 ff.; Polybius VII. i. 3. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time letters from Sicily and
                    Sardinia were brought to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> First to be
                    read in the senate were those from Sicily and Titus Otacilius, the propraetor,
                    reporting that Publius Furius, the praetor, had come with his fleet from Africa
                    to Lilybaeum; that Furius himself had been seriously wounded and his life was in
                    the utmost danger; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that neither pay nor grain
                    was being furnished to the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> soldiers and the
                    crews at the proper date, and they had no means of doing so; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> that he strongly urged that both be sent as soon as
                    possible, and that they send a successor chosen, if they saw fit, from the
                    number of the new praetors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Much the same
                    facts in regard to pay and grain were reported from Sardinia by Aulus Cornelius
                    Mammula, the propraetor. To each the reply was that there <pb n="p.73"/> was
                    nothing on hand to send, and they were ordered <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> to provide for their own
                    fleets and armies. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Titus Otacilius sent
                    legates to Hiero, the mainstay of the Roman people, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Hiero II had ruled Syracuse 270- <date when="-0215">215
                            B.C.</date> ; a faithful ally of the Romans from 263 to his death. For
                        his sympathy and aid, including the gift of a golden Victory, after the
                        battle of the Trasumennus, cf. <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> xxxvii. </note> and received what money
                    was needed for pay, and grain for six months. In Sardinia the allied states made
                    generous contributions to Cornelius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And at
                    Rome besides, on account of the lack of money, three bank-commissioners were
                    named in accordance with a bill of Marcus Minucius, a tribune of the plebs,
                    namely, Lucius Aemilius Papus, who <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> had been
                    consul and censor, and Marcus Atilius Regulus, who had been consul twice, and
                    Lucius Scribonius Libo, who was at that time a tribune of the plebs. And Marcus
                    Atilius and Gaius Atilius, elected duumvirs, dedicated a temple of Concord,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the citadel, begun in <date
                            when="-0217">217 B.C.</date> ; XXII. xxxiii. 7 f. </note> which Lucius
                    Manlius had vowed in his praetorship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And
                    three pontiffs, Quintus Caecilius Metellus and Quintus Fabius Maximus and
                    Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, were elected <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> by the college of pontiffs. Fabius is the
                        Delayer, dictator in <date when="-0217">217 B.C.</date> Fulvius was consul
                        twice before this war, and twice again during the war, 212 and 209. </note>
                    in place of Publius Scantinius, deceased, and of Lucius Aemilius Paulus, the
                    consul, and Quintus Aelius Paetus, both of whom had fallen in the battle- of
                    Cannae. </p>
                <p> XXII. After making good, in so far as they could accomplish it by human wisdom,
                    the other losses fortune had caused by a series of disasters, the fathers at
                    last had regard for themselves as well and for the desolate Senate House and the
                    small number that came to the council of state. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> For since the censorship of Lucius Aemilius and Gaius Flaminius the list of
                    the senate had not been revised, although the defeats and in addition the fate
                    of individuals <pb n="p.75"/> had in the five years carried off so large a
                    number <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note>
                    of senators. Marcus Aemilius, the praetor, raised that question, as all demanded
                    that he should, since the dictator had already gone to the army after the loss
                    of Casilinum. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thereupon Spurius Carvilius,
                    after complaining in a long speech, not of the lack of senators only, but also
                    of the small number of citizens from whom <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    men might be chosen into the senate, said that for the sake of recruiting the
                    senate and of linking the Latins more closely with the Roman people, he strongly
                    urged that citizenship be bestowed upon two senators from each of the Latin
                    states, to be selected by the Roman fathers; and that from this number men be
                    chosen into the senate in place of the deceased members. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The fathers gave no more favourable hearing to this
                    proposal than they had given to a former demand of the Latins themselves. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. above, vi. 8 and note.</note> There
                    was a murmur of indignation everywhere in the hall, and in particular Titus
                    Manlius said that there still lived a man of the family to which belonged the
                    consul who on the Capitol had once threatened that he would slay with his own
                    hand any Latin he should see in the Senate House. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The threat was recorded in VIII. v. 7. The present
                        Manlius had opposed ransoming the captives at Cannae; XXII. lx. 5 ff. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Upon that Quintus Fabius Maximus said that
                    never had anything been mentioned in the senate at a more unfavourable moment
                    than this had been broached, in the midst of such unsettled feeling and wavering
                    loyalty among the allies, only to stir them up the more; that that rash
                    utterance of a single man should be drowned by silence on the part of them all;
                    and that, if there was ever any hallowed secret to be left unmentioned <pb
                        n="p.77"/> in the senate, this above all others must be covered, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> concealed,
                    forgotten, considered unsaid. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So mention of
                    the matter was suppressed. </p>
                <p> It was decided that as dictator, to draw up the list of the senate, a man should
                    be appointed who had previously been censor and was senior to all the other
                    living ex-censors. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And they ordered that
                    Gaius Terentius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Varro, defeated at Cannae. </note> the consul,
                    be summoned that he might name a dictator. He returned to Rome by long stages
                    from Apulia, leaving a garrison there; and that night, as was the custom, in
                    accordance with the decree of the senate he named Marcus Fabius Buteo dictator
                    for six months without master of the horse. <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius mounted the Rostra with his lictors and
                    said that he did not approve of two dictators at the <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> same time, an unprecedented thing, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Minucius, master of the horse, had finally been given
                        by the people equal authority with Fabius, but that did not make him legally
                        a dictator; XXII. xxvi. 7; xxvii. 3. </note> nor of a dictator without
                    master of the horse, nor of conferring a censor's power upon one man, and in
                    fact to the same man a second time, nor of giving the full military authority
                    for six months to a dictator not appointed for the conduct of affairs. He said
                    that he would set a limit to such possible irregularities as the crisis and
                    necessity had occasioned. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For he would not
                    eject from the senate any of those whom Gaius Flaminius and Lucius Aemilius as
                    censors had chosen into the senate, but would order their names merely
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> to be copied and read out, that judgment
                    and decision in regard to the reputation and character of a senator might not
                    rest with one man. And in place of the deceased he would make his choice in such
                    a way that rank should obviously have been preferred to rank, not man to man.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After reading the list of the old senate,
                    he chose in place of the deceased first those who since the censorship of Lucius
                    Aemilius <pb n="p.79"/> and Gaius Flaminius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In <date when="-0220">220 B.C.</date> ; <hi
                            rend="italics">Periocha</hi> 20. </note> had held a curule office and
                    had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> not
                    yet been chosen into the senate, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Pending the revision of the list by the censors, once in five years in the
                        normal course of things. </note> in each case in the order of his election.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then he chose those who had been aediles,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> plebeian aediles. </note> tribunes of the
                    people or quaestors; then, from the number of those who had not held offices,
                    the men who had spoils of the enemy affixed to their houses or had received the
                    civic wreath. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The reward of a soldier
                        who had saved the life of a fellow-citizen. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having thus chosen a hundred and seventy-seven
                    into the senate with great approval, he at once abdicated his office and came
                    down from the Rostra a private citizen, after ordering his lictors to leave him.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And he mingled with the crowd of those
                    engaged in private business, deliberately killing time, in order not to draw the
                    people away from the forum for the purpose of escorting him. Yet men's attention
                    was not relaxed by that delay, and so in large numbers they escorted him home.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul returned that night to the army
                    without informing the senate, for fear of being detained in the city to conduct
                    the elections. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the next day the senate, presided over by
                    Marcus Pomponius, the praetor, decreed that the dictator should be informed by
                    letter that, if he thought it to the public interest, he should come with the
                    master of the horse and the praetor, Marcus Marcellus, for the election of
                    consuls, in <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> order that from them in person
                    the fathers could learn what was the condition of the state and make their plans
                    in accordance with the facts. All of those summoned came, leaving their
                    lieutenants to command the legions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    dictator spoke briefly and <pb n="p.81"/> modestly of himself, and then diverted
                    a large share <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        216</note> of the glory <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> What were
                        the special achievements of M. Junius Pera we are not told. Probably
                            <quote>glory</quote> is only conventional for <quote>credit.</quote> The
                        consul is absent with the army. </note> to the master of the horse, Tiberius
                    Sempronius Gracchus; and he ordered the elections at which these consuls were
                    named: Lucius Postumius for the third time, then absent with Gaul as his sphere
                    of action, and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus, who was at that time master of the
                    horse and curule aedile. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then the following
                    men were elected as praetors: Marcus Valerius Laevinus for the second time,
                    Appius Claudius Pulcher, Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, Quintus Mucius Scaevola.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The dictator, after the election of
                    magistrates, returned to the army and the winter quarters at Teanum, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The northernmost town in Campania was
                        Teanum Sidicinum, an important road centre in a strong position. </note>
                    leaving the master of the horse at Rome, in order that he, inasmuch as he was to
                    enter upon office a few days later, might advise with the fathers in regard to
                    enrolling and providing armies for the year. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Just as these measures were being taken, a
                    fresh disaster was reported —for fortune was piling one upon another for that
                    year —namely, that the consul designate, Lucius Postumius, had perished, himself
                    and his army, in Gaul. There was a huge forest, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Near Mutina (Modena), and northwest of Bononia
                        (Bologna). </note> called Litana by the Gauls, by way of which he was about
                    to lead his army. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In that forest the Gauls
                    hacked the trees to right and left of the road in such a way that, if not
                    disturbed, they stood, but fell if pushed slightly. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Postumius had two Roman legions, and had enlisted from the
                    coast of the Upper Sea <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. xxxviii. 1;
                        contrast i. 5.</note> such numbers of allies that he led twenty-five
                    thousand armed men into the enemy's territory. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The Gauls had surrounded the very edge of the forest, <pb n="p.83"/> and when
                    the column entered a defile <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        particular spot chosen for the trap. Although <hi rend="italics">saltus</hi>
                        often = <hi rend="italics">silva,</hi> the hacking of trees must have been
                        confined to some stretch of the road offering special advantages to the
                        enemy, and near the point where the road emerged into open country. Cf.
                        xxxiii. 8. </note> they pushed <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 261.</note> against the outermost of the trees that had
                    been hacked near the ground. As these fell, each upon the next tree, which was
                    in itself unsteady and had only a slight hold, piling up from both sides they
                    overwhelmed arms, men and horses, so that hardly ten men escaped. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> For after very many had been killed by tree-trunks
                    and broken branches, and the rest of the troops were alarmed by the unforeseen
                    calamity, the Gauls under arms, surrounding the whole defile <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Here also it is difficult to believe
                        that <hi rend="italics">saltus</hi> is used as another word for
                            <quote>forest,</quote> since the whole <hi rend="italics">silva
                            vasta</hi> (§ 7) could hardly be surrounded by the Gauls. Cf. Frontinus
                        I. vi. 4. Even in <date when="-0043">43 B.C.</date> there were still
                        remnants of forest along the Aemilian Way; <hi rend="italics">ib.</hi> II.
                        v. 39. </note> slew them, while but few out of so many were captured, —the
                    men who were making their way to a bridge over a river, but were cut off, since
                    the bridge had by that time been occupied by the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> There Postumius fell fighting with all his might to avoid
                    capture. Spoils taken from his body and the severed head of the general were
                    carried in triumph by the Boians to the temple which is most revered in their
                    land. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then after cleaning the head they
                    adorned the skull with gold according to their custom. And it served them as a
                    sacred vessel from which to pour libations at festivals and at the same time as
                    a drinking cup for the priests and keepers of the temple. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The booty also meant no less to the Gauls than the victory.
                    For although a large part of the cattle had been crushed by fallen trees, still
                    everything else was found strewn the whole length of the column of the slain,
                    since nothing was scattered by flight. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this disaster was reported, the city was
                    for many days in such alarm that, in view of the stillness, like that of night,
                    produced <pb n="p.85"/> throughout the city by the closing of the shops, the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note>
                    senate charged the aediles with the duty of going about the city and ordering
                    that shops be opened and the appearance of public mourning removed from the
                    city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And then Tiberius Sempronius held a
                    session of the senate; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This he did as
                            <hi rend="italics">magister equitum.</hi> His consulship would begin at
                        the Ides of March; xxx. 17. </note> and he comforted the fathers, and urged
                    that men who had not given way to the catastrophe at Cannae should not lose
                    heart in the face of lesser disasters. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So far
                    as concerned the Carthaginian enemy and Hannibal, he said that, if only coming
                    events should prove favourable, as he hoped, a Gallic war could be both safely
                    neglected and postponed, and punishment for that treachery would be in the power
                    of the gods and of the Roman people. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was in
                    regard to the Carthaginian enemy and the armies with which to carry on that war
                    that they must deliberate and debate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He
                    himself first stated what number of infantry and cavalry, of citizens and
                    allies, were in the dictator's army. Then Marcellus set forth the total of his
                    forces. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As to what troops were in Apulia with
                    the consul Gaius Terentius, those who knew were questioned; and no method of
                    making up consular armies strong enough for so great a war was found. And so,
                    although righteous indignation goaded them, it was decided that Gaul should be
                    left out of account that year. The dictator's army was assigned to the consul.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As for the army of Marcus Marcellus, it
                    was voted that those of them who were survivors of the rout at Cannae should be
                    transported to Sicily and serve there so long as there should be war in Italy;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> also that from the dictator's legions all
                    the least efficient soldiers should be sent away to the same province, with no
                    definite term of service except that of the campaigns <pb n="p.87"/> fixed by
                    law. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two city legions were assigned to
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> the
                    other consul, to be elected in place of Lucius Postumius; and it was voted that
                    he be elected as soon as possible with due regard to the auspices; <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> further, that two legions be summoned as soon as
                    might be from Sicily, and that from them the consul to whom the city legions
                    fell should take as many soldiers as he needed; <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> also that the command of Gaius Terentius, the consul, should be extended
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The usual word would be <hi
                            rend="italics">prorogari.</hi> But Cicero has <hi rend="italics"
                            >provinciae propagator, Att.</hi> VIII. iii. 3, and uses the verb in the
                        sense of <quote>prolong</quote> in <hi rend="italics">Cat.</hi> iii. 26; so
                        Suetonius <hi rend="italics">Aug.</hi> 23. </note> for one year and no
                    reduction made in the army which he had for the defence of Apulia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these operations and these preparations
                    in Italy the war in Spain was no less active, but up to that time more
                    successful <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> than in Italy. </note> for the Romans.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Publius and Gnaeus Scipio had divided the
                    forces between them, so that Gnaeus should carry on the war on land, Publius
                    with the fleet; and Hasdrubal, commander-in-chief of the Carthaginians, since he
                    could not fully depend upon either arm of his forces, remained far from the
                    enemy, being protected by distance and position, until, in answer to pleas
                    urgent and long-continued, four thousand infantry and five hundred cavalry were
                    sent from Africa to reinforce him. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As
                        voted by the Carthaginian senate, xiii. 7.</note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then, with hopes at last renewed, he moved his
                    camp nearer to the enemy, and he too ordered that a fleet should be built and
                    equipped, in order to protect the islands and the sea-coast. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In the very flush of renewed operations he met a blow in
                    the desertion of the commanders of his ships, who, being severely reprimanded
                    after their abandonment of the fleet at the Hiberus in their fright, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXII. xix. 11 f. Their desertion
                        now consisted in going over to native tribes which sided with the Romans,
                        especially to the Tartesii (Turdetani), on the lower Baetis (Guadalquivir).
                    </note> had never <pb n="p.89"/> since been entirely loyal either to the general
                    or to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note>
                    the cause of Carthage. These deserters had made trouble in the tribe of the
                    Tartesii, and at their instigation a number of cities had rebelled. One city had
                    even been stormed by them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was against this tribe that the war was now
                    diverted from the <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> Romans, and Hasdrubal,
                    having entered the territory of the enemy with a hostile army, resolved to
                    attack a noble in command of the Tartesii, Chalbus, who with a strong army was
                    keeping to his camp before the walls of a city captured a few days before.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Therefore Hasdrubal, sending the
                    light-armed in advance, to draw out the enemy to battle, scattered part of his
                    cavalry over the farms to ravage them and to capture stragglers. There was
                    confusion at the camp and at the same time flight and slaughter in the country
                    around. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then, after they had made their way
                    from all sides back to the camp by different roads, fear was so suddenly
                    banished from their hearts that they had sufficient spirit not only to defend
                    the fortifications but also to attack the enemy. Accordingly they sallied out of
                    the camp in a column, dancing, as is their custom; and their sudden boldness
                    inspired alarm in the enemy, who a little before had been the aggressor.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And so Hasdrubal likewise led his forces
                    up a very steep hill, further defended by a river in front. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Also he got back the light-armed who had been sent ahead
                    and the scattered cavalry to the same position. Unable to put sufficient
                    confidence in either the hill or the river, he strongly fortified his camp with
                    an earthwork. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While fear was shifting thus
                    from one side to the other, a number of engagements took place, and the Numidian
                    horseman was no match for the <pb n="p.91"/> Spaniard, nor the Moorish
                    dart-thrower for the man <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 216</note> with the wicker shield, the Spaniard in both cases being an
                    equal in speed and quite superior in spirit and strength. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Tartesii had repeatedly failed to
                    draw the Carthaginian out to battle by facing his camp, and it was also not easy
                    to assault the camp, they took by storm the city of Ascua, to which Hasdrubal,
                    on entering the land of the enemy, had brought grain and other supplies;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and they gained possession of all the
                    country around. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And they could no longer be
                    restrained by any authority either on the march or in camp. Hasdrubal,
                    perceiving that this carelessness came, as usually happens, from success,
                    exhorted his soldiers to attack the enemy while dispersed and in no formation,
                    and coming down from the hill he proceeded to their camp in battle order.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When his approach was reported by
                    messengers fleeing wildly from the watch-towers and guard-posts, they shouted
                        <quote>To arms!</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Snatching up arms, each man for himself,
                    without commanders, without orders, in no units or formations, they dashed into
                    battle. Already the first men had engaged, while some charged in separate masses
                    and others had not yet left the camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Nevertheless they at first frightened the enemy by sheer audacity. Then, as
                    stragglers advancing against dense ranks, finding no safety in small numbers,
                    they looked to one another for help; and, beaten back from every side, they
                    formed a circle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And as they crowded bodies
                    against bodies and touched arms to arms, they were forced into close quarters.
                    Having hardly room enough to move their weapons, they were encircled by the
                    enemy, and the slaughter continued until late in the <pb n="p.93"/> day.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A very small part of them sallied out and
                    made <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> for
                    the woods and the mountains. In no less alarm the camp was abandoned, and on the
                    next day the whole tribe surrendered. </p>
                <p> Yet not for long did the tribe abide by the agreement. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> For soon came the order from Carthage that Hasdrubal should
                    at the first opportunity lead his army into Italy. And the spreading of this
                    news throughout Spain made nearly all incline to the side of the Romans. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Evidently exaggerated, as in xxix. 16
                        and xxxii. 6. A prosperous city near the Hiberus is mentioned in xxviii. 10
                        as still loyal to the Carthaginians. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly Hasdrubal at once sent a letter
                    to Carthage, showing what a loss the mere report of his departure had caused;
                    that if he were actually to leave the country, Spain would belong to the Romans
                    before he should cross the Hiberus. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >The Ebro was the treaty boundary; XXI. ii. 7.</note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For besides the lack of both an army and a
                    general to leave in his place, so able were the Roman generals that they could
                    scarcely be resisted if the forces were evenly matched. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> And so, if they had any regard for Spain, they should send
                    him a successor with a strong army. Even if all should go well, that man would
                    still find it no peaceful province. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though this letter at first greatly stirred
                    the senate, nevertheless, since concern for Italy was older and stronger, no
                    change was made either in regard to Hasdrubal or to his forces. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But Himilco was sent with a complete army and an enlarged
                    fleet to hold and defend Spain by land and sea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> After transporting his land and naval forces, Himilco fortified a camp,
                    beached his ships and surrounded them with an earthwork. Then he himself with
                    picked horsemen, making his way with all possible speed, and with equal
                    alertness through the <pb n="p.95"/> wavering and the hostile tribes, reached
                    Hasdrubal. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        216</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After setting forth the decrees and
                    instructions of the senate, and being himself informed in turn how the war in
                    Spain must be conducted, he went back to his own camp, being protected by his
                    quickness more than anything else, since he had left each place before the enemy
                    could agree upon action. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, before
                    breaking camp, exacted money from all the tribes under his rule, knowing well
                    that Hannibal had repeatedly bought the right of passage, and that he had Gallic
                    auxiliaries only by hiring them; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but that if
                    he had set out on so long a march without funds, he would scarcely have made his
                    way to the Alps. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Therefore he exacted money in
                    haste and came down to the Hiberus. </p>
                <p> When news of the decrees of the Carthaginians and Hasdrubal's expedition reached
                    the Roman commanders, both dropped everything, and uniting their forces prepared
                    to meet and resist his efforts, thinking <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    that if Hannibal, who was himself an enemy Italy could scarcely endure, should
                    be joined by Hasdrubal as a general and by an army from Spain, that would be the
                    end of the Roman power. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Troubled by these
                    apprehensions, they concentrated their troops at the Hiberus, crossed the river,
                    and after protracted deliberation, whether to pitch camp near that of the enemy
                    or to be satisfied with keeping him from his projected march by attacking
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> allies of the Carthaginians, they
                    prepared to attack a city which had its name Hibera from the river near by, the
                    richest city of the region at that time. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On
                    learning this Hasdrubal, instead of bringing aid to his allies, proceeded
                    likewise to attack a city which had recently surrendered to the Romans.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thus the siege <pb n="p.97"/> already
                    begun was abandoned by the Romans and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 216</note> the war directed against Hasdrubal himself. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They had their camps five miles apart for a
                    few days, not without skirmishes, but without drawing up lines of battle.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Finally on one and the same day, as though
                    by agreement, the signal for battle was raised on both sides and with all their
                    forces they went down into the plain. The Roman line stood in triple ranks.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some of the light-armed were posted in the
                    intervals between the maniples in advance of the standards, some placed behind
                    the standards. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Cavalry covered the wings.
                    Hasdrubal made a strong centre of Spanish troops; on the right wing he placed
                    Carthaginians, on the left Africans and mercenary auxiliaries. Of the cavalry he
                    stationed the Numidians on the wing of the Carthaginian infantry, the rest on
                    that of the Africans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And not all of his
                    Numidians were placed on the right wing, but only those who, taking two horses
                    apiece <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXXV. xxviii. 8.</note>
                    after the manner of performers, had the custom of leaping armed from the tired
                    horse to the fresh, often in the very heat of battle; such was the agility of
                    the men, and so well-trained their breed of horses. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> While they were standing in this array, the hopes of the
                    generals on the two sides were fairly balanced; for there was also not much
                    superiority for the one army or the other either in the number or the type of
                    its soldiers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the spirit of the soldiers
                    was far from being matched. For the Romans, although fighting far from their
                    country, had been easily persuaded by their generals that they were fighting in
                    defence of Italy and the city of Rome. And so, as men whose return to their
                    native land would depend upon the issue of that battle, they had made up their
                        <pb n="p.99"/> minds to win or die. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    other battle-line had men <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 216</note> less firmly resolved. For the majority were
                    Spaniards, who preferred to be vanquished in Spain, rather than as victors to be
                    dragged to Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Therefore at the first
                    clash, when they had barely hurled their javelins, the centre fell back, and, as
                    the Romans advanced with a great charge, retreated. On the wrings, however,
                    there was more spirited fighting. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the one
                    hand the Carthaginians pressed them hard, on the other hand the Africans; and it
                    was a double conflict against men presumed to have been surrounded. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> But, although the whole Roman line had by this time
                    crowded into the centre, it had sufficient strength to force apart the wings of
                    the enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thus there were two battles in
                    opposite directions. In both the Romans were unquestionably victorious, since,
                    once the centre had been routed, they were superior both in the numbers and in
                    the strength of their men. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A great number of
                    men <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As many as 25,000 according to
                        Eutropius III. 11.</note> were slain there, and if the Spaniards had not
                    fled in such confusion when the battle had scarcely begun, very few out of that
                    entire line would have survived. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The cavalry
                    were not engaged at all, since, as soon as the Mauri and the Numidians saw the
                    centre giving way, they at once abandoned the wings, exposed by their wild
                    flight as they drove the elephants also before them. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, after waiting for the final outcome of the
                    battle, escaped with a few men out of the midst of the slaughter. His camp the
                    Romans captured and plundered. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> That battle
                    brought to the Roman side all that still wavered in Spain, and Hasdrubal had
                    left to him no hope, not only of leading his army over into Italy, but not even
                    of remaining with any safety in Spain. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> When
                    these facts were generally known <pb n="p.101"/> at Rome through the letter of
                    the Scipios, people <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        216</note> rejoiced, not so much over the victory, as that Hasdrubal's
                    crossing into Italy had been prevented. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Hasdrubal's invasion of Italy was carried out nine
                        years later to a fatal conclusion at the Metaurus, XXVII. xlix. 4. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were going on in Spain,
                    Petelia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For the long siege of Petelia
                        cf. the note on xx. 10.</note> in the land of the Bruttii, was taken by
                    Himilco, Hannibal's prefect, some months after the siege began. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> That victory cost the Carthaginians much blood and many
                    wounds, and starvation <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Polybius also
                        (VII. i. 3) gave such details as follow.</note> more than any assault
                    overpowered the besieged. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For after they had
                    consumed their food-supply in cereals and flesh, the familiar and the
                    unfamiliar, of four-footed beasts of every kind, they finally lived on hides and
                    grasses and roots and tender bark and leaves stripped off. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And they were not overpowered until they had no strength
                    left to stand on the walls and bear arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Having taken Petelia, the Carthaginian led his troops across to Consentia, and
                    as it was less obstinately defended, he received its surrender within a few
                    days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About the same time an army of the
                    Bruttians also besieged Croton, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        story of the siege and capture of Croton, on the Gulf of Tarentum, is told
                        in some detail in XXIV. ii f. </note> a Greek city formerly rich in arms and
                    men, but even then so crushed by many great disasters that, including all ages,
                    less than two thousand citizens remained. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And
                    so the enemy easily gained possession of the city bereft of its defenders. Only
                    the citadel was still held, and to it some, in the uproar of a captured city,
                    made their escape out of the midst of slaughter. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> And Locri went over to the Bruttians and Carthaginians, the populace having
                    been betrayed by the leading men. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Regium alone
                    in that region remained loyal to the Romans and to the very last independent.
                        <pb n="p.103"/> The same trend of feeling reached Sicily also, and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 216</note> even the
                    house of Hiero did not hold aloof entirely from the revolt. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> For Gelo, the eldest son, scorning both the old age of his
                    father and <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> the Roman alliance since the
                    disaster at Cannae, went over to the Carthaginians. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius makes him a model of filial devotion (VII.
                        viii. 9). Coins prove that he was king with his father. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And he would have caused an uprising in
                    Sicily, had not death, so timely as to besmirch even his father with suspicion,
                    carried him off as he was arming the populace and trying to gain allies.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Such were the checkered events of that
                    year in Italy, in Africa, in Sicily, in Spain. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This brief resume covers the events narrated from XXII.
                        xxxviii up to this point. An eventful year. </note>
                </p>
                <p> At the end of the year Quintus Fabius Maximus requested of the senate that he be
                    permitted to dedicate the Temple of Venus of Eryx <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Where the temple was we learn presently, xxxi. 9. Her
                        chief temple was on the western headland of Sicily, Mt. Eryx. </note> which
                    he had vowed in his dictatorship. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The senate
                    decreed that Tiberius Sempronius, consul designate, as soon as he entered upon
                    his office should propose to the people that they order that Quintus Fabius
                    should be a duumvir for the purpose of dedicating the temple. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> And in honour of Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, who had been
                    consul twice and augur, his three sons, Lucius, Marcus, Quintus, gave funeral
                    games for three days and showed twenty-two pairs of gladiators in the Forum.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The earliest known example of a
                        gladiatorial combat at Rome was in <date when="-0264">264 B.C.</date> That
                        also was on the occasion of a funeral, and the gift of sons. </note>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The curule aediles, Gaius Laetorius and
                    Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus, consul designate, who in his aedileship had been
                    master of the horse, celebrated the Roman Games, and on three of the days they
                    were repeated. The Plebeian Games of the aediles, Marcus Aurelius Cotta and
                    Marcus Claudius Marcellus, were repeated three times. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.105"/>
                <p> The third year of the Punic War being at an end, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> Tiberius Sempronius
                    entered upon office as consul on the Ides of March. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> Of the praetors Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, who had previously
                    been consul <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In fact twice, 237 and
                            <date when="-0224">224 B.C.</date>
                    </note> and censor, had by lot his assignment as judge between citizens, Marcus
                    Valerius Laevinus had his as judge in the cases of strangers, while to Appius
                    Claudius Pulcher Sicily was allotted, and Sardinia to Quintus Mucius Scaevola.
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> That Marcus Marcellus should have full
                    military authority as proconsul was ordered by the people, because he alone of
                    the Roman commanders since the disaster at Cannae had met with success in Italy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate on the first day on which it was in
                    session on the Capitol, decreed that a double tax should be imposed that year
                    and the normal tax collected at once; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that
                    from it pay should be given in cash to all the soldiers except those who had
                    been soldiers at Cannae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As for the armies,
                    they decreed that Tiberius Sempronius, the consul, should set for the two city
                    legions a date for mobilization at Cales; that these legions should be led
                    thence to the Claudian Camp <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In fact
                        twice, 237 and <date when="-0224">224 B.C.</date>
                    </note> above Suessula; that the legions already there —it <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> was chiefly the army of Cannae —should be taken over into
                    Sicily by Appius Claudius Pulcher, the praetor, and that those which were in
                    Sicily should be brought to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Claudius Marcellus was sent to the army for which a date of mobilization at
                    Cales had been set; and he was ordered to conduct the city legions to the
                    Claudian Camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To take over the old army and
                    conduct it thence to Sicily, Appius Claudius sent his lieutenant, Tiberius
                    Maecilius Croto. </p>
                <p> At first men had been waiting in silence for the <pb n="p.107"/> consul to
                    preside over an election for the naming of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> his colleague. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Then, when they saw that Marcus Marcellus, whom they
                    particularly desired to have elected consul for that year, on account of
                    remarkable successes in his praetorship, had been sent away, apparently on
                    purpose, murmurs began to be heard in the Senate House. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Noting this the consul said: <quote> Both acts were to the
                        advantage of the state, fellow-senators, that Marcus Claudius should be sent
                        to Campania to make the change of armies, and that the coming election
                        should not be proclaimed until he, after accomplishing the task which was
                        assigned him, should return thence, so that you might have the consul whom
                        the critical situation in the state requires and whom you particularly
                        desire. </quote> So until Marcellus returned, nothing was said about an
                    election. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Meanwhile Quintus Fabius Maximus and
                    Titus Otacilius Crassus were made duumvirs for the dedication of temples,
                    Otacilius for that of Mens, Fabius for that of Venus of Eryx. Both are on the
                    Capitol, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Exact situation of the
                        temples is unknown; cf. xxxii. 20; XXII. ix. 10; x, 10. </note> separated by
                    a single water-channel. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And in regard to the
                    three hundred Campanian knights 2 who, after loyally serving their terms in
                    Sicily, had come to Rome, a bill was brought before the people that they should
                    be Roman citizens; further, that they should be townsmen of Cumae from the day
                    before that on which the Campanian people had revolted from the Roman people.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Roman citizenship which they
                        had lost with the revolt of Capua was restored, while their municipal rights
                        and privileges were transferred to loyal Cumae and made to antedate the
                        Campanian secession. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> What had chiefly prompted the making of this
                    proposal was that they said they did not themselves know with whom they
                    belonged, having given up their old home-city, and not being enrolled as yet in
                    the city to which they had returned. After Marcellus returned from the army, an
                    election to name one consul in place of Lucius <pb n="p.109"/> Postumius was
                    ordered by edict. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> With great <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> unanimity
                    Marcellus was elected, to assume office at once. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Just as he was entering upon his consulship it thundered,
                    and thereupon the augurs, being summoned, declared that there seemed to be a
                    defect in his election. And the fathers widely circulated the statement that it
                    did not meet the approval of the gods that two plebeians had then for the first
                    time been elected consuls. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> In place of
                    Marcellus, after he had abdicated, Quintus Fabius Maximus was substituted as
                    consul for the third time. </p>
                <p> The sea was aflame in the course of that year. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                    /> At Sinuessa a cow gave birth to a colt. At the Temple of Juno Sospita at
                    Lanuvium images of the gods dripped blood, and it rained stones around the
                    temple —a shower on account of which there were ceremonies, as usual, for nine
                    days. And the rest of the portents were duly expiated. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A very short list of portents and expiations, compared
                        with those in XXI. lie., XXII. i. and elsewhere. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls divided the armies between them.
                    To Fabius fell the army at Teanum, formerly commanded by Marcus Junius, the
                    dictator; to Sempronius the slave volunteers <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the slaves who, after the battle of Cannae,
                        volunteered and were purchased by the state. By good service as soldiers
                        they earned their freedom; xxxv. 6; XXII. lvii. 11; XXIV. x. 3; xiv. 4 f.,
                        etc. </note> who were at that place and twenty-five thousand of the allies.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To Marcus Valerius, the praetor, were
                    assigned the legions which had returned from Sicily. Marcus Claudius was sent as
                    proconsul to the army which was above Suessula, in order to guard Nola. The
                    praetors set out for Sicily and Sardinia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls issued an edict that, whenever they might call a meeting of the senate,
                    the senators and any who had the right to give an opinion in the senate <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the present case the persons meant
                        can only be the newly-elected magistrates, since the list has just been
                        revised, and none can be waiting for a new <hi rend="italics">lectio
                            senatus.</hi> Cf. xxiii. 5. </note> should assemble at the <pb n="p.111"
                    /> Porta Capena. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> By this gate in the
                            <quote>Servian Wall</quote> the Via Appia left the city, near the east
                        end of the Circus Maximus. Meeting probably in the nearby Temple of Honos,
                        the senate could confer with returning generals outside the city. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The praetors who had judicial duties <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> set up
                    their tribunals at the Piscina Publica. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This swimming-pool of uncertain location was also
                        outside the gate. </note> That place should be named —so they ordered —in
                    recognizances, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The defendant was
                        bound to give assurances (in one of the various forms prescribed by the
                        praetor's edict) that he would appear on the day and at the place named
                        —here at the Piscina instead of in the Forum. </note> and there justice was
                    rendered that <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> year. </p>
                <p> Meanwhile Carthage, from which Mago, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        He had not yet gone to Spain, as was intended in xiii. 8. </note> Hannibal's
                    brother, was on the point of transporting into Italy twelve thousand infantry
                    and fifteen hundred cavalry, twenty elephants and a thousand talents of silver,
                    with a convoy of sixty warships, received the news that in Spain operations
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> had failed and nearly all the tribes in
                    that province had revolted to the <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Romans.
                    There were some who, neglecting Italy, were ready to divert Mago to Spain with
                    that fleet and those forces, when there suddenly appeared a ray of hope of
                    recovering <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Sardinia. It was reported that the
                    Roman army there was small; that the old praetor, Aulus Cornelius, who was well
                    acquainted with the province, was retiring, and a new praetor <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> expected; further, that the Sardinians were now weary of
                    the long continuance of Roman rule, and in the previous year had been ruled with
                    harshness and greed; that they were burdened by a heavy tribute and an unfair
                    requisition of grain; that nothing was lacking but a leader to whom they might
                    go <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> over. Such was the report of a secret
                    embassy sent by the leading men at the special instigation of Hampsicora, who at
                    that time was far above the rest in prestige and <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> wealth. By such news they were almost at the <pb n="p.113"
                    /> same moment dejected and encouraged, and sent <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> Mago with his fleet and
                    his forces to <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Spain. For Sardinia they chose
                    Hasdrubal as general, and voted him about the same number of troops as to Mago. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And at Rome the consuls did what had to be
                    done in the city, and were now bestirring themselves for the <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> war. Tiberius Sempronius set his soldiers a date for
                    mobilization at Sinuessa, and Quintus Fabius, after first consulting the senate,
                    gave orders that all should bring their grain crops <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Either ripe or ripening, to be threshed in towns of
                        such regions as were named in the order. </note> from the farms into
                    fortified cities before the next Kalends of June; that if any man should fail to
                    do so, he would lay waste his farm, sell his slaves at auction and burn the farm
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> buildings. Not even those praetors who
                    had been appointed to administer justice <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In normal times short absences only from the city were
                        permissible for the <hi rend="italics">urbanus</hi> and the <hi
                            rend="italics">peregrinus.</hi>
                    </note> were granted exemption from the conduct of the <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> war. It was decided that Valerius, the praetor, should go
                    to Apulia, to take over the army from Terentius; that when the legions should
                    arrive from Sicily, he should chiefly use these troops for the defence of that
                    region; that Terentius' army should be sent to Tarentum under some one of the
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> lieutenants. And twenty-five ships were
                    given him, that with them he might be able to defend the coast between
                    Brundisium and <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Tarentum. An equal number of
                    ships was assigned by decree to Quintus Fulvius, the city praetor, for the
                    defence of the shore near the <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> city. Gaius
                    Terentius as proconsul was given the task of conducting a levy of troops in the
                    Picene territory and defending that <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> region.
                    And Titus Otacilius Crassus, after dedicating the Temple of Mens on the Capitol,
                    was sent with full authority to Sicily, where he was to command the fleet. </p>
                <pb n="p.115"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this conflict of the two richest peoples
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> in
                    the world all kings and nations had turned their attention, among them
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Philip, king of the Macedonians, all the
                    more since he was nearer to Italy and separated from it only by the Ionian Sea.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On first learning by report that Hannibal
                    had crossed the Alps, although he had rejoiced at the outbreak of war between
                    the Romans and the Carthaginians, still, as their resources were not yet known,
                    he had wavered, uncertain which of the two peoples he wished to have the
                    victory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now that a third battle, a third
                    victory, favoured the Carthaginians, he inclined to the side of success and sent
                    ambassadors to Hannibal. These avoided the ports of Brundisium and Tarentum,
                    because they were kept guarded by Roman ships, and landed at the Temple of
                    Lacinian Juno. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A famous temple on a
                        promontory near Croton; cf. XXIV. iii. 3 ff.; XLII. iii. 2 ff.; Strabo VI.
                        i. 11. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Making their way thence toward Capua by way of
                    Apulia, they encountered the centre of the Roman forces and were brought before
                    Valerius Laevinus, the praetor, whose camp was near Luceria. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> There Xenophanes, the leader of the embassy, boldly said
                    that he had been sent by King Philip to negotiate a friendly alliance with the
                    Roman people; that he had communications for the consuls and for the senate and
                    the Roman people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The praetor, who in the
                    midst of the revolts of old allies was greatly delighted by a new alliance with
                    so famous a king, hospitably received enemies as guests. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He furnished men to escort them, to indicate the roads
                    carefully, and what positions and what passes were held either by the Romans or
                    by the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Xenophanes made his way through
                    the Roman forces into <pb n="p.117"/> Campania and thence by the shortest road
                    to the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note>
                    camp of Hannibal, and arranged a treaty of friendship with him on the following
                    terms: that King Philip with the largest possible fleet —and <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> it was thought that he would make it two hundred ships
                    —should cross to Italy and ravage the coast, and should carry on the war on land
                    and sea with all his might; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that after the
                    war was over all Italy with the city of Rome itself should belong to the
                    Carthaginians and Hannibal, and all the booty fall to Hannibal; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> that after the complete subjugation of Italy they
                    should sail to Greece and wage war with such enemies as the king might choose;
                    and that such states on the mainland and such islands as face Macedonia should
                    belong to Philip and be a part of his kingdom. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On terms such as these a treaty was made
                    between the Carthaginian general and the ambassadors of the Macedonians.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And Gisgo and Bostar and Mago, who were
                    sent with them as ambassadors, to reassure the king himself, reached the same
                    place, the Temple of Juno Lacinia, where a ship lay in a hidden anchorage.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Setting out thence and making for the open
                    sea, they were sighted by the Roman fleet which was defending the coasts of
                    Calabria. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And Valerius Flaccus sent light
                    craft to pursue the ship and bring her back; whereupon the king's ambassadors at
                    first attempted to flee. Then, when they saw that they were being outstripped in
                    speed, they surrendered to the Romans and were brought before the admiral of the
                    fleet. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When he asked who they were and whence,
                    and whither they were bound, Xenophanes at first set up the false pretence which
                    had been quite successful once before: that, being sent by Philip to the Romans,
                    he had made his way <pb n="p.119"/> to Marcus Valerius, the one man to whom
                    there was <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        215</note> a safe road; that he had been unable to get across Campania,
                    which was blocked by the enemy's forces. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then,
                    when Carthaginian dress and appearance cast suspicion on Hannibal's ambassadors,
                    upon being questioned they were betrayed by their speech. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Thereupon their attendants were led aside and frightened by
                    threats; and a letter also from Hannibal to Philip was found, along with
                    agreements between the king of the Macedonians and the Carthaginian general.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So much being established, it seemed best
                    to send the captured men and their attendants as soon as possible to the senate
                    at Rome, or else to the consuls, wherever they might be. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> For that purpose five very swift ships were selected and
                    Lucius Valerius Antias was sent to command them. And instructions were given him
                    to distribute the ambassadors among all his ships, to be separately guarded; and
                    he was to see to it that there should be no conversation among them or any
                    interchange of plans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> About the same time at Rome Aulus Cornelius
                    Mammula, on retiring from his province of Sardinia, reported what was the
                    condition of affairs in the island: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that all
                    were aiming at war and rebellion; that Quintus Mucius, his successor, upon
                    arriving was affected by the unwholesome climate and bad water, and having
                    contracted an illness not so dangerous as protracted, would for a long time be
                    useless for the performance of war duties; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    also that the army there, while strong enough to garrison a peaceful province,
                    was not so for the war which seemed on the point of breaking out. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> The senate thereupon decreed that Quintus Fulvius
                    Flaccus should enlist five thousand <pb n="p.121"/> infantry and four hundred
                    cavalry, and should see <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 215</note> to it that that legion should be transported to Sardinia at
                    the first opportunity; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> also that he should
                    send whomever he thought best with full authority, to carry on the war until
                    Mucius should recover. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For that duty Titus
                    Manlius Torquatus was sent, a man who had been consul twice and censor, and in
                    his consulship had conquered the Sardinians. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In his first consulship, <date when="-0235">235
                            B.C.</date> ; cf. xxii. 7. </note>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> About the same time a fleet which had been
                    sent from Carthage also to Sardinia, under command of the Hasdrubal who was
                    surnamed Calvus, was damaged by a terrible storm and driven to the Balearic
                    Islands. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> And there the ships were beached, to
                    such an extent had not only the rigging but also the hulls been injured; and
                    while undergoing repairs they caused a considerable loss of time. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Italy, while the war was less active after
                    the battle of Cannae, since the resources of one side had been broken and the
                    spirit of the other sapped, the Campanians attempted without assistance to
                    reduce the state of Cumae to subjection, at first tempting them to revolt from
                    the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When that failed, they contrived a
                    ruse to entrap them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All the Campanians had a
                    regular sacrifice at Hamae. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> To the
                        north-east of Cumae. An inscription gives some clue to its location. </note>
                    To it they informed the men of Cumae that the Campanian senate would come, and
                    requested that the senate of Cumae should come thither to deliberate together,
                    so that both peoples might have the same allies and enemies. They said they
                    would have an armed guard there, lest there be any danger from the Roman or the
                    Carthaginian. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Cumaeans, though they had
                    suspected guile, made no objections, thinking that a ruse of their own <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Their plan to aid the consul against the
                        Campanians.</note> to outwit them could thus be concealed. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.123"/>
                <p> Meanwhile Tiberius Sempronius, the Roman consul, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> after reviewing his army
                    at Sinuessa, at which place he had announced a date for mobilization, crossed
                    the river Volturnus and pitched camp near Liternum. There, since the permanent
                    camp lacked occupation, he required the soldiers to manœuvre frequently, that
                    the recruits —they <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> were most of the
                    slave-volunteers —might learn to follow the standards and to recognize their own
                    ranks in the battle-line. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In this it was the
                    commander's greatest care, and he had instructed the lieutenants and tribunes to
                    the same effect, that no reproach of any man's previous lot should sow strife
                    between the different classes of soldiers; that the old soldier should allow
                    himself to be rated with the recruit, the freeman with the slave-volunteer; that
                    they should consider all to whom the Roman people had entrusted its arms and
                    standards as sufficiently honoured and well-born. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He said that the same fortune which had compelled them to
                    do so now compelled them to defend what had been done. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> These injunctions were not given with greater care by the
                    commanders than that with which they were followed by the soldiers. And soon
                    they were all united in a harmony so great that it was almost forgotten from
                    what status each man had been made a soldier. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While Gracchus was thus employed, legates
                    from Cumae reported to him on what mission an embassy had come a few days before
                    from the Campanians, and what answer they had themselves given them; <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> that the festival was to be three days later, and
                    not only would the whole senate be there, but a camp also and a Campanian army.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Gracchus, having ordered the Cumaeans to
                    bring everything from the <pb n="p.125"/> farms into the city and to remain
                    inside the walls, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        215</note> moved his own camp to Cumae the day before the Campanians had
                    their regular sacrifice. Hamae is three miles distant. Already the Campanians in
                    large numbers had gathered there according to agreement. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> And in concealment, not far from there, Marius Alfius, the
                        <hi rend="italics">medix tuticus,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For this Oscan term cf. XXIV. xix.
                        2.</note> that is, the chief magistrate of the Campanians, had his camp,
                    with fourteen thousand armed men, he being decidedly more intent upon preparing
                    the sacrifice and contriving treachery during the same than upon fortifying his
                    camp or upon any task of the soldier. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                    sacrifice took place at night, but it was to be finished before midnight.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Gracchus, thinking he must be in waiting
                    for that moment, placed guards at the gates, that no one might be able to carry
                    away news of his undertaking. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> And having
                    assembled his soldiers as early as the tenth hour of the day, he ordered them to
                    get themselves in condition and take care to sleep, so that, as soon as it was
                    dark, they might come together at the signal; and at about the first watch he
                    ordered that the standards be taken up. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> And
                    setting out with a silent column, he reached Hamae at midnight and entered the
                    Campanian camp by all its gates at once; for, as was to be expected in view of
                    the vigil, it was carelessly guarded. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Some
                    they slew as they lay asleep, others as they were returning unarmed after the
                    rite had been completed. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> More than two
                    thousand men were slain in that affray by night, including Marius Alfius, the
                    commander himself. Captured were . . . thousand men <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The large number makes the correctness of <hi
                            rend="italics">capta</hi> (sc. <hi rend="italics">milia</hi> ) doubtful;
                        cf. xxxvii. 11. </note> and thirty-four military standards. </p>
                <pb n="p.127"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Gracchus, having captured the camp of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> the enemy
                    with the loss of less than a hundred soldiers, hastily withdrew to Cumae in fear
                    of Hannibal, who had his camp on Mount Tifata above Capua. And he was not
                    mistaken in his forecast. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For as soon as the
                    defeat was reported at Capua, Hannibal, thinking he would find the army of
                    recruits, largely slaves, at Hamae gloating for once over a success, spoiling
                    the defeated and driving off the booty, rushed his column with all speed past
                    Capua, and ordered that those of the fleeing <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    Campanians whom he met should be furnished with an escort and led to Capua, and
                    the wounded carried on wagons. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As for himself,
                    he found at Hamae a camp deserted by the enemy, and nothing except the traces of
                    recent slaughter and corpses of his allies scattered everywhere. Some advised
                    him to lead his troops away forthwith to Cumae and to attack the city.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although Hannibal was very eager to do so,
                    in order that he might <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> have Cumae at least
                    as a seaport, since he had been unable to gain one at Neapolis, nevertheless, as
                    his soldiers in their rapidly moving column had brought out nothing but their
                    arms with them, he withdrew again to his campon Tifata. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Moved by the importunities of the Campanians, he returned
                    thence on the following day to Cumae with all the equipment for besieging the
                    city, and after ravaging the territory of Cumae, pitched his camp a mile from
                    the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Meanwhile Gracchus, ashamed to
                    desert allies in such straits and begging for his help and that of the Roman
                    people, rather than because he had full confidence in his army, had remained
                    there. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor did the other consul, Fabius, who
                    had his camp at Cales, venture to lead his army across the river Volturnus,
                    being <pb n="p.129"/> employed at first in taking new auspices and then <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> with the
                    portents which were being reported one after another. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> And as he was making expiation, the soothsayers kept
                    repeating their opinion that it was not easy to obtain favourable omens. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these reasons detained Fabius,
                    Sempronius was blockaded and already beset by siege-works. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As a defence against a great wooden tower which was moved
                    up to the city, the Roman consul reared from the wall itself another tower
                    considerably higher. For he had used the wall, which in itself was quite high,
                    as a base, shoring it up with stout timbers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    From that tower the defenders first held the wall and the city by hurling stones
                    and stakes and every other missile. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Finally,
                    seeing that the enemy's tower had been pushed close against the wall, they
                    hurled a vast amount of fire all at once from their blazing torches. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> While great numbers of armed men, alarmed by the
                    fire, were leaping down from the tower, a sally out of two gates of the town at
                    the same time routed the enemy's guards and sent them in flight to the camp, so
                    that on that day the Carthaginian resembled a besieged army more than a
                    besieger. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About one thousand and three hundred
                    were slain and fifty-nine captured alive of the Carthaginians, who were relaxing
                    and idling along the walls and <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> at
                    guard-posts, and, having feared anything rather than a sally, had unexpectedly
                    been overpowered. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Gracchus, before the enemy
                    could recover from their sudden fright, gave the signal for the recall and
                    withdrew his men inside the walls. On the next day Hannibal, supposing that the
                    consul, elated by success, would engage in a regular battle, drew up his line
                    between the camp and the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.131"/> But on seeing that no one stirred from the usual <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> defence of
                    the city and that nothing was entrusted to a rash hope, he returned with nothing
                    accomplished to Tifata. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the same time that the siege of Cumae was
                    raised, Tiberius Sempronius, surnamed Longus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This Sempronius was consul with P. Scipio in <date
                            when="-0218">218 B.C.</date> , and defeated by Hannibal at the Trebia;
                        XXI. vi. 3 and liv ff. </note> also fought successfully in Lucania, near
                    Grumentum, with Hanno the Carthaginian. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He
                    slew above two thousand men, and captured two hundred and eighty soldiers and
                    some forty-one military standards. Driven out of Lucanian territory, Hanno
                    withdrew into the land of the Bruttians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And
                    three towns of the Hirpini, Vercellium, Vescellium and Sicilinum, which had
                    revolted from the Roman people, were forcibly recovered by Marcus Valerius, the
                    praetor, and those who had advised revolt were beheaded. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Over five thousand captives were sold at auction; the rest
                    of the booty was given over to the soldiers, and the army led back to Luceria. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were going on in Lucania
                    and among the Hirpini, the five ships which were carrying to Rome the captured
                    ambassadors of the Macedonians and the Carthaginians cruised along nearly the
                    whole coast of Italy from the Upper Sea to the Lower. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> from the Adriatic to the Mare Tuscum; cf. i. 5;
                        xxiv. 8. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And when they were passing Cumae under sail,
                    and it was uncertain whether they belonged to enemies or friends, Gracchus sent
                    ships from his fleet to meet them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When in the
                    course of questioning on both sides it was learned that the consul was at Cumae,
                    the ships put in at Cumae and the prisoners were brought before the consul and
                    the letters handed over to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul,
                    after reading the letters of Philip and Hannibal, sent everything under seal by
                    land to the senate, and ordered the <pb n="p.133"/> ambassadors to be carried on
                    the ships. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Letters <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> and ambassadors arrived at
                    Rome on about the same day, and upon enquiry their words and the texts were in
                    agreement. Thereupon the senators were at first gravely concerned, seeing how
                    serious a war with Macedonia threatened, at a time when they could scarcely
                    endure that with the Carthaginians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However,
                    they were so far from giving way to that concern that they at once discussed how
                    by actual aggressive warfare they might keep the enemy away from Italy.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The prisoners were ordered put in chains,
                    their attendants were sold at auction, and it was decreed that, in addition to
                    the twenty-five ships which Publius Valerius Flaccus commanded as admiral,
                    twenty-five others should be made ready. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    latter being now ready and launched, with the addition of the five ships which
                    had brought the ambassadors as captives, thirty ships sailed from Ostia for
                    Tarentum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And Publius Valerius was ordered to
                    put on board the soldiers who had been Varro's, and at Tarentum were commanded
                    by Lucius Apustius, the lieutenant, and then with a fleet of fifty-five <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The total should be fifty; the five
                        which carried the captives are counted twice; cf. xxxiv. 9. </note> ships
                    not merely to defend the coast of Italy, but to get information in regard to the
                    Macedonian war. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If the designs of Philip
                    should agree with the letters and with the statements of the ambassadors, then
                    he was to inform Marcus Valerius, the praetor, by letter; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> and Valerius, after placing his lieutenant, Lucius
                    Apustius, in command of the army, was to proceed to the fleet at Tarentum, and
                    as soon as possible to cross into Macedonia and take steps to keep Philip within
                    his kingdom. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For the maintenance of the fleet
                    and for the Macedonian war there was voted the money which had been sent to
                    Appius Claudius in Sicily, to <pb n="p.135"/> be repaid to king Hiero. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Pay for the soldiers had been lent by
                        him in the previous year; cf. xxi. 5. His successor presently took the
                        Carthaginian side; XXIV. vi f. </note> This money was carried <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> to
                    Tarentum by Lucius Antistius, the lieutenant. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    At the same time two hundred thousand pecks of wheat and a hundred thousand of
                    barley were sent by Hiero. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the Romans were engaged in these
                    preparations and activities, the one captured ship escaped while under weigh
                    from those which had been sent to Rome, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. xxxiv. 8 f.</note> and returned to Philip.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thus it became known that the ambassadors
                    had been captured with the letter. And so the king, not knowing what had been
                    agreed upon between his ambassadors and Hannibal, and what message the latter's
                    ambassadors were to have brought to him, sent another embassy with the same
                    instructions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As ambassadors to Hannibal there
                    were sent Heraclitus, surnamed Scotinus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This term ( <quote>The Obscure</quote> ) had been
                        applied to the early philosopher of Ephesus of the same name, <hi
                            rend="italics">ca.</hi>
                        <date when="-0500">500 B.C.</date> A pointless marginal note may have got
                        into the text here, displacing the adjective of place which would be
                        expected with this unknown Heraclitus. </note> and Crito, the Boeotian, and
                    Sositheus, of Magnesia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These succeeded in
                    carrying and in bringing back instructions; but the summer was over before the
                    king could make any active preparations. So effectual was the capture of a
                    single ship and ambassadors in postponing a war which threatened the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Also in the vicinity of Capua both consuls
                    were carrying on the war, now that Fabius, after finally making atonement for
                    the prodigies, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Mentioned in xxxi.
                        15.</note> had crossed the Volturnus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    cities of Combulteria and Trebula and Austicula, which had revolted to the
                    Carthaginian, were forcibly taken by Fabius, and in them Hannibal's garrisons
                    and very many Campanians were captured. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And at
                    Nola, just as in the previous year, the senate sided with the Romans, the common
                    people with Hannibal, and secret plans were being formed for the <pb n="p.137"/>
                    murder of the leading men and the betrayal of the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> city. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> That their undertaking should go no farther, Fabius led his
                    army between Capua and the camp of Hannibal, which was on Tifata, and
                    established himself above Suessula in the Claudian Camp. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. xxxi. 3 and 5; xlvi. 9.</note> From there he sent
                    Marcus Marcellus, the propraetor, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Really proconsul; cf. xxx. 18; xxxii. 2; xlviii. 2.</note> with the forces
                    which he had to Nola, to serve as a garrison. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And in Sardinia under the direction of Titus
                    Manlius, the praetor <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Acting in place
                        of the regular praetor; cf. xxxiv. 15.</note> the operations which had been
                    neglected ever since Quintus Mucius, the praetor, was attacked by a serious
                    malady, were resumed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Manlius, after beaching
                    his warships at Carales and arming their crews, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Regularly called <hi rend="italics">socii navales,</hi>
                        from the time when seamen and oarsmen were allies, while the soldiers on
                        board were Romans. </note> in order to wage war on land, and receiving an
                    army from the praetor, made up a total of twenty-two thousand infantry and
                    twelve hundred cavalry. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> With these cavalry and
                    infantry forces he set out for the enemy's territory and pitched camp not far
                    from the camp of Hampsicora. At that time Hampsicora, as it happened, had gone
                    to the region of the Skin-clad Sardinians, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> An earlier population living in the mountainous
                        interior of the island and wearing goat-skins. </note> to arm their young
                    men, in order to enlarge his forces. His son named Hostus was in command of the
                    camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He with the overconfidence of youth
                    rashly went into battle, was routed and put to flight. About three thousand
                    Sardinians were slain in that battle, some eight hundred taken alive. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The rest of the army, at first wandering in flight
                    through the farms and woods, then fled to the place to which it was reported
                    that the commander had fled, a city named Cornus, the capital of that region.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And the war in Sardinia would have been
                    ended by that battle, had not the <pb n="p.139"/> Carthaginian fleet commanded
                    by Hasdrubal, which <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        215</note> had been carried by a storm to the Balearic Islands, arrived at
                    the right moment to revive hopes for the rebellion. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Manlius, when the arrival of the Punic fleet was reported,
                    withdrew to Carales. By so doing he gave Hampsicora the opportunity to unite
                    with the Carthaginian. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, after
                    landing his forces and sending the fleet back to Carthage, set out with
                    Hampsicora as his guide to lay waste the lands of allies of the Roman people.
                    And he would have reached Carales, had not Manlius by confronting him with an
                    army restrained him from his widespread devastation. At first camp faced camp at
                    no great distance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then charges led to
                    skirmishes with varying results. Finally they went into line of battle. With
                    standards against standards they fought a regular engagement for four hours.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For a long time the Carthaginians made
                    the issue uncertain, while the Sardinians were used to being easily defeated.
                    Finally, when the slain and the fleeing Sardinians had covered the whole field,
                    the Carthaginians also were routed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But when
                    they tried to flee, the Roman general hemmed them in by a flank movement of the
                    wing with which he had beaten back the Sardinians. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> It was a slaughter after that, rather than a battle. Twelve
                    thousand of the enemy were slain, Sardinians and Carthaginians reckoned
                    together. About three thousand seven hundred were captured, and twenty-seven
                    military standards. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> What more than all made it a famous and
                    memorable battle was the capture of Hasdrubal, the commander, and Hanno and
                    Mago, Carthaginian nobles, Mago being of the Barca <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> family and nearly related to Hannibal, while Hanno had
                    advised the <pb n="p.141"/> Sardinians to rebel and had undoubtedly fomented
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> that
                    war. And the Sardinians' generals made the battle no less notable by their
                    deaths. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For Hostus, the son of Hampsicora,
                    fell in battle, and also Hampsicora as he fled with a few horsemen, on hearing,
                    not of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the defeat only, but also of the
                    death of his son, took his own life, doing this at night, that no one might come
                    upon him and interfere with his attempt. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For
                    all the rest the same city of Cornus was a place of refuge, as before. Manlius
                    with his victorious army attacked it and took it within a few days. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Then other cities also which had revolted to
                    Hampsicora and the Carthaginians gave hostages and surrendered. From these
                    cities Manlius exacted tribute and grain in proportion to the resources of each
                    or its guilt, and led his army back to Carales. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> There he launched his warships, took on board the soldiers he had brought
                    with him, sailed for Rome, and reported to the senate the complete subjugation
                    of Sardinia. He also turned over the tribute to the quaestors, the grain to the
                    aediles, the captives to Quintus Fulvius, the praetor. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About the same time Titus Otacilius, the
                    praetor, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Here = <hi rend="italics"
                            >praefectus,</hi> commander of the fleet. </note> sailed with his fleet
                    from Lilybaeum across to Africa, and after laying waste the country about
                    Carthage, was steering thence toward Sardinia, to which it was reported that
                    Hasdrubal had recently crossed from the Balearic Islands, when he encountered
                    the fleet returning to Africa; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and in a slight
                    engagement fought in open water he captured seven of their ships together with
                    their crews. The rest were widely scattered by their fear quite as much as they
                    had been by the storm. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.143"/>
                <p> About the same time, moreover, as it happened, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> Bomilcar arrived at Locri
                    with the soldiers sent as reinforcements from Carthage and with elephants and
                    supplies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In order to take him unawares
                    Appius Claudius, with the pretence of making the round of his province, led his
                    army in haste to Messana, and with wind and current in his favour crossed over
                    to Locri. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Already Bomilcar had left that
                    place, to join Hanno among the Bruttii, and the Locrians closed their gates
                    against the Romans. Appius, having accomplished nothing by his great effort,
                    returned to Messana. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The same summer Marcellus from Nola, which he
                    held with a garrison, made frequent raids into the country of the Hirpini and
                    the Samnites about Caudium and laid waste the whole <milestone n="14??"
                        unit="section"/> region with fire and sword so completely that he revived
                    the Samnites' memory of their old disasters. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In the Samnite Wars, as narrated in books VII to X,
                        especially their defeats at Suessula, <date when="-0343">343 B.C.</date> ,
                        and at Sentinum, 295. </note>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accordingly ambassadors were sent at once to
                    Hannibal from both tribes, and they addressed the Carthaginian thus: <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The speech is, of course, that of their
                        leader.</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> We were enemies of the Roman people, Hannibal, at first by ourselves, so
                        long as our arms and our resources were able to defend us. When we had lost
                        confidence in these, we attached ourselves to Pyrrhus, the king. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Abandoned by him we accepted an inevitable peace,
                        and have remained in that peace for about fifty years, down to the time when
                        you came to Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is not more your
                        courage and success than your singular kindness and consideration toward our
                        citizens, whom you captured and then sent back to us, that so won us over to
                        you that, so long as you were a friend safe and sound, we not only did not
                        fear the Roman people, but not even the anger of the gods, if it is right to
                        say so. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But in fact, <pb n="p.145"/> while
                        you are not merely safe and victorious, but also <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> here present, although
                        you could almost hear the wailing of our wives and children and could see
                        the blazing houses, we have been so ravaged several times this summer that
                        Marcus Marcellus, not Hannibal, appears to have been the victor at Cannae,
                        and the Romans are boasting that you, having strength for but a single
                        stroke, are inactive, as if you had spent your sting. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> For a hundred years we waged war with the Roman people,
                        unaided either by commander or army from abroad, except that for two years
                        Pyrrhus did not so much defend us with his resources as enlarge these by
                        adding our soldiers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I shall not boast of
                        our successes, that two consuls and two consular armies were sent under the
                        yoke by us, nor of any other events which have brought us either joy or
                        fame. But the hardships and defeats which then befel us we can relate with
                        less indignation than the things that are happening today. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Great dictators <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">E.g.</hi> Papirius Cursor, VIII. xxix ff.; again IX.
                            xxxviii; five times consul. </note> and masters of the horse, two
                        consuls and two consular armies, used each time to enter our territory.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After first reconnoitring and posting
                        reserves, and in regular array they would lead out for a raid. But now we
                        are the prey of a single propraetor <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> In disparagement of Marcellus, a proconsul; cf.
                            xliii. 12. </note> and a small garrison assigned to the defence of Nola.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Already they roam over our whole
                        territory, not even in maniples, but after the manner of brigands, with less
                        caution than if they were wandering in the country around Rome. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The reason moreover is this: that you are not
                        defending us, and at the same time our young men, who would be protecting us
                        if they were at home, are all serving under your standards. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> I should be unacquainted both with you and your
                        army if I were not to hold <pb n="p.147"/> it easy for one who, I know, has
                        routed and laid low <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                            >B.C. 215</note> so many Roman battle-lines to surprise our scattered
                        plunderers, roaming without their standards wherever a man is drawn by even
                        the vain hope of booty. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> To a few
                        Numidians they will in any case fall a prey, and you will have sent us
                        troops and at the same time will have rid Nola of its garrison, if only men
                        whom you have considered worthy to be your allies are not judged by you
                        unworthy to be taken under your protection and defended. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this Hannibal replied that the Hirpini and
                    Samnites were doing everything at once, reporting their losses, and asking for
                    troops, and complaining that they were undefended and neglected. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> But they ought first to have reported, then asked for
                    protection, finally, if this was not obtained, they should then, and not sooner,
                    have complained that help had been besought in vain. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He would lead his army, not into the territory of the
                    Hirpini or the Samnites, in order not to be another burden, but into the nearest
                    lands of allies of the Roman people. By devastating these he would satisfy his
                    own army and drive the frightened enemy to a distance from them. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> As for the Roman war, if the battle of Lake
                    Trasumennus was more celebrated than that of the Trebia, if Cannae than
                    Trasumennus, he would overshadow the memory even of Cannae by a greater and more
                    famous victory. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With this answer and also with ample gifts he
                    sent the ambassadors away. He himself set out, leaving a moderate force on
                    Tifata, and proceeded with the rest of his army to Nola. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Hanno also came thither from the land of the Bruttii with
                    reinforcements brought from Carthage and with the elephants. <pb n="p.149"/>
                    Having pitched his camp not far away, Hannibal <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> found on enquiry that
                    everything was very different from what he had heard from the legates of his
                    allies. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For Marcellus had not done anything in
                    such a way that it could be said to have been left to fortune or rashly left to
                    the enemy. After reconnoitring, having strong forces and a safe refuge, he had
                    gone out to forage, and every possible precaution had been taken, as though
                    against Hannibal in person. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then on learning
                    of the approach of the enemy, he kept his troops inside the walls. He ordered
                    the senators of Nola to walk up and down on the walls, and to observe everything
                    that went on among the enemy all around. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Hanno, having come close to the wall, called out from their number Herennius
                    Bassus and Herius Pettius to a conference, and when they came out with
                    Marcellus' permission, he addressed them through an interpreter. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> He lauded Hannibal's courage and success. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> He belittled the majesty of the Roman people, as
                    wasting away along with their resources. And if these qualities were evenly
                    matched, he said, as once they had been, nevertheless those who had found out
                    how burdensome was Roman rule to the allies, how great had been Hannibal's
                    indulgence even to all captives who called themselves Italians, these were bound
                    to prefer Carthaginian alliance and friendship to Roman. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> If both consuls were at Nola with their armies, still they
                    would be no more a match for Hannibal than they had been at Cannae; much less
                    could one praetor with a few raw soldiers defend Nola. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> It was their own concern more than Hannibal's whether he
                    took Nola by capture or by surrender. For he would take it, as he had taken
                    Capua and Nuceria. But what a difference <pb n="p.151"/> there was between the
                    lot of Capua and that of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 215</note> Nuceria the men of Nola themselves knew, being situated
                    about half-way between them. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He did not wish
                    to forecast what would happen to the city if captured, but assured them instead
                    that if they surrendered Marcellus and Nola with the garrison, no one but
                    themselves should name the terms on which they might enter alliance and
                    friendship with Hannibal. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this Herennius Bassus replied that for many
                    years there had been friendship between the Roman people and that of Nola; that
                    down to that time neither party regretted it, and for themselves, if with
                    altered fortune they ought to have changed their loyalty, it was now too late to
                    change. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If they were going to surrender to
                    Hannibal, had they needed to send for a Roman garrison? With the men who had
                    come to defend them they had allied themselves in everything, and it would be so
                    to the end. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This conference deprived Hannibal of the hope
                    of getting Nola by treachery. And so he completely invested the town, in order
                    to attack the walls from all sides at once. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Marcellus, on seeing that Hannibal had approached the walls, drew up his line
                    inside the gate and sallied out with a great uproar. Not a few were terrified by
                    the first attack and slain. Then, when they had charged the attacking force and
                    brought up equal numbers, the battle began to be a fierce one, and would have
                    been among the most memorable, if a downpour of rain in heavy squalls had not
                    separated the combatants. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That day, after
                    beginning an engagement of no importance and merely inflaming their passions,
                    they withdrew, the Romans into the city, the Carthaginians to the camp. For of
                        <pb n="p.153"/> the Carthaginians not more than thirty, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The small number is probably an error of
                        the copyists.</note> who were <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 215</note> terrified by the first sally, fell, of the
                    Romans fifty. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The rain continued incessantly
                    throughout the night to the third hour of the next day. And so, although both
                    sides were eager for the fray, they nevertheless kept within their
                    fortifications that day. </p>
                <p> On the third day Hannibal sent a part of his forces into the country about Nola
                    to plunder. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On observing this Marcellus at
                    once drew up his troops in line. And Hannibal did not refuse battle. There was
                    about a mile between the city and the camp. In that space —and there is only a
                    plain around Nola —they met each other. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A
                    shout raised on both sides recalled to a battle already begun the nearest men of
                    the cohorts which had gone out to the farms for booty. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> And the men of Nola reinforced the Roman line. Marcellus
                    praised them and ordered them to keep their place among the reserves and to
                    carry off the wounded from the field; to refrain from fighting unless they
                    should receive a signal from him. <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle was doubtful. The generals were
                    doing their utmost in cheering on their men, the soldiers in fighting. Marcellus
                    bids them attack men defeated two days before, driven from Cumae in flight a few
                    days earlier, beaten back from Nola the previous year by himself, the same
                    commander, and other soldiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not all of the
                    enemy, he said, were in the line of battle; the booty-hunters were roaming about
                    the country, and those who were fighting were weakened by Campanian luxury,
                    exhausted by wine and harlots and every kind of dissipation the whole winter
                    through. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Gone was that force and energy, lost
                    the strength of body and spirit with which they had crossed the ranges of the
                    Pyrenees and the Alps. <pb n="p.155"/> Remnants only of those men were fighting,
                    scarcely <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note>
                    able to hold up their weapons and their limbs. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Capua had been Hannibal's Cannae. It was there that warlike courage had been
                    extinguished, there the discipline of the soldier, there the past reputation,
                    there the hope for the future. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While by thus
                    reviling the enemy Marcellus was raising the spirits of his soldiers, Hannibal
                    was uttering much more serious reproaches; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> he
                    recognized the same arms and standards which he had seen and had at the Trebia
                    and Trasumennus, finally at Cannae; but as for the soldier, he had certainly led
                    one man into winter quarters at Capua, and out of them a different man.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Are you,</quote> he said, <quote> hardly able with great effort to hold
                        out against a mere Roman lieutenant, <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified">Again disparagement of Marcellus, as in xlii.
                            10.</note> and an engagement with a single legion and its auxiliaries
                        —you, whom two consular armies combined have never withstood? <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Marcellus with recruits and with reserves from
                        Nola is now attacking us for the second time with impunity! Where is that
                        soldier of mine who pulled Gaius Flaminius, the consul, down from his horse
                        and carried away his head? <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A
                            somewhat different account in XXII. vi. 4.</note> Where the man who slew
                        Lucius Paulus at Cannae? <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXII.
                            xlix. 12.</note> Is the sword now blunted? Or are your right hands
                        benumbed? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Or is it some other portent? You
                        who, though few, were wont to defeat larger numbers, now in larger numbers
                        with difficulty resist the few? You used to boast, brave men in speech, that
                        if some one led you, you would take Rome by storm. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Look you, in a less difficult situation, here and now I
                        wish to test your might and courage. Take Nola by storm, a city of the
                        plain, not fenced by a river nor by the sea. From this place, a city of such
                        wealth, I will either lead you, laden with booty and <pb n="p.157"/> spoils,
                        or I will follow you whithersoever you shall <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> desire. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Neither encouragement nor reproaches had any
                    effect in steadying their spirits. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Since they
                    were everywhere beaten back, while the Romans' courage rose, as not only the
                    general exhorted them, but the men of Nola also kindled their ardour for battle
                    by shouting as evidence of their support, the Carthaginians retreated and were
                    forced back into the camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman soldiers
                    were eager to assault the camp, but Marcellus led them back to Nola, in the
                    midst of great rejoicing and congratulation on the part of the common people as
                    well, who had previously been more inclined to the Carthaginians. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Of the enemy more than five thousand were slain that
                    day, six hundred captured alive, and nineteen military standards and two
                    elephants were taken, four killed in battle. Of the Romans less than a thousand
                    were slain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next day they spent under a
                    tacit armistice, burying those slain in the battle on both sides. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Marcellus burned the spoils of the enemy, paying a
                    vow to Vulcan. Two days later in anger on some account, I suppose, or in the
                    hope of a more generous service, two hundred and seventy-two horsemen, partly
                    Numidians, partly Spaniards, deserted to Marcellus. Their brave and loyal
                    services were repeatedly employed by the Romans in that war. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As a reward for their courage farm land was given after the
                    war to the Spaniards in Spain, to the Numidians in Africa. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hannibal, sending Hanno back from Nola into
                    the country of the Bruttii with the forces with which he had come, himself
                    sought winter quarters in Apulia and established himself near Arpi. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius, <pb n="p.159"/> on hearing that
                    Hannibal had gone into Apulia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 215</note> brought in grain from Nola and Neapolis to the
                    camp above Suessula, strengthened the fortifications, and left a garrison which
                    was strong enough to hold the place through the winter season. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> He then moved his camp nearer to Capua and ravaged the
                    Campanian territory with fire and sword, until the Campanians, who had no
                    confidence at all in their own resources, were compelled to come out of the
                    gates and fortify a camp in the open before the city. They had six thousand
                    armed men, infantry unfit for war; but in cavalry they were more effective.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly they kept harassing the enemy
                    by cavalry battles. </p>
                <p> Among the many distinguished Campanian horsemen was Cerrinus Vibellius, surnamed
                    Taurea. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A citizen of that state, he was far
                    the bravest horseman of all the Campanians, so much so that while he served with
                    the Romans only one Roman, Claudius Asellus, rivalled him in reputation as a
                    cavalryman. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At this time Taurea, looking all
                    around again and again, rode up to the squadrons of the enemy's cavalry and,
                    when silence was at last obtained, asked where Claudius Asellus was, and why,
                    since he had been in the <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> habit of disputing
                    with him about their courage, did he not settle the matter with the sword and,
                    if vanquished, give, or if victorious, take, the splendid spoils. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Strictly speaking the <hi
                            rend="italics">opima spolia</hi> were those taken by a Roman general in
                        command from the general of the enemy after a single combat; I. x. 4-7
                        (Romulus); IV. xx. 2 and 5-6 (Cossus); <hi rend="italics">Periocha</hi> 20
                        (Marcellus). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this was reported to Asellus in the camp,
                    he waited only to ask the consul whether he might fight out of the ranks against
                    an enemy who <pb n="p.161"/> challenged him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    With the consul's permission he at <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 215</note> once took up his arms, and riding out in front
                    of the guard-posts he addressed Taurea by name and bade him engage wherever he
                    pleased. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Already the Romans had gone out in
                    crowds to that spectacle of a combat, and the Campanians who looked on had
                    filled not only the earthwork of the camp but also the walls of the city. First
                    calling attention to the affair by high-spirited words, they levelled spears and
                    spurred their horses. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then, dodging each other
                    in the open space, they prolonged the bloodless fray. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Then the Campanian said to the Roman: <quote> This will be
                        a contest of horses, not of horsemen, unless we let our horses go down from
                        the open field into this deep-cut road. There, with no room to avoid each
                        other, we shall fight hand to hand. </quote> Almost sooner than said
                    Claudius put his horse into the road. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Taurea,
                    more spirited in words than in action, said: <quote>Never a nag, please, into a
                        ditch!</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> To be supplied is a verb, probably
                            <hi rend="italics">demiseris.</hi> Colloquial <hi rend="italics"
                            >sis</hi> (= <hi rend="italics">si vis,</hi> an insistent
                            <quote>please</quote> ) merely strengthens the prohibition. </note>
                    —words which have come down from that time as a farmer's parable. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Claudius rode a long way on that road, and then
                    riding back to the field without meeting any enemy, returned as victor to the
                    camp, reviling the cowardice of his enemy in the midst of great rejoicing and
                    congratulations. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To this combat of horsemen
                    some annals add what is certainly marvellous —how true, it is for everyone to
                    judge —that, as Claudius was pursuing Taurea fleeing to the city, he rode in
                    through the enemy's open gate and, while they were spellbound in amazement,
                    escaped unharmed by the opposite gate. </p>
                <pb n="p.163"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thereafter the winter quarters were <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note>
                    undisturbed, and the consul moved his camp back again, that the Campanians might
                    do their sowing. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The time is early
                        autumn.</note> And he did not ravage the Campanian country until the growing
                    grain in the fields was tall enough to furnish fodder. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This he transported to the Claudian Camp above Suessula and
                    there built winter barracks. He ordered Marcus Claudius, the proconsul, to keep
                    at Nola only the garrison needed to defend the city, and to send away the rest
                    of the soldiers to Rome, lest they be a burden to the allies and an expense to
                    the state. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And Tiberius Gracchus, after
                    leading his legions from Cumae to Luceria in Apulia, sent thence Marcus
                    Valerius, the praetor, to Brundisium with the army which he had had at Luceria,
                    and ordered him to defend the coast of the Sallentine region <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the extreme south of Calabria; XXIV.
                        xx. 16; XXV. i. 1. </note> and to take measures concerning Philip and the
                    Macedonian war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the end of the summer in which occurred the
                    events I have described, there came a letter from Publius and Gnaeus Scipio,
                    reporting how great and how successful had been their operations in Spain; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">As told in XXII. xxii. and XXIII. xxvi
                        ff.</note> but that money for pay, also clothing and grain, were lacking for
                    the army, and for the crews everything. So far as pay was concerned, if the
                    treasury was empty, they would find some method of getting it from the
                    Spaniards. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Everything else, they said, must in
                    any case be sent from Rome, and in no other way could either the army or the
                    province be kept. After the reading of the letter, there was no one among them
                    all <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the senators present. </note> who did not admit
                    that the statements were true and the demands fair. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But they reflected what great forces on land and sea they
                    were maintaining, and how large a new fleet must soon be made ready <pb
                        n="p.165"/> if a Macedonian war should begin; that Sicily and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> Sardinia,
                    which before the war had paid taxes in kind, were hardly feeding the armies that
                    garrisoned those provinces; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that necessary
                    expenses were met only by the property tax; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">A direct tax paid by Roman citizens.</note> that the
                    number of those who paid that particular tax had been diminished by such great
                    losses of troops at Lake Trasumennus and also at Cannae; that if the few who
                    survived should be burdened by a much greater levy, they would perish by another
                    malady. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And so they thought that, unless
                    support should be found in credit, the <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> state
                    would not be sustained by its assets; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that
                    Fulvius, the praetor, must go before the assembly, inform the people of the
                    public needs and exhort those who by contracts had increased their property to
                    allow the state, the source of <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> their
                    wealth, time for payment, and to contract for furnishing what was needed for the
                    army in Spain, on the condition that they should be the first to be paid, as
                    soon as there was money in the treasury. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To
                    this effect the praetor addressed the people, and named a date on which he would
                    let the contracts for furnishing clothing and grain to the army in Spain and
                    whatever else was needed for the crews. <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When that day came, three companies of
                    nineteen members presented themselves to take the contracts. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And their demands were two: one, that they should be exempt
                    from military duty so long as they were in that public service, the other, that
                    the cargoes which they shipped should be at the risk of the state, so far as
                    concerned the violence of enemies and of storms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Both demands being obtained, they contracted, and the state was carried on by
                    private funds. Such character and such love of country pervaded all the classes
                    virtually without <pb n="p.167"/> exception. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    As all the supplies were magnanimously <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 215</note> contracted for, so they were delivered with
                    great fidelity, and nothing was furnished to the soldiers less generously than
                    if they were being maintained, as formerly, out of an ample treasury. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When these supplies arrived, the town of
                    Iliturgi, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In southern Spain, on the
                        upper course of the Baetis (Guadalquivir), destroyed by Scipio Africanus in
                            <date when="-0206">206 B.C.</date> ; XXVIII. xx. </note> because of its
                    revolt to the Romans, was being besieged by Hasdrubal and Mago and Hannibal, the
                    son of Bomilcar. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Between these three camps of
                    the enemy the Scipios made their way into a city of their allies with great
                    effort and great loss to those that opposed them. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And they brought grain, of which it had no supply, and
                    encouraged the townspeople to defend their walls with the same spirit with which
                    they had seen the Roman army fighting for them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Then they led their troops to an attack upon the largest camp, which
                    Hasdrubal commanded. To it also came the other two generals and two armies of
                    the Carthaginians, seeing that the whole issue was at stake there. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly a sally from the camp opened the battle.
                    Sixty thousand of the enemy were in the battle that day, about sixteen thousand
                    on the Roman side. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Yet so far was the victory
                    from being uncertain that <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> the Romans slew
                    more than their own number, captured more than three thousand men, a little less
                    than a thousand horses, fifty-nine military standards, seven elephants, five
                    having been slain in battle. And they took the three camps that day. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> The siege of Iliturgi having been raised, the
                    Carthaginian armies were led over to attack Intibili, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Apparently not far from Iliturgi; cf. Frontinus II.
                        iii. 1. The only town of this name of which we hear elsewhere was on the
                        east coast south of the Hiberus (Ebro). </note> while their forces were
                    recruited from a province which, more than any <pb n="p.169"/> other, was eager
                    for war, if only there was booty or <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 215</note> pay, and at that time was well supplied with
                    young men. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A second time there was a battle
                    in regular line, with the same result for each side. Over thirteen thousand of
                    the enemy were slain, over two thousand captured, with forty-two standards and
                    nine elephants. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then indeed nearly all the
                    peoples of Spain revolted to the Romans, and there were much greater
                    achievements that summer in Spain than in Italy. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
