<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 23</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="book">
                <head>Hannibal at Capua</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately after the battle of Cannae and
                        the capture and plunder of the Roman camp, Hannibal moved out of Apulia into
                        Samnium, in consequence of an invitation he had received from a man named
                        Statius Trebius, who promised to hand over Compsa to him if he would visit
                        the territory of the Hirpini. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Trebius was
                        a native of Compsa, a man of note amongst his people, but his influence was
                        less than that of the faction of the Mopsii, a family which owed its
                        predominance to the favour and support of Rome. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> After the report of the battle of Cannae had reached
                        the town, and Trebius was telling everybody that Hannibal was coming, the
                        Mopsian party left the city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was then
                        peacefully handed over to the Carthaginian and a garrison placed in it.
                        There Hannibal left all his booty and his baggage, and then forming his army
                        into two divisions, gave Mago the command of one and retained the other
                        himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He gave Mago instructions to
                        receive the submission of the cities in the district which were revolting
                        from Rome and to compel those which were hanging back to revolt, whilst he
                        himself marched through the Campanian district towards the Lower Sea with
                        the view of attacking Neapolis so that he might have a city accessible from
                        the sea. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When he entered the confines of
                        Neapolis he placed some of his Numidians wherever he conveniently could in
                        ambuscade, for the roads are mostly deep, with many unseen windings.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The others he ordered to ride up to
                        the gates driving ostentatiously before them the plunder they had collected
                        from the fields. As they appeared to be a small and disorganised force, a
                        troop of cavalry came out against them, they were drawn on by the retreating
                        Numidians into the ambuscade and surrounded. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> Not a man would have escaped had not the proximity of the sea, and some
                        ships, mostly fishing vessels, which they saw not far from the shore,
                        afforded a means of escape to those who were good swimmers. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Several young nobles, however, were either taken or
                        killed in the skirmish, amongst them Hegeas, the commandant of the cavalry,
                        who fell whilst following the retreating foe too incautiously. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The aspect of the walls deterred the
                        Carthaginian from attacking the city; they by no means offered facilities
                        for an assault. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From there he directed his march towards
                        Capua. This city had become demoralised by a long course of prosperity and
                        the indulgence of Fortune, but most of all by the universal corruption
                        produced by the wild excesses of a populace who exercised their liberty
                        without any restraint. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Pacuvius Calavius
                        had got the senate of Capua entirely in his own power and that of the
                        populace. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was a noble, and at the same
                        time a favourite with the people, but he had gained his influence and power
                        by resorting to base practices. He happened to be chief magistrate in the
                        year in which the defeat at Trasumennus occurred, and knowing the hatred
                        which the populace had long felt towards the senate, he thought it highly
                        probable that they would seize their opportunity, create a violent
                        revolution, and, if Hannibal with his victorious army should visit their
                        neighbourhood, murder the senators and hand over Capua to him. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Bad as the man was, he was not utterly abandoned,
                        since he preferred to play the autocrat in a commonwealth which was
                        constitutionally sound rather than in one that was ruined, and he knew that
                        no political constitution could be sound where there was no council of
                        state. He embarked on a plan by which he could save the senate and at the
                        same time render it completely subservient to himself and to the populace.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He summoned a meeting of the senate
                        and commenced his speech by saying that any idea of a <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> revolt from Rome would have been quite repugnant to him
                        had it not been a necessity, seeing that he had children by the daughter of
                        Appius Claudius and had given his own daughter in marriage to M. Livius in
                        Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "But," he went on, "there is a much
                        more serious and formidable danger impending, for the populace are not
                        simply contemplating beginning their revolt from Rome by banishing the
                        senate from the city, they mean to murder the senators and then hand over
                        the city to Hannibal and the Carthaginians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> It is in my power to save you from this peril if you will put yourselves
                        in my hands, and, forgetting all our past quarrels, trust me." Overcome by
                        their fears they all placed themselves in his hands. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> "I will," he then said, "shut you in your House, and
                        whilst appearing myself to participate in their act by approving of designs
                        which I should in vain attempt to oppose, I will discover a way of safety
                        for you. Take any guarantee in this matter which you please." <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> When he had given the guarantee he went out and
                        ordered the doors to be fastened, and left a guard in the vestibule to
                        prevent any one from entering or leaving without his orders. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next, he called an assembly of the people
                        and addressed them thus: "You have often wished, citizens of Capua, that you
                        had the power to execute summary justice on the unscrupulous and infamous
                        senate. You can do so now safely, and none can call you to account.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> You need not risk your lives in
                        desperate attempts to force the houses of individual senators guarded as
                        they are by their clients and slaves; take them as they now are, locked up
                        in the Senate-house, all by themselves, unarmed. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Do not be in a hurry, do nothing rashly. I will put you
                        in a position to pass sentence of life and death so that each of them in
                        turn may pay the penalty he deserves. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But
                        whatever you do see that you do not go too far in satisfying your feelings
                        of resentment, make the security and welfare of the State your first
                        consideration. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For, as I understand it, it
                        is these particular senators that you hate, you do not want to go without a
                        senate altogether; for you must either have a king which is an abomination,
                        or a senate, which is the only consultative body that can exist in a free
                        commonwealth. So you have to do two things at once, remove the old senate
                        and choose a fresh one. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I shall order the
                        senators to be summoned one by one and I shall take your opinion as to their
                        fate, and whatever decision you arrive at shall be carried out. But before
                        punishment is inflicted on any one found guilty you must choose a strong and
                        energetic man to take his place as senator." <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> He then sat down, and after the names of the senators had been cast into
                        the urn he ordered the man whose name was drawn first to be brought out of
                        the Senate-house. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as they heard
                        the name they all shouted that he was a worthless scoundrel and richly
                        deserved to be punished. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then Pacuvius
                        said: "I see clearly what you think of this man, in place of a worthless
                        scoundrel you must choose a worthy and honest man as senator. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> For a few minutes there was silence as they were
                        unable to suggest a better man. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then one
                        of them, laying aside his diffidence, ventured to suggest a name, and a
                        greater clamour than ever arose. Some said they had never heard of him,
                        others imputed to him shameful vices and humble birth, sordid poverty, and a
                        low class of occupation or trade. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A still
                        more violent demonstration awaited the second and third senators who were
                        summoned, and it was obvious that while they intensely disliked the man,
                        they had no one to put in his place. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It
                        was no use mentioning the same names again and again, for it only led to
                        everything that was bad being said about them and the succeeding names were
                        those of people much more low born and unknown than those which were first
                        suggested. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So the crowd dispersed saying
                        to one another that the evils they were best acquainted with were the
                        easiest to bear. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate had to thank Pacuvius for its
                        life, and it was much more under his control than under that of the
                        populace. By common consent he now wielded supreme power and needed no armed
                        support. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Henceforth the senators,
                        forgetting their rank and independence, flattered the populace, saluted them
                        courteously, invited them as guests, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                        received them at sumptuous banquets, undertook their cases, always appeared
                        on their side, and when they were trying suits they always decided the
                        actions in a way to secure the favour of the mob. In fact, the proceedings
                        in the senate were exactly as though it had been a popular assembly.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The city had always been disposed to
                        luxury and extravagance, not only through the weakness of the character of
                        its citizens, but also through the superabundance of the means of enjoyment
                        and the incitements to every kind of pleasure which land or sea could
                        furnish, and now, owing to the obsequiousness of the nobility and the
                        licence of the populace, it was becoming so demoralised that the sensuality
                        and extravagance which prevailed exceeded all bounds. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They treated the laws, the magistrates, the senate with
                        equal contempt, and now after the defeat of Cannae they <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> began to feel contempt for the one thing which they had
                        hitherto held in some respect-the power of Rome. The only circumstances
                        which prevented them from immediately revolting were the old established
                        right of intermarriage which had led <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> to
                        many of their illustrious and powerful families becoming connected with Rome
                        and the fact that several citizens were serving with the Romans. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The strongest tie of this nature was the presence
                        of three hundred cavalry, from the noblest families in Capua, in Sicily,
                        whither they had been specially sent by the Roman authorities to garrison
                        the island. The parents and relatives of these troopers succeeded after much
                        difficulty in getting envoys sent to the Roman consul. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul had not yet started for
                        Canusium; they found him and his scanty, insufficiently armed force still at
                        Venusia, an object calculated to arouse the deepest compassion in trusty
                        allies, and nothing but contempt amongst arrogant and treacherous ones like
                        the Campanians. The consul made matters worse and increased the contempt
                        felt for himself and his fortunes by revealing too plainly and openly the
                        extent of the disaster. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the envoys
                        assured him that the senate and people of <milestone n="3??" unit="section"
                        /> Capua were much grieved that any mischance had happened to the Romans and
                        expressed their readiness to supply all that was needed for the war, he
                        replied: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "In bidding us requisition from
                        you what we need for the war you have preserved the tone in which we speak
                        to allies instead of suiting your language to the actual state of our
                        circumstances. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For what was left us at
                        Cannae that we should wish what is lacking-as though we still possessed
                        something-to be made up by our allies? Are we to ask you to furnish infantry
                        as though we still possessed any cavalry? Are we to say that we want money,
                        as though that were the only thing we want? Fortune has not even left us
                        anything which we can supplement. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Legions,
                        cavalry, arms, standards, men and horses, money, supplies-all have gone
                        either on the battlefield or when the two camps were lost the following day.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So then, men of Capua, you have not to
                        help us in the war but almost to undertake the war for us. Call to mind how
                        once when your forefathers were driven in hurried flight within their
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> walls in dread of the Sidicine as
                        well as the Samnite we took them under our protection at Saticula, and how
                        the war which then commenced with the Samnites on your behalf was kept up by
                        us with all its changeful fortunes for nearly a century. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Besides all this you must remember that after you had
                        surrendered we gave you a treaty on equal terms, we allowed you to retain
                        your own laws, and-what was, before our defeat at Cannae at all events, the
                        greatest privilege-we granted our citizenship to most of you and made you
                        members of our commonwealth. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Under these
                        circumstances, men of Capua, you ought to realise that you have suffered
                        this defeat as much as we have, and to feel that we have a common country to
                        defend. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It is not with the Samnites or
                        the Etruscans that we have to do; if they deprived us of our power it would
                        still be Italians who would hold it. But the Carthaginian is dragging after
                        him an army that is not even made up of natives of Africa, he has collected
                        a force from the furthest corners of the earth, from the ocean straits, and
                        the Pillars of Hercules, men devoid of any sense of right, destitute of the
                        condition, and almost of the speech of men. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> Savage and barbarous by nature and habit, their general has made them
                        still more brutal by building up bridges and barriers with human bodies
                        and-I shudder to say it-teaching them to feed on human flesh. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> What man, if he were merely a native of Italy,
                        would not be horrified at the thought of looking upon men who feast upon
                        what it is impious even to touch as his lords and masters, looking to Africa
                        and above all to Carthage for his laws, and having to submit to Italy
                        becoming a dependency of the Numidians and the Moors? <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> It will be a splendid thing, men of Capua, if the
                        dominion of Rome, which has collapsed in defeat, should be saved and
                        restored by your loyalty, your strength. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        I think that in Campania you can raise 30,000 infantry and 4000 cavalry; you
                        have already sufficient money and corn. If you show a loyalty corresponding
                        to your means Hannibal will not feel that he has conquered or that the
                        Romans are vanquished." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this speech of the consul's, the
                        envoys were dismissed. As they were on their way home, one of their number,
                        Vibius Virrius, told them that the time had come when the Campanians could
                        not only recover the territory wrongfully taken from them by the Romans, but
                        even achieve the dominion over Italy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                        could make a treaty with Hannibal on any terms they chose, and there was no
                        disputing the fact that when the war was over and Hannibal after his
                        conquest returned with his army to Africa, the sovereignty over Italy would
                        fall to the Campanians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They all agreed
                        with what Virrius said, and they gave such an account of their interview
                        with the consul as to make everybody think that the very name of Rome was
                        blotted out. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The populace and a majority
                        of the senate began at once to prepare for a revolt; it was owing to the
                        exertions of the senior members that the crisis was staved off for a few
                        days. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At last the majority carried their
                        point, and the same envoys who had been to the Roman consul were now sent to
                        Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I find it stated in some
                        annalists that before they started or it was definitely decided to revolt,
                        envoys were sent from Capua to Rome to demand as the condition of their
                        rendering assistance that one consul should be a Campanian, and amidst the
                        indignation which this demand aroused the envoys <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> were ordered to be summarily ejected from the
                        Senate-house, and a lictor told off to conduct them out of the City with
                        orders not to remain a single day on Roman territory. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As, however, this demand is too much like one made by
                        the Latins in earlier times, and Caelius amongst others would not have
                        omitted to mention it without good reason, I will not venture to vouch for
                        the truth of the statement. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys came to Hannibal and negotiated
                        a peace with him on the following terms: No Carthaginian commander or
                        magistrate was to have any jurisdiction over the citizens of Capua nor was
                        any Campanian citizen to be obliged to serve in any military or other
                        capacity against his will; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Capua was to
                        retain its own magistrates and its own laws; and the Carthaginian was to
                        allow them to choose three hundred Romans out of his prisoners of war whom
                        they were to exchange for the Campanian troopers who were serving in Sicily.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These were the terms agreed upon, but
                        the Campanians went far beyond the stipulations in their criminal excesses.
                        The populace seized officers in command of our allies and other Roman
                        citizens, some whilst occupied with their military duties, others whilst
                        engaged in their private business, and ordered them to be shut up in the
                        baths on the presence of keeping them in safe custody; unable to breathe
                        owing to the heat and fumes they died in great agony. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Decius Magius was a man who, if his fellow-citizens had
                        been rational, would have gained very great authority with them. He did his
                        best to prevent these crimes and to stop the envoys from going to Hannibal.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When he heard that troops were being
                        sent by Hannibal to garrison the city, he protested most earnestly against
                        their being admitted and referred, as warning examples, to the tyranny of
                        Pyrrhus and the wretched servitude into which the Tarentines fell.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After they were admitted he urged that
                        they should be expelled, or what was better, if the Capuans wished to clear
                        themselves by a deed which would be remembered from their guilt in revolting
                        from ancient allies and blood-relations, let them put the Carthaginian
                        garrison to death and be once more friends with Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When this was reported to Hannibal-for
                        there was no secrecy about Magius' action-he sent to summon him to his camp.
                        Magius sent a spirited refusal; Hannibal, he said, had no legal authority
                        over a citizen of Capua. The Carthaginian, furious at the rebuff, ordered
                        the man to be thrown into chains and brought to him. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Fearing, however, on second thoughts, that the use of
                        force might create a tumult and feelings once aroused might lead to a sudden
                        outbreak, he sent a message to Marius Blossius, the chief magistrate of
                        Capua, that he would be there on the morrow, and started with a small escort
                        for the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marius called the people
                        together and gave public notice that they should assemble in a body with
                        their wives and children and go to meet Hannibal. The whole population
                        turned out, not because they were ordered, but because the mob were
                        enthusiastic in favour of Hannibal, and were eager to see a commander famous
                        for so many victories. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Decius Magius did
                        not go to meet him, nor did he shut himself up at home, as this might have
                        implied a consciousness of guilt; he strolled leisurely about the Forum with
                        his son and a few of his clients, whilst the whole city was in a state of
                        wild excitement at seeing and welcoming Hannibal. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> When he had entered the city Hannibal asked that the
                        senate should be convened at once. The leading Campanians, however, implored
                        him not to transact any serious business then, but to give himself up to the
                        joyous celebration of a day which had been made such a happy one by his
                        arrival. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Though he was naturally
                        impulsive in his anger, he would not begin with a refusal, and spent most of
                        the day in viewing the city. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He stayed with two brothers, Sthenius and
                        Pacuvius, men distinguished for their high birth and wealth. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Pacuvius Calavius, whom we have already
                        mentioned, the leader of the party which brought the city over to the
                        Carthaginians, brought his young son to the house. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The youth was closely attached to Decius Magius, and
                        had stood up most resolutely with him for the alliance with Rome and against
                        any terms with the Carthaginians, and neither the changing over of the city
                        to the other side nor the authority of his father had been able to shake his
                        resolution. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Pacuvius dragged him away from
                        Magius' side and now sought to obtain Hannibal's pardon for the youth by
                        intercessions rather than by any attempts at exculpation. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He was overcome by the father's prayers and tears and
                        went so far as to order him to be invited to a banquet to which none were to
                        be admitted but his hosts and Vibellius Taureas, a distinguished soldier.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The banquet began early in the day,
                        and was not at all in accordance with Carthaginian customs or military
                        discipline, but as was natural in a city, still more in a house full of
                        wealth and luxury, the table was furnished with every kind of dainty and
                        delicacy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Young Calavius was the only one
                        who could not be persuaded to drink, though his hosts and occasionally
                        Hannibal invited him; he excused himself on the ground of health, and his
                        father alleged as a further reason his not unnatural excitement under the
                        circumstances. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was nearly sunset when
                        the guests rose. Young Calavius accompanied his father out of the banquet
                        chamber and when they had come to a retired spot in the garden behind the
                        house, he stopped and said: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "I have a plan
                        to propose to you, father, by which we shall not only obtain pardon for the
                        Romans for our offence in revolting to Hannibal, but also possess much more
                        influence and prestige in Capua than we have ever done before." <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> When his father asked him in great surprise what
                        his plan was, he threw his toga back from his shoulder and showed him a
                        sword belted on to his side. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "Now," he
                        said, "this very moment will I ratify our treaty with Rome in Hannibal's
                        blood. I wanted you to know first, in case you would rather be away when the
                        deed is done." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The old man, beside himself with terror at
                        what he saw and heard, as though he were actually witnessing the act his son
                        had spoken of, exclaimed: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "I pray and
                        beseech you, my son, by all the sacred bonds which unite parents and
                        children, not to insist upon doing and suffering everything that is horrible
                        before your father's eyes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is only a
                        few hours ago that we pledged our faith, swearing by all the gods and
                        joining hand to hand, and do you want us, when we have just separated after
                        friendly talk, to arm those hands, consecrated by such a pledge, against
                        him? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Have you risen from the hospitable
                        board to which you were invited by Hannibal with only two others out of all
                        Capua that you may stain that board with your host's blood? I, your father,
                        was able to make Hannibal friendly towards my son, am I powerless to make my
                        son friendly towards Hannibal? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But let
                        nothing sacred hold you back, neither the plighted word, nor religious
                        obligation, nor filial affection; dare infamous deeds, if they do not bring
                        ruin as well as guilt upon us. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But what
                        then? Are you going to attack Hannibal single-handed? What of that throng of
                        free men and slaves with all their eyes intent on him alone? <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> What of all those right hands? Will they hang
                        down listlessly during that act of madness? Armed hosts cannot bear even to
                        gaze on the face of Hannibal, the Roman people dread it, and will yon endure
                        it? Though other help be lacking, will you have the courage to strike me, me
                        your father, when I interpose myself to protect Hannibal? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> And yet it is through my breast that you must pierce
                        his. Suffer yourself to be deterred here rather than vanquished there. Let
                        my prayers prevail with you as they have already to-day prevailed for you."
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By this time the youth was in tears,
                        and seeing this, the father flung his arms round him, clung to him with
                        kisses, and persisted in his entreaties until he made his son lay aside his
                        sword and give his word that he would do nothing of the kind. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Then the son spoke: "I must pay to my father the
                        dutiful obedience which I owe to my country. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> I am indeed grieved on your account for you have to
                        bear the guilt of a threefold betrayal of your country; first when you
                        instigated the revolt from Rome, secondly when you urged peace with
                        Hannibal, and now once more when you are the one let and hindrance in the
                        way of restoring Capua to the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Do
                        you, my country, receive this sword with which I armed myself in your
                        defence when I entered the stronghold of the enemy." <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> With these words he flung the sword over the garden
                        wall into the public road, and to allay all suspicions returned to the
                        banqueting room. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following day there was a full meeting
                        of the senate to hear Hannibal. At first his tone was very gracious and
                        winning; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> he thanked the Capuans for
                        preferring his friendship to alliance with Rome, and amongst other
                        magnificent promises he assured them that Capua would soon be the head of
                        all Italy and that Rome, in common with all the other nationalities, would
                        have to look to her for their laws. Then his tone changed. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> There was one man, he thundered, who was outside the
                        friendship of Carthage and the treaty they had made with him, a man that was
                        not, and ought not to be called a Campanian-Decius Magius. He demanded his
                        surrender and asked that this matter should be discussed and a decision
                        arrived at before he left the House. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They
                        all voted for surrendering the man, though a great many thought that he did
                        not deserve such a cruel fate and felt that a long step had been taken in
                        the abridgment of their rights and liberties. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> On leaving the Senate-house Hannibal took his seat on
                        the magistrates' tribunal and ordered Decius Magius to be arrested, brought
                        before him, and put on his defence, alone and unbefriended. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The high spirit of the man was still unquelled, he said
                        that by the terms of the treaty this could not be insisted on, but he was at
                        once placed in irons and ordered to be conducted to the camp, followed by a
                        lictor. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As long as his head was uncovered
                        he was incessantly haranguing and shouting to the crowds round him: "You
                        have got the liberty, you Campanians, that you asked for. In the middle of
                        the Forum, in the broad daylight, with you looking on, I a man second to
                        none in Capua am being hurried off in chains to death. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Could any greater outrage have been committed if the
                        city had been taken? Go and meet Hannibal, decorate your city, make the day
                        of his arrival a public holiday that you may enjoy the spectacle of this
                        triumph over a fellow-citizen! <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As the mob
                        appeared to be moved by these outbursts, his head was muffled up and orders
                        were given to hurry him more quickly outside the city gate. In this way he
                        was brought into the camp and then at once put on board a ship and sent to
                        Carthage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal's fear was that if any
                        disturbance broke out in Capua in consequence of such scandalous treatment
                        the senate might repent of having surrendered their foremost citizen, and if
                        they sent to ask for his restoration he would either offend his new allies
                        by refusing the first request they made, or, if he granted it, would have in
                        Capua a fomenter of disorder and sedition. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> The vessel was driven by a storm to Cyrenae which was then under a
                        monarchy. Here Magius fled for sanctuary to the statue of King Ptolemy, and
                        his guards conveyed him to the King of Alexandria. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> After he had told him how he had been thrown into
                        chains by Hannibal in defiance of all treaty rights, he was liberated from
                        his fetters and permission accorded to him to go to Rome or Capua, whichever
                        he preferred. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Magius said that he would
                        not be safe at Capua, and as there was at that time war between Rome and
                        Capua, he would be living in Rome more like a deserter than a guest. There
                        was no place where he would sooner live than under the rule of the man whom
                        he had known as the champion and asserter of his freedom. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these occurrences Q. Fabius Pictor
                        returned home from his mission to Delphi. He read the response of the oracle
                        from a manuscript, in which were contained the names of the gods and
                        goddesses to whom supplications were to be made, and the forms to be
                        observed in making them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was the
                        closing paragraph: "If ye act thus, Romans, your estate will be better and
                        less troubled, your republic will go forward as ye would have it, and the
                        victory in the war will belong to the people of Rome. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When your commonwealth is prosperous and safe send to
                        Pythian Apollo a gift from the gains you have earned and honour him with
                        your substance out of the plunder, the booty, and the spoils. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Put away from you all wanton and godless living."
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He translated this from the Greek as
                        he read it, and when he had finished reading he said that as soon as he left
                        the oracle he offered sacrifice with wine and incense to all the deities who
                        were named, and further that he was instructed by the priest to go on board
                        wearing the same laurel garland in which he had visited the oracle and not
                        to lay it aside till he got to Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        stated that he had carried out all his instructions most carefully and
                        conscientiously, and had laid the garland on the altar of Apollo. The senate
                        passed a decree that the sacrifices and intercessions which were enjoined
                        should be carefully performed at the earliest opportunity. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During these occurrences in Rome and
                        Italy, Mago, Hamilcar's son, had arrived at Carthage with the news of the
                        victory of Cannae. He had not been sent by his brother immediately after the
                        battle, but had been detained for some days in receiving into alliance
                        Bruttian communities as they successively revolted. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> When he appeared before the senate he unfolded the
                        story of his brother's successes in Italy, how he had fought pitched battles
                        with six commanders-in-chief, four of whom were consuls and two a Dictator
                        and his Master of Horse, and how he had killed about 200,000 of the enemy
                        and taken more than 50,000 prisoners. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Out
                        of four consuls two had fallen, of the two survivors one was wounded and the
                        other, after losing the whole of his army, had escaped with fifty men.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Master of the Horse, whose powers
                        were those of a consul, had been routed and put to flight, and the Dictator,
                        because he had never fought an action, was looked upon as a matchless
                        general. The Bruttians and Apulians, with some of the Samnite and Lucanian
                        communities, had gone over to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Capua, which was not only the chief city of Campania,
                        but now that the power of Rome had been shattered at Cannae was the head of
                        Italy, had surrendered to Hannibal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For
                        all these great victories he felt that they ought to be truly grateful and
                        public thanksgivings ought to be offered to the immortal gods. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As evidence that the joyful tidings he
                        brought were true, he ordered a quantity of gold rings to be piled up in the
                        vestibule of the Senate-house, and they formed such a great heap that,
                        according to some authorities, they measured more than three modii; the more
                        probable account, however, is that they did not amount to more than one
                        modius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He added by way of explanation, to
                        show how great the Roman losses had been, that none but knights, and amongst
                        them only the highest in rank, wore that ornament. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The main purport of his speech was that the nearer
                        Hannibal's chances were of bringing the war to a speedy close the more need
                        there was to render him every possible assistance; he was campaigning far
                        from home, in the midst of a hostile country; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> vast quantities of corn were being consumed and much
                        money expended, and all those battles, whilst they destroyed the armies of
                        the enemy, at the same time wasted very appreciably the forces of the
                        victor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Reinforcements, therefore, must be
                        sent, money must be sent to pay the troops, and supplies of corn to the
                        soldiers who had done such splendid service for Carthage. Amidst the general
                        delight with which Mago's speech was received, Himilco, a member of the
                        Barcine party, thought it a favourable moment for attacking Hanno.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "Well, Hanno," he began, "do you still
                        disapprove of our commencing a war against Rome? <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Give orders for Hannibal to be surrendered, put your
                        veto upon all thanksgivings to the gods after we have received such
                        blessings, let us hear the voice of a Roman senator in the Senate-house of
                        Carthage?" </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then Hanno spoke to the following effect:
                        "Senators, I would have kept silence on the present occasion, for I did not
                        wish on a day of universal rejoicing to say anything which might damp your
                        happiness. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But as a senator has asked me
                        whether I still disapprove of the war we have commenced against Rome,
                        silence on my part would show either insolence or cowardice; the one implies
                        forgetfulness of the respect due to others, the other of one's own
                        self-respect. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> My reply to Himilco is
                        this: I have never ceased to disapprove of the war, nor shall I ever cease
                        to censure your invincible general until I see the war ended upon conditions
                        that are tolerable. Nothing will banish my regret for the old peace that we
                        have broken except the establishment of a new one. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Those details which Mago has proudly enumerated make
                        Himilco and the rest of Hannibal's caucus very happy; they might make me
                        happy too, for a successful war, if we choose to make a wise use of our good
                        fortune, will bring us a more favourable peace. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> If we let this opportunity slip, when we are in a
                        position to offer rather than submit to terms of peace, I fear that our
                        rejoicing will become extravagant and finally turn out to be groundless.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But even now, what is it that you are
                        rejoicing at? 'I have slain the armies of the enemy; send me troops.' What
                        more could you ask for, if you had been defeated? <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> 'I have captured two of the enemy's camps, filled, of
                        course, with plunder and supplies; send me corn and money.' What more could
                        you want if you had been despoiled, stripped of your own camp? <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> And that I may not be the only one to be
                        surprised at your delight-for as I have answered Himilco, I have a perfect
                        right to ask questions in my turn-I should be glad if either Himilco or Mago
                        would tell me, since, you say, the battle of Cannae has all but destroyed
                        the power of Rome and the <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> whole of
                        Italy is admittedly in revolt, whether, in the first place, any single
                        community of the Latin nation has come over to us, and, secondly, whether a
                        single man out of the thirty-five Roman tribes has deserted to Hannibal."
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Mago answered both questions in the
                        negative. "Then there are still," Hanno continued, "far too many of the
                        enemy left. But I should like to know how much courage and confidence that
                        vast multitude possess." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mago said he did not know. "Nothing,"
                        replied Hanno, "is easier to find out. Have the Romans sent any envoys to
                        Hannibal to sue for peace? Has any rumour reached your ears of any one even
                        mentioning the word 'peace' in Rome?" Again Mago replied in the negative.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "Well, then," said Hanno, "we have as
                        much work before us in this war as we had on the day when Hannibal first set
                        foot in Italy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Many of us are still alive
                        who can remember with what changeful fortunes the first Punic war was
                        fought. Never did our cause appear to be prospering more by sea and land
                        than immediately before the consulship of C. Lutatius and A. Postumius.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But in their year of office we were
                        utterly defeated off the Aegates. But if (which heaven forfend!) fortune
                        should now turn to any extent, do you hope to obtain when you are defeated a
                        peace which no one offers to give you now that you are victorious?
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If any one should ask my opinion about
                        offering or accepting terms of peace I would say what I thought. But if the
                        question before us is simply whether Mago's demands should be granted, I do
                        not think that we are concerned with sending supplies to a victorious army,
                        much less do I consider that they ought to be sent if we are being deluded
                        with false and empty hopes." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Very few were
                        influenced by Hanno's speech. His well-known dislike of the Barcas deprived
                        his words of weight and they were too much preoccupied with the delightful
                        news they had just heard to listen to anything which would make them feel
                        less cause for joy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They fancied that if
                        they were willing to make a slight effort the war would soon be over. A
                        resolution was accordingly passed with great enthusiasm to reinforce
                        Hannibal with 4000 Numidians, 40 elephants, and 500 talents of silver.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Bostar also was sent with Mago into
                        Spain to raise 20,000 infantry and 4000 cavalry to make good the losses of
                        the armies in Italy and Spain. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As usual, however, in seasons of
                        prosperity, these measures were executed with great remissness and
                        dilatoriness. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans, on the other
                        hand, were kept from being dilatory by their native energy and still more by
                        the necessities of their position. The consul did not fail in any single
                        duty which he had to perform, nor did the Dictator show less energy. The
                        force now available comprised the two legions which had been enrolled by the
                        consuls at the beginning of the year, a levy of slaves and the cohorts which
                        had been raised in the country of Picenum and Cisalpine Gaul. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The Dictator decided to still further increase
                        his strength by adopting a measure to which only a country in an almost
                        hopeless state could stoop, when honour must yield to necessity. After duly
                        discharging his religious duties and obtaining the necessary permission to
                        mount his horse, he published an edict that all who had been guilty of
                        capital offences or who were in prison for debt and were willing to serve
                        under him would by his orders be released from punishment and have their
                        debts cancelled. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> 6000 men were raised in
                        this way, and he armed them with the spoils taken from the Gauls and which
                        had been carried in the triumphal procession of C. Flaminius. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He then started from the City with 25,000 men.
                        After taking over Capua, and making another fruitless appeal to the hopes
                        and fears of Neapolis, Hannibal marched into the territory of Nola.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He did not at once treat it in a
                        hostile manner as he was not without hope that the citizens would make a
                        voluntary surrender, but if they delayed, he intended to leave nothing
                        undone which could cause them suffering or terror. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The senate, especially its leading members, were
                        faithful supporters of the Roman alliance, the populace as usual were all in
                        favour of revolting to Hannibal; they conjured up the prospect of ravaged
                        fields and a siege with all its hardships and indignities; nor were there
                        wanting men who were actively instigating a revolt. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The senate were afraid that if they openly opposed the
                        agitation they would not be able to withstand the popular excitement, and
                        they found a means of putting off the evil day by pretending to go with the
                        mob. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They represented that they were in
                        favour of revolting to Hannibal, but nothing was settled as to the
                        conditions on which they were to enter into a new treaty and alliance.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having thus gained time, they sent
                        delegates in great haste to Marcellus Claudius the praetor, who was with his
                        army at Casilinum, to inform him of the critical position of Nola, how their
                        territory was in Hannibal's hand, and the city would be <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> in the possession of the Carthaginians unless it
                        received succour. and how the senate, by telling the populace that they
                        might revolt when they pleased. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> had made
                        them less in a hurry to do so. Marcellus thanked the delegates and told them
                        to adhere to the same policy and postpone matters till he arrived.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He then left Casilinum for Caiatia
                        and from there he marched across the Vulturnus, through the districts of
                        Saticula and Trebia, over the hills above Suessula, and so arrived at Nola.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the approach of the Roman praetor the
                        Carthaginian evacuated the territory of Nola and marched down to the coast
                        close to Neapolis, as he was anxious to secure a seaport town to which there
                        might be a safe passage for ships coming from Africa. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When, however, he learnt that Neapolis was held by a
                        Roman officer, M. Junius Silanus, who had been invited by the Neapolitans,
                        he left Naples, as he had left Nola, and went to Nuceria. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He spent some time in investing the place, often
                        attacking it, and often making tempting proposals to the chief men of the
                        place and to the leaders of the populace, but all to no purpose. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> At last famine did its work, and he received the
                        submission of the town, the inhabitants being allowed to depart without arms
                        and with one garment apiece. Then, to keep up his character of being
                        friendly to all the Italian nationalities except the Romans, he held out
                        honours and rewards to those who consented to remain in his service.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Not a single man was tempted by the
                        prospect; they all dispersed, wherever they had friends, or wherever each
                        man's fancy led him, amongst the cities of Campania, mainly Nola and
                        Neapolis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About thirty of their senators,
                        and, as it happened, their principal ones, endeavoured to enter Capua, but
                        were refused admission because they had closed their gates against Hannibal.
                        They accordingly went on to Cumae. The plunder of Nuceria was given to the
                        soldiers, the city itself was burnt. </p>
                    <p> Marcellus retained his hold on Nola quite as much by the support of its
                        leading men as by the confidence he felt in his troops. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Fears were entertained as to the populace and
                        especially L. Bantius. This enterprising young man was at that time almost
                        the most distinguished among the allied cavalry, but the knowledge that he
                        had attempted revolt and his fear of the Roman praetor were driving him on
                        to betray his country or, if he found no means of doing that, to become a
                        deserter. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He had been discovered lying
                        half-dead on a heap of bodies on the field of Cannae, and after being taken
                        the utmost care of, Hannibal sent him home loaded with presents. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> His feelings of gratitude for such kindness made
                        him wish to place the government of Nola in the hands of the Carthaginian,
                        and his anxiety and eagerness for a revolution attracted the observation of
                        the praetor. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As it was necessary either
                        to restrain the youth by punishment or to win him by kindness, the praetor
                        chose the latter course, preferring to secure such a brave and enterprising
                        youth as a friend rather than to lose him to the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He invited him to come and see him and spoke to him
                        most kindly. "You can easily understand," he told him, "that many of your
                        countrymen are jealous of you, from the fact that not a single citizen of
                        Nola has pointed out to me your many distinguished military services.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But the bravery of a man who has
                        served in a Roman camp cannot be hidden. Many of your fellow-soldiers tell
                        me what a young hero you are, and how many perils and dangers you have
                        undergone in defence of the safety and honour of Rome. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> I am told that you did not give up the struggle on the
                        field of Cannae until you were buried almost lifeless, beneath a falling
                        mass of men and horses and arms. May you long live to do still more gallant
                        deeds! <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> With me you will gain every honour
                        and reward, and you will find that the more you are in my company the more
                        will it lead to your profit and promotion." The young man was delighted with
                        these promises. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The praetor made him a
                        present of a splendid charger and authorised the quaestor to pay him 500
                        silver coins; he also instructed his lictors to allow him to pass whenever
                        he wished to see him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The high-spirited youth was so completely
                        captivated by the attention Marcellus paid him that for the future none
                        among the allies of Rome gave her more efficient or more loyal help.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hannibal once more moved his camp from
                        Nuceria to Nola, and when he appeared before its gates the populace again
                        began to look forward to revolting. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As the
                        enemy approached Marcellus retired within the walls, not because he feared
                        for his camp, but because he would not give any opportunity to the large
                        number of citizens who were bent on betraying their city. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Both armies now began to prepare for battle; the Romans
                        before the walls of Nola and the Carthaginians in front of their camp.
                        Slight skirmishes took place between the city and the camp with varying
                        success, as the generals would not prohibit their men from going forward in
                        small parties to offer defiance to the enemy nor would they give the signal
                        for a general action. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Day after day the
                        two armies took up their respective stations in this way, and during this
                        time the leading citizens of Nola informed Marcellus that nocturnal
                        interviews were taking place between the populace and the Carthaginians, and
                        that it had been <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> arranged that when the
                        Roman army had passed out of the gates they should plunder their baggage and
                        kits, then close the gates and man the walls so that having become masters
                        of their city and government they might forthwith admit the Carthaginians
                        instead of the Romans. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On receiving this information Marcellus
                        warmly thanked the Nolan senators and made up his mind to try the fortune of
                        a battle before any disturbances arose in the city. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He formed his army into three divisions and stationed
                        them at the three gates which faced the enemy, he ordered the baggage to
                        follow close behind, and the camp-servants, sutlers, and disabled soldiers
                        were to carry stakes. At the centre gate he posted the strongest part of the
                        legions and the Roman cavalry, at the two on either side he stationed the
                        recruits, the light infantry, and the cavalry of the allies. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The Nolans were forbidden to approach the walls
                        or gates and a special reserve was placed in charge of the baggage to
                        prevent any attack upon it whilst the legions were engaged in the battle.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In this formation they remained
                        standing inside the gates. Hannibal had his troops drawn up for battle, as
                        he had had for several days, and remained in this position till late in the
                        day. At first it struck him with surprise that the Roman army did not move
                        outside the gates and that not a single soldier appeared on the walls.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then, supposing that the secret
                        interviews had been betrayed and that his friends were afraid to move, he
                        sent back a portion of his troops to their camp with orders to bring all the
                        appliances for attacking the town as soon as possible to the front of the
                        line. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He felt fairly confident that if he
                        attacked them whilst thus hesitating the populace would raise some
                        disturbance in the town. Whilst his men were hurrying up to the front ranks,
                        each to his allotted task, and the whole line was approaching the walls,
                        Marcellus ordered the gates to be suddenly flung open, the attack sounded,
                        and the battle shout raised; the infantry, followed by the cavalry, were to
                        attack with all the fury possible. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They
                        had already carried enough confusion and alarm into the enemies' centre when
                        P. Valerius Flaccus and C. Aurelius, divisional commanders, burst out from
                        the other two gates and charged. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The
                        sutlers and camp-servants and the rest of the troops who were guarding the
                        baggage joined in the shouting, and this made the Carthaginians, who had
                        been despising the fewness of their numbers, think that it was a large army.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I would hardly venture to assert, as
                        some authorities do, that 2800 of the enemy were killed, and that the Romans
                        did not lose more than 500. But whether <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/>
                        the victory was as great as that or not, I do not think that an action more
                        important in its consequences was fought during the whole war, for it was
                        more difficult for those who conquered to escape being defeated by Hannibal
                        than it was afterwards to conquer him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As there was no hope of his getting
                        possession of Nola, Hannibal withdrew to Acerrae. No sooner had he departed
                        than Marcellus shut the gates and posted guards to prevent any one from
                        leaving the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He then opened a public
                        inquiry in the forum into the conduct of those who had been holding secret
                        interviews with the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Above seventy
                        were found guilty of treason and beheaded and their property confiscated.
                        Then, after handing the government over to the senate, he left with his
                        entire force and took up a position above Suessula, where he encamped.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At first the Carthaginian tried to
                        persuade the men of Acerrae to make a voluntary surrender, but when he found
                        that their loyalty remained unshaken he made preparations for a siege and an
                        assault. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Acerrans possessed more
                        courage than strength, and when they saw that the blockade was being carried
                        round their walls and that it was hopeless to attempt any further defence,
                        they decided to escape before the enemies' line of <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> circumvallation was closed, and stealing away in the
                        dead of night through any unguarded gaps in the earthworks they fled,
                        regardless of roads or paths, as chance or design led them. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They escaped to those cities of Campania which they had
                        every reason to believe had not changed their allegiance. After plundering
                        and burning Acerrae Hannibal marched to Casilinum in consequence of
                        information he received of the Dictator's march on Capua with his legions.
                        He was apprehensive that the proximity of the Roman army might create a
                        counter-revolution in Capua. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At that time
                        Casilinum was held by 500 Praenestines with a few Roman and Latin troops,
                        who had gone there when they heard of the disaster at Cannae. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The levy at Praeneste had not been completed by
                        the appointed day, and these men started from home too late to be of use at
                        Cannae. They reached Casilinum before news of the disaster arrived, and,
                        joined by Romans and allies, they advanced in great force. Whilst on the
                        march they heard of the battle and its result and returned to Casilinum.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here, suspected by the Campanians and
                        fearing for their own safety, they passed some days in forming and evading
                        plots. When they were satisfied that Capua was in revolt and that Hannibal
                        would be admitted, they massacred the townsmen of Casilinum at night and
                        took possession of the part of the city on this side of the Vulturnus-the
                        river divides the city in two-and held it as a Roman garrison. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> They were joined also by a cohort of Perusians
                        numbering 460 men who were driven to Casilinum by the same intelligence that
                        sent the Praenestines there a few days previously. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The force was quite adequate for the small circuit of
                        walls, protected, too, as they were on one side by the river, but the
                        scarcity of corn made even that number appear too large. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hannibal was now not far from the
                        place he sent on in advance a troop of Gaetulians under an officer named
                        Isalca, to try and get a parley with the inhabitants and persuade them by
                        fair words to open their gates and admit a Carthaginian detachment to hold
                        the town. If they refused, they were to use force and make an attack,
                        wherever it seemed feasible, on the place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        When they approached the walls the town was so silent that they thought it
                        was deserted, and taking it for granted that the inhabitants had fled
                        through fear they began to force the gates and break down the bars.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Suddenly the gates were thrown open
                        and two cohorts which had been standing inside ready for action dashed out
                        and made a furious charge, utterly discomfiting the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Maharbal was sent with a stronger force to their
                        assistance, but even he was unable to withstand the impetuosity of the
                        cohorts. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At last Hannibal pitched his camp
                        before the walls, and made preparations for assaulting the little town and
                        its small garrison with the combined strength of his entire army. After
                        completing the circle of his investing lines he began to harass and annoy
                        the garrison, and in this way lost some of his most daring soldiers who were
                        hit with missiles from the wall and turrets. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> On one occasion when the defenders were taking the aggressive in a sortie
                        he nearly cut them off with his elephants and drove them in hasty flight
                        into the city; the loss, considering their numbers, was quite severe enough,
                        and more would have fallen had not night intervened. The next day there was
                        a general desire to begin the assault. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        enthusiasm of the men had been kindled by the offer of a "mural crown" of
                        gold and also by the way in which the general himself remonstrated with the
                        men who had taken Saguntum for their slackness in attacking a little
                        fortress situated in open country, and also reminded them one and all of
                        Cannae, Trasumennus, and the Trebia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        vineae were brought up and mines commenced, but the various attempts of the
                        enemy were opposed with equal strength and skill by the defenders, the
                        allies of Rome; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> they created defences
                        against the vineae, intercepted their mines with counter-mines, and met all
                        their attacks above ground or below with steady resistance until at last
                        Hannibal for very shame gave up his project. He contented himself with
                        fortifying his camp and leaving a small force to defend it, so that it might
                        not be supposed that the siege was entirely abandoned; after which he
                        settled in Capua as his winter quarters. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There he kept his army under shelter for
                        the greater part of the winter. A long and varied experience had inured that
                        army to every form of human suffering, but it had not been habituated to or
                        had any experience of ease and comfort. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        So it came about that the men whom no pressure of calamity had been able to
                        subdue fell victims to a prosperity too great and pleasures too attractive
                        for them to withstand, and fell all the more utterly the more greedily they
                        plunged into new and untried delights. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Sloth, wine, feasting, women, baths, and idle lounging, which became every
                        day more seductive as they became more habituated to them, so enervated
                        their minds and bodies that they were saved more by the memory of past
                        victories than by any fighting strength they possessed now. Authorities in
                        military matters have regarded the wintering at Capua as a greater mistake
                        on the part of Hannibal than his not marching straight to Rome after his
                        victory at Cannae. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For his delay at that
                        time might be looked upon as only postponing his final victory but this may
                        be considered as having deprived him of the strength to win victory.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And it certainly did look as if he
                        left Capua with another army altogether; it did not retain a shred of its
                        former discipline. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A large number who had
                        become entangled with women went back there, and as soon as they took to
                        tents again and the fatigue of marching and other military toils had to be
                        endured their strength and spirits alike gave way just as though they were
                        raw recruits. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> From that time all through
                        the summer campaign a large number left the standards without leave, and
                        Capua was the only place where the deserters sought to hide themselves. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, when the mild weather came,
                        Hannibal led his army out of their winter quarters and marched back to
                        Casilinum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Although the assault had been
                        suspended, the uninterrupted investment had reduced the townsfolk and the
                        garrison to the extremity of want. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus was in command of the Roman camp, as the
                        Dictator had to leave for Rome to take the auspices afresh. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Marcellus was equally anxious to assist the besieged
                        garrison, but he was detained by the Vulturnus being in flood, and also by
                        the entreaties of the people of Nola and Acerrae who feared the Campanians
                        in case the Romans withdrew their protection. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Gracchus simply watched Casilinum, for the Dictator had
                        given strict orders that no active operations should be undertaken in his
                        absence. He therefore kept quiet, though the reports from Casilinum might
                        easily have been too much for any man's patience. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was stated as a fact that some, unable to endure
                        starvation any longer, had flung themselves from the walls, others had stood
                        there unarmed and exposed their defenceless bodies to the missiles of the
                        enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These tidings sorely tried his
                        patience, for he durst not fight against the Dictator's orders, and he saw
                        that he would have to fight if he were seen getting corn into the place, and
                        there was no chance of getting it in without being seen. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He gathered in a supply of corn from all the fields
                        round and filled a number of casks with it, and then sent a messenger to the
                        chief magistrate at Casilinum asking him to pick up the casks which the
                        river carried down. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The next night, while
                        all were intently watching the river, after their hopes had been raised by
                        the Roman messenger, the casks floated down in the middle of the stream; and
                        the corn was divided in equal shares amongst them all. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The same thing happened on the two following days; they
                        were sent off by night and reached their destination; so far they had
                        escaped the notice of the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then,
                        owing to the perpetual rain, the river became more rapid than usual and the
                        cross currents carried the casks to the bank which the enemy were guarding.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They caught sight of them as they
                        stuck amongst the osier beds which grew on the bank and a report was made to
                        Hannibal in consequence of which greater caution was observed and a closer
                        watch was kept, so that nothing could be sent by the Vulturnus to the city
                        without being detected. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Nuts, however,
                        were scattered on the river from the Roman camp; these floated down the
                        mid-stream and were caught in baskets. At last things came to such a pitch
                        that the inhabitants tried to chew the leather straps and hides which they
                        tore from their shields, after softening them in boiling water, nor did they
                        refuse mice and other animals; they even dug up from the bottom of their
                        walls grass and roots of all sorts. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When
                        the enemy had ploughed up all the grass outside the walls they sowed it with
                        rape, which made Hannibal exclaim: "Am I to sit here before Casilinum until
                        these seeds have grown?" <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and whereas he
                        had never allowed any terms of surrender to be mentioned in his hearing, he
                        now consented to proposals for the ransom of all the freeborn citizens. The
                        price agreed upon was seven ounces of gold for each person. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> When their liberty was guaranteed they
                        surrendered, but were kept in custody till all the gold was paid, then in
                        strict observance of the terms they were released. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> This is much more likely to be true than that after
                        they had left cavalry were sent after them and put them all to death. The
                        great majority were Praenestines. Out of the 570 who formed the garrison not
                        less than half had perished by sword and famine, the rest returned in safety
                        to Praeneste with their commanding officer, M. Anicius, who had formerly
                        been a notary. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> To commemorate the event
                        his statue was set up in the forum of Praeneste, wearing a coat of mail with
                        a toga over it and having the head veiled. A bronze plate was affixed with
                        this inscription: "Marcus Anicius has discharged the vow he made for the
                        safety of the garrison of Casilinum." The same inscription was affixed to
                        the three images standing in the temple of Fortune. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The town of Casilinum was given back to
                        the Campanians, and a garrison of 700 men from Hannibal's army was placed in
                        it in case the Romans should attack it after Hannibal's departure.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate decreed that double pay and
                        an exemption for five years from further service should be granted to the
                        Praenestine troops. They were also offered the full Roman citizenship, but
                        they preferred not to change their status as citizens of Praeneste.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There is more obscurity as to what
                        happened to the Perusians, as there is no light thrown upon it by any
                        monument of their own or any decree of the senate. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The people of Petelia, who alone of all the Bruttii had
                        remained friendly to Rome, were now attacked not only by the Carthaginians,
                        who were overrunning that district, but also by the rest of the Bruttii who
                        had adopted the opposite policy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Finding
                        themselves helpless in the presence of all these dangers, they sent envoys
                        to Rome to ask for support. The senate told them that they must look after
                        themselves, and on hearing this they broke into tears and entreaties and
                        flung themselves on the floor of the vestibule. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Their distress excited the deep sympathy of both senate
                        and people, and the praetor, M. Aemilius asked the senators to reconsider
                        their decision. After making a careful survey of the resources of the
                        empire, they were compelled to admit that they were powerless to protect
                        their distant allies. They advised the envoys to return home and now that
                        they had proved their loyalty to the utmost they must adopt such measures as
                        their present circumstances demanded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When
                        the result of their mission was reported to the Petelians, their senate was
                        so overcome by grief and fear that some were in favour of deserting the city
                        and seeking refuge wherever they <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> could,
                        others thought that as they had been abandoned by their old allies they had
                        better join the rest of the Bruttii and surrender to Hannibal. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The majority, however, decided that no rash
                        action should be taken, and that the question should be further debated.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the matter came up the next day
                        a calmer tone prevailed and their leading statesmen persuaded them to
                        collect all their produce and possessions from the fields and put the city
                        and the walls into a state of defence. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time despatches arrived from
                        Sicily and Sardinia. The one sent from T. Otacilius, the propraetor
                        commanding in Sicily, was read in the senate. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> It stated in effect that P. Furius had reached
                        Lilybaeum with his fleet; that he himself was seriously wounded and his life
                        in great danger; that the soldiers and sailors had no pay or corn given them
                        from day to day, nor was there any means of procuring any, and he strongly
                        urged that both <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> should be sent as soon
                        as possible, and that, if the senate agreed, one of the new praetors should
                        be sent to succeed him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The despatch from
                        A. Cornelius Mammula dealt with the same difficulty as to pay and corn. The
                        same reply was sent to both; there was no possibility of sending either, and
                        they were instructed to make the best arrangements they could for their
                        fleets and armies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> T. Otacilius sent
                        envoys to Hiero, the one man whom Rome could fall back upon, and received in
                        reply as much money as he needed and a six months' supply of corn. In Sicily
                        the allied cities sent generous contributions. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Even in Rome, too, the scarcity of money was felt and a
                        measure was carried by M. Minucius, one of the tribunes of the plebs, for
                        the appointment of three finance commissioners. The men appointed were: L.
                        Aemilius Papus, who had been consul and censor; M. Atilius Regulus, who had
                        been twice consul, and L. Scribonius Libo, one of the tribunes of the plebs.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcus and Caius Atilius, two
                        brothers, were appointed to dedicate the temple of Concord which L. Manlius
                        had vowed during his praetorship. Three new pontiffs were also chosen-Q.
                        Caecilius Metellus, Q. Fabius Maximus, and Q. Fulvius Flaccus-in the place
                        of P. Scantinius who had died, and of L. Aemilius Paulus, the consul, and Q.
                        Aelius Paetus, both of whom fell at Cannae. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the senate had done their best-so far
                        as human wisdom could do so-to make good the losses which Fortune had
                        inflicted in such an <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> uninterrupted
                        series of disasters, they at last turned their attention to the emptiness of
                        the Senate-house and the small number of those who attended the national
                        council. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There had been no revision of the
                        roll of the senate since L. Aemilius and C. Flaminius were censors, though
                        there had been such heavy losses amongst the senators during the last five
                        years on the field of battle, as well as from the fatalities and accidents
                        to which all are liable. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In compliance
                        with the unanimous wish, the subject was brought forward by the praetor, M.
                        Aemilius, in the absence of the Dictator, who after the loss of Casilinum
                        had rejoined the army. Sp. Carvilius spoke at considerable length about the
                        dearth of senators, and also the very small number of citizens from whom
                        senators could be chosen. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He went on to
                        say that for the purpose of filling up the vacancies, and also of
                        strengthening the union between the Latins and Rome, he should strongly urge
                        that the full citizenship be granted to two senators out of each Latin city,
                        to be approved by the senate, and that these <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> men should be chosen into the senate in the place of
                        those who had died. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate listened to
                        these proposals with quite as much impatience as they had previously felt at
                        the demand of the Latins. A murmur of indignation went through the House. T.
                        Manlius in particular was heard asserting that there was even still one man
                        of the stock to which that consul belonged who once in the Capitol
                        threatened that he would kill with his own hand any Latin whom he saw
                        sitting in the senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Q. Fabius Maximus
                        declared that no proposal had ever been mooted in the senate at a more
                        inopportune time than this; it had been thrown out at a moment when the
                        sympathies of their allies were wavering and their loyalty doubtful, and it
                        would make them more restless than ever; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        those rash inconsiderate words uttered by one man ought to be stifled by the
                        silence of all men. Whatever secret or sacred matter had at any time imposed
                        silence on that House, this most of all must be concealed, buried,
                        forgotten, considered as never having been uttered. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> All further allusion to the subject was accordingly
                        suppressed. It was ultimately decided to nominate as Dictator a man who had
                        been censor before, and was the oldest man living who had held that office,
                        in order that the roll of senators might be revised. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> C. Terentius was recalled to nominate the Dictator.
                        Leaving a garrison in Apulia he returned to Rome by forced marches, and the
                        night after his arrival nominated, in accordance with ancient custom M.
                        Fabius Buteo to act as Dictator for six months without any Master of the
                        Horse. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accompanied by his lictors, Fabius mounted
                        the rostra and made the following speech: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        "I do not approve of there being two Dictators at the same time, a thing
                        wholly unprecedented, nor of there being a Dictator without a Master of the
                        Horse, nor of the censorial powers being entrusted to one individual and
                        that for the second time, nor of the supreme authority being placed in the
                        hands of a Dictator for six months unless he has been created to wield
                        executive powers. These irregularities may perhaps be necessary at this
                        juncture, but I shall fix a limit to them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        I shall not remove from the roll any of those whom C. Flaminius and L.
                        Aemilius, the last censors, placed on it, I shall simply order their names
                        to be transcribed and read out, as I do not choose to allow the power of
                        judging and deciding upon the reputation or character of a senator to rest
                        with any single individual. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I shall fill
                        up the places of those who are dead in such a way as to make it clear that
                        preference is given to rank and not to persons." <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After the names of the old senate had been read out,
                        Fabius began his selection. The first chosen were men who, subsequent to the
                        censorship of L. Aemilius and C. Flaminius, had filled a curule office, but
                        were not yet in the senate, and they were taken according to the order of
                        their previous appointments. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were
                        followed by those who had been aediles, tribunes of the plebs, or quaestors.
                        Last of all came those who had not held office, but had the spoils of an
                        enemy set up in their houses or had received a "civic crown." <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> In this way names were added to the senatorial
                        roll, amidst general approbation. Having completed his task he at once laid
                        down his Dictatorship and descended from the rostra as a private citizen.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He ordered the lictors to cease their
                        attendance and mingled with the throng of citizens who were transacting
                        their private business, deliberately idling his time away in order that he
                        might not take the people out of the Forum to escort him home. The public
                        interest in him, however, did not slacken through their having to wait, and
                        a large crowd escorted him to his house. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        The following night the consul made his way back to the army, without
                        letting the senate know, as he did not want to be detained in the City for
                        the elections. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day the senate, on being
                        consulted by M. Pomponius, the praetor, passed a decree to write to the
                        Dictator, asking him, if the interests of the State permitted, to come to
                        Rome to conduct the election of fresh consuls. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He was to bring with him his Master of the Horse and M.
                        Marcellus, the praetor, so that the senate might learn from them on the spot
                        in what condition the affairs of the Republic were, and form their plans
                        accordingly. On receiving the summons they all came, after leaving officers
                        in command of the legions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Dictator
                        spoke briefly and modestly about himself; he gave most of the credit to
                        Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus, his Master of the Horse, and then gave notice
                        of the elections. The consuls elected were L. Postumius for the third
                        time-he was elected in his absence, as he was then administering the
                        province of Gaul-and Ti. Sempronius Gracchus, Master of the Horse, and at
                        that time curule aedile also. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then the
                        praetors were elected. They were M. Valerius Laevinus, for the second time,
                        Appius Claudius Pulcher, Q. Fulvius Flaccus, and Q. Mucius Scaevola.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the various magistrates had been
                        elected the Dictator returned to his army in winter quarters at Teanum. The
                        Master of the Horse was left in Rome; as he would be entering upon office in
                        a few days, it was desirable for him to consult the senate about the
                        enrolment and equipment of the armies for the year. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While these matters were engrossing
                        attention a fresh disaster was announced, for Fortune was heaping one
                        disaster upon another this year. It was reported that L. Postumius, the
                        consul elect, and his army had been annihilated in Gaul. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> There was a wild forest called by the Gauls Litana, and
                        through this the consul was to conduct his army. The Gauls cut through the
                        trees on both sides of the road in such a way that they remained standing as
                        long as they were undisturbed, but a slight pressure would make them fall.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Postumius had two Roman legions, and
                        he had also levied a force from the country bordering on the Upper Sea,
                        sufficiently large to bring the force with which he entered the hostile
                        territory up to 2s,000 men. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Gauls had
                        posted themselves round the outskirts of the forest, and as soon as the
                        Roman army entered they pushed the sawn trees on the outside, these fell
                        upon those next to them, which were tottering and hardly able to stand
                        upright, until the whole mass fell in on both sides and buried in one common
                        ruin arms and men and horses. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hardly ten
                        men escaped, for when most of them hail been crushed to death by the trunks
                        or broken branches of the trees, the remainder, panic-struck at the
                        unexpected disaster, were killed by the Gauls who surrounded the forest. Out
                        of the whole number only very few were made prisoners, and these, whilst
                        trying to reach a bridge over the river, were intercepted by the Gauls who
                        had already seized it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was there that
                        Postumius fell whilst fighting most desperately to avoid capture. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> The Boii stripped the body of its spoils and cut
                        off the head, and bore them in triumph to the most sacred of their temples.
                        According to their custom they cleaned out the skull and covered the scalp
                        with beaten gold; it was then used as a vessel for libations and also as a
                        drinking cup for the priest and ministers of the temple. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The plunder, too, which the Gauls secured was as great
                        as their victory, for although most of the animals had been buried beneath
                        the fallen trees, the rest of the booty, not having been scattered in
                        flight, was found strewn along the whole line where the army lay. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of this disaster arrived the
                        whole community was in such a state of alarm that the shops were shut up and
                        a solitude like that of night pervaded the City. Under these circumstances
                        the senate instructed the aediles to make a round of the City and order the
                        citizens to re-open their shops and lay aside the aspect of public mourning.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Ti. Sempronius then convened the
                        senate, and addressed them in a consolatory and encouraging tone. "We," he
                        said, "who were not crushed by the overthrow at Cannae must not lose heart
                        at smaller calamities. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If we are
                        successful, as I trust we shall be, in our operations against Hannibal and
                        the Carthaginians, we can safely leave the war with the Gauls out of account
                        for the present; the gods and the Roman people will have it in their power
                        to avenge that act of treachery. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is
                        with regard to the Carthaginians and the armies with which the war is to be
                        carried on that we have now to deliberate and decide." <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He first gave details as to the strength of infantry
                        and cavalry, and the proportion in each of Roman and allied troops, which
                        made up the Dictator's army; Marcellus followed with similar details as to
                        his own force. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then inquiry was made of
                        those who were acquainted with the facts as to the strength of the force
                        with C. Terentius Varro in Apulia. No practical method suggested itself for
                        bringing up the two consular armies to sufficient strength for such an
                        important war. So in spite of the justifiable resentment which was generally
                        felt they decided to discontinue the campaign in Gaul for that year.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Dictator's army was assigned to
                        the consul. It was decided that those of Marcellus' troops who were involved
                        in the flight from Cannae should be transported to Sicily to serve there as
                        long as the war continued in Italy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All
                        the least efficient in the Dictator's army were also to be removed there, no
                        period of service being fixed in their case, except that they must each
                        serve out their time. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two legions
                        raised in the City were allocated to the other consul who should succeed L.
                        Postumius; and it was arranged that he should be elected as soon as
                        favourable auspices could be obtained. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The two legions in Sicily were to be recalled at the earliest possible
                        moment, and the consul to whom the legions from the City had been assigned
                        was to take out of those what men he required. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> C. Terentius had his command extended for another year,
                        and no reduction was to be made in the army with which he was protecting
                        Apulia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these preparations were going on in
                        Italy, the war in Spain was being carried on with as much energy as ever
                        and, so far, in favour of the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        two Scipios, Publius and Cnaeus, had divided their forces between them,
                        Cnaeus was to operate on land and Publius by sea. Hasdrubal, the
                        Carthaginian commander, did not feel himself strong enough in either arm,
                        and kept himself safe by taking up strong positions at a distance from the
                        enemy; until, in response to his many earnest appeals for reinforcements,
                        4000 infantry and 1000 cavalry were sent to him from Africa. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Then, recovering his confidence, he moved nearer
                        the enemy, and gave orders for the fleet to be put into readiness to protect
                        the islands and the coast. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the very
                        middle of his preparations for a fresh campaign he was dismayed by news of
                        the desertion of the naval captains. After they had been heavily censured
                        for their cowardice in abandoning the fleet at the Ebro they had never been
                        very loyal either to their general or to the cause of Carthage. These
                        deserters had started an agitation amongst the tribe of the Tartesii and had
                        induced several cities to revolt, and one they had actually taken by storm.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The war was now diverted from the
                        Romans to this tribe, and Hasdrubal entered their territories with an
                        invading army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Chalbus, a distinguished
                        general amongst them, was encamped with a strong force before the walls of a
                        city which he had captured a few days before, and Hasdrubal determined to
                        attack him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He sent forward skirmishers to
                        draw the enemy into an engagement and told off a part of his cavalry to lay
                        waste the surrounding country and pick up stragglers. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> There was confusion in the camp and panic and bloodshed
                        in the fields, but when they had regained the camp from all directions their
                        fears so suddenly left them that they became emboldened, not only to defend
                        their camp, but even to take the aggressive against the enemy. They burst in
                        a body out of their camp, executing war dances after their manner, and this
                        unexpected daring on their part carried terror into the hearts of the enemy,
                        who had shortly before been challenging them. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Hasdrubal thereupon withdrew his force to a fairly
                        lofty hill, which was also protected by a river which served as a barrier.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He retired his skirmishers and his
                        scattered cavalry also to this same position. Not, however, feeling
                        sufficiently protected by either hill or river he strongly entrenched
                        himself. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Several skirmishes took place
                        between the two sides who were alternately frightening and fearing each
                        other, and the Numidian trooper proved to be no match for the Spaniard, nor
                        were the darts of the Moor very effective against the ox-hide shields of the
                        natives, who were quite as rapid in their movements and possessed more
                        strength and courage. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they found that though they rode up
                        to the Carthaginian lines they could not entice the enemy into action,
                        whilst an attack upon the camp was a far from easy matter, they successfully
                        assaulted the town of Ascua, where Hasdrubal had stored his corn and other
                        supplies on entering their territories, and became masters of all the
                        country round. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now there was no longer any
                        discipline amongst them, whether on the march or in camp. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Hasdrubal soon became aware of this, and seeing that
                        success had made them careless, he urged his men to attack them whilst they
                        were scattered away from their standards; he himself meanwhile descended
                        from the hill and marched with his men in attack formation straight to their
                        camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> News of his approach was brought by
                        men rushing in from the look-out stations and outposts and there was a
                        general call to arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As each man seized
                        his weapons he hurried with the others into battle, without order or
                        formation, or word of command or standards. The foremost of them were
                        already engaged, whilst others were still running up in small groups and
                        some had not yet left the camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Their
                        reckless daring, however, at first checked the enemy, but soon, finding that
                        whilst loose and scattered themselves, they were charging an enemy in close
                        formation, and that their scanty numbers imperilled their safety, they
                        looked round at one another, and as they were being repulsed in every
                        direction they formed a square. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Standing
                        close together with their shields touching they were gradually driven into
                        such a close mass that they had hardly room to use their weapons, and for a
                        great part of the day were simply cut down by the enemy who completely
                        surrounded them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A very few cut their way
                        out and made for the woods and hills. The camp was abandoned in the same
                        panic and the whole tribe made their surrender the following day. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> But they did not remain quiet long, for just
                        after this battle an order was received from Carthage for Hasdrubal to lead
                        his army as soon as he could into Italy. This became generally known
                        throughout Spain and the result was that there was a universal feeling in
                        favour of Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal at once sent a
                        despatch to Carthage pointing out what mischief the mere rumour of his
                        departure had caused, and also that if he did really leave Spain it would
                        pass into the hands of the Romans before he crossed the Ebro. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> He went on to say that not only had he neither a
                        force nor a general to leave in his place, but the Roman generals were men
                        whom he found it difficult to oppose even when his strength was equal to
                        theirs. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If, therefore, they were at all
                        anxious to retain Spain they should send a man with a powerful army to
                        succeed him, and even though all went well with his successor he would not
                        find it an easy province to govern. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although this despatch made a great
                        impression on the senate, they decided that as Italy demanded their first
                        and closest attention, the arrangements about Hannibal and his forces must
                        not be altered. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Himilco was sent with a
                        large and well-appointed army and an augmented fleet to hold and defend
                        Spain by sea and land. As soon as he had brought his military and naval
                        forces across he formed an entrenched camp, hauled his ships up on the beach
                        and surrounded them with a rampart. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After
                        providing for the safety of his force he started with a picked body of
                        cavalry, and marching as rapidly as possible, and being equally on the alert
                        whether passing through doubtful or through hostile tribes, succeeded in
                        reaching Hasdrubal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After laying before
                        him the resolutions and instructions of the senate and being in his turn
                        shown in what way the war was to be managed in Spain, he returned to his
                        camp. He owed his safety most of all to the speed at which he travelled, for
                        he had got clear of each tribe before they had time for any united action.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Before Hasdrubal commenced his march,
                        he levied contributions on all the tribes under his rule, for he was quite
                        aware that Hannibal had secured a passage through some tribes by paying for
                        it, and had obtained his Gaulish auxiliaries simply by hiring them.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To commence such a march without money
                        would hardly bring him to the Alps. The contributions were therefore
                        hurriedly called in and after receiving them he marched down to the Ebro.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the resolutions of the
                        Carthaginians and Hasdrubal's march were reported to the Roman generals, the
                        two Scipios at once put aside all other matters and made preparations to
                        meet him at the outset with their joint forces and stop his further
                        progress. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They believed that if Hannibal,
                        who single-handed was almost too much for Italy, were joined by such a
                        general as Hasdrubal and his Spanish army it would mean the end of the Roman
                        empire. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> With so much to make them anxious
                        they concentrated their forces at the Ebro and crossed the river. They
                        deliberated for some considerable time as to whether they should meet him,
                        army against army, or whether it would be enough for them to hinder his
                        proposed march by attacking the tribes in alliance with the Carthaginians.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The latter plan seemed the best, and
                        they made preparations for attacking a city which from its proximity to the
                        river was called Hibera, the wealthiest city in that country. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as Hasdrubal became aware of this,
                        instead of going to the assistance of his allies he proceeded to attack a
                        city which had recently put itself under the protection of Rome. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> On this the Romans abandoned the siege which
                        they had begun and turned their arms against Hasdrubal himself. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For some days they remained encamped at a
                        distance of about five miles from each other, and though frequent skirmishes
                        took place there was no general action. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At
                        last on the same day, as though by previous agreement, the signal was given
                        on both sides and they descended with their entire forces on to the plain.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman line was in three divisions.
                        Some of the light infantry were posted between the leading ranks of the
                        legions, the rest amongst those behind; the cavalry closed the wings.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal strengthened his centre with
                        his Spaniards, on the right wing he posted the Carthaginians, on the left
                        the Africans and the mercenaries, the Numidian horse he stationed in front
                        of the Carthaginian infantry, and the rest of the cavalry in front of the
                        Africans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Not all the Numidian horse,
                        however, were on the right wing, but only those who were trained to manage
                        two horses at the same time like circus-riders and, when the battle was at
                        the hottest, were in the habit of jumping off the wearied horse on to the
                        fresh one, such were the agility of the riders and the docility of the
                        horses. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These were the dispositions on each side,
                        and whilst the two armies were standing ready to engage, their commanders
                        felt almost equally confident of victory, for neither side was much superior
                        to the other either in the numbers or the quality of the troops. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> With the men themselves it was far otherwise.
                        Though the Romans were fighting far away from their homes their generals had
                        no difficulty in making them realise that they were fighting for Italy and
                        for Rome. They knew that it hung upon the issue of that fight whether they
                        were to see their homes again or not, and they resolutely determined either
                        to conquer or to die. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The other army
                        possessed nothing like the same determination, for they were most of them
                        natives of Spain and would rather be defeated in Spain than win the victory
                        and be dragged to Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At the first
                        onset, almost before they had hurled their javelins, the centre gave ground,
                        and when the Romans came on in a tremendous charge they turned and fled.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The brunt of the fighting now fell
                        upon the wings; the Carthaginians pressed forward on the right, the Africans
                        on the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> left, and slowly wheeling round
                        attacked the advancing Roman infantry on both flanks. But the whole force
                        had now concentrated on the centre, and forming front in both directions
                        beat back the attack on their flanks. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> So
                        two separate actions were going on. The Romans, having already repulsed
                        Hasdrubal's centre, and having the advantage as regarded both the numbers
                        and the strength of their men, proved themselves undoubtedly superior on
                        both fronts. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A very large number of the
                        enemy fell in these two attacks, and had not their centre taken to hasty
                        flight almost before the battle began, very few would have survived out of
                        their whole army. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The cavalry took no
                        part whatever in the fighting, for no sooner did the Moors and Numidians see
                        the centre of the line giving way than they fled precipitately, leaving the
                        wings exposed, and even driving the elephants before them. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Hasdrubal waited to see the final issue of the battle
                        and then escaped out of the slaughter with a few followers. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> The camp was seized and plundered by the Romans.
                        This battle secured for Rome all the tribes who were wavering and deprived
                        Hasdrubal of all hopes of taking his army to Italy or even of remaining with
                        anything like safety in Spain. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> When the
                        contents of the despatch from the Scipios was made known in Rome, the
                        gratification felt was not so much on account of the victory as that
                        Hasdrubal's march into Italy was at an end. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these incidents in Spain, Petelia
                        in Bruttium was taken by Himilco, one of Hannibal's lieutenants, after a
                        siege which lasted several months. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That
                        victory cost the Carthaginians heavy losses in both killed and wounded, for
                        the defenders only yielded after they had been starved out. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They had consumed all their corn and eaten every kind
                        of animal whether ordinarily used as food or not, and at last kept
                        themselves alive by eating leather and grass and roots and the soft bark of
                        trees and leaves picked from shrubs. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It
                        was not until they had no longer strength to stand on the walls or to bear
                        the weight of their armour that they were subdued. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After the capture of Petelia the Carthaginian marched
                        his army to Consentia. The defence here was less obstinate and the place
                        surrendered in a few days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About the same
                        time an army of Bruttians invested the Greek city of Croton. At one time
                        this city had been a military power, but it had been overtaken by so many
                        and such serious reverses that its whole population was now reduced to less
                        than 2000 souls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The enemy found no
                        difficulty in gaining possession of a city so denuded of defenders; the
                        citadel alone was held, after some had sought refuge there from the massacre
                        and confusion which followed the capture of the city. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Locri also went over to the Bruttians and Carthaginians
                        after the aristocracy of the city had betrayed the populace. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The people of Rhegium alone in all that country
                        remained loyal to the Romans and kept their independence to the end. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The same change of feeling extended to
                        Sicily and even the house of Hiero did not altogether shrink from deserting
                        Rome. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Gelo, the eldest son of the family,
                        treating with equal contempt his aged father and the alliance with Rome,
                        after the defeat of Cannae, went over to the Carthaginians. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> He was arming the natives and making friendly
                        overtures to the cities in alliance with Rome and would have brought about a
                        revolution in Sicily had he not been removed by the hand of death, a death
                        so opportune that it cast suspicion even on his father. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Such were the serious occurrences in Italy, Africa,
                        Sicily, and Spain during the year (216 B.C.). Towards the close of the year
                        Q. Fabius Maximus asked the senate to allow him to dedicate the temple of
                        Venus Erycina which he had vowed when Dictator. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The senate passed a decree that Tiberius Sempronius the
                        consul-elect should immediately upon his entering office propose a
                        resolution to the people that Q. Fabius be one of the two commissioners
                        appointed to dedicate the temple. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After
                        the death of M. Aemilius Lepidus, who had been augur and twice consul, his
                        three sons, Lucius, Marcus, and Quintus, celebrated funeral games in his
                        honour for three days and exhibited twenty-two pairs of gladiators in the
                        Forum. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The curule aediles, C. Laetorius
                        and Ti. Sempronius Gracchus, consul elect, who during his aedileship had
                        been Master of the Horse, celebrated the Roman Games; the celebration lasted
                        three days. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The Plebeian Games given by
                        the aediles Marcus Aurelius Cotta and Marcus Claudius Marcellus were
                        solemnised three times. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The third year of
                        the Punic war had run its course when Ti. Sempronius entered on his
                        consulship on March 15. The praetors were Q. Fulvius Flaccus, who had been
                        previously censor and twice consul, and M. Valerius Laevinus; the former
                        exercised jurisdiction over citizens, the latter over foreigners. App.
                        Claudius Pulcher had the province of Sicily allotted to him, Q. Mucius
                        Scaevola that of Sardinia. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The people
                        made an order investing M. Marcellus with the powers of a proconsul, because
                        he was the only one out of the Roman commanders who had gained any successes
                        in Italy since the disaster at Cannae. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first day the senate met for business
                        at the Capitol they passed a decree that the war-tax for that year should be
                        doubled, and that half the whole amount should be <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> collected at once to furnish pay for all the soldiers,
                        except those who had been present at Cannae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> As regarded the armies they decreed that Ti. Sempronius should fix a day
                        on which the two City legions were to muster at Cales, and that they should
                        march from there to Claudius' camp above Suessula. The legions there, mostly
                        made up from the army which fought at Cannae, were to be transferred by App.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Claudius Pulcher to Sicily and the
                        legions in Sicily were to be brought to Rome. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> M. Claudius Marcellus was sent to take command of the
                        army which had been ordered to assemble at Cales and he received orders to
                        conduct it to Claudius' camp. Ti. Maecilius Croto was sent by App.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Claudius to take over the old army and
                        conduct it to Sicily. At first people waited in silent expectation for the
                        consul to hold an Assembly for the election of a colleague, but when they
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> saw that M. Marcellus, whom they
                        particularly wished to have as consul this year after his brilliant success
                        as praetor, was kept out of the way, murmurs began to be heard in the
                        Senate-house. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the consul became aware
                        of this he said, "It is to the interest of the State, senators, that M.
                        Claudius has gone into Campania to effect the exchange of armies, and it is
                        equally to the interest of the State that notice of election should not be
                        given until he has discharged the commission entrusted to him and returned
                        home, so that you may have for your consul the man whom the circumstances of
                        the republic call for and whom you most of all wish for." After this nothing
                        more was said about the election till Marcellus returned. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the two commissioners were
                        appointed for the dedication of temples: T. Otacilius Crassus dedicated the
                        temple to Mens, Q. Fabius Maximus the one to Venus Erycina. Both are on the
                        Capitol, separated only by a water channel. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> In the case of the three hundred Campanian knights, who after loyally
                        serving their time in Sicily had now come to Rome, a proposal was made to
                        the people that they should receive the full rights of Roman citizenship and
                        should be entered on the roll of the burghers of Cumae, reckoning from the
                        day previous to the revolt of the Campanians from Rome. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The main reason for this proposal was their declaration
                        that they did not know to what people they belonged, as they had abandoned
                        their old country and had not yet been admitted as citizens into that to
                        which they had returned. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On Marcellus'
                        return from the army notice was given of the election of a consul in the
                        place of L. Postumius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Marcellus was
                        elected by a quite unanimous vote in order that he might take up his
                        magistracy at once. Whilst he was assuming the duties of the consulship
                        thunder was heard; the augurs were summoned and gave it as their opinion
                        that there was some informality in his election. The patricians spread a
                        report that as that was the first time that two plebeian consuls were
                        elected together, the gods were showing their displeasure. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Marcellus resigned his office and Q. Fabius Maximus was
                        appointed in his place; this was his third consulship. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> This year the sea appeared to be on fire; at Sinuessa a
                        cow brought forth a colt; the statues in the temple of Juno Sospita at
                        Lanuvium sweated blood and a shower of stones fell round the temple. For
                        this portent there were the usual nine days' religious observances; the
                        other portents were duly expiated. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls divided the armies between
                        them; the army at Teanum which M. Junius the Dictator had been commanding
                        passed to Fabius, Sempronius took command of the volunteer slaves there and
                        25,000 troops furnished by the allies; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the
                        legions which had returned from Sicily were assigned to M. Valerius the
                        praetor; M. Claudius was sent to the army which was in camp above Suessa to
                        protect Nola; the praetors went to their respective provinces in Sicily and
                        Sardinia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls issued a notice that
                        whenever the senate was summoned the senators and all who had the right of
                        speaking in the senate should meet at the Capena gate. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The praetors whose duty it was to hear cases set up
                        their tribunals near the public bathing place and ordered all litigants to
                        answer to their recognisances at that place, and there they administered
                        justice during the year. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the meanwhile
                        the news was brought to Carthage that things had gone badly in Spain and
                        that almost all the communities in that country had gone over to Rome. Mago,
                        Hannibal's brother, was preparing to transport to Italy a force of 12,000
                        infantry, 1500 cavalry, and 20 elephants, escorted by a fleet of 60
                        warships. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the receipt of this news,
                        however, some were in favour of Mago, with <milestone n="7??" unit="section"
                        /> such a fleet and army as he had, going to Spain instead of Italy, but
                        whilst they were deliberating there was a sudden gleam of hope that Sardinia
                        might be recovered. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were told that
                        "there was only a small Roman army there, the old praetor, A. Cornelius, who
                        knew the province well, was leaving and a fresh one was expected; <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> the Sardinians, too, were tired of their long
                        subjection, and during the last twelve months the government had been harsh
                        and rapacious and had crushed them with a heavy tax and an unfair exaction
                        of corn. Nothing was wanting but a leader to head their revolt. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> "This report was brought by some secret agents
                        from their leaders, the prime mover in the matter being Hampsicora, the most
                        influential and wealthy man amongst them at that time. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Perturbed by the news from Spain, and at the same time
                        elated by the Sardinian report, they sent Mago with his fleet and army to
                        Spain <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> and selected Hasdrubal to conduct
                        the operations in Sardinia, assigning to him a force about as large as the
                        one they had furnished to Mago. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After they had transacted all the
                        necessary business in Rome the consuls began to prepare for war. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Ti. Sempronius gave his soldiers notice of the
                        date when they were to assemble at Sinuessa, and Q. Fabius, after previously
                        consulting the senate, issued a proclamation warning every one to convey the
                        corn from their fields into the fortified cities by the <milestone n="15??"
                            unit="section"/> first day of the following June, all those who failed
                        to do so would have their land laid waste, their farms burnt, and they
                        themselves would be sold into slavery. Even the praetors who had been
                        appointed to administer the law were not exempted from military duties.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It was decided that Valerius should
                        be sent to Apulia to take over the army from Terentius: when the legions
                        came from Sicily he was to employ them mainly for the defence of that
                        district and send the army of Terentius under one of his lieutenants to
                        Tarentum. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> A fleet of twenty-five vessels
                        was also supplied him for the protection of the coast between Brundisium and
                        Tarentum. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> A fleet of equal strength was
                        assigned to Q. Fulvius, the praetor in charge of the City, for the defence
                        of the coast near Rome. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> C. Terentius, as
                        proconsul, was commissioned to raise a force in the territory of Picenum to
                        defend that part of the country. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Lastly,
                        T. Otacilius Crassus was despatched to Sicily, after he had dedicated the
                        temple of Mens, with full powers as propraetor to take command of the fleet.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This struggle between the most powerful
                        nations in the world was attracting the attention of all men, kings and
                        peoples alike, and <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> especially of Philip,
                        the King of Macedon, as he was comparatively near to Italy, separated from
                        it only by the Ionian Sea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he first
                        heard the rumour of Hannibal's passage of the Alps, delighted as he was at
                        the outbreak of war between Rome and Carthage, he was still undecided, till
                        their relative strength had been tested, which of the two he would prefer to
                        have the victory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But after the third
                        battle had been fought and the victory rested with the Carthaginians for the
                        third time, he inclined to the side which Fortune favoured and sent
                        ambassadors to Hannibal. Avoiding the ports of Brundisium and Tarentum which
                        were guarded by Roman ships, they landed near the temple of Juno Lacinia.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst traversing Apulia on their way
                        to Capua they fell into the midst of the Roman troops who were defending the
                        district, and were conducted to Valerius Laevinus, the praetor, who was
                        encamped near Luceria. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Xenophanes, the
                        head of the legation, explained, without the slightest fear or hesitation,
                        that he had been sent by the king to form a league of friendship with Rome,
                        and that he was conveying his instructions to the consuls and senate and
                        people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Amidst the defection of so many
                        old allies, the praetor was delighted beyond measure at the prospect of a
                        new alliance with so illustrious a monarch, and gave his enemies a most
                        hospitable reception. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He assigned them an
                        escort, and pointed out carefully what route they should take, what places
                        and passes were held by the Romans and what by the enemy. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Xenophanes passed through the Roman troops into
                        Campania and thence by the nearest route reached Hannibal's camp. He made a
                        treaty of friendship with him on these terms: <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> King Philip was to sail to Italy with as large a fleet
                        as possible-he was, it appears, intending to fit out two hundred ships-and
                        ravage the coast, and carry on war by land and sea to the utmost of his
                        power; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> when the war was over the whole of
                        Italy, including Rome itself, was to be the possession of the Carthaginians
                        and Hannibal, and all the plunder was to go to Hannibal; <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> when the Carthaginians had thoroughly subdued Italy
                        they were to sail to Greece and make war upon such nations as the king
                        wished; the cities on the mainland and the islands lying off Macedonia were
                        to form part of Philip's kingdom. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These were, in effect, the terms on which
                        the treaty was concluded between the Carthaginian general and the King of
                        Macedon. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On their return the envoys were
                        accompanied by commissioners sent by Hannibal to obtain the king's
                        ratification of the treaty: they were Gisgo, Bostar, and Mago. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> They reached the spot near the temple of Juno
                        Lacinia, where they had left their ship moored in a hidden creek, and set
                        sail for Greece. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When they were out to sea
                        they were descried by the Roman fleet which was guarding the Calabrian
                        coast. Valerius Flaccus sent some light boats to chase and bring back the
                        strange vessel. At first the king's men attempted flight, but finding that
                        they were being overhauled they surrendered to the Romans. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> When they were brought before the admiral of the fleet
                        he questioned them as to who they were, where they had come from, and
                        whither they were sailing. Xenophanes, who had so far been very lucky, began
                        to make up a tale; he said that he had been sent by Philip to Rome and had
                        succeeded in reaching M. Valerius, as he was the only person he could get to
                        safely; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> he had not been able to go through
                        Campania as it was beset by the enemy's troops. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Then the Carthaginian dress and manner of Hannibal's
                        agents aroused suspicion, and on being questioned their speech betrayed
                        them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Their comrades were at once taken
                        aside and terrified by threats, a letter from Hannibal to Philip was
                        discovered, and also the articles of agreement between the King of Macedon
                        and the Carthaginian general. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the
                        investigation was completed, it seemed best to carry the prisoners and their
                        companions as soon as possible to the senate at Rome or to the consuls,
                        wherever they were. Five of the swiftest ships were selected for the purpose
                        and L. Valerius Antias was placed in charge of the expedition with
                        instructions to distribute the envoys amongst the ships under guard and to
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> be careful that no conversation was
                        allowed amongst them or any communication of plans. </p>
                    <p> During this time A. Cornelius Mammula on leaving his province made a report
                        on the condition of Sardinia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> All, he
                        said, were contemplating war and revolt; Q. Mucius, who had succeeded him,
                        had been affected by the unhealthy climate and impure water and had fallen
                        into an illness which was tedious rather than dangerous, and would make him
                        for some considerable time unfit to bear the responsibilities of war.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The army, too, which was quartered
                        there, though strong enough for the occupation of a peaceable province, was
                        quite inadequate for the war which seemed likely to break out. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The senate made a decree that Q. Fulvius Flaccus
                        should raise a force of 5000 infantry and 400 cavalry and arrange for its
                        immediate transport to Sardinia, <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> and
                        further that he should send whom he considered the most suitable man,
                        invested with full powers, to conduct operations until Mucius recovered his
                        health. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He selected T. Manlius Torquatus,
                        who had been twice consul as well as censor, and during his consulship had
                        subdued the Sardinians. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> About the same
                        time a Carthaginian fleet which had been despatched to Sardinia under the
                        command of Hasdrubul, surnamed "the Bald," was caught in a storm and driven
                        on the Balearic Isles. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> So much damage was
                        caused, not only to the rigging but also to the hulls, that the vessels were
                        hauled ashore and a considerable time was spent in repairing them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Italy the war had been less vigorously
                        conducted since the battle of Cannae; for the strength of the one side was
                        broken and the temper of the other enervated. Under these circumstances the
                        Campanians made an attempt by themselves to become masters of Cumae.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They first tried persuasion, but as
                        they could not succeed in inducing them to revolt from Rome, they decided to
                        employ stratagem. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All the Campanians held
                        a sacrificial service at stated intervals at Hamae. They informed the Cumans
                        that the Campanian senate was going there, and they asked the Cuman senate
                        also to be present in order to come to a common understanding, so that both
                        peoples might have the same allies and the same enemies. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> They also promised that they would have an armed force
                        there, to guard against any danger from either Romans or Carthaginians.
                        Although the Cumans suspected a plot, they made no difficulty about going,
                        for they thought that by thus consenting they would be able to conceal a
                        maneuver of their own. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul Tiberius
                        Sempronius had in the meanwhile purified his army at Sinuessa, the appointed
                        rendezvous, and after crossing the Vulturnus pitched his camp near Liternum.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As there was nothing for them to do in
                        camp, he put his men through frequent war maneuvers to accustom the
                        recruits, most of whom were volunteer slaves, to follow the standards and
                        know their places in the ranks when in action. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> In carrying out these exercises, the general's main
                        object-and he had given similar instructions to the officers-was that there
                        should be no class-feeling in the ranks, through the slaves being twitted
                        with their former condition; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the old
                        soldiers were to regard themselves as on a perfect equality with the
                        recruits, the free men with the slaves; all to whom Rome had entrusted her
                        standards and her arms were to be regarded as equally honourable, equally
                        well-born; Fortune had compelled them to adopt this state of things, and now
                        that it was adopted she compelled them to acquiesce to it. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The soldiers were quite as anxious to obey these
                        instructions as the officers were to enforce them, and in a short time the
                        men had become so fused together <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> that
                        it was almost forgotten what condition of life each man had been in before
                        he became a soldier. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While Gracchus was thus occupied
                        messengers from Cumae informed him of the proposals made by the Campanians a
                        few days previously and of their reply, and that the festival was to be held
                        in three days' time, when not only the whole senate would be there but also
                        the Campanian army in camp. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Gracchus gave
                        the Cumans orders to remove everything from their fields into the city and
                        to remain within their walls, whilst he himself moved his camp to Cumae the
                        day before the Campanians were to perform their sacrifice. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Hamae was about three miles distant. The Campanians had
                        already, as arranged, assembled there in large numbers and not far away
                        Marius Alfius, the "Medixtuticus" (the chief magistrate of the Campanians),
                        was secretly encamped with 14,000 troops, but he <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> was more intent on making preparations for the
                        sacrifice and the stratagem he was to execute during its performance than on
                        fortifying his camp or any other military duty. The ceremonial took place at
                        night and was over by midnight. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Gracchus
                        thought this the best time for his purpose, <milestone n="16??"
                            unit="section"/> and after stationing guards at the camp gate to prevent
                        any one from conveying information of his design, he ordered his men to
                        refresh themselves and get what sleep they could at four o'clock in the
                        afternoon so that they might be ready to assemble round the standards as
                        soon as it was dark. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> About the first
                        watch he ordered the advance to be made and the army marched in silence to
                        Hamae, which they reached at midnight. The Campanian camp, as might be
                        expected during a nocturnal festival, was negligently guarded, and he made a
                        simultaneous attack on all sides of it. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        Some were slain whilst stretched in slumber, others whilst returning unarmed
                        after the ceremony. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> In the confusion and
                        terror of the night more than 2000 men were killed, including their general,
                        Marius Alfius, and 34 standards seized. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After getting possession of the enemies'
                        camp with a loss of less than 100 men, Gracchus speedily retired, fearing an
                        attack from Hannibal, who had his camp at Tifata, overlooking Capua. Nor
                        were his anticipations groundless. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> No
                        sooner had the news of the disaster reached Capua than Hannibal, expecting
                        to find at Hamae an army, composed mostly of raw recruits and slaves, wildly
                        delighted at their victory, despoiling their vanquished foes and carrying
                        off the plunder, hurried on with all speed past Capua, and ordered all the
                        Campanian fugitives he met <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> to be
                        escorted to Capua and the wounded to be carried there in wagons. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> But when he got to Hamae he found the camp
                        abandoned, nothing was to be seen but the traces of the recent slaughter and
                        the bodies of his allies lying about everywhere. Some advised him to march
                        straight to Cumae and attack the place. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Nothing would have suited his wishes better for, after his failure to secure
                        Neapolis, he was very anxious to get possession of Cumae that he might have
                        one maritime city at all events. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As,
                        however, his soldiers in their hurried march had brought nothing with them
                        beyond their arms he returned to his camp on Tifata. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The next day, yielding to the importunities of the
                        Campanians, he marched back to Cumae with all the necessary appliances for
                        attacking the city, and after effectually devastating the neighbourhood,
                        fixed his camp at the distance of one mile from the place. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Gracchus still remained in occupation of Cumae, more
                        because he was ashamed to desert the allies who were imploring his
                        protection and that of the Roman people than because he felt sufficiently
                        assured as to his army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The other consul,
                        Fabius, who was encamped at Cales, did not venture to cross the Vulturnus;
                        his attention was occupied first with taking fresh auspices and then with
                        the portents which were being announced one after another, and which the
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> soothsayers assured him would be
                        very difficult to avert. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these causes kept Fabius from
                        moving, Sempronius was invested, and the siege works were now actually in
                        operation. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A huge wooden tower on wheels
                        had been brought up against the walls and the Roman consul constructed
                        another still higher upon the wall itself, which was fairly high and which
                        served as a platform, after he had placed stout beams across. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The besieged garrison protected the walls of the
                        city by hurling stones and sharpened stakes and other missiles from their
                        tower; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> at last when they saw the other
                        tower brought up to the walls they flung blazing brands over it and caused a
                        large fire. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Terrified by the conflagration
                        the crowd of soldiers in it flung themselves down and at the same moment a
                        sortie was made from two of the gates, the outposts of the enemy were
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> overpowered and driven in flight to
                        their camp, so that for that day the Carthaginians were more like a besieged
                        than a besieging force. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As many as 1300
                        Carthaginians were killed and 59 taken prisoners who had been surprised
                        while standing careless and unconcerned round the walls or at the outposts,
                        and least of all fearing a sortie. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Before
                        the enemy had time to recover from their panic Gracchus gave the signal to
                        retire and withdrew with his men inside the walls. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The following day, Hannibal, expecting that the consul,
                        elated with his success, would be prepared to fight a regular battle, formed
                        his line on the ground between his camp and the city; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> when, however, he saw that not a single man moved from
                        his usual post of defence and that no risks were being taken through rash
                        confidence, he returned to Tifata without accomplishing anything. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Just at the time when the siege of Cumae was
                        raised Ti. Sempronius, surnamed "Longus," fought a successful action with
                        the Carthaginian Hanno at Grumentum in Lucania. Over 2000 were killed, 280
                        men and 41 military standards were captured. Driven out of Lucania, Hanno
                        retreated to Bruttium. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Amongst the
                        Hirpini, also, three towns which had revolted from Rome, Vercellium,
                        Vescellium, and Sicilinum, were retaken by the praetor M. Valerius, and the
                        authors of the revolt beheaded. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Over 5000
                        prisoners were sold, the rest of the booty was presented to the soldiers,
                        and the army marched back to Luceria. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these incidents amongst the
                        Lucanians and Hirpini, the five ships which were carrying the Macedonian and
                        Carthaginian agents to Rome, after sailing almost round the whole of Italy
                        in their passage from the upper to the lower sea were off Cumae, when
                        Gracchus, uncertain whether they belonged to friends or foes, sent vessels
                        from his own fleet to intercept them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        After mutual questionings those on board learnt that the consul was at
                        Cumae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The vessels accordingly were
                        brought into the harbour and the prisoners were brought before the consul
                        and the letters placed in his hands. He read the letters of Philip and
                        Hannibal through and sent everything under seal by land to the senate, the
                        agents he ordered to be taken by sea. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        letters and the agents both reached Rome the same day, and when it was
                        ascertained that what the agents said in their examination agreed with the
                        letters, the senate were filled with very gloomy apprehensions. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> They recognised what a heavy burden a war with
                        Macedon would impose upon them at a time when it was all they could do to
                        bear the weight of the Punic war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They did
                        not, however, so far give way to despondency as not to enter at once upon a
                        discussion as to how they could divert the enemy from Italy by themselves
                        commencing hostilities against him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Orders
                        were given for the agents to be kept in chains and their companions to be
                        sold as slaves; they also decided to equip twenty vessels in addition to the
                        twenty-five which P. Valerius Flaccus already had under his command.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After these had been fitted out and
                        launched, the five ships which had carried the agents were added and thirty
                        vessels left Ostia for Tarentum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Publius
                        Valerius was instructed to place on board the soldiers which had belonged to
                        Varro's army and which were now at Tarentum under the command of L.
                        Apustius, and with his combined fleet of fifty-five vessels he was not only
                        to protect the coast of Italy but try to obtain information about the
                        hostile attitude of Macedon. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If Philip's
                        designs should prove to correspond to the captured despatches and the
                        statements of the agents, he was to write to Marcus Valerius, the praetor,
                        to <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> that effect and then, after placing
                        his army under the command of L. Apustius, go to the fleet at Tarentum and
                        sail across to Macedonia at the first opportunity and do his utmost to
                        confine Philip within his own dominions. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        A decree was made that the money which had been sent to Appius Claudius in
                        Sicily to be returned to King Hiero should now be devoted to the maintenance
                        of the fleet and the expenses of the Macedonian war, and it was conveyed to
                        Tarentum through L. Antistius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Two
                        hundred thousand modii of wheat and barley were sent at the same time by
                        King Hiero. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these various steps were being
                        taken, one of the captured ships which were on their way to Rome escaped
                        during the voyage to Philip, and he then learnt that his agents had been
                        captured together with his despatches. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As
                        he did not know what understanding they had come to with Hannibal, or what
                        proposals Hannibal's agents were bringing to him, he despatched a second
                        embassy with the same instructions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Their
                        names were Heraclitus, surnamed Scotinus, Crito of Boeotia, and Sositheus
                        the Magnesian. They accomplished their mission successfully, but the summer
                        passed away before the king could attempt any active measures. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> So important was the seizure of that one ship
                        with the king's agents on board in delaying the outbreak of the war which
                        now threatened Rome! Fabius at last succeeded in expiating the portents and
                        crossed the Vulturnus; both consuls now resumed the campaign round Capua.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Combulteria, Trebula, and Austicula,
                        all of which had revolted to Hannibal, were successfully attacked by Fabius,
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> and the garrisons which Hannibal had
                        placed in them as well as a large number of Campanians were made prisoners.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At Nola, the senate were on the side
                        of the Romans, as they had been the year before, and the populace, who were
                        on the side of Hannibal, were hatching secret plots for the murder of the
                        aristocrats and the betrayal of the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        To prevent them from carrying out their intentions Fabius marched between
                        Capua and Hannibal's camp on Tifata and established himself in Claudius'
                        camp overlooking Suessula. From there he sent M. Marcellus, who was
                        propraetor, with the force under his command to occupy Nola. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The active operations in Sardinia which
                        had been dropped owing to the serious illness of Q. Mucius were resumed
                        under the direction of T. Manlius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                        hauled ashore his war-ships and furnished the seamen and rowers with arms,
                        so that they might be available for service on land; with these and the army
                        he had taken over from the praetor he made up a force of 22,000 infantry and
                        1200 cavalry. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> With this combined force he
                        invaded the hostile territory and fixed his camp at no great distance from
                        Hampsicora's lines. Hampsicora himself happened to be absent; he had paid a
                        visit to the Pelliti-Sardinians in order to arm the younger men amongst them
                        so as to increase his own strength. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His
                        son Hostus was in command and in the impetuosity of youth he rashly offered
                        battle, with the result that he was defeated and put to flight. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> 3000 Sardinians were killed in that battle and
                        800 taken alive; the rest of the army after wandering in their flight
                        through fields and woods heard that their general had fled to a place called
                        Cornus, the chief town of the district, and thither they directed their
                        flight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That battle would have finished
                        the war had not the Carthaginian fleet under Hasdrubal, which had been
                        driven by a storm down to the Balearic Isles, arrived in time to revive
                        their hopes of renewing the war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When
                        Manlius heard of its arrival he retired upon Carales, and this gave
                        Hampsicora an opportunity of forming a junction with the Carthaginian.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal disembarked his force and
                        sent the ships back to Carthage, and then, under Hampsicora's guidance,
                        proceeded to harry and waste the land belonging to the allies of Rome. He
                        would have gone as far as Carales if Manlius had not met him with his army
                        and checked his widespread ravages. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At
                        first the two camps faced each other, with only a small space between; then
                        small sorties and skirmishes took place with varying results; at last it
                        came to a battle, a regular action, which lasted for four hours. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> For a long time the Carthaginians made the issue
                        doubtful, the Sardinians, who were accustomed to defeat, being easily
                        beaten, but at last when they saw the whole field covered with dead and
                        flying <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> Sardinians they too gave way,
                        but when they turned to flee the Roman wing which had routed the Sardinians
                        wheeled round and hemmed them in. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then it
                        was more of a massacre than a battle. 12,000 of the enemy, Sardinians and
                        Carthaginians, were slain, about 3700 were made prisoners, and 27 military
                        standards were captured. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> What more than anything else made the
                        battle glorious and memorable was the capture of the commander-in-chief,
                        Hasdrubal, and also of Hanno and Mago, two Carthaginian nobles. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Mago was a member of the house of Barca, a near
                        relative of Hannibal; Hanno had taken the lead in the Sardinian revolt and
                        was unquestionably the chief instigator of the war. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The battle was no less famous for the fate which
                        overtook the Sardinian generals; Hampsicora's son, Hostus, fell on the
                        field, and when Hampsicora, who was fleeing from the carnage with a few
                        horsemen, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> heard of his son's death, he
                        was so crushed by the tidings, coming as it did on the top of all the other
                        disasters, that in the dead of night, when none could hinder his purpose, he
                        slew himself with his own hand. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The rest
                        of the fugitives found shelter as they had done before in Cornus, but
                        Manlius leading his victorious troops against it effected its capture in a
                        few days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On this the other cities which
                        had espoused the cause of Hampsicora and the Carthaginians gave hostages and
                        surrendered to him. He imposed upon each of them a tribute of money and
                        corn; the amount was proportioned to their resources and also to the share
                        they had taken in the revolt. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After this
                        he returned to Carales. There the ships which had been hauled ashore were
                        launched, the troops he had brought with him were re-embarked, and he sailed
                        for Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On his arrival he reported to
                        the senate the complete subjugation of Sardinia, and made over the money to
                        the quaestors, the corn to the aediles, and the prisoners to Q. Fulvius, the
                        praetor. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> During this time T. Otacilius had crossed
                        with his fleet from Lilybaeum to the coast of Africa and was ravaging the
                        territory of Carthage, when rumours came to him that Hasdrubal had recently
                        sailed from the Balearic Isles to Sardinia. He set sail for that island and
                        fell in with the Carthaginian fleet returning to Africa. A brief action
                        followed on the high seas in which Otacilius took seven ships with their
                        crews. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The rest dispersed in a panic far
                        and wide, as though they had been scattered by a storm. It so happened at
                        this time that Bomilcar arrived at Locri with reinforcements of men and
                        elephants and also with supplies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Appius
                        Claudius intended to surprise him, and with this view he led his army
                        hurriedly to Messana as though he were going to make a circuit of the
                        province, and finding the wind and tide favourable, crossed over to Locri.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Bomilcar had already left to join
                        Hanno in Bruttium and the Locrians shut their gates against the Romans;
                        Appius after all his efforts achieved no results and returned to Messana.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This same summer Marcellus made
                        frequent excursions from Nola, which he was holding with a garrison, into
                        the territory of the Hirpini and in the neighbourhood of Samnite Caudium.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Such utter devastation did he spread
                        everywhere with fire and sword that he revived throughout Samnium the memory
                        of her ancient disasters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Both nations sent envoys simultaneously to
                        Hannibal, who addressed him thus: "We have been the enemies of Rome,
                        Hannibal, from very early times. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At first
                        we fought her in our own might as long as our arms, our strength, sufficed
                        to protect us. When we could trust them no more we took our place by the
                        side of King Pyrrhus; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> when we were
                        abandoned by him we were compelled to accept terms of peace and by those
                        terms we stood for almost fifty years, down to the time of your arrival in
                        Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was your conspicuous courtesy
                        and kindness towards our fellow-countrymen who were your prisoners and whom
                        you sent back to us, quite as much as your courage and success, which have
                        so won our hearts that as long as you, our friend, are safe and prosperous
                        we should not fear-I do not say the Romans, but-even the wrath of heaven, if
                        I may say so without irreverence. But, good heavens! <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> while you are not only safe and victorious but actually
                        here amongst us, when you could almost hear the shrieks of our wives and
                        children and see our blazing houses, we have suffered such repeated
                        devastations this summer that it would seem as if M. Marcellus and not
                        Hannibal had been the victor at Cannae, and as if the Romans had good cause
                        to boast that you have only strength enough for one blow, and that like a
                        bee that has left its sting you are now inert and powerless. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> For a hundred years we have been at war with Rome
                        and no general, no army from without, has come to our aid save for the two
                        years when Pyrrhus used our soldiers to increase his strength rather than
                        use his strength to defend us. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I will not
                        boast of our successes-the two consuls with their armies whom we sent under
                        the yoke, and all the other fortunate or glorious events which we can
                        recall. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The trials and sufferings we then
                        went through can be recounted with less bitter feelings than those which are
                        happening today. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then great Dictators with
                        their Masters of the Horse would invade our borders, two consuls and two
                        consular armies found it necessary to act together against us, and they took
                        every precaution, careful scouting, reserves duly posted, their army in
                        order of battle, when they ravaged our country; now we are the prey of a
                        solitary propraetor and a small garrison at Nola! <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> They do not even march in military detachments, but
                        they scour the whole of our country like brigands and more carelessly than
                        if they were roaming about on Roman ground. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> The reason is simply this: you do not defend us, and our soldiery who
                        could protect us if they were at home are all serving under your standards.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> I should be utterly ignorant of you
                        and your army if I did not think it an easy task for the man, by whom to my
                        knowledge so many Roman armies have been routed and laid low, to crush these
                        plunderers of our country while they are roving about in disorder and
                        wandering wherever any one is led by hopes of plunder, however futile such
                        hopes may be. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They will be the prey of a
                        few Numidians, and you will relieve both us and Nola of its garrison if only
                        you count the men whom you thought worthy of your alliance still worthy of
                        your protection." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To all this Hannibal replied: "You
                        Samnites and Hirpini are doing everything at once; you point out your
                        sufferings and ask for protection and complain of being unprotected and
                        neglected. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But you ought to have first
                        made your representations, then asked for protection, and if you did not
                        obtain it then only should you have complained that you had sought help in
                        vain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I shall not lead my army into the
                        country of the Hirpini and Samnites because I do not want to be a burden to
                        you, but I shall march into those districts belonging to the allies of Rome
                        which are nearest to me. By plundering these I shall satisfy and enrich my
                        soldiers and shall frighten the enemy sufficiently to make him leave you
                        alone. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As to the war with Rome, if
                        Trasumennus was a more famous battle than the Trebia, if Cannae was more
                        famous than Trasumennus, I shall make even the memory of Cannae fade in the
                        light of a greater and more brilliant victory." <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> With this reply and with munificent presents he
                        dismissed the envoys, and then leaving a somewhat small detachment on Tifata
                        marched with the rest of his army to Nola, whither Hanno also came with the
                        reinforcements he had brought from Carthage and the elephants. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Encamping at no great distance, he found out, on
                        inquiry, that everything was very different from the impression he had
                        received from the envoys. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> No one who
                        watched Marcellus' proceedings could ever say that he trusted to Fortune or
                        gave the enemy a chance through his rashness. Hitherto his plundering
                        expeditions had been made after careful reconnoitring, with strong supports
                        for the marauding parties and a secure retreat. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Now when he became aware of the enemy's approach, he
                        kept his force within the fortifications and ordered the senators of Nola to
                        patrol the ramparts and keep a sharp lookout all round and find out what the
                        enemy were doing. </p>
                    <p> Hanno had come close up to the walls, and, seeing amongst the senators
                        Herennius Bassus and Herius Pettius, asked for an interview with them.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having obtained permission from
                        Marcellus they went out to him. He addressed them through an interpreter.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After magnifying the merits and good
                        fortune of Hannibal and dwelling upon the decaying strength and greatness of
                        Rome, he went on to urge that even if Rome were <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> what she once had been, still men who knew by
                        experience how burdensome the Roman government was to their allies and with
                        what indulgence Hannibal had treated all those of his prisoners who belonged
                        to any Italian nation must surely prefer the alliance and friendship of
                        Carthage to those of Rome. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If both the
                        consuls and their two armies had been at Nola, they would still be no more a
                        match for Hannibal than they were at Cannae, how then could one praetor with
                        a few raw soldiers defend the place? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It
                        was of more importance to them whether the town were taken or surrendered
                        than it was to Hannibal; he would get possession of it in any case as he had
                        got possession of Capua and Nuceria. But what a difference there was between
                        the fate of Capua and that of Nola, they knew best, situated as they were
                        midway between the two places. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He did not
                        want to prophesy what would happen to the city if it were captured; he
                        preferred to pledge his word that if they would give up Marcellus and his
                        garrison and the city of Nola no one but themselves should dictate the terms
                        on which they would become allies and friends of Hannibal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Herennius Bassus briefly replied that the
                        friendship between Rome and Nola had now lasted many years, and up to that
                        day neither party had had any reason to regret it. If they had wished to
                        change their allegiance when the change came in their fortunes, it was too
                        late to do so now. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If they had thought of
                        surrendering to Hannibal would they have asked for a Roman garrison? They
                        were in perfect accord with those who had come to protect them, and they
                        would continue to be so to the last. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This
                        interview destroyed any expectations Hannibal might have formed of securing
                        Nola by treachery. He therefore drew his lines completely round the town so
                        that a simultaneous attack might be made on all sides. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When Marcellus saw that he was close up to the
                        ramparts, he drew up his men inside one of the gates and then burst out in a
                        fierce tumultuous charge. A few were overthrown and killed in the first
                        shock, but as men ran up into the fighting line and the two sides became
                        more equalised, the contest was beginning to be a severe one, and few
                        battles would have been more memorable had not a very heavy storm of rain
                        and wind separated the combatants. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                        retired for that day after only a brief encounter but in a state of great
                        exasperation, the Romans to the city, the Carthaginians to their camp. Of
                        the latter not more than thirty fell in the first attack; the Romans lost
                        fifty. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The rain fell without any
                        intermission all through the night and continued till the third hour of the
                        following day, so, though both sides were eager for battle, they remained
                        that day within their lines. The following day Hannibal sent part of his
                        force on a plundering expedition in the Nolan territory. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> No sooner was Marcellus aware of it than he formed his
                        line of battle, nor did Hannibal decline the challenge. There was about a
                        mile between his camp and the city, and within that space-it is all level
                        ground round Nola-the armies met. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        battle shout raised on both sides brought back the nearest amongst the
                        cohorts who had been sent off to plunder; the Nolans, too, on the other
                        side, took their place in the Roman line. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Marcellus addressed a few words of encouragement and thanks to them, and
                        told them to take their station amongst the reserve and help to carry the
                        wounded from the field, they were to keep out of the fighting unless they
                        received the signal from him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle was obstinately contested; the
                        generals encouraged the men, and the men fought to the utmost of their
                        strength. Marcellus urged his men to press vigorously on those whom they had
                        vanquished only three days ago, who had been driven in flight from Cumae,
                        and whom he had himself, with another army, defeated the year before.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "All his forces," he said, "are not in
                        the field, some are roving through the land bent on plunder, whilst those
                        who are fighting are enervated by the luxury of Capua and have worn
                        themselves out through a whole winter's indulgence in wine and women and
                        every kind of debauchery. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They have lost
                        their force and vigour, they have dissipated that strength of mind and body
                        in which they surmounted the Alpine peaks. The men who did that are mere
                        wrecks now; they can hardly bear the weight of their armour on their limbs
                        while they fight. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Capua has proved to be
                        Hannibal's Cannae. All soldierly courage; all military discipline, all glory
                        won in the past, all hopes for the future have been extinguished there."
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By showing his contempt for the enemy,
                        Marcellus raised the spirits of his men. Hannibal, on the other hand,
                        reproached his own men in much more severe terms. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> "I recognise," he said, "the same arms and standards
                        here which I saw and used at the Trebia, at Trasumennus, and finally at
                        Cannae, but not the same soldiers. It is quite certain that I led one army
                        into winter quarters at Capua and marched out with quite a different one.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Are you, whom two consular armies
                        never withstood, hardly able now to hold your own against a subordinate
                        officer, with his one legion and its contingent of allies? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Is Marcellus to challenge us with impunity a second
                        time with his raw recruits and Nolan supports? Where is that soldier of mine
                        who dragged the consul, C. Flaminius, from his horse and struck off his
                        head? Where is the one who slew L. Paulus at Cannae? Has the sword lost its
                        edge; have your right hands lost their power? <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Or has any other miracle happened? Though but few
                        yourselves, you have been wont to vanquish an enemy that far outnumbered
                        you; now you can hardly stand up against a force far smaller than your own.
                        You used to boast, tongue-valiant as you are, that you would take Rome by
                        storm if any one would lead you. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Well, I
                        want you to try your courage and your strength in a smaller task. Carry
                        Nola; it is a city in a plain, with no protection from river or from sea.
                        When ye have loaded yourselves with the plunder of such a wealthy city as
                        this, I will lead you or follow you wherever you wish." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Neither his censures nor his promises had
                        any effect in strengthening the morale of his men. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When they began to fall back in all directions the
                        spirits of the Romans rose, not only because of their general's cheering
                        words, but also because the Nolans raised encouraging shouts and fired them
                        with the glow of battle, until the Carthaginians fairly turned to flee and
                        were driven to their camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans were
                        anxious to storm the camp, but Marcellus marched them back to Nola amid the
                        joyous congratulations even of the populace who had before been more
                        inclined to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> More than
                        5000 of the enemy were killed that day and 600 made prisoners, 18 military
                        standards were taken and two elephants; four had been killed in the battle.
                        The Romans had less than a thousand killed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> The next day was spent by both sides in burying those killed in battle,
                        under an informal truce. Marcellus burnt the spoils taken from the enemy in
                        fulfilment of a vow to Vulcan. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Three days
                        later, owing, I fancy, to some disagreement or in hope of more liberal pay,
                        272 troopers, Numidians and Spaniards, deserted to Marcellus. The Romans
                        often availed themselves of their brave and loyal help in the war.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At its close a gift of land was made
                        in Spain to the Spaniards and in Africa to the Numidians as a reward for
                        their valour. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hanno was sent back into Bruttium with the
                        force he had brought, and Hannibal went into winter quarters in Apulia and
                        encamped in the neighbourhood of Arpi. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As
                        soon as Q. Fabius heard that Hannibal had left for Apulia, he had a quantity
                        of corn from Nola and Neapolis conveyed into the camp above Suessula, and
                        after strengthening its defences and leaving a force sufficient to hold the
                        position through the winter months, he moved his own camp nearer to Capua
                        and laid waste its territory with fire and sword. The Campanians had no
                        confidence whatever in their strength, but they were at last compelled to
                        come out of their gates into the open and form an entrenched camp in front
                        of the city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They had 6000 men under
                        arms, the infantry were absolutely useless, but the mounted men were more
                        efficient, so they kept harassing the enemy by cavalry skirmishes.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There were several Campanian nobles
                        serving as troopers, amongst them Cerrinus Vibellius, surnamed Taurea.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He was a citizen of Capua and by far
                        the finest soldier in the Campanian horse, so much so indeed that when he
                        was serving with the Romans there was only one Roman horseman that enjoyed
                        an equal reputation, and that was Claudius Asellus. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Taurea had for a long time been riding up to the
                        enemy's squadrons to see if he could find this man, and at last when there
                        was a moment's silence he asked where Claudius Asellus was. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> "He has often," he said, "argued with me about
                        our respective merits, let him settle the matter with the sword, and if he
                        is vanquished yield me the spolia opima, or if he is the victor take them
                        from me." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this was reported to Asellus in the
                        camp, he only waited till he could ask the consul whether he would be
                        allowed, against the regulations, to fight his challenger. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Permission being granted he at once armed himself and,
                        riding in front of the outposts, called Taurea by name and told him to meet
                        him wherever he pleased. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans had
                        already gone out in crowds to watch the duel, and the Campanians had not
                        only lined the rampart of their camp, but had gathered in large numbers on
                        the fortifications of the city. After a great flourish of words and
                        expressions of mutual defiance they levelled their spears and spurred their
                        horses. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As there was plenty of space they
                        kept evading each other's thrusts and the fight went on without either being
                        wounded. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then the Campanian said to the
                        Roman: "This will be a trial of skill between the horses and not their
                        riders unless we leave the open and go down into this hollow lane. There
                        will be no room for swerving aside there, we shall fight at close quarters."
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Almost before the words were out of
                        his mouth, Claudius leaped his horse into the lane, and Taurea, bolder in
                        words than deeds, shouted, "Never be an ass in a ditch," and this expression
                        became a rustic proverb. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After riding some
                        distance along the lane and finding no opponent, Claudius got into the open
                        and returned to camp, saying strong things about the cowardice of his
                        adversary. He was welcomed as victor with cheers and congratulations by his
                        comrades. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the accounts of this duel on
                        horseback some annalists record an additional circumstance-how far there is
                        any truth in it each must judge for himself, but it is at least remarkable.
                        They say that Claudius went in pursuit of Taurea who fled to the city, and
                        galloped in through one open gate and out through another unhurt, the enemy
                        standing dumbfounded at the extraordinary sight. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this incident the Roman camp was
                        undisturbed; the consul even shifted his camp further away that the
                        Campanians might complete their sowing, and he did not inflict any injury on
                        their land until the corn was high enough in the blade to yield fodder.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then he carried it off to Claudius'
                        camp above Suessula and built huts for his men to winter in there. M.
                        Claudius, the proconsul, received orders to keep a force at Nola sufficient
                        to protect the place and send the rest of his troops to Rome to prevent
                        their being a burden to the allies and an expense to the republic.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And Ti. Gracchus, having marched his
                        legions from Cumae to Luceria in Apulia, sent the praetor, M. Valerius, to
                        Brundisium with the army he had had at Luceria, and gave him orders to
                        protect the coast of the Sallentine territory and to make such provision as
                        might be necessary with regard to Philip and the Macedonian war. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Towards the end of the summer in which the events
                        we have been describing occurred, despatches from P. and Cn. Scipio arrived,
                        giving an account of the great successes they had achieved, but also stating
                        that money to pay the troops was needed, as also clothing and corn for the
                        army, whilst the seamen were destitute of everything. As regarded the pay,
                        if the treasury were low they (the Scipios) would devise some means by which
                        they could obtain it from the Spaniards, but all the other things must in
                        any case be sent from Rome, otherwise they could neither keep their army nor
                        the province. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the despatches had been
                        read there was no one present who did not admit that the statements were
                        true and the demands fair and just. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But
                        other considerations were present to their minds-the enormous land and sea
                        forces they had to keep up; the large fleet that would have to be fitted out
                        if the war with Macedon went forward; the condition of Sicily and Sardinia,
                        which before the war had helped to fill the treasury and were now hardly
                        able to support the armies which were protecting those islands; and, above
                        all, the shrinkage in the revenue. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For the
                        war-tax from which the national expenditure was met had diminished with the
                        number of those who paid it after the destruction of the armies at
                        Trasumennus and at Cannae, and if the few survivors had to pay at a very
                        much higher rate, they too, would perish, though not in battle. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> If, therefore, the State could not be upheld by
                        credit it could not stand by its own resources. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> After thus reviewing the position of affairs the senate
                        decided that Fulvius, one of the praetors, should appear <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> before the Assembly and point out to the people the
                        pressing needs of the State and ask those who had augmented their
                        patrimonies by making contracts with the government <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> to extend the date of payment for the State, out of
                        which they had made their money, and contract to supply what was needed for
                        the army in Spain on condition that as soon as there was money in the
                        treasury they should be the first to be paid. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> After making this proposal, the praetor fixed a date
                        for making the contracts for the supply of clothing and corn to the army in
                        Spain, and for furnishing all that was required for the seamen. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the appointed day three syndicates
                        appeared, consisting each of nineteen members, prepared to tender for the
                        contracts. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They insisted on two
                        conditions-one was that they should be exempt from military service whilst
                        they were employed on this public business, and the other that the cargoes
                        they shipped should be insured by the government against storm or capture.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both demands were conceded, and the
                        administration of the State was carried on with private money. Such were the
                        moral tone and lofty patriotism which pervaded all ranks of society!
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As the contracts had been entered into
                        from a generous and noble spirit, so they were executed with the utmost
                        conscientiousness; the soldiers received as ample supplies as though they
                        had been furnished, as they once were, from a rich treasury. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> When these supplies reached Spain, the town of
                        Iliturgi, which had gone over to the Romans, was being attacked by three
                        Carthaginian armies under Hasdrubal, Mago, and Hannibal, the son of
                        Bomilcar. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Between these three camps the
                        Scipios forced their way into the town after hard fighting and heavy losses.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They brought with them a quantity of
                        corn, of which there was a great scarcity, and encouraged the townsfolk to
                        defend their walls with the same courage that they saw the Roman army
                        display when fighting on their behalf. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Then they advanced to attack the largest of the three camps, of which
                        Hasdrubal was in command. The other two commanders and their armies saw that
                        the decisive struggle would be fought there and they hastened to its
                        support. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As soon as they had emerged from
                        their camps the fighting began. There were 60,000 of the enemy engaged that
                        day and about 16,000 Romans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And yet the
                        victory was such a crushing one that the Romans slew more than their
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> own number of the enemy, made
                        prisoners of more than 3000, captured somewhat less than 1000 horses, 59
                        military standards, 7 elephants, 5 having been killed in the battle, and got
                        possession of the three camps-all in that one day. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> After the siege of Iliturgi was thus raised, the
                        Carthaginian armies marched to attack Intibili. They had repaired their
                        losses out of that province which, above all others, was eager for fighting,
                        if only plunder and money were to be got out of it, and which, too, abounded
                        in young men. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A pitched battle was again
                        fought with the same result for both sides. Over 13,000 of the enemy were
                        killed, more than 2000 made prisoners, 42 standards and 9 elephants were
                        also taken. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And now nearly all the tribes
                        of Spain went over to Rome, and the successes gained in Spain that summer
                        were far greater than those in Italy. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
