<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six - 23</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp> literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by </resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>

                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1849</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="835" xml:id="p.835"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXIII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> The Campanians revolt to Hannibal. Mago is sent to Carthage to announce the
                        victory of Cannœ. Hanno advises the Carthaginian senate to make peace with
                        the Romans, but is overborne by the Barcine faction. Claudi- us Marcellus
                        the praetor defeats Hannibal at Nola. Hannibal's army is enervated in mind
                        and body by luxurious living at Capua. Casilinum is besieged by the
                        Carthaginians, and the inhabitants reduced to the last extremity of famine.
                        A hundred and ninety-seven senators elected from the equestrian order.
                        Lucius Postumius is, with his army, cut off by the Gauls. Cneius and Publius
                        Scipio defeat Hasdrubal in Spain, and gain possession of that country. The
                        remains of the army, defeated at Cannœ, are sent off to Sicily, there to
                        remain until the termination of the war. An alliance is formed between
                        Philip, king of Macedon, and Hannibal. Sempronius Gracchus defeats the
                        Campanians. Successes of Titus Manlius in Sardinia: he takes Hasdrubal the
                        general, Mago, and Han- no prisoners. Claudius Marcellus again defeats the
                        army of Hannibal at Nola, and the hopes of the Romans are revived as to the
                        results of the war. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> AFTER the battle of Cannae, Hannibal, having
                    captured and plundered the Roman camp, had immediately removed from Apulia into
                    Samnium; invited into the territory of the Hirpini by Statius, who promised that
                    he would surrender Compsa. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Trebius, a native
                    of Compsa, was conspicuous for rank among his countrymen; but a faction of the
                    Mopsii kept him down — a family of great influence through the favour of the
                    Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After intelligence of the battle of
                    Cannae, and a report of the approach of Hannibal, circulated by the discourse of
                    Trebius, the Mopsian party had retired from the city; which was thus given up to
                    the Carthaginian without opposition, and a garrison received into it. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Leaving there all his booty and baggage, and dividing
                    his forces, he orders Mago to receive under his protection the cities of that
                    district which might revolt from the Romans, and to force to defection those
                    which might be disinclined. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He himself,
                    passing through the territory of Campania, made for the lower sea, with the
                    intention of assaulting Naples, in order that he might be master of a maritime
                    city. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as he entered the confines of
                    the Neapoli- <pb n="836" xml:id="p.836"/> tan territory, he placed part of his
                    Numidians in ambush, wherever he could find a convenient spot; for there are
                    very many hollow roads and secret windings: others he ordered to drive before
                    them the booty they had collected from the country, and, exhibiting it to the
                    enemy, to ride up to the gates of the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As
                    they appeared to be few in number and in disorder, a troop of horse sallied out
                    against them, which was cut off, being drawn into an ambuscade by the others,
                    who purposely retreated: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> nor would one of them
                    have escaped, had not the sea been near, and some vessels, principally such as
                    are used in fishing, observed at a short distance from the shore, afforded an
                    escape for those who could swim. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Several noble
                    youths, however, were captured and slain in that affair. Among whom, Hegeas, the
                    commander of the cavalry, fell when pursuing the retreating enemy too eagerly.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The sight of the walls, which were not
                    favourable to a besieging force, deterred the Carthaginian from storming the
                    city. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thence he turned his course to Capua, which
                    was wantoning under a long course of prosperity, and the indulgence of fortune:
                    amid the general corruption, however, the most conspicuous feature was the
                    extravagance of the commons, who exercised their liberty without limit.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Pacuvius Calavius had rendered the senate
                    subservient to himself and the commons, at once a noble and popular man, but who
                    had acquired his influence by dishonourable intrigues. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Happening to hold the chief magistracy during the year in
                    which the defeat at the Trasimenus occurred, and thinking that the commons, who
                    had long felt the most violent hostility to the senate, would attempt some
                    desperate measure, should an opportunity for effecting a change present itself;
                    and if Hannibal should come into that quarter with his victorious army, would
                    murder the senators and deliver Capua to the Carthaginians; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> as he desired to rule in a state preserved rather than
                    subverted (for though depraved he was not utterly abandoned); and as he felt
                    convinced that no state could be preserved if bereaved of its public council, he
                    adopted a plan by which he might preserve the senate and render it subject to
                    himself and the commons. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having assembled the
                    senate, he prefaced his remarks by observing, <quote> that nothing would induce
                        him to acquiesce in a plan of defection from the Romans, were it not
                        absolutely necessary; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> since he had
                        children by the daughter <pb n="837" xml:id="p.837"/> of Appius Claudius,
                        and had a daughter at Rome married to Livius: but that a much more serious
                        and alarming matter threatened them, than any consequences which could
                        result from such a measure. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For that the
                        intention of the commons was not to abolish the senate by revolting to the
                        Carthaginians, but to murder the senators, and deliver the state thus
                        destitute to Hannibal and the Carthaginians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> That it was in his power to rescue them from this danger, if they would
                        resign themselves to his care, and, forgetting their political dissensions,
                        confide in him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When, overpowered with fear, they all put
                    themselves under his protection, he proceeded: <quote> I will shut you up in the
                        senate-house, and pretending myself to be an accomplice in the meditated
                        crime, I will, by approving measures which I should in vain oppose, find out
                        a way for your safety. For the performance of this take whatever pledge you
                        please. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having given his honour, he went out; and
                    having ordered the house to be closed, placed a guard in the lobby that no one
                    might enter or leave it without his leave. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then assembling the people, he thus addressed
                    them: <quote> What you have so often wished for, Campanians, the power of
                        punishing an unprincipled and detestable senate, you now have, not at your
                        own imminent peril, by riotously storming the houses of each, which are
                        guarded and garrisoned with slaves and dependants, but free and without
                        danger. Take them all, shut up in the senate-house, alone and unarmed; nor
                        need you do any thing precipitately or blindly. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> I will give you the opportunity of pronouncing upon the
                        life or death of each, that each may suffer the punishment he has deserved.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But, above all, it behoves you so to
                        give way to your resentment, as considering that your own safety and
                        advantage are of greater importance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For I
                        apprehend that you hate these particular senators, and not that you are
                        unwilling to have any senate at all; for you must either have a king, which
                        all abominate, or a senate, which is the only course compatible with a free
                        state. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly you must effect two
                        objects at the same time; you must remove the old senate and elect a new
                        one. I will order the senators to be summoned one by one, and I shall put it
                        to you to decide whether they deserve to live or die: <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> whatever you may determine respecting each shall be
                        done; but before you execute your sentence on the culprit, you shall <pb
                            n="838" xml:id="p.838"/> elect some brave and strenuous man as a fresh
                        senator to supply his place. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Upon this he took his seat, and, the names
                    having been thrown together into an urn, he ordered that the name which had the
                    lot to fall out first should be proclaimed, and the person brought forward out
                    of the senate-house. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the name was heard,
                    each man strenuously exclaimed that he was a wicked and unprincipled fellow, and
                    deserved to be punished. Pacuvius then said, <quote> I perceive the sentence
                        which has been passed on this man; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> now
                        choose a good and upright senator in the room of this wicked and
                        unprincipled one. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At first all was silence, from the want of a
                    better man whom they might substitute; afterwards, one of them, laying aside his
                    modesty, nominating some one, in an instant a much greater clamour arose;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> while some denied all knowledge of him,
                    others objected to him at one time on account of flagitious conduct, at another
                    time on account of his humble birth, his sordid circumstances, and the
                    disgraceful nature of his trade and occupation. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> The same occurred with increased vehemence with respect to the second and
                    third senators, so that it was evident that they were dissatisfied with the
                    senator himself, but had not any one to substitute for him; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> for it was of no use that the same persons should be
                    nominated again, to no other purpose than to hear of their vices, and the rest
                    were much more mean and obscure than those who first occurred to their
                    recollection. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Thus the assembly separated,
                    affirming that every evil which was most known was easiest to be endured, and
                    ordering the senate to be discharged from custody. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Pacuvius, having thus rendered the senators
                    more subservient to himself than to the commons by the gift of their lives,
                    ruled without the aid of arms, all persons now acquiescing. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Henceforward the senators, forgetful of their rank and
                    independence, flattered the commons; saluted them courteously; invited them
                    graciously; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> entertained them with sumptuous
                    feasts; undertook those causes, always espoused that party, decided as judges in
                    favour of that side, which was most popular, and best adapted to conciliate the
                    favour of the commons. Now, indeed, every thing was transacted in the senate as
                    if it had been an assembly of the people. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    Capuans, ever prone to luxurious indulgence not only from natural turpitude, but
                    from the profusion of the means of voluptuous enjoyment which flowed in upon
                    them, and the <pb n="839" xml:id="p.839"/> temptations of all the luxuries of
                    land and sea; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> at that time especially
                    proceeded to such a pitch of extravagance in consequence of the obsequiousness
                    of the nobles and the unrestrained liberty of the commons, that their lust and
                    prodigality had no bounds. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To a disregard for
                    the laws, the magistrates, and the senate, now, after the disaster of Cannae,
                    was added a contempt for the Roman government also, for which there had been
                    some degree of respect. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The only obstacles to
                    immediate revolt were the intermarriages which, from a remote period, had
                    connected many of their distinguished and influential families with the Romans;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and, which formed the strongest bond of
                    union, that while several of their countrymen were serving in the Roman armies,
                    particularly three hundred horsemen, the flower of the Campanian nobility, had
                    been selected and sent by the Romans to garrison the cities of Sicily. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The parents and relations of these men with
                    difficulty obtained that ambassadors should be sent to the Roman consul. The
                    consul, who had not yet set out for Canusium, they found at Venusia with a few
                    half-armed troops, an object of entire commiseration to faithful, but of
                    contempt to proud and perfidious allies, like the Campanians. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The consul too increased their contempt of himself and his
                    cause, by too much exposing and exhibiting the disastrous state of his affairs;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for when the ambassadors had delivered
                    their message, which was, that the senate and people of Capua were distressed
                    that any adverse event should have befallen the Romans, and were promising every
                    assistance in <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> prosecuting the war, he
                    observed, <quote> In bidding us order you to furnish us with all things which
                        are necessary for the war, Campanians, you have rather observed the
                        customary mode of addressing allies, than spoken suitably to the present
                        posture of our affairs; for hath anything been left us at Cannae, so that,
                        as if we possessed that, we can desire what is wanting to be supplied by our
                        allies? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Can we order a supply of infantry,
                        as if we had any cavalry? Can we say we are deficient in money, as if that
                        were the only thing we wanted? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Fortune has
                        not even left us anything which we can add to. Our legions, cavalry, arms,
                        standards, horses, men, money, provisions, all perished either in the
                        battle, or in the two camps which were lost the following day. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> You must, therefore, Campanians, not assist us in
                            <pb n="840" xml:id="p.840"/> the war, but almost take it upon yourselves
                        in our stead. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Call to mind how formerly at
                        Saticula we received into our protection and defended your ancestors, when
                        dismayed and driven within their walls; terrified not only by their Samnite
                        but Sidicinian enemies; and how we carried on, with varying success, through
                        a period of almost a century, a war with the Samnites, commenced on your
                        account. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Add to this, that when you gave
                        yourselves up to us we granted you an alliance on equal terms, that we
                        allowed you your own laws, and lastly, what before the disaster at Cannae
                        was surely a privilege of the highest value, we bestowed the freedom of our
                        city on a large portion of you, and held it in common with you. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> It is your duty, therefore, Campanians, to look
                        upon this disaster which has been suffered as your own, and to consider that
                        our common country must be protected. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It
                        is not a Samnite or Tuscan foe we are engaged with, so that the empire taken
                        from us might still continue in Italy. A Carthaginian enemy draws after him
                        from the remotest regions of the world, from the straits of the ocean and
                        the pillars of Hercules, a body of soldiers who are not even natives of
                        Africa, destitute of all laws, and of the condition and almost of the
                        language of men. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Savage and ferocious
                        from nature and habit, their general has rendered them still more so, by
                        forming bridges and works with heaps of human bodies; and, what the tongue
                        can scarcely utter, by teaching them to live on human flesh. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> What man, provided he were born in any part of
                        Italy, would not abominate the idea of seeing and having for his masters
                        these men, nourished with such horrid food, whom even to touch were an
                        impiety; of fetching laws from Africa and Carthage; and of suffering Italy
                        to become a province of the Moors and Numidians? <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> It will be highly honourable, Campanians, that the
                        Roman empire, sinking under this disastrous defeat, should be sustained and
                        restored by your fidelity and your strength. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> I conceive that thirty thousand foot and four thousand
                        horse may be raised in Campania. You have already abundance of money and
                        corn. If your zeal corresponds with your means, neither will Hannibal feel
                        that he has been victorious, nor the Romans that they have been defeated.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the consul had thus spoken, the
                    ambassadors were dismissed; and as they were returning home, one of them, <pb
                        n="841" xml:id="p.841"/> named Vibius Virius, observed, <quote> that the
                        time had arrived at which the Campanians might not only recover the
                        territory once injuriously taken away by the Romans, but also possess
                        themselves of the sovereignty of Italy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        For they might form a treaty with Hannibal on whatever terms they pleased;
                        and there could be no question but that after Hannibal, having put an end to
                        the war, had himself retired victorious into Africa, and had withdrawn his
                        troops, the sovereignty of Italy would be left to the Campanians. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All assenting to Vibius, as he said this, they
                    framed their report of the embassy so that all might conclude that the Roman
                    power was annihilated. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Immediately the commons
                    and the major part of the senate turned their attention to revolt. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The measure, however, was postponed for a few days at
                    the instigation of the elder citizens. At last, the opinion of the majority
                    prevailed, that the same ambassadors who had gone to the Roman consul should be
                    sent to Hannibal. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I find in certain annals,
                    that before this embassy proceeded, and before they had determined on the
                    measure of revolting, ambassadors were sent by the Campanians to Rome, requiring
                    that one of the consuls should be elected from Campania if they wished
                    assistance to the Roman cause. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That from the
                    indignation which arose, they were ordered to be removed from the senate-house,
                    and a lictor despatched to conduct them out of the city and command them to
                    lodge that day without the Roman frontier. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                    as this request is too much like that which the Latins formerly made, and as
                    Cœlius and other writers had, not without reason, made no mention of it, I have
                    not ventured to vouch for its truth. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassadors came to Hannibal and concluded
                    a treaty of peace with him on the terms, <quote> That no Carthaginian commander
                        should have any authority over a Campanian citizen, nor any Campanian serve
                        in war or perform any office against his will: <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> that Capua should have her own laws and her own
                        magistrates: that the Carthaginian should give to the Campanians three
                        hundred captives selected by themselves, who might be exchanged for the
                        Campanian horse who were serving in Sicily. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Such were the stipulations: but in addition to
                    them, the Campanians perpetrated the following atrocities; for the commons
                    ordered that the prefects of the allies and other citizens of Rome should be
                    suddenly seized, <pb n="842" xml:id="p.842"/> while some of them were occupied
                    with military duties, others engaged in private business, and be shut up in the
                    baths, as if for the purpose of keeping them in custody; where, suffocated with
                    heat and vapour, they might expire in a horrid manner. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Decius Magius, a man who wanted nothing to complete his
                    influence except a sound mind on the part of his countrymen, had resisted to the
                    uttermost the execution of these measures, and the sending of the embassy to
                    Hannibal; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and when he heard that a body of
                    troops was sent by Hannibal, bringing back to their recollection, as examples,
                    the haughty tyranny of Pyrrhus and the miserable slavery of the Tarentines, he
                    at first openly and loudly protested that the troops should not be admitted;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> then he urged either that they should
                    expel them when received, or, if they had a mind to expiate, by a bold and
                    memorable act, the foul crime they had committed in revolting from their most
                    ancient and intimate allies, that having slain the Carthaginian troops they
                    should give themselves back to the Romans. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    These proceedings having been reported to Hannibal, for they were not carried on
                    in secret, he at first sent persons to summon Magius into his presence at his
                    camp; then, on his vehemently refusing to come, on the ground that Hannibal had
                    no authority over a Campanian, the Carthaginian, excited with rage, ordered that
                    the man should be seized and dragged to him in chains; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> but afterwards, fearing lest while force was employed some
                    disturbance might take place, or lest, from excitement of feeling, some
                    undesigned collision might occur, he set out himself from the camp with a small
                    body of troops, having sent a message before him to Marius Blosius, the praetor
                    of Campania, to the effect, that he would be at Capua the next day. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Marius calling an assembly, issued an order that they
                    should go out and meet Hannibal in a body, accompanied by their wives and
                    children. This was done by all, not only with obedience, but with zeal, with the
                    full agreement of the common people, and with eagerness to see a general
                    rendered illustrious by so many victories. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Decius Magius neither went out to meet him, nor kept himself in private, by
                    which course he might seem to indicate fear from a consciousness of demerit; he
                    promenaded in the forum with perfect composure, attended by his son and a few
                    dependants, while all the citizens were in a bustle to go to see and receive the
                    Carthaginian. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Han- <pb n="843" xml:id="p.843"
                    /> nibal, on entering the city, immediately demanded an audience of the senate;
                    when the chief men of the Campanians, beseeching him not to transact any serious
                    business on that day, but that he would cheerfully and <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> willingly celebrate a day devoted to festivity in
                    consequence of his own arrival, though naturally extremely prone to anger, yet,
                    that he might not deny them any thing at first, he spent a great part of the day
                    in inspecting the city. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He lodged at the house of the Ninii Celeres,
                    Stenius and Pacuvius, men distinguished by their noble descent and their wealth.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thither Pacuvius Calavius, of whom mention
                    has already been made, who was the head of the party which had drawn over the
                    state to the Carthaginian cause, brought his son, <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> a young man, whom he had forced from the side of Decius
                    Magius, in conjunction with whom he had made a most determined stand for the
                    Roman alliance in opposition to the league with the Carthaginians; nor had the
                    leaning of the state to the other side, or his father's authority, altered his
                    sentiments. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For this youth his father procured
                    pardon from Hannibal, more by prayers than by clearing him. Hannibal, overcome
                    by the entreaties and tears of his father, even gave orders that he should be
                    invited with his father to the banquet; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> to
                    which entertainment he intended to admit no Campanian besides his hosts, and
                    Jubellius Taurea, a man distinguished in war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They began to feast early in the day, and the entertainment was not conformable
                    to the Carthaginian custom, or to military discipline, but as might be expected
                    in a city and in a house both remarkable for luxury, was furnished with all the
                    allurements of voluptuousness. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Perolla, the
                    son of Calavius, was the only person who could not be won either by the
                    solicitations of the masters of the house, or those which Hannibal sometimes
                    employed. The youth himself pleaded ill health as an apology, while his father
                    urged as an excuse the disturbed state of his mind, which was not surprising.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About sunset, Calavius, who had gone out
                    from the banquet, was followed by his son; and when they had arrived at a
                    retired place, (it was a garden at the back part <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> of the house,) he said, <quote> I have a plan to propose to
                        you, my father, by which we shall not only obtain pardon from the Romans for
                        our crime, in that we revolted from them to the Carthaginian, but shall be
                        held in much higher esteem, <pb n="844" xml:id="p.844"/> than we Campanians
                        ever have been. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the father inquired with surprise what
                    that plan could be, he threw back his gown off his shoulder and exposed to view
                    his side, which was girt with a sword. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Forthwith will I ratify the alliance with Rome with the blood of
                        Hannibal. I was desirous that you should be informed of it first, in case
                        you might prefer to be absent while the deed is performing. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On hearing and seeing which the old man, as
                    though he were actually present at the transactions which were being <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> named to him, wild with fear, exclaimed, <quote> I
                        implore, I beseech you, my son, by all the ties which unite children to
                        parents, that you will not resolve to commit and to suffer every thing that
                        is horrible before the eyes of a father. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Did we but a few hours ago, swearing by every deity, and joining right
                        hands, pledge our fidelity to Hannibal, that immediately on separating from
                        the conference we should arm against him the hands which were employed as
                        the sacred pledges of our faith? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Do you
                        rise from the hospitable board to which as one of three of the Campanians
                        you have been admitted by Hannibal, that you may ensanguine that very board
                        with the blood of your host. Could I conciliate Hannibal to my son, and not
                        my son to Hannibal? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But let nothing be
                        held sacred by you, neither our pledges, nor the sense of religion, nor
                        filial duty; let the most horrid deeds be dared, if with guilt they bring
                        not ruin upon us. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Will you singly attack
                        Hannibal? What will that numerous throng of freemen and slaves be doing?
                        What the eyes of all intent on him alone? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        What those so many right hands? Will they be torpid amidst your madness?
                        Will you be able to bear the look of Hannibal him- self, which armed hosts
                        cannot sustain, from which the Roman people shrink with horror? <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> And though other assistance be wanting, will you
                        have the hardihood to strike me when I oppose my body in defence of
                        Hannibal's? But know that through my breast you must strike and transfix
                        him. Suffer yourself to be deterred from your attempt here, rather than to
                        be defeated there. May my entreaties prevail with you, as they did for you
                        this day. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Upon this, perceiving the youth in tears, he
                    threw his arms around him, and kissing him affectionately, ceased not his
                    entreaties until he prevailed upon him to lay aside his sword and give his
                    promise that he would do no such thing. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    young man then observed, <quote> I will in- <pb n="845" xml:id="p.845"/> deed
                        pay to my father the debt of duty which I owe to my country, but I am
                        grieved for you on whom the guilt of having thrice betrayed your country
                        rests; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> once when you sanctioned the
                        revolt from the Romans; next when you advised the alliance with Hannibal;
                        and thirdly, this day, when you are the delay and impediment of the
                        restoration of Capua to the Romans. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Do
                        thou, my country, receive this weapon, armed with which in thy behalf I
                        would fain have defended this citadel, since a father wrests it from me. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Having thus said, he threw the sword into the
                    highway over the garden wall, and that the affair might not be suspected,
                    himself returned to the banquet. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day an audience of a full senate was
                    given to Hannibal, when the first part of his address was full of graciousness
                    and benignity, in which he thanked the Campanians for having preferred his
                    friendship to an alliance with the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Romans,
                    and held out among his other magnificent promises <quote> that Capua should soon
                        become the capital of all Italy, and that the Romans as well as the other
                        states should receive laws from it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That
                        there was, however, one person who had no share in the Carthaginian
                        friendship and the alliance formed with him, Decius Magius, who neither was
                        nor ought to be called a Campanian. Him he requested to be surrendered to
                        him, and that the sense of the senate should be taken respecting his
                        conduct, and a decree passed in his presence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All concurred in this proposition, though a
                    great many considered him as a man undeserving such severe treatment; and that
                    this proceeding was no small infringement of their liberty to begin with.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Leaving the senate-house, the magistrate
                    took his seat on the consecrated bench, ordered Decius Magius to be apprehended,
                    and to be placed by himself before his feet to plead his cause. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But he, his proud spirit being unsubdued, denied that such
                    a measure could be enforced agreeably to the conditions of the treaty; upon
                    which he was ironed, and ordered to be brought into the camp before a lictor.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As long as he was conducted with his head
                    uncovered, he moved along earnestly haranguing and vociferating to the multitude
                    which poured around him on all sides. <quote> You have gotten that liberty,
                        Campanians, which you seek; in the middle of the forum, in the light of day,
                        before your eyes, I, a man second to none of the Campanians, am dragged in
                        chains <pb n="846" xml:id="p.846"/> to suffer death. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> What greater outrage could have been committed had
                        Capua been captured? Go out to meet Hannibal, decorate your city to the
                        utmost, consecrate the day of his arrival, that you may behold this triumph
                        over a fellow-citizen. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As the populace seemed to be excited by him,
                    vociferating these things, his head was covered, and he was ordered to be
                    dragged away more speedily without the gate. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Having been thus brought to the camp, he was immediately put on board a ship and
                    sent to Carthage, lest if any commotion should arise at Capua on account of the
                    injustice of the proceeding, the senate also should repent of having given up a
                    leading citizen; and lest if an embassy were sent to request his restoration, he
                    must either offend his new allies by refusing their first petition, or, by
                    granting it, be compelled to retain at Capua a promoter of sedition and
                    disturbance. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A tempest drove the vessel to
                    Cyrenae, which was at that time under the dominion of kings. Here flying for
                    refuge to the statue of king Ptolemy, he was conveyed thence in custody to
                    Alexandria to Ptolemy; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and having instructed
                    him that he had been thrown into chains by Hannibal, contrary to the law of
                    treaties, he was liberated and allowed to return to whichever place he pleased,
                    Rome or Capua. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But Magius said, that Capua
                    would not be a safe place for him, and that Rome, at a time when there was war
                    between the Romans and Capuans, would be rather the residence of a deserter than
                    a guest. That there was no place that he should rather dwell in, than in the
                    dominions of him whom he esteemed an avenger and the protector of his liberty. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were carrying on, Quintus
                    Fabius Pictor, the ambassador, returned from Delphi to Rome, and read the
                    response of the oracle from a written copy. In it both the gods were mentioned,
                    and in what manner supplication should be made. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> It then stated, <quote> If you do thus, Romans, your affairs will be more
                        prosperous and less perplexed; your state will proceed more agreeably to
                        your wishes; and the victory in the war will be on the side of the Roman
                        people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After that your state shall have
                        been restored to prosperity and safety, send a present to the Pythian Apollo
                        out of the gains you have earned, and pay honours to him out of the plunder,
                        the booty, and the spoils. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Banish
                        licentiousness from among you. </quote>
                    <pb n="847" xml:id="p.847"/>
                </p>
                <p> Having read aloud these words, translated from the Greek verse, he added, that
                    immediately on his departure from the oracle, he had paid divine honours to all
                    these deities with wine and <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> frankincense; and
                    that he was ordered by the chief priest of the temple, that, as he had
                    approached the oracle land performed the sacred ceremonies decorated with a
                    laurel crown, so he should embark wearing the crown, and not put it off till he
                    had arrived at <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Rome. That he had executed all
                    these injunctions with the most scrupulous exactness and diligence, and had
                    deposited the garland on the altar of Apollo at Rome. The senate decreed that
                    the sacred ceremonies and supplications enjoined should be carefully performed
                    with all possible <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> expedition. During these
                    events at Rome and in Italy, Mago, the son of Hamilcar, had arrived at Carthage
                    with the intelligence of the victory at Cannae. He was not sent direct from the
                    field of battle by his brother, but was detained some days in receiving the
                    submission of such states of the Bruttii as were in <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> revolt. Having obtained an audience of the senate he gave a
                    full statement of his brother's exploits in Italy: <quote> That he had fought
                        pitched battles with six generals, four of whom were consuls, two a dictator
                        and master of the horse, with six consular armies; that he had slain above
                        two hundred thousand of the enemy, and captured above fifty <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> thousand. That out of the four consuls he had slain
                        two; of the two remaining, one was wounded, the other, having lost his whole
                        army, had fled from the field with scarcely fifty men; that the master of
                        the horse, an authority equal to that of consul, had been routed and put to
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> flight; that the dictator, because he
                        had never engaged in a pitched battle, was esteemed a matchless general;
                        that the Bruttii, the Apulians, part of the Samnites and of the Lucanians
                        had revolted to the <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Carthaginians. That
                        Capua, which was the capital not only of Campania, but after the ruin of the
                        Roman power by the battle of Cannas, of Italy also, had delivered itself
                        over to <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hannibal. That in return for
                        these so many and so great victories, gratitude ought assuredly to be felt
                        and thanks returned to the immortal gods. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then, in proof of this such joyful news, he
                    ordered the golden rings to be poured out in the vestibule of the senate-house,
                    of which there was such a heap that some have taken upon themselves to say that
                    on being measured they <pb n="848" xml:id="p.848"/> filled three pecks and a
                    half. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The statement has obtained and is more
                    like the truth, that there were not more than a peck. He then added, by way of
                    explanation, to prove the greater extent of the slaughter, that none but
                    knights, and of these the principal only, wore that ornament. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The main drift of his speech was, <quote> that the nearer
                        the prospect was of bringing the war to a conclusion, the more should
                        Hannibal be aided by every means, for that the seat of war was at a long
                        distance from home and in the heart of the enemy's country. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> That a great quantity of corn was consumed and money
                        expended; and that so many pitched battles, as they had annihilated the
                        armies of the enemy, had also in some degree diminished the forces of the
                        victor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That a reinforcement therefore
                        ought to be sent; and money for the pay, and corn for the soldiers, who had
                        deserved so well of the Carthaginian name. </quote> After this speech of
                    Mago's, all being elated with joy, Himilco, a member of the Barcine faction,
                    conceiving this a good opportunity for inveighing against Hanno, said to him,
                        <quote> What think you now, Hanno? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> do you
                        now also regret that the war against the Romans was entered upon? <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Now urge that Hannibal should be given up; yes,
                        forbid the rendering of thanks to the immortal gods amidst such successes;
                        let us hear a Roman senator in the senate-house of the Carthaginians. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Upon which Hanno replied, <quote> I should
                        have remained silent this day, conscript fathers, lest, amid the general
                        joy, I should utter any thing which might be too gloomy for you. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> But now, to a senator, asking whether I still
                        regret the undertaking of the war against the Romans, if I should forbear to
                        speak, I should seem either arrogant or servile, the former of which is the
                        part of a man who is forgetful of the independence of others, the latter of
                        his own. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I may answer therefore to
                        Himilco, that I have not ceased to regret the war, nor shall I cease to
                        censure your invincible general until I see the war concluded on some
                        tolerable terms; nor will any thing except a new peace put a period to my
                        regret for the loss of the old one. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Accordingly those achievements, which Mago has so boastingly recounted, are
                        a source of present joy to Himilco and the other adherents of Hannibal; to
                        me they may become so; because successes in war, if we have a mind to make
                        the best use of fortune, will afford us a peace on more equitable terms;
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> for if we allow this opportunity to
                        pass by, on which <pb n="849" xml:id="p.849"/> we have it in our power to
                        appear to dictate rather than to receive terms of peace, I fear lest even
                        this our joy should run into excess, and in the end prove groundless.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> However, let us see of what kind it
                        is even now. I have slain the armies of the enemy, send me soldiers.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> What else would you ask if you had
                        been conquered? I have captured two of the enemy's camps, full, of course,
                        of booty and provisions; supply me with corn and money. What else would you
                        ask had you been plundered and stripped of your camp? <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> And that I may not be the only person perplexed, I
                        could wish that either Himilco or Mago would answer me, for it is just and
                        fair that I also should put a question, since I have answered Himilco.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Since the battle at Cannae
                        annihilated the Roman power, and it is a fact that all Italy is in a state
                        of revolt; in the first place, has any one people of the Latin confederacy
                        come over to us? In the next place, has any individual of the five and
                        thirty tribes deserted to Hannibal? </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> When Mago had answered both these questions
                    in the negative, he continued: <quote> there remains then still too large a body
                        of the enemy. But I should be glad to know what degree of spirit and hope
                        that body possesses. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mago declaring that he did not know;
                        <quote>Nothing,</quote> said he, <quote> is easier to be known. Have the
                        Romans sent any ambassadors to Hannibal to treat of peace? Have you, in
                        short, ever heard that any mention has been made of peace at Rome? </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On his answering these questions also in the
                    negative: <quote> We have upon our hands then, said he, a war as entire as we
                        had on the day on which Hannibal crossed over into Italy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> There are a great many of us alive now who remember how
                        fluctuating the success was in the former Punic war. At no time did our
                        affairs appear in so prosperous a condition as they did before the
                        consulship of Caius Lutatius and Aulus Posthumius. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In the consulship of Caius Lutatius and Aulus
                        Posthumius we were completely conquered at the islands Aegates. But if now,
                        as well as then, (oh! may the gods avert the omen!) fortune should take any
                        turn, do you hope to obtain that peace when we shall be vanquished which no
                        one is willing to grant now we are victorious. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> I have an opinion which I should express if any one
                        should advise with me on the subject of proffering or accepting terms of
                        peace with the enemy; but with respect to the supplies requested <pb n="850"
                            xml:id="p.850"/> by Mago, I do not think there is any necessity to send
                        them to a victorious army; and I give it as my opinion that they should far
                        less be sent to them, if they are deluding us by groundless and empty hopes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But few were influenced by the harangue of
                    Hanno, for both the jealousy which he entertained towards the Barcine family,
                    made him a less weighty authority; and men's minds being taken up with the
                    present exultation, would listen to nothing by which their joy could be made
                    more groundless, but felt convinced, that if they should make a little
                    additional exertion the war might be speedily terminated. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly a decree of the senate was made with very
                    general approbation, that four thousand Numidians should be sent as a
                    reinforcement to Hannibal, with four hundred elephants and many talents of
                    silver. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Moreover, the dictator was sent
                    forward into Spain with Mago to hire twenty thousand foot and four thousand
                    horse, to recruit the armies in Italy and Spain. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But these resolutions, as generally happens in
                    the season of prosperity, were executed in a leisurely and slothful manner.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans, in addition to their inborn
                    activity of mind, were prevented from delaying by the posture of their affairs.
                    For the consul was not wanting in any business which was to be done by him; and
                    the dictator, Marcus Junius Pera, after the sacred ceremonies were concluded,
                    and after having, as is usual, proposed to the people that he might be allowed
                    to mount his horse; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> besides the two legions
                    which had been enlisted by the consuls in the beginning of the year, and besides
                    the cohorts collected out of the Picenian and Gallic territories, descended to
                    that last resort of the state when almost despaired of, and when propriety gives
                    place to utility, and made proclamation, that of such persons as had been guilty
                    of capital crimes or were in prison on judgment for debt, those who would serve
                    as soldiers with him, he would order to be released from their liability to
                    punishment and their debts. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These six thousand
                    he armed with the Gallic spoils which were carried in the procession at the
                    triumph of Caius Flaminius. Thus he marched from the city at the head of
                    twenty-five thousand men. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal, after
                    gaining Capua, made a second fruitless attempt upon the minds of the
                    Neapolitans, partly by fear and partly by hope; and then marched his troops
                    across into the territory of Nola: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="851" xml:id="p.851"/> not immediately in a hostile attitude, for he did
                    not despair of a voluntary surrender, yet intending to omit nothing which they
                    could suffer or fear, if they delayed the completion of his hopes. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The senate, and especially the principal members of
                    it, persevered faithfully in keeping up the alliance with the Romans; the
                    commons, as usual, were all inclined to a change in the government and to
                    espouse the cause of Hannibal, placing before their minds the fear lest their
                    fields should be devastated; and the many hardships and indignities which must
                    be endured in a siege; nor were there wanting persons who advised a revolt.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In this state of things, when a fear took
                    possession of the senate, that it would be impossible to resist the excited
                    multitude if they went openly to work, devised a delay of the evil by secret
                    simulation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They pretended that they were
                    agreeable to the revolt to Hannibal; but that it was not settled on what terms
                    they should enter into the new alliance and friendship. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Thus having gained time, they promptly sent ambassadors to
                    the Roman praetor, Marcellus Claudius, who was at Casilinum with his army, and
                    informed him what a critical situation Nola was in; that the fields were already
                    in the possession of Hannibal and the Carthaginians, and that the city soon
                    would be, unless succour were sent; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that the
                    senate, by conceding to the commons that they would revolt when they pleased,
                    had caused them not to hasten too much to revolt. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Marcellus, after bestowing high commendations on the
                    Nolans, urged them to protract the business till his arrival by means of the
                    same pretences; in the mean time, to conceal what had passed between them, as
                    well as all hope of succour from the Romans. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    He himself marched from Casilinum to Calatia, and thence crossing the Vulturnus,
                    and passing through the territories of Saticula and Trebula, pursuing his course
                    along the mountains above Suessula, he arrived at Nola. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the approach of the Roman praetor, the
                    Carthaginians retired from the territory of Nola and marched down to the sea
                    close upon Naples, eager to get possession of a maritime town to which there
                    would be a safe course for ships from Africa. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But hearing that Naples was held by a Roman prefect, Marcus Junius Silanus, who
                    had been invited thither by the Neapolitans themselves, he left Naples as he had
                    left Nola, and directed his course to <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    Nuceria, which he at length <pb n="852" xml:id="p.852"/> starved into
                    capitulation, after having besieged it for a considerable time, often by open
                    force, and often by soliciting to no purpose sometimes the commons, at other
                    times the nobles; agreeing that they should depart with single garments and
                    without arms. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then, as wishing to appear from
                    the beginning to show lenity to all the inhabitants of Italy except the Romans,
                    he proposed rewards and honours to those who might remain with him, and would be
                    willing to serve with him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He retained none,
                    however, by the hopes he held out; they all dispersed in different directions
                    throughout the cities of Campania, wherever either hospitable connexions or the
                    casual impulse of the mind directed them, but principally to Nola and Naples.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About thirty senators, including as it
                    happened all of the first rank, made for Capua; but being shut out thence,
                    because they had closed their gates on Hannibal, they betook themselves to
                    Cumae. The plunder of Nuceria was given to the soldiery, the city sacked and
                    burned. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcellus continued to hold possession
                    of Nola, relying not more from confidence in his own troops than from the
                    favourable disposition of the leading inhabitants. Apprehensions were
                    entertained of the commons, particularly Lucius Bantius, whose having been privy
                    to an attempt at defection, and dread of the Roman praetor, stimulated sometimes
                    to the betrayal of his country, at others, should fortune fail him in that
                    undertaking, to desertion. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was a young man
                    of vigorous mind, and at that time enjoying the greatest renown of almost any of
                    the allied cavalry. Found at Cannae half dead amid a heap of slain, Hannibal had
                    sent him home, after having had him cured, with the kindest attention, and even
                    with presents. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In gratitude for this favour,
                    he had conceived a wish to put Nola under the power and dominion of the
                    Carthaginian; but his anxiety and solicitude for effecting a change did not
                    escape the notice of the praetor. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> However, as
                    it was necessary that he should be either restrained by penal inflictions or
                    conciliated by favours, he preferred attaching to himself a brave and strenuous
                    ally, to depriving the enemy of him; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and
                    summoning him into his presence, in the kindest manner said, <quote> that the
                        fact that he had many among his countrymen who were jealous of him, might be
                        easily collected from the circumstance that not one citizen of Nola had
                        informed him how many were his splendid military exploits. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> But that it <pb n="853" xml:id="p.853"/> was impossible
                        for the valour of one who served in the Roman camp to remain in obscurity;
                        that many who had served with him had reported to him how brave a man he
                        was, how often and what dangers he had encountered for the safety and honour
                        of the Roman people; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and how in the
                        battle of Cannae he had not given over fighting till, almost bloodless, he
                        was buried under a heap of men, horses, and arms which fell upon him.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Go on then, </quote> says he, <quote>
                        and prosper in your career of valour, with me you shall receive every honour
                        and every reward, and the oftener you be with me, the more you shall find it
                        will be to your honour and emolument. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He presented the young man, delighted with
                    these promises, with a horse of distinguished beauty, ordered the quaestor to
                    give him five hundred denarii, and commanded the lictors to allow him to
                    approach him whenever he might please. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The violent spirit of the youth was so much
                    soothed by the courteous treatment of Marcellus, that thenceforward no one of
                    the allies displayed greater courage or fidelity in aiding the Roman cause.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hannibal being now at the gates, for he
                    had moved his camp back again from Nuceria to Nola, and the commons beginning to
                    turn their attention to revolt afresh, Marcellus, on the approach of the enemy,
                    retired within the walls; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> not from
                    apprehension for his camp, but lest he should give an opportunity for betraying
                    the city, which too many were anxiously watching for. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The troops on both sides then began to be drawn up; the
                    Romans before the walls of Nola, the Carthaginians before their own camp. Hence
                    arose several battles of small account between the city and the camp, with
                    varying success, as the generals were neither willing to check the small parties
                    who inconsiderately challenged the enemy, nor to give the signal for a general
                    engagement. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While the two armies continued to
                    be thus stationed day after day, the chief men of the Nolans informed Marcellus,
                    that conferences were held by night between the commons of Nola and the
                    Carthaginians; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and that it was fixed, that,
                    when the Roman army had gone out at the gates, they should make plunder of their
                    baggage and packages, then close the gates and post themselves upon the walls,
                    in order that when in possession of the government and the city, they might then
                    receive the Carthaginian instead of the Roman. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    On receiving this intelligence Marcellus, having bestowed the highest <pb
                        n="854" xml:id="p.854"/> commendations on the senators, resolved to hazard
                    the issue of a battle before any commotion should arise within the city.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He drew up his troops in three divisions
                    at the three gates which faced the enemy; he gave orders that the baggage should
                    follow close by; that the servants, suttlers' boys, and invalids should carry
                    palisades; at the centre gate he stationed the choicest of the legionary troops
                    and the Roman cavalry, at the two gates on either side, the recruits, the
                    light-armed, and the allied cavalry. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    Nolans were forbidden to approach the walls and gates, and the troops designed
                    for a reserve were set over the baggage, lest while the legions were engaged in
                    the battle an attack should be made upon it. Thus arranged they were standing
                    within the gates. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal, who had waited
                    with his troops drawn up in battle-array, as he had done for several days, till
                    the day was far advanced, at first was amazed that neither the Roman army
                    marched out of the gates, nor any armed man was to be seen on the walls;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> but afterwards concluding that the
                    conferences had been discovered, and that they were quiet through fear, he sent
                    back a portion of his troops into the camp, with orders to bring into the front
                    line, with speed, every thing requisite for assaulting the city; satisfied that
                    if he urged them vigorously while they were indisposed to action, the populace
                    would excite some commotion in the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    While, in the van, the troops were running up and down in a hurried manner in
                    discharge of their several duties, and the line was advancing up to the gates,
                    suddenly throwing open the gate, Marcellus ordered that the signal should be
                    given, and a shout raised, and that first the infantry and after them the
                    cavalry should burst forth upon the enemy with all possible impetuosity.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They had occasioned abundant terror and
                    confusion in the centre of the enemy's line, when, at the two side gates, the
                    lieutenant-generals, Publius Valerius Flaccus and Caius Aurelius, sallied forth
                    upon the wings. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The servants, suttlers' boys,
                    and the other multitude appointed to guard the baggage, joined in the shout, so
                    that they suddenly exhibited the appearance of a vast army to the Carthaginians,
                    who despised chiefly their paucity of numbers. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                    /> For my own part I would not take upon me to assert what some authors have
                    declared, that two thousand eight hundred of the enemy were slain, and that the
                    Romans lost not more than five hundred. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Whether the <pb n="855" xml:id="p.855"/> victory was so great or not, it is
                    certain that a very important advantage, and perhaps the greatest during the
                    war, was gained on that day; for not to be vanquished by Hannibal was then a
                    more difficult task to the victorious troops, than to conquer him afterwards. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hannibal, all hope of getting possession
                    of Nola being lost, had retired to Acerrae, Marcellus, having closed the gates
                    and posted guards in different quarters to prevent any one from going out,
                    immediately instituted a judicial inquiry in the forum, into the conduct of
                    those who had been secretly in communication with the enemy. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He beheaded more than seventy who were convicted of
                    treason, and ordered their goods to be confiscated to the Roman state;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and then committing the government to the
                    senate, set out with all his forces, and, pitching a camp, took up a position
                    above Suessula. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian, having at
                    first endeavoured to win over the people of Acerrae to a voluntary surrender,
                    but finding them resolved, makes preparations for a siege and assault. But the
                    people of Acerrae had more spirit than power. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Despairing, therefore, of the defence of the city, when they saw their walls
                    being circumvallated, before the lines of the enemy were completed, they stole
                    off in the dead of night through the opening in the works, and where the watches
                    had been neglected; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and pursuing their course
                    through roads and pathless regions, accordingly as design or mistake directed
                    each, made their escape to those towns of Campania which they knew had not
                    renounced their fidelity. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After Acerrae was
                    plundered and burnt, Hannibal, having received intelligence that the Roman
                    dictator with the new-raised legions was seen at some distance from Casilinum,
                    and fearing lest, the camp of the enemy being so near, something might occur at
                    Capua, marched his army to Casilinum. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At that
                    time Casilinum was occupied by five hundred Praenestines, with a few Romans and
                    Latins, whom the news of the defeat at Cannae had brought to the same place.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These men setting out from home too late,
                    in consequence of the levy at Praeneste not being completed at the appointed
                    day, and arriving at Casilinum before the defeat was known there, where they
                    united themselves with other troops, Romans and allies, were proceeding thence
                    in a tolerably large body, but the news of the battle at Cannae turned them back
                    to Casilinum. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having spent several days <pb
                        n="856" xml:id="p.856"/> there in evading and concerting plots, in fear
                    themselves and suspected by the Campanians, and having now received certain
                    information that the revolt of Capua and the reception of Hannibal were in
                    agitation, they put the townsmen to the sword by night, and seized upon the part
                    of the town on this side the Vulturnus, for it is divided by that river.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such was the garrison the Romans had at
                    Casilinum; to these was added a cohort of Perusians, in number four hundred and
                    sixty, who had been driven to Casilinum by the same intelligence which had
                    brought the Praenestines a few days before. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    They formed a sufficient number of armed men for the defence of walls of so
                    limited extent, and protected on one side by the river. The scarcity of corn
                    made them even appear too numerous. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal having now advanced within a short
                    distance of the place, sent forward a body of Getulians under a commander named
                    Isalca, and orders them in the first place, if an opportunity of parley should
                    be given, to win them over by fair words, to open the gates, and admit a
                    garrison; but, if they persisted in obstinate opposition, to proceed to action,
                    and try if in any part he could force an entrance into the city. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> When they had approached the walls, because silence
                    prevailed there appeared a solitude; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and the
                    barbarian, supposing that they had retired through fear, made preparation for
                    forcing the gates and breaking away the bars, when, the gates being suddenly
                    thrown open, two cohorts, drawn up within for that very purpose, rushed forth
                    with great tumult, and made a slaughter of the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The first party being thus repulsed, Maharbal was sent with
                    a more powerful body of troops; but neither could even he sustain the sally of
                    the cohorts. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Lastly, Hannibal, fixing his camp
                    directly before the walls, prepared to assault this paltry city and garrison,
                    with every effort and all his forces, and having completely surrounded the city
                    with a line of troops, lost a considerable number of men, including all the most
                    forward, who were shot from the walls and turrets, while he pressed on and
                    provoked the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Once he was very near
                    cutting them off, by throwing in a line of elephants, when aggressively sallying
                    forth, and drove them in the utmost confusion into the town; a good many, out of
                    so small a number, having been slain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> More
                    would have fallen had not night interrupted the battle. <pb n="857"
                        xml:id="p.857"/> On the following day, the minds of all were possessed with
                    an ardent desire to commence the assault, especially after a golden mural crown
                    had been promised, and the general himself had reproached the conquerors of
                    Saguntum with the slowness of their siege of a little fort situated on level
                    ground; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> reminding them, each and all, of
                    Cannae, Trasimenus, and Trebia. They then began to apply the vineae and to
                    spring mines: nor was any measure, whether of open force or stratagem,
                    unemployed against the various attempts of the enemy. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> These allies of the Romans erected bulwarks against the
                    vineae, cut off the mines of the enemy by cross-mines, and met their efforts
                    both covertly and openly, till, at last, shame compelled Hannibal to desist from
                    his undertaking; and, fortifying a camp in which he placed a small guard, that
                    the affair might not appear to have been abandoned, he retired into winter
                    quarters to Capua. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There he kept, under
                    cover, for the greater part of the winter, that army, which, though fortified by
                    frequent and continued hardships against every human ill, had yet never
                    experienced or been habituated to prosperity. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, excess of good fortune and unrestrained indulgence were the ruin of
                    men whom no severity of distress had subdued; and so much the more completely,
                    in proportion to the avidity with which they plunged into pleasures to which
                    they were unaccustomed. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For sleep, wine,
                    feasting, women, baths, and ease, which custom rendered more seductive day by
                    day, so completely unnerved both mind and body, that from henceforth their past
                    victories rather than their present strength protected them; and in this the
                    general is considered by those who are skilled in the art of war to have
                    committed a greater error than in not having marched his troops to Rome
                    forthwith from the field of Cannae: <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> for his
                    delay on that occasion might be considered as only to have postponed his
                    victory, but this mistake to have bereaved him of the power of conquering.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Accordingly, by Hercules, as though he
                    marched out of Capua with another army, it retained in no respect any of its
                    former discipline; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> for most of the troops
                    returned in the embrace of harlots; and as soon as they began to live under
                    tents, and the fatigue of marching and other military labours tried them, like
                    raw troops, they failed both in bodily strength and spirit. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> From that time, during the whole period of the summer
                    campaign, a great number of them slunk away from <pb n="858" xml:id="p.858"/>
                    the standards without furloughs, while Capua was the only retreat of the
                    deserters. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, when the rigour of winter began to
                    abate, marching his troops out of their winter quarters he returned to
                    Casilinum; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> where, although there had been an
                    intermission of the assault, the continuance of the siege had reduced the
                    inhabitants and the garrison to the extremity of want. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Titus Sempronius commanded the Roman camp, the dictator
                    having gone to Rome to renew the auspices. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    swollen state of the Vulturnus and the entreaties of the people of Nola and
                    Acerrae, who feared the Campanians if the Roman troops should leave them, kept
                    Marcellus in his place; although desirous himself also to bring assistance to
                    the besieged. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Gracchus, only maintaining his
                    post near Casilinum, because he had been enjoined by the dictator not to take
                    any active steps during his absence, did not stir; although intelligence was
                    brought from Casilinum which might easily overcome every degree of patience.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For it appeared that some had precipitated
                    themselves from the walls through famine, and that they were standing unarmed
                    upon the walls, exposing their undefended bodies to the blows of the missile
                    weapons. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Gracchus, grieved at the
                    intelligence, but not daring to fight contrary to the injunctions of the
                    dictator, and yet aware that he must fight if he openly attempted to convey in
                    provisions, and having no hope of introducing them clandestinely, collected corn
                    from all parts of the surrounding country, and filling several casks sent a
                    message to the magistrate to Casilinum, directing that they might catch the
                    casks which the river would bring down. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    following night, while all were intent upon the river, and the hopes excited by
                    the message from the Romans, the casks sent came floating down the centre of the
                    stream, and the corn was equally distributed among them all. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> This was repeated the second and third day; <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> they were sent off and arrived during the same
                    night; and hence they escaped the notice of the enemy's guards. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> But afterwards, the river, rendered more than
                    ordinarily rapid by continual rains, drove the casks by a cross current to the
                    bank which the enemy were guarding; there they were discovered sticking among
                    the osiers which grew along the banks; and, it being reported to Hannibal, from
                    that time the watches were kept more strictly, that nothing <pb n="859"
                        xml:id="p.859"/> sent to the city by the Vulturnus might escape notice.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> However, nuts poured out at the Roman
                    camp floated down the centre of the river to Casilinum, and were caught with
                    hurdles. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At length they were reduced to such
                    a degree of want, that they endeavoured to chew the thongs and skins which they
                    tore from their shields, after softening them in warm water; nor did they
                    abstain from mice or any other kind of animals. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> They even dug up every kind of herb and root from the lowest mounds of their
                    wall; and when the enemy had ploughed over all the ground producing herbage
                    which was without the wall, they threw in turnip seed, so that Hannibal
                    exclaimed, Must I sit here at Casilinum even till these spring up? <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> and he, who up to that time had not lent an ear to
                    any terms, then at length allowed himself to be treated with respecting the
                    ransom of the free persons. Seven ounces of gold for each person were agreed
                    upon as the price; and then, under a promise of protection, they surrendered
                    themselves. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> They were kept in chains till the
                    whole of the gold was paid, after which they were sent back to Cumae, in
                    fulfilment of the promise. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> This account is
                    more credible than that they were slain by a body of cavalry, which was sent to
                    attack them as they were going away. They were for the most part Prae- nestines.
                    Out of the five hundred and seventy who formed the garrison, almost one half
                    were destroyed by sword or famine; the rest returned safe to Praeneste with
                    their praetor Manicius, who had formerly been a scribe. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> His statue placed in the forum at Praeneste, clad in a coat
                    of mail, with a gown on, and with the head covered, formed an evidence of this
                    account; as did also three images with this legend inscribed on a brazen plate,
                        <quote>Manicius vowed these in behalf of the soldiers who were in the
                        garrison at Casilinum.</quote> The same legend was inscribed under three
                    images placed in the temple of Fortune. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The town of Casilinum was restored to the
                    Campanians, strengthened by a garrison of seven hundred soldiers from the army
                    of Hannibal, lest on the departure of the Carthaginian from it, the Romans
                    should assault it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To the Praenestine soldiers
                    the Roman senate voted double pay and exemption from military service for five
                    years. On being offered the freedom of the state, in consideration of their
                    valour, they would not make the exchange. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    account of <pb n="860" xml:id="p.860"/> the fate of the Perusians is less clear,
                    as no light is thrown upon it by any monument of their own, or any decree of the
                    Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the same time the Petelini, the
                    only Bruttian state which had continued in the Roman alliance, were attacked not
                    only by the Carthaginians, who were in possession of the surrounding country,
                    but also by the rest of the Bruttian states, on account of their having adopted
                    a separate policy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Petelini, unable to
                    bear up against these distresses, sent ambassadors to Rome to solicit aid, whose
                    prayers and entreaties (for on being told that they must themselves take
                    measures for their own safety, they gave themselves up to piteous lamentations
                    in the vestibule of the senate-house) excited the deepest commiseration in the
                    fathers and the people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the question being
                    proposed a second time to the fathers by Manius Pomponius, the praetor, after
                    examining all the resources of the empire, they were compelled to confess that
                    they had no longer any protection for their distant allies, and bid them return
                    home, and having done every thing which could be expected from faithful allies,
                    as to what remained to take measures for their own security in the present state
                    of fortune. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the result of this embassy
                    being reported to the Petelini, their senate was suddenly seized with such
                    violent grief and dismay, that some advised that they should run away wherever
                    each man could find an asylum, and abandon the city. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Some advised, that as they were deserted by their ancient
                    allies, they should unite themselves with the rest of the Bruttian states, and
                    through them surrender themselves to Hannibal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The opinion however which prevailed was that of those who thought that nothing
                    should be done in haste and rashly, and that they should take the whole matter
                    into their consideration again. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The next day,
                    when they had cooled upon it, and their trepidation had somewhat subsided, the
                    principal men carried their point that they should collect all their property
                    out of the fields, and fortify the city and the walls. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Much about the same time letters were brought
                    from Sicily and Sardinia. That of Titus Otacilius the proprietor was first read
                    in the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It stated that Lucius Furius
                    the praetor had arrived at Lilybaeum from Africa with his fleet. That he
                    himself, having been severely wounded, was in imminent danger of his life; that
                    neither pay nor corn was <pb n="861" xml:id="p.861"/> punctually furnished to
                    the soldiers or the marines; nor were there any resources from which they could
                    be furnished. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That he earnestly advised that
                    such supplies should be sent with all possible expedition; and that, if it was
                    thought proper, they should send one of the new praetors to succeed him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nearly the same intelligence respecting corn
                    and pay was conveyed in a letter from Aulus Cornelius Mammula, the propraetor,
                    from Sardinia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The answer to both was, that
                    there were no resources from whence they could be supplied, and orders were
                    given to them that they should themselves provide for their fleets and armies.
                    Titus Otacilius having sent ambassadors to Hiero, the only source of assistance
                    the Romans had, received as much money as was wanting to pay the troops and a
                    supply of corn for six months. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In Sardinia,
                    the allied states contributed liberally to Cornelius. The scarcity of money at
                    Rome also was so great, that on the proposal of Marcus Minucius, plebeian
                    tribune, a financial triumvirate was appointed, consisting of Lucius Aemilius
                    Papus, who had been consul and censor, Marcus Atilius Regulus, who had been
                    twice consul, and Lucius Scribonius Libo, who was then plebeian tribune.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcus and Caius Atilius were also created
                    a duumvirate for dedicating the temple of Concord, which Lucius Manlius had
                    vowed when praetor. Three pontiffs were also created, Quintus Caecilius
                    Metellus, Quintus Fabius Maximus, and Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, in the room of
                    Publius Scantinius deceased, and of Lucius Aemilius Paulus the consul, and of
                    Quintus Aelius Paetus, who had fallen in the battle of Cannae. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The fathers having repaired, as far as human
                    counsels could effect it, the other losses from a continued series of
                    unfortunate events, at length turned their <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    attention on themselves, on the emptiness of the senate-house, and the paucity
                    of those who assembled for public deliberation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> For the senate-roll had not been reviewed since the censorship of Lucius
                    Aemilius and C. Flaminius, though unfortunate battles, during a period of five
                    years, as well as the private casualties of each, had carried off so many
                    senators. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Manius Pomponius, the praetor, as
                    the dictator was now gone to the army after the loss of Casilinum, at the
                    earnest request of all, brought in a bill upon the subject. When Spurius
                    Carvilius, after having lamented in a long speech not only the scantiness of the
                    senate, but the fewness of citizens who were eligible into that <pb n="862"
                        xml:id="p.862"/> body, with the design of making up the numbers of the
                    senate <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and uniting more closely the Romans
                    and the Latin confederacy, declared that he strongly advised that the freedom of
                    the state should be conferred upon two senators from each of the Latin states,
                    if the Roman fathers thought proper, who might be chosen into the senate to
                    supply the places of the deceased senators. This proposition the fathers
                    listened to with no more equanimity than formerly to the request when made by
                    the Latins themselves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A loud and violent
                    expression of disapprobation ran through the whole senate-house. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> In particular, Manlius reminded them that there was
                    still existing a man of that stock, from which that consul was descended who
                    formerly threatened in the Capitol that he would with his own hand put to death
                    any Latin senator he saw in that house. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Upon
                    which Quintus Fabius Maximus said, <quote> that never was any subject introduced
                        into the senate at a juncture more unseasonable than the present, when a
                        question had been touched upon which would still further irritate the minds
                        of the allies, who were already hesitating and wavering in their allegiance.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That that rash suggestion of one
                        individual ought to be annihilated by the silence of the whole body; and
                        that if there ever was a declaration in that house which ought to be buried
                        in profound and inviolable silence, surely that above all others was one
                        which deserved to be covered and consigned to darkness and oblivion, and
                        looked upon as if it had never been made. </quote> This put a stop to the
                    mention of the subject. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They determined that
                    a dictator should be created for the purpose of reviewing the senate, and that
                    he should be one who had been a censor, and was the oldest living of those who
                    had held that office. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They likewise gave
                    orders that Caius Terentius, the consul, should be called home to nominate a
                    dictator; who, leaving his troops in Apulia, returned to Rome with great
                    expedition; and, according to custom, on the following night nominated Marcus
                    Fabius Buteo dictator, for six months, without a master of the horse, in
                    pursuance of the decree of the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He having mounted the rostrum attended by the
                    lictors, declared, that he neither approved of there being two dictators at one
                    time, which had never been done before, nor of his being appointed dictator
                    without a master of the horse; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> nor of the
                    censorian authority being committed to one person, and <pb n="863"
                        xml:id="p.863"/> to the same person a second time; nor that command should
                    be given to a dictator for six months, unless he was created for active
                    operations. That he would himself restrain within proper bounds those
                    irregularities which chance, the exigencies of the times, and necessity had
                    occasioned. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For he would not remove any of
                    those whom the censors Flaminius and Aemilius had elected into the senate;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but would merely order that their names
                    should be transcribed and read over, that one man might not exercise the power
                    of deciding and determining on the character and morals of a senator; and would
                    so elect in place of deceased members, that one rank should appear to be
                    preferred to another, and not man to man. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    old senate-roll having been read, he chose as successors to the deceased, first
                    those who had filled a curule office since the censorship of Flaminius and
                    Aemilius, but had not yet been elected into the senate, as each had been
                    earliest created. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He next chose those who had
                    been aediles, plebeian tribunes, or quaestors; then of those who had never
                    filled the office of magistrate, he selected such as had spoils taken from an
                    enemy fixed up at their homes, or had received a civic crown. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Having thus elected one hundred and seventy-seven senators,
                    with the entire approbation of his countrymen, he instantly abdicated his
                    office, and, bidding the lictors depart, he descended from the rostrum as a
                    private citizen, and mingled with the crowd of persons <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> who were engaged in their private affairs, designedly
                    wearing away this time, lest he should draw off the people from the forum for
                    the purpose of escorting him home. Their zeal, however, did not subside by the
                    delay, for they escorted him to his house in great numbers. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The consul returned to the army the ensuing night, without
                    acquainting the senate, lest he should be detained in the city on account of the
                    elections. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day, on the proposition of Manius
                    Pomponius the praetor, the senate decreed that a letter should be written to the
                    dictator, to the effect, that if he thought it for the interest of the state, he
                    should come, together with the master of the horse and the <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> praetor, Marcus Marcellus, to hold the election for the
                    succeeding consuls, in order that the fathers might learn from them in person in
                    what condition the state was, and take measures according to circumstances. All
                    who were summoned came, leaving lieutenant-generals to <pb n="864"
                        xml:id="p.864"/> hold command of the legions. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator, speaking briefly and modestly of himself,
                    attributed much of the glory of the campaign to the master of the horse,
                    Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus. He then gave out the day for the comitia, at which
                    the consuls created were Lucius Posthumius in his absence, being then employed
                    in the government of the province of Gaul, for the third time, and Tiberius
                    Sempronius Gracchus, who was then master of the horse and curule aedile.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius Laevinus, Appius Claudius
                    Pulcher, Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, and Quintus Mucius Scaevola, were then created
                    Praetors. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the election of the
                    magistrates, the dictator returned to his army, which was in winter quarters at
                    Teanum, leaving his master of the horse at Rome, to take the sense of the
                    fathers relative to the armies to be enlisted and embodied for the service of
                    the year, as he was about to enter upon the magistracy after a few days.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While busily occupied with these matters,
                    intelligence arrived of a fresh disaster —fortune crowding into this year one
                    calamity after another —that Lucius Posthumius, consul elect, himself with all
                    his army was destroyed in Gaul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He was to
                    march his troops through a vast wood, which the Gauls called Litana. On the
                    right and left of his route, the natives had sawed the trees in such a manner
                    that they continued standing upright, but would fall when impelled by a slight
                    force. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Posthumius had with him two Roman
                    legions, and besides had levied so great a number of allies along the Adriatic
                    Sea, that he led into the enemy's country twenty-five thousand men. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> As soon as this army entered the wood, the Gauls, who
                    were posted around its extreme skirts, pushed down the outermost of the sawn
                    trees, which falling on those next them, and these again on others, which of
                    themselves stood tottering and scarcely maintained their position, crushed arms,
                    men, and horses in an indiscriminate manner, so that scarcely ten men escaped.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For most of them being killed by the
                    trunks and broken boughs of trees, the Gauls, who beset the wood on all sides in
                    arms, killed the rest, panic-struck by so unexpected a disaster. A very small
                    number, who attempted to escape by a bridge, were taken prisoners, being
                    intercepted by the enemy who had taken possession of it before them. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Here Posthumius fell, fighting with all his might to
                    prevent his being taken. The Boii, having cut off his head, carried it and the
                    spoils they stript <pb n="865" xml:id="p.865"/> off his body, in triumph into
                    the most sacred temple they had. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Afterwards
                    they cleansed the head according to their custom, and having covered the skull
                    with chased gold, used it as a cup for libations in their solemn festivals, and
                    a drinking cup for their high priests and other ministers of the temple.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The spoils taken by the Gauls were not
                    less than the victory. For though great numbers of the beasts were crushed by
                    the falling trees, yet as nothing was scattered by flight, every thing else was
                    found strewed along the whole line of the prostrate band. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The news of this disaster arriving, when the
                    state had been in so great a panic for many days, that the shops were shut up as
                    if the solitude of night reigned through the city; the senate gave it in charge
                    to the aediles to go round the city, cause the shops to be opened, and this
                    appearance of public affliction to be removed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Then Titus Sempronius, having assembled the senate, consoled and encouraged the
                    fathers, requesting, <quote> that they who had sustained the defeat at Cannae
                        with so much magnanimity would not now be cast down with less calamities.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That if their arms should prosper, as
                        he hoped they would, against Hannibal and the Carthaginians, the war with
                        the Gauls might be suspended and deferred without hazard. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The gods and the Roman people would have it in their
                        power to revenge the treachery of the Gauls another time. That they should
                        now deliberate about the Carthaginian foe, and the forces with which the war
                        was to be prosecuted. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He first laid before them the number of foot
                    and horse, as well citizens as allies, that were in the dictator's army.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then Marcellus gave an account of the
                    amount of his. Those who knew were asked what troops were in Apulia with Caius
                    Terentius Varro the consul. But no practicable plan could be devised for raising
                    consular armies sufficient to support so important a war. For this reason,
                    notwithstanding a just resentment irritated them, they determined that Gaul
                    should be passed over for that year. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    dictator's army was assigned to the consul; and they ordered such of the troops
                    of Marcellus's army as had fled from Cannae, to be transported into Sicily, to
                    serve there as long as the war continued in Italy. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Thither, likewise, were ordered to be sent as unfit to
                    serve with him, the weakest of the dictator's troops, no time of service being
                    appointed, but the <pb n="866" xml:id="p.866"/> legal number of campaigns.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two legions in the city were voted to
                    the other consul who should be elected in the room of Posthumius; and they
                    resolved that he should be elected as soon as the auspices would permit.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Besides, two legions were immediately to
                    be recalled from Sicily, out of which the consul, to whom the city legions fell,
                    might take what number of men he should have occasion for. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The consul Caius Terentius Varro was continued in his
                    command for one year, without lessening the army he had for the defence of
                    Apulia. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these transactions and preparations in
                    Italy, the war in Spain was prosecuted with no less vigour; but hitherto more
                    favourably to the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The two generals had
                    divided their troops, so that Cneius acted by land, and Publius by sea.
                    Hasdrubal, general of the Carthaginians, sufficiently trusting to neither branch
                    of his forces, kept himself at a distance from the enemy, secured by the
                    intervening space and the strength of his fortifications, until, after much
                    solicitation, four thousand foot and five hundred horse were sent him out of
                    Africa as a reinforcement. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At length, inspired
                    with fresh hopes, he moved nearer the enemy; and himself also ordered a fleet to
                    be equipped and prepared for the protection of the islands and sea-coasts.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the very onset of renewing the war, he
                    was greatly embarrassed by the desertion of the captains of his ships, who had
                    ceased to entertain a sincere attachment towards the general and the
                    Carthaginian cause, ever since they were severely reprimanded for abandoning the
                    fleet in a cowardly manner at the Iberus. These deserters had raised an
                    insurrection among the Tartessians, and at their instigation some cities had
                    revolted; they had even taken one by force. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The war was now turned from the Romans into that country, which he entered in a
                    hostile. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> manner, and resolved to attack
                    Galbus, a distinguished general of the Tartessians, who with a powerful army
                    kept close within his camp, before the walls of a city which had been captured
                    but a few days before. Accordingly, he sent his light-armed troops in advance to
                    provoke the enemy to battle, and part of his infantry to ravage the country
                    throughout in every direction, and to cut off stragglers. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> There was a skirmish before the camp, at the same time that
                    many were killed and put to flight in the fields. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> But having by different routes <pb n="867" xml:id="p.867"/>
                    returned to their camp, they so quickly shook off all fear, that they had
                    courage not only to defend their lines, but challenge the enemy to fight. They
                    sallied out, therefore, in a body from the camp, dancing according to their
                    custom. Their sudden boldness terrified the enemy, who a little before had been
                    the assailants. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal therefore drew off
                    his troops to a tolerably steep eminence, and secured further by having a river
                    between it and the enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here the parties of
                    light-armed troops which had been sent in advance, and the horse which had been
                    dispersed about, he called in to join him. But not thinking himself sufficiently
                    secured by the eminence or the river, he fortified his camp completely with a
                    rampart. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While thus fearing and feared
                    alternately, several skirmishes occurred, in which the Numidian cavalry were not
                    so good as the Spanish, nor the Moorish darters so good as the Spanish
                    targetteers, who equalled them in swiftness, but were superior to them in
                    strength and courage. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The enemy seeing they could not, by coming up
                    to Hasdrubal's camp, draw him out to a battle, nor assault it without great
                    difficulty, stormed Asena, whither Hasdrubal, on entering their territories, had
                    laid up his corn and other stores. By this they became masters of all the
                    surrounding country. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But now they became quite
                    ungovernable, both when on march and within their camp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, therefore, perceiving their
                    negligence, which, as usual, was the consequence of success, after having
                    exhorted his troops to attack them while they were straggling and without their
                    standards, came down the hill, and advanced to their camp in order of battle.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On his approach being announced in a
                    tumultuous manner, by men who fled from the watch-posts and advanced guards,
                    they shouted to arms; and as each could get his arms, they rushed precipitately
                    to battle, without waiting for the word, without standards, without order, and
                    without ranks. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The foremost of them were
                    already engaged, while some were running up in parties, and others had not got
                    out of their camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However, at first, the very
                    boldness of their attack terrified the enemy. But when they charged their close
                    ranks with their own which were thin, and were not able to defend themselves for
                    want of numbers, each began to look out for others to support him; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and being repulsed in all quarters they collected
                    themselves in form of <pb n="868" xml:id="p.868"/> a circle, where being so
                    closely crowded together, body to body, armour to armour, that they had not room
                    to wield their arms, they were surrounded by the enemy, who continued to
                    slaughter them till late in the day. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A small
                    number, having forced a passage, made for the woods and hills. With like
                    consternation, their camp was abandoned, and next day the whole nation
                    submitted. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But they did not continue long
                    quiet, for immediately upon this, Hasdrubal received orders from Carthage to
                    march into Italy with all expedition. The report of which, spreading over Spain,
                    made almost all the states declare for the Romans. Accordingly he wrote
                    immediately to Carthage, to inform them how much mischief the report of his
                    march had produced. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That if he really did leave Spain, the Romans would be masters of it all
                        before he could pass the Iberus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For,
                        besides that he had neither an army nor a general whom he could leave to
                        supply his place, so great were the abilities of the Roman generals who
                        commanded there, that they could scarcely be opposed with equal forces.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If, therefore, they had any concern
                        for preserving Spain, they ought to send a general with a powerful army to
                        succeed him. To whom, however prosperous all things might prove, yet the
                        province would not be a position of ease. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though this letter made at first a great
                    impression on the senate, yet, as their interest in Italy was first and most
                    important, they did not at all alter their resolution in relation to Hasdrubal
                    and his troops. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> However, they despatched
                    Himilco with a complete army, and an augmented fleet, to preserve and defend
                    Spain both by sea and land. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he had
                    conveyed over his land and naval forces, he fortified a camp; and having drawn
                    his ships upon dry land, and surrounded them with a rampart, he marched with a
                    chosen body of cavalry, with all possible expedition; using the same caution
                    when passing through people who were wavering, and those who were actually
                    enemies; and came up with Hasdrubal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As soon
                    as he had informed him of the resolutions and orders of the senate, and in his
                    turn been thoroughly instructed in what manner to prosecute the war in Spain, he
                    returned to his camp; his expedition more than any thing else saving him, for he
                    quitted every place before the people could conspire. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Before Hasdrubal quitted his position he laid all the
                    states in subjection to him under contribution. He knew <pb n="869"
                        xml:id="p.869"/> well, that Hannibal purchased a passage through some
                    nations; that he had no Gallic auxiliaries but such as were hired; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> and that if he had undertaken so arduous a march
                    without money, he would scarcely have penetrated so far as the Alps. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> For this reason, having exacted the contributions
                    with great haste, he marched down to the Iberus. As soon as the Roman generals
                    got notice of the Carthaginian senate's resolution, and Hasdrubal's march, they
                    gave up every other concern, and uniting their forces, determined to meet him
                    and oppose his attempt. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They reflected, that
                    when it was already so difficult to make head against Hannibal alone in Italy,
                    there would be an end of the Roman empire in Spain, should Hasdrubal join him
                    with a Spanish army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Full of anxiety and care
                    on these accounts, they assembled their forces at the Iberus, and crossed the
                    river; and after deliberating for some time whether they should encamp opposite
                    to the enemy, or be satisfied with impeding his intended march by attacking the
                    allies of <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the Carthaginians, they made
                    preparations for besieging a city called Ibera, from its contiguity to the
                    river, which was at that time the wealthiest in that quarter. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> When Hasdrubal perceived this, instead of carrying
                    assistance to his allies, he proceeded himself to besiege a city which had
                    lately placed itself under the protection of the Romans; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and thus the siege which was now commenced was given up by
                    them, and the operations of the war turned against Hasdrubal himself. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For a few days they remained encamped at a
                    distance of five miles from each other, not without skirmishes, but without
                    going out to a regular engagement. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At length
                    the signal for battle was given out on both sides on one and the same day, as
                    though by concert, and they marched down into the plain with all their forces.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman army stood in triple line; a
                    part of the light troops were stationed among the first line, the other half
                    were received behind the standards, the cavalry covering the wings. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal formed his centre strong with Spaniards,
                    and placed the Carthaginians in the right wing, the Africans and hired
                    auxiliaries in the left. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His cavalry he placed
                    before the wings, attaching the Numidians to the Carthaginian infantry, and the
                    rest to the Africans. Nor were all the Numidians placed in the right wing, but
                    such as taking two horses each into the field are accus- <pb n="870"
                        xml:id="p.870"/> tomed frequently to leap full armed, when the battle is at
                    the hottest, from a tired horse upon a fresh one, after the manner of vaulters:
                    such was their own agility, and so docile their breed of horses. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> While they stood thus drawn up, the hopes entertained
                    by the generals on both sides were pretty much upon an equality; for neither
                    possessed any great superiority, either in point of the number or quality of the
                    troops. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The feelings of the soldiers were
                    widely different. Their generals had, without difficulty, induced the Romans to
                    believe, that although they fought at a distance from their country, it was
                    Italy and the city of Rome that they were defending. Accordingly, they had
                    brought their minds to a settled resolution to conquer or die; as if their
                    return to their country had hinged upon the issue of that battle. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The other army consisted of less determined men; for
                    they were principally Spaniards, who would rather be vanquished in Spain, than
                    be victorious to be dragged into Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On the
                    first onset, therefore, ere their javelins had scarcely been thrown, their
                    centre gave ground, and the Romans pressing on with great impetuosity, turned
                    their backs. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the wings the battle
                    proceeded with no less activity; on one side the Carthaginians, on the other the
                    Africans, charged vigorously, while the Romans, in a manner surrounded, were
                    exposed to a two-fold attack. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But when the
                    whole of the Roman troops had united in the centre, they possessed sufficient
                    strength to compel the wings of the enemy to retire in different directions;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and thus there were two separate battles,
                    in both of which the Romans were decidedly superior, as after the defeat of the
                    enemy's centre they had the advantage both in the number and strength of their
                    troops. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Vast numbers were slain on this
                    occasion; and had not the Spaniards fled precipitately from the field ere the
                    battle had scarce begun, very few out of the whole army would have survived.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> There was very little fighting of the
                    cavalry, for as soon as the Moors and Numidians perceived that the centre gave
                    way, they fled immediately with the utmost precipitation, leaving the wings
                    uncovered, and also driving the elephants before them. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, after waiting the issue of the battle to the
                    very last, fled from the midst of the carnage with a few attendants. The Romans
                    took and plundered the camp. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> This victory
                    united with the Romans whatever states of Spain were wavering, and left
                    Hasdrubal <pb n="871" xml:id="p.871"/> no hope, not only of leading an army over
                    into Italy, but even of remaining very safely in Spain. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> When these events were made generally known at Rome by
                    letters from the Scipios, the greatest joy was felt, not so much for the
                    victory, as for the stop which was put to the passage of Hasdrubal into Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these transactions were going on in
                    Spain, Petilia, in Bruttium, was taken by Himilco, an officer of Hannibal's,
                    several months after the siege of it began. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This victory cost the Carthaginians much blood and many wounds, nor did any
                    power more subdue the besieged than that of famine; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> for after having consumed their means of subsistence,
                    derived from fruits and the flesh of every kind of quadrupeds, they were at last
                    compelled to live upon skins found in shoemakers' shops, on herbs and roots, the
                    tender barks of trees, and berries gathered from brambles: <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> nor were they subdued until they wanted strength to stand
                    upon the walls and support their arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After
                    gaining Petilia, the Carthaginian marched his forces to Consentia, which being
                    less obstinately defended, he compelled to surrender within a few days.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nearly about the same time, an army of
                    Bruttians invested Croton, a Greek city, formerly powerful in men and arms, but
                    at the present time reduced so low by many and great misfortunes, that less than
                    twenty thousand inhabitants of all ages remained. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The enemy, therefore, easily got possession of a city
                    destitute of defenders: of the citadel alone possession was retained, into which
                    some of the inhabitants fled from the midst of the carnage during the confusion
                    created by the capture of the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    Locrians too revolted to the Bruttians and Carthaginians, the populace having
                    been betrayed by the nobles. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Rhegians were
                    the only people in that quarter who continued to the last in faithful attachment
                    to the Romans, and in the enjoyment of their independence. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The same alteration of feeling extended itself into Sicily
                    also; and not even the family of Hiero altogether abstained from defection;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for Gelo, his eldest son, conceiving a
                    contempt for his father's old age, and, after the defeat of Cannae, for the
                    alliance with Rome, went over to the Carthaginians; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and he would have created a disturbance in Sicily, had he
                    not been carried off, when engaged in arming the people and soliciting the
                    allies, by a death so seasonable, that it threw some degree of suspicion even
                    upon <pb n="872" xml:id="p.872"/> his father. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Such, with various result, were the transactions in Italy, Africa, Sicily, and
                    Spain during this year. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> At the close of the
                    year, Quintus Fabius Maximus requested of the senate, that he might be allowed
                    to dedicate the temple of Venus Erycina, which he had vowed when dictator. The
                    senate decreed, that Tiberius Sempronius, the consul elect, as soon as ever he
                    had entered upon his office, should propose to the people, that they should
                    create Quintus Fabius duumvir, for the purpose of dedicating the temple.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Also, in honour of Marcus Aemilius
                    Lepidus, who had been consul twice and augur, his three sons, Lucius, Marcus,
                    and Quintus exhibited funeral games and twenty-two pairs of gladiators for three
                    days in the forum. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The curule aediles, Caius
                    Laetorius, and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus consul elect, who during his
                    aedileship had been master of the horse, celebrated the Roman games, which were
                    repeated for three days. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The plebeian games
                    of the aediles, Marcus Aurelius Cotta and Marcus Claudius Marcellus, were thrice
                    repeated. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> At the conclusion of the third year
                    of the Punic war, Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus the consul entered upon his
                    office on the ides of March. Of the praetors, Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, who had
                    before been consul and censor, had by lot the city jurisdiction; Marcus Valerius
                    Laevinus, the foreign. Sicily fell to the lot of Appius Claudius Pulcher;
                    Sardinia to Quintus Mucius Scaevola. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The
                    people ordered that Marcus Marcellus should be in command as proconsul, because
                    he was the only Roman general who had been successful in his operations in Italy
                    since the defeat at Cannae. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate decreed, the first day they
                    deliberated in the Capitol, that double taxes should be imposed for that year,
                    one moiety of which should be immediately levied, as a fund <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> from which pay might be given forthwith to all the
                    soldiers, except those who had been at Cannae. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    With regard to the armies they decreed, that Tiberius Sempronius the consul
                    should appoint a day for the two city legions to meet at Cales, whence these
                    legions should be conveyed into the Claudian camp above Suenula. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> That the legions which were there, and they consisted
                    principally of the troops which had fought at Cannae, Appius Claudius Pulcher,
                    the praetor, should transport into Sicily; and that those in Sicily should be
                    removed to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcus Claudius Marcellus was
                    sent to the army, <pb n="873" xml:id="p.873"/> which had been ordered to meet at
                    Cales on a certain day, with orders to march the city legions thence to the
                    Claudian camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Titus Metilius Croto,
                    lieutenant-general, was sent by Appius Claudius Pulcher to receive the old army
                    and remove it into Sicily. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> People at first had
                    expected in silence that the consul would hold an assembly for the election of a
                    colleague, but afterwards perceiving that Marcus Marcellus, whom they wished
                    above all others to be consul this year, on account of his brilliant success
                    during his praetorship, was removed to a distant quarter, as it were on purpose,
                    a murmuring arose in the senate-house, which <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    the consul perceiving, said, <quote> Conscript fathers, it was conducive to the
                        interest of the state, both that Marcus Marcellus should go into Campania to
                        make the exchange of the armies, and that the assembly should not be
                        proclaimed before he had returned thence after completing the business with
                        which he was charged, in order that you might have him as consul whom the
                        situation of the republic required and yourselves prefer. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus nothing was said about the assembly till
                    Marcellus returned. Meanwhile Quintus Fabius Maximus and Titus Otacilius Crassus
                    were created duumvirs for dedicating temples; Otacilius to Mens, Fabius to Venus
                    Erycina. Both are situated in the Capitol, and separated by one channel.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was afterwards proposed to the people,
                    to make Roman citizens of the three hundred Campanian horsemen who had returned
                    to Rome after having faithfully served their period, and also that they should
                    be considered to have been citizens of Cumae from the day before that on which
                    the Campanians had revolted from the Roman people. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> It had been a principal inducement to this proposition,
                    that they themselves said they knew not to what people they belonged, having
                    left their former country, and being not yet admitted into that to which they
                    had returned. After Marcellus returned from the army, an assembly was proclaimed
                    for electing one consul in the room of Lucius Posthumius. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Marcellus was elected with the greatest unanimity, and was
                    immediately to enter upon his office; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> but as
                    it thundered while he entered upon it, the augurs were summoned, who pronounced
                    that they considered the creation informal; and the fathers spread a report that
                    the gods were displeased, because on that occasion, for the first time, two
                    plebeians had been elected consuls. Upon Marcellus's ab- <pb n="874"
                        xml:id="p.874"/> dicating his office, Fabius Maximus, for the third time,
                    was elected in his room. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> This year the sea
                    appeared on fire; at Sinuessa a cow brought forth a horse foal; <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> the statues in the temple of Juno Sospita Lanuvium
                    flowed down with blood; and a shower of stones fell in the neighbourhood of that
                    temple: on account of which shower the nine days' sacred rite was celebrated, as
                    is usual on such occasions, and the other prodigies were carefully expiated. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls divided the armies between them.
                    The army which Marcus Junius the dictator had commanded fell to the lot of
                    Fabius. To that of Sempronius fell the volunteer slaves, with twenty-five
                    thousand of the allies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To Marcus Valerius the
                    praetor were assigned the legions which had returned from Sicily. Marcus
                    Claudius, proconsul, was sent to that army which lay above Suessula for the
                    protection of Nola. The praetors set out for Sicily and Sardinia. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls issued a proclamation, that as often as
                    they summoned a senate, the senators and those who had a right to give their
                    opinion in the senate, should assemble at the Capuan gate. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The praetors who were charged with the administration of
                    justice, fixed their tribunals in the public fish market; there they ordered
                    sureties to be entered into, and here justice was administered this year.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Meanwhile news was brought to Carthage,
                    from which place Mago, Hannibal's brother, was on the point of carrying over
                    into Italy twelve thousand foot, fifteen hundred horse, twenty elephants, and a
                    thousand talents of silver, under a convoy of sixty men of war, that the
                    operations of <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the war had not succeeded in
                    Spain, and that almost all the people in that province had gone over to the
                    Romans. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were some who were for sending
                    Mago with that fleet and those forces into Spain, neglecting Italy, when an
                    unexpected prospect of regaining Sardinia broke upon them. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> They were informed, that <quote> the Roman army there was
                        small, that Aulus Cornelius, who had been praetor there, and was well
                        acquainted with the province, was quitting it, and that a new one was
                        expected. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Moreover, that the minds of the
                        Sardinians were now wearied with the long continuance of rule; and that
                        during the last year it had been exercised with severity and rapacity. That
                        the people were weighed down with heavy taxes, and an oppressive
                        contribution of corn; that there was nothing wanting but a leader to whom
                        they <pb n="875" xml:id="p.875"/> might revolt. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This secret embassy had been sent by the
                    nobles, Hampsicora being the chief contriver of the measure, who at that time
                    was first by far in wealth and influence. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Disconcerted and elated almost at the same time by these accounts, they sent
                    Mago with his fleet <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> and forces into Spain,
                    and selecting Hasdrubal as general for Sardinia, assigned to him about as large
                    a force as to Mago. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At Rome, the consuls,
                    after transacting what was necessary to be done in the city, now prepared
                    themselves for the war. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Tiberius Sempronius
                    appointed a day for his soldiers to assemble at Sinuessa; and Quintus Fabius
                    also, having first consulted the senate, issued a proclamation, that all persons
                    should convey corn from the fields into fortified towns, before the calends of
                    June next ensuing: <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> if any neglected to do so
                    he would lay waste his lands, sell his slaves by auction, and burn his
                    farmhouses. Not even the praetors, who were created for the purpose of
                    administering justice, were allowed an exemption from military employments.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It was resolved that Valerius the praetor
                    should go into Apulia, to receive the army from Terentius, and that, when the
                    legions from Sicily had arrived, he should employ them principally for the
                    protection of that quarter. That the army of Terentius should be sent into
                    Sicily, with some one of the lieutenant-generals. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> Twenty-five ships were given to Marcus Valerius, to protect
                    the seacoast between Brundusium and Tarentum. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    An equal number was given to Quintus Fulvius, the city praetor, to protect the
                    coasts in the neighbourhood of the city. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> To
                    Caius Terentius, the proconsul, it was given in charge to press soldiers in the
                    Picenian territory, and to protect that part of the country; <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> and Titus Otacilius Crassus, after he had dedicated the
                    temple of Mens in the Capitol, was invested with command, and sent into Sicily
                    to take the conduct of the fleet. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On this contest, between the two most powerful
                    people in the world, all kings and nations had fixed their attention. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Among them Philip, king of the Macedonians, regarded
                    it with greater anxiety, in proportion as he was nearer to Italy, and because he
                    was separated from it only by the Ionian Sea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When he first heard that Hannibal had crossed the Alps, as he was rejoiced that
                    a war had arisen between the Romans and the Carthaginians, so while their
                    strength was yet undetermined, he felt doubtful which he should rather wish to
                        <pb n="876" xml:id="p.876"/> be victorious. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> But after the third battle had been fought, and the third victory had been on
                    the side of the Carthaginians, he inclined to fortune, and sent ambassadors to
                    Hannibal. These, avoiding the harbours of Brundusium and Tarentum, because they
                    were occupied by guards of Roman ships, landed at the temple of Juno Lacinia.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thence passing through Apulia, on their
                    way to Capua, they fell in with the Roman troops stationed to protect the
                    country, and were conveyed to Marcus Valerius Laevinus, the praetor, who lay
                    encamped in the neighbourhood of Luceria. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here
                    Xenophanes, who was at the head of the embassy, fearlessly stated, that he was
                    sent by King Philip to conclude a treaty of alliance and friendship with the
                    Roman people, and that he had commissions to the Roman consuls, senate, and
                    people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The praetor, highly delighted with
                    this new alliance with a distinguished potentate, amidst the desertions of her
                    old allies, courteously entertained these enemies as guests, and furnished them
                    with persons to accompany them carefully to point out the roads, and inform
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> them what places, and what passes, the
                    Romans or the enemy occupied. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Xenophanes
                    passing through the Roman troops came into Campania, whence, by the shortest
                    way, he entered the camp of Hannibal, and concluded a treaty of alliance and
                    friendship with him on the following terms: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    That <quote> King Philip, with as large a fleet as he could, (and it was thought
                        he could make one of two hundred ships,) should pass over into Italy, and
                        lay waste the sea-coast, that he should carry on the war by land and sea
                        with all his might; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> when the war was
                        concluded, that all Italy, with the city of Rome itself, should be the
                        property of the Carthaginians and Hannibal, and that all the booty should be
                        given up to Hannibal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That when Italy was
                        completely subdued they should sail into Greece, and carry on war with such
                        nations as the king pleased. That the cities on the continent and the
                        islands which border on Macedonia, should belong to Philip, and his
                        dominions. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A treaty was concluded between the
                    Carthaginian general and the ambassadors, upon nearly these terms; and Gisgo,
                    Bostar, and Mago were sent as ambassadors with them to receive the ratification
                    of the king in person. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They arrived at the
                    same place, near the temple of Juno Lacinia, where the vessel lay concealed in a
                    creek. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Setting out thence, when they had got
                    into the open sea, they were descried by <pb n="877" xml:id="p.877"/> the Roman
                    fleet, which was guarding the coasts of Calabria. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Valerius Flaccus having sent fly-boats to pursue
                    and bring back the ship, the king's party at first attempted to fly; but
                    afterwards, finding that they were overmatched in swiftness, they delivered
                    themselves up to the Romans, and were brought to the commander of the fleet.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Upon being asked by him who they were,
                    whence they came, and whither they were going, Xenophanes, having once been
                    pretty successful, made up a fictitious story and said, <quote> that he was sent
                        from Philip to the Romans; that he had succeeded in reaching Marcus
                        Valerius, to whom alone he had safe access; that he was unable to make his
                        way through Campania, which was beset with the troops of the enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But afterwards the Carthaginian dress and
                    manners excited suspicions of the messengers of Hannibal, and when interrogated,
                    their speech betrayed them; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> then on their
                    companions being removed to separate places, and intimidated by threats, even a
                    letter from Hannibal to Philip was discovered, and the agreement made between
                    the king of the Macedonians and the Carthaginian. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> These points having been ascertained, the best course
                    appeared to be, to convey the prisoners and their companions as soon as possible
                    to the senate at Rome, or to the consuls, wheresoever they might be; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> for this service five of the fastest sailing vessels
                    were selected, and Lucius Valerius Antias sent in command of them, with orders
                    to distribute the ambassadors through all the ships separately, and take
                    particular care that they should hold no conversation or consultation with each
                    other. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> About the same time Aulus Cornelius
                    Mammula, on his return from the province of Sardinia, made a report of the state
                    of affairs in the island; that every body contemplated war and revolt;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that Quintus Mucius who succeeded him,
                    being on his arrival affected by the unwholesomeness of the air and water, had
                    fallen into a disorder rather lingering than dangerous, and would for a long
                    time be incapable of sustaining the violent exertion of the war; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> that the army there, though strong enough for the
                    protection of a province in a state of tranquillity, was, nevertheless, not
                    adequate to the maintenance of the war which seemed to be about to break out.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Upon which the fathers decreed, that
                    Quintus Fulvius Flaccus should enlist five thousand foot and four hundred horse,
                    and take care that the legion thus formed should be trans- <pb n="878"
                        xml:id="p.878"/> ported as soon <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> as
                    possible into Sardinia, and send invested with command whomsoever he thought fit
                    to conduct the business of the war until Mucius had recovered. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> For this service Titus Manlius Torquatus was sent; he had
                    been twice consul and censor, and had subdued the Sardinians during his
                    consulate. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Nearly about the same time a fleet
                    sent from Carthage to Sardinia under the conduct of Hasdrubal, surnamed the
                    Bald, having suffered from a violent tempest, was driven upon the Balearian
                    islands, where a good deal of time was lost in refitting <milestone n="17??"
                        unit="section"/> the ships, which were hauled on shore, so much were they
                    damaged, not only in their rigging but also in their hulls. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the war was carried on in Italy with less
                    vigour since the battle of Cannae, the strength of one party having been broken,
                    and the energy of the other relaxed, the Campanians of themselves made an
                    attempt to subjugate Cumae, at first by soliciting them to revolt from the
                    Romans, and when <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> that plan did not succeed,
                    they contrived an artifice by which to entrap them. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> All the Campanians had a stated sacrifice at Hamae. They
                    informed the Cumans that the Campanian senate would come there, and requested
                    that the Cuman senate should also be present to deliberate in concert, in order
                    that both people might have the same allies and the same enemies; they said that
                    they would have an armed force there for their protection, that there might be
                    no danger from the Romans or Carthaginians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The Cumans, although they suspected treachery, made no objection, concluding
                    that thus the deception they meditated might be concealed. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Meanwhile Tiberius Sempronius, the Roman consul, having
                    purified his army at Sinuessa, where he had appointed a day for their meeting,
                    crossed the Vulturnus, and pitched his camp in the neighbourhood of Liternum.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As his troops were stationed here without
                    any employment, he compelled them frequently to go through their exercise, that
                    the recruits, which consisted principally of volunteer slaves, might accustom
                    themselves to follow the standards, and know their own centuries in battle.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While thus engaged, the general was
                    particularly anxious for concord, and therefore enjoined the lieutenant-generals
                    and the tribunes that <quote> no disunion should be engendered among the
                        different orders, by casting reproaches on any one on account of his former
                        condition. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That the veteran soldier should
                        be content <pb n="879" xml:id="p.879"/> to be placed on an equal footing
                        with the tiro, the freeman with the volunteer slave; that all should
                        consider those men sufficiently respectable in point of character and birth,
                        to whom the Roman people had intrusted their arms and standards; that the
                        measures which circumstances made it necessary to adopt, the same
                        circumstances also made it necessary to support when adopted. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This was not more carefully prescribed by the
                    generals than observed by the soldiers; and in a short time the minds of all
                    were united in such perfect harmony, that the condition from which each became a
                    soldier was almost forgotten. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While Gracchus
                    was thus employed, ambassadors from Cumae brought him information of the embassy
                    which had come to them from the Campanians, a few days before, and the answer
                    they had given them; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that the festival would
                    take place in three days from that time; that not only the whole body of their
                    senate, but that the camp and the army of the Campanians would be there.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Gracchus having directed the Cumans to
                    convey every thing out of their fields into the town, and to remain within their
                    walls, marched himself to Cumae, on the day before that on which the Campanians
                    were to attend the sacrifice. Hamae was three miles distant from his position.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Campanians had by this time assembled
                    there in great numbers according to the plan concerted; and not far off Marius
                    Alfius, Medixtuticus, which is the name of the chief magistrate of the
                    Campanians, lay encamped in a retired spot with fourteen thousand armed men,
                    considerably more occupied <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> in making
                    preparation for the sacrifice and in concerting the stratagem to be executed
                    during it, than in fortifying his camp or any other military work. The sacrifice
                    at Hamae lasted for three days. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> It was a
                    nocturnal rite, so arranged as to be completed before midnight. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> Gracchus, thinking this the proper time for
                    executing his plot, placed guards at the gates to prevent any one from carrying
                    out intelligence of his intentions; and having compelled his men to employ the
                    time from the tenth hour in taking refreshment and sleep, in order that they
                    might be able to assemble on a signal given as soon as it was dark. <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> He ordered the standards to be raised about the
                    first watch, and marching in silence, reached Hamae at midnight; where, finding
                    the Campanian camp in a neglected state, as might be expected during a nocturnal
                    festival, he assaulted it at every gate at once; <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> some <pb n="880" xml:id="p.880"/> he butchered while
                    stretched on the ground asleep, others as they were returning unarmed after
                    finishing the sacrifice. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> In the tumultuous
                    action of this night more than two thousand men were slain, together with the
                    general himself, Marius Alfius, and thirty-four military standards were
                    captured. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Gracchus, having made himself master of the
                    enemy's camp with the loss of less than a hundred men, hastily returned to
                    Cumae, fearful of an attack from Hannibal, who lay encamped above Capua on
                    Tifata; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> nor did his provident anticipation of
                    the future deceive him; for as soon as intelligence was brought to Capua of this
                    loss, Hannibal, concluding that he should find at Hamae this army, which
                    consisted for the most part of recruits and slaves, extravagantly elated with
                    its success, despoiling the vanquished and collecting booty, marched by Capua at
                    a <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> rapid pace, ordering those Campanians whom
                    he met in their flight to be conducted to Capua under an escort, and the wounded
                    to be conveyed in carriages. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He found at Hamae
                    the camp abandoned by the enemy, where there was nothing to be seen but the
                    traces of the recent carnage, and the bodies of his allies strewed in every
                    part. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some advised him to lead his troops
                    immediately thence to Cumae, and assault the town. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Though Hannibal desired, in no ordinary degree, to get
                    possession of Cumae at least, as a maritime town, since he could not gain
                    Neapolis; yet as his soldiers had brought out with them nothing besides their
                    arms on their hasty march, he retired to his camp on Tifata. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> But, wearied with the entreaties of the Campanians, he
                    returned thence to Cumae the following day, with every thing requisite for
                    besieging the town; and having thoroughly wasted the lands of Cumae, pitched his
                    camp a mile from the town, in which Gracchus <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    had stayed more because he was ashamed to abandon, in such an emergency, allies
                    who implored his protection and that of the Roman people, than because he felt
                    confidence in his army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor dared the other
                    consul, Fabius, who was encamped at Cales, lead his troops across the Vulturnus,
                    being employed at first in taking new auspices, and afterwards with the
                    prodigies which were reported one after another; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and while expiating these, the aruspices answered that they
                    were not easily atoned. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these causes detained Fabius, Sempronius
                    was besieged, and now works were employed in the attack. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Against <pb n="881" xml:id="p.881"/> a very large wooden
                    tower which was brought up to the town, the Roman consul raised up another
                    considerably higher from the wall itself; for he had made use of the wall, which
                    was pretty high of itself, as a platform, placing strong piles as supports.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From this the besieged at first defended
                    their walls and city, with stones, javelins, and other missiles; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> but lastly, when they perceived the tower advanced
                    into contact with the wall, they threw upon it a large quantity of fire, making
                    use of blazing fire-brands; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and while the
                    armed men were throwing themselves down from the tower in great numbers, in
                    consequence of the flames thus occasioned, the troops sallying out of the town
                    at two gates at once, routed the enemy, and drove them back to their camp; so
                    that the Carthaginians that day were more like persons besieged than besiegers.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As many as one thousand three hundred of
                    the Carthaginians were slain, and fifty-nine made prisoners, having been
                    unexpectedly overpowered, while standing careless and unconcerned near the walls
                    and on the outposts, fearing any thing rather than a sally. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Gracchus sounded a retreat, and withdrew his men within the
                    walls, before the enemy could recover themselves from the effects of this sudden
                    terror. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The next day Hannibal, supposing that
                    the consul, elated with his success, would engage him in a regular battle, drew
                    up his troops in battle-array between the camp and the city; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> but finding that not a man was removed from the customary
                    guard of the town, and that nothing was hazarded upon rash hopes, he returned to
                    Tifata without accomplishing any thing. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At
                    the same time that Cumae was relieved from siege, Tiberius Sempronius, surnamed
                    Longus, fought successfully with the Carthaginian general, Hanno, at Grumentum
                    in Lucania. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He slew above two thousand of the
                    enemy, losing two hundred and eighty of his own men. He took as many as
                    forty-one military standards. Hanno, driven out of the Lucanian territory, drew
                    back among the Bruttii. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Three towns belonging
                    to the Hirpinians, which had revolted from the Romans, were regained by force by
                    the praetor, Marcus Valerius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Vercellius and
                    Sicilius, the authors of the revolt, were beheaded; above a thousand prisoners
                    sold by auction; and the rest of the booty having been given up to the soldiery,
                    the army was marched back to Luceria. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were taking place in
                    Lucania and <pb n="882" xml:id="p.882"/> Hirpinia, the five ships, which were
                    conveying to Rome the captured ambassadors of the Macedonians and Carthaginians,
                    after passing round the whole coast of Italy from the upper to the lower sea,
                    were sailing by Cumae, when, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> it not being
                    known whether they belonged to enemies or allies, Gracchus despatched some ships
                    from his fleet to meet them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When it was
                    ascertained, in the course of their mutual inquiries, that the consul was at
                    Cumae, the ships put in there, the captives were brought before the consul, and
                    their letters placed in his hands. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul,
                    after he had read the letters of Philip and Hannibal, sent them all, sealed up,
                    to the senate by land, ordering that the ambassadors should be conveyed thither
                    by sea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The ambassadors and the letters
                    arriving at Rome nearly on the same day, and on examination the answers of the
                    ambassadors corresponding with the contents of the letters, at first intense
                    anxiety oppressed the fathers, on seeing what a formidable war with Macedonia
                    threatened them, when with difficulty bearing up against the Punic war;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> yet so far were they from sinking under
                    their calamities, that they immediately began to consider how they might divert
                    the enemy from Italy, by commencing hostilities themselves. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> After ordering the prisoners to be confined in chains, and
                    selling their attendants by public auction, they decreed, that twenty more ships
                    should be got ready, in addition to the twenty-five ships which Publius Valerius
                    Flaccus had been appointed to command. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These
                    being provided and launched, and augmented by the five ships which had conveyed
                    the captive ambassadors to Rome, a fleet of fifty ships set sail from Ostia to
                    Tarentum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Publius Valerius was ordered to put
                    on board the soldiers of Varro, which Lucius Apustius, lieutenant-general,
                    commanded at Tarentum; and, with this fleet of fifty ships, not only to protect
                    the coast of Italy, but also to make inquiry respecting the Macedonian war.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If the plans of Philip corresponded with
                    his letter, and the discoveries made by his ambassadors, he was directed to
                    acquaint the praetor, <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius, with
                    it, who, leaving Lucius Apustius, lieutenant-general, in command of the army,
                    and going to Tarentum to the fleet, was to cross over to Macedonia with all
                    speed, and endeavour to detain Philip in his own dominions. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The money which had been sent into Sicily to Appius
                    Claudius, to be repaid to Hiero, was assigned for the support of the fleet and
                    the main- <pb n="883" xml:id="p.883"/> tenance of the Macedonian war. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> This money was conveyed to Tarentum, by Lucius
                    Apustius, lieutenant-general, and with it Hiero sent two hundred thousand pecks
                    of wheat, and a hundred thousand of barley. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the Romans were engaged in these
                    preparations and transactions, the captured ship, which formed one of those
                    which had been sent to Rome, made its escape on the voyage and returned to
                    Philip; from which source it became known that the ambassadors with their
                    letters had been made prisoners. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not knowing,
                    therefore, what had been agreed upon between Hannibal and his ambassadors, or
                    what proposals they were to have brought back to him, he sent another embassy
                    with the same instructions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The ambassadors
                    sent to Hannibal were Heraclitus, surnamed Scotinus, Crito of Beraea, and
                    Sositheus of Magnesia; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> these successfully took
                    and brought back their commissions, but the summer had passed before the king
                    could take any step or make any attempt. Such an influence had the capture of
                    one vessel, together with the ambassadors, in deferring a war which threatened
                    the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Fabius crossed the Vulturnus,
                    after having at length expiated the prodigies, and both the consuls prosecuted
                    the war in the neighbourhood of Capua. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Fabius
                    regained by force the towns Compulteria, Trebula, and Saticula, which had
                    revolted to the Carthaginians; and in them were captured the garrisons of
                    Hannibal and a great number of Campanians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At
                    Nola, as had been the case the preceding year, the senate sided with the Romans,
                    the commons with Hannibal; and deliberations were held clandestinely on the
                    subject of massacring the nobles and betraying the city; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> but to prevent their succeeding in their designs, Fabius
                    marched his army between Capua and the camp of Hannibal on Tifata, and sat down
                    in the Claudian camp above Suessula, whence he sent Marcus Marcellus, the
                    proconsul, with those forces which he had under him, to Nola for its protection. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Sardinia also the operations of the war,
                    which had been intermitted from the time that Quintus Mucius, the praetor, had
                    been seized with a serious illness, began to be conducted by Titus Manlius, the
                    praetor. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Having hauled the ships of war on
                    shore at Carale, and armed his mariners, in order that he might prosecute the
                    war by land, and received the army from the praetor, he made up the number of
                    twenty- <pb n="884" xml:id="p.884"/> two thousand foot and twelve hundred horse.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Setting out for the territory of the enemy
                    with these forces of foot and horse, he pitched his camp not far from the camp
                    of Hampsicora. It happened that Hampsicora was then gone among the Sardinians,
                    called Pelliti, in order to arm their youth, whereby he might augment his
                    forces. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His son, named Hiostus, had the
                    command of the camp, who coming to an engagement, with the presumption of youth,
                    was routed and put to flight. In that battle as many as three thousand of the
                    Sardinians were slain, and about eight hundred taken alive. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The rest of the army at first wandered in their flight
                    through the fields and woods, but afterwards all fled to a city named Cornus,
                    the capital of that district, whither there was a report that their general had
                    fled; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and the war in Sardinia would have been
                    brought to a termination by that battle, had not the Carthaginian fleet under
                    the command of Hasdrubal, which had been driven by a storm upon the Balearian
                    islands, come in seasonably for inspiring a hope of renewing the war. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Manlius, after hearing of the arrival of the Punic
                    fleet, returned to Carale, which afforded Hampsicora an opportunity of forming a
                    junction with the Carthaginian. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal,
                    having landed his forces and sent back his fleet to Carthage, set out under the
                    guidance of Hampsicora, to lay waste the lands of the allies of the Romans; and
                    he would have proceeded to Carale, had not Manlius, meeting him with his army,
                    restrained him from this wide-spread depredation. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> At first their camps were pitched opposite to each other,
                    at a small distance; afterwards skirmishes and slight encounters took place with
                    varying success; lastly, they came down into the field and fought a regular
                    pitched battle for four hours. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginians caused the battle to continue long doubtful, for the Sardinians
                    were accustomed to yield easily; but at last, when the Sardinians fell and fled
                    on all sides around them, the Carthaginians themselves were routed. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> But as they were turning their backs, the Roman
                    general, wheeling round that wing with which he had driven back the Sardinians,
                    intercepted them, after which it was rather a carnage than a battle. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Two thousand of the enemy, Sardinians and
                    Carthaginians together, were slain, about three thousand seven hundred captured,
                    with twenty-seven military standards. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Above all, the general, Hasdrubal, and two
                    other noble <pb n="885" xml:id="p.885"/> Carthaginians having been made
                    prisoners, rendered the bat- tle glorious and memorable; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Mago, who was of the Barcine family, and nearly related to
                    Hannibal, and Hanno, the author of the revolt of the Sardinians, and without
                    doubt the instigator of this war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor less did
                    the Sardinian generals render that battle distinguished by their disasters; for
                    not only was Hiostus, son of Hampsicora, slain in the battle, but Hampsicora
                    himself flying with a few horse, having heard <milestone n="4??" unit="section"
                    /> of the death of his son in addition to his unfortunate state, committed
                    suicide by night, lest the interference of any person should prevent the
                    accomplishment of his design. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To the other
                    fugitives the city of Cornus afforded a refuge, as it had done before; but
                    Manlius, having assaulted it with his victorious troops, regained it in a few
                    days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then other cities also which had gone
                    over to Hampsicora and the Carthaginians, surrendered themselves and gave
                    hostages, on which having imposed a contribution of money and corn, proportioned
                    to the means and delinquency of each, he led back his troops to Carale.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There launching his ships of war, and
                    putting the soldiers he had brought with him on board, he sailed to Rome,
                    reported to the fathers the total subjugation of Sardinia, and handed over the
                    contribution of money to the quaestors, of corn to the aediles, and the
                    prisoners to the praetor Fulvius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During the
                    same time, as Titus Otacilius the praetor, who had sailed over with a fleet of
                    fifty ships from Lilybaeum to Africa, and laid <milestone n="9??" unit="section"
                    /> waste the Carthaginian territory, was returning thence to Sardinia, to which
                    place it was reported that Hasdrubal had recently crossed over from the
                    Baleares, he fell in with his fleet on its return to Africa; and after a slight
                    engagement in the open sea, captured seven ships with their crews. Fear
                    dispersed the rest far and wide, not less effectually than a storm. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> It happened also, at the same time, that Bomilcar
                    arrived at Locri with soldiers sent from Carthage as a reinforcement, bringing
                    with him also elephants and provisions. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In
                    order to surprise and overpower him, Appius Claudius, having hastily led his
                    troops to Messana, under pretext of making the circuit of the province, crossed
                    over to Locri, the tide being favourable. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Bomilcar had by this time left the place, having set out for Bruttium to join
                    Hanno. The Locrians closed their gates against the Romans, and Appius Claudius
                    returned to Rome without achieving any thing, <pb n="886" xml:id="p.886"/> by
                    his strenuous efforts. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The same summer
                    Marcellus made frequent excursions from Nola, which he was occupying with a
                    garrison, into the lands of the Hirpini and Caudine Samnites, and so destroyed
                    all <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> before him with fire and sword, that he
                    renewed in Samnium the memory of her ancient disasters. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ambassadors were therefore despatched from
                    both nations at the same time to Hannibal, who thus addressed the Carthaginian:
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Hannibal, we carried on hostilities with the Roman people, by ourselves
                        and from our own resources, as long as our own arms and our own strength
                        could protect us. Our confidence in these failing, we attached ourselves to
                        king Pyrrhus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Abandoned by him, we
                        accepted of a peace, dictated by necessity, which we continued to observe up
                        to the period when you arrived in Italy, through a period of almost fifty
                        years. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Your valour and good fortune, not
                        more than your unexampled humanity and kindness displayed towards our
                        countrymen, whom, when made prisoners, you restored to us, so attached us to
                        you, that while you our friend were in health and safety, we not only feared
                        not the Romans, but not even the anger of the gods, if it were lawful so to
                        express ourselves. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And yet, by Hercules,
                        you not only being in safety and victorious, but on the spot, (when you
                        could almost hear the shrieks of our wives and children, and see our
                        buildings in flames,) we have suffered, during this summer, such repeated
                        devastations, that Marcellus, and not Hannibal, would appear to have been
                        the conqueror at Cannae; while the Romans boast that you had strength only
                        to inflict a single blow; and having as it were left your sting, now lie
                        torpid. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For near a century we waged war
                        with the Romans, unaided by any foreign general or army; except that for two
                        years Pyrrhus rather augmented his own strength by the addition of our
                        troops, than defended us by his. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I will
                        not boast of our successes, that two consuls and two consular armies were
                        sent under the yoke by us, nor of any other joyful and glorious events which
                        have happened to us. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> We can tell of the
                        difficulties and distresses we then experienced, with less indignation than
                        those which are now occurring. Dictators, those officers of high authority,
                        with their <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> masters of horse, two consuls
                        with two consular armies, entered our borders, and, after having
                        reconnoitred and posted reserves, led on their troops in regular array to
                        devastate our country. Now we <pb n="887" xml:id="p.887"/> are the prey of a
                        single proprietor, and of one little garrison, for the defence of Nola.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Now they do not even confine
                        themselves to plundering in companies, but, like marauders, range through
                        our country from one end to the other, more unconcernedly than if they were
                        rambling through the Roman territory. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And
                        the reason is this, you do not protect us yourself, and the whole of our
                        youth, which, if at home, would keep us in safety, is serving under your
                        banners. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> We know nothing either of you or
                        your army, but we know that it would be easy for the man who has routed and
                        dispersed so many Roman armies, to put down these rambling freebooters of
                        ours, who roam about in disorder to whatsoever quarter the hope of booty,
                        however groundless, attracts them. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They
                        indeed will be the prey of a few Numidians, and a garrison sent to us will
                        also dislodge that at Nola, provided you do not think those men undeserving
                        that you should protect them as allies, whom you have esteemed worthy of
                        your alliance. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this Hannibal replied, <quote> that the
                        Hirpini and Samnites did every thing at once: that they both represented
                        their sufferings, solicited succours, and complained that they were
                        undefended and neglected. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whereas, they
                        ought first to have represented their sufferings, then to have solicited
                        succours; and lastly, if those succours were not obtained, then, at length,
                        to make complaint that assistance had been implored without effect.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That he would lead his troops not into
                        the fields of the Hirpini and Samnites, lest he too should be a burthen to
                        them, but into the parts immediately contiguous, and belonging to the allies
                        of the Roman people, by plundering which, he would enrich his own soldiers,
                        and cause the enemy to retire from them through fear. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> With regard to the Roman war, if the battle of
                        Trasimenus was more glorious than that at Trebia, and the battle of Cannae
                        than that of Trasimenus, that he would eclipse the fame of the battle of
                        Cannae by a greater and more brilliant victory. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With this answer, and with munificent
                    presents, he dismissed the ambassadors. Having left a pretty large garrison in
                    Tifata, he set out with the rest of his troops to go to Nola. Thither came Hanno
                    from the Bruttii with recruits and elephants brought from Carthage. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Having encamped not far from the place, every thing,
                    upon examination, was found to be widely different from what he had heard from
                    the am- <pb n="888" xml:id="p.888"/> bassadors of the allies. For Marcellus was
                    doing nothing, in such a way that he could be said to have committed himself
                    rashly either to fortune or to the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                    had gone out on plundering expeditions, having previously reconnoitred, planted
                    strong guards, and secured a retreat; the same caution was observed and the same
                    provisions made, as if Hannibal were present. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    At this time, when he perceived the enemy on the approach, he kept his forces
                    within the walls, ordered the senators of Nola to patrole the walls, and explore
                    on all hands what was doing among the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Of these Herennius Bassus and Herius Petrius, having been invited by Hanno, who
                    had come up to the wall, to a conference, and gone out with the permission of
                    Marcellus, were thus addressed by him, through an interpreter. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> After extolling the valour and good fortune of Hannibal,
                    and vilifying the majesty of the Roman people, which he represented as sinking
                    into decrepitude with their strength; he said, "but though they were on an
                    equality in <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> these respects, as once perhaps
                    they were, yet they who had experienced how oppressive the government of Rome
                    was towards its allies, and how great the clemency of Hannibal, even towards all
                    his prisoners of the Italian name, were bound to prefer the friendship and
                    alliance of the Carthaginians to those of the Romans. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> If both the consuls with their armies were at Nola, still
                    they would no more be a match for Hannibal than they had been at Cannae, much
                    less would one praetor with a few raw soldiers be able to defend it. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> It was a question which concerned themselves more
                    than Hannibal, whether he should take possession of Nola as captured or
                    surrendered, for that he would certainly make himself master of it, as he had
                    done with regard to Capua and Nuceria, and what difference there was between the
                    fate of Capua and Nuceria, the Nolans themselves, situated as they were nearly
                    midway between them, were well aware. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He said
                    he was unwilling to presage the evils which would result to the city if taken by
                    force, but would in preference pledge himself that if they would deliver up
                    Nola, together with Marcellus and his garrison, no other person than themselves
                    should dictate the conditions on which they should come into the friendship and
                    alliance of Hannibal. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this Herennius Bassus replied, that,
                        <quote> a friendship had subsisted now for many years between the Romans and
                            <pb n="889" xml:id="p.889"/> the Nolans, which neither party up to that
                        day regretted; and even had they been disposed to change their friends upon
                        a change of fortune, it was now too late to change; <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> had they intended to surrender themselves to Hannibal,
                        they should not have called a Roman garrison to their aid: that all fortunes
                        both were now and should to the last be shared with those who had come to
                        their protection. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This conference deprived Hannibal of the hope
                    of gaining Nola by treachery; he therefore completely invested the city, in
                    order that he might attack the walls in every part at once. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Marcellus, when he perceived that he had come near to the
                    walls, having drawn up his troops within the gate, sallied forth with great
                    impetuosity; several were knocked down and slain on the first charge: afterwards
                    the troops running up 'to those who were engaged, and their forces being thus
                    placed on an equality, the battle began to be fierce; nor would there have been
                    many actions equally memorable, had not the combatants been separated by a
                    shower of rain attended with a tremendous storm. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> On that day, after having engaged in a slight contest, and with inflamed
                    minds, they retired, the Romans to the city, the Carthaginians to their camp. Of
                    the Carthaginians, however, there fell from the shock of the first sally not
                    more than thirty, of the Romans not one. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    rain continued without intermission through the whole night, until the third
                    hour of the following day, and therefore, though both parties were eager for the
                    contest, they nevertheless kept themselves within their works for that day. On
                    the third day Hannibal sent a portion of his troops into the lands of the Nolans
                    to plunder. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcellus perceiving this,
                    immediately led out his troops and formed for battle, nor did Hannibal decline
                    fighting. The interval between the city and the camp was about a mile. In that
                    space, and all the country round Nola consists of level ground, the armies met.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The shout which was raised on both sides,
                    called back to the battle, which had now commenced, the nearest of those cohorts
                    which had gone out into the fields to plunder. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The Nolans too joined the Roman line. Marcellus having highly commended them,
                    desired them to station themselves in reserve, and to carry the wounded out of
                    the field, but not take part in the battle, unless they should receive a signal
                    from him. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was a doubtful battle; the generals
                    exerting them- <pb n="890" xml:id="p.890"/> selves to the utmost in exhorting,
                    and the soldiers in fighting. Marcellus urged his troops to press vigorously on
                    men who had been vanquished but three days before, who had been put to flight at
                    Cumae only a few days ago, and who had been driven from Nola the preceding year
                    by himself, as general, though with different troops. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He said, <quote> that all the forces of the enemy were not
                        in the field; that they were rambling about the country in plundering
                        parties, and that even those who were engaged, were enfeebled with Campanian
                        luxury, and worn out with drunkenness, lust, and every kind of debauchery,
                        which they had been indulging in through the whole winter. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> That the energy and vigour had left them, that the
                        strength of mind and body had vanished, by which the Pyrenees and the tops
                        of the Alps had been passed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That those
                        now engaged were the remains of those men, with scarcely strength to support
                        their arms and limbs. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That Capua had been
                        a Cannae to Hannibal; that there his courage in battle, his military
                        discipline, the fame he had already acquired, and his hopes of future glory,
                        were extinguished. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While Marcellus was raising the spirits of his
                    troops by thus inveighing against the enemy, Hannibal assailed them with still
                    heavier reproaches. He said, <quote> he recognised the arms and standards which
                        he had seen and employed at Trebia and Trasimenus, and lastly at Cannae; but
                        that he had indeed led one sort of troops into winter quarters at Capua, and
                        brought another out. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Do you, whom two
                        consular armies could never withstand, with difficulty maintain your ground
                        against a Roman lieutenant-general, and a single legion with a body of
                        auxiliaries? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Does Marcellus now a second
                        time with impunity assail us with a band of raw recruits and Nolan
                        auxiliaries? Where is that soldier of mine, who took off the head of Caius
                        Flaminius, the consul, after dragging him from his horse? Where is the man
                        who slew Lucius Paulus at Cannae? Is it that the steel hath lost its edge?
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> or that your right hands are benumbed?
                        or what other miracle is it? You who, when few, have been accustomed to
                        conquer numbers, now scarce maintain your ground, the many against the few.
                        Brave in speech only, you were wont to boast that you would take Rome by
                        storm if you could find a general to lead you. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Lo! here is a task of less difficulty. I would have you
                        try your strength and courage here. Take Nola, a town situated <pb n="891"
                            xml:id="p.891"/> on a plain, protected neither by river nor sea; after
                        that, when you have enriched yourselves with the plunder and spoils of that
                        wealthy town, I will either lead or follow you whithersoever you have a
                        mind. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Neither praises nor reproaches had any effect
                    in confirming their courage. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Driven from their
                    ground in every quarter, while the Romans derived fresh spirits, not only from
                    the exhortations of their general, but from the Nolans, who, by their
                    acclamations in token of their good wishes, fed the flame of battle, the
                    Carthaginians turned their backs, and were driven to their camp, which the Roman
                    soldiers were eager to attack; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but Marcellus
                    led them back to Nola, amidst the great joy and congratulations even from the
                    commons, who hitherto had been more favourable to the Carthaginians. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Of the enemy more than five thousand were slain on
                    that day, six hundred made prisoners, with nineteen military standards and two
                    elephants. Four elephants were killed in the battle. Of the Romans less than a
                    thousand were killed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next day was
                    employed by both parties in burying their dead, under a tacit truce. Marcellus
                    burnt the spoils of the enemy, in fulfilment of a vow to Vulcan. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> On the third day after, on account of some pique, I
                    suppose, or in the hope of more advantageous service, one thousand two hundred
                    and seventy-two horsemen, Numidians and Spaniards, deserted to Marcellus. The
                    Romans had frequently availed themselves of their brave and faithful service in
                    that war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After the conclusion of the war,
                    portions of land were given to the Spaniards in Spain, to the Numidians in
                    Africa, in consideration of their valour. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Having sent Hanno back from Nola to the Bruttians with the troops with which he
                    had come, Hannibal went himself into winter quarters in Apulia, and took up a
                    position in the neighbourhood of Arpi. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Quintus
                    Fabius, as soon as he heard that Hannibal was set out into Apulia, conveyed
                    corn, collected from Nola and Naples, into the camp above Suessula; and having
                    strengthened the fortifications and left a garrison sufficient for the
                    protection of the place during the winter, moved his camp nearer to Capua, and
                    laid waste the Campanian lands with fire and sword; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> so that at length the Campanians, though not very confident
                    in their strength, were obliged to go out of their gates and fortify a camp in
                    the open space before the city. They had six thousand armed men, <pb n="892"
                        xml:id="p.892"/> the infantry, unfit for action. In their cavalry they had
                    more strength. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They therefore harassed the
                    enemy by attacking them with these. Among the many distinguished persons who
                    served in the Campanian cavalry was one Cerrinus Jubellius, surnamed Taurea.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Though of that extraction, he was a Roman
                    citizen, and by far the bravest horseman of all the Campanians, insomuch that
                    when he served under the Roman banners, there was but one man, Claudius Asellus,
                    a Roman, who rivalled him in his reputation as a horseman. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Taurea having for a long time diligently sought for this
                    man, riding up to the squadrons of the enemy, at length having obtained silence,
                    inquired where Claudius Asellus was, and asked why, since he had <milestone
                        n="14??" unit="section"/> been accustomed to dispute about their merit in
                    words, he would not decide the matter with the sword, and if vanquished give him
                        <hi rend="italics">spolia opima,</hi> or if victorious take them. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Asellus, who was in the camp, having been
                    informed of this, waited only to ask the consul leave to depart from the
                    ordinary course and fight an enemy who had challenged him. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> By his permission, he immediately put on his arms, and
                    riding out beyond the advanced guards called on Taurea by name, and bid him come
                    to the encounter when he pleased. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By this time
                    the Romans had gone out in large bodies to witness the contest, and the
                    Campanians had crowded not only the rampart of the camp, but the walls of the
                    city to get a view of it. After a flourish of expressions of mutual defiance,
                    they spurred on their horses with their spears pointed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then evading each other's attacks, for they had free space
                    to move in, they protracted the battle without a wound. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Upon this the Campanian observed to the Roman, <quote> This
                        will be only a trial of skill between our horses and not between horsemen,
                        unless we ride them down from the plain into this hollow way. There, as
                        there will be no room for retiring, we shall come to close quarters.
                    </quote> Almost quicker than the word, Claudius leaped into the hollow way.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Taurea, bold in words more than in
                    reality, said, <quote>Never be the ass in the ditch;</quote> an expression which
                    from this circumstance became a common proverb among rustics. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Claudius having rode up and down the way to a considerable
                    distance, and again come up into the plain without meeting his antagonist, after
                    reflecting in reproachful terms on the cowardice of the enemy, returned in
                    triumph to the camp, amidst great rejoicing and congratulation. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> To the <pb n="893" xml:id="p.893"/> account of this
                    equestrian contest, some histories add a circumstance which is certainly
                    astonishing; how true it is, is an open matter of opinion: that Claudius, when
                    in pursuit of Taurea, who fled back to the city, rode in at one of the gates of
                    the enemy which stood open and made his escape unhurt through another, the enemy
                    being thunderstruck at the strangeness of the circumstance. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The camps were then undisturbed; the consul
                    even moved his camp back, that the Campanians might complete their sowing; nor
                    did he do any injury to the lands till the blades in the corn-fields were grown
                    sufficiently high to be useful for forage. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This he conveyed into the Claudian camp above Suessula, and there erected winter
                    quarters. He ordered Marcus Claudius, the proconsul, to retain at Nola a
                    sufficient force for the protection of the place, and send the rest to Rome,
                    that they might not be a burthen to their allies nor an expense to the republic.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Tiberius Gracchus also, having led his
                    legions from Cumae to Luceria in Apulia, sent Marcus Valerius, the praetor,
                    thence to Brundusium with the troops which he had commanded at Luceria, with
                    orders to protect the coast of the Sallentine territory, and make provisions
                    with regard to Philip and the Macedonian war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    At the close of the summer, the events of which I have described, letters
                    arrived from Publius and Cneius Scipio, stating the magnitude and success of
                    their operations in Spain, but that the army was in want of money, clothing, and
                    corn, and that their crews were in want of every thing. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> With regard to the pay, they said, that if the treasury was
                    low, they would adopt some plan by which they might procure it from the
                    Spaniards; but that the other supplies must certainly be sent from Rome, for
                    otherwise neither the army could be kept together nor the province preserved.
                    When the letters were read, all to a man admitted that the statement was
                    correct, and the request reasonable; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but it
                    occurred to their minds, what great forces they were maintaining by land and
                    sea, and how large a fleet must soon be equipped if a war with Macedon should
                    break out; that Sicily and Sardinia, which before the war had yielded a revenue,
                    were scarcely able to maintain the troops which protected those provinces;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that the expenses were supplied by a tax;
                    that both the number of the persons who contributed this tax was diminished by
                    the great havoc made <pb n="894" xml:id="p.894"/> in their armies at the
                    Trasimenus and Cannae, and the few who survived, if they were oppressed with
                    multiplied impositions, would perish by a calamity of a different kind.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That, therefore, if the republic could not
                    subsist by credit, it could not stand by its own resources. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> It was resolved, therefore, that Fulvius, the praetor,
                    should present himself to the public assembly of the people, point out
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the necessities of the state, and
                    exhort those persons who had increased their patrimonies by farming the public
                    revenues, to furnish temporary loans for the service <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> of that state, from which they had derived their wealth,
                    and contract to supply what was necessary for the army in Spain, on the
                    condition of being paid the first when there was money in the treasury.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These things the praetor laid before the
                    assembly, and fixed a day on which he would let on contract the furnishing the
                    army in Spain with clothes and corn, and with such other things as were
                    necessary for the crews. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the day arrived, three companies, of
                    nineteen persons, came forward to enter into the contract; but they made two
                    requests: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> one was, that they should be exempt
                    from military service while employed in that revenue business; the second was,
                    that the state should bear all losses of the goods they shipped, which might
                    arise either from the attacks of the enemy or from storms. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Having obtained both their requests, they entered into the
                    contract, and the affairs of the state were conducted by private funds. This
                    character and love of country uniformly pervaded all ranks. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> As all the engagements were entered into with magnanimity,
                    so were they fulfilled with the strictest fidelity; and the supplies were
                    furnished in the same manner as formerly, from an abundant treasury. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> At the time when these supplies arrived, the town of
                    Illiturgi was being besieged by Hasdrubal, Mago, and Hamilcar the son of
                    Bomilcar, on account of its having gone over to the Romans. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Between these three camps of the enemy, the Scipios
                    effected an entrance into the town of their allies, after a violent contest and
                    great slaughter of their opponents, and introduced some corn, of which there was
                    a scarcity; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and after exhorting the townsmen
                    to defend their walls with the same spirit which they had seen displayed by the
                    Roman army fighting in their behalf, led on their troops to attack the largest
                    of the camps, in which Hasdrubal had <pb n="895" xml:id="p.895"/> the command.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To this camp the two other generals of the
                    Carthaginians with their armies came, seeing that the great business was to be
                    done there. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They therefore sallied from the
                    camp and fought. Of the enemy engaged there were sixty thousand; of the Romans
                    about sixteen; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the victory, however, was so
                    decisive, that the Romans slew more than their own number of the <milestone
                        n="11??" unit="section"/> enemy, and captured more than three thousand, with
                    nearly a thousand horses and fifty-nine military standards, five elephants
                    having been slain in the battle. They made themselves masters of the three camps
                    on that day. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The siege of Illiturgi having
                    been raised, the Carthaginian armies were led away to the siege of Intibili; the
                    forces having been recruited out of that province, which was, above all others,
                    fond of war, provided there was any plunder or pay to be obtained, and at that
                    time had an abundance of young men. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A second
                    regular engagement took place, attended with the same fortune to both parties;
                    in which above three thousand of the enemy were slain, more than two thousand
                    captured, together with forty-two standards and nine elephants. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Then, indeed, almost all the people of Spain came
                    over to the Romans, and the achievements in Spain during that summer were much
                    more important than those in Italy. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
