<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 36</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="book">
                <head>War Against Antiochus-First Stage</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On entering upon their office the new
                        consuls, P. Cornelius Scipio and Manius Acilius Glabrio, were instructed by
                        the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> senate to make it their first
                        business before balloting for their provinces to sacrifice adult victims in
                        all the temples in which for the greater part of the year there was a
                        lectisternium and to offer up special prayers that the intention of the
                        senate to undertake a fresh war might bring prosperity and happiness to the
                        senate and people of Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All these
                        sacrifices were performed without anything untoward occurring, and in the
                        victims which were first offered the omens were entirely favourable. The
                        haruspices accordingly assured the consuls that the boundaries of Rome would
                        be extended by this war and that everything pointed to victory and triumph.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When this report was laid before the
                        senate their minds were at rest so far as the sanctions of religion
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> were concerned and they ordered the
                        question to be submitted to the people, "Whether it was their will and
                        intention that war should be undertaken against Antiochus and those who were
                        of his party?" <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If this proposal were
                        carried, the consuls, if they thought fit, were to bring the matter afresh
                        before the senate. P. Cornelius put the question to the people, and it was
                        carried; the senate then decreed that the consuls should ballot for the
                        provinces of Greece and Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The one to
                        whom Greece was allotted was to take over the army which by order of the
                        senate L. Quinctius had raised from Roman citizens and allies for service in
                        that province, and in addition the army which M. Baebius had with the
                        authority of the senate taken to Macedonia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> He was also commissioned to take up reinforcements of not more than 5000
                        men from the allies outside Italy. It was further decided that L. Quinctius
                        should be appointed second in command for this war. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The other consul to whom Italy was allotted was
                        instructed to conduct operations against the Boii with whichever army he
                        preferred of the two which the late consuls had, and to send the other to
                        Rome to form the City legions and be ready to go wherever the senate thought
                        fit. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the decrees made by the senate
                        up to the actual allocation of the provinces. Then at last the consuls
                        balloted, and Greece fell to Acilius, Italy to Cornelius. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When this was settled a senatus consultum was passed in
                        the following terms: "Whereas the Roman people have at this time ordered
                        that there be war with Antiochus and with all who are under his rule, the
                        consuls shall on this behalf issue orders for a public intercession and M.
                        Acilius shall vow Great Games to Jupiter and gifts and offerings to all the
                        shrines.'' <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This vow was made by the consul
                        in the following formula, as dictated by P. Licinius the Pontifex Maximus:
                        "If the war which the people has ordered to be taken in hand against King
                        Antiochus be brought to such a close as the senate and people <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> of Rome desire, then all the Roman people shall
                        celebrate in thy honour, Jupiter, Great Games for the space of ten days, and
                        oblations of money shall be made to all thy shrines in such wise as the
                        senate shall decree. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whatsoever magistrate
                        shall hold these Games, whensoever and wheresoever he shall celebrate them,
                        may they be deemed to be duly and rightly celebrated and the oblations duly
                        and rightly offered!" <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then the consul
                        proclaimed special intercessions to be offered for two days. After the
                        balloting for the consular provinces the praetors drew for theirs. M. Junius
                        Brutus obtained the two civil jurisdictions; Bruttium fell to A. Cornelius
                        Mammula; Sicily to M. Aemilius Lepidus; Sardinia to L. Oppius Salinator; the
                        command of the fleet to C. Livius Salinator; and Further Spain to L.
                        Aemilius Paullus. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The distribution of the armies amongst
                        them was as follows: The new levies which had been raised by L. Quinctius
                        the preceding year were assigned to A. Cornelius, and his duty was to
                        protect the whole of the coast round Tarentum and Brundisium. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> It was decreed that L. Aemilius Paullus should
                        take over the army which M. Fulvius had commanded as proconsul the year
                        before and also raise 3000 fresh infantry and 300 cavalry for service in
                        Further Spain, two-thirds to consist of allied troops, the remainder being
                        Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A reinforcement of the same
                        strength was sent to C. Flaminius, who was continued in his command in
                        Hither Spain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> M. Aemilius Lepidus was
                        ordered to take over the province and army of Sicily from <milestone
                            n="11??" unit="section"/> L. Valerius, whom he was to succeed, and if it
                        seemed advisable he was to retain him as propraetor and divide the province
                        with him; one section was to extend from Agrigentum to Pachynum, the other
                        from Pachynum to Tyndareum. L. Valerius was also to guard the latter coast
                        with twenty ships of war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Lepidus was
                        further commissioned to requisition two-tenths of all the corn in the island
                        and have it conveyed to Greece. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> L. Oppius
                        was ordered to make the same requisition in Sardinia, the corn, however, was
                        not to be sent to Greece but to Rome. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> C.
                        Livius, the praetor who was to command the fleet, received instructions to
                        sail to Greece with twenty vessels which had completed their armament and
                        take over the ships which Atilius had commanded. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> The repairing and fitting out of the ships in the
                        dockyards was placed in the hands of M. Junius, and he was to select the
                        crews of these vessels from freedmen. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Six commissioners were sent to Africa to
                        procure corn for Greece, the cost to be borne by Rome; three went to
                        Carthage and three to Numidia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> So
                        determined were the citizens to be in perfect readiness for the war that the
                        consul published an edict forbidding anyone who was a senator or had the
                        right of speaking in the senate, or held office as an inferior magistrate,
                        from leaving Rome for any place from which he could not return in a day.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was also forbidden for five
                        senators to be absent from the City at any one time. Whilst C. Livius was
                        doing his utmost to make the fleet ready for sea he was for some time
                        delayed by a dispute with the citizens of the maritime colonies. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> When they were impressed for the fleet they
                        appealed to the tribunes of the plebs, who referred them to the senate.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate unanimously decreed that
                        there was no exemption from service for the colonists. The colonies
                        concerned were Ostia, Fregenae, Castrum Novum, Pyrgi, Antium, Tarracina,
                        Minturnae and Sinuessa. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul
                        Acilius, in compliance with a resolution of the senate, submitted two
                        questions to the College of Fetials. One was whether the declaration of war
                        had to be made to Antiochus personally, or whether it would be sufficient to
                        announce it at one of his frontier garrisons. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The other was whether a separate declaration of war
                        must be made to the Aetolians and whether in that case the league of amity
                        and alliance must first be denounced. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        Fetials replied that they had already on a previous occasion, when they were
                        consulted in the case of Philip, decided that it was a matter of
                        indifference whether the declaration were made personally or in one of his
                        garrison towns. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As to the league of amity,
                        they held that it was obviously denounced, seeing that after the frequent
                        demands put forward by our ambassadors the king had neither surrendered the
                        towns nor given any satisfaction. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the
                        case of the Aetolians, they had actually declared war on Rome by taking
                        forcible possession of Demetrias, <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> a
                        city belonging to the allies of Rome, by going to attack Chalcis by land and
                        sea, and by bringing Antiochus into Europe to levy war on Rome. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> When all the preparations were at last
                        completed, Acilius issued an edict for a general muster at Brundisium by the
                            <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> 15th of May of the Roman soldiers
                        whom L. Quinctius had called up and those who had been supplied to him by
                        the Latins and allies, who were under orders to go with him to his province
                        as well as the military tribunes of the first and third legions. He himself
                        left the City wearing his paludamentum on the 3rd of that month. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> The praetors left at the same time for their
                        respective provinces. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just before this a mission from the two
                        sovereigns, Philip and Ptolemy, arrived in Rome. Philip offered to furnish
                        troops, money and corn for the war; Ptolemy sent 1000 pounds of gold and
                        20,000 pounds of silver. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate
                        declined to accept any of it and passed a vote of thanks to both the kings.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On their each offering to enter
                        Aetolia with all their forces and take their part in the war, Ptolemy was
                        excused, but Philip's envoys were informed that the senate and people of
                        Rome would be grateful to him if he gave his support to Acilius. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Similar missions were despatched by the
                        Carthaginians and by Masinissa. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        Carthaginians offered 100,000 modii of wheat and 50,000 of barley for the
                        use of the army; half the amount they would transport to Rome, and they
                        pressed the Romans to accept it as a free gift. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They were further prepared to fit out a fleet at their
                        own expense and pay in one lump sum the tribute of which many annual
                        instalments had still to run. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Masinissa's
                        envoys stated that he was prepared to supply 50,000 modii of wheat and
                        300,000 of barley for the army in Greece, and 300,000 modii of wheat and
                        250,000 of barley for consumption in Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        He would also furnish Acilius with 500 cavalry and 20 elephants. In the
                        matter of corn both parties were informed that the Roman people would make
                        use of it on condition that they paid for it; <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> the Carthaginian offer of a fleet was declined, beyond
                        the vessels which they were bound to supply under the terms of the treaty,
                        and in reply to the offer of money the Romans refused to accept any before
                        the dates at which the instalments became due. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these proceedings in Rome
                        Antiochus, who was at Chalcis, was not idle during the winter. Some of the
                        Greek communities he endeavoured to win over by despatching embassies to
                        them, others sent embassies spontaneously to him, as for instance the
                        Epirots, in accordance with the general determination of their people, and
                        also the Eleans from the Peloponnese. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        Eleans sought his assistance against the Achaeans, who having declared war
                        on Antiochus against their wish would, they expected, attack them first of
                        all. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A detachment of infantry 1000 strong
                        was sent to them under the command of Euphanes, a Cretan. The deputation
                        from Epirus showed a by no means honest and straightforward spirit to either
                        side; they wanted to ingratiate themselves with Antiochus, but at the same
                        time to give no offence to the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        They asked the king not to involve them in the war hastily, for from their
                        position on the front of Greece facing Italy they would have to meet the
                        first onslaught of the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But if he
                        could protect Epirus with his fleet and army all the Epirots would eagerly
                        welcome him in their cities and harbours; if he was unable to do so, they
                        begged him not to expose them unprotected and defenceless to the hostility
                        of Rome. Their object was perfectly clear. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        If, as they were inclined to believe, he kept clear of Epirus, all would be
                        safe so far as the Roman armies were concerned, whilst they would have
                        secured the king's good graces by expressing their readiness to receive him,
                        had he gone to them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If on the other hand
                        he entered Epirus, they hoped that the Romans would pardon them for yielding
                        to the superior strength of one who was on the spot, without waiting for
                        succour from a distance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As Antiochus was
                        at a loss what reply to make to this ambiguous plea, he said he would send
                        envoys to them to discuss the matters which concerned him and them alike.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He next proceeded to Boeotia. The reasons
                        which the Boeotians gave for their animosity towards Rome I have already
                        stated-the assassination of Brachyllus and Quinctius' attack on Coronea in
                        consequence of the massacre of Roman soldiers. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> But as a matter of fact, that nation once so famous for
                        its discipline had been for many generations deteriorating both in its
                        public and private life, and many were in a condition which could not
                        possibly long continue without a revolutionary change. The leading Boeotians
                        from all parts of the country assembled at Thebes, and thither Antiochus
                        went to meet them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In spite of the fact
                        that by his attack on the Roman detachments at Delium and Chalcis he had
                        committed hostile acts which were neither trifling nor such as could be
                        explained away, he took the same line in addressing the Boeotian council
                        that he had taken at his first conference at Chalcis and had instructed his
                        envoys to take in the council of the Achaeans. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He simply asked that friendly relations might be
                        established with him, not that war should be declared against Rome. No one
                        was deceived as to what he really meant; however, a resolution veiled in
                        inoffensive terms was passed in support of the king and in opposition to
                        Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having thus secured the nation he
                        returned to Chalcis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Letters had been
                        previously sent to the Aetolian leaders requesting them to meet him at
                        Demetrias that he might discuss with them the general conduct of the war,
                        and he arrived there by sea on the day fixed for the meeting. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Amynander, who had been invited from Athamania to
                        take part in the discussion, and Hannibal, who had not been consulted for
                        some time, were both present. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A discussion
                        arose regarding the people of Thessaly; all present thought they ought to be
                        won over, the only divergence of opinion was as to when and how this ought
                        to be done. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some were of opinion that they
                        ought to set about it at once; others were for postponing action till the
                        spring, it being now midwinter; some again thought that it would be enough
                        to send a deputation, others were in favour of going there with the whole of
                        their forces and frightening <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> them into
                        compliance if they hesitated. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the debate was revolving entirely
                        round these details Hannibal was asked for his opinion, and in what he said
                        he turned the thoughts of the king and of all present to the consideration
                        of the war as a whole. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He spoke as
                        follows: "If I had been taken into your counsels after we landed in Greece
                        and you were deliberating about Euboea and the Achaeans and Boeotia, I
                        should have expressed the same view which I am expressing now with regard to
                        the Thessalians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I consider that it is of
                        the first importance that we should use every possible means to bring Philip
                        and the Macedonians into an armed alliance with us. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> As to Euboea and the Boeotians and the Thessalians, who
                        can doubt that these people who have no strength of their own and always
                        cringe before a power which is present to their eyes will display the same
                        craven spirit which marks the proceedings of their councils in suing for
                        pardon, and as soon as they see a Roman army in Greece will turn to their
                        accustomed obedience? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor will they be
                        blamed for refusing to try conclusions with your strength when you and your
                        army are amongst them and the Romans are far away. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> How much sooner ought we-how much better would it be-to
                        secure the adhesion of Philip than of these people! For if he once takes up
                        the cause he will have everything at stake, and he will contribute an amount
                        of strength which will not only be an accession to us in a war with Rome,
                        but was not long ago sufficient of itself to withstand the Romans.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I trust I shall not give offence in
                        saying that with him as our ally I cannot feel doubtful as to the issue, for
                        I see that those through whose assistance the Romans prevailed against
                        Philip will now be the men by whom the Romans themselves are opposed.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Aetolians, who as is universally
                        admitted defeated Philip, will now be fighting in company with him against
                        the Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Amynander and the Athamanians,
                        who next to the Aetolians rendered the greatest service in the war, will be
                        on our side. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While you, Antiochus, had
                        not yet moved, Philip sustained the whole weight of the war; now you and he,
                        the mightiest monarchs in Asia and Europe, will direct your united strength
                        against a single people who-to say nothing of my own fortunes, good or
                        bad-were at all events in the days of our fathers no match for even one king
                        of Epirus, and how can he possibly be compared with you? </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "What considerations then give me ground
                        for believing that Philip can be made our ally? One is the identity of
                        interests, which is the surest bond of alliance. The other is your own
                        assurance, Aetolians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For amongst the
                        reasons which your envoy Thoas gave for inducing Antiochus to come to
                        Greece, the strongest was his constant asseveration that Philip was
                        complaining and chafing under the servile conditions imposed upon him in the
                        guise of peace. He used to compare the king's rage to that of some animal
                        chained or shut up and longing to burst his prison bars. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> If that is his state of mind, let us loose his chains
                        and burst the bars that hold him in so that he can vent his long-restrained
                        rage on our common foe. But if our delegates are unable to influence him,
                        let us at all events see to it that if we cannot get him on our side the
                        enemy does not get him on his side. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Your
                        son Seleucus is at Lysimachia; if with the army he has with him he traverses
                        Thrace and begins to lay waste the adjacent parts of Macedonia, he will
                        easily turn Philip aside from actively assisting the Romans to the defence
                        of his own dominions. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> "You are in possession of my opinions
                        about Philip. As regards the general strategy of the war, you have known
                        from the outset what my views are. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Had I
                        been listened to then, it would not have been the capture of Chalcis or the
                        storming of a fort on the Euripus that the Romans would have heard about;
                        they would have learnt that Etruria and Liguria and the coastal districts of
                        Cisalpine Gaul were wrapped in the flames of war and, what would have
                        alarmed them most of all, that Hannibal was in Italy. I am of opinion that
                        even now you ought to bring up the whole of your military and naval forces
                        and let a fleet of transports accompany them laden with supplies. <milestone
                            n="17" unit="section"/> We here are too few for the requirements of war
                        and too many for our scanty commissariat. When you have concentrated your
                        entire strength, Antiochus, you might divide your fleet and keep one
                        division cruising off Corcyra, that there may be no safe and easy passage
                        for the Romans, the other you would <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/>
                        send across to the coast of Italy opposite Sardinia and Africa. <milestone
                            n="19" unit="section"/> You yourself would advance with all your land
                        forces into the country round Byllis; from there you would protect Greece
                        and give the Romans the impression that you are going to sail to Italy, and
                        should circumstances render it necessary you will be in readiness to do so.
                            <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> This is what I advise you to do, and
                        though I may not be profoundly versed in every phase of war, how to war with
                        the Romans at all events I have learnt through success and failure alike. In
                        the measures which I have advised you to take I promise to co-operate most
                        loyally and energetically. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> I trust that
                        whatever course, Antiochus, seems best to you may receive the approval of
                        the gods." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the substance of Hannibal's
                        speech, which was applauded at the time but led to no practical results. Not
                        one of the measures he advocated was carried out beyond the despatch of
                        Polyxenidas to bring up the fleet and the troops from Asia. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Delegates were sent to the council of the Thessalians
                        which was sitting at Larisa, and the Aetolians and Amynander fixed a day for
                        the muster of their armies at Pherae, whither the king proceeded with his
                        troops at once. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whilst waiting there for
                        Amynander and the Aetolians he sent Philip the Megalopolitan with 2000 men
                        to collect the bones of the Macedonians who had fallen in the final battle
                        with Philip at Cynoscephalae. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Either
                        Philip himself suggested this to Antiochus as a means of making himself
                        popular with the Macedonians and stirring up ill-will against their king for
                        having left his soldiers unburied, or else Antiochus, with the vanity
                        natural to kings, formed this in his own mind, a project apparently of
                        importance but really trivial. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The bones
                        which were scattered in all directions were collected into a heap and buried
                        under a tumulus, but the proceeding awoke no gratitude in the Macedonians
                        and aroused strong resentment in Philip. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        He had so far been waiting on events, but now in consequence of this he at
                        once sent to the propraetor M. Baebius to tell him that Antiochus had
                        invaded Thessaly, and asking him, if he thought proper, to move out of his
                        winter quarters; he himself would go to meet him so that they might consult
                        as to what steps ought to be taken. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Antiochus was now encamped at Pherae,
                        where the Aetolians and Amynander had joined him, when a deputation came
                        from Larisa to ask him what the Thessalians had said or done to justify his
                        making war on them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They begged him to
                        withdraw his army so that any question which he thought necessary might be
                        discussed with them through his envoys. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At
                        the same time they sent a detachment of 500 men under Hippolochus to protect
                        Pherae. Finding all the routes closed by the king's troops they fell back on
                        Scotusa. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king gave the deputation a
                        gracious answer and explained that he had not entered Thessaly for the
                        purpose of aggression, but solely to establish and protect the freedom of
                        the Thessalians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A commissioner was
                        despatched to Pherae to make a similar statement, but without giving him any
                        reply the Pheraeans sent their chief magistrate to Antiochus. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> He spoke in pretty much the same strain as the
                        Chalcidians at the conference under similar circumstances on the Euripus,
                        though some things he said showed greater courage and resolution. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The king advised them to consider their position
                        most carefully lest they should adopt a policy which, whilst they were
                        cautiously providing against future contingencies, might give them immediate
                        cause for regret, and with this advice he dismissed their envoy. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> When the result of this mission was reported at
                        Pherae, the people did not hesitate for a moment; they were determined to
                        suffer everything which the chances of war might bring in defence of their
                        loyalty to Rome, and made every possible preparation for the defence of
                        their city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The king commenced a
                        simultaneous attack on all sides; he quite saw, what indeed was
                        indisputable, that it depended upon the fate of the first city which he
                        attacked whether he would be held in contempt or in dread throughout the
                        whole of Thessaly, so he did his utmost to spread terror everywhere.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At first the beleaguered garrison
                        offered a stout resistance to his furious assaults, but when they saw many
                        of the defenders killed or wounded their courage began <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> to sink and it was only by the reproaches of their
                        officers that they were recalled to the necessity of holding to their
                        purpose. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their numbers became so
                        diminished that they abandoned the outer circuit of their walls and
                        retreated to the interior of the city, which was surrounded by a shorter
                        line of fortifications. At last their position became hopeless and fearing,
                        if the place were taken by storm, that they would meet with no mercy, they
                        surrendered. The king lost no time in taking advantage of the alarm which
                        this capture created and sent 4000 men to Scotusa. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Here the townsmen promptly surrendered in view of the
                        recent example of the Pheraeans, seeing that they had been compelled by
                        stress of circumstances to do what at first they were determined not to do.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Hippolochus and his garrison from
                        Larisa were included in the capitulation. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        These were all sent away unhurt as the king thought that this act would go
                        far to gain the sympathies of the Lariseans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These successes he accomplished within ten
                        days of his appearance before Pherae. Continuing his march with the whole of
                        his army he reached Crannon, which he took immediately on his arrival.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He next secured Cierium and Metropolis
                        and the various forts in their neighbourhood, and by this time every part of
                        that district with the exception of Atrax and Gyrto was in his power.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His next objective was Larisa, where
                        he expected that either the dread of meeting the fate of the other towns
                        taken by storm or gratitude for his free dismissal of their garrison or the
                        example of so many cities voluntarily surrendering would dissuade them from
                        an obstinate resistance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In order to
                        intimidate the defenders he had his elephants driven in front of the line,
                        the army following in order of battle up to the city. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The sight made a great many of the Lariseans waver
                        between fear of the enemy at their gates and fear of being false to their
                        distant allies. During this time Amynander and his Athamanians seized
                        Pellinaeum, and Menippus advancing into Perrhaebia with an Aetolian force of
                        3000 infantry and 200 cavalry took Malloea and Cyretiae by storm and ravaged
                        the territory of Tripolis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After these
                        rapid successes they returned to the king at Larisa and found him holding a
                        council of war to decide what should be done about the city. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> There was considerable diversity of opinion. Some
                        were in favour of an immediate assault as the city was situated in a plain
                        open on all sides to an approach over level ground, and they urged that
                        there should be no delay in constructing siege works and bringing up
                        artillery to attack the walls on all sides simultaneously. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Others reminded the council that there was no
                        comparison between the strength of this city and that of Pherae; <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> besides, it was now winter, a season quite
                        unsuitable for warlike operations, most of all so for investing and
                        assaulting a city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While the king was
                        uncertain as to whether there was most to be hoped or feared from the
                        attempt, delegates from Pharsalus arrived to tender the submission of their
                        city and this raised his spirits. M. Baebius had in the meanwhile met Philip
                        at Dassaretiae and they both agreed that Ap. Claudius should be sent to
                        protect Larisa. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Claudius traversed
                        Macedonia by forced marches and gained the summit of the ridge which looks
                        down on Gonni, a place twenty miles distant from Larisa at the head of the
                        Vale of Tempe. Here he marked out a camp of greater extent than the force
                        with him required, and kindled more numerous fires than were needed in order
                        to give the enemy the impression that the entire Roman army was there
                        together with Philip. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Antiochus withdrew
                        from Larisa the very next day and returned to Demetrias, alleging the
                        approach of winter as the reason for his retreat. The Aetolians and the
                        Athamanians also retired within their own frontiers. Although Appius saw
                        that the purpose of his march, the raising of the siege, was effected he
                        nevertheless went on to Larisa to reassure his allies as to the future.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They were doubly delighted, first at
                        the withdrawal of the enemy from their soil and then <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> at the sight of Roman troops within their walls. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king left Demetrias for Chalcis. Here
                        he fell in love with a daughter of Cleoptolemus, a Chalcidian magnate, and
                        after numerous communications to her father followed by personal interviews
                        (for he was reluctant to be entangled in an alliance so far above his own
                        rank) Antiochus married the girl. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        wedding was celebrated as though it were a time of peace, and forgetting the
                        two vast enterprises in which he had embarked-war with Rome and the
                        liberation of Greece-he dismissed all his cares and spent the rest of the
                        winter in banquets and the pleasures attendant on wine, sleeping off his
                        debauches, wearied rather than satisfied. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        All the king's officers who were in command of the different winter
                        stations, especially those in Boeotia, fell into the same dissolute mode of
                        life; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> even the common soldiers were
                        completely sunk in it, not a man amongst them ever put on his armour or went
                        on duty as guard or sentry, or discharged any military duty whatever.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When, therefore, at the commencement
                        of spring Antiochus passed through Phocis on his way to Chaeronea, where he
                        had given orders for the whole of his army to muster, it was easy for him to
                        see that the men had passed the winter under no stricter discipline than
                        their leader. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From Chaeronea he ordered
                        Alexander the Acarnanian and the Macedonian Menippus to take the troops to
                        Stratus in Aetolia. He himself, after sacrificing to Apollo at Delphi, went
                        to Naupactus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Here he had an interview
                        with the Aetolian leaders, and then taking the road which runs past Calydon
                        and Lysimachia he arrived at Stratum, where he met his army who were coming
                        by the Maliac Gulf. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Mnasilochus, one of
                        the leading men in Acarnania, who had received many presents from Antiochus,
                        was trying to persuade his people to take the king's side. He had succeeded
                        in bringing Clytus, in whom the supreme power was vested at the time, over
                        to his views, but he saw that there would be difficulty in inducing
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> Leucas, the capital, to revolt from
                        Rome, owing to their fear of the Roman fleet under Atilius, a portion of
                        which was cruising off Cephalania. He therefore decided to adopt a ruse.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At a meeting of the council he told
                        them that the ports of Acarnania ought to be protected and that all who
                        could bear arms ought to go to Medione and Tyrrheum to prevent their being
                        seized by Antiochus and the Aetolians. Some of those present protested
                        against this indiscriminate calling out of their fighting strength as quite
                        unnecessary and said that a force of 500 men would be adequate for this
                        purpose. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When he had got this force he
                        placed 300 men in Medione and 200 in Tyrrheum, his intention being that they
                        should fall into the king's hands and be practically hostages. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the king's agents arrived in
                        Medione. They were received in audience by the council and in the subsequent
                        discussion on the reply that they <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> were
                        to receive some speakers thought they ought to stand by the alliance with
                        Rome, others urged that they ought not to reject the proffered friendship of
                        the king; Clytus urged a middle course which the council decided to adopt,
                        viz., <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> to send to the king and ask him to
                        allow them to consult the National Council of Acarnania on such an important
                        matter. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Mnasilochus and his supporters
                        managed to get themselves put on this commission, and they despatched a
                        secret message to Antiochus urging him to bring up his army while they
                        wasted time by delay. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consequence was
                        that the commission had hardly started when Antiochus appeared within their
                        frontiers and in a short time at their gates. Whilst those who were not
                        privy to the plot were hurrying in confusion through the streets and calling
                        their fighting men to arms, Antiochus was introduced into the city by
                        Mnasilochus and Clytus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Many came round
                        him of their own accord and even his opponents were constrained by their
                        fears to meet him. He quieted their apprehensions by a gracious speech, and
                        when his clemency became generally known several of the communities in
                        Acarnania went over to him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From Medione
                        he marched to Tyrrheum, having sent Mnasilochus and his agents on in
                        advance. The Tyrrheans, however' saw through the treachery at Medione, and
                        instead of intimidating them it only put them more on their guard.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They returned a perfectly unambiguous
                        answer to his summons and told him that they would not enter into any fresh
                        alliance unless the Roman commanders authorised them to do so, at the same
                        time they closed their gates and manned their walls. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Cn. Octavius had been supplied with a body of troops
                        and a few ships by A. Postumius, whom Atilius had placed in command at
                        Cephalania, and his timely arrival in Leucas <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> gave the Acarnanians fresh heart, as he reported that
                        the consul Manius Acilius had crossed the sea with his legions and the
                        Romans were encamped in Thessaly. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> His
                        report was the more readily believed because the season of the year was
                        favourable for navigation, and the king, after placing garrisons in Medione
                        and in one or two other towns in Acarnania, withdrew from Tyrrheum and
                        passing through the cities of Aetolia and Phocis returned to Chalcis. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Baebius and Philip, after their meeting
                        at Dassaretiae, when they sent Ap. Claudius to relieve Larisa had returned
                        to their respective winter quarters as it was too early in the year for
                        active operations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the beginning of
                        spring they went down with their united forces into Thessaly; Antiochus was
                        in Acarnania at the time. Philip laid siege to Malloea in Perrhaebia and
                        Baebius attacked Phacium. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He took the
                        place at the first assault and captured Phaestum with equal rapidity.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marching back to Atrax he advanced
                        from there against Cyretiae and Eritium both of which places he gained
                        possession of, and after placing garrisons in the captured towns he rejoined
                        Philip, who was still besieging Malloea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        On the arrival of the Roman army the garrison, either cowed by the strength
                        of the besieging force or hoping to obtain more favourable terms, made their
                        surrender. The two commanders then went on with their combined forces to
                        recover those towns which the Athamanians were holding, namely Aeginium,
                        Ericinium, Gomphi, Silana, Tricca, Meliboea and Phaloria. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They next invested Pellinaeum, where Philip of
                        Megalopolis was stationed <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> with 500
                        infantry and 40 cavalry, and before they delivered the assault they sent to
                        Philip to warn him against forcing them to take extreme measures. He sent
                        back a defiant answer and said that he would have trusted himself in the
                        hands of Romans or Thessalians, but he would not place himself at the mercy
                        of Philip. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As it was evident that force
                        must be employed, and that while the siege was <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> going on Limnaea could be attacked, it was decided that
                        the king should go there whilst Baebius remained to conduct the siege of
                        Pellinaeum. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meantime the consul Manius Atilius had
                        landed with 10,000 infantry, 2000 cavalry and 15 elephants. He ordered the
                        military tribunes to take the infantry to Larisa, whilst he went with the
                        cavalry to join Philip at Limnaea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the
                        consul's arrival the place at once surrendered and the garrison of
                        Antiochus, together with the Athamanians, were delivered up. From Limnaea
                        the consul went on to Pellinaeum. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here the
                        Athamanians were the first to surrender, they were followed by the
                        Megalopolitan Philip. As he was leaving the fort, Philip of Macedon happened
                        to meet <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> him, and ordered his men to
                        salute him in mockery as king, and, in a spirit of scorn quite unworthy of
                        his own rank, addressed him as "brother." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        When he was brought before the consul, he was ordered to be kept a close
                        prisoner, and not long afterwards was sent in chains to Rome. All the
                        Athamanian garrisons, as well as those of Antiochus, which had been
                        surrendered were handed over to Philip. They amounted to 4000 men. The
                        consul went on to Larisa to hold a council of war to decide as to future
                        operations, and on his route he was met by delegates from Cierium and
                        Metropolis, who offered the surrender of their cities. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Philip was in hopes of gaining possession of Athamania,
                        and he treated his Athamanian prisoners with special indulgence, with the
                        design of winning their countrymen through them. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> After sending them home he led his army into the
                        country. The account which the returned prisoners brought of the king's
                        clemency and generosity towards them produced a great effect upon their
                        countrymen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Had Amynander remained in his
                        kingdom he might have kept some of his subjects loyal by his personal
                        authority, but the fear of being betrayed to his old enemy Philip made him
                        flee, together with his wife and children, to Ambracia. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The whole of Athamania in consequence submitted to
                        Philip. </p>
                    <p> The consul remained a few days at Larisa, mainly in order to recruit the
                        horses and draught cattle, which owing to the voyage and the subsequent
                        marching had got out of condition. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When
                        his army was, so to speak, renewed by the short rest, he marched to Crannon,
                        and on his way he received the surrender of Pharsalus, Scotusa and Pherae,
                        together with the garrisons which Antiochus had placed in them. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> These troops were asked whether they would be
                        willing to remain with him. A thousand volunteered, and these he handed over
                        to Philip; the rest he disarmed and sent back to Demetrias. He next captured
                        Proerna and the fortified posts in the neighbourhood, and continued his
                        march towards the Maliac Gulf. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As he
                        approached the pass above which Thaumaci is situated, all the men who could
                        bear arms armed themselves, left the city and occupied the woods and roads,
                        and from their higher ground made attacks upon the Roman column of march.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The consul sent parties to approach
                        them within speaking distance and warn them against such madness, but when
                        he saw that they persisted he ordered a military tribune to work round them
                        with two maniples and cut off their retreat to the city, which in the
                        absence of its defenders the consul occupied. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> When they heard the shouts from the captured city
                        behind them, they fled back from all sides and were cut to pieces.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The next day the consul reached the
                        Spercheus, and from there ravaged the fields of the Hypataeans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Antiochus was all this time at Chalcis,
                        having at last discovered that he had gained nothing from Greece beyond a
                        pleasant winter at Chalcis and a disreputable marriage. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He now accused the Aetolians of having made empty
                        promises and admired Hannibal, not only as a man of prudence and foresight,
                        but also as little short of a prophet, seeing how he had foretold everything
                        which was happening. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In order that his
                        reckless adventure might not be ruined through his own inactivity, he sent a
                        message to the Aetolians requesting them to concentrate all their fighting
                        strength at Lamia, where he himself joined them with about 10,000 infantry,
                        made up largely of troops which had come from Asia, and 500 cavalry.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Aetolians mustered in considerably
                        smaller numbers than on any previous occasion, only the leading men with a
                        few of their dependents were present. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                        said that they had done their utmost to call up as many as possible from
                        their respective cities, but their personal influence, their appeals, their
                        official authority, were alike powerless against those who declined to
                        serve. Finding himself deserted on all sides by his own troops, who were
                        hanging back in Asia, and by his allies, who were not doing what they
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> undertook to do when they invited
                        him, he withdrew into the pass of Thermopylae. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> This mountain range cuts Greece in two, just as Italy
                        is intersected by the Apennines. To the north of the pass are situated
                        Epirus, Perrhaebia, Magnesia, Thessaly, the Achaeans of Phthiotis, and the
                        Maliac Gulf. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> South of it lie the greater
                        part of Aetolia, Acarnania, Locris, Phocis, Boeotia, the adjoining island of
                        Euboea, and Attica, which projects into the sea like a promontory; beyond
                        these is the Peloponnese. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This range
                        extends from Leucas on the western sea through Aetolia to the eastern sea,
                        and is so rugged and precipitous that even light infantry-let alone an
                        army-would have great difficulty in finding any paths by which to cross it.
                        The eastern end of the range is called Oeta, and its highest peak bears the
                        name of Callidromus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The road running
                        through the lower ground between its base and the Maliac Gulf is not more
                        than sixty paces broad and is the only military road which can be traversed
                        by an army, and then only if it meets with no opposition. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> For this reason the place is called Pylae, and also
                        Thermopylae, from the hot springs there, and is famous <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> for the battle against the Persians, but still more so
                        for the glorious death of the Lacedaemonians who fought there. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In a state of mind very unlike theirs
                        Antiochus pitched his camp inside the narrowest part of the pass and
                        barricaded it with defensive works, protecting every part of it with a
                        double line of fosse and rampart <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> and
                        where it seemed necessary with a wall built up from the stones which were
                        lying about everywhere. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He felt pretty
                        confident that the Roman army would never force a passage there, and so he
                        sent two detachments out of the 4000 Aetolians who had joined him, one to
                        hold Heraclea, a place just in front of the pass, the other to Hypata.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He quite expected that the consul
                        would attack Heraclea; and from Hypata numerous messages had come stating
                        that the whole of the surrounding country was being laid waste. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The consul ravaged the territory of Hypata first
                        and then that of Heraclea; in neither place did the Aetolians prove of the
                        slightest use, and finally encamped opposite the king in the mouth of the
                        pass at the hot springs. Both the Aetolian detachments shut themselves up in
                        Heraclea. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before the actual appearance of
                        his enemy Antiochus thought that the whole of the pass was fortified and
                        blocked by his troops, but now he felt anxious lest the Romans might find
                        some paths on the surrounding heights by which they could turn his defences,
                        for the Lacedaemonians <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> were stated to
                        have been similarly taken in the rear by the Persians, and Philip quite
                        recently by the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly he
                        sent a message to the Aetolians at Heraclea asking them to do him this
                        service at least in the war, namely, to seize and hold the crests of the
                        surrounding mountains and prevent the Romans from crossing them anywhere. On
                        the receipt of this message there was a sharp difference of opinion among
                        the Aetolians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some thought that they
                        ought to comply with the king's request and go; others were in favour of
                        remaining in their quarters at Heraclea, prepared for either eventuality.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If the king were defeated they would
                        then have their forces intact and be able to assist in the defence of the
                        cities round them, if on the other hand he were victorious they would then
                        be in a position to take up the pursuit of the fugitive Romans. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Each party held to its opinion, and not only
                        held to it but acted upon it; 2000 remained in Heraclea, and the others,
                        formed into three divisions, occupied the three heights of Callidromus,
                        Rhoduntia and Tichius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consul saw that the heights were
                        occupied by the Aetolians he sent M. Porcius Cato and L. Valerius Flaccus,
                        men of consular rank commanding under him, to attack their fortified
                        positions, Flaccus against Rhoduntia and Tichius, and Cato against
                        Callidromus. They each took a picked force of 2000 infantry. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Before making his general advance against the
                        enemy, the consul called his men on parade and addressed a few words to
                        them. "Soldiers," he said, "I see that there are very many amongst you, men
                        of all ranks, who have campaigned in this very province under the leadership
                        and auspices of T. Quinctius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the
                        Macedonian war the pass at the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> Aous was
                        more difficult to force than this one, for here we have gates and this
                        passage as though provided by nature is the only one available, every other
                        route between the two seas being closed to us. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> On that occasion, too, the enemy defences were stronger
                        and constructed on more advantageous ground; the hostile army was more
                        numerous and made up of far better soldiery; there were in that army
                        Macedonians, Thracians and Illyrians, all very warlike tribes; here there
                        are Syrians and Asiatic Greeks, the meanest of mankind, and born only for
                        slavery. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The monarch who was opposed to us
                        then was a true soldier, trained from his youth in wars with the Thracians
                        and the Illyrians and all the nations round him; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> this man-to say nothing of his previous life-has done
                        nothing during the whole of the winter months more memorable than marrying a
                        girl for love out of a private family and, even when compared with their
                        fellow-townsmen, of obscure origin, and now the newly-wedded bridegroom,
                        fattened up as it were with marriage feasts, has come out to fight.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His main hope was in the Aetolians,
                        they were his chief strength, and you have already learnt by experience as
                        Antiochus is learning now what an untrustworthy and ungrateful race they
                        are. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They have not come in any
                        considerable number, it was impossible to keep them in camp, they are at
                        loggerheads among themselves, and after insisting that Hypata and Heraclea
                        must be defended they refused to defend either place and took refuge on the
                        mountain heights, some shutting themselves up in Heraclea. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The king himself has shown clearly that he durst not
                        venture to meet us on fair ground, he is not even fixing his camp in open
                        country; he has abandoned the whole of the district in front of him which he
                        boasts of having taken from us and from Philip, and has hidden himself
                        amongst the rocks. His camp is not even placed at the entrance to the path,
                        as we are told the Lacedaemonians placed theirs, but is withdrawn far within
                        it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> What difference is there, as a
                        visible proof of fear, between his shutting himself up here or behind the
                        walls of a besieged city? The pass, however, will not protect Antiochus, nor
                        will the heights which the Aetolians have seized protect them. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Sufficient caution and foresight have been
                        exercised to prevent your having anything to fight against but the actual
                        enemy. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> You must bear in mind that you are
                        not fighting only for the freedom of Greece, though it will be a splendid
                        record to deliver out of the hands of the Aetolians and Antiochus the
                        country which you formerly rescued from Philip. Nor will it be only the
                        spoil in the enemy's camp that will fall to you as a prize; all the stores
                        and material which he is daily looking for from Ephesus will be your booty;
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> you will open up Asia and Syria and
                        all the wealthiest realms to the furthest East to the supremacy of Rome.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> What will then prevent us from
                        extending our dominion from Gades to the Red Sea with no limit but the Ocean
                        which enfolds the world, and making the whole human race look up to Rome
                        with a reverence only second to that which they pay to the gods? Show
                        yourselves worthy in heart and mind of such vast rewards so that we may take
                        the field tomorrow assured that <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> the
                        gods will help us." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this address the soldiers were
                        dismissed and got their armour and weapons ready before they took food and
                        rest. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As soon as it began to grow light
                        the consul hung out the signal for battle and formed his line on a narrow
                        front to suit the confined limits of the ground. When the king saw the
                        standards of the enemy he also led out his men. Part of his light infantry
                        he stationed in front of their rampart to form the first line. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Behind them in support he posted the Macedonians,
                        the main strength of his arm, known as the "sarisophori"; they extended
                        across the whole length of the rampart. To the left of them were posted a
                        body of javelin men, bowmen and slingers immediately under the foot of the
                        mountains, so that they might from their higher ground harass the
                        unprotected flank of the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the
                        right of the Macedonians, towards the end of his lines, where the ground
                        beyond down to the sea is impassable owing to bogs and quicksands, he posted
                        the elephants with their usual guard, and behind them the cavalry, and a
                        short distance behind them again the rest of his troops. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The Macedonians in front of the rampart had no
                        difficulty at first in resisting the Romans, who were trying at all points
                        to break through, and they received considerable assistance from those on
                        the higher ground, who discharged bullets from their slings, arrows and
                        javelins all at once, a perfect cloud of missiles. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> But as the enemy's pressure increased and the attack
                        was made in greater force they gradually fell back to their rampart, and
                        standing upon it made practically a second rampart with their levelled
                        spears. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The rampart, owing to its moderate
                        height, not only offered a higher position from which to fight, but also
                        enabled them to reach the enemy below with their long spears. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Many in their reckless attempts to mount the
                        rampart were run through, and they would have had either to retire baffled
                        or sustain serious losses had not M. Porcius appeared on a hill which
                        commanded the camp. He had dislodged the Aetolians from the crest of
                        Callidromus and killed the greater part of them, attacking them when they
                        were off their guard and most of them asleep. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Flaccus was not so fortunate, his attempt
                        to reach the fortified posts on Tichius and Rhoduntia was a failure.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Macedonians and the other troops
                        in the king's camp could at first only make out a moving mass of men in the
                        distance, and were under the impression that the Aetolians had seen the
                        fighting from afar and were coming to their assistance. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When, however, they recognised the approaching
                        standards and arms and discovered their mistake, they were so panic-struck
                        that they flung away their weapons and fled. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> The pursuit was impeded by the entrenchments of the camp and the confined
                        space through which the pursuers had to pass, but the elephants were the
                        greatest hindrance, for it was difficult for the infantry to get past them,
                        and impossible for the cavalry; the frightened horses created more confusion
                        than in the actual battle. The plunder of the camp still further delayed the
                        pursuit. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> However, they followed up the
                        enemy as far as Scarphea, after which they returned to camp. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Large numbers of men and horses had been either
                        killed or captured on the way, and even the elephants, which they were
                        unable to secure, had been killed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While
                        the battle was going on the Aetolians who had been holding Heraclea made an
                        attempt on the Roman camp, but they gained nothing from their enterprise,
                        which was certainly not lacking in audacity. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> At the third watch of the following night the consul sent the cavalry to
                        continue the pursuit, and at daybreak he put the legions in motion. The king
                        had gained a considerable start, as he did not stop in his headlong ride
                        till he reached Elatia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Here he collected
                        what was left of his army out of the battle and the flight and retreated
                        with a very small body of half-armed soldiers to Chalcis. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The Roman cavalry did not succeed in overtaking the
                        king himself at Elatia, but they cut off a large part of his army, who were
                        unable to go any further through sheer fatigue, or else had lost their way
                        in an unknown country, with none to guide them. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Out of the whole army not a single man escaped beyond
                        the 500 who formed the king's bodyguard, an insignificant number even if we
                        accept Polybius' statement which I have mentioned above that the force the
                        king brought with him out of Asia did not exceed 10,000 men. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> What proportion would it be if we are to believe
                        Valerius Antias, that there were 60,000 men in the king's army, of whom
                        40,000 fell and over 5000 made prisoners, and 230 standards captured? In the
                        battle itself the Roman losses amounted to 150, and in the defence of the
                        camp against the Aetolians not more than 50 were killed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the consul was taking his army
                        through Phocis and Boeotia the citizens of the revolted towns, conscious of
                        their guilt and fearing lest they should be treated as enemies, stood
                        outside their gates in suppliant garb. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        army, however, marched past all their cities one after the other, without
                        doing any damage, just as though they were in friendly territory, till they
                        came to Coronea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here great indignation
                        was aroused by the sight of a statue of Antiochus set up in the temple of
                        Minerva Itonia, and the soldiers were allowed to plunder the temple domain.
                        It occurred, however, to the consul that as the statue had been placed there
                        by a decree of the national council of Boeotia it was unfair to take
                        vengeance on the territory of Coronea alone. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> He at once recalled the soldiers and stopped the pillaging, and contented
                        himself with sternly rebuking the Boeotians for their ingratitude to Rome
                        after the many benefits she had so lately conferred upon them. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> At the time of the battle ten of the king's
                        ships, with Isidorus in command, were standing off Thronium in the Maliac
                        Gulf. Alexander the Acarnanian, who had been severely wounded, fled thither
                        with tidings of the defeat, and the ships sailed hurriedly away to Cenaeus
                        in Euboea. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here Alexander died and was
                        buried. Three vessels, which had come from Asia and were making for the same
                        port, on hearing of the disaster which had overtaken the army, returned to
                        Ephesus. Isidorus left Cenaeus for Demetrias, in case the king's flight
                        should have carried him there. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During this
                        time A. Atilius, who was in command of the Roman fleet, intercepted a large
                        convoy of supplies for the king which had passed through the strait between
                        Andros and Euboea. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Some of the vessels he
                        sank, others he captured; those in the rearmost line turned their course
                        towards Asia. Atilius sailed back with his train of captured ships and
                        distributed the large stock of corn on board to the Athenians and the other
                        friendly cities in that quarter. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just before the consul's arrival Antiochus
                        left Chalcis and directed his course first to Tenos and from there to
                        Ephesus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As the consul drew near to
                        Chalcis the king's commandant, Aristoteles, left the city and the gates were
                        thrown open to the consul. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All the other
                        cities in Euboea were delivered up without any fighting, and in a few days
                        peace was established everywhere in the island and the army returned to
                        Thermopylae without injuring a single city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> This moderation displayed after the victory was much more deserving of
                        praise than even the victory itself. In order that the senate and people
                        might receive an authoritative report of the operations the consul sent M.
                        Cato to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He set sail from Creusa, the
                        emporium of Thespia, situated in the innermost part of the Gulf of Corinth,
                        and made for Patrae in Achaia; from Patrae he went on to Corcyra, skirting
                        the shores of Aetolia and Acarnania, and so made his passage to Hydruntum in
                        Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From there he journeyed by land,
                        and by rapid travelling reached Rome in five days. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Entering the City before it was light he went straight
                        to the praetor, M. Junius, who summoned a meeting of the senate at daybreak.
                        L. Cornelius Scipio had been sent on by the consul some days previously, and
                        on his arrival found that Cato had outstripped him. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He went into the senate house while Cato was making his
                        report and the two generals were conducted by order of the senate to the
                        Assembly, where they gave the same details of the Aetolian campaign as had
                        been given to the senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A decree was
                        made that there should be thanksgivings for three days, and the praetor was
                        to sacrifice forty full-grown victims to such of the gods as he thought fit.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> M. Fulvius Nobilior, who had gone to
                        Spain as praetor two years previously, entered the City about this time in
                        ovation. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He had carried before him
                        130,000 silver denarii and 12,000 pounds of other silver, as well as 127
                        pounds of gold. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Acilius was at Thermopylae he sent a
                        message to the Aetolians, advising them, now that they had found out how
                        empty the king's promises were, to return to a right mind and think about
                        delivering up Heraclea and begging pardon of the senate for their madness
                        and delusion. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Other cities in Greece, he
                        reminded them, had been faithless to their best friends, the Romans, in that
                        war, but after the flight of the king, whose assurances had seduced them
                        from their duty, they did not aggravate their fault by willful obstinacy,
                        and had once more been received as allies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Even in the case of the Aetolians, though they had not followed the king,
                        but had actually invited him, and were not his associates but his leaders in
                        the war-even for them there was still the possibility, if they showed true
                        repentance, of remaining unharmed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To this
                        message they returned a defiant answer; the question would evidently have to
                        be decided by arms, and though the king was overcome, the war with the
                        Aetolians was clearly only just beginning. The consul accordingly moved his
                        army from Thermopylae to Heraclea, and on the very same day he rode round
                        the entire circuit of the walls to ascertain the situation of the city.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Heraclea lies at the foot of Mount
                        Oeta; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the city itself is situated in a
                        plain, and it has a citadel which commands it from a position of
                        considerable elevation and precipitous on all sides. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> After carefully considering all there was to be learnt
                        he decided to deliver a simultaneous attack from four different points. In
                        the direction of the Asopus, where the Gymnasium stood, he placed L.
                        Valerius in charge of the operations. Towards the citadel outside the walls,
                        where the houses were almost closer together than in the city itself, he
                        gave the direction of the assault to Tiberius Sempronius Longus. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> On the side facing the Maliac Gulf, where the
                        approach presented considerable difficulty, M. Baebius was in command.
                        Towards the stream which they call the Melana, opposite the temple of Diana,
                        he posted Appius Claudius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Through the
                        strenuous exertions of these commanders, each trying to outdo the other, the
                        towers and battering rams and all the other preparations for an assault were
                        completed in a few days. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The land round
                        Heraclea is marshy and covered with tall trees, which furnished a liberal
                        supply of timber for siege works <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> of
                        every kind, and as the Aetolians living in the suburb had taken refuge in
                        the city the deserted houses afforded useful materials for various purposes,
                        including not only beams and planks, but also bricks and building stones of
                        all shapes and sizes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans made more use of machines than
                        of arms in their attack on the city, the Aetolians on the other hand trusted
                        more to their arms for their defence. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When
                        the walls were battered by the rams they did not, as is usual, turn aside
                        the blows by using looped ropes, but they made sorties in considerable
                        strength and some carried firebrands to throw on the siege works. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> There were also arched sally-ports in the walls,
                        and when they built up the wall where it had been destroyed they left more
                        of these openings to allow of more numerous sorties. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In the early days of the siege while their strength was
                        unimpaired these sallies were frequent and powerful, but as time went on
                        they became fewer and feebler. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Amidst the
                        many difficulties they had to contend with nothing wore them down so much as
                        want of sleep. The Romans owing to their numbers were able to arrange
                        regular reliefs for their men, but the Aetolians were comparatively few, and
                        the same men having to be on duty night and day they were completely
                        exhausted by the incessant strain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For
                        four-and-twenty days, without a moment's respite day or night, they had to
                        sustain the attack of the enemy, who were delivering their assaults from
                        four different quarters at once. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Considering the time during which the attack had been going on, and in view
                        of the information brought by deserters, the consul felt pretty sure that
                        the Aetolians were at last worn out, and he formed the following plan.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When it was midnight he gave the
                        signal to retire and called off all the soldiers from the assault. He kept
                        them quiet in the camp till the third hour of the following day, when he
                        recommenced the attack and carried it on <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                        until midnight, when it was again suspended till the third hour of the
                        following day. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Aetolians supposed
                        that the cause of the assault not being kept up was the same as that which
                        was acting upon them, namely excessive fatigue, and when the signal for
                        retiring was given to the Romans, they too, as though it recalled them also,
                        quitted their posts and did not resume duty on the walls till the third hour
                        of the following day. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After suspending the operations at
                        midnight the consul recommenced the assault at the fourth watch with extreme
                        violence on three sides. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the fourth
                        side he ordered Tiberius Sempronius to keep his soldiers on the alert and
                        ready for the signal, as he felt no doubt that the Aetolians would in the
                        nocturnal confusion rush to the places from which the battle-shout arose.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some of the Aetolians were asleep,
                        worn out by toil and want of rest, and only roused themselves with great
                        difficulty; those who were still awake, hearing the noise of battle, ran
                        towards it through the darkness. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        assailants were trying to climb over the fallen parts of the wall into the
                        city, others were endeavouring to mount the walls by scaling ladders, and
                        the Aetolians were hurrying up from all parts to meet the attack. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The one quarter where the suburban buildings
                        stood was so far neither attacked nor guarded, but those who were to attack
                        it were eagerly awaiting the signal and none were there to defend it.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was already dawn when the consul
                        gave the signal and they penetrated into the city without any opposition,
                        some over the ruined walls, others, where the walls were intact, by means of
                        scaling ladders. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as the shouting
                        was heard which announced that the city was captured the Aetolians left
                        their posts and fled to the citadel. </p>
                    <p> The consul gave his victorious troops leave to sack the city, not as an act
                        of vengeance, but in order that the soldiery who had been forbidden this in
                        so many captured cities might in one place at least taste the fruits of
                        victory. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About midday he recalled his men
                        and formed them into two divisions. One he ordered to march round the foot
                        of the mountain to a peak which was the same height as that on which the
                        citadel stood and separated from it by a ravine as though torn away from it.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The twin peaks were so near one
                        another that missiles could be thrown from the rock on to the citadel. With
                        the other division the consul intended to mount up to the citadel, and he
                        waited in the city for the signal from those who were to surmount the peak.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Their cheers on occupying the height
                        and the attack of the other division from the city were too much for the
                        Aetolians, utterly broken as their courage was and with no preparation for
                        standing a siege in the citadel, which could hardly contain, much less
                        protect, the women and children and the other non-combatants who had crowded
                        there. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So at the first assault they laid
                        down their arms and surrendered. Amongst them was Damocritus, the first
                        magistrate of Aetolia. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At the beginning
                        of the war he had told T. Quinctius, on his request for a copy of the decree
                        inviting Antiochus, that be would give it him in Italy when the Aetolians
                        were encamped there. This piece of arrogance made his surrender all the more
                        pleasing to the victors. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans were laying siege to
                        Heraclea, Philip, as arranged with the consul, was attacking Lamia. He had
                        gone to Thermopylae to offer the consul and the people of Rome his
                        congratulations on the victory and at the same time to excuse himself on the
                        ground of illness <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> for not having taken
                        part in the operations against Antiochus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Then the two commanders separated to carry on the siege of the two places
                        simultaneously. These are about seven miles distant from each other, and as
                        Lamia stands on rising ground and looks towards Mount Oeta the distance
                        between them seems very short and all that goes on in the one place can be
                        seen from the other. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans and the
                        Macedonians were strenuously engaged as though in mutual rivalry in siege
                        operations or in actual fighting night and day. But the Macedonians had the
                        more difficult task owing to the fact that the Roman galleries and vineae
                        and all their siege engines were above ground while the Macedonians
                        conducted the attack by means of subterranean mines, and in difficult places
                        they often came to rock upon which iron tools could make no impression.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Finding that he was making little
                        progress, the king held conferences with the leading men of the place in the
                        hope that the townsmen might be induced to surrender. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He felt quite certain that if Heraclea were taken first
                        they would surrender to the Romans sooner than to him and that the consul
                        would win their gratitude for having raised the siege. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> His surmise proved correct, for no sooner was Heraclea
                        taken than a message reached him requesting him to abandon the siege, for as
                        it was the Romans who had fought the engagement with the Aetolians it was
                        but fair that they should have the prize of victory. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> So Lamia was relieved and through the fall of a
                        neighbouring city escaped a similar fate. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Shortly before the fall of Heraclea the
                        Aetolians, assembled in council at Hypata, sent a deputation to Antiochus
                        including Thoas, who had been sent before. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        They were instructed to ask the king to call up his land and sea forces once
                        more and cross over into Greece; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> if
                        anything prevented him from doing this, then they were to ask him to send
                        money and troops and to point out to him that it concerned his regal dignity
                        and his personal honour not to betray his allies, and if he allowed the
                        Romans after destroying the Aetolians to have a perfectly free hand and land
                        in Asia with all <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> their forces the very
                        safety of his kingdom would be imperilled. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        What they said was true and therefore made all the deeper impression on the
                        king. He gave them money for their immediate requirements and pledged
                        himself to send military and naval assistance. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Thoas he kept with him, and the man was very glad to
                        remain behind, as being on the spot he might make the king fulfil his
                        promises. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The fall of Heraclea, however, broke the
                        spirit of the Aetolians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Within a few days
                        of their asking Antiochus to resume hostilities and return to Greece they
                        laid aside all thoughts of war and sent envoys to the consul to sue for
                        peace. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they began to speak, the
                        consul cut them short by saying that there were other matters which had to
                        be attended to first. He then granted them a ten days' armistice and
                        directed them to return to Hypata accompanied by L. Valerius Flaccus, to
                        whom they were to refer the questions they had intended to discuss with him,
                        and any other matters which they wished to discuss. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> On his arrival at Hypata, Flaccus found the Aetolian
                        leaders assembled in council and deliberating as to what line they should
                        take in negotiating with the consul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                        were preparing to begin by alleging the old-standing treaty-rights and their
                        service to Rome, when Flaccus bade them desist from appealing to treaties
                        which they had themselves violated and broken. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They would gain much more, he told them, by confessing
                        their misdoings and simply asking for mercy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Their only hope of safety lay not in the strength of their case but in
                        the clemency of the Roman people, and if they adopted a suppliant attitude
                        he would stand by them before the consul and in the senate at Rome, for they
                        would have to send their delegates there also. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> All those present saw that only one path led to safety,
                        namely their formal submission to Rome. They believed that their appearance
                        as suppliants would give them an inviolable character in Roman eyes, and
                        they would still preserve their independence should Fortune hold out any
                        better prospect. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they appeared before the consul,
                        Phaeneas, the head of the deputation, made a long speech, adapted in various
                        ways to mitigate the victor's wrath, and concluded by saying that the
                        Aetolians committed themselves and all that they had to the honour and good
                        faith of the people of Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the
                        consul heard that he said, "Be quite sure that these are the terms on which
                        you surrender." Phaeneas showed him the decree in which they were expressly
                        stated. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> "Since then," he replied, "you do
                        make this complete surrender, I require you to give up at once Dicaearchus,
                        your fellow-citizen, and Menestus the Epirote"-he was the man who introduced
                        a body of troops into Naupactus and drove the citizens into revolt-"and
                        Amynander and the Athamanian leaders who persuaded you to revolt from us."
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Phaeneas hardly allowed the Roman to
                        finish his sentence before he replied: "We have not surrendered ourselves
                        into slavery, but to your protection and good faith, and I am quite sure
                        that it is because you do not know us that you lay upon us commands which
                        are opposed to the usage of the Greeks." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        To this the consul retorted: "No, I do not trouble myself much as to what
                        the Aetolians consider the usage of the Greeks as long as I follow the usage
                        of the Romans and impose my commands on those who, after being vanquished by
                        force of arms, have just surrendered by their own formal decree. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> If, then, my command is not promptly obeyed, I
                        shall at once order you to be thrown into irons." He then ordered fetters to
                        be brought and the lictors to close round Phaeneas. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Phaeneas and the other Aetolians were now thoroughly
                        cowed, they at last realised their position, and he said that he and the
                        Aetolians with him quite saw that they must carry out the consul's commands,
                        but it was necessary that a decree to that effect should be made at a
                        meeting of the national council. In order that this might be done he asked
                        for a ten days' armistice. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Flaccus
                        supported the request, which was granted, and they returned to Hypata. Here
                        Phaeneas reported to the inner council-known as the Apokleti-the commands
                        laid upon them and the fate which had all but overtaken him and his
                        colleagues. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The magnates deplored the
                        situation to which they were reduced, but they decided that their conqueror
                        must be obeyed and that the Aetolians from every town should be summoned to
                        a general council. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The whole population of Aetolia was thus
                        assembled, and when they heard the report they were so exasperated by what
                        they considered as the harshness and insulting tone of the order that even
                        had they been at peace the angry outburst would have driven them into war.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Besides the anger thus aroused, there
                        were difficulties in the way of carrying out the command. How, they asked,
                        could they possibly surrender Amynander? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Their hopes, too, had been raised by the presence of Nicander, who had just
                        returned from his mission to Antiochus and had filled the minds of the
                        populace with the illusory prospect of huge forces being massed both by land
                        and sea. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After a voyage of twelve days
                        from Ephesus he landed at Phalara on the Maliac Gulf, on his way to Aetolia.
                        From there he went to Lamia, where he left the money which the king had
                        given them, and then started early in the evening for Hypata, with an escort
                        of light troops, through by-paths with which he was familiar. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst traversing the country between the Roman
                        and Macedonian camps, he came upon a Macedonian outpost and was taken to the
                        king. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Philip had not finished dinner, and
                        when he was informed of the arrest he treated him, not as an enemy but as a
                        guest, and bade him sit down and partake of the banquet. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Then after the other guests had left he detained him,
                        telling him at the same time that he had nothing to fear. He proceeded to
                        blame the Aetolians severely for their crooked policy, which had always
                        recoiled <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> on their own heads, for it was
                        they who first brought the Romans and afterwards Antiochus into Greece.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He went on to say that he should
                        forget the past, which it was easier to censure than to amend, and he would
                        not do anything to insult the Aetolians amidst their misfortunes; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> they in return ought to put an end to their
                        ill-will towards him, and Nicander in particular ought never to forget that
                        day in which he had saved his life. He then assigned him an escort to
                        conduct him to a place of safety, and Nicander arrived <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> at Hypata whilst the Aetolians were debating the
                        question of making peace with Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The booty secured round Heraclea was
                        either sold by Manius Acilius or given to the soldiers. On learning that the
                        decision come to at Heraclea did not make for peace and that the Aetolians
                        had concentrated at Naupactus, where they intended to <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> meet the whole brunt of the war, the consul sent Appius
                        Claudius with 4000 men to occupy the heights which commanded the difficult
                        mountain passes while he himself ascended Mount Oeta. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Here he offered sacrifice to Hercules at a place called
                        Pyra, because it was there that the mortal body of the god was cremated.
                        From there he continued his march with the whole of his army and made fairly
                        satisfactory progress till he came to Corax. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> This is the highest peak between Callipolis and Naupactus, and whilst
                        crossing it many of the draught animals fell with their packs down the
                        precipices, and there were casualties among the troops. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> It was easy to see with what an inactive enemy he had
                        to deal, for no attempt had been made to post troops so as to close the
                        pass, which was so difficult and dangerous. As it was, the army had
                        sustained casualties before the consul got down to Naupactus. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Opposite the citadel he established a fortified
                        post, the other quarters of the city he invested, the troops being
                        distributed according to the situation of the walls. This siege involved
                        quite as much labour and effort as that of Heraclea. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Messene, in the Peloponnese, had refused
                        to join the Achaean league, and the Achaeans now laid siege to it.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Neither of the two cities, Messene and
                        Elis, were members of the league; their sympathies were with the Aetolians.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Eleans, however, after Antiochus'
                        flight from Greece, returned a more conciliatory reply to the Achaean envoy
                        and said that when the king's garrison was withdrawn they would consider
                        what they ought to do. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Messenians, on
                        the other hand, dismissed the envoys without vouchsafing any reply whatever
                        and commenced hostilities. But the devastation of their <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> land in all directions by fire and sword and the sight
                        of the Achaean camp near their city made them tremble for their safety, and
                        they sent a message to T. Quinctius at Chalcis to the effect that as he was
                        the author of their liberty the men of Messene were prepared to open their
                        gates to the Romans and surrender their city to them, but not to the
                        Achaeans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On receipt of this message
                        Quinctius at once left Chalcis and sent word to Diophanes, the
                        captain-general of the Achaeans, to withdraw his army at once from Messene
                        and go to him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Diophanes obeyed and raised
                        the siege, and then hurrying on in advance of his army met Quinctius near
                        Andania, a town lying between Megalopolis and Messene. When he began to
                        explain his reasons for attacking the place Quinctius gently rebuked him for
                        taking such <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> an important step without
                        his sanction and ordered him to disband his army and not to disturb the
                        peace which had been established for the good of all. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He commanded the Messenians to recall their banished
                        citizens and join the Achaean league; if there were any conditions they
                        objected to, or any safeguards for the future which they wanted, they were
                        to go to him at Corinth. At the same time he ordered Diophanes to convene a
                        meeting of the Achaean league forthwith, at which he would be present.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In his address to the council he
                        pointed out how the island of Zacynthus had been treacherously seized, and
                        he now demanded its restoration to the Romans. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The island, he explained, had at one time formed part
                        of Philip's dominions and he had given it to Amynander as the price of being
                        allowed to march through Athamania into the north of Aetolia, the result of
                        his expedition being that the Aetolians abandoned all further resistance and
                        sued for peace. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Amynander made Philip of
                        Megalopolis governor of the island. Subsequently when Amynander joined
                        Antiochus in war against Rome he recalled Philip to take up active service
                        and sent Hierocles of Agrigentum to succeed him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After Antiochus' flight from Thermopylae
                        and the expulsion of Amynander from Athamania at the hands of Philip,
                        Hierocles entered into negotiations with Diophanes and sold the island to
                        the Achaeans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans considered it
                        their lawful prize of war; it was not for the benefit of Diophanes and the
                        Achaeans that the legions of Rome fought at Thermopylae. In his reply
                        Diophanes sought to exculpate himself and his nation and brought forward
                        arguments to justify their action. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some of
                        those present protested that they had from the beginning discountenanced
                        that action, and they now remonstrated against the pertinacious attitude of
                        their chief magistrate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They succeeded in
                        getting a decree made referring the whole question to Quinctius for him to
                        deal with. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To those who opposed him
                        Quinctius was stern and uncompromising, but if you gave way he was just as
                        placable. Laying aside every trace of anger in look and voice, he said: "If
                        I thought that the possession of that island would be an advantage to the
                        Achaeans I should advise the senate and people of Rome to allow you to keep
                        it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When, however, I look at a tortoise
                        which has completely shrunk into its shell I see that it is safe against
                        every blow, but when it puts forth any portion of its body, the part put
                        forth is exposed and defenceless. Just so with you, Achaeans. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> As long as you are shut in on all sides by the
                        sea, you have no difficulty in incorporating in your league and protecting
                        all the States within the frontiers of the Peloponnese, but if through a
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> passion for aggrandisement you go
                        beyond those frontiers all that you possess outside is defenceless and lies
                        at the mercy of every assailant." <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> With the
                        unanimous assent of the council-not even Diophanes venturing to raise any
                        opposition-Zacynthus was ceded to the Romans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the consul was starting for Naupactus,
                        Philip asked him if he wished him to recover the cities which had renounced
                        their alliance with Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On receiving the
                        consul's consent he marched his army to Demetrias, as he was fully aware of
                        the confusion which prevailed there. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        citizens were in despair, they saw themselves deserted by Antiochus, with no
                        prospect of help from the Aetolians, and were daily expecting the arrival of
                        their enemy Philip, or of a more relentless enemy still, the Romans, who had
                        more reason to be angry with them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There
                        was in the city a disorganised body of Antiochus' soldiers, the small force
                        which had been left to hold the city, joined afterwards by the fugitives
                        from the battle, who came in, most of them, without arms. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They had neither the strength nor the resolution to
                        stand a siege, and when emissaries from Philip held out to them hopes of
                        obtaining pardon they sent to him to say that the gates were open to the
                        king. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some of the principal men left the
                        city as he entered it; Eurylochus committed suicide. In accordance with the
                        stipulation, the soldiers of Antiochus were sent through Macedonia and
                        Thrace to Lysimachia under the protection of a Macedonian escort. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> There were also at Demetrias a few ships under
                        the command of Isodorus, they too were allowed to depart with their
                        commander. Philip then went on to reduce Dolopia, Aperantia, and some cities
                        in Perrhaebia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Philip was thus engaged T.
                        Quinctius, after taking over Zacynthus from the Achaean council, sailed to
                        Naupactus, which had been standing a siege for two months, but was now
                        nearing its fall. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Its forcible capture
                        would probably have brought ruin on the Aetolians as a nation. Quinctius had
                        every reason for being embittered against them; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> he had not forgotten that they were the only people
                        that had spoken slightingly of him when he was winning the glory of
                        liberating Greece and had refused to be guided by him when he sought to
                        dissuade them from their mad project by forewarning them as to what would
                        happen to them, a forewarning which events had just now proved to be true.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As, however, he looked upon himself as
                        especially bound to see that no State in the Greece which he had freed was
                        utterly destroyed, he decided to walk up to the walls so that the Aetolians
                        could easily see who he was. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He was at
                        once recognised by the advanced posts, and the news rapidly spread
                        throughout the city and troops that Quinctius was there. There was a general
                        rush to the walls; the people all held out their hands in supplication, and
                        with one voice appealed to him by name and implored him to come to their
                        succour and save them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He was deeply moved
                        by this appeal, but at the same time he made signs to them that it was not
                        in his power to help them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When he saw the
                        consul he said to him, "M. Acilius, do you fail to see what is going on, or
                        if you are quite aware of it do you consider that it in no way touches the
                        supreme interest of the Republic?" <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        consul's attention was aroused and he replied, "Why are you not explicit?
                        What do you mean?" Quinctius continued, "Do you not see, now that Antiochus
                        is crushed, how you are wasting time in laying siege to a couple of cities
                        when your year of office has almost expired, while Philip, who has never
                        seen the standards or the battle-line of the enemy, has been annexing not
                        cities only, but all those States, Athamania, Perrhaebia, Aperantia,
                        Dolopia? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And yet it is not so important to
                        us that the strength and resources of the Aetolians should be weakened as it
                        is that Philip should not be allowed to extend his dominions indefinitely
                        and hold all those States as the prize <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                        of victory while you and your soldiers cannot pride yourselves on the
                        conquest of two cities." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul quite agreed, but he felt it
                        somewhat humiliating to abandon the siege without accomplishing anything.
                        Finally the matter was left for Quinctius to settle. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He went back to that section of the walls from which
                        the Aetolians had been calling out to him. They were still there and began
                        to implore him still more earnestly to take pity on the nation of the
                        Aetolians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On this he told some of them to
                        come out to him; Phaeneas and others of their leaders at once went out. As
                        they prostrated themselves at his feet, he said, "Your unhappy plight makes
                        me check the expression of my angry feelings. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> What I told you beforehand would come to pass has
                        actually happened, and you have not even the comfort left you of believing
                        that you do not deserve your fate. Since, however, I have been somehow
                        destined to be the nursing father of Greece, I shall not desist from showing
                        kindness even to those who have shown themselves ungrateful. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Send a deputation to the consul and ask him for
                        an armistice to allow you time to send envoys to Rome with instructions to
                        place yourselves entirely at the mercy of the senate. I will support you
                        before the consul as your advocate and intercessor." <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They followed his advice and the consul was not deaf to
                        their appeal; an armistice was granted until the result of the mission to
                        Rome was known; the siege was raised and the army sent into Phocis.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul accompanied by T. Quinctius
                        went to Aegium to attend a meeting of the Achaean council. The subjects of
                        discussion were the entrance of the Eleans into the league and the
                        restoration of the Lacedaemonian exiles. Neither question was settled; the
                        Achaeans preferred that the latter should be left to them to carry out as an
                        act of grace, and the Eleans wished their incorporation into the league to
                        be spontaneous on their part rather than that it should be effected through
                        the Romans. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A deputation from the Epirots visited the
                        consul. It was pretty generally understood that their professions of
                        friendship were insincere, for though they had not furnished Antiochus with
                        troops it was alleged that they had given him pecuniary assistance and they
                        made no attempt to deny that they had opened negotiations with him.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Their request to be allowed to
                        continue on the old friendly footing was met by the consul with the remark
                        that he did not know whether he was to regard them as friends or as foes.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The senate would decide that; he
                        referred their whole cause to Rome, and for that purpose he granted them an
                        armistice for ninety days. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When they
                        appeared before the senate they were more concerned to mention acts of
                        hostility which they had not committed than to clear themselves from the
                        actual charges made against them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        reply they received was such as to make them understand that they had
                        obtained pardon rather than proved their innocence. Just before this a
                        deputation from Philip was introduced into the senate to present his
                        congratulations upon the recent victory and to request to be allowed to
                        offer sacrifices in the Capitol and place an offering of gold in the temple
                        of Jupiter Optimus Maximus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On receiving
                        the senate's permission they deposited a golden crown weighing 100 pounds.
                        Not only was this gracious reception accorded to them, but Philip's son
                        Demetrius, who was living in Rome as a hostage, was placed in their hands to
                        be taken back to his father. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Such was the
                        close of the campaign which Manius Acilius the consul conducted against
                        Antiochus in Greece. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The other consul, Publius Cornelius
                        Scipio, had in the ballot drawn Gaul as his province. Before leaving for the
                        coming war with the Boii he asked the senate to vote a sum of money for the
                        Games which he had vowed in the crisis of battle during his praetorship in
                        Spain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They looked upon his request as
                        unprecedented and unjustifiable and passed a resolution to the effect that
                        as he had vowed Games on his own initiative without consulting the senate he
                        should meet the cost of them from the proceeds of the spoils taken from the
                        enemy, if he had any money reserved for the purpose, otherwise he must bear
                        the expense himself. He celebrated the Games for ten days. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The temple of Mater Magna Idaea was dedicated about
                        this time. It was during the consulship of P. C. Scipio-afterwards called
                        Africanus-and P. Licinius that the goddess was brought from Asia; the
                        above-named P. Cornelius conducted her from the harbour to the Palatine.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The censors, M. Livius and C.
                        Claudius, had signed the contract for the building in accordance with
                        instructions from the senate during the consulship of M. Cornelius and P.
                        Sempronius. After the lapse of thirteen years M. Junius Brutus dedicated it,
                        and the Games which were exhibited on the occasion of its dedication were,
                        according to Valerius Antias, the first scenic Games ever given and were
                        called the Megalesia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Another dedication
                        was that of the temple of Juventas in the Circus Maximus, which was carried
                        out by C. Licinius Lucullus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> M. Livius had
                        vowed it on the day when he destroyed Hasdrubal and his army, and when he
                        was censor he signed the contract for its construction in the consulship of
                        M. Cornelius and P. Sempronius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Games were
                        celebrated in connection with this dedication also and everything was done
                        with greater solemnity in view of the fresh war which was impending with
                        Antiochus. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the year in which the
                        above events took place, before M. Acilius had left for the war and whilst
                        P. Cornelius was still in Rome, various portents were announced. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> There is a tradition that two tame oxen in the
                        Carinae climbed up the stairs on to the flat roof of a building. The
                        haruspices ordered them to be burnt alive and the ashes thrown into the
                        Tiber. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Terracina and Amiternum several
                        showers of stones were said to have fallen. At Menturnae the temple of
                        Jupiter and the booths round the forum were reported to have been struck by
                        lightning, and at Volturnus two ships in the mouth of the river which had
                        been similarly struck were burnt out. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                        consequence of these portents the senate gave directions for the decemviri
                        to consult the Sibylline Books, and they ordained that a fast day must be
                        instituted in honour of Ceres to be observed every five years; <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> that the sacrifices should be offered for nine
                        days and solemn intercessions for one day, the suppliants to wear wreaths of
                        laurel leaves, and that the consul should offer sacrifice to such deities
                        and with such victims as the decemvirs should name. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> After the gods had been appeased and the portents duly
                        expiated the consul left for his province. On his arrival he ordered the
                        proconsul Cneius Domitius to disband his army and depart for Rome; he
                        himself led his army into the country of the Boii. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Shortly before this the Ligurians had
                        assembled an army under the "Lex Sacrata" and made a sudden attack upon the
                        camp where the proconsul Q. Minucius was in command. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He kept his men drawn up within the rampart until
                        daybreak to prevent the enemy from getting over his lines at any point.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As soon as it was light he made a
                        sortie from two of the camp gates simultaneously. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> But the Ligurians were not, as he had expected,
                        repulsed at the first attempt; for more than two hours they maintained the
                        struggle without either side gaining any advantage. At length, as detachment
                        after detachment issued from the camp, and fresh troops relieved those who
                        were exhausted with fighting, the Ligurians, worn out and suffering
                        especially from want of sleep, turned and fled. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Over 4000 of the enemy were killed, the Romans and
                        allied troops lost less than 300. About two months later, P. Cornelius
                        fought a most successful action with the army of the Boii. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Valerius Antias states that 28,000 of the enemy were
                        slain and 3400 made prisoners, and that the spoils included 124 standards,
                        1230 horses and 247 wagons, whilst in the victorious army 1484 men fell.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though we can place little confidence
                        in this writer so far as numbers are concerned, for no one is more reckless
                        in exaggerating them, it was evidently a great victory, for the camp of the
                        Boii was captured and they made their surrender immediately after the
                        battle. Moreover, special thanksgivings were ordered by the senate for the
                        victory and full-grown victims sacrificed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was about this time that M. Fulvius
                        Nobilior entered the City in ovation after his return from Further Spain.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He brought over 10,000 pounds of
                        silver, 13,000 silver denarii and 127 pounds of gold. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> After receiving the hostages from the Boii, P. C.
                        Scipio by way of punishment mulcted them of nearly half their territory in
                        order that the Roman people might if they chose settle colonists on it.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When on the point of departure to
                        celebrate, as he confidently expected, his triumph, he disbanded his army
                        with orders to be in Rome by the day of triumph. The day following his
                        arrival the senate met in the temple of Bellona and after he <milestone
                            n="5??" unit="section"/> had given a full account of his campaign he
                        requested to be allowed to make a triumphal entry into the City. One of the
                        tribunes of the plebs, P. Sempronius Blaesus, was of opinion that though the
                        honour of a triumph ought not to be refused altogether it ought to be
                        delayed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The wars with the Ligurians, he
                        said, were always closely connected with those against the Gauls, for these
                        nations being neighbours rendered each other mutual help. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> If after his decisive defeat of the Boii Scipio had
                        either crossed the Ligurian frontiers with his army or sent a part of his
                        force to the assistance of Q. Minucius, who had now been detained there
                        three years by an indecisive war, the Ligurian resistance might have been
                        completely broken. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In order to swell his
                        triumph he had now brought back soldiers who could have rendered invaluable
                        service to the commonwealth and could do so still if the senate would agree
                        to make good what he in his haste to enjoy a triumph had left undone by
                        delaying that triumph. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He should be
                        ordered to return with his legions to his province and see that the
                        Ligurians were thoroughly subdued; unless they were brought under the
                        dominion of Rome the Boii would be in a constant state of unrest; whether it
                        be peace or war it must be with both of them together. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> When he has reduced the Boii to submission P. Cornelius
                        will enjoy his triumph a few months hence like many before him who did not
                        celebrate their triumph during their year of office. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul in his reply reminded the
                        tribune that he did not receive Liguria as his province nor was it with the
                        Ligurians that he had been at war, nor was it <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> over the Ligurians that he asked for a triumph.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Q. Minucius would, he felt quite sure,
                        soon subjugate them, and then he would ask for a triumph and it would be
                        granted him because it would be well deserved. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He (the speaker) was asking for a triumph over the Boii
                        after defeating them in battle, depriving them of their camp, receiving the
                        submission of the entire nation two days after the battle, and bringing away
                        a number of hostages as a guarantee of peace for the future. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> But a much stronger reason for his request being
                        granted was the fact that the number of Gauls killed amounted to more than
                        all the thousands of Boii, to say the least, with which any Roman general
                        before his time had ever fought. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Out of
                        50,000 men more than half had fallen, many thousands had been made
                        prisoners, only old men and boys were left among the Boii. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Could then anyone wonder why the victorious army after
                        leaving not a single active enemy in the province had come to Rome to grace
                        the consul's triumph? "If," he continued, "the senate wishes to employ these
                        soldiers in another field, in what way do you think they will be made more
                        ready to face fresh toils and dangers? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By
                        recompensing them in full for the perils and labours they have already
                        undergone, or by sending them off with expectations instead of rewards after
                        they have been cheated of the hopes already formed? As for myself, I had
                        glory enough to last my lifetime on the day when the senate judged me to be
                        the best and worthiest in the commonwealth and sent me to receive Mater
                        Idaea. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The bust of P. Scipio Nasica will
                        be sufficiently honoured by bearing that record inscribed upon it though
                        neither consulship nor triumph were added." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Not only were the senate unanimous in
                        decreeing a triumph, but the tribune bowed to their authority and withdrew
                        his opposition. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So the consul P.
                        Cornelius triumphed over the Boii. In the triumphal procession armour,
                        weapons, standards and booty of all descriptions, including bronze vases,
                        were carried in Gaulish wagons. There were also borne in the procession 1471
                        golden torques, 247 pounds of gold, 2340 pounds of silver, partly in bars,
                        partly wrought, not inartistically, into native vessels, and 23,400 silver
                        denarii. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To each of the soldiers who
                        marched behind his chariot he gave as largesse 125 ases, twice as much to
                        each centurion, and three times as much to each of the horsemen. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The next day the Assembly met, and in his speech
                        he gave an account of his campaign and dwelt on the injustice of their
                        tribune in trying to involve him in a war which was outside his province,
                        and so rob him of the fruits of the victory which he had won. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> At the close of his speech he released his men
                        from their military oath and discharged them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> All this time Antiochus was stopping in
                        Ephesus quite unconcerned about the war with Rome as though the Romans had
                        no intention of landing in Asia. This apathy was due either to the blindness
                        or the flattery of most of his councillors. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Hannibal, who at that time had great influence with the king, was the
                        only one who told him the truth. He said that so far from feeling any doubt
                        about the Romans going, his only wonder was that they were not there
                        already. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The voyage, he pointed out, from
                        Greece to Asia was shorter than from Italy to Greece, and Antiochus was a
                        more dangerous foe than the Aetolians, nor were the arms of Rome less potent
                        on sea than on land. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their fleet had been
                        for some time cruising off Malea, and he understood that fresh ships and a
                        fresh commander had come from Italy to take part in the war. He begged
                        Antiochus therefore to give up all hopes of being left in peace. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Asia would be the scene of conflict, for Asia
                        itself he would have to fight by sea and by land, and either he must wrest
                        the supreme power from those who were aiming at world-wide dominion or else
                        he must lose his own throne. The king realised that Hannibal was the only
                        one who saw what was coming and told him the honest truth. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Following his advice, he took all the ships that were
                        ready for war to the Chersonese in order to strengthen the places there with
                        garrisons in case the Romans came by land. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Polyxenidas received instructions to fit out the rest of the fleet and put
                        to sea, and a number of scouting vessels were sent to patrol the waters
                        round the islands. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> C. Livius was in command of the Roman
                        fleet. He proceeded with fifty decked ships to Neapolis, where the open
                        vessels which the cities on that coast were bound by treaty to furnish had
                        received orders to assemble. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From there he
                        steered for Sicily and sailed through the strait past Messana. When he had
                        picked up the six vessels which had been sent by Carthage and the ships
                        which Regium and Locris and the other cities under the same treaty
                        obligation had contributed he performed the lustration of the fleet and put
                        out to sea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On reaching Corcyra, which was
                        the first Greek city he came to, he made inquiries as to the state of the
                        war-for peace did not prevail throughout Greece-and the whereabouts of the
                        Roman fleet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he learnt that the
                        consul and the king were encamped near the Pass of Thermopylae, and that the
                        Roman fleet was lying in the Piraeus, he felt that for every reason he ought
                        to lose no time and at once set sail for the Peloponnese. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> As Same and Zacynthus had taken the side of the
                        Aetolians he devastated those islands and then shaped his course to Malea,
                        and as the weather was favourable he reached the Piraeus in a few days and
                        here he found the fleet. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whilst off
                        Scyllaeum he was joined by Eumenes with three ships. Eumenes had remained
                        for some time at Aegina, unable to make up his mind what to do, whether to
                        return home and defend his kingdom, as he was constantly being told that
                        Antiochus was concentrating naval and military forces at Ephesus. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> or whether to remain in close touch with the
                        Romans, on whom he knew that his fate depended. A. Atilius handed over to
                        his successor the twenty-four decked ships in the Piraeus, and then left for
                        Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Livius sailed to Delos with
                        eighty-one decked vessels and many smaller, some undecked and beaked, others
                        without beaks, to be used as scouts. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul was laying siege to Naupactus
                        at the time. Livius was detained at Delos by contrary winds for several
                        days; the seas round the Cyclades are liable to violent storms, owing to the
                        numerous channels, some narrower, some wider, which separate the islands.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas received intelligence
                        through the scouting vessels which were patrolling those waters that the
                        Roman fleet was lying at Delos, and he sent on the information to the king.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Antiochus abandoned his designs in the
                        Hellespont and returned to Ephesus with all possible speed, taking his
                        warships with him. He at once called a council of war to decide whether he
                        ought to risk an engagement. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas
                        was opposed to any delay, and said that they certainly ought to engage
                        before Eumenes and the Rhodians joined the Roman fleet. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> In that case they would not be so very unequally
                        matched in point of numbers and in everything else they would have the
                        advantage, in the speed of their vessels and in various <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> other respects, for the Roman ships were awkwardly
                        built and slow, and as they were going to a hostile country they would be
                        heavily laden with stores, whilst the king's ships, having none but friends
                        all round them, would carry nothing but soldiers and their equipment.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They would be greatly assisted, too,
                        by their familiarity with the sea and the coasts and their knowledge of the
                        winds; the enemy on the other hand, who was ignorant of all this, would be
                        thrown into confusion by them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The council
                        unanimously approved of his proposal, since the man who made it was also the
                        one who was to carry it out. </p>
                    <p> Two days were spent in preparations, on the third day they set sail for
                        Phocaea with a fleet of a hundred ships, seventy decked, the rest open
                        ships, but all smaller than the corresponding vessels of the enemy fleet.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On hearing that the Roman fleet was
                        approaching, the king, who had no intention of taking part in a naval
                        battle, withdrew to Magnesia ad Sipylum to assemble his land forces, the
                        fleet sailing on to Cissus, the port <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> of
                        Erythrae, as that appeared a more suitable place in which to await the
                        enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Romans had been detained at
                        Delos for some days by northerly winds; when these subsided they put out
                        from Delos and steered for the harbour of Phanae, at the southern end of
                        Chios, facing the Aegean. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They then
                        brought their ships up to the city, and after taking in supplies sailed to
                        Phocaea. Eumenes, who had gone to his fleet at Elea, returned in a few days
                        with twenty-four decked ships and a larger number of open ones, and sailed
                        on to Phocaea, where he found the Romans getting their ships ready and
                        making every preparation for the coming naval contest. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> From Phocaea they put to sea with one hundred and five
                        decked ships and about fifty open ones. At first they were driven towards
                        the land by the northerly winds which blew across their course and were
                        forced to sail in almost a single line; when the wind became less violent
                        they endeavoured to make the harbour of Corycus, which lies beyond Cissus.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When news was brought to Polyxenidas of
                        the approach of the Roman fleet he was delighted at the prospect of a fight.
                        Extending his left towards the open sea he ordered the captains of the right
                        division to align their ships towards the land, and in this way he advanced
                        to battle with a straight front. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On seeing
                        this the Roman commander took in sail, lowered his masts, and stowing away
                        the tackle waited for the ships in the rear to come up. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> His front line now consisted of thirty ships, and in
                        order to make it extend as far as the enemy's left he directed these vessels
                        to set up their foresails and steer for the open sea; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> those behind, as they came up, were ordered to direct
                        their course landward against the enemy's right. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Eumenes was bringing up the rear, but as soon as he saw
                        the hurried removal of the masts and rigging he urged his ships on with all
                        possible speed. Full in view of both fleets were two Carthaginian vessels
                        which outstripped the Roman fleet and three of the king's ships went to meet
                        them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The inequality of numbers enabled
                        two of these to close on one of the Carthaginian vessels, and after shearing
                        off both banks of oars they boarded it and flinging overboard or killing the
                        defenders captured the ship. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The other
                        Carthaginian ship which had only one opponent, seeing its sister-ship
                        captured, fled back to the Roman fleet before the three could make a
                        simultaneous attack upon it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Livius was
                        furious and made straight in his flagship for the enemy, and as the two
                        vessels which had overpowered the single Carthaginian ship bore down upon
                        him, expecting the same success, he ordered the rowers to back water on both
                        sides so that the way of the ship might be stopped. Then he ordered them to
                        hook their grappling irons on to the enemy ships and when they had made a
                        soldiers' battle of it to remember that they were Romans and not to look
                        upon the slaves of Antiochus as men. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This
                        one ship now defeated and captured the two much more easily than the two had
                        captured the single one previously. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> By
                        this time the fleets were engaged along the whole line and as the fighting
                        went on the ships became everywhere intermixed. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Eumenes, who had come up after the battle had commenced
                        seeing that Livius had thrown the enemy's left into confusion, attacked the
                        right division where the struggle was still an equal one. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was not long before the enemy's left
                        division took to flight, for when Polyxenidas saw that he was clearly
                        worsted as far as the courage of his soldiers was concerned he lowered his
                        foresails and fled away in disorder, and those who had been engaged with
                        Eumenes near the land very soon did the same. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> As long as the rowers could hold out and there was any
                        chance of harassing the hindmost ships Eumenes and the Romans kept up a
                        vigorous pursuit. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But when they found that
                        owing to the speed of the enemy's ships, which were light as compared with
                        theirs, loaded as they were with supplies, their attempt to overtake them
                        was baffled, they desisted from the pursuit, after capturing thirteen
                        vessels with their troops and crews and sinking ten. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The only vessel lost in the Roman fleet was the
                        Carthaginian vessel, overpowered by the two assailants at the beginning of
                        the battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas did not stop his
                        flight till he was in the harbour of Ephesus. The Romans remained for that
                        day at Cissus, from which place the king's fleet had gone out to battle; the
                        next day they continued to follow up the enemy. Midway on their course they
                        were met by twenty-five decked ships from Rhodes under the command of
                        Pausistratus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With their united fleets
                        they still followed up the enemy and appeared in line of battle before the
                        entrance of the harbour. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After they had
                        thus forced the enemy to admit his defeat, the Rhodians and Eumenes were
                        sent home and the Romans started for Chios. They sailed past Phocaea, one of
                        the Erythraean ports, and then anchored for the night. The next day they
                        sailed up to the city itself. Here they stayed for a few days mainly to
                        recruit the crews and then they proceeded to Phocaea. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Here four quinqueremes were left to guard the city and
                        the fleet went on to Canae, where as the winter was approaching the ships
                        were drawn up on land and protected by a ring of entrenchments. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> At the close of the year the elections were held.
                        The new consuls were L. Cornelius Scipio and C. Laelius, and all were
                        looking upon Africanus to end the war with Antiochus. The praetors elected
                        on the following day were M. Tuccius, L. Aurunculeius, Cn. Fulvius, L.
                        Aemilius, P. Junius and C. Atinius Labeo. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
