<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab urbe condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 8-10 - 11s</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books VIII-X With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1926: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11s" type="book">
                <head>Summary of Book XI</head>
                <p> WHEN Fabius Gurges the consul had fought an unsuccessful battle with the
                    Samnites and the senate was debating his removal from the command, Fabius
                    Maximus his father begged them to spare his son this ignominy. <reg>what</reg>
                    particularly moved the senate was his promise to go out as his son's lieutenant,
                    which he did. <reg>aided</reg> by his advice and services, his son the consul
                    defeated the Samnites and triumphed. <name>Gaius</name> Pontius, the general of
                    the Samnites, was led in the triumph and beheaded. <reg>when</reg> the state was
                    troubled with a pestilence, the envoys dispatched to bring over the image of
                    Aesculapius from Epidaurus to Rome fetched away a serpent, which had crawled
                    into their ship and in which it was generally believed that the god himself was
                    present. <reg>on</reg> the serpent's going ashore on the island of the Tiber, a
                    temple was erected there to Aesculapius. <name>The</name> consular Lucius
                    Postumius was convicted of having used the labour of soldiers on his own land
                    when in command of the army. <name>The</name> Samnites sought peace and the
                    treaty with them was renewed for the fourth time. <name>Curius</name> Dentatus
                    the consul having slaughtered the Samnites and conquered the Sabines, who had
                    revolted, and received their submission, triumphed twice in the same year of
                    office. <reg>colonies</reg> were established at Castrum, Sena, and Hadria.
                        <reg>a</reg> board of three to deal with capital offences was then chosen
                    for the first time. <name>The</name> number of citizens was returned as 272,000.
                    Because of their debts, the plebs, after serious and protracted quarrels,
                    seceded to Janiculum, whence they were brought back by Quintus Hortensius the
                    dictator, who died before the expiration of his term. <name>The</name> book
                    contains also campaigns with the Vulsinienses and likewise with the Lucanians,
                    against whom the Romans had voted to assist the people of Thurii. </p>
                <pb n="p.549"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
