<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to forty-five -
                    37</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">William A. McDevitte, Sen. Class. Mod. Ex. Schol.
                    A.B.T.C.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title> History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to the end,
                                with the epitomes and fragments of the lost books </title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>William A. McDevitte</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXXVII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Lucius Cornelius Scipio the consul, having as lieutenant Publius Scipio
                        Africanus, (who had declared that he would be his brother's lieutenant if
                        the province of Greece was decreed to him, when that province appeared
                        likely to be assigned to Caius Laelius, who had great influence in the se-
                        nate,) set out to wage war against Antiochus, and was the first Roman
                        general that ever passed over into Asia. Aemilius Regillus, with the
                        assistance of the Rhodians, fought successfully against the royal fleet of
                        Antiochus at Myonnesus. The son of Africanus, having been taken by
                        Antiochus, was sent back to his father. Manius Acilius Glabrio tri- umphed
                        over Antiochus, whom he had driven out of Greece, and over the Aetolians.
                        Antiochus being subsequently conquered by Lucius Cornelius Scipio, with the
                        aid of Eumenes, son of Attalus, and king of Pergamus, peace was granted to
                        hint on these terms-that he should evacuate all the provinces on this side
                        Mount Taurus. The kingdom of Eumenes, through whose assistance Antiochus had
                        been conquered, was enlarged. Some states were granted to the Rhodians too,
                        who also had assisted them. The colony of Bononia was founded. Aemilius
                        Regillus, who had conquered the admirals of Antiochus in a naval engagement,
                        triumphed. Lucius Cornelius Scipio, who had brought the war with Antiochus
                        to a conclu- sion, was called Asiaticus, attaining to an equality with his
                        brother by this surname. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius CORNELIUS SCIPIO and Caius Laelius
                    being consuls, no business, after the duties of religion, was transacted in the
                    senate prior to that of the Aetolians. Not only their ambassadors were urgent,
                    because they had a truce of a short period, but they were aided by Titus
                    Quinctius also, who had then returned to Rome from Greece. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Aetolians, as being persons to whom there was more hope
                    in the mercy of the senate than in their cause, acted suppliantly, weighing
                    their by-gone services against their recent misconduct. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But when <pb n="1656" xml:id="p.1656"/> present, they were
                    importuned by questions of the senators, wringing from them an acknowledgment of
                    their guilt rather than replies, and when ordered to depart from the senate,
                    they caused a great contest. Resentment had more power in their case than
                    compassion; for the senate were incensed against them not merely as enemies, but
                    as an uncivilized and unsocial race. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After it
                    had been contested several days, it was at last resolved, that peace should
                    neither be granted nor refused. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Two conditions
                    were offered them, either that they should yield to the senate unconditional
                    power over them, or pay one thousand talents, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 193,750 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note> and have the same friends and enemies. To them, desirous to elicit in
                    what things they should give to the senate unconditional power over them, no
                    positive answer is given; but being thus dismissed, without having concluded a
                    peace, they were ordered to quit the city that very day, and Italy within
                    fifteen days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They then began to debate
                    concerning the provinces for the consuls. Both of these wished for Greece.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Laelius had a powerful interest in the
                    senate; and when the senate had ordered that the consuls should either cast lots
                    for the provinces, or settle them between themselves, he observed, that they
                    would act with more propriety in leaving that matter to the wisdom of the
                    senators, than to the decision of lot. To this Scipio, an answer being given
                    that he would take advice how he ought to act, having spoken to his brother
                    alone, and having been desired by him to leave it unhesitatingly to the senate,
                    answered his colleague that he would do what he recommended. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When this plan, either original or supported by precedents
                    of a record now lost by antiquity, being referred to the senate, had aroused
                    them by the expectation of a contest, Publius Scipio Africanus said, that
                        <quote> if they decreed that province to his brother, Lucius Scipio, he
                        would go along with him, as his lieutenant-general. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This proposal being received with universal
                    approbation, put an end to all dispute. The senate were well pleased to make the
                    trial, whether king Antiochus should have more effectual aid in the vanquished
                    Hannibal, or the Roman consul and legions in his conqueror Africanus; and they
                    almost all voted Greece to Scipio, and Italy to Laelius. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The praetors then cast lots for their provinces: Lucius
                    Aurunculeius obtained the city jurisdiction; Cneius Fulvius, the foreign; Lucius
                    Aemilius Regil- <pb n="1657" xml:id="p.1657"/> lus, the fleet; Publius Junius
                    Brutus, the Tuscans; Marcus Tuccius, Apulia and Bruttium; and Caius Atinius,
                    Sicily. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then to the consul to whom the province of
                    Greece had been decreed, in addition to the army which he was about to receive
                    from M. Acilius, (but they were two legions,) three thousand Roman foot and one
                    hundred horse, and of the Latin confederates five thousand foot and two hundred
                    horse, are added as a reinforcement; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and it
                    was further ordered, that if, when he arrived in his province, he would judge it
                    conducive to the public interest, he should be at liberty to carry over the army
                    into Asia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the other consul was decreed an
                    army entirely new; two Roman legions, and of the Latin confederates fifteen
                    thousand foot and six hundred horse. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Quintius
                    Minucius was ordered to remove his forces out of Liguria (for he had written,
                    that the province was completely subdued, and that the whole nation of the
                    Ligurians had surrendered) into the country of the Boians, and to give up the
                    command to Publius Cornelius, proconsul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    two city legions, enlisted the year before, about to be brought home from the
                    country in which Cornelius had fined the conquered Boians, were assigned to
                    Marcus Tuccius, praetor, together with fifteen thousand foot and six hundred
                    horse, of the Latin confederates, to occupy Apulia and Bruttium. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Orders were given to Aulus Cornelius, a praetor of
                    the preceding year, who occupied Bruttium with an army, that if the consul
                    judged it proper, he should <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> transport his
                    legions into Aetolia, and give them to Manius Acilius, provided the latter was
                    inclined to remain there; but if Acilius wished to come to Rome, that then Aulus
                    Cornelius should stay in Aetolia with that army. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> It was resolved that Caius Atinius Labeo should receive from Marcus Aemilius
                    the province of Sicily, and the army there; and should, if he deemed it proper,
                    enlist in the province itself two thousand foot and one hundred horse, for a
                    reinforcement. Publius Junius Brutus was ordered to raise a new army for
                    Tuscany, consisting of one Roman legion, and ten thousand foot of the allies and
                    Latin nation, and four hundred horse. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lucius
                    Aemilius, whose province was the sea, was ordered to receive from Marcus Junius,
                    praetor of the former year, twenty <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> ships of
                    war, with their crews, and himself to enlist one thousand marines and two
                    thousand foot soldiers, with which ships and soldiers he <pb n="1658"
                        xml:id="p.1658"/> was to sail to Asia, and receive the command of the fleet
                    from Caius Livius. To the governors of the two Spains and Sardinia, their
                    command is prolonged for a year, and the same armies were decreed them.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Sicily and Sardinia were, this year,
                    assessed in two-tenths of their corn. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> All the
                    corn from Sicily was ordered to be carried into Aetolia, to the army there; of
                    that to be collected from Sardinia, one-half to Rome, and the other half into
                    Aetolia, for the same use as the corn from Sicily. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was judged proper, that, previous to the
                    departure of the consuls for their provinces, the prodigies should be expiated
                    under the direction of the pontiffs. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    temple of Juno Lucina, at Rome, was struck by lightning in such a manner, that
                    the summit and the folding-doors were much damaged. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> At Puteoli, the wall and a gate were struck by lightning in
                    several parts, and two men killed. It was clearly proved, that, at Nursia, in
                    the midst of a calm, a tempest suddenly burst forth; and there also two freemen
                    were killed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Tusculans reported, that a
                    shower of earth fell in their country; and the Reatines, that a mule brought
                    forth young in theirs. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These prodigies were
                    expiated, and the Latin festival was celebrated a second time, because the
                    flesh-meat, which ought to be given to the Laurentians, had not been given them.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There was also a supplication made on
                    account of those religious fears; the decemvirs gave directions from the books,
                    to which of the gods it should be performed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Ten free-born youths, and ten virgins, all of whom had their fathers and mothers
                    living, were employed in that ceremony; and the decemvirs sacrificed sucklings
                    by night. Publius Cornelius Scipio Africanus, before he left the city, erected
                    an arch on the Capitol, facing the road by which we ascend to it, with seven
                    gilded statues and two horses, and placed two marble cisterns in the front of
                    the arch. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During that period, forty-three of
                    the principal Aetolians, among whom were Damocritus and his brother, were
                    brought to Rome by two cohorts, sent by Manius Acilius, and were thrown into the
                    prison called Lautumiae, or the quarry. Lucius Cornelius the consul ordered the
                    cohorts after that to return to the army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Ambassadors came from Ptolemy and Cleopatra, king and queen of Egypt,
                    congratulating the Romans because the consul Manius Acilius had driven king
                    Antiochus out of Greece, <pb n="1659" xml:id="p.1659"/> and advising that they
                    should carry over their army into Asia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For
                        <quote> all places, not only in Asia, but also in Syria, were filled with
                        consternation; and the king and queen of Egypt would be prepared to do those
                        things which the senate should direct. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thanks were returned to the king and queen,
                    and presents were ordered to be made to the ambassadors, four thousand <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 12 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to each. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul Lucius Cornelius, having finished
                    what was necessary to be done at Rome, gave public notice, in an assembly of the
                    people, that the soldiers, whom he himself had enlisted for a reinforcement, and
                    those who were in Bruttium with Aulus Cornelius, proprietor, should all meet him
                    at Brundusium on the ides of July. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He likewise
                    appointed three lieutenants-general, Sextus Digitius, Lucius Apustius, and Caius
                    Fabricius Luscinus; who were to bring together ships from all parts of the
                    sea-coast to Brundusium; and now, every thing being ready, he set out from the
                    city in his military robe of state. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> About five
                    thousand volunteers of the Romans and allies, who had served out their
                    campaigns, under the command of Publius Africanus, attended the consul at his
                    departure, and gave in their names. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the
                    time in which the consul set out to the war during the celebration of the
                    Apollinarian games, on the fifth day before the ides of July, though the sky was
                    serene, the light was obscured in the middle of the day, when the moon passed
                    beneath the orb of the sun. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> L. Aemilius
                    Regillus, to whom the sea had fallen as his province, set out at the same time.
                    To Lucius Aurunculeius this business was assigned by the senate, that he should
                    build thirty quinqueremes and twenty triremes, because there was a report that
                    Antiochus, since the engagement at sea, was fitting out a much larger fleet.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Aetolians, after the ambassadors
                    brought back word from Rome that there was no hope of peace, although their
                    whole seacoast, which was opposite to Peloponnesus, was ravaged by the Achaeans,
                    regarding the danger more than their losses, seized on Mount Corax, in order to
                    shut up the pass against the Romans; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> for they
                    had no doubt that they would return in the beginning of spring to the siege of
                    Naupactum. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It appeared better to Acilius, who
                    knew that this was expected, to attempt a thing that was not anticipated, and to
                    lay <pb n="1660" xml:id="p.1660"/> siege to Lamia; for the garrison had been
                    reduced by Philip almost to a state of desperation; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and being then off their guard, because they feared no such
                    attempt, might be surprised by himself. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Marching from Elatia, he formed his first encampment in the enemy's country, on
                    the banks of the river Sperchius, and decamping thence in the night, he at break
                    of day attacked the town with a line of troops that encircled it. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As is usual in an unexpected affair, great
                    consternation and tumult ensued; yet the besieged, with greater resolution than
                    any one could suppose them capable of under such a sudden alarm, when the men
                    fought, and the women brought weapons of every kind, and stones, to the walls,
                    defended the city for that day, although the scaling ladders were raised against
                    the walls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> About mid-day, Acilius, the signal
                    for retreat being given, drew off his men to their camp. After their bodies were
                    refreshed by food and rest, before he dismissed the meeting in the Praetorium,
                    he gave them notice, <quote> to be ready and under arms before day; and that
                        they were not to return to their tents until the city should be taken. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Next day, at the same hour as before, having
                    began the assault in a greater number of places, as not only the strength, but
                    also the weapons, and above all, the courage of the garrison began to fail, he
                    took the town in the space of a few hours. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> One
                    half of the spoil found there was sold in parcels; the other was divided among
                    the soldiers; and a council was held to determine what he should next undertake.
                    No one approved of going against Naupactum, while the pass at Corax was occupied
                    by the Aetolians. That, however, the summer campaign might not be an idle one,
                    and that the Aetolians might not through his supineness possess the peace that
                    they could not obtain from the senate, Acilius resolved to besiege Amphissa; his
                    army was led thither from Heraclea by Œta. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Having encamped under the walls, he proceeded to attack the town, not by general
                    assault, as at Lamia, but by regular approaches. The ram was brought up to the
                    walls in many places at once; and though these were shaken by it, yet the
                    townsmen never attempted to provide or contrive any sort of defence against such
                    a description of mechanism. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All their hope was
                    in arms and courage. By frequent sallies they much annoyed not only the advanced
                    guards of the Romans, but even those who were employed at the works and
                    machines. <pb n="1661" xml:id="p.1661"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, the wall was broken down in many
                    places, when word was brought, that his successor, having landed his army at
                    Apollonia, was coming through Epirus and Thessaly. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The consul came with thirteen thousand foot and five
                    hundred horse. He had already arrived at the Malian bay; and after that, to his
                    messengers sent forward to Hypata, to order a surrender of the city, this
                    response was given, that they would do nothing except by the common consent of
                    the Aetolians: that the siege of Hypata might not detain him while Amphissa was
                    not yet recovered, having sent forward his brother Africanus, he leads his
                    forces to Amphissa. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A little before their
                    arrival, the towns-people having abandoned the city, for it was now, for the
                    most part, stripped of its walls; all, armed and unarmed, retired into the
                    citadel, which they deemed an impregnable fortress. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The consul pitched his camp at the distance of about six
                    miles from the town; and thither came ambassadors from the Athenians,
                    addressing, first, Publius Scipio, who preceded the main body as before
                    mentioned, and afterwards the consul, with earnest supplications in favour of
                    the Aetolians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They received a milder answer
                    from Africanus, who, wishing for an honourable pretext for relinquishing the
                    Aetolian war, was directing his views towards Asia and king Antiochus, and had
                    recommended to the Athenians to persuade, not only the Romans, but the Aetolians
                    likewise, to prefer peace to war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By the
                    advice of the Athenians a numerous embassy of the Aetolians came speedily from
                    Hypata, and the discourse of Africanus, whom they addressed first, augmented
                    their hopes of peace; for he mentioned, that <quote> many nations and states,
                        first in Spain, and afterwards in Africa, had thrown themselves on his
                        protection; and that, in all of them, he had left greater monuments of
                        clemency and kindness than of military prowess. </quote> The business seemed
                    to be concluded, when the consul, on being applied to, repeated the very same
                    answer with which they had been driven off by the senate. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> When the Aetolians were thunderstruck at this, as if they
                    had never heard it before, (for they now perceived that no progress was made
                    either from the Athenian embassy or the favourable reply of Africanus,) they
                    said that they wished to consult their countrymen on the affair. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They then returned to Hypata, nor were their
                    plans cleared of difficulties. For they had no means of paying the thousand <pb
                        n="1662" xml:id="p.1662"/> talents and, in case of an unconditional
                    submission, they dreaded lest cruelty should be inflicted on their persons.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They, therefore, ordered the same
                    ambassadors to return to the consul and Africanus, and to request, that if they
                    meant in reality to grant them peace, and not merely to amuse them with a
                    prospect of it, frustrating the hopes of the wretched, they would either remit
                    some part of the money required to be paid, or order that the unconditional
                    submission should not extend to their persons. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Nothing was accomplished whereby the consul might change his resolution; and
                    that embassy, also, was dismissed without effect. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Athenian ambassadors accompanied them. And Echedemus,
                    their principal in the embassy, recalled to hope the Aetolians, dejected by so
                    many repulses, and deploring with unavailing lamentations the hard fate of their
                    nation —by advising them to request a suspension of arms for six months, in
                    order that they might send an embassy to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    He urged that "the delay could add nothing to their present calamities, which
                    were already severe in the extreme; but that, if time intervened, their present
                    calamities might be alleviated by many chances. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Agreeably to this advice of Echedemus, the same ambassadors were sent again;
                    who, making their first application to Publius Scipio, obtained, through him,
                    from the consul, a suspen- sion of arms for the time they desired: <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and the siege of Amphissa being raised, Manius
                    Acilius, the army being delivered to the consul, left the province; and the
                    consul returned from Amphissa into Thessaly, with intention of leading his
                    troops into Asia through Macedonia and Thrace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Here Africanus said to his brother, Lucius Scipio, "I also, Lucius Scipio,
                    approve of the route which you adopt. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the
                    whole matter rests on the inclinations of Philip; for if he be faithful to our
                    government, he will afford us a passage, and provisions and all things which
                    support and aid an army on a long march. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But
                    if he should fail in this, you will find no safety in any part of Thrace. In my
                    opinion, therefore, the king's disposition ought in the first place to be
                    discovered. He will be best tested if the person who shall be sent will come
                    suddenly upon him, doing nothing by a preconcerted plan. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus, a young man, the most active
                    of all the youths at that time, being selected for this purpose, by means of
                    relays of horses, and travelling with almost incredi- <pb n="1663"
                        xml:id="p.1663"/> ble expedition, made good the journey from Amphissa,
                    whence he had been despatched, to Pella, on the third day. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The king was sitting at a banquet, and was far gone in his
                    cups: that very relaxation of mind removed all suspicion of any intention of
                    changing his measures. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> His guest was kindly
                    entertained for the present; and next day he saw provisions in abundance already
                    prepared for the army, bridges made over rivers, and roads fortified where the
                    passage was difficult. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As he was bringing
                    back this intelligence, with the same speed which he had used in coming, he met
                    the consul at Thaumaci. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> From this the army
                    rejoicing, marched with more certain and greater hopes into Macedon, where all
                    things were prepared. On their arrival, the king received them with royal
                    magnificence, and accompanied them on their march. Much pleasantry and good
                    humour appeared in him, which recommended him much to Africanus, a man who, as
                    he was unparalleled in other respects, was not averse to courteousness
                    unaccompanied by luxury. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Passing from this
                    not only through Macedon, but also through Thrace, they arrived at the
                    Hellespont, Philip escorting them and making every preparation. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Antiochus, after the sea-fight at Corycus,
                    when he had the whole winter disengaged to carry on his preparations by land and
                    water, was chiefly intent on the refitting of his ships, lest he should be
                    entirely excluded from the sea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It occurred to
                    him that he had been defeated when the Rhodian fleet was absent; if this fleet
                    were present in an engagement, (and the Rhodians would certainly not be guilty
                    of being late a second time,) he required a vast number of ships to equal the
                    fleet of the enemy, in the strength of their crews and size of their vessels.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For this reason, he sent Hannibal into
                    Syria, to bring in the Phœnician navy, and gave orders to Polyxenidas, that, the
                    more unsuccessfully affairs had been managed before, the more diligently he
                    should now repair the ships which he had, and procure others. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He himself passed the winter in Phrygia, calling in
                    auxiliaries from every quarter. He had even sent for that purpose to
                    Gallograecia. The people of that country were then more warlike than at present,
                    retaining the Gallic spirit, as the generation which had emigrated thither was
                    not yet extinct. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He had left his son Seleucus
                    with an army in Aeolia, to keep in obedience the maritime cities, which on one
                    side Eumenes from Perga- <pb n="1664" xml:id="p.1664"/> mus, on the other, the
                    Romans from Phocaea and Erythrae, were soliciting to revolt. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman fleet, as mentioned before, wintered at Canae;
                    thither, about the middle of the season, came king Eumenes, with two thousand
                    foot and one hundred horse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He, when he
                    affirmed that vast quantities of spoil might be brought off from the enemy's
                    country round Thyatira; by his persuasions, prevailed on Livius to send with him
                    five thousand soldiers. Those that were sent within a few days carried off an
                    immense booty. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile a sedition broke out at Phocaea, in
                    consequence of some endeavouring to bring over the multitude to the party of
                    Antiochus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The winter quarters of the ships
                    were burdensome: the tribute was burdensome, because five hundred gowns with
                    five hundred tunics were exacted from them: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    the scarcity of corn was also galling, on account of which the ships also and
                    garrison of Rome evacuated the place. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    faction which laboured in their assemblies to draw the commonalty over to
                    Antiochus, was now freed from all apprehension: the senate, and higher ranks,
                    were of opinion that they should persevere in the alliance with Rome. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> But the advisers of a revolt had greater influence
                    with the multitude. The Rhodians, the earlier in proportion to their having been
                    too late in the former summer, sent in the vernal equinox, as commander of their
                    fleet, with thirty-six ships, the same Pausistratus. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At this time Livius, with thirty ships and seven
                    quadriremes, which king Eumenes had brought with him, was on his passage from
                    Canae to the Hellespont, in order to prepare every thing necessary for the
                    transportation of the army, which he expected to come by land. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He first brought his fleet into the harbour called the
                    Achaean; whence he went up to Ilium, and having offered sacrifice to Minerva,
                    gave a kind reception to the embassies from the states in the neighbourhood,
                    from Elaeus, Dardanum, and Rhetaeum, surrendering their respective states to
                    him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then he sailed to the entrance of the
                    Hellespont; and, leaving ten ships stationed opposite to Abydos, he crossed over
                    to Europe with the rest of the fleet, to attack Sestos. As the troops were
                    advancing up to the walls, first of all inspired priests of Cybele, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Called Galli, and Corybantes.</note> in
                    their solemn dress, met them before the gate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    These said, that, <quote> by order of the mother of the gods, they, <pb n="1665"
                            xml:id="p.1665"/> the immediate servants of the goddess, were come to
                        pray the Roman commander to spare the walls and the city. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> None of them was injured; and, presently, the
                    whole senate and the magistrates came out to surrender the place. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The fleet then sailed over to Abydos; where when,
                    their minds being sounded by conferences, no peaceable answer was given, they
                    prepared themselves for a siege. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these transactions are carried on at the
                    Hellespont, Polyxenidas, the commander of the king's fleet, (but he was an exile
                    from Rhodes,) having heard that <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the ships of
                    his countrymen had sailed from home, and that Pausistratus, who commanded them,
                    had, in a public speech, uttered several haughty and contemptuous expressions
                    respecting him, and having conceived a particular jealousy against him,
                    considered nothing else, night or day, than that by his acts he should refute
                    his boastful words. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He sent a person, who was
                    known to him, to say, that <quote> if it were allowed, he would be of great
                        service to Pausistratus, and to his native country; and that he might be
                        restored by Pausistratus to his country. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When Pausistratus, in surprise, asked by what
                    means such things could be effected; and pledged his faith to the other, at his
                    request, that he would either concur in the execution of the design, or bury it
                    in silence; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the emissary then told him, that
                        <quote> Polyxenidas would deliver into his hands, either the whole of the
                        king's fleet or the greater part of it; and as a reward, he stipulated for
                        nothing more, than a return to his native country. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The importance of the business had this
                    effect, that he neither believed nor despised his proposition. He sailed to
                    Panormus, in the Samian territory, and stopped there in order to examine
                    thoroughly the business which was proposed to him. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Messengers passed rapidly from both parties, nor was
                    confidence inspired into Pausistratus until, in the presence of his messenger,
                    Polyxenidas wrote, with his own hand, an engagement that he would perform all
                    that he had promised, and sent the tablets sealed with his own seal. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> By such a pledge as this, he thought that the traitor
                    was completely engaged to him. For, <quote> that he who lived under a king would
                        never act so absurdly as to give evidence of guilt against himself, attested
                        by his own signature. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The method of conducting the pretended plot
                    was then settled: Polyxenidas said that <quote> he would neglect every kind of
                        preparation; that <pb n="1666" xml:id="p.1666"/> he would not keep any
                        considerable numbers on board, either of rowers or mariners; that he would
                        haul up on land some of the ships, under pretence of refitting them;
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> would send away others into the
                        neighbouring ports, and keep a few at sea before the harbour of Ephesus;
                        which, if circumstances made it necessary to come out, he would expose to a
                        battle. </quote> The negligence which Pausistratus heard that Polyxenidas
                    was about to use in his fleet, he himself immediately practised. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Part of his ships he sent to Halicarnassus to bring
                    provisions, another part to the city of Samos, while he himself waited at
                    Panormus, that he might be ready when he should receive the signal of attack
                    from the traitor. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas encouraged his
                    mistake by counterfeiting neglect; hauled up some ships, and, as if he intended
                    to haul up others, put the docks in repair; he did not call the rowers from
                    their winter quarters to Ephesus, but assembled them secretly at Magnesia. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By chance one of Antiochus's soldiers, when he
                    had come to Samos on account of private business, being seized as a spy, is
                    brought to Panormus to the admiral. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This man,
                    it is uncertain whether through fear or treachery towards his countrymen,
                    disclosed all things to him, inquiring what was going on at Ephesus: <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> that the fleet lay in harbour, fully equipped and
                    ready for sea; that all the rowers had been sent to Magnesia (at Sipylus); that
                    very few of the ships had been hauled on land; that the docks were shut, and
                    that never was the business of the fleet conducted with greater diligence. But
                    the mind of Pausistratus, prepossessed by misplaced confidence and vain hopes,
                    caused these things not to be attended to as true. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Polyxenidas, having fully adjusted all his measures, having
                    called in the rowers from Magnesia, and launched hastily the ships that were in
                    dock, by night, after wasting the day not so much in preparation as because he
                    was unwilling that <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> the fleet should be seen
                    going to sea, set sail after sun-set with seventy decked ships, and, the wind
                    being contrary, put into the harbour of Pygelia before daylight. Where when he
                    had rested during the day, for the same reason as before, he passed over in the
                    night to the nearest part of the Samian territory. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> From this place, having ordered a certain Nicander, a chief
                    pirate, to sail with five decked ships to Palinurus, and thence to lead his
                    armed men by the shortest road through the fields towards Panor- <pb n="1667"
                        xml:id="p.1667"/> mus, and so to come behind the enemy; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> he himself, in the mean time, with his fleet in two
                    divisions, in order that it might command the mouth of the harbour on both
                    sides, proceeded to Panormus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Pausistratus was
                    at first confused for a little, as the thing was unexpected; but afterwards,
                    being an old soldier, having quickly regained his courage, and judging that the
                    enemy would be more easily repelled by land than by sea, he marched his armed
                    forces in two bodies to the promontories, which, by their heads projecting into
                    the deep, formed the harbour; under the impression that he could easily repel
                    the enemy by weapons on both sides, from the two promontories. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When the sight of Nicander on the land had disconcerted
                    this undertaking, having suddenly changed his design, he ordered all to go on
                    board the ships. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then truly a great confusion
                    arose among soldiers and sailors alike, and a sort of flight to the ships took
                    place, when they perceived themselves surrounded by land and sea at the same
                    time. Pausistratus supposed that the only way of safety was to force through the
                    narrow entrance of the port, and push out into the open sea; and after that he
                    saw his men embarked, ordering the rest to follow, he himself the first, with
                    ship urged vigorously by the oars, pressed to the mouth of the harbour.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Just as his ship was clearing the
                    entrance, Polyxenidas, with three quinqueremes, surrounded it. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The vessel, shattered by their beaks, sunk; the crew were
                    overwhelmed with weapons, and, among them, Pausistratus, fighting gallantly, was
                    slain. Of the rest of the ships, some were taken outside of the harbour, some
                    within, and others by Nicander, while they were putting off from the shore.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Only five Rhodian and two Coan ships
                    effected an escape, a passage being made for them through the thick of the
                    enemy, by the terror of shining flames; for they carried before them, on two
                    poles projecting from their prows, a great quantity of fire contained in iron
                    vessels. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The galleys of Erythrae, after
                    meeting not far from Samos the Rhodian ships, then flying, which they were
                    coming to succour, bore away to the Romans in the direction of the Hellespont.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> About the same time, Seleucus got
                    possession of Phocaea by treachery, one gate being opened by the sentinels.
                    Cyme, with the other cities on that coast, revolted to him through fear. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these events are taking place in
                    Aeolis, after <pb n="1668" xml:id="p.1668"/> Abydos, which was defended by a
                    garrison of the king's troops, had sustained a siege of several days, all
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> parties then grew weary of the struggle,
                    and the magistrates, with the permission of Philotas, the commander of the
                    garrison, began to treat with Livius, concerning the terms on which they should
                    surrender the city. Because they could not agree whether the king's troops
                    should march out with their arms, or without them, this question protracted the
                    matter. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the intelligence of the
                    destruction of the Rhodians interrupted them, treating of these things, the
                    matter was dropped. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For Livius, fearing lest
                    Polyxenidas, elated by his recent success in such an important enterprise, might
                    surprise the fleet which lay at Canae, instantly abandoned the siege of Abydos
                    and the guard of the Hellespont, and drew out the ships that were in dock at
                    Canae, and Eumenes came to Elaea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Livius, with
                    the whole fleet, to which he had joined two triremes of Mitylene, sailed to
                    Phocaea; but, having learned that this place was held by a strong garrison of
                    the king's troops, and that the camp of Seleucus was not far distant, he ravaged
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the sea-coast, hastily conveying on
                    board the booty, which consisted chiefly of men, and waiting only until Eumenes,
                    with his fleet, came up, he endeavours to reach Samos. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Among the Rhodians, the news of their misfortune excited,
                    at first, both consternation, and the greatest grief, at the same time. For,
                    besides the loss of their ships and soldiers, they had lost the flower and
                    strength of their youth; many young men of distinction having been induced,
                    among other motives, by the character of Pausistratus, which was deservedly very
                    high among his countrymen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Afterwards, because
                    they had been circumvented by treachery, and by a countryman of their own, above
                    all men, their grief was changed into anger. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    They sent out ten ships immediately, and, in a few days, ten more, Eudamus being
                    commander of all; who, though far inferior to Pausistratus in warlike
                    qualifications, they supposed would be a more cautious leader, as he was not of
                    so high a spirit. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Romans, and king
                    Eumenes, put in their fleet, first, at Erythrae; and, having staid there one
                    night, they, on next day, reached Corycus, a promontory in Teios. When they
                    intended to pass over hence, to the nearest part of the Samian territory;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> not waiting for the rising of the sun,
                    from which the pilots could learn the state of the weather, they exposed
                    themselves to the varying storm. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> About the
                    middle <pb n="1669" xml:id="p.1669"/> of the passage, the wind changing from
                    north-east to north, they began to be tossed about on the sea, stormy with
                    billows. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas, taking it for granted that the
                    enemy would go to Samos to join the Rhodian fleet, set sail from Ephesus, and
                    stopped first at Myonnesus, from whence he crossed over to the island which they
                    call Macris; in order that, when the enemy's fleet should sail by, he might be
                    able to attack, with advantage, either any ships that straggled from the main
                    body, or might attack the rear of the fleet itself. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> After that he saw the fleet dispersed by the storm, first
                    of all he thought this a good opportunity to attack it; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> but, in a little time, the wind increasing and raising a
                    heavy sea, because he could not possibly come up with them, he steered to the
                    island of Aethalia, that, from thence, he might next day fall on the ships, as
                    they made for Samos, from the main sea. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A
                    small number of Roman vessels, just as it grew dark, got into a desert harbour
                    on the Samian coast; the rest, after being tossed about all night, ran into the
                    same harbour. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then when it was learned from
                    the country people, that the enemy's fleet lay at Aethalia, a consultation was
                    held whether they should attack them immediately, or wait for that of the
                    Rhodian fleet. The attack being deferred, for so they resolved, they sailed away
                    to Corycus, whence they had come. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas
                    also, having kept his station for some time, without effecting any thing,
                    returned to Ephesus. On this the Roman ships, the sea being clear of the enemy,
                    sailed to Samos. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Rhodian fleet came to the
                    same place after a few days. And that it might appear that they were only
                    waiting for this, they immediately sailed away to Ephesus, that they should
                    either decide it in a naval contest, or, in case the enemy should decline a
                    battle, to extort from them a confession of fear, which would have the best
                    effect on the minds of the states of Asia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    They lay opposite the entrance of the harbour, with the fleet formed in a line
                    abreast of it, but none came out against them; the fleet being divided, one part
                    lay at anchor before the mouth of the harbour, the other landed a body of
                    soldiers. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Andronicus, a Macedonian, who was in
                    garrison at Ephesus, then made a sally against them, driving off great booty
                    from the widely-deserted country; when they came near the walls, he stripped
                    them of the greatest part of their <pb n="1670" xml:id="p.1670"/> plunder, and
                    drove them down to the shore and their ships. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    On the day following, the Romans, having laid an ambuscade about the middle of
                    the way, marched in a body to the city, in order to entice the Macedonians out
                    of the gates. Then, when that same fear had deterred any one from coming out,
                    the Romans returned to their ships. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And the
                    enemy avoiding a contest by land or sea, the fleet sailed back to Samos, whence
                    it came. The praetor then detached two Rhodian triremes, and two belonging to
                    the Italian allies, under the command of Epicrates, a Rhodian, to guard the
                    strait of Cephallenia. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hybristas, a
                    Lacedaemonian, at the head of a band of young Cephallenians, infested it with
                    piracies; and the passage was shut against the convoys from Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Epicrates met, at Piraeeus, Lucius, Aemilius
                    Regillus, who was on his way to take the command of the fleet. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> On hearing of the defeat of the Rhodians, as he had only
                    two quinqueremes, he carried back with him to Asia Epicrates and his four ships.
                    Some undecked vessels of the Athenians followed him. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He crossed the Aegean Sea to Chios. To which place came, in
                    the middle of the night, Timasicrates, a Rhodian, with two quadriremes from
                    Samos, and, being presented to Aemilius, he told him that he was despatched for
                    the purpose of convoying him in safety, because the king's ships, by frequent
                    excursions from the Hellespont and Abydos, rendered the sea on that coast
                    dangerous to transports. Two Rhodian quadriremes met Aemilius on his passage
                    from Chios to Samos, being sent by Livius to attend him, and king Eumenes with
                    two quinqueremes met him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Aemilius, after he
                    arrived at Samos, as soon as he had received the command of the fleet from
                    Livius, and duly performed the usual sacrifices, called a council. Here, Caius
                    Livius, whose opinion was first asked, said, that <quote> no one could give
                        advice with more sincerity than he, who recommended to another what himself
                        would do in the same case. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That he had
                        intended to sail with the whole fleet to Ephesus; to take with him ships of
                        burden, heavily laden with ballast, and to sink them in the entrance of the
                        harbour. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the narrow passage might be
                        shut up with less difficulty on this account, because the mouth of the port
                        was like a river, long and narrow, and full of shoals. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> By this expedient he was about to cut off the enemy's
                        communication with the sea, and render their fleet useless. </quote>
                    <pb n="1671" xml:id="p.1671"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This plan was not approved by any of the
                    council. King Eumenes asked, <quote> What then? when, by sinking the ships, they
                        should have barred the pass to the sea, their own fleet being at liberty,
                        would they depart from the place to bear aid to the allies, and strike
                        terror into their enemies? or whether, with no less ardour, they would block
                        up the port with their whole force? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For,
                        if they should withdraw, who could doubt that the enemy would weigh up the
                        masses that were sunk, and open the port with less labour than it had cost
                        to shut it? But if, after all, they were to remain there, what advantage
                        would accrue from the harbour being closed? <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Nay, on the contrary, the enemy enjoying a safe haven, and an opulent
                        city, furnished, at the same time, with every thing from Asia, would pass
                        the summer at their ease, while the Romans, exposed in the open sea to winds
                        and waves, and in want of every accommodation, must continue on guard,
                        without intermission; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and would be
                        themselves tied down, and hindered from doing any thing that ought to be
                        done, rather than to keep the enemy shut up. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Eudamus, commander of the Rhodian fleet,
                    rather showed his disapprobation of the plan proposed, than proposed himself
                    what he thought should be done. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Epicrates, the
                    Rhodian, advised, <quote> not to think of Ephesus for the present, but that a
                        part of the fleet should be sent to Lycia, and that Patara, the metropolis
                        of that nation, should be brought into a treaty of alliance. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> This would conduce to two important purposes:
                        first, the Rhodians, owing to peace being established in the countries
                        opposite to their island, could apply the whole of their strength to the
                        care of the war against Antiochus; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and
                        then the fleet which the enemy were fitting out in Lycia, would be blocked
                        up, and prevented from joining Polyxenidas. </quote> This plan influenced
                    the most. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, it was determined that
                    Regillus should sail, with the entire fleet, to the harbour of Ephesus, to
                    strike terror into the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Caius Livius was sent to Lycia, with two Roman
                    quinqueremes, four Rhodian quadriremes, and two open vessels of Smyrna; being
                    ordered to proceed, first, to Rhodes, and to communicate all his designs to the
                    government there. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The states which he passed
                    in his way, Miletus, Myndus, Halicarnassus, Cnidus, and Cous, diligently
                    executed his orders. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he came to Rhodes,
                    he explained, to the persons in authority, the business on which he was sent,
                    and, at the same <pb n="1672" xml:id="p.1672"/> time, desired their opinion. All
                    approving his design, and three quadriremes being added to that fleet which he
                    had, he set sail for Patara. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The wind being
                    favourable at first, carried them very near the city, and they were in hopes of
                    effecting something by surprise. After that, the wind veering, the sea had begun
                    to roll in heavy waves, they persevered at their oars until they reached the
                    land; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but there was no safe anchorage there,
                    nor could they ride in the road, as the sea was rough, and night was coming on.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They, therefore, sailed past the city, to
                    the port of Phœnicus, which was not quite two miles distant, and which afforded
                    shelter from the violence of the waves, but high cliffs overlooked it, which the
                    towns-people, joined by the king's troops which were in garrison, immediately
                    seized. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Livius, though the landing-places were
                    rugged and difficult, sent against them a party of the auxiliaries, composed of
                    Issaeans, and light infantry of Smyrna. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These
                    (whilst they were skirmishing with missile weapons, and in slight attacks on the
                    few who were there at first, rather than engaging in battle) supported the
                    contest sufficiently well. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After that greater
                    numbers flocked thither from the city, and at length, the whole multitude
                    pouring <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> out, fear seized Livius, not only
                    that the auxiliaries might be cut off, but that the ships would be in danger
                    from the land. In consequence he led out to the engagement, not only the
                    soldiers, but the marines, and even the crowd of rowers, armed with such weapons
                    as each could find. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After all, however, the
                    fight was doubtful; and, besides a considerable number of soldiers, Lucius
                    Apustius fell in this disorderly combat. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At
                    last, the Lycians were routed, and driven within their gates; and the Romans,
                    with a bloody victory, returned to their ships. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> They then proceeded to the gulf of Telmissus, which washes Caria on one side,
                    and Lycia on the other, where all thoughts of any further attempt on Patara were
                    laid aside, the Rhodians were sent home, and Livius, sailing along the coast of
                    Asia, crossed over to Greece, that he might have a meeting with the Scipios, who
                    were <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> at that time in Thessaly, and then
                    take his passage to Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aemilius, although he himself had been driven
                    off from Ephesus by a storm, and had returned to Samos without effecting any
                    thing, after he knew that the expedition to Lycia was dropped, and that Livius
                    had gone to <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Italy, having thought <pb
                        n="1673" xml:id="p.1673"/> it disgraceful that Patara should be attacked in
                    vain, resolved to go thither and attack the city with his utmost force.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Having sailed past Miletus, and the rest
                    of the coast of the allies, he made a descent in the bay of Bargyllae, with the
                    design of reducing Jassus. A garrison of the king's troops held the city, and
                    the Romans made hostile depredations on all the country round. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He then sent persons to confer with the magistrates and
                    principal inhabitants, and sound their' dispositions. After they answered that
                    nothing was in their power, he advanced to lay siege to the city. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> There were, with the Romans, some exiles from Jassus,
                    who, in a body, earnestly importuned the Rhodians <quote> not to suffer an
                        unoffending city, which was as well a neighbouring one as also connected
                        with them in consanguinity, to be ruined. They themselves were banished for
                        no other cause than their faithful attachment to the Romans; and those who
                        remained in the place were held in subjection by the same force by which
                        they had been expelled. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The wish of the
                        people of Jassus was one, to escape from a state of slavery under the king. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Rhodians, moved by their entreaties, and
                    calling in the assistance of king Eumenes, by representing, at the same time,
                    their own connexions with them, and also the unfortunate condition of the city,
                    which was kept in bondage by the king's garrison, prevailed on Aemilius to drop
                    the siege. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Departing hence, and coasting along
                    the shore of Asia, the other places being at peace, they arrived at Loryma, a
                    port opposite to Rhodes. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Here, at
                    head-quarters, a private conversation arises first among the tribunes of the
                    soldiers, and afterwards reached the ears of Aemilius, that the fleet was going
                    off to a distance from Ephesus, from the war which concerned themselves; so that
                    the enemy, being left behind, without control, might safely make whatever
                    attempts they pleased against so many states of the allies, in their
                    neighbourhood. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These remarks moved Aemilius;
                    and calling the Rhodians to him, he asked them, whether the whole fleet could
                    lie in the harbour of Patara: when they answered that it could not, furnished
                    with an excuse for laying aside the design, he sailed back to Samos. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time Seleucus, son of Antiochus,
                    who had <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> kept his army in Aetolia, through
                    the whole of the winter employed, partly, in succouring his allies, partly, in
                    ravaging the <pb n="1674" xml:id="p.1674"/> lands of those whom he could not
                    seduce to his side, resolved to make an incursion on the territory of king
                    Eumenes, while he, at a great distance from home, was assisting the Romans and
                    Rhodians, in attacks on the maritime parts of Lycia. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He advanced with hostile standards, first, to Elaea;
                    afterwards, the design of besieging it being given up, having wasted the country
                    in a hostile manner, he led his army to lay siege to Pergamus, the capital and
                    principal fortress of the kingdom. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Attalus, at
                    first, posting advanced guards outside the city, and sending out parties of
                    cavalry and light infantry, harassed rather than withstood the enemy. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> But, after some time, having discovered, in slight
                    skirmishes, that he was not a match for the enemy in any respect, he drew back
                    his men within the fortifications, and then the city began to be besieged.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About this time, Antiochus, leaving Apamea
                    with a vast army compounded of various nations, encamped first at Sardis, and
                    afterwards took post at a small distance from the camp of Seleucus, at the head
                    of the river Caicus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The most formidable part
                    of his force was a body of four thousand Gauls, procured for hire: these, with a
                    few others intermixed, he detached, with orders to waste utterly the country
                    about Pergamus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When news of these
                    transactions arrived at Samos, Eumenes being thus recalled by a war in his own
                    dominions, sailed with his fleet to Elaea; and finding there, in readiness, some
                    light troops of horse and foot, he took them for an escort, and proceeded
                    directly to Pergamus, before the enemy could be apprised of his arrival, or
                    could put themselves in motion. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then again
                    skirmishes began to take place in the sallies, Eumenes undoubtedly shrinking
                    from the risk of a decisive engagement. In a few days after the combined fleet
                    of the Romans and Rhodians came from Samos to Elaea, to support the king.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When information was brought to Antiochus
                    that these had landed troops at Elaea, and that so many fleets were assembled in
                    one harbour, and at the same time heard that the consul, with his army, was
                    already in Macedonia, and that the things that were necessary for the passage of
                    the Hellespont were being prepared, he judged that now was the time for
                    negotiation, before he should be pressed on sea and land at once; <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> and with this view he chose for his camp a rising
                    ground opposite to Elaea. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Leaving there all
                    the infantry, with his cavalry, amounting to six thousand, he <pb n="1675"
                        xml:id="p.1675"/> went down into the plains, which lay under the walls of
                    the town, having despatched a herald to Aemilius, to acquaint him that he wished
                    to treat of peace. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aemilius sent to Pergamus for Eumenes, and
                    desiring the Rhodians to be present, held a council on the message. The Rhodians
                    were not averse to a pacification; but Eumenes affirmed that <quote> it was not
                        honourable to treat of peace at that time, nor could an end be put to the
                        thing. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For, </quote> said he, <quote> how
                        can we, shut up as we are, within our walls, and besieged, with honour
                        accept terms of peace? Or to whom shall that treaty be valid, which we shall
                        conclude, without the presence of the consul, without a vote of the senate,
                        and without an order of the Roman people? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        For, let me ask, supposing the matter concluded by you, would you
                        immediately go home to Italy, and carry away your fleet and army, or would
                        you wait to know the consul's determination on the case; what the senate
                        should decree, or the people order? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It
                        remains therefore that you must stay in Asia, that your troops being led
                        back again into winter quarters, the war being given over, must exhaust the
                        allies in furnishing provisions; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and then,
                        if it seem fit to those who have the power of determining, we must begin the
                        whole war anew, which we are able, with the aid of the gods, to finish
                        before winter, if no relaxation from our present vigorous movements is made
                        by delay. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This opinion prevailed; and the answer given
                    to Antiochus was, that they could not treat of peace before the arrival of the
                    consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Antiochus, peace being tried for in
                    vain, ravaged, first, the territory of Elaea, then that of Pergamus; and,
                    leaving there his son Seleucus, marched in a hostile manner to Adramyttium,
                    whence he proceeded to a rich tract of country called the Plain of Thebes, a
                    city celebrated in one of Homer's poems; and in no other place in Asia did the
                    king's soldiers find such a plenty of booty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    At the same time, Aemilius and Eumenes also, sailing round with the fleet, came
                    to Adramyttium, to protect the city. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By chance, at this time, one thousand foot
                    with one hundred horse came to Elaea from Achaia, Diophanes being commander of
                    all these forces; whom, on their landing, persons, sent by Eumenes to meet them,
                    conducted by night to Pergamus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Veterans they
                    all were, well skilled in war; and their commander was a disciple of Philopœmen,
                        <pb n="1676" xml:id="p.1676"/> the most consummate general among the Greeks
                    in that age. They set apart two days to give rest to the men and horses, and, at
                    the same time, to view the posts of the enemy, and to learn at what places, and
                    what times, they advanced and retired. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    king's troops generally approached to the foot of the hill on which the town
                    stands; so that the plundering in the rear was unimpeded, as not a man ever
                    sallied out, even to throw darts from a distance, against their guards.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After that they were once driven in, and
                    with fear confined themselves within the walls, a contempt for them arises among
                    the king's troops, and consequently negligence. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The greater number did not keep their horses either saddled or bridled; while
                    few remained under arms, and in the ranks; the rest, slipping away, had
                    scattered themselves every where over the entire plain, some diverting
                    themselves with youthful sports and amusements, others eating in the shade, and
                    some even stretched on the ground asleep. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Diophanes, having observed all these particulars from the lofty city of
                    Pergamus, ordered his men to take arms, and to be ready at a particular gate. He
                    himself went to Attalus, and told him that he intended to attack the outposts of
                    the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Attalus giving his consent with
                    reluctance, as he saw that one hundred horse must fight against six hundred, one
                    thousand foot against four thousand, Diophanes then marched out of the gate, and
                    took post at a small distance from the enemy's guard, waiting his opportunity.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Both the people in Pergamus thought that
                    it was madness rather than daring, and the enemy, after observing his party for
                    a short time, as soon as they saw no movement among them, did not change their
                    usual negligence, ridiculing moreover the smallness of their number. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Diophanes for a long time kept his men quiet, as if
                    they had been brought out merely for the purpose of looking about them; but as
                    soon as he perceived that the enemy had quitted their ranks, ordering the
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> infantry to follow as fast as they
                    could, he himself, with his own troop, led the way at the head of the cavalry,
                    and pushing on, with all possible speed, made a sudden charge on the enemy's
                    party, while a shout was raised by every horseman and footman at once.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Not only were the men so attacked
                    terrified, but the horses also; and when they broke their collars, they caused
                    great confusion and tumult throughout. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A few
                    of the horses, indeed, stood unaffrighted; but even these <pb n="1677"
                        xml:id="p.1677"/> the troopers could not easily saddle, or bridle, or mount;
                    for the Achaeans struck much greater terror than would be supposed from so small
                    a party of horse. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But now the infantry, in
                    due order and preparation, assailed the enemy, dispersed through their own
                    negligence, and almost half asleep; and slaughter and flight ensued in every
                    part of the plain. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Diophanes pursued the
                    runaways as far as he could with safety, and then returned into garrison, after
                    acquiring very great honour for the Achaean nation; for not only the men, but
                    also the women, had been spectators from the walls of Pergamus. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next day the enemy's guard, in more regular
                    and orderly condition, pitched their camp five hundred paces farther from the
                    city, and the Achaeans marched out at nearly the same time as before, and to the
                    same place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During many hours, both parties
                    intently awaited the assault, as if it were about to take place immediately.
                    When it was not far from sun-set, the usual time of their returning to the main
                    camp, the king's troops, forming in close order, began to retire in a body,
                    arranged for a march rather than for a battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Diophanes did not stir until they were out of sight; and then he rushed on their
                    rear-guard with the same vehemence as before, and again excited such dismay and
                    confusion, that, though the hindmost were put to the sword, not one of them
                    halted to fight; they were driven into their camp in confusion, and scarcely
                    observing any order in their march. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These
                    daring exertions of the Achaeans obliged Seleucus to decamp, and quit the
                    territory of Pergamus. Antiochus, having learned that the Romans and Eumenes
                    were come to protect Adramyttium, made no attempt on that city, but ravaged the
                    country adjoining. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He afterwards reduced
                    Peraea, a colony of Mityleneans; Cotton, Corylenus, Aphrodisias, and Crene, were
                    all taken at the first assault. He then returned through Thyatira to Sardis.
                    Seleucus, remaining on the sea-coast, was a terror to one party, a protection to
                    the other. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman fleet, with Eumenes and
                    the Rhodians, retired, first to Mitylene, and then to Elaea, whence they had set
                    out. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On their way to Phocaea, they put in at
                    an island called Bachius; it is near the city of Phocaea; and when they had
                    plundered the temples and statues, which they had before spared, (for the island
                    was surpassingly adorned with them,) they then passed over to the city.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they, having divided the <pb n="1678"
                        xml:id="p.1678"/> quarters among themselves, assaulted it, and saw that it
                    could not be taken by arms and scaling-ladders, without regular works;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> after that a reinforcement of three
                    thousand soldiers, sent by Antiochus, had got into the city, they immediately
                    broke up the siege, and the fleet retired to the island, without having effected
                    any thing more than the devastation of the enemy's country in the neighbourhood. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was then resolved that Eumenes should
                    return home, and make every necessary preparation for the passage of the consul
                    and his army over the Hellespont; and that the Roman and Rhodian fleets should
                    sail back to Samos, and remain stationed there, that Polyxenidas might not make
                    any movement from Ephesus. The king returned to Elaea, the Romans and Rhodians
                    to Samos. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There, Marcus Aemilius, brother of
                    the praetor, died. After his obsequies were performed, the Rhodians sailed, with
                    thirteen of their own ships, one Coan, and one Cnidian quinquereme, to Rhodes,
                    in order that they might take up a position there, against a fleet which was
                    reported to be coming from Syria. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Two days
                    before the arrival of Eudamus and the fleet from Samos, another fleet of
                    thirteen ships, under the command of Pamphilidas, had been sent out against the
                    same Syrian fleet; and taking with them four ships, which had been left to
                    protect Caria, they relieved from blockade Daedala, and several other fortresses
                    of Peraea, which the king's troops were besieging. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It was determined that Eudamus should put to sea directly,
                    and an addition of six undecked ships was made to his fleet. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He accordingly set sail; and using all possible expedition,
                    overtook the first squadron at a port called Magiste, from whence they proceeded
                    in one body to Phaselis, resolving to wait there for the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Phaselis stands on the confines of Lycia and
                    Pamphylia; it projects far into the sea, and is the first land seen by persons
                    coming from Cilicia to Rhodes, and from hence ships can be seen at a great
                    distance. For this reason, chiefly, this place was made choice of, that they may
                    lie in the way of the enemy's fleet. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But in
                    consequence of the unwholesomeness of the place, and of the season of the year,
                    (for it was now the middle of summer,) and of the unusual stench, diseases began
                    to spread with violence, particularly among the rowers, an event which they did
                    not foresee. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And having <pb n="1679"
                        xml:id="p.1679"/> left the place from fear of this pestilence, when they
                    were sailing by the Pamphylian bay, their fleet putting into port <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> at the river Eurymedon, they hear from the people
                    of Aspendus, that the enemy are now at Sida. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The king's fleet had been the slower in its passage, the season of the Etesiae
                    being opposed to them, for this is the periodical time for the northwest winds.
                    The Rhodians had thirty-two quadriremes and four triremes. In the king's fleet
                    were thirty-seven ships of the larger rates; among which were three of seven,
                    and four of six banks of oars; and besides these, ten triremes. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> They discovered too, from some watch-tower, that the
                    Rhodians were at hand. Both fleets, at the dawn of the next day, moved out of
                    port, as if resolved to come to an immediate engagement; and, as soon as the
                    Rhodians passed the promontory that stretches into the deep from Sida, they
                    descried the enemy, and were observed by them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    On the king's side, Hannibal had the command of the left squadron, which
                    stretched away seaward; Apollonius, one of the nobles, had the command of the
                    right, and they had their ships already formed in a line a-head. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The Rhodians approached in a long line. First was the
                    admiral's ship, with Eudamus in it; Chariclitus brought up the rear; and
                    Pamphilidas commanded the centre division. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    When Eudamus saw the enemy's line formed and ready for battle, he pushed out
                    towards the main, ordering the ships that followed to form, regularly, as they
                    came up, in line of battle. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This caused
                    confusion at first; for he had not stretched out to the main far enough for the
                    line of all the ships to form in the direction of the land, and he himself
                    hurrying on with precipitation, with only five ships, engaged with Hannibal; the
                    rest, having received orders to form their line, did not come up. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The rear division had no room left for it next to
                    the land; and, while they were in disorder, the fight was already begun on the
                    right against Hannibal. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the goodness of their ships, and the
                    expertness of their men in nautical business, quickly freed the Rhodians from
                    all embarrassment. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They pushed out hastily
                    towards the main, and each made room next the land for the one immediately
                    behind; and when any made a stroke with its beak against a ship of the enemy, it
                    either shattered its prow, or swept off its oars; or passing by it in the clear
                    space <pb n="1680" xml:id="p.1680"/> between the vessels, made an attack on its
                    stern. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> One of the king's seven-banked ships
                    being sunk with one stroke, by a Rhodian vessel of much smaller size,
                    discouraged them very much. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Therefore the
                    right wing of the enemy was now undoubtedly verging to flight. Hannibal, in the
                    open sea, by means chiefly of his superior number of ships, pressed hard on
                    Eudamus, who surpassed him in every other respect: and he would have surrounded
                    him were it not that, on the signal being given from the admiral's fleet, (by
                    which it is usual to collect together the fleet when dispersed,) all the ships
                    which had conquered on the right wing came speedily to bear aid to their own
                    party. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This made Hannibal himself, with all
                    his division, betake themselves to flight; while the Rhodians could not pursue,
                    because their rowers being most of them sick, were therefore the sooner wearied.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they were recruiting their strength
                    with food on the sea where they brought to, Eudamus, observing the enemy towing,
                    by means of their open vessels, several damaged and crippled ships, and seeing
                    little more than twenty that were going off uninjured, commanded silence from
                    the castle of the commander's ship, and then called out, <quote>Arise, and feast
                        your eyes with an extraordinary sight.</quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They all started up, and perceiving the
                    disorderly flight of the enemy, cried out, almost with one voice, that they
                    ought to pursue. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Eudamus's ship was bulged in
                    many places; he therefore ordered Pamphilidas and Chariclitus to pursue as far
                    as they should think it safe. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They,
                    accordingly, pursued for a considerable time: but after that Hannibal make-in
                    close to the land, fearing to be wind-bound on an enemy's coast, they steered
                    back to Eudamus, and with difficulty towed to Phaselis a captured seven-banked
                    ship, which had been damaged in the beginning of the engagement. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> They then sailed home to Rhodes, not so much
                    exulting in their victory as blaming one another because the entire fleet had
                    not been taken or sunk, when it could have been done. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal, disheartened by the loss of this one battle, did
                    not even then dare to sail past the coast of Lycia, though he wished to join the
                    king's main fleet as soon as possible. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And
                    that this action might not be unimpeded, the Rhodians sent Chariclitus with
                    twenty ships of war to Patara and the harbour of Megiste. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> They then ordered Eudamus, with seven of the largest
                    vessels belonging to the fleet which he had com- <pb n="1681" xml:id="p.1681"/>
                    manded, to rejoin the Romans at Samos, and to endeavour by every argument, and
                    by all his influence, to prevail on the Romans to besiege Patara. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now first of all the intelligence of the
                    victory, and subsequently the arrival of the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    Rhodians, caused great joy to the Romans, and it appeared to them that if that
                    anxiety was taken away from the Rhodians, they would when at leisure render the
                    seas of that country safe. But the march of Antiochus from Sardis did not allow
                    them to quit the guard of Ionia and Aeolia, lest the maritime cities should be
                    crushed by his arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, they sent
                    Pamphilidas, with four decked ships, to join the fleet which was at Patara.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Antiochus not only collected aids from the
                    states that lay around, but also sent to Prusias, king of Bithynia, ambassadors
                    and letters, in which he inveighed against the pressing of the Romans into Asia.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>They were coming,</quote> he said, <quote> to abolish all kingly
                        governments; so that there should be no empire in any part of the world,
                        save that of Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Philip and Nabis were
                        subdued: he was the third object of attack. Thus the conflagration would
                        spread, without interruption, from one to another, as each lay nearest to
                        the one last ruined, until it enveloped them all. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> From him there was but one step to Bithynia, now that
                        Eumenes had submitted to voluntary servitude. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Though Prusias was greatly affected by these
                    observations, his mind was relieved from all such doubts by a letter from
                    Scipio, the consul, and still more so by one from his brother Africanus, who,
                    besides urging the invariable practice of the Roman people of augmenting, by
                    every honourable addition, the grandeur of kings in alliance with them, by
                    instances taken from his own family, induced Prusias to earn their friendship.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>The petty chieftains in Spain,</quote> he said, <quote> who had been
                        received into alliance, he had left kings. Masinissa he had not only
                        re-established in his father's kingdom, but had put him in possession of
                        that of Syphax, by whom he had been formerly dethroned: <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> so that he was, at the present, not only by far the
                        most powerful of all the kings in Africa, but equal, both in dignity and
                        strength, to any monarch in any part of the world. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Philip and Nabis, avowed enemies, were conquered in war
                        by Titus Quintius; nevertheless, they were left in possession of their
                        kingdoms. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Philip even had the tribute
                        remitted to him last year, and his son, who was a <pb n="1682"
                            xml:id="p.1682"/> hostage, restored. Through the indulgence of the Roman
                        commanders, he had also got possession of several states beyond the
                        boundaries of Macedonia. As to Nabis, he might have remained in the same
                        honourable rank, had not first his own madness, and afterwards the treachery
                        of the Aetolians, brought him to ruin. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The king's resolution was especially
                    confirmed after that Caius Livius, who had commanded the fleet as praetor, came
                    to him as ambassador from Rome, and informed him how much better hope the Romans
                    had of success than Antiochus; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and how much
                    more sacred and lasting an alliance with them would be. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Antiochus, after he lost the hope of an
                    alliance with Prusias, went from Sardis to Ephesus, to review the fleet which
                    was fitted out, and lay there ready, for several months; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> rather because he saw it impossible, with his land forces,
                    to make any stand against the Roman army and its commanders, the two Scipios,
                    than that his naval force by itself had ever been tried by him successfully, or
                    afforded at this juncture any great or well-grounded confidence. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Yet there was an incentive to hope on the present
                    occasion; for he had heard that a large portion of the Rhodian fleet was at
                    Patara, and that king Eumenes had gone to the Hellespont, with all his ships, to
                    meet the consul. Besides, the destruction of the Rhodian fleet at Samos, on an
                    opportunity prepared by treachery, inspired some degree of confidence.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Relying on these things, he sent
                    Polyxenidas with orders to try, at all events, the fortune of a naval
                    engagement; while he himself marched his land forces to Notium. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This town, which belongs to Colophon, stands close to the
                    sea, and is distant about two miles from Old Colophon. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He wished to get this city into his power, because it was
                    so near to Ephesus that nothing could be done there, on sea or land, that was
                    not open to the view of the Colophonians, and, through them, instantly made
                    known to the Romans; and he had no doubt that the latter, having heard of the
                    siege, would bring their fleet from Samos to the relief of an ally, which would
                    give Polyxenidas an opportunity of coming to action. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore began to lay regular siege to the city, making
                    his approaches at the same time on the two sides next the sea; in both places he
                    joined his engines and mounds to the wall, and brought up the rams under covered
                    galleries. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1683" xml:id="p.1683"/> By which dangers the Colophonians being
                    terrified, sent en- voys to Lucius Aemilius, at Samos, imploring the protection
                    of the praetor and people of Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> His lying
                    so long inactive at Samos offended Aemilius, thinking nothing more improbable
                    than that Polyxenidas, whom he had twice challenged in vain to fight, should
                    ever offer him battle; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and he considered it
                    as dishonourable, that the fleet of Eumenes should assist the consul in
                    conveying the legions into Asia, that he should be fettered by bearing to the
                    besieged Colophon an assistance destined to have an uncertain end. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Eudamus, the Rhodian, (who had before prevailed upon
                    him to stay at Samos, when he wished to go to the Hellespont,) <milestone
                        n="12??" unit="section"/> with all the other officers, pressed him to
                    comply, representing <quote> how much more eligible it would be, either to
                        relieve confederates <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> from a siege, or
                        to vanquish that fleet which he had vanquished before, and to take from the
                        enemy the entire possession of the sea, than, deserting his allies, and
                        delivering Asia to Antiochus by land and sea, to depart from his own part of
                        the war to the Hellespont, when the fleet of Eumenes was sufficient for that
                        station. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They accordingly, having set sail from Samos
                    in quest of provisions, their stock being consumed, were preparing to pass over
                    to Chios. Samos served as a granary to the Romans, and thither all the
                    store-ships sent from Rome directed their course. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When they had sailed round from the city to the back of the
                    island, which looks northward towards Chios and Erythrae, and were preparing to
                    cross over, the praetor is informed by a letter, that a vast quantity of corn
                    had arrived at Chios, from Italy; but that the vessels laden with wine were
                    detained by storms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the same time accounts
                    were received, that the people of Teos had furnished large supplies of
                    provisions to the king's fleet, and had promised five thousand vessels of wine.
                    On this the praetor immediately changed his course, and steered away to Teos,
                    resolved either to make use of the provisions prepared for the enemy, with the
                    consent of the inhabitants, or to treat them as foes. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> When they had turned their prows to the land, about fifteen
                    vessels appeared in sight near Myonnesus, which the praetor at first supposed to
                    belong to the king's fleet, and hastened to pursue. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> It appeared afterwards, that they were piratical cutters
                    and galleys. They, having ravaged the sea-coast of Chios, re- <pb n="1684"
                        xml:id="p.1684"/> turning with booty of every kind, betook themselves to
                    flight when they saw the fleet on the open sea. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> They had much the advantage in swiftness, their galleys being lighter and
                    constructed for the purpose, and were nearer the land; therefore before the
                    fleet could overtake them, they made their escape to Myonnesus. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And the praetor, unacquainted with the place, followed in
                    expectation of forcing their ships from it out of the harbour. Myonnesus is a
                    promontory between Teos and Samos. It consists of a hill rising from a pretty
                    large base to a sharp top, in the shape of an obelisk. From the land it has
                    access by a narrow path towards the sea, cliffs undermined by the waves
                    terminate it, so that in some places the superimpending rocks project beyond the
                    vessels that lie at anchor. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The ships not
                    daring to approach lest they should be exposed to the weapons of the pirates,
                    who stood above on the cliffs, wasted the day to no purpose. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> At length, after they had desisted from this useless
                    undertaking a little before night, they the next day reached Teos. Here the
                    praetor, after mooring in the port at the back of the city, which the
                    inhabitants call Geraesticum, sent out the soldiers to ravage the land about the
                    city. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Teians, as these ravages passed under
                    their eyes, sent deputies to the Roman commander, carrying fillets, and other
                    badges of suppliants. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And when they were
                    exculpating their state from every hostile act or word against the Romans, he
                    strongly charged them with <quote> having assisted the enemy's fleet with
                        provisions, and with having promised a quantity of wine to Polyxenidas. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He further told them, that <quote> if they
                        would furnish the same supplies to the Roman fleet, he would recall his
                        troops from plundering; otherwise, he would treat them as enemies. </quote>
                    When the deputies carried back this distressing answer, the people were summoned
                    to an assembly by the magistrates, to consult on what they should do. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> It happened that Polyxenidas, who had sailed with the
                    king's fleet from Colophon, after he heard that the Romans had left Samos and
                    pursued the pirates to Myonnesus, and that they were laying waste the lands of
                    the Teians, and that their fleet lay in the harbour of Geraesticus, cast
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> anchor, in a retired harbour of an
                    island called by the sailors Macris, opposite to Myonnesus. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then from his neighbouring position, exploring what his
                    enemies were doing, at first he was in great hopes of van- <pb n="1685"
                        xml:id="p.1685"/> quishing the Roman fleet here, in like manner as he had
                    vanquished the Rhodian at Samos, by besetting the narrow entrance at the mouth
                    of the port. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor is the nature of the place
                    unlike: by the promontories advancing towards each other, the harbour is
                    enclosed in such a manner, that two ships can scarcely go out together.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas intended to seize this narrow
                    pass in the night; and, while ten ships stood at each of the promontories, to
                    attack, from the right and left, both sides of the enemy's fleet sailing out,
                    having landed his armed men from the fleet, as he had done at Panormus, to
                    overpower the Romans on land and sea at once. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    And this design would not have been formed by him in vain, had it not appeared
                    to the Romans better for receiving the provisions, when the Teians had promised
                    to execute their commands, that the fleet should pass into that harbour, which
                    is before the city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It is said, also, that
                    Eudamus, the Rhodian, had pointed out the fault of the outer harbour, when two
                    ships broke their oars locked together in the narrow entrance. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Among other motives, this too induced the praetor to remove
                    his fleet, because there was danger from the land, as Antiochus kept his camp
                    not far from it. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the fleet was brought round to the city,
                    all being ignorant of the approach of the enemy, both soldiers and sailors went
                    on shore to divide the provisions, and the wine particularly, among the ships;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> when, about mid-day, a peasant happened to
                    be brought before the praetor, who told him, that the enemy's fleet was lying at
                    the island of Macris these two days; and that, a little while ago, some of them
                    were observed to be in motion, as if preparing to sail. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Greatly alarmed at this unexpected event, the praetor
                    ordered the trumpets to sound, to call in such as might have straggled into the
                    country, and sent the tribunes into the city, to hasten the soldiers and sailors
                    on board. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The confusion was not less than if
                    the place were on fire, or taken by an enemy; some running to call out the men;
                    others hurrying to the ships, while the orders of the officers were confounded
                    by irregular shouts, amid which the trumpets raised their din, until at length
                    the crowd collected at the ships. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here
                    scarcely could each know his own ship, or make his way through the tumult; and
                    the disorder would probably have been productive of much mischief, on land and
                    sea, had not Aemilius, in the commander's ship, sailed out first <pb n="1686"
                        xml:id="p.1686"/> into the main; where, receiving those following, he put
                    each into its own place, so as to form a line abreast: <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and Eudamus, with the Rhodian fleet, waited at the shore,
                    that the men might be embarked without confusion, and that every ship might
                    leave the harbour as soon as it was ready. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By
                    these means, the foremost division formed under the eye of the praetor, while
                    the rear was brought up by the Rhodians; and then the whole line, in as regular
                    order as if within sight of the foe, advanced into the open sea. They were
                    between Myonnesus and the promontory of Corycus, when they first got sight of
                    the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The king's fleet, which was coming
                    in a long line, with only two vessels abreast, then formed themselves in order
                    of battle, stretching out their left division so far, as that it might enclose
                    the right of the Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When Eudamus, who
                    commanded in the rear, perceived that the Romans could not form an equal front,
                    but were just on the point of being surrounded, he pushed up his ships. They
                    were Rhodians, by far the fastest sailers of any of the fleet; and having filled
                    up the deficiency in the extent of the line, he opposed his own ship to the
                    commander's, on board of which was Polyxenidas. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now the entire fleets in every part were
                    engaged in action. On the side of the Romans eighty ships were fighting, of
                    which twenty-two were Rhodian. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The enemy's
                    fleet consisted of eighty-nine ships, and they had of the largest rates, three
                    of six, and two of seven banks. In the strength of the vessels, and valour of
                    the soldiers, the Romans had greatly the advantage of the king's party, as had
                    the Rhodians in the activity of their vessels, the skill of the pilots, and the
                    dexterity of the rowers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, those which
                    carried fire before them were the greatest terror to the enemy: and what was the
                    sole cause of their preservation when they were surrounded at Panormus, proved
                    here the principal means of victory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For when
                    the king's ships, through fear of the fire, had turned aside, in order to avoid
                    at the same time encountering the enemy's prow with their own, they could not
                    strike their antagonist with the beaks, but exposed the side of their ships to
                    his strokes; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and if any did venture an
                    encounter, it was immediately overspread with the fire that was poured in; while
                    the men were more alarmed at the fire than the battle. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> How- ever, the bravery of the soldiers, as is generally the
                    case, <pb n="1687" xml:id="p.1687"/> chiefly availed in deciding the battle. For
                    the Romans, having broke through the centre of the enemy's line, tacked about
                    and fell upon the rear of the division which was engaged with the Rhodians; and,
                    in an instant of time, both Antiochus's centre division, and the ships on the
                    left, were surrounded and sunk. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The squadron
                    on the right, which was still entire, was terrified rather by the disaster of
                    their friends, than by any immediate danger threatening themselves; but, when
                    they saw the others surrounded, and Polyxenidas's ship deserting its associates,
                    and sailing away, having quickly hoisted their topsails, they betook themselves
                    to flight, (and they steering for Ephesus had a favourable wind,) having lost
                    forty-two ships in that battle; of which thirteen struck, and fell into the
                    hands of the Romans; the rest were burned or sunk. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Two Roman ships were shattered, and several were much
                    damaged. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> One Rhodian vessel was taken by an
                    extraordinary casualty; for, on its striking a Sidonian ship with its beak, its
                    anchor, thrown out by the force of the shock, caught fast hold of the other's
                    prow with its fluke, as if it were a grappling-iron thrown in. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Great confusion ensuing thereon, when the Rhodians, who
                    wished to disengage themselves from the enemy, pulled back, its cable being
                    dragged forcibly, and at the same time entangled with the oars, swept off one
                    side of them. The very ship, which, when struck, had grappled with it, took the
                    Rhodian galley in its weakened state. The naval battle at Myonnesus was fought
                    principally in this manner. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By which Antiochus being terrified, because,
                    as he was driven from the possession of the sea, he despaired of being able to
                    defend his distant possessions, ordered the garrison to be withdrawn from
                    Lysimachia, which plan was ill devised, as the event subsequently proved, lest
                    it should be there cut off by the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As
                    it was easy for him, not only to defend Lysimachia from the first attack of the
                    Romans, but to protract the siege through the whole winter; and by thus
                    prolonging the time, to reduce the besiegers to the extremity of want; and in
                    the mean time try the hope of peace, as opportunities should present themselves.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But, after the defeat at sea, he not only
                    gave up Lysimachia, but even raised the siege of Colophon, and retired to
                    Sardis. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here, bending all his thoughts to one
                    single object, that of meeting the enemy in <pb n="1688" xml:id="p.1688"/> the
                    field, he sent into Cappadocia, to Ariarathes, to request assistance, and to
                    every other place within his power, to collect forces. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Aemilius Regillus, after his victory at sea, proceeded to
                    Ephesus, having drawn up his ships before the harbour, when he had extorted from
                    the enemy a final acknowledgment of their having surrendered the dominion of the
                    sea, sailed to Chios, to which he had directed his course from Samos, before the
                    sea-fight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as he had refitted the
                    ships that had been damaged in the battle, he sent off Lucius Aemilius Scaurus,
                    with thirty others, to the Hellespont, to transport the army; and decorating the
                    Rhodian vessels with naval spoils, and allowing them a part of the booty, he
                    ordered them to return home. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Rhodians
                    energetically took the lead, and proceeded to assist in transporting the
                    consul's forces, and when they had completed that service also, then at length
                    returned to Rhodes. The Roman fleet sailed from Chios to Phocaea. This city
                    stands at the bottom of a bay, and is of an oblong shape. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The wall encompasses a space of two miles and a half in
                    length, and then contracts on both sides into a very narrow wedge-like form,
                    which place they call Lampter (or the light-house). The breadth here extends one
                    thousand two hundred paces; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and a tongue of
                    land stretching out about a mile into the sea, divides the bay nearly in the
                    middle, as if with a line; where it is connected with the main land by a narrow
                    isthmus, it has two very safe harbours, turned to each side. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The one that fronts the south they call Naustathmos, (the
                    station for ships,) from the circumstance of its being capable of containing a
                    vast number of ships; the other is close to Lampter. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Roman fleet had taken possession of
                    these very safe harbours, the praetor thought proper, before he attempted the
                    fortifications, either by escalade or works, that persons should be sent to
                    sound the disposition of the magistrates and principal people in the place: when
                    he saw them obstinate, he determined to attack the city in two places at the
                    same time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One part was thinly occupied by
                    private dwellings, temples of the gods occupying a great deal of the ground.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In that part first, having brought up the
                    battering-ram, he began to shake the wall and towers; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and when the multitude within ran thither to defend that
                    spot, the battering-ram, were applied in the other quarter, and the walls <pb
                        n="1689" xml:id="p.1689"/> were now knocked down in both places. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> On the fall of which, when some of the Roman soldiers
                    were making an assault over the scattered masses of ruins, others attempted to
                    scale walls; the townsmen made such an obstinate resistance, as plainly showed
                    that they had a firmer dependence on their arms and courage, than on their
                    fortifications. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The praetor, compelled by the
                    danger of the soldiers, sounded a retreat, that he might not expose them
                    incautious to his opponents, maddened with despair and rage. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The fighting being ended, the besieged did not, even then,
                    think of rest; but all hastened from every quarter, to strengthen the walls, and
                    to raise new ones in the place of those that had been demolished. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> While they were busily employed in this manner,
                    Quintus Antonius, being sent by the praetor, came to them, who, after having
                    blamed their obstinacy, assured them that <quote> the Romans were more anxious
                        than they were themselves that the battle should not be carried on to the
                        destruction of the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If they would
                        desist from their madness, Aemilius would allow them to capitulate on the
                        same terms on which they had formerly surrendered to Caius Livius. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When they heard this, having taken five days'
                    time to deliberate, and having in the mean time tried the hope of aid from
                    Antiochus, after that the ambassadors sent to the king had brought back word
                    that there was no aid in him, they opened their gates, stipulating that they
                    should suffer nothing hostile. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When the
                    troops were marching into the city, and the praetor had proclaimed that it was
                    his pleasure that the surrendered townsmen should be spared, there arose an
                    universal clamour, <quote> that it was shameful that the Phocaeans, who had
                        never been faithful to any alliance, and had always been bitter in enmity,
                        should escape with impunity. </quote> After which words, as if a signal had
                    been given by the praetor, they ran, in parties, every way, to plunder the city.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Aemilius, at first, began to resist, and
                    call them back, saying, that <quote> towns taken by storm, and not such as
                        surrendered, were plundered; and that, even with regard to the former, the
                        determination lay with the commander, not with the soldiers. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But rage and avarice were too strong for his
                    authority; wherefore, despatching heralds through all parts of the city, he
                    ordered, that all persons of free condition should come to him in the forum,
                    that they should not be injured: and in all things which were in his power, the
                        <pb n="1690" xml:id="p.1690"/> promise of the praetor was observed.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He restored to them their city, their
                    lands, and their laws; and, as the winter now approached, he chose the harbour
                    of Phocaea for his fleet to pass the winter in. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time it was announced to the
                    consul, as he was marching along the frontiers of the Aenians and Maronites,
                    that the king's fleet was conquered at Myonnesus, and that Lysimachia was
                    evacuated by its garrison. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This latter event
                    gave much more satisfaction than even the success at sea; especially after they
                    came thither, and were hospitably received in the city, filled with provisions
                    of all sorts, as if provided for the arrival of the army; when, in besieging the
                    city, they had anticipated extreme want and hardship. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There they made a halt for a few days, that the baggage and
                    sick might overtake them, who, overcome by diseases, or the length of the way,
                    had been left behind in all the forts of Thrace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> When all had joined, they began again their march through the Chersonese, and
                    arrived at the Hellespont; where every thing requisite for their passage having
                    been previously got ready, by the care of king Eumenes, they crossed over,
                    without confusion, as if to friendly shores, no one opposing, and the ships
                    putting in at several different places. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This
                    raised to a high degree the spirits of the Romans, who saw the passage into Asia
                    left open to them; which thing they supposed would cost them a severe struggle.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They afterwards remained encamped a
                    considerable time at the Hellespont, because it happened to be a period too holy
                    for marching, during which the sacred shields are moved. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The same festival had separated Publius Scipio from the
                    army, as the religious ceremony was more incumbent on him, because he was one of
                    the Salian priests; and he himself was a source of delay, till he overtook the
                    rest of the army. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time an ambassador came from
                    Antiochus to the camp, —Heraclides, a Byzantian, having mandates concerning
                    peace. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The delay and tardiness of the Romans
                    gave him great hope that this might be attained; for he had imagined, that as
                    soon as they set foot in Asia, they would advance in a rapid march against the
                    king. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He resolved, however, not to address
                    himself to the consul until he had first applied to Publius Scipio, and
                    instructions to that effect were given him by the king. In him he had the
                    greatest <pb n="1691" xml:id="p.1691"/> hope, besides that his greatness of
                    soul, and the fulness of his glory, tended very much to make him inclined to
                    peace, and <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> it was known to all nations what
                    sort of a conqueror he had been, both in Spain and afterwards in Africa; and
                    also because his son was then a prisoner with Antiochus. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Where, and when, and by what accident he became a prisoner,
                    is, like very many other things, not ascertained among writers. Some say, that
                    in the beginning of the war, as he was going from Chalcis to Oreum, he was
                    intercepted by some of the king's ships; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    others, that after the army came into Asia, he was sent with a troop of
                    Fregellans to Antiochus's camp, to gain intelligence; that on the cavalry
                    sallying out against him, he retreated, and having fallen from his horse in the
                    confusion, he was, together with two horsemen, overpowered, and thus conducted
                    to the king. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This however is fully
                    ascertained, that if peace had still subsisted with the Romans, and likewise a
                    personal friendship between the king and the Scipios, the young man could not
                    have been treated and courted with greater kindness than he was. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> When the ambassador, for these reasons, had waited
                    the arrival of Publius Scipio, as soon as he came he applied to the consul, and
                    requested that he should hear his instructions. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A full council being assembled, audience was
                    given to the ambassador, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> who said, that,
                        <quote> though many embassies about peace had already been sent backwards
                        and forwards, without producing any effect, yet he conceived strong hopes of
                        obtaining it, because the former ambassadors had obtained nothing. For the
                        objects of contention in those discussions were Smyrna and Lampsacus,
                        Alexandria in the Troad, and Lysimachia in Europe. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Of these, the king had already ceded Lysimachia, that
                        they might not say that he possessed any thing in Europe; and those cities
                        which lay in Asia, he was now ready to deliver up as well as any others,
                        which the Romans might wish to render independent of the king's government,
                        because they belonged to their party. The king was also willing to pay to
                        the Roman people half the expense of the war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These were the conditions of peace. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The rest of his discourse was, <quote> that, mindful
                        of human affairs, they should use with moderation their own good fortune,
                        and not press too severely on the misfortune of others; that they should
                        limit their empire by Europe; that single acquisitions <pb n="1692"
                            xml:id="p.1692"/> could be made with more ease than that necessary for
                        holding them collectively. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But if they
                        would wish to take away some part of Asia, provided <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> that they would define it by indisputable limits, the
                        king, for the sake of peace and harmony, would willingly suffer his own
                        moderate temper to be overcome by the insatiableness of the Romans. </quote>
                    These concessions, which appeared to the ambassador of great moment towards
                    obtaining a peace, the Romans deemed trifling. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    They thought it just, that <quote> the king should defray the whole expense
                        occasioned by the war, because it was through his fault that it was begun.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And that, not only Ionia and Aeolia
                        ought to be evacuated by the king's troops, but as all Greece had been set
                        free, so all the cities of that nation in Asia should also be free.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That this could be effected in no
                        other way, than by Antiochus relinquishing the possession of that part of
                        Asia on the hither side of Mount Taurus. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassador, after he came to the
                    conclusion that lie could obtain no reasonable terms in the council, tried to
                    influence the mind of Publius Scipio in private (for such were his orders).
                    First of all he told him that the king would restore him his son without a
                    ransom; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and then, as ignorant of the
                    disposition of Scipio as he was of the Roman manners, he promised an immense
                    weight of gold, and, excepting the title of king, an absolute partnership in the
                    sovereignty, if through his means he should obtain a peace. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To which Scipio answered, <quote> I am the less surprised
                        that you are ignorant of the Romans in general, and of me, to <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> whom you have been sent, when I see that you
                        are unacquainted with the situation even of the person from whom you come.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You ought to have kept Lysimachia to
                        prevent our entering the Chersonese, or to have opposed us at the Hellespont
                        to hinder our passing into Asia, if you meant to ask peace from us as from
                        people solicitous about the issue of war. But after leaving the passage into
                        Asia open, and receiving not only a bridle, but also a yoke, what
                        negotiation on an equality has been left you, when you must submit to
                        orders? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I shall consider my son as a very
                        great gift from the munificence of the king; I pray to the gods that my
                        circumstances may never require others, my mind certainly never will require
                        any. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For such an act of generosity to me
                        he shall find me grateful, if for a personal favour he will accept a
                        personal <pb n="1693" xml:id="p.1693"/> return of gratitude. In my public
                        capacity, I will neither accept from him nor give him any thing. All that I
                        can give at present is sincere advice. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Go
                        then, and desire him in my name, to cease hostilities, and to refuse no
                        terms of peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These words had no effect on the king, who
                    thought that the chance of war would be comparatively safe, since terms were
                    dictated to him already as if he were totally vanquished. Laying aside,
                    therefore, for the present, all farther mention of peace, he turned his whole
                    attention to the preparations for war. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul having made every preparation for
                    the execution of his designs, when he had quitted the post where he lay, marched
                    first to Dardanus, and then to Rhœteum; from both states the people came out in
                    crowds to meet him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He then advanced to Troy,
                    and having pitched his camp in the plain which is under the walls, when he had
                    gone up to the city and into the citadel, he offered sacrifices to Minerva, the
                    guardian of the citadel; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the Trojans, by every
                    act and expression of respect, showing themselves proud of the Romans being
                    descended from them, and the Romans expressing their delight in their origin.
                    The army marching thence, arrived, on the sixth encampment, at the source of the
                    Caicus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To this place also king Eumenes came.
                    He at first endeavoured to bring back his fleet from the Hellespont to Elaea,
                    for the winter; subsequently, when by adverse winds he could not, for several
                    days, pass the promontory of Lectos, that he might not be absent at the
                    commencement of operations, he landed and came, with a small body of men, by the
                    shortest road to the Roman camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From the camp
                    he was sent home to Pergamus, to hasten supplies of provisions; and when the
                    corn was delivered to the persons whom the consul had ordered to receive it, he
                    returned to the same camp. The plan was, provisions for several days being
                    prepared, to march hence against the enemy, before the winter should prevent
                    them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The king's camp was near Thyatira; and
                    Antiochus, hearing there that Publius Scipio had fallen sick and was conveyed to
                    Elaea, sent ambassadors to conduct his son to him. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As this present was highly grateful to the mind of the
                    father, so was the satisfaction which it gave no less salutary to his body.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At length, being sated with the em- braces
                    of his son, he said to the ambassadors, <quote> Tell the king <pb n="1694"
                            xml:id="p.1694"/> that I return him thanks; that at present I can make
                        him no other requital than my advice; which is, not to come to an
                        engagement, until he shall have heard that I have rejoined the army. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Although sixty-two thousand foot, and more
                    than twelve thousand horse, inspired the king at times with hopes in the result
                    of a battle; yet, moved by the advice of so great a man as Scipio, in whom, when
                    he considered the uncertainty of the events of war, he placed safety in any
                    reverse of fortune, he retired, and having crossed the Phrygian river, pitched
                    his camp near Magnesia, which is at Sipylus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And lest, if he wished to prolong the time, the Romans might attack his works,
                    he drew round it a fosse six cubits deep and twelve broad, and on the outside
                    surrounded the fosse with a double rampart: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    on the inside bank, he raised a wall flanked with towers at small distances, by
                    which the enemy could easily be prevented from crossing the fosse. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, thinking that the king was still
                    in the neighbourhood of Thyatira, came down by continued marches on the fifth
                    day into the Hyrcanian plains. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then when he
                    heard that the other had departed, he followed his track, and pitched his camp
                    on the hither side of the Phrygian river, at the distance of four miles from the
                    enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here, a body of about one thousand
                    horse, (the greatest part of whom were Gallograecians, the rest Dahans, and
                    archers on horseback, of other nations intermixed,) passing the river with great
                    tumult, made an attack on the advanced Roman guards. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> First of all they threw into confusion those unprepared;
                    then, when the contest continued longer, and the number of the Romans increased,
                    as succours were easily sent from the neighbouring camp, the king's troops,
                    becoming weary and unable to withstand superior numbers, endeavoured to retreat;
                    but, before they could reach the river, very many were killed on the bank, by
                    the enemy pressing on their rear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For two days
                    after there was quiet, neither party passing the river. On the third, the Romans
                    passed it with their whole force, and encamped at the distance of about two
                    miles and a half from the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While they
                    were employed in measuring and fortifying the camp, a body of the king's troops,
                    consisting of three thousand chosen horse and foot, approached with great
                    rapidity and violence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The party on guard,
                    though much inferior in number, (being only two thousand,) without <pb n="1695"
                        xml:id="p.1695"/> calling off any of the soldiers from the fortifying of the
                    camp, sustained the combat with equal success at first, and, in the progress of
                    the contest, repulsed the enemy, killing a hundred, and taking about the same
                    number. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During the four ensuing days, both
                    armies stood in order of battle, before their respective camps. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> On the fifth, the Romans advanced into the middle of the
                    plain, but Antiochus did not stir; so that his rear was not so far as a thousand
                    feet from his rampart. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, after perceiving that he declined
                    the contest, called a council next day, and asked their opinion, <quote> how he
                        ought to act if Antiochus would not give him an opportunity of engaging.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For the winter was at hand, and he
                        must either keep the soldiers in camp; or, if they chose to retire to winter
                        quarters, defer the business of the war until summer. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans never despised any enemy so much.
                    The assembly on every side called on him to lead on immediately, and make use of
                    the present ardour of the troops; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> who, as if
                    the business were not to fight against so many thousands, but to slaughter an
                    equal number of cattle, were ready to force their way, through trenches and
                    ramparts, into the camp, if the enemy would not come out to battle. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Cneius Domitius was sent to discover the nature of
                    the ground, and on what side the enemies' rampart could be approached; after he
                    returned with a full account of every particular, it was resolved that the camp
                    should next day be moved nearer to the enemy. On the third day, the standards
                    were carried forward into the middle of the plain, and the soldiers began to
                    form line. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Antiochus, thinking that he could
                    hesitate no longer, lest, by declining a battle, he should damp the courage of
                    his men, and add to the confidence of the enemy, drew out his forces in person,
                    advancing only so far from the enemy's camp as to make it apparent that he was
                    willing to come to an engagement. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Roman
                    line was nearly uniform throughout with respect to both men and armour. There
                    were two Roman legions, and two brigades of allies and Latins, each containing
                    five thousand four hundred men. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Romans
                    formed the centre, the Latins the wings. The spearmen com- posed the first line,
                    the first-rank men the second, and the veterans closed the rear. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Beyond this, which formed as it were the regular line
                    of battle, the consul formed on the <pb n="1696" xml:id="p.1696"/> right of it,
                    and in one continued line, the auxiliary troops of Eumenes, intermixed with
                    Achaean targeteers, making about three thousand foot; beyond these he posted
                    somewhat less than three thousand horse, of which, eight hundred belonged to
                    Eumenes; all the rest of the cavalry were Roman: <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and in the extremity of the line he placed bodies of
                    Trallians and Cretans, equal in number, who were composed of five hundred men
                    each. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> His left wing did not appear to require
                    such supports, because a river and steep banks flanked it. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> However, four troops of horse were posted there. This was
                    the whole amount of the Roman force, besides two thousand Macedonians and
                    Thracians, who had, as volunteers, accompanied the army. These were left to
                    guard the camp. They placed sixteen elephants behind the veterans, in reserve.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For besides that they were not supposed
                    capable of withstanding the great number of the king's elephants, which were no
                    less than fifty-four, the African elephants are not able to cope with an equal
                    number of Indians, either because they are inferior to them in size, (in which
                    the Indian have much the advantage,) or in unyielding courage. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king's line was more chequered with troops
                    of many nations, dissimilar both in their persons and armour. There was a body
                    of sixteen thousand men armed after the manner of the Macedonians, which were
                    called a phalanx. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This formed the centre, and
                    was divided in front into ten parts. These parts were separated by two elephants
                    placed between each two; the line of soldiers was thirty-two ranks deep from
                    point to rear. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This was the main strength of
                    the king's army, and it exhibited a formidable sight, both in the other
                    particulars of its appearance, and in the elephants towering so high among the
                    soldiers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were of huge bulk, and the
                    caparisons of their foreheads and crests, and the towers fixed on their backs,
                    with four armed men standing on each tower, besides the managers of the beasts,
                    gave them a terrific appearance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the right
                    side of the phalanx, he placed five hundred Gallograecian horsemen. To these he
                    joined three thousand horsemen clad in complete armour, whom they call
                    Cataphracti, or mailed. To these were added a brigade of near a thousand horse,
                    which they called Agema. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were Medes, all
                    picked men, with a mixture of horsemen from many other nations in that part of
                    the world. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Adjoining <pb n="1697"
                        xml:id="p.1697"/> these, a body of sixteen elephants was placed in reserve.
                    On the same side, a little farther on towards the wing, was the royal cohort;
                    these were called Argyraspides, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Silver
                        shield-bearers.</note> from the kind of armour which they wore. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Next to these stood one thousand two hundred Dahan
                    bowmen on horseback; then, three thousand light infantry, part Cretans and part
                    Trallians, the number of each being equal; adjoining these, were two thou- sand
                    five hundred Mysian archers. Four thousand Cyrtaean slingers and Elymaean
                    archers mixed together covered the flank of the wing. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Next to the left flank of the phalanx, stood one thousand
                    five hundred Gallograecian horse, and two thousand Cappadocians, (which were
                    sent by king Ariarathes,) wearing the same kind of armour; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> then, auxiliaries of all kinds mixed together, two thousand
                    seven hundred; then, three thousand mailed horsemen; then, one thousand other
                    horsemen, being a royal cohort, equipped with lighter coverings for themselves
                    and their horses, but, in other respects, not unlike the rest; they were mostly
                    Syrians, with a mixture of Phrygians and Lydians. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> In the front of this body of cavalry were the chariots
                    armed with scythes, and a kind of camels called dromedaries. These were ridden
                    by Arabian archers, who carried thin swords four cubits long, that they might be
                    able to reach the enemy from so great a height. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> Then followed another multitude, like that in the right wing, —first,
                    Tarentines; then, two thousand five hundred Gallograecian horsemen; then, one
                    thousand new Cretans, and one thousand five hundred Carians and Cilicians, armed
                    in the same manner; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> then, an equal number of
                    Trallians, with three thousand targeteers (these were Pisidians, Pamphylians,
                    and Lycians); then came brigades of Cyrtaeans and Elymaeans, equal to the
                    auxiliaries placed on the right wing, and sixteen elephants, separated by a
                    small interval. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The king himself was in the
                    right wing; the command of the left he gave to his son Seleucus, and Antipater,
                    the son of his brother; the centre was intrusted to three, Minio, Zeuxis, and
                    Philip, the master of the elephants. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A morning mist, which as the day advanced rose
                    up in clouds, spread a general darkness; and the moisture issuing from it, and
                    coming from the southward, wetted every thing. This circumstance, which was
                    scarcely any inconvenience to <pb n="1698" xml:id="p.1698"/> the Romans, was
                    very disadvantageous to the king's troops. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For
                    the indistinctness of the light did not take away from the Romans the view of
                    all parts of their line, since it was of moderate length; and the moisture
                    tended but little to blunt their swords and javelins, as they were almost all
                    heavy-armed troops. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The king's soldiers, as
                    the line was so extensive, could not even see their wings from the centre, much
                    less could those at the extremities see one another; and then, the moisture
                    relaxed the strings of their bows, their slings, and the thongs of their
                    javelins. Besides, the armed chariots, by means of which Antiochus had trusted
                    utterly to disorder the enemy's line, turned the terror of their operations on
                    their owners. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The manner in which they were
                    armed was this: from the yoke, on both sides of the pole, they had lances <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The difficulty, which Scheffer,
                        Crevier, and Drakenborch apparently had, in interpreting this passage with
                        the reading <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> (decem cubita), seems to me to
                        have arisen principally from their misinterpretation of the word cuspis;
                        which in the classics is no where used as the edge of a cutting, but the
                        point of a piercing instrument —differt a mucrone, quae est acies gladii.
                        —Facciolati. That the cuspides, here spoken of, must have been piercing,
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> not cutting instruments, is likewise
                        proved from the meaning of the word <quote>transfigerent,</quote> which is
                        never used in reference to a cutting instrument. Taking it for granted,
                        then, that the <quote>cuspitibus decem cubita</quote> were spears ten feet
                        long, fastened to the pole and extended from the yoke, I can easily
                        understand how <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> they, being so long, were
                        likely to clear the way far in front of the horses, while the
                            <quote>falces</quote> on either side were intended to cut down those
                        that escaped the cuspides; and this being the case, I see no necessity for
                        Scheffer's reading, <quote>cubito,</quote> which Crevier also seems to
                        favour, and Drakenborch's <quote>duo</quote> for <quote>decem;</quote> both
                        of which seem to have been adopted, owing to the seeming improbability of
                        cutting weapons so long, and proportionably heavy, being attached to the
                        poles of chariots. </note> ten cubits <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    long, projecting like horns, to transfix any thing that came in their way. At
                    each extremity of the yoke, two scytheblades projected, one on a line with the
                    yoke, the other on its lower side, pointing to the ground; the former to cut
                    through any thing that might come within its reach on <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> the side, the other to catch such as fell, or endeavoured
                    to go under it. At each extremity of the axle of the wheels, two scythe-blades
                    were fastened in the same manner. The king, as we mentioned before, had placed
                    the chariots so armed in the front, because if they were placed in the rear, or
                    between the ranks, they must be driven through their own soldiers. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Which when Eumenes saw, not being ignorant of the
                    method of op- <pb n="1699" xml:id="p.1699"/> posing them, and knowing that aid
                    of that sort might be rendered as dangerous to one side as the other, if an
                    opponent should cast terror into the horses, rather than attack them in a
                    regular battle, ordered the Cretan bowmen, and slingers, and javelin-bearers,
                    with some troops of horse, not in a body, but scattering themselves as widely as
                    possible, to rush forwards, and pour weapons on them from all sides at once.
                    This storm, as it were, partly by the wounds made by the missile <milestone
                        n="11??" unit="section"/> weapons thrown from every quarter, and partly by
                    the discordant shouts raised, so terrified the horses, that immediately, as if
                    unbridled, they galloped about at random. The light infantry, the
                    lightly-accoutred slingers, and the active Cretans, quickly evaded their
                    encounter. The horsemen, following them, increased the tumult and the terror of
                    the horses and camels, which were likewise affrighted, the clamour being
                    multiplied and increased by the rest of the crowd of bystanders. By these means,
                    the chariots were driven <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> out of the ground
                    between the two lines. When this fruitless mimicry of war was over, both parties
                    gave the signal, and advanced to a regular engagement. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But that futile affair was soon the cause of
                    real loss. For the auxiliaries in reserve, which were posted next, being
                    terrified at the turn and disorder of the chariots, betook them- selves to
                    flight, leaving all exposed as far as the post of the mailed horsemen;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> to whom when the Roman cavalry, after
                    dispersing the reserves, approached, they did not sustain their first onset.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some fled, and others, being delayed by
                    the weight of their coverings and armour, were put to the sword. The whole left
                    wing then gave way, and the auxiliaries, posted between the cavalry and the
                    phalanx, being thrown into confusion, the terror spread even to the centre.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here the ranks were broken, and by the
                    flying soldiers rushing in between them, the use of their long spears, called by
                    the Macedonians sarissas, was hindered. The Roman legions advanced and
                    discharged their javelins among them in disorder. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Even the elephants, standing in the way, did not deter the
                    Roman soldiers, who had learned by experience in the African wars, both to evade
                    the onset of the animal, and, getting at one side of it, either to ply it with
                    darts, or, if they could come near enough, to wound its sinews with their
                    swords. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The front of the centre was now almost
                    crushed, and the reserve, being surrounded, <pb n="1700" xml:id="p.1700"/> was
                    attacked on the rear, when the Romans perceived their troops in another quarter
                    flying, and heard shouts of dismay almost close to their camp. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> For Antiochus, who commanded the right wing, having
                    observed that the enemy, through confidence in the river, had placed no reserve
                    there, except four troops of horse, and that these, keeping close to the
                    infantry, left an open space on the bank of the river, made a charge on them,
                    with a body of auxiliaries and mailed horsemen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> He not only attacked them in front, but having surrounded the wing in the
                    direction of the river, pressed them in flank also; until the routed cavalry
                    first, and then the infantry that were next them, fled with precipitation to the
                    camp. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Aemilius, a military tribune, son of
                    Marcus Lepidus, who, in a few years after, became chief pontiff, had the charge
                    of the camp. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He, when he saw the troops
                    flying, went out, with his whole guard, to meet them. He ordered them, first, to
                    halt, and then to return to the fight; at the same time upbraiding them with
                    cowardice and disgraceful flight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then
                    proceeded to threats, —that if they did not obey his orders, they would rush
                    blindly on their own destruction. At last he gave orders to his own men to kill
                    the foremost of the runaways, and with sword-wounds to drive the crowd of
                    fugitives back against the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The greater
                    fear now overcame the less. Compelled by the danger on either side, they first
                    halted, and then returned to the encounter, and Aemilius, with his guard,
                    consisting of two thousand men of distinguished valour, gave a vigorous check to
                    the furious pursuit of Antiochus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At the same
                    time, Attalus, the brother of Eumenes, came up in good time with two hundred
                    horse from the right wing, by which the left of the enemy had been routed, at
                    the beginning of the engagement, as soon as he observed the flight of his
                    friends on the left, and the tumult near the camp. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When Antiochus saw those men renewing the fight, whom, but
                    just before, he had seen running away, and another large body advancing from the
                    camp, with a third from the line, he turned his horse to flight. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The Romans, thus victorious in both wings, advanced
                    over heaps of slain, (which had been raised principally in the centre, where the
                    strength of the bravest men and the armour by its weight had prevented flight,)
                    to plunder the camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The horsemen of <pb
                        n="1701" xml:id="p.1701"/> Eumenes first, and then the rest of the cavalry,
                    pursued the enemy through all parts of the plain, and killed the hindmost as
                    they overtook them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the fugitives suffered
                    more severe loss by the chariots, elephants, and camels intermixed, and by their
                    own disorderly crowd; for, after they once broke their ranks, they rushed, as if
                    blind, one upon another, and were trodden to death by the trampling of the
                    beasts. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the camp also there was great
                    slaughter committed, rather greater than even in the field; for the flight of
                    the first generally tended to the camp. The guard, through confidence in the
                    great number of these, defended their works with the more obstinacy. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The Romans having been stopped at the gates and
                    rampart, which they had expected to take at the first rush, when they did at
                    length break through, actuated by rage, made the more dreadful carnage. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Up to fifty thousand foot and three thousand
                    horse are said to have been killed that day; one thousand four hundred taken,
                    with fifteen elephants and their drivers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of
                    the Romans, many were wounded, but no more than three hundred foot and
                    twenty-four horsemen killed; and of the troops of Eumenes, twenty-five.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That day the victors, after plundering the
                    enemy's camp, returned with great store of booty to their own. On the day
                    following, they stripped the bodies of the slain, and collected the prisoners.
                    Ambassadors came from Thyatira and Magnesia, near Sipylus, with a surrender of
                    those cities. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Antiochus fled, with very few
                    attendants; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but greater numbers collecting
                    about him on the road, he arrived at Sardis, with a tolerable body of soldiers,
                    about the middle of the night. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then when he
                    heard that his son Seleucus and several of his friends had gone on to Apamea, he
                    likewise at the fourth watch set out for Apamea with his wife and daughter,
                    having committed to Zeno the command of the city, and having placed Timon over
                    Lydia; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> which being disregarded, ambassadors
                    are sent to the consul, by the unanimous voice of the citizens and soldiers who
                    were in the garrison. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time deputies came from Tralles,
                    from Magnesia on the Maeander, and from Ephesus, to surrender those cities.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Polyxenidas had quitted Ephesus, as soon
                    as he heard of the battle; and, sailing with the fleet as far as Patara, in
                    Lycia, where, through fear of the Rhodian fleet stationed at <pb n="1702"
                        xml:id="p.1702"/> Megiste, he landed, and, with a small retinue, pursued his
                    journey, by land, into Syria. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The several
                    states of Asia placed themselves under the protection of the consul and the
                    dominion of the Roman people. He was now at Sardis, whither Publius Scipio came
                    from Elaea, as soon as he was able to endure the fatigue of travelling.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Shortly after, a herald from Antiochus
                    solicited through Publius Scipio, and obtained from the consul, permission for
                    the king to send ambassadors. In a few days' time, Zeuxis, who had been governor
                    of Lydia, and Antipater, the king's nephew, arrived. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> These, having first had a meeting with Eumenes, whom they
                    expected to find most averse to peace, on account of old disputes, and
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> seeing him better disposed than they or
                    the king could have hoped, addressed themselves then to Publius Scipio, and
                    through him to the consul: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and a numerously
                    attended council being granted to them at their request to declare their
                    commission, Zeuxis said, <quote> we have not any thing to propose ourselves, but
                        rather to inquire from you, Romans, by what atonements we can expiate the
                        error of our king, and obtain pardon and peace from our conquerors. You have
                        ever pardoned, with the greatest magnanimity, vanquished kings and nations.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With how much greater and more
                        placable spirit ought you to act now, after your late victory, which has
                        made you masters of the whole world! You ought now, like deities laying
                        aside all disputes with mortal beings, to protect and spare the human race. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It had been determined, before the ambassadors
                    came, what answer should be given them; and it was agreed that Africanus should
                    deliver it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He is said to have spoken thus:
                        <quote> Of those things that are in the gift of the immortal gods, we,
                        Romans, possess as much as the gods have been pleased to bestow. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> In every state of fortune we have had, and have,
                        the same spirit for this, under the sway of our reason: prosperity has never
                        elated, nor adversity depressed it. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Of
                        the truth of this, (to omit other instances,) I might produce your friend
                        Hannibal as a convincing proof: but I can appeal to yourselves. We now
                        conquerors offer to you conquered the same conditions which we offered to
                        you when on an equal footing, at the time that you made proposals <milestone
                            n="13??" unit="section"/> of peace, after we crossed the Hellespont,
                        before we beheld the king's camp or army, when the chance of war was equal
                        and the issue uncertain. Resign all pretensions in Europe, and cede that
                        part of Asia which <pb n="1703" xml:id="p.1703"/> lies on this side of Mount
                        Taurus. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then, towards the expenses of the
                        war, ye shall pay fifteen thousand talents of Eubœa; <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> About 2,900,000 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                        </note> five hundred immediately, two thousand five hundred when the senate
                        and people of Rome shall have ratified the peace, and one thousand annually
                        for twelve years after. It likewise pleases us, that four hundred talents be
                        paid to Eumenes, and the quantity of corn remaining unpaid, of what was due
                        to his father. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When we shall have settled
                        these articles, it will be a sort of pledge, that we may consider it certain
                        that you will perform them, if you give twenty hostages such as we shall
                        choose. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But it never will be clear to us
                        that the Roman people will enjoy peace where Hannibal shall be. Him,
                        therefore, we demand, above all. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Ye shall
                        also deliver up Thoas, the Aetolian, the fomenter of the Aetolian war, who
                        armed you against us by the assurances of their support, and them by
                        assurances of yours; and, together with him, Mnesilochus, the Acarnanian,
                        and Philo, and Eubulidas, of Chalcis. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The
                        king will now make peace under worse circumstances on his side, because he
                        makes it later than he might have done. If he now causes any delay, let him
                        consider, that it is more difficult to pull down the majesty of kings from
                        the highest to the middle stage, than it is to precipitate it from the
                        middle to the lowest. </quote> The ambassadors were sent by the king with
                    these instructions, that they should accede to any terms of peace. <milestone
                        n="19" unit="section"/> It was resolved, therefore, that ambassadors should
                    be sent to Rome. The consul distributed his army in winter quarters at Magnesia,
                    on the Maeander, Tralles, and Ephesus. A few days after, the king brought the
                    hostages to Ephesus to the consul; the ambassadors also, who were to go to Rome,
                    arrived. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Eumenes set out for Rome at the same
                    time with the king's ambassadors, and they were followed by <milestone n="21??"
                        unit="section"/> embassies from all the states of Asia. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these things are being transacted in
                    Asia, two proconsuls arrived almost together at Rome, from their provinces, with
                    hopes of triumphing: Quintus Minucius, from Liguria, and Manius Acilius, from
                    Aetolia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After hearing their services, the
                    senate refused a triumph to Minucius, but, with great unanimity, decreed one to
                    Acilius, and he rode through the city in triumph over king Antiochus and the
                    Aetolians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the procession were carried, two
                    hundred and <pb n="1704" xml:id="p.1704"/> thirty military ensigns; of unwrought
                    silver, three thousand pounds' weight; of coin, one hundred and thirteen
                    thousand Attic tetradrachms; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 14,596
                            <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 16 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 8 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and two hundred and forty-eight thousand <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 4270 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 19 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 9 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> cistophoruses; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A coin so
                        called, from its bearing the image of a priest carrying in a box (cistus)
                        the consecrated things, used in the mysteries of Ceres, and of other
                        deities. Its value, 7 1/2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi> , was <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> equal to four drachmas. </note> of chased silver
                    vessels, a great number, and of great weight. He bore, also, the king's silver,
                    furniture, and splendid wardrobe; golden crowns, presents from the allied
                    states, forty-five; with spoils of all kinds. He led thirty-six prisoners of
                    distinction, generals of the Aetolian and royal armies. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Damocritus, the Aetolian general, a few days before, when
                    he had escaped out of prison in the night, being overtaken by the guards on the
                    bank of the Tiber, stabbed himself with a sword before he was seized. Nothing
                    was wanted but the <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> soldiers, to follow the
                    general's chariot; in every other respect the triumph was magnificent, both in
                    the grandeur of the procession and the fame of his achievements. Sad
                    intelligence from Spain diminished the joy of <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    this triumph, viz. that in an unsuccessful battle in the territory of the
                    Bastitani, under the command of Lucius Aemilius, the proconsul, at the town of
                    Lycon, there fell six thousand of the Roman army against the Lusitanians;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and that the rest, being driven in a panic
                    within their rampart, found it difficult to defend <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> the camp, and had retreated, by forced marches, as if
                    flying, into a friendly country. Such were the accounts from Spain. Lucius
                    Aurunculeius, the praetor, introduced to the senate the deputies of Placentia
                    and Cremona, in Cisalpine Gaul. When they complained of the want of colonists,
                    some having been carried off by the casualties of war, others by sickness, and
                    several having left the colonies, through disgust at the vicinity of the Gauls;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> on this, the senate decreed, that <quote>
                        Caius Laelius, the consul, if he thought proper, should enrol six thousand
                        families, to be distributed <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> among these
                        colonies, and that Lucius Aurunculeius, the praetor, should appoint
                        commissioners to conduct the colonists. </quote> Accordingly, Marcus Atilius
                    Serranus, Lucius Valerius Flaccus, son of Publius, and Lucius Valerius Tappo,
                    son of Caius, were nominated to that office. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not long after, as the time of the consular
                    elections <pb n="1705" xml:id="p.1705"/> drew nigh, the consul, Caius Laelius,
                    came home to Rome from Gaul. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He not only
                    enrolled the colonists, according to a decree of the senate, passed in his
                    absence, as a supplement to Cremona and Placentia, but proposed, —and, on his
                    recommendation, the senate voted, —that two new colonies should be established
                    in the lands which had belonged to the Boians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    At the same time arrived a letter from the praetor, Lucius Aemilius, containing
                    intelligence of the sea-fight that took place at Myonnesus, and of Lucius Scipio
                    the consul having transported his army into Asia. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> A supplication for one day was decreed, on account of the
                    naval victory, and another, for the second day, in order that, as the Roman army
                    had then for the first time pitched a camp in Asia, this circumstance might turn
                    out prosperous and happy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul was
                    ordered to sacrifice twenty of the greater victims on occasion of each
                    supplication. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The election of consuls was then
                    held with a warm contest. Marcus Aemilius Lepidus sought the office under
                    general censure, for having, in order to sue for the office, left his province
                    of Sicily without having asked the senate for permission to do so. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Marcus Fulvius Nobilior, Cneius Manlius Vulso, and
                    Marcus Valerius Messala, were his com- petitors for the office. Fulvius alone
                    was elected consul, since the rest could not make up the number of centuries;
                    and the next day, rejecting Lepidus, (for Messala had declined,) he declared
                    Cneius Manlius his colleague. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then were chosen
                    praetors, two of the name of Quintus Fabius, Labeo and Pictor, (the latter of
                    whom had in that year been inaugurated flamen quirinalis,) Marcus Sempronius
                    Tuditanus, Spurius Posthumius Albinus, Lucius Plautius Hypsaeus, and Lucius
                    Baebius Dives. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias says, that at the time when
                    Marcus Fulvius Nobilior and Cneius Manlius Vulso were consuls, a rumour
                    prevailed strongly at Rome, and was received as almost certain, that <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> the consul, Lucius Scipio, and with him Publius
                    Africanus, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> had been invited by the king to a
                    conference, under pretence of restoring young Scipio, and were both seized, and
                    that when the leaders were thus made prisoners, the enemy's army was immediately
                    led up to the Roman camp, that this was stormed, and the forces entirely cut
                    off; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that in consequence of this, the
                    Aetolians had taken courage and refused to obey orders; and that several of
                    their <pb n="1706" xml:id="p.1706"/> principal men had gone into Macedonia,
                    Dardania, and Thrace, to hire auxiliaries; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    that Aulus Tarentius Varro, and Marcus Claudius Lepidus, had been sent by Aulus
                    Cornelius, proprietor, from Aetolia, to carry this intelligence to Rome.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To this story Valerius annexed that the
                    Aetolian ambassadors were asked in the senate this question among others, from
                    whom they had heard that the Roman generals were made prisoners by king
                    Antiochus in Asia, and the army cut off; and that the Aetolians answered, that
                    they had been informed of it by their own ambassadors, who were with the consul.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As I have no other authority for this
                    report, it has neither been confirmed in my opinion, nor has it been overlooked
                    as groundless. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Aetolian ambassadors were brought to
                    an audience of the senate, although their cause and their circumstances
                    required, that they, by an ample confession, should suppliantly seek pardon for
                    what was either their misfortune <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> or their
                    fault, yet having begun with enumerating their services to the Roman people, and
                    talking reproachfully of their own valour in the war with Philip, they offended
                    the ears of the senators by the insolence of their discourse. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> By calling up old and forgotten matters, they brought the
                    affair to this, that the memory of many more injuries than services done by that
                    nation occurred to the minds of the senate; and that they, who needed
                    compassion, provoked anger and hatred. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They
                    were asked by one senator whether they yielded the disposal of themselves to the
                    Roman people; then, by another, whether they would have the same allies and
                    enemies as the Roman people: when they gave no answer, they were ordered to
                    withdraw from the senate-house. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The whole
                    senate then, almost with one voice, cried out, that <quote> the Aetolians were
                        still entirely devoted to Antiochus; and that on that solitary hope their
                        spirits depended. Wherefore the war ought to be carried on against such
                        decided enemies, and their haughty spirits tamed. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another circumstance inflamed the resentment
                    of the senate, because that, in the very moment in which they were soliciting
                    peace from the Romans, they were making war on Dolopia and Athamania. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> A decree of the senate was passed, on the motion of
                    Manius Acilius, who had defeated Antiochus and the Aetolians, that <quote> the
                        Aetolian ambassadors should be ordered to leave the city that day, and <pb
                            n="1707" xml:id="p.1707"/> to quit Italy within fifteen days. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Aulius Terentius Varro was appointed to escort
                    them on the road; and a threatening notice was given to them, that, <quote> if
                        any embassy from the Aetolians should thenceforth come to Rome, unless with
                        the permission of the general who might be in command of that province, and
                        with a Roman deputy, all such would be treated as enemies. </quote> —In this
                    manner were the Aetolians dis- missed. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls then consulted the senate
                    concerning the provinces; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and it was resolved
                    that they should cast lots for Aetolia and Asia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> To him who should obtain by lot Asia, was assigned the army which Lucius
                    Scipio then had; and, as a reinforcement, four thousand Roman foot and two
                    hundred horse, and of the allies and Latins eight thousand foot and four hundred
                    horse: with which force he was to carry on the war with Antiochus. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> To the other consul was decreed the army in Aetolia;
                    and he was allowed to raise, for a reinforcement, the same number of natives and
                    allies as his colleague. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The same consul was
                    likewise ordered to equip and take with him the ships that had been fitted out
                    the year before; and not only to wage war with the Aetolians, but also to pass
                    over into the island of Cephallenia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Instructions were given to the same consul, that if he could do it to the
                    advantage of the republic, he should come home to Rome to hold the elections;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> for, besides that the annual magistrates
                    were to be replaced, it was resolved that censors also should be created; and if
                    any particular business should detain him, he was then to acquaint the senate,
                    that he could not attend at the time of the elections. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Aetolia fell by lot to Marcus Fulvius; Asia, to Cneius
                    Manlius. The praetors then cast lots, and Spurius Postumius Albinus obtained the
                    city and foreign jurisdiction; Marcus Sempronius Tuditanus, Sicily; Quintus
                    Fabius Pictor, the priest of Romulus, Sardinia; Quintus Fabius Labeo, the fleet;
                    Lucius Plautius Hypsaeus, Hither Spain; Lucius Baebius Dives, Farther Spain.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> One legion, and the squadron which was
                    then in Sicily, were decreed for that province; and it was ordered that the new
                    praetor should levy on the Sicilians two tenths of the corn; one of which he was
                    to send into Asia, the other into Aetolia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It
                    was also ordered, that the same impost should be collected in Sardinia, and the
                    corn sent to the same armies as the Sicilian <pb n="1708" xml:id="p.1708"/>
                    corn. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A reinforcement was given to Lucius
                    Baebius, for Spain, one thousand Roman foot and fifty horse, with six thousand
                    Latin foot and two hundred horse. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To Plautius
                    Hypsaeus, for the Hither Spain, were assigned one thousand Roman foot, and two
                    thousand Latins, with two hundred horse; so that with these supplies the two
                    Spains should have each a legion. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In the case
                    of the magistrates of the preceding year, the command was prolonged to Caius
                    Laelius for a year, with his present army, and to Publius Junius, the proprietor
                    in Etruria, with the army which was then in the province, and Marcus Tuccius,
                    the propraetor in Bruttium and Apulia. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the praetors went into their provinces,
                    a dispute arose between Publius Licinius, chief pontiff, and Quintus Fabius
                    Pictor, priest of Romulus; such as had happened in the recollection of their
                    fathers, between Lucius Metellus and Postumius Albinus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Metellus, who was chief pontiff at the time, had detained,
                    for the performance of the business of religion, Albinus, the consul, who was
                    setting out with his colleague, Caius Lutatius, to the fleet at Sicily;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and now Publius Licinius detained the
                    praetor Fabius from going to Sardinia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    matter was agitated in stormy debates, both in the senate and before the
                    commons: authoritative commands were issued on both sides, pledges were seized,
                    fines imposed, the tribunes applied to, and appeals made to the people.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At last religion prevailed, so that the
                    flamen obeyed the order of the pontiff; and the fines were remitted by order of
                    the people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate by their authority
                    prevented the praetor when attempting to abdicate the magistracy through anger
                    at the loss of his province, and decreed that he should dispense justice among
                    foreigners. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The levies being finished in a few
                    days, (for the soldiers to be enlisted were not many,) the consuls and praetors
                    repaired to their provinces. Then a report of the transactions in Asia spread
                    vaguely without an author; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and in a few days
                    after, certain information, and a letter from the general, arrived at Rome;
                    which occasioned joy, not so much from recent fear, (for they had ceased to fear
                    him who was conquered in Aetolia,) as from former fame; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> because by them commencing this war he was considered as a
                    very formidable enemy, both on account of his own strength and because he had
                    Hannibal to direct the business of the war. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The senate determined that no change should be made <pb n="1709" xml:id="p.1709"
                    /> in their sending the consul into Asia, and that no diminution of his forces
                    should take place through apprehension of a war with the Gauls. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In a short time after, Marcus Aurelius Cotta,
                    deputy from Lucius Scipio, with ambassadors from king Antiochus and king
                    Eumenes, and the Rhodian delegates, arrived at Rome. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Cotta, first in the senate, and then by their order in the
                    assembly of the people, stated the services which were performed in Asia. Then a
                    supplication for three days was decreed, and forty victims of the greater kinds
                    ordered to be sacrificed. Then audience was given first to Eumenes. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> He, when he had briefly returned thanks to the
                    senate, <quote> because they had relieved him and his brother from a siege, and
                        protected his kingdom from the unjust attacks of Antiochus; </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and had congratulated them <quote> because
                        they had carried on affairs successfully by sea and land, and because they
                        had utterly routed, driven out of his camp, and expelled king Antiochus,
                        first from Europe, and then from all Asia on this side of Mount Taurus; </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> then said <quote> he preferred that they
                        should learn his own deserts from their generals and deputies, rather than
                        from his mouth. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All being pleased with his discourse, and
                    desiring him to tell frankly, bashfulness being for the present laid aside,
                        <quote>what recompence he thought proper to be given by the senate and
                        people of Rome;</quote> assuring him that <quote> the senate were inclined
                        to act with greater zeal and more abundant liberality, if possible,
                        according to his deserts. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To this the king answered, <quote> if the
                        choice of rewards were offered him by others, if only permission to consult
                        the Roman senate were given to him, he would have availed himself of the
                        advice of that most noble body, lest he might appear to have been either
                        immoderate in his desires or shameless in his requests. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But now, when they themselves were the donors, it was
                        much more proper that their munificence towards him and his brothers should
                        be regulated by their own judgment. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The senate were not discouraged by this answer
                    from desiring him to speak; and when there had been a long contest of kindness
                    on one side, and reserve on the other, whilst they deferred to one another with
                    a politeness not more mutual than insuperable, Eumenes departed from the
                    senate-house. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The senate persisted in their
                    resolution so far as to say, <quote> that it was <pb n="1710" xml:id="p.1710"/>
                        absurd that the king should not know with what hopes or request he came.
                        That he himself best knew what would be suitable to his own dominions. He
                        was much better acquainted with Asia than were the senate. That he ought to
                        be called back and compelled to state what were his wishes and sentiments.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king, being brought back by the praetor
                    into the senate-house, and desired to speak freely, began thus: <quote>
                        Conscript fathers, I should have persevered in being silent, but that I knew
                        you would presently call in the Rhodian ambassadors, and that when they had
                        been heard, the necessity of speaking would be imposed on me. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> And this my speech will be the more difficult on
                        this account, because their demands will be of such a nature, that they will
                        appear not only to make no demands which may be contrary to my interests,
                        but not even to request any thing which may be intimately connected with
                        themselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For they will plead the cause
                        of the Grecian states, and allege that they ought to be set free; <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> which point being gained, to whom is it doubtful
                        that they will alienate from us not only those states which shall be
                        liberated, but likewise our ancient tributaries; and that after having bound
                        them under so great an obligation, they will keep them under the
                        denomination of allies, in reality subject to their government and entirely
                        at their disposal? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And, if it pleases the
                        gods, while they will aspire to this so great power, they will pretend that
                        this is no way connected with them; they will only say, that it is becoming
                        you and conformable to your past conduct. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        You must be cautious, therefore, lest this speech deceive you; and lest by
                        an unfair distribution, you not only depress some of your allies too much,
                        while you exalt others beyond measure, but also put those who bore arms
                        against you in a better state than your allies and friends. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> As to what regards myself in other cases, I should
                        prefer to appear to any one to have yielded within the limit of my right,
                        rather than to have struggled too obstinately in maintaining it; but in a
                        contest of friendship and good-will towards you, and of the respect to be
                        paid to you, I cannot with any patience bear to be outdone. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This was the principal inheritance that I received from
                        my father; who, of all the inhabitants of Asia and Greece, was the first who
                        embraced your friendship; and this he maintained with <pb n="1711"
                            xml:id="p.1711"/> constant and invariable fidelity to the last hour of
                        his life. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor did he display merely a
                        faithful and kind inclination towards you, but was actively engaged in all
                        the wars which you waged in Greece, whether on land or sea; he aided you
                        with all kinds of provisions in such a manner, that not one of your allies
                        could vie with him in any respect; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and
                        finally, while he was exhorting the Bœotians to an alliance with you, having
                        fainted in the middle of his discourse, he shortly expired. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> In his steps have I trodden; and though I could
                        not surpass the warmth of his wishes, and his zeal in courting your
                        friendship —for <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> these could not be
                        exceeded —yet fortune, the times, Antiochus, and the war waged in Asia,
                        afforded me occasions of surpassing him in real acts and merits, and
                        valuable services. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Antiochus, king of
                        Asia, and of a part of Europe, offered me his daughter in marriage; offered
                        to restore immediately the states that had revolted from us, and gave great
                        hopes of enlarging my dominions, if I would have carried on war in
                        conjunction with him against you. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> I will
                        not boast on this account, because I was guilty of no trespass against you;
                        but I will rather mention those instances of conduct which are worthy of the
                        very early friendship between our house and you. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> I assisted your commanders with forces by land and sea,
                        so that not one of your allies can stand in competition with me. I supplied
                        them with provisions by land and sea. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> I
                        was present in all the naval engagements which are fought in many places;
                        and I never was sparing of my labour and danger. I underwent a siege, the
                        most dreadful suffering that can occur in war, being shut up in Pergamus, in
                        the utmost danger both of my kingdom and of my life. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Afterwards when liberated from the siege, although in
                        one part Antiochus, in another Seleucus, were encamped about the citadel of
                        my kingdom, having deserted my own affairs, I went with my whole fleet to
                        the Hellespont, to meet your consul Lucius Scipio, to assist in transporting
                        his army. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> From the time that the army
                        came over into Asia, I never quitted the consul; no Roman soldier was more
                        regular in his attendance in your camp, than I and my brothers. No
                        expedition, no cavalry action, was undertaken without me. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> In the field I took that post, and I maintained that
                        ground, in which the consul wished me to be. I do not intend, conscript
                        fathers, to say who <pb n="1712" xml:id="p.1712"/> in that war can be
                        compared to me in services towards you. I would not hesitate to compare
                        myself to any of those nations or kings whom you hold in great honour.
                            <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Masinissa was your enemy before he
                        became your ally; <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> nor did he repair to
                        you with his auxiliaries when his kingdom was safe; but dethroned, exiled,
                        and stripped of all his forces, he fled for refuge to your camp with one
                        troop of horse. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, because he
                        faithfully and diligently adhered to your cause in Africa, against Syphax
                        and the Carthaginians, you not only restored him to the throne of his
                        father, but by adding to his domain the most opulent part of the kingdom of
                        Syphax, rendered him the most potent of all the kings in Africa. <milestone
                            n="23" unit="section"/> What reward then, and what honour are we worthy
                        of at your hands, who have never been foes, but always allies? My father,
                        myself, my brothers, have carried arms in your cause by sea and land, not
                        only in Asia, but in countries remote from our home; <milestone n="24"
                            unit="section"/> in Peloponnesus, in Bœotia, in Aetolia, during the wars
                        with Philip, and Antiochus, and the Aetolians. Some one may say, what
                        therefore do you demand? <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> Conscript
                        fathers, since I must obey you when you desire me to explain my wishes: if
                        you have removed Antiochus beyond the mountains of Taurus with the intention
                        of holding those countries yourselves, I wish for no other people to settle
                        near me, no other neighbours than you; nor could I hope that my kingdom
                        would be rendered safer or firmer by any other event. <milestone n="26"
                            unit="section"/> But if your purpose is to retire hence, and withdraw
                        your armies, I may venture to affirm, that not one of your allies is more
                        deserving than I am of possessing what you have acquired. <milestone n="27"
                            unit="section"/> But then it will be a glorious act to liberate states
                        that are in slavery. I agree that it will, provided they have committed
                        nothing hostile against you. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/> But if they
                        took part with Antiochus, is it not much more becoming your wisdom and
                        equity, to consult the interest of your well-deserving friends than that of
                        your enemies? </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king's speech was pleasing to the senate,
                    and it was very evident that they would do all things liberally, and with a
                    desire to serve him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As one of the Rhodian
                    ambassadors was absent, an embassy from Smyrna was next introduced, which was
                    briefly disposed of. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the Smyrnaeans were
                    highly complimented because they had resolved to endure the last extremities
                    rather than surrender to the king, <pb n="1713" xml:id="p.1713"/> the Rhodians
                    were next introduced. The chief of their embassy, after stating the commencement
                    of their friendship with the Roman people and merits of the Rhodians, first iii
                    the war with Philip, and afterwards in that with Antiochus, said: <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Conscript fathers, there is nothing in the <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> whole course of our affairs that gives us more trouble
                        and uneasiness than that we should have a debate with Eumenes; with whom
                        alone, of all the kings in the world, each of us as individuals has a
                        private tie of hospitality, and, what weighs more with us, our state has a
                        public one. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But, conscript fathers, it is
                        not our own inclinations that disunite us, but the nature of circumstances
                        which exercise an all-powerful influence, so that we, being free ourselves,
                        plead the cause of other men's freedom; while kings wish to have all things
                        subservient and subject to their command. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Yet, be that as it may, our respect towards the king is an obstacle to us,
                        rather than that the debate is intricate, or likely to give you perplexity
                        in your deliberations. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For if no honour
                        could be otherwise paid to the king, your friend and ally, who has merited
                        highly in this very war, and concerning whose reward the consideration is,
                        unless you should deliver free states into his power, the deliberation would
                        be a difficult one, lest you should either send away a king, your friend,
                        without due honour, or <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> depart from your
                        own institutions, and sully now, by the servitude of so many states, the
                        glory which you have acquired in the war with Philip. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> But from this necessity of diminishing either your
                        gratitude towards your friend, or your own glory, fortune completely frees
                        you. For, through the bounty of the gods, your victory is not more glorious
                        than it is rich, so that it can easily acquit you of that just as a debt.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Lycaonia, both the Phrygias, with
                        Pisidia, the Chersonese, and the adjoining parts of Europe, are all in your
                        power; and any one of these, given to the king, can double his dominions;
                        but if they were all conferred upon him, they would set him on a level with
                        the greatest of kings. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> You have it,
                        therefore, in your power to enrich your allies with the prizes of the war;
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and, not to depart from your usual
                        line of policy, and to remember what motive you assigned as your cause of
                        war, formerly against Philip, latterly against Antiochus; what you performed
                        on the conquest of Philip; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> what is now
                        desired and expected from you, not so much because you have <pb n="1714"
                            xml:id="p.1714"/> done it before, as because it becomes you to do it.
                        For different persons look on different circumstances as specious and
                        plausible motives for taking up arms. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Some go to war to get possession of land, some of villages, some of towns,
                        some of ports, and some of the sea-coast. Such things you never coveted,
                        when you had them not; and you cannot covet them now, when the whole world
                        is under your dominion. You ever fought for your dignity and glory, in the
                        sight of the whole human race, which long since has learned to respect your
                        name and empire next to that of the immortal gods. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> And to procure and acquire these was an arduous task. I
                        know not whether it may be more difficult to retain them. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> You have undertaken to defend from the slavery of kings
                        the liberty of a nation the most ancient and most highly distinguished, both
                        by the fame of its exploits, and by universal praise for politeness and
                        learning; it becomes you to make this patronage of an entire nation,
                        received under your care and protection, perpetual. The cities standing on
                        the original soil, are not more Grecian than their colonies, which formerly
                        migrated thence into Asia; nor has change of country changed either their
                        race or manners. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Every state among us has
                        ventured to contend in a respectful contest, in every good quality and
                        virtue, with its parents and founders. Most of you have visited the cities
                        in Greece, and those in Asia. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> We are
                        surpassed in no other circumstance than that we are too far distant from
                        you. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> We hear that the inhabitants of
                        Marseilles (who, if nature, implanted, as it were, in their bosoms, could be
                        overcome by the genus of the soil, would ere this have been rendered savage,
                        by the many barbarous tribes surrounding them) are deservedly held in as
                        high honour and esteem by you as if they were inhabitants of the very centre
                        of Greece. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> For they have preserved, not
                        only the sound of the language, the mode of dress, and the habit; but, above
                        all, the manners, the laws, and a mind pure and untainted by contagion from
                        their neighbours. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> The boundary of your
                        empire, at present, is Mount Taurus. Nothing within that line ought to be
                        thought remote. To whatever extent your arms have reached, let justice,
                        emanating from Rome, spread. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> Let
                        barbarians, with whom the commands of masters have always served instead of
                        laws, have kings, in which government they delight; the Greeks endure their
                        own fortune; they have a spirit like your <pb n="1715" xml:id="p.1715"/>
                        own. They too, in former times, grasped at empire by their internal
                        strength. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> They now pray that empire may
                        remain to eternity where it is at present. They consider it sufficient that
                        their liberty should be defended by your arms, since they are unable to
                        protect it by their own. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> But it is
                        objected, that some of their states sided with Antiochus. So did others,
                        before, with Philip; so did the Tarentines with Pyrrhus. <milestone n="26"
                            unit="section"/> Not to enumerate other nations, Carthage enjoys liberty
                        and its own laws. Consider, conscript fathers, how much you owe to this
                        example, set by yourselves. You will surely make up your mind to refuse to
                        the ambition of Eumenes, what you refused to your own most just resentment.
                            <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> With what brave and faithful
                        exertions we, Rhodians, have assisted you, both in this late war, and in all
                        the wars that you have waged in that part of the world, we leave to your own
                        judgment. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/> We now, in peace, offer you
                        such advice, that if you conform to it, all the world will judge that you
                        used your victory with more honour to yourselves, than that with which you
                        gained it. </quote> Their arguments seemed well adapted to the Roman
                    grandeur. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Rhodians, the ambassadors of
                    Antiochus were called. These, after the common practice of petitioners for
                    pardon, acknowledged the king's error, and besought the conscript fathers to
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> deliberate, mindful rather of their own
                    mercy than of the misconduct of the king, who had suffered enough and more than
                    enough of punishment; in fine, to ratify, by their authority, the peace granted
                    by their general, Lucius Scipio, with the conditions on which he had given it.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate voted, that the peace should be
                    observed; and the people, a few days after, ordered it. The treaty was concluded
                    in the Capitol with Antipater, chief of the embassy, and son of the brother of
                    king Antiochus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then the other embassies from
                    Asia were heard, to all of whom was returned the same answer, that <quote> the
                        senate, in conformity with the usage of their ancestors, would send ten
                        ambassadors to examine and adjust the affairs of Asia. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> That the general plan was to be this: that the places
                        on this side of Mount Taurus, which had been within the limits of the realm
                        of Antiochus, should be assigned to Eumenes, excepting Lycia and Caria, as
                        far as the river Maeander; and that these last-mentioned should become the
                        property of the Rhodians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the other
                            <pb n="1716" xml:id="p.1716"/> states of Asia, which had been tributary
                        to Attalus, should likewise pay tribute to Eumenes; and such as had been
                        tributary to Antiochus, should be free and independent. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They appointed ten ambassadors, Quintus
                    Minucius Rufus, Lucius Furius Purpureo, Quintus Minucius Thermus, Appius
                    Claudius Nero, Cneius Cornelius Merula, Marcus Junius Brutus, Lucius
                    Aurunculeius, Lucius Aemilius Paulus, Publius Cornelius Lentulus, and Publius
                    Aelius Tubero. </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To these full instructions were given to
                    decide whatever required an examination of the place. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Concerning the general plan the senate voted: that <quote>
                        all Lycaonia, both the Phrygias, and Mysia, the royal forests, and Lydia,
                        and Ionia, excepting those towns which had been free on the day whereon the
                        battle was fought with Antiochus, and excepting by name Magnesia at Sipylus;
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> then the city of Caria, called also
                        Hydrela, and the territory of Hydrela, stretching towards Phrygia, and the
                        forts and villages on the river Maeander, and likewise the towns, excepting
                        such as had been free before the war, and excepting by name, Telmissus, and
                        the fort of Telmissium, and the lands which had belonged to Ptolemy of
                        Telmissus; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> all these which are written
                        above, were ordered to be given to king Eumenes. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Lycia was given to the Rhodians, excepting the same
                        Telmissus, and the fort of Telmissium, with the lands which had belonged to
                        Ptolemy of Telmissus; these were withheld both from Eumenes and the
                        Rhodians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To the latter was given also
                        that part of Caria which lies beyond the river Maeander nearest to the
                        island of Rhodes, with its towns, villages, forts, and lands, extending to
                        Pisidia, excepting those towns which had been in a state of freedom on the
                        day before that of the battle with Antiochus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Rhodians, after returning thanks for these
                    favours, mentioned the city of Soli in Cilicia, <quote>the inhabitants of
                        which,</quote> they said, <quote> as well as themselves, derived their
                        origin from Argos; and, in consequence of this relation, a brotherly
                        affection subsisted between the two states. They, therefore, requested the
                        senate, as an extraordinary favour, to exempt that city from subjection to
                        the king. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The ambassadors of Antiochus were called in,
                    and the matter was pro- posed to them, but their consent could not be obtained;
                    Antipater appealing to the treaty, in opposition to which, not only Soli, but
                    Cilicia was sought by the Rhodians, and they were <pb n="1717" xml:id="p.1717"/>
                    passing the summits of Taurus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Rhodians
                    being summoned again before the senate, the fathers, after they had stated how
                    earnestly the king's ambassador opposed the measure, added, that <quote> if the
                        Rhodians were of opinion that the affair particularly affected the dignity
                        of their state, the senate would try by all means to overcome the obstinacy
                        of the ambassadors. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hereupon the Rhodians, with greater warmth
                    than before, returned thanks and declared, that they would rather give way to
                    the arrogance of Antipater, than afford any reason for disturbing the peace. So
                    no change was made with respect to Soli. </p>
                <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the time in which these things were
                    transacted, deputies from Marseilles announced that Lucius <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> Baebius, the praetor, on his way into his province of
                    Spain, had been surrounded by the Ligurians; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    that a great part of his retinue being slain, he himself, wounded, had made his
                    escape, without his lictors, and with but few <milestone n="4??" unit="section"
                    /> attendants, to Marseilles, and in three days after expired. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The senate, on hearing of this misfortune, decreed, that
                    Publius Junius Brutus, who was the proprietor in Etruria, having delivered the
                    province and army to whichsoever of the lieutenants he should think proper,
                    should <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> go himself into Farther Spain, which
                    was to be his province. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This decree of the
                    senate and a letter was sent by the praetor, Spurius Posthumius, into Etruria;
                    and Publius Junius, the proprietor, set out for Spain, in <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> which province, long before a successor could arrive,
                    Lucius Aemilius Paulus, who afterwards with great glory conquered king Perseus,
                    though <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> he had carried on matters
                    unsuccessfully the year before, having raised an army by a hasty levy, fought a
                    pitched battle with the Lusitanians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    enemy were routed, and put to flight; eighteen thousand were killed, three
                    thousand three hundred taken, and their camp stormed. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The fame of this victory made matters more tranquil in
                    Spain. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In the same year, on the third day
                    before the calends of January, Lucius Valerius Flaccus, Marcus Atilius Serranus,
                    and Lucius Valerius Tappo, triumvirs, settled a Latin colony at Bononia,
                    according to a decree of the senate. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Three
                    thousand men were led to that place. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Seventy
                    acres were given to each horseman, fifty to each of the other colonists.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The land had been taken from the Boian
                    Gauls, who had formerly expelled the Tuscans. <pb n="1718" xml:id="p.1718"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year, many distinguished men
                    strove for the censorship; and this business, as if it furnished in itself
                    insufficient grounds for dispute, gave rise to another contest of a much more
                    violent nature. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The candidates were, Titus
                    Quintius Flamininus, Publius Cornelius Scipio, son of Cneius, Lucius Valerius
                    Flaccus, Marcus Porcius Cato, Marcus Claudius Marcellus, and Manius Acilius
                    Glabrio, who had defeated Antiochus and the Aetolians at Thermopylae. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The favour of the people inclined to the last in
                    particular, because he had given many largesses, by which he had bound a great
                    number of men to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When so many nobles
                    could ill brook that a man of no family should be so much preferred to them,
                    Publius Sempronius Gracchus and Caius Sempronius Rutilus, tribunes of the
                    people, commenced a prosecution against him, on a charge, that he had neither
                    exhibited in his triumph, nor lodged in the treasury, a large part of the royal
                    treasure, and of the booty taken in the camp of Antiochus. The depositions of
                    the lieutenants-general and military tribunes were at variance. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Beyond all the other witnesses, Marcus Cato was remarkable,
                    whose authority, acquired by the uniform tenor of his life, the fact of his
                    being a candidate diminished. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He, when a
                    witness, affirmed, that he had not observed, in the triumph, the gold and silver
                    vessels which, on the taking of the camp, he had seen among the other spoils of
                    the king. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At last Glabrio declared, that he
                    declined the election, chiefly to throw odium on Cato; since he, a candidate of
                    an origin as humble as his own, by an abominable perjury, attacked that which
                    men of noble birth bore with silent indignation. A fine of one hundred thousand
                        <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 322 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> was proposed to the people against him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Twice there was a contest on the subject. On the third hearing, as the
                    accused had declined the election, and the people were unwilling to vote about
                    the fine, the tribunes also dropped the business. The censors elected were,
                    Titus Quintius Flamininus and Marcus Claudius Marcellus. </p>
                <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time, when an audience of the
                    senate, in the temple of Apollo outside the city, was granted to Lucius Aemilius
                    Regillus, who, with the fleet, had defeated the admiral of king Antiochus; after
                    hearing the recital of his services, with what great fleets of the enemy he had
                    engaged, how many of their ships he had sunk or taken, a naval tri- <pb n="1719"
                        xml:id="p.1719"/> umph was voted him by the unanimous consent of the
                    fathers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He triumphed on the calends of
                    February. In this procession were carried forty-nine golden crowns; the quantity
                    of money was by no means so great considering the appearance of the triumph over
                    the king, being only thirty-four thousand seven hundred Attic tetradrachms,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 4482 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 1
                            <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and one hundred and thirty-two thousand three hundred cistophoruses.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> About 2260 <hi rend="italics"
                            >l.</hi>
                    </note> Supplications were then performed, by order of the senate, in
                    consideration of the successful services to the state, achieved in Spain by
                    Lucius Aemilius Paulus. Not long after, Lucius Scipio arrived in the city; and,
                    that he might not be inferior to his brother in point of a surname, he chose to
                    be called Asiaticus. He spoke largely of his services both before the senate and
                    a general assembly. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There were some who judged
                    that the war was greater by fame than by real difficulty; for it was terminated
                    entirely by one memorable engagement; and that the glory of that victory had
                    been stripped of its bloom at Thermopylae. But, to any person judging
                    impartially, it must appear, that the fight at Thermopylae was with the
                    Aetolians, rather than with the king. For with how small a portion of his own
                    strength did Antiochus engage in that battle! <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    whereas, in the other, in Asia, the strength of the whole Asiatic continent
                    stood combined; for he had collected auxiliaries of all nations from the most
                    remote quarters of the east. Justly, therefore, were the greatest possible
                    honours paid to the immortal gods, for having rendered a most important victory
                    easy in the acquisition; and a triumph was decreed to the commander. He
                    triumphed in the intercalary month, the day before the calends of March; which
                    triumph was greater in the display to the eye than that of Africanus his
                    brother, yet if we recall to our memory the circumstances, and estimate the
                    dangers and difficulty, it was no more to be compared to it, than if you would
                    contrast one general with the other, Antiochus with Hannibal. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He carried, in his triumph, military standards, two hundred
                    and thirty-four; models of towns, one hundred and thirty-four; elephants' teeth,
                    one thousand two hundred and thirty; crowns of gold, two hundred and
                    twenty-four: pounds-weight of silver, one hundred and thirty-seven thousand four
                    hundred and twenty; Attic tetradrachms, two hundred and twenty-four thousand;
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 28,984 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                        6 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> cisto- <pb n="1720" xml:id="p.1720"/> phoruses, three hundred and
                    thirty-one thousand and seventy; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 5699
                            <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 5 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> gold pieces, called Philippians, one hundred and forty thousand; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 77,629 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 3 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> silver vases, all engraved, to the amount of one thousand four hundred
                    and twenty-four pounds' weight; of golden vases, one thousand and twenty-four
                    pounds' weight; and of the king's generals, governors, and officers at court,
                    thirty-two were led before his chariot. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Twenty-five denariuses <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 16 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 1 1/2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> were given to each of his soldiers, double that sum to a centurion,
                    triple it to a horseman; and after the triumph, their pay and allowance of corn
                    were doubled. He had already doubled them after the battle in Asia. He triumphed
                    about a year after the expiration of his consulship. </p>
                <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Cneius Manlius, the consul, arrived in Asia,
                    and Quintus Fabius Labeo, the praetor, reached the fleet, nearly at the same
                    time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul did not want reasons for war
                    against the Gauls; the sea was subjected to the Romans since the conquest of
                    Antiochus. It appeared best to Quintus Fabius, considering to what thing in
                    particular he should apply himself, lest he might seem to have had a province in
                    which there was no employment, to sail over to the island of Crete. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The Cydonians were engaged in war against the
                    Gortynians and Gnossians; and a great number of Roman and Italian captives were
                    said to be in slavery in different parts of the island. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Having sailed with the fleet from Ephesus, as soon as he
                    touched the shore of Crete, he despatched orders to all the states to cease from
                    hostilities, and to search each of them for the captives in its own cities and
                    territory, and bring them to him; also, to send ambassadors to him, to treat of
                    matters belonging alike to the Romans and Cretans. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> These orders had little influence on the Cretans. Excepting
                    the Gortynians, none of them restored the captives. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Valerius Antias relates, that as many as four thousand
                    captives were restored out of the whole island, because the Cretans feared his
                    threats of war; and that this was deemed a sufficient reason for Fabius
                    obtaining from the senate a naval triumph, although he performed no other
                    exploit. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From Crete Fabius returned to
                    Ephesus: having despatched three ships from the latter place to the coast of
                    Thrace, he ordered the garrisons of Antiochus to be withdrawn from Aenos and
                    Maronea, that these cities might be left at liberty. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
