<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader status="new">
    	<fileDesc>
    		<titleStmt>
    			<title type="work">Poems</title>
    			<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    			<author n="Petr.">Petronius</author>
    			<editor role="editor">Michael Heseltine</editor>
    			<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder> </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
    		 <sourceDesc>
    			<biblStruct>
                	<monogr>
                		<author>Petronius Arbiter</author>
                		<title>Petronius</title>
                		<editor role="editor" n="Heseltine">Michael Heseltine</editor>                        
                		<imprint>
                			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                			<publisher>William Heinemann</publisher>
                			<date>1913</date>
                		</imprint>
                	</monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <state delim="." unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            	<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>--><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader><text xml:lang="en"><body>
            <pb id="p.343"/>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Every man shall find his own desire; there is no one
                thing which pleases all: one man gathers thorns and another roses.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Now autumn had brought its chill shades, and Phoebus
                was looking winterwards with cooler reins. Now the plane-tree had begun to shed down
                her leaves, now the young shoots had withered on the vine, and she had begun to
                number her grapes: the whole promise of the year was standing before our eyes.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="3"/>It was fear first created gods in the world, when
                the lightning fell from high heaven, and the ramparts of the world were rent with
                flame, and Athos was smitten and blazed. Soon 'twas Phoebus sank to earth, after he
                had traversed earth from his rising; the Moon grew old and once more renewed her
                glory; next the starry signs were spread through the firmament, and the year divided
                into changing seasons. The folly spread, and soon vain superstition bade the
                labourer yield to Ceres the harvest's chosen firstfruits, and garland Bacchus with
                the fruitful vine, and made Pales to rejoice in the shepherd's work; Neptune swims
                deepplunged beneath all the waters of the world, Pallas watches over shops, and the
                man who wins his prayer or has betrayed the world for gold now strives greedily to
                create gods of his own.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>I would not always steep my head with the same sweet
                nard, nor strive to win my stomach with familiar<pb id="p.345"/> wine. The bull
                loves to change his valley-pasture, and the wild beast maintains his zest by change
                of food. Even to be bathed in the light of day is pleasant only because the
                night-hour races back with altered steeds.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>A wife is a burden imposed by law, and should be
                loved like one's fortune. But I do not wish to love even my fortune for ever.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Leave thine home, O youth, and seek out alien
                shores: a larger range of life is ordained for thee. Yield not to misfortune; the
                far-off Danube shall know thee, the cold North-wind, and the untroubled kingdoms of
                Canopus, and the men who gaze on the new birth of Phoebus or upon his setting: he
                that disembarks on distant sands, becomes thereby the greater man.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/>For there is naught that may not serve the need of
                mortal men, and in adversity despised things help us. So when a ship sinks, yellow
                gold weighs down its possessor, while a flimsy oar bears up the shipwrecked body.
                When the trumpets sound, the savage's knife stands drawn at the rich man's throat;
                the poor man's rags wear the amulet of safety.</p>
            <pb id="p.347"/>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>My little house is covered by a roof that fears no
                harm, and the grape swollen with wine hangs from the fruitful elm. The boughs yield
                cherries, the orchards ruddy apples, and the trees sacred to Pallas<note>The olive,
                    which she gave to Athens. By this gift, which the Gods considered more useful
                    than the horse given by Poseidon, she became the presiding deity of the
                city.</note> break under the wealth of their branches. And now where the smooth soil
                drinks from the runnels of the spring, Corycian kale springs up for me and creeping
                mallows, and the poppy with promise of untroubled sleep. Moreover, if my pleasure is
                to lay snares for birds, or if I choose rather to entrap the timid deer, or draw out
                the quivering fish on slender line, so much deceit is all that is known to my humble
                fields. Go, then, and barter the hours of flying life for rich banquets. My prayer
                is that since at the last the same end waits for me, it may find me here, here call
                me to account for the time that I have spent.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Is it not enough that mad youth engulfs us, and our
                good name is sunk in reproach and sweeps us astray? Behold! even bondmen and the
                rabble that is kindred to the mire wanton amid our gathered hoards! The low slave
                enjoys the treasure of a kingdom, and the thrall's room shames Vesta and the cottage
                of Romulus. So goodness lies obscured in the deep mud, and the fleet of the
                unrighteous carries snowy sails.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="10"/>So, too, the body will shut in the belly's wind,
                which, when it labours to come forth again from its deep dungeon, prizes forth a way
                by sharp blows: and<pb id="p.349"/> there is no end to the cold shiver which rules
                the cramped frame, till a warm sweat bedews and loosens the body.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="11"/>O sea-shore and sea more sweet to me than life!
                Happy am I who may come at once to the lands I love. O beauteous day! In this
                country long ago I used to rouse the Naiads with my hands' alternate stroke. Here is
                the fountain's pool, there the sea washes up its weeds: here is a sure haven for
                quiet love. I have had life in full; for never can harder fortune take away what was
                given us in time overpast.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="12"/>With these words he tore the white hair from his
                trembling head, and rent his cheeks; his eyes filled with tears, and as the
                impetuous river sweeps down the valleys when the cold snow has perished, and the
                gentle south-wind will not suffer the ice to live on the unfettered earth, so was
                his face wet with a full stream, and his heart rang with the troubled murmur of deep
                groaning.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="13"/>For sooner will men hold fire in their mouths than
                keep a secret. Whatever you let escape you in your hall flows forth and beats at
                city walls in sudden rumours. Nor is the breach of faith the end. The work of
                betrayal issues forth with increase, and strives<pb id="p.351"/> to add weight to
                the report. So was it that the greedy slave, who feared to unlock his knowledge, dug
                in the ground and betrayed the secret of the king's hidden ears. For the earth
                brought forth sounds, and the whispering reeds sang how Midas was even such an one
                as the tell-tale had revealed.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="14"/>There sea and sky struggle and buffet each other,
                here the tiny stream runs through smooth and smiling country. There the sailor
                laments for his sunken ship, here the shepherd dips his flock in the gentle river.
                There death confronts and chokes the vast gape of greed, here the earth laughs to
                lie low before the curved sickle. There, with water everywhere, dry thirst burns the
                throat, here kisses are given in plenty to faithless man. Let Ulysses go sail and
                weary the waters in beggar's rags: the chaste Penelope dwells on land.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="15"/>The man that would not haste to die, nor force the
                Fates to snap the tender threads with impetuous hand, should know only this much of
                the sea's anger. Lo! where the tide flows back, and the wave bathes his feet without
                peril! Lo! where the mussel is thrown up among the green sea-weed, and the hoarse
                whorl of the slippery shell is rolled along! Lo! where the wave turns the sands to
                rush back in the eddy, there pebbles of many a hue appear on the wave-worn floor.
                Let the man who may have these things under his feet, play safely on the shore, and
                count this alone to be the sea.</p>
            <pb id="p.353"/>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="16"/>Outward beauty is not enough, and the woman who
                would appear fair must not be content with any common manner. Words, wit, play,
                sweet talk and laughter, surpass the work of too simple nature. For all expense of
                art seasons beauty, and naked loveliness is wasted all in vain, if it have not the
                will to please.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="17"/>So, contrary to the known operations of nature, the
                raven lays her eggs when the crops are ripe. So the she-bear shapes her cubs with
                her tongue, and the fish is ignorant of love's embrace, yet brings forth young. So
                the tortoise, sacred to Phoebus, delivered by the will of mother Lucina, hatches her
                eggs with the warmth of her nostrils. So the bee, begotten without wedlock from the
                woven cells, throbs with life and fills her camp with bold soldiery. The strength of
                nature lies not in holding on one even way, but she loves to change the fashion of
                her laws.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="18"/>My<note>A parrot is speaking.</note> birthplace was
                India's glowing shore, where the day returns in brilliance with fiery orb. Here I
                was born amid the worship of the gods, and exchanged my barbaric speech for the
                Latin tongue. O healer of Delphi, now dismiss thy swans; here is a voice more worthy
                to dwell within thy temple.</p>
            <pb id="p.355"/>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="19"/>The sailor, naked from the shipwreck, seeks out a
                comrade stricken by the same blow to whom he may bewail his fate. The farmer who has
                lost his crops and the whole year's fruits in the hail, weeps his sad lot on a bosom
                wounded like his own. Death draws the unhappy together; bereaved parents utter their
                groans with one voice, and the moment makes them equal. We too will strike the stars
                with words in unison; the saying is that prayers travel more strongly when united.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="20"/>You send me golden apples, my sweet Martia, and you
                send me the fruit of the shaggy chestnut. Believe me, I would love them all; but
                should you choose rather to come in person, lovely girl, you would beautify your
                gift. Come, if you will, and lay sour apples to my tongue, the sharp flavour will be
                like honey as I bite. But if you feign you will not come, dearest, send kisses with
                the apples; then gladly will I devour them.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="21"/>If you are sister to Phoebus, Delia, I entrust my
                petition to you, that you may carry to your brother the words of my prayer.
                    <quote>God of Delphi, I have built for you a temple of Sicilian marble, and have
                    given you fair words of song from a slender pipe of reed. Now if you hear us,
                    Apollo, and are indeed divine, tell me where a man who has no money is to find
                    it.</quote></p>
            <pb id="p.357"/>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="22"/>Honest Heaven ordained that all things which can
                end our wretched complaints should be ready to hand. Common green herbs and the
                berries that grow on rough brambles allay the gnawing hunger of the belly. A fool is
                he who goes thirsty with a river close by, and shivers in the east wind while a
                blazing fire roars on the warm hearth. The law sits armed by the threshold of a
                wanton bride; the girl who lies on a lawful bed knows no fear. The wealth of nature
                gives us enough for our fill: that which unbridled vanity teaches us to pursue has
                no end to it.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="23"/>Doves have made a nest in the soldier's helmet: see
                how Venus loveth Mars.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="24"/>The Jew may worship his pig-god and clamour in the
                ears of high heaven, but unless he also cuts back his foreskin with the knife, he
                shall go forth from the holy city cast forth from the people, and transgress the
                sabbath by breaking the law of fasting.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="25"/>This is the one nobility and proof of honourable
                estate, that a man's hands have shown no fear.</p>
            <pb id="p.359"/>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="26"/>At rest in bed, I had scarce begun to enjoy the
                first silence of night, and to give up my conquered eyes to sleep, when fierce Love
                took hold of me and drew me up by the hair, and tore me, bidding me watch till day.
                    <quote>Ah, my slave,</quote> he said, <quote>thou lover of a thousand girls,
                    canst thou lie alone here, alone, oh hard of heart?</quote> I leaped up, and
                with bare feet and disordered raiment started on every path and found a way by none.
                Now I run, now to move is weariness: I repent of turning back, and am ashamed to
                halt in the midst of the road. Lo, the voices of men and the roar of the streets,
                the singing of birds and the faithful company of watchdogs are all silent. I alone
                of all men dread both sleep and my bed, and follow thy command, great Lord of
                desire.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="27"/>Long may that night be dearto us, Nealce, that
                first laid you to rest upon my heart. Dear be the bed and the genius of the couch,
                and the silent lamp that saw you come softly to do our pleasure. Come, then, let us
                endure though we have grown older, and employ the years which a brief delay will
                blot out. It is lawful and right to prolong an old love: grant that what we began in
                haste may not hastily be ended.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="28"/>The pleasure of the act of love is gross and brief,
                and love once consummated brings loathing after it. Let us then not rush blindly
                thither straightway like lustful beasts, for love sickens and the flame dies down;
                but even so, even so, let us keep eternal holi<pb id="p.361"/> day, and lie with thy
                lips to mine. No toil is here and no shame: in this, delight has been, and is, and
                long shall be; in this there is no diminution, but a beginning everlastingly.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="29"/>To love and accuse at one time were a labour
                Hercules himself could scarce have borne.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="30"/>Our eyes deceive us, and our wandering senses weigh
                down our reason and tell us falsehoods. For the tower which stands almost
                four-square has its corners blunted at a distance and becomes rounded. The full
                stomach turns from the honey of Hybla, and the nose often hates the scent of
                cinnamon. One thing could not please us more or less than another, unless the senses
                strove in set conflict with wavering balance.</p>
            <p><milestone unit="section" n="31"/>It is not the shrines of the gods, nor the powers
                of the air, that send the dreams which mock the mind with flitting shadows; each man
                makes dreams for himself. For when rest lies about the limbs subdued by sleep, and
                the mind plays with no weight upon it, it pursues in the darkness whatever was its
                task by daylight. The man who makes towns tremble in war, and overwhelms unhappy
                cities in flame, sees arms, and routed hosts, and the deaths of kings, and plains
                streaming with outpoured blood. They whose life is to plead cases have statutes and
                the courts before their eyes, and look with terror upon the judgement-seat
                surrounded by a throng. The miser hides his gains and discovers buried treasure.<pb
                    id="p.363"/> The hunter shakes the woods with his pack. The sailor snatches his
                shipwrecked bark from the waves, or grips it in death-agony. The woman writes to her
                lover, the adulteress yields herself: and the dog follows the tracks of the hare as
                he sleeps. The wounds of the unhappy endure into the night-season.</p>
            <pb/>
        		
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
</body></text></TEI>