<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>In Defense of Marcus Aemilius Scaurus </title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>

  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>

  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="en">English</language>
    <language ident="la">Latin</language>
    <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>

  <revisionDesc>
   <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge2_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.9  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.7  2011-03-21 16:06:41  lcerrato
fixed typo in while to in which

Revision 1.6  2011-03-17 14:59:55  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.5  2010/08/31 18:43:06  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.2  2010/07/08 22:49:11  student
fixing place tags - AD

Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:15 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 
     
Revision 1.8 2009/09/22 16:21:37 rsingh04 
fixed references to Cic. Ver. 

Revision 1.7 2007/01/04 20:06:59 packel 
fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius 

Revision 1.6 2006/05/05 17:38:06 packel 
fixed date tags 

Revision 1.5 2006/02/10 20:50:18 packel
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.4 2005/11/21 16:51:16 lcerrato 
changed thought you shall not perceive them to though... 

Revision 1.3 2005/11/21 16:49:41 lcerrato 
changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this
     
Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:24 packel 
removed stray item tags 

Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:53 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.19 2005/03/24 19:34:54 lcerrato 
Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83 

Revision 1.18 2005/03/23 18:13:06 lcerrato 
changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.17 2005/01/19 18:03:37 mimno 
div1s missing type attributes 

Revision 1.16 2004/06/14 17:34:00 lcerrato 
changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave" 

Revision 1.15 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc
     Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and
     typos.) 

Revision 1.14 2001/03/14 19:13:33 lcerrato 
changed ought to he to ought to be in first
     oration against Cataline 

Revision 1.13 2000/05/04 16:23:18 amahoney 
really fix language ids
     
Revision 1.12 2000/05/04 16:21:33 amahoney 
fix language codes 

Revision 1.11 2000/03/04 20:34:16 dasmith 
Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.10 2000/02/22 18:11:54 amahoney
     fix a couple of broken bibl refs 

Revision 1.9 1996/12/02 21:58:39 amahoney 
replace the
     refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors 

Revision 1.8 1996/11/30 20:38:39 lcerrato 
revised and proofread again 

Revision 1.7 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.6 1999/09/01 20:30:38 dasmith
     Removed tag from attribute value. 

Revision 1.5 1999/08/12 17:17:35 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl
     
Revision 1.4 1997/11/07 18:45:17 textgod 
Fixed typo. 

Revision 1.3 1997/10/31 18:58:38 textgod
     Fixed typo. 

Revision 1.2 1997/09/01 19:53:11 textgod 
Added sections. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:46 textgod 
Added to repository. 
    </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="en">
  <front>
   <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF MARCUS AEMILIUS SCAURUS. <note anchored="true"
     >This oration is in a very corrupt and fragmentary state. It is here translated as corrected
     and filled up by Beier in the edition of Orellius. Beier's "supplements," as Orellius calls
     them, are inserted between brackets [ ].</note>
   </head>
   <argument>
    <head>THE ARGUMENT</head>
    <p>Marcus Scaurus was the stepson of Sulla, in the time of whose triumph he had behaved with the
     greatest moderation. He had been aedile, in which office he had exhibited the games with the
     greatest magnificence, so as greatly to embarrass his private fortunes. He then became praetor
     and afterwards having received Sardinia as his province, he lost his character for moderation,
     being said to have treated the natives with rapacity and excessive arrogance. After his return
     to Rome, he obtained some celebrity by defending some persons under prosecution; and among
     others Caius Cato. </p>
    <p>At the end of June A. U. C. 699, he returned to Rome to stand for the consulship; on which he
     was accused by Publius Valerius Triarius, (a young man of a high reputation for industry and
     eloquence) of acts of oppression and extortion among the Sardinians. And the trial came on
     before Marcus Cato, who was a great friend of Triarius, only three days after Caius Cato had
     been acquitted by the exertions of Scaurus. Lucius Marius and Marcus and Quintus Pacuvius
     seconded Triarius in the prosecution, these two last having had a commission given to them to
     go to Corsica and Sardinia to inquire into the state of the case there, which commission they
     had neglected, excusing themselves on the ground that the consular <foreign xml:lang="la"
      >comitia</foreign> were at hand and that they were afraid that while they were away Scaurus
     would buy the consulship, and so get the means of oppressing other provinces. </p>
    <p>Scaurus relied on the support of Pompeius with whom he was connected by marriage; and he was
     defended by Cicero and five other advocates among whom was Quintus Hortensius. While the
     prosecution was going on, Faustus Sulla, the son of the great Sulla, and half brother of
     Scaurus, who was also quaestor at the time, came out among the people severely wounded crying
     out that Scaurus' competitors had attempted to murder him. He went about with three hundred
     armed guard prepared to defend himself, if need were, by force; Scaurus also made a speech on
     his own behalf and produced a great effect on the judges by the recollection of his own
     aedileship and the recollection of his father's high character. He was acquitted, but he did
     not succeed in obtaining the consulship.</p>
   </argument>
  </front>
  <body>
   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
   <p>
    <milestone n="1. a." unit="section"/>
   </p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>It was desirable above all things for Marcus Scaurus, O judges, to return
    (as he has always been most especially anxious and attentive to do) the dignity of his race, and
    family, and name, without incurring the hatred of any one, and without either giving offence to
    or receiving annoyance from <gap reason="***"/></p>
   <p>[But since his adverse destiny has brought about this state of things, he does not think that
    he ought to grumble at meeting with the same fortune as his father, who was more than once
    compelled by his enemies to plead his cause as a defendant.] <milestone n="1. b." unit="section"
    /></p>
   <p>[We know that the most eminent man of our state was accused by Marcus Brutus. Orations are
    extant from which it can be seen that many things were said against Scaurus himself. Falsely. No
    one doubts that; but still they were said and urged against him as accusations by his enemy.]
     <gap reason="*****"/></p>
   <p>he also was tried before the people, when Cnaeus Domitius, a tribune of the people, instituted
    the prosecution <gap reason="***"/>
    <milestone n="2." unit="section"/></p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>He was prosecuted by Quintus Servilius Caepio, under the Servilian law, at
    the time when the tribunals of judges were furnished exclusively by the equestrian body; and
    after Publius Rutilius was condemned, no one could appear so innocent as to have no reason to
    fear that tribunal. </p>
   <p>
    <gap reason="******"/>
    <milestone n="3." unit="section"/>
   </p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>again also that guardian of the republic was accused of treason by the
    same man, under the Varian law. And not long before he was attacked by Quintus Varius, a tribune
    of the people. </p>
   <p>[And now, O judges, his enviers and enemies seek to bring disgrace on the son of this man who
    was in his time attacked by the false accusations of many men, by an ignominious prosecution on
    the ground of extortion. And I have thought it due to the memory of his most illustrious father
    to undertake his cause.] <milestone n="4. a." unit="section"/></p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>for I not only admired that man as every one else did, but I also loved
    him above all things. For when I was burning with a desire for glory, he first encouraged me to
    hope that virtue without any assistance from fortune could, by means of labour and perseverance,
    arrive at the object of its desires. <gap reason="***"/><milestone n="4. b." unit="section"
    /></p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>and since the prosecution has been loaded with a vast heap of charges, but
    without any great diversity or variety of kind; [if] I were to reply to these generally [rather
    than by arguments on each separate charge, I should appear to have fallen short of what I owe to
    the cause, and to my own duty. Nevertheless, O judges, we will first unfold the whole cause to
    you, and consider it when we have laid it open before your eyes. And by this means you will most
    easily arrive at the understanding of the things about which it is necessary for us to speak,
    and of the arguments which you are required to follow.] <milestone n="4. c." unit="section"
    /></p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>a man of the name of Bostar, a Norensian, fleeing from Sardinia <gap
     reason="***"/> [Triarius alleges as an article of accusation, that he was recalled from his
    flight by the insidious blandishments of Scaurus, and received at his table inhospitality, and
    then murdered by poison by his host and <gap reason="***"/> ] <gap reason="***"/> that he was
    buried before Scaurus's supper was taken away. <gap reason="***"/><milestone n="4. d."
     unit="section"/></p>
   <p>[And how slight are the grounds for any suspicion of poison having been administered, O
    judges, will appear immediately, if you will only consider the many causes which frequently
    produce sudden death.] <gap reason="***"/>
    <milestone n="4. e." unit="section"/></p>
   <p>[Scaurus was a man so happily situated by fortune, that he could not only retain his own
    possessions with the greatest ease, but that he was more likely to be able to acquire new] ones,
    than to be forced to sell what he had. Come, then, while I defend Scaurus, O Triarius, you
    defend the mother [of Bostar, whom I accuse of being implicated in this crime.] <gap
     reason="***"/>
   </p>
   <p>[I have also refuted that assertion of yours] that you were afraid that <gap reason="****"/>
    [unless, as Bostar had died intestate, he had managed the matter in such a way as if the
    inheritance belonged to himself, and as if this did not seem to him a sufficient reason for
    putting Bostar to death by poison.] <milestone n="4. f." unit="section"/></p>
   <p>[But Scaurus] <gap reason="****"/> could not by any possibility have entered on the possession
    of that property. <gap reason="***"/>
    <milestone n="5." unit="section"/></p>
   <p>If, in truth, O judges, I were speaking in defence of Lucius Tubulus, who is reported to have
    been the most wicked and most audacious man that ever lived, still I should not be afraid that
    if he were accused of having given poison to any guest or companion of his while he was supping
    with him, though he was not his heir, and had no quarrel with him <gap reason="***"/> [any one
    would think that credible.] <milestone n="6." unit="section"/></p>
   <p>[I come now to the charge of incontinence, and intemperate lust with which the accuser has
    endeavoured to brand Scaurus and his character,] when Aris would not give up [the very wife,
    says he, whom he himself loved <gap reason="*****"/> to his inflamed lust and unbridled desire.]
     <gap reason="***"/>
    <milestone n="7." unit="section"/></p>
   <p>He was compelled to make his escape secretly out of Sardinia. <gap reason="***"/></p>
   <p>[Forsooth, he left his wife behind him and consulted his own safety by flight, just as
    beavers, they say, flying from the hunters] <gap reason="****"/> ransom themselves with that
    part of their body on account of which they are chiefly sought for! <gap reason="***"/>
    <milestone n="8." unit="section"/>[But even though Scaurus had at all times been the most
    dissolute and licentious of all men, still that is incredible, O judges, which Triarius added,
    that the wife of Aris was reduced to such distress by the licentiousness of the praetor as to
    seek a remedy for her embarrassment by hanging herself. For the very first desire which is
    implanted in man by nature, and one which we have in common with the very beasts, is that which
    prompts and induces a man to preserve his life, and which instigates him to shun death and all
    those things which seem likely to produce death.] <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><milestone
     n="1. a." unit="section"/></p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>And this, I say, O judges, is the state of the case. Nor is this a new
    assertion of mine; but it has been elicited by the investigations of others <gap reason="*****"/>
    <milestone n="1. b." unit="section"/></p>
   <p>[But still it can be proved by examples. Lucretia having been ravished by force by the king's
    son, having invoked the citizens to revenge her, slew herself. And this indignation of hers was
    the cause of liberty to the state. And even the bravest men have not sought death of their own
    accord, except in the most extreme necessity, for the purpose of avoiding some disgrace. As
    Publius Crassus Mucianus, when waging war against Aristonicus, in Asia, being intercepted
    between Elaea and Smyrna, by the Thracians, of whom Aristonicus had a great number in his
    different garrisons, and fearing to fall into his power, escaped disgrace by provoking death
    intentionally. For he is said to have run the stick which he had been using to manage his horse,
    into the eye of one of the barbarians, who, being infiltrated by the pain, stabbed Crassus with
    his dagger, and so, while avenging himself, delivered the Roman general from the disgrace of
    captivity. And by this means Crassus showed to Fortune how little the man whom she was loading
    with such bitter insult deserved it, since with equal prudence and courage he burst the chains
    which she was throwing over his liberty, and restored himself to his own dignity, though she had
    almost given him to Aristonicus.] <gap reason="****"/> This, indeed, we know from hearsay; but
    this we ourselves can recollect and have almost seen, namely, how Publius Crassus, of the same
    family and name, slew himself that he might not fall into the hands of the enemy. <gap
     reason="***"/></p>
   <p>But Marcus Aquillius, who had behaved like a thoroughly brave man in war, and who had attained
    the same honours as the elder Crassus, could not imitate his action <milestone n="2"
     unit="section"/>
    <gap reason="****"/>[but] he disgraced [the recollection of his you]th and of his early exploits
    by the infamy of his old age. What need I say besides? Could either those most illustrious men
    the Julii, or could Marcus Antonius a man of the very highest ability, imitate the conduct of
    the other Crassus in those times? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Need I cite any more
    instances? Who is there found among all the records of Greece (which are richer in fine stories
    than in great actions) if you only forget Ajax and the plays of the tragedians, who of his own
    accord, as the poet says, being <quote>
     <l>A conqueror all unused to infamy</l>
     <l>Would not survive defeat,</l>
    </quote> except Themistocles the Athenian who did put himself to death? <milestone n="4"
     unit="section"/>But these Greeks invent heaps of stories and among them they make out that
    Cleombrotus of Ambracia threw himself down from a high wall not because he had suffered any
    misfortune, but (as I see it written among the Greeks) after having read a very eloquently and
    elegantly written book, of that greatest of philosophers Plato about death; the one, I suppose,
    in which Socrates, on that very day on which he was to die, argues at great length that this is
    death which we fancy to be life when the soul is held in shut up in the body as in a prison and
    that that is life when the same soul, having been released from the bonds of the body, flies
    back to that place from which it originated. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Had that Sardinian
    woman of yours then, known anything about or had she read Pythagoras or Plato? Though even these
    men praise death with such limitations that they forbid our flying from life, and say that such
    conduct is contrary to the conditions and laws of nature. And in truth you will not be able to
    find any other reason which can justify a voluntary death. And this, too, the prosecutor saw;
    for he let out an insinuation, somewhere, that that woman preferred being deprived of life to
    being robbed of her chastity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>But immediately he went off from
    that point and said no more about chastity, being afraid, I suppose, lest he should be giving us
    some opportunity for joking and laughing. For it is quite notorious that she was abominably ugly
    and excessively old. And so, however lustful that Sardinian may have been, what suspicions of
    licentiousness or love can there be on the part of my client? <milestone n="7" unit="section"
    /></p>
   <p>And that you may not suppose, O Triarius, that I am inventing the allegations which I am now
    making, and that I have not derived my information on the subject from the instructions of the
    defendant, I will tell you what were the opinions in Sardinia about that woman's death, (for
    there were two opinions,) so that you may the more easily <gap reason="******"/> [and that these
    men may see the innocence of Scaurus, and the audacity of your witnesses, and the scandalous
    nature of the actions which were then done. Aris, the husband of that Sardinian woman <gap
     reason="*******"/>] had for a long time loved [the mother of Bostar <gap reason="***"/>]
     <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
    <gap reason="***"/> a licentious and wicked woman, and had lived in shameless and notorious
    adultery with her. He was afraid of his wife, who was an old woman, rich and ill-tempered;
    still, though he did not like to keep her as his wife, because of her ugliness, he did not like
    to divorce her, because of her riches. And so, by previous agreement he concerted a plan with
    the mother of Bostar, that they should both of them come to Rome; and he promised that when
    there he would find out some contrivance for making her his wife. <milestone n="9"
     unit="section"/></p>
   <p>There were, as I have said, two opinions,—one, not inconsistent with the circumstances or with
    the nature of the case, that the wife of Aris was very indignant at his adultery when she heard
    that he had fled to Rome with that love of his, pretending to have fled for fear of her, or in
    order, as there had been a criminal connection between them before, to be now formally joined in
    wedlock; and that she was so excited with feminine indignation, that she preferred dying to
    bearing it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>The other was no less probable, and, as I believe,
    was even more generally believed in Sardinia, namely, that Aris, that witness and host of yours,
    O Triarius, when departing for Rome, had entrusted the commission to his freedman, not indeed to
    offer open violence to that old woman, for that would not have been right to his mistress, but
    to press her throat with his two fingers, and then to fasten a little cord round it, so that she
    might be supposed to have died by hanging. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>And this suspicion
    prevailed all the more, because, when the Norensians were celebrating their festivals in honour
    of the dead, and <gap reason="******"/> had all, according to the custom of their tribe, left
    the city, then she was said by the freedman to have hanged herself; and it was clearly desirable
    for a man who strangled his mistress to seek for the solitary time when the people left the
    city; but his mistress, who wished to die, had no such necessity for doing so. <milestone n="12"
     unit="section"/>And the suspicion was confirmed, because, immediately after the old woman was
    dead, the freedman started for Rome, as if he had executed his commission; and Aris, as soon as
    his freedman brought him news of the death of his wife, instantly, at Rome, married that mother
    of Bostar. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>See now, O judges, to what a foul and polluted and infamous <gap reason="***"/> family you are
    called on, O judges, to surrender this family of Scaurus. Just consider who the witnesses are by
    whom you are required to be influenced in your decision about a great man, about a noble family,
    about an illustrious name! Do you think that it becomes you to forget the crimes of the mothers
    against their children, and of the husbands against their wives? You see, you behold infamous
    lust mingled with cruelty. You have before you the authors of two most enormous crimes, by which
    our cause is endeavoured to be tainted by men who are either ignorant of the truth, or else who
    are prompted only by envy. You have before you men disgraced by every sort of guilt and
    atrocity. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
   </p>
   <p>Is there, then, the slightest suspicion attaching to us after all these charges of the
    prosecutor? Have they not been wholly cleared up? Have they not been refuted? Have they not been
    scattered to the winds? And how has that been done? Because you gave me, O Triarius, a charge
    which I could efface, which I could argue about which I could dilate upon; because it was a
    charge of that sort which did not entirely depend on the witness, but which the judge could by
    himself form his own opinion on. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Nor, O judges, ought we to do
    anything else in the case of an unknown witness, except by argument and conjecture, and by
    suspicion, inquire as well as we can, into the state and nature of the circumstances to which he
    deposes. In truth, not only an African witness, (or indeed a Sardinian one, if that is what they
    prefer being called,) but even more civilized and scrupulous men than they, are liable to be
    prompted, or deterred, or guided, or diverted from their purpose; and such a man is the master
    of his own inclination, and may, if he pleases, lie with impunity. <milestone n="16"
     unit="section"/>But the argument which is suited to the case, (and nothing else can properly be
    called argument) is the voice of circumstances, the traces of nature, the mark of truth; and of
    whatever sort it be, it must remain immutable, for it is not invented by the orator, but
    assumed. Wherefore, if I were worsted by that sort of accusation, I should yield and submit; I
    should be defeated in every respect. I should be defeated in the cause, I should be defeated by
    truth. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>Are you going to bring up against me troops and armies
    of Sardinians? and are you going to endeavour to frighten me, not by accusations, but by the
    roaring of Africans? I shall not, indeed, be able to argue, but I shall be able [to flee for
    refuge to] the good faith and clemency of these [judges, to their regard for their oaths, to the
    equity of the Roman people, which has considered the family of Scaurus as one of the chief
    families in the city; and I shall be able to implore the divine protection of the immortal gods,
    who have always been favourers of his race and name. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>“He demanded money, he exacted it, he seized it by violence, he extorted it.” If the accuser
    proves all that by the accounts, since the way in which the accounts are made up show the
    regular series and order in which he transacted his affairs, I will attend carefully, and I will
    consider how I am to proceed in conducting the defence. If you rely on witnesses, (I will not
    insist upon their being good and respectable men, as long as they are men of whom it is known
    who they are,) then I will consider how I am to struggle with each of them separately.
     <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>If there is but one complexion, one voice, and one notion
    among all the witnesses; if, as they say, they not only do not attempt to corroborate their
    statements by any arguments, but if they do not even produce any description of documents either
    public or private, (which, however, can easily be forged,) then, O judges, which way am I to
    turn, or what am I to do? Am I to argue with every one of them? <gap reason="***"/> Had you
    nothing to give? He will say he had. Who is to know that? Who is to judge that there was no
    reason <gap reason="***"/>? He will make out that there was. How can we refute him, and show
    that it was in his power not to give if he did not choose? He will say that it was extorted by
    force. What eloquence is able by force of argument to confute the impudence of a man whom one
    does not know? <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>I will not, therefore plead against that
    conspiracy of Sardinians, and with perjury ingeniously contrived, and procured, and suborned;
    nor will I even examine at all into some of the elaborately wrought-out arguments; but with all
    my power I will meet and struggle against their direct attack. I do not want to drag forward
    each individual out of their line of battle, nor to fight and do battle with each separate
    champion. I must rout their whole array at one shock, and I will. <milestone n="21"
     unit="section"/></p>
   <p>For there is one especial most important charge concerning corn, and applying to the whole of
    Sardinia, about which Triarius questioned all the Sardinians; and that was corroborated by the
    agreement and unanimity of evidence of all the witnesses. And before I touch upon that charge, I
    beg of you, O judges, to allow me to lay down a few principles to serve, as it were, for the
    foundations of our whole defence. And if they are once laid down, and established according to
    my intentions and expectations, I shall then fear no part of the prosecution. <milestone n="22"
     unit="section"/>For I will speak first of the sort of accusation; after that I will speak of
    the Sardinians; then I will say a little about Scaurus himself; and when I have said enough on
    these subjects, then at last I will come to this horrible and formidable charge about the corn.
     <milestone n="23" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>What sort of accusation, then, is this, O Triarius? First of all, that you did not go to
    examine into it. What was the meaning of the fierce and positive confidence that you had as to
    trusting this man? It seems to me that when we were children we heard that Lucius Aelius, a
    freedman, a well-educated and witty man, when he was avenging injuries sustained by his patron,
    instituted a prosecution against Quintus Multo, a very mean man. And when he was asked what
    province he required to conduct his investigation in, or how many days he would want to collect
    his witnesses in, he asked till eight o'clock, during which time he might prosecute his
    investigation in the cattle-market. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>Did you think that you
    were to act in the same way in the case of Marcus Aemilius Scaurus? “Yes,” says he, “for the
    whole cause was fully reported to me at Rome.” Well? Did not the Sicilians lay before me every
    particular of the cause of Sicily while we were both at Rome? And they were men prudent by
    nature, cunning by experience, and learned by education. And still I thought it necessary to go
    into the province itself; for the purpose of coming to a right understanding and thorough
    knowledge of the cause of the province. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>Was I not bound to
    examine into the complaints and injuries of the cultivators of the soil, in the very lands and
    fields themselves? I traveled, I say, O Triarius, in a most bitter winter over the valleys and
    hills of the Agrigentines. That noble and most fertile plain of the Leontini itself; I may
    almost say, instructed me in the cause. I visited the cottages of the farmers; men talked with
    me at the plough; <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>and therefore that cause was so thoroughly
    sifted and laid open by me, that the judges seemed not so much to hear the facts which I
    related, as to see them and lay hold of them. For it seemed neither reasonable nor honest for
    me, when I had undertaken the cause of a most faithful and ancient province, to learn the
    particulars of it as I might have done in the case of an individual client, in my chamber.
     <milestone n="27" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>When lately the people of Reate, who were devoted to my interest, wished me to plead the
    public cause of their state, concerning the streams of the Velinus and the subterranean canals,
    before the present consuls, I do not think that I should either satisfy the claims of the
    dignity of a most eminent prefecture, or do all that was required by good faith on my part, if I
    did not get instruction as to the cause not only from the people themselves, but from the place
    also and from the lake itself. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>Nor would you have acted in any
    different manner, O Triarius, if those Sardinians of yours had wished you to do so; I mean those
    who in reality were above all things unwilling that you should enter Sardinia, lest you should
    find that everything was in a totally different condition from that in which it had been
    represented to you; that there were no complaints on the part of the people in Sardinia, nor any
    hatred of the populace towards Scaurus. [And consider, O Triarius, how vast a difference there
    is between your accusation and mine; I never delayed one moment until, just as Jupiter (if we
    believe the fables of the poets) covered over Enceladus when he was stricken down and half burnt
    by putting the whole island on him, or as some say Typhon,] <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
    [by whose panting they say that Aetna is kept constantly on fire,—until, I say, I had in the
    same manner overwhelmed Verres by producing all Sicily as a witness against him.] You adjourned
    the case against the defendant after one witness had been produced. And what a witness! O ye
    immortal gods! It was not enough that he was only one; it was not enough that he was a man
    utterly unknown; it was not enough that he was a man on whom no one could rely. Did you not ruin
    also your former trial by producing Valerius as a witness, who, having had the rights of a
    citizen conferred on him by the favour of your father, requited his kindness not by honourable
    services, but by open perjury? <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>But if you were perhaps swayed
    by the omen of your name, still we, according to the precedent of our ancestors, because we
    think that a fortunate omen, interpret it not to the injury of others, but to their safety. But
    all that rapidity and haste, the fact of your having put an end to the investigation and to the
    whole of the previous trial, has made that plain and notorious—which, however, was never a
    secret—that this trial was contrived, not for the sake of justice, but because of the consular
     <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>And while speaking on this point, I will on no occasion find fault with Appius Claudius, a
    most gallant consul and a most accomplished man, and who, as I hope, is connected with me by a
    trustworthy and lasting reconciliation. For this part belonged either to that man whom his own
    indignation and suspicion compelled to act in that manner, or to him who requested that part for
    himself; because either he did not perceive whom he was attacking, or because he thought that
    the path to a reconciliation would be easy. <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>I will only say
    this, which may be sufficient for my cause and which cannot appear otherwise than far removed
    from harshness or severity towards him. For what disgrace is there in the fact of Appius
    Claudius being an enemy to Marcus Scaurus? What, I say? Was not his grandfather an enemy to
    Publius Africanus? What, I say? Is not that very man himself an enemy to me? Or am not I to him?
    And those enmities have perhaps at times caused vexation to each of us, but certainly have never
    brought disgrace upon either of us. <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>The one who was quitting
    office envied his successor, and wished him to meet with as many disasters as possible in order
    that his own memory might be the more conspicuous. A state of things not only not foreign to our
    habits, but one that has become very usual, and exceedingly frequent. Nor indeed would such an
    everyday occurrence have of itself had any influence at all upon Appius Claudius, a man endowed
    with the greatest humanity and wisdom, if he had not thought that Scaurus was going to be a
    competitor of Caius Claudius his brother. <milestone n="34" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>Who, whether he was a patrician, or a plebeian, (for he had not yet settled that for a
    certainty,) thought that the contest would lie chiefly with him: and Appius thought it would be
    so much the more severe a contest because he recollected that when standing for the pontificate,
    for the priesthood of Mars, and for other offices, he had stood as a patrician. <milestone
     n="35" unit="section"/>Wherefore, while he was consul he did not wish his brother to meet with
    a repulse, and yet if he stood as a patrician, he saw that he would certainly not be equal to
    Scaurus, unless he could get rid of him either by some terror, or by some disgrace. </p>
   <p>Should not I think that a brother may be excused for such an idea, when the most distinguished
    honours of his brother are at stake, especially when I am aware, almost beyond all other men,
    how great is the influence of brotherly love? Oh, but his brother is now not a candidate. What
    then? If he, having been detained by all Asia, which came to him as his suppliant—if he,
    yielding to the entreaties of the men of business, and of the farmers of the revenues, and of
    all men both allies and citizens, preferred the advantage and safety of the province to the
    acquisition of honour for himself; is that a reason for your thinking that a disposition once
    thoroughly diseased can be so easily cured? <milestone n="36" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>Although, in all those affairs, especially among barbarian nations, opinion is often of more
    influence than the facts <pb n="517"/> themselves. The Sardinians were persuaded that they could
    do nothing which would be more acceptable to Appius than if they disparaged the reputation of
    Scaurus. They are swayed besides by the hope of many advantages and many rewards; they thank
    that a consul can do everything, especially when he makes promises of his own accord. About
    which I will not at present say any more; although what I have said I have said in no other
    manner than I should have said them if I had been his brother; not such an one as he is who is
    his brother, and who has said a great deal, but such an one as I am accustomed to be towards my
    own brother. You ought, therefore, O judges, to resist every part of an accusation of this sort,
    in which nothing is done according to precedent nothing with moderation, nothing with
    consideration, nothing with integrity; but, on the contrary, you see that everything has been
    undertaken wickedly, turbulently, precipitately, rapidly,—everything by means of a conspiracy,
    and of absolute power, and of illegal influence, and of hopes, and of threats. <milestone n="38"
     unit="section"/></p>
   <p>I come now to the witnesses; and I will not only show that there is no confidence to be placed
    in, no authority to be attributed to them, but I will prove that there is not even any
    appearance of or resemblance to evidence in them. In truth, in the first place, the minute
    agreement between them all destroys their credibility, which was proved by the reading of the
    undertaking entered into by the Sardinians, and by the conspiracy which they formed. Secondly,
    their covetousness, which was excited by the hope and promise of rewards, does so too. Lastly,
    their national origin does so, for the worthlessness of their nation is such that they think
    that liberty is only to be distinguished from slavery by the boundless licence for telling lies
    which it gives. <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>Nor do [I say] that these judges ought never
    to be influenced by the complaints of the Sardinians. I am not so inhuman, nor so hostile to the
    Sardinians, especially when my brother has only lately left their island, having been sent
    thither by Cnaeus Pompeius to superintend the corn-markets and supplies of the island; in which
    office he, as became his integrity and humanity, consulted their interests himself, and was in
    turn very popular and very much beloved among them. <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>Let then
    this refuge be open to indignation, let it be open to just complaints, but let the path be
    closed against conspiracy, let it be closed against treachery: and this not more among the
    Sardinians than among the Gauls, among the Africans, and among the Spaniards. Titus Albucius was
    condemned; Caius Meguboccus was condemned on account of complaints proceeding from Sardinia,
    though some of the Sardinians even praised him. And in that case the very variety of their
    sentiments gained them the more credit. For those men were convicted by fair witnesses, and by
    documents which no one had tampered with. <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>Now there is but one
    language and one feeling; one not extorted by indignation, but feigned; not excited by the
    injuries inflicted by this man, but by the promises and bribes of others. But the Sardinians
    have not been always disbelieved. And perhaps they will again be believed sometime or other, if
    they come like honest men, and without having been bribed, and of their own accord, and not
    because of the instigation of any one else, and under no obligation to any one, and free. And
    when all these circumstances are united, still they may exult and marvel if they are believed.
    But when these circumstances are all wanting, will they still persist in forgetting who they
    are? will they not take care to shun the reputation of their race? <milestone n="42"
     unit="section"/></p>
   <p>All the monuments of the ancients and all histories have handed down to us the tradition that
    the nation of the Phoenicians is the most treacherous of all nations. The Poeni, who are
    descended from them, have proved by many rebellions of the Carthaginians, and very many broken
    and violated treaties, that they have in no respect degenerated from them. The Sardinians, who
    are sprung from the Poeni, with an admixture of African blood, were not led into Sardinia as
    colonists and established there, but are rather a tribe who were draughted off, and put there to
    get rid of them. <milestone n="43" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>Wherefore, as there was never anything honest in the nation when united, how must we suppose
    that its roguery has been sharpened by so many mixtures of different races? And here Cnaeus
    Domitius Sincerus, a most accomplished man, my ancient and intimate friend, will pardon me <gap
     reason="****"/> all who had the freedom of the city conferred on them by the same Cnaeus
    Pompeius; all of whom we now cite as favourable witnesses; and other virtuous men from Sardinia
    will pardon me; for I believe there are some such men there. <milestone n="44" unit="section"
    />Nor indeed, when I speak of the vices of the nation, do I except no one. But I am forced to
    speak generally of the entire race; in which, perhaps, some individuals by their own civilized
    habits and natural humanity have got the better of the vices of their family and nation. That
    the greater part of the nation is destitute of faith, destitute of any community and connection
    with our name, the facts themselves plainly show. For what province is there besides Sardinia
    which has not one city in it on friendly terms with the Roman people, not one free city?
     <milestone n="45a" unit="section"/></p>
   <p>Africa itself is the parent of Sardinia, which has waged many most bitter wars against our
    ancestors, and not only in its kingdoms which were loyal to their native monarchs, but even in
    our very province, it kept itself from all alliance with us at the time of the Punic wars as the
    case of Utica proves. The further Spain ennobled by the de[ath of the Scipios, and by the
    funeral pile of the Saguntine loyalty, has the city of Gades joined to us by reciprocal good
    offices, by common dangers, and by treaty. I ask now whether any city of Sardinia can be
    mentioned which is joined to us by treaty? Not one. With what face, then, can a Sardinian
    witness dare to come before the Roman people] <gap reason="***"/> powerless in resources,
    treacherous by descent? <gap reason="****"/> [Have you, too, come hither to repulse Marcus
    Scaurus from the consulship, and are you attempting to deprive him of the kindness of the Roman
    people? By what authority are you acting in this manner?] </p>
   <p>[The prosecutor has said that you are afraid lest Scaurus might purchase the consulship with
    that money which he has taken from the allies; and, as his father did before him, enter on his
    province before any decision could be come to respecting him, and again plunder other provinces
    before he gave any account of his former administration; and Triarius alleged this as the very
    reason why he had undertaken the conduct of this prosecution in so hasty and so disorderly a
    manner. What extraordinary thing is this? What prodigy is this?] <gap reason="****"/> Did the
    sheepskins of the Sardinians move that man whom the royal purple could not influence <gap
     reason="****"/>
   </p>
   <p>[For there is no one so completely a stranger in this city, no one whose ears are so much on
    their travels, and so wholly ignorant of the ordinary conversation in the republic, as not to
    know that Marcus Scaurus, when his step-father Sulla was victorious, and liberal enough to his
    comrades in victory, was so moderate that he would not allow any presents to be made to him, nor
    did he purchase anything at any auction. This seems a strange thing to others; but it was
    impossible for him to act otherwise. For he recollected that he was the son of that man, who, by
    the resolution of the senate, of which he was the chief; and almost by his own nod, had
    governed, I may almost say, the entire world. Wherefore, O you venal Sardinians, I command you
     <gap reason="***"/>] <gap reason="****"/> when you hear this name, which is well known among
    all the nations upon earth, to entertain also, with respect to that noble family, the same
    sentiments which all the rest of the earth entertains. </p>
   <p>[At present, Marcus Scaurus, in mourning attire, worn out with tears and misery, is your
    suppliant, O judges, implores the aid of your good faith, entreats your pity and clemency, and
    fixes his eyes and hopes on your power and your protection. Do not, I entreat you, by the
    immortal gods, O judges, permit your fellow-citizen and suppliant to be deprived by unknown
    witnesses and barbarians, not only of the consulship by which he trusted to receive an accession
    of honour, but also of the other distinctions which he had acquired before, and of all his
    dignity and fortune. Scaurus, O judges, also begs and entreats you to save him from this, if he
    has never injured any one unjustly, nor offended any one's ears or inclination, if (to use the
    mildest expression) he has never given any one any reason to hate him. Once only has his filial
    affection imposed on him the duty of so doing] <gap reason="****"/>
   </p>
   <p><gap reason="****"/>for as, out of many men who had done so, Dolabella was the only one of his
    father's enemies who remained, who had joined Quintus Caepio, his relation, in signing articles
    of accusation against Scaurus his father; he thought it behoved him for the sake of [his filial
    affection to continue that enmity which he had not originated himself; but had bequeathed to him
    as an inheritance; emulating Marcus and Lucius Lucullus, who being men of like industry and like
    piety with himself; when very young men, had adopted and followed out the quarrels of their
    fathers to their own great glory.] </p>
   <p>[But how great has been the injustice of Triarius accusing Scaurus of having so magnificent a
    house! Oh for that ancient and severe censor; according to whom even a man who had attained the
    highest honours of the state, and who was one of the chief men in it, was not allowed to have a
    convenient or splendid house] <gap reason="****"/> especially when its nearness to the street,
    and the populous character of its situation, must remove from him all suspicion of laziness or
    ambition.</p>
   <p>
    <gap reason="******"/>
   </p>
   <p>[But in what an arrogant way, O Triarius, did your oration go on, when you said that such
    enormous masses of Lucullus's marbles and pillars, which we now see placed in Scaurus's hall,
    were carried through the city, past the plaster ornaments on the tops of the temples of the
    gods, to a private house,—that the contractor for keeping the drains in repair had a claim for
    the damage done by dragging them up the Palatine Hill in wagons. I suppose those pillars which
    are thus held up to odium were carried there solely for the purpose of gratifying the pride of
    individuals, which the Roman people detests, and not for the sake of being a public ornament to
    the city, which it approves of. Are you the only man in Rome ignorant that Scaurus used those
    pillars when he was aedile for the ornamenting of the theatre, in order that, by the
    magnificence of his exhibition, and by his great liberality devoted in that manner to the honour
    of the immortal gods, he might increase the religious reverence with which the games were
    observed by the splendour of his preparation?] <gap reason="***"/></p>
   <p><gap reason="***"/>Moreover, I, who have pillars of Alban marble, brought them up in panniers!
     <gap reason="***"/></p>
   <p> [What? what vast and what prodigal expense did you yourself, O Triarius, incur in procuring
    pillars!] </p>
   <p><gap reason="***"/>For this I do marvel at and of this I do complain,—that any man should be
    so anxious to do injury to another by his words, as to bore holes in the ship in which he
    himself is sailing. <gap reason="***"/></p>
   <p><gap reason="***"/>Were you in want of a house? You had one. Had you too much money? You were
    in want of money. But you went mad after pillars. You were frantic to get hold of what belonged
    to other people. You valued a pulled down, windowless, destroyed house, at a greater price than
    yourself and all your fortunes. <gap reason="***"/>
   </p>
   <p>[What then? Suppose Scaurus had appealed to you as an arbitrator, to decide “whether you had
    not gone to much greater expense, whether you had not committed much greater extravagance in
    proportion to your income, for pillars than he had,” would it have been necessary to go through
    the formalities of a trial to decide whether he had been guilty of prodigality, who, being
    possessed of a most ample estate, and of great family wealth and reputation, had set off his
    dignity with a fine house, or he who, when he was over head and ears in debt before, had sought
    to obtain dignity by building a house?] <gap reason="***"/>
   </p>
   <p>As it would not be possible for you to escape this argument, will you still argue and demand
    that Marcus Aemilius, with all his own dignity,—with the splendid memory of his father,—with the
    renown of his grandfather, be sacrificed to a most sordid, fickle and insignificant nation, and
    to a lot of (I had almost said) barbarian witnesses? <gap reason="***"/></p>
   <p><gap reason="***"/>Wherever I turn, not only my thoughts, but even my eyes, every place
    supplies me with arguments to advance in favour of Marcus Scaurus. That senate-house bears
    witness to you of the fearless and dignified way in which his father held the post of the chief
    man of the city. Lucius Metellus himself, his grandfather, appears, O judges, to have placed
    those most holy gods in that temple in your sight, that they might gain from you the safety of
    his grandson by their entreaties, as they have, before now, often aided by their divine
    assistance many other men in distress who implored their help. That Capitol, adorned with three
    temples,—the approaches to the temples of the all-good and all-powerful Jupiter, and of Juno the
    queen, and of Minerva, adorned by most magnificent presents of this man's father and of himself;
    defend Marcus Scaurus [before you now by the recollection of this munificence and liberality to
    the public, from every suspicion of avarice or covetousness. That temple of Vesta, which is
    close at hand, warns you to keep it in your minds.] That great Lucius Metellus, the Pontifex
    Maximus, who, when that temple was on fire threw himself into the middle of the flames, and
    saved from the fire that image of Minerva, which, as if it were a pledge of our safety and of
    the empire, is guarded by the protection of Vesta;—would that that great man could be among us,
    though but for a short time; he, forsooth, would save from the flames this man, his descendant,
    as he before saved from that other conflagration that heavenly pledge of our safety. I am moved
    by the thought that the gods should be so little propitious to a priest, that even though they
    were saved by him, they do not preserve his race which was recommended by him to their
    protection. But as for you, O Marcus Scaurus, I see you, I do not merely think of you; nor,
    indeed, is it without great distress and grief of mind that I do call you to mind when I behold
    the mournful appearance of your son. </p>
   <p>And I wish that, as during the whole of this cause you have been constantly present before my
    eyes, you would, in like manner, now present yourself to the minds of these our judges, and
    plant yourself deeply in all their thoughts. If your appearance, I call [the gods to witness,
    could come to life again, (for we have never seen any one equal to you in wisdom, and dignity,
    and firmness, and all other virtues,) it would have such weight with every one, that whoever
    beheld it] even if by chance he did not recognise it would still pronounce it to be one of the
    chief men in the state. </p>
   <p>How, then, can I now address you? As a man? But you are no longer among us. As a deceased
    person? But you live and flourish; but you are present to the minds of all this court,—you are
    visible to their eyes; your godlike soul had nothing mortal about it, nor was anything belonging
    to you which could die, except your body. Whatever way, therefore, [it is proper for you to be
    addressed, be present to us, I entreat you, and terrify, by your mere countenance,—by the bare
    sight of yourself; the emptiness and impudence of those most worthless and mendacious witnesses.
    Be present to us, and bring to your fellow-citizens the light of your counsel, to the authority
    of which they never repented deferring, and so prevent them from dishonouring your race with
    ignominy and disaster, and from crushing by their sentence your own son, who is no degenerate
    heir of his father's name.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>

</TEI>
