<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
w<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight books - 8</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight Books</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1857</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/4/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="503" xml:id="p.503"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="book">
                <head>BOOK VIII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> The Latins with the Campanians revolt; and ambassadors having been sent to
                        the senate, they propose that, if they wished for peace, they should elect
                        one of the consuls from among the Latins. Titus Manlius, the consul, put his
                        son to death, because he had fought, though successfully, against the
                        Latins, contrary to orders. The Romans being hard pressed in the battle,
                        Publius Decius, then consul with Manlius, devoted himself for the army. The
                        Latins surrender. None of the young men came out to meet Manlius on his
                        return to the city. Minucia, a vestal virgin was con- demned for incest.
                        Several matrons convicted of poisoning. Laws then first made against that
                        crime. The Ausonians, Privernian, and Pa- laepolitans subdued. Quintus
                        Publilius the first instance of a person con- tinuing in command after the
                        expiration of his office, and of triumph decreed to any person not a consul.
                        Law against confinement for debt. Quintus Fabius, master of the horse,
                        fights the Samnites with success, contrary to the orders of Lucius Papirius,
                        dictator; and, with difficulty, obtains pardon, through the intercession of
                        the people. Successful expe- dition against the Samnites. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THE consuls now were Caius Plautius a second
                    time, and Lucius Aemilius Mamercinus; when the people of Setia and Norba came to
                    Rome to announce the revolt of he Privernians, with complaints of the damages
                    received by them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> News were brought that the
                    army of the Volscians, under the guidance of the people of Antium, had taken
                    post at Satricum. Both wars fell by lot to Plautius. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He, marching first to Privernum, immediately came to an
                    engagement. The enemy were defeated after a slight resistance: the town was
                    taken, and given back to the Privernians, a strong garrison being placed in it:
                    two thirds of their land were taken front them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> The victorious army was marched thence to Satricum against the Antians; there
                    a desperate battle was fought with great slaughter on both sides; and when a
                    storm separated the combatants, hope inclining to neither side, the Romans,
                    nowise disheartened by this so indecisive an engagement, pre- <pb n="504"
                        xml:id="p.504"/> pare for battle against the following day. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Volscians, reckoning up what men they had lost in
                    battle, had by no means the same spirits to repeat the risk. They went off in
                    the night to Antium as a vanquished army in the utmost confusion, leaving behind
                    their wounded and a part of their baggage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A
                    vast quantity of arms was found, both among the dead bodies of the enemy, and
                    also in the camp. These, the consul declared, that he offered up to Mother Lua;
                    and he laid waste the enemy's country as far as the sea-coast. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The other consul, Aemilius, on entering the Sabellan
                    territory, found neither a camp of the Samnites nor legions opposed to him.
                    Whilst he laid waste their territories with fire and sword, the ambassadors of
                    the Samnites came to him, suing for peace; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> by
                    whom being referred to the senate, after leave to address them was granted,
                    laying aside their ferocious spirits, they sued for peace for themselves from
                    the Romans, and the right of waging war against the Sidicinians. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Which requests, [they alleged,] that <quote> they
                        were the more justified in making, because they had both united in
                        friendship with the Roman people, when their affairs were flourishing, not
                        under circumstances of distress, as the Campanians had done, and they were
                        taking up arms against the Sidicinians, ever their enemies, never the
                        friends of the Roman people; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> who had
                        neither, as the Samnites, sought their friendship in time of peace, nor, as
                        the Campanians, their assistance in time of war, and were neither in
                        alliance with, nor under subjection to the Roman people. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the praetor Tiberius Aemilius had
                    consulted the senate respecting the demands of the Samnites, and the senate
                    voted that the treaty should be renewed with them, the praetor returned this
                    answer to the Samnites: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "That it neither had
                    been the fault of the Roman people that their friendship with them was not
                    perpetual; nor was any objection made to that friendship being once more
                    re-established, since they themselves were now become tired of a war entered
                    into through their own fault. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> With respect to
                    what regarded the Sidicinians, they did not interfere with the Samnite nation
                    having the free decision of peace and war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    treaty being concluded, on their return home, the Roman army was immediately
                    withdrawn after they had received a year's pay, and corn for three months: for
                    which the consul had stipulated, to grant time for a truce, <pb n="505"
                        xml:id="p.505"/> until the ambassadors should return. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Samnites having marched against the Sidicinians with
                    the same force which they had employed in their war against the Romans, enter-
                    tained rather sanguine hopes of becoming masters of the ene- mies' citadel.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then the Sidicinians first began to
                    surrender to the Romans. Afterwards, when the senate rejected that offer as too
                    late, and as being wrung from them by extreme necessity, it was made to the
                    Latins, who were already taking up arms on their own account. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Nor did even the Campanians (so much stronger was their
                    recollection of the injuries done them by the Samnites than of the kindness of
                    the Romans) keep themselves from this quarrel. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Out of these so many states, one vast army, entering the territories of the
                    Samnites under the direction of the Latins, committed more damage by
                    depredations than by battles; and though the Latins had the advantage in the
                    field, they retired out of the enemies' territory without reluctance, that they
                    might not be obliged to fight too frequently. This opportunity was afforded to
                    the Samnites to send ambassadors to Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                    they appeared before the senate, having complained that they, though now
                    confederates, were subjected to the same hardships as those they had suffered as
                    enemies, solicited, with the humblest entreaties, that <quote> the Romans would
                        think it enough <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the victory, of which
                        they had deprived the Samnites, over their Campanian and Sidicinian enemy;
                        that they would not besides suffer them to be vanquished by these most
                        dastardly states. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That they could by
                        their sovereign authority keep the Latins and the Campanians out of the
                        Samnite territory, if they really were under the dominion of the Roman
                        people; but if they rejected their authority, that they might compel them by
                        arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To this an equivocal answer was returned,
                    because it was mortifying to acknowledge, that the Latins were not now in their
                    power, and they were afraid lest by finding fault they might estrange them from
                    their side: <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> that the case of the Campanians
                    was different, they having come under their protection, not by treaty but by
                    surrender: accordingly, that the Campanians, whether they wished or not, should
                    remain quiet: that in the Latin treaty there was no clause by which they were
                    prevented from going to war with whomsoever they pleased. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Which answer, whilst it sent away the Samnites
                    uncertain <pb n="506" xml:id="p.506"/> as to what conduct they were to think
                    that the Romans would pursue, it further estranged the Campanians through fear;
                    it rendered the Samnites more presuming, they considering that there was nothing
                    which the Romans would now refuse them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore, proclaiming frequent meetings under the pretext of preparing for war
                    against the Samnites, their leading men, in their several deliberations among
                    themselves, secretly fomented the plan of a war with Rome. In this war the
                    Campanians too joined against their preservers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> But though all their schemes were carefully concealed, and they were anxious
                    that their Samnite enemy should be got rid of in their rear before the Romans
                    should be aroused, yet through the agency of some who were attached [to the
                    latter] by private <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> friendships and other
                    ties, information of their conspiracy made its way to Rome, and the consuls
                    being ordered to resign their office before the usual time, in order that the
                    new consuls might be elected the sooner to meet so important a war, a religious
                    scruple entered their minds at the idea of the elections being held by persons
                    whose time of office had been cut short. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly an interregnum took place. There were two interreges, Marcus
                    Valerius and Marcus Fabius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls
                    elected were Titus Manlius Torquatus a third time, and Publius Decius Mus. It is
                    agreed on that, in this year, Alexander, king of Epirus, made a descent on Italy
                    with a fleet. Which war, if the first commencement had been sufficiently
                    successful, would unquestionably have extended to the Romans. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The same was the era of the exploits of Alexander the
                    Great, whom, being son to the other's sister, in another region of the world,
                    having shown himself invincible in war, fortune cut short in his youth by
                    disease. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the Romans, although the revolt
                    of their allies and of the Latin nation was now no matter of doubt, yet as if
                    they felt solicitude regarding the Samnites, not for themselves, summoned ten of
                    the leading men of the Latins to Rome, to whom they wished to issue such orders
                    as they might wish. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Latium had at that time
                    two praetors, Lucius Annius, a native of Setia, and Lucius Numisius of Circeii,
                    both from the Roman colonists; through whose means, be- sides Signia and
                    Velitrae, also Roman colonies, the Volscians too had been stirred up to arms.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was determined that these two should
                    be summoned specially; it was a matter of <pb n="507" xml:id="p.507"/> doubt to
                    no one, on what matter they were sent for. Accordingly the praetors, having held
                    an assembly, before they set out for Rome, inform them, that they were summoned
                    by the Roman senate, and consult them as to what answer it was their wish should
                    be given on those subjects which they thought would be discussed with them. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When different persons advanced different
                    opinions, then Annius says: <quote> Though I myself put the question, as to what
                        answer it might be your pleasure should be given, yet I think it more
                        concerns our general interest how we should act than how we should speak.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Your plans being once unfolded, it
                        will be easy to suit words to the subject; for if even now we are capable of
                        submitting to slavery under the shadow of a confederacy on equal terms, what
                        is wanting but to betray the Sidicinians, be obedient to the orders not only
                        of the Romans, but of the Samnites, and tell the Romans, that we will lay
                        down our arms whenever they intimate it to be their wish? <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> But if at length a desire of liberty stimulates your
                        minds, if a confederacy does subsist, if alliance be equalization of rights,
                        if there be reason now to boast that we are of the same blood as the Romans,
                        of which they were formerly ashamed, if they have such an army of allies, by
                        the junction of which they may double their strength, such a one as their
                        consuls would be unwilling to separate from themselves either in concluding
                        or commencing their own wars; why are not all things equalized? <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> why is not one of the consuls chosen from the
                        Latins? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Where there is an equal share of
                        strength, is there also an equal share in the government? This indeed in
                        itself reflects no extraordinary degree of honour on us, as still
                        acknowledging Rome to be the metropolis of Latium; but that it may possibly
                        appear to do so, has been effected by our long-continued forbearance.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But if ye ever wished for an
                        opportunity of sharing in the government, and enjoying freedom, lo!
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> this opportunity is now at hand,
                        presented both by your own valour and the bounty of the gods. Ye have tried
                        their patience by refusing them soldiers. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Who doubts that they were fired with rage, when we broke through a custom of
                        more than two hundred years? Still they submitted to this feeling of
                        resentment. We waged war with the Pelignians in our own name. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> They who formerly did not even concede to us the
                        right of defending our own territories through our- <pb n="508"
                            xml:id="p.508"/> selves, interfered not. They heard that the Sidicinians
                        were received under our protection, that the Campanians had revolted from
                        themselves to us, that we were preparing armies against their confederates,
                        the Samnites; yet they stirred not from the city. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Whence this so great forbearance on their part, except
                        from a knowledge of our strength and their own? I have it from competent
                        authority, that when the Samnites complained of us, such an answer was given
                        them by the Roman senate, as plainly showed that not even themselves
                        insisted that Latium was under the Roman jurisdiction. Only assume your
                        rights in demanding that which they tacitly concede to you. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> If fear prevents any one from saying this, lo! I
                        pledge myself that I will say it, in the hearing not only of the Roman
                        people and senate, but of Jupiter himself, who inhabits the Capitol; that if
                        they wish us to be in confederacy and alliance with them, they are to
                        receive one consul from us, and one half of the senate. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When he not only recommended these measures
                    boldly, but promised also his aid, they all, with acclamations of assent,
                    permitted him to do and say whatever might appear to him conducive to the
                    republic of the Latin nation and his own honour. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they arrived in Rome, an audience of the
                    senate was granted them in the Capitol. There, when Titus Manlius the consul, by
                    direction of the senate, required of them not to make war on their confederates
                    the Samnites, Annius, as if <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> he had taken the
                    Capitol by arms as a victor, and were not addressing them as an ambassador
                    protected by the law of nations, says: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> It were time, Titus Manlius, and you, conscript fathers, to cease at
                        length treating with us on a footing of superiority, when you see Latium in
                        a most flourishing state by the bounty of the gods in arms and men, the
                        Samnites being vanquished in war, the Sidicinians and Campanians our allies,
                        the Volscians now united to us in alliance, and that your own colonies even
                        prefer the government of Latium to that of Rome. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> But since ye do not bring your minds to put an end to
                        your arbitrary despotism, we, though able by force of arms to vindicate the
                        independence of Latium, yet will make this concession to the ties of blood
                        between us, as to offer terms of peace on terms <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> of equality for both, since it has pleased the immortal
                        gods that the strength of both is equalized. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> One of the consuls must be selected out of Rome, <pb n="509"
                            xml:id="p.509"/> the other out of Latium; an equal portion of the senate
                        must be from both nations; we must be one people, one republic; and that the
                        seat of government may be the same, and we all may have the same name, since
                        the concession must be made by the one party or other, let this, and may it
                        be auspicious to both, have the advantage of being the mother country, and
                        let us all be called Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It so happened that the Romans also had a
                    consul, a match for this man's high spirit; who, so far from restraining his
                    angry feelings, openly declared, that if such infatuation took possession of the
                    conscript fathers, that they would receive laws from a man of Setia, he would
                    him- self come into the senate armed with a sword, and would slay with his hand
                    any Latin whom he should see in the senate- house. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> And turning to the statue of Jupiter, <quote>Hear thou,
                        Jupiter,</quote> says he, <quote> hear these impious proposals; hear ye
                        them, Justice and Equity. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Jupiter, art
                        thou to behold foreign consuls and a foreign senate in thy consecrated
                        temple, as if thou wert a captive and overpowered? Were these the treaties
                        which Tullus, a Roman king, concluded with the Albans, your forefathers,
                        Latins, and which Lucius Tarquinius subsequently concluded with you?
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Does not the battle at the Lake
                        Regillus occur to your thoughts? Have you so forgotten your own calamities
                        and our kindnesses towards you? </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the indignation of the senate followed
                    these words of the consul, it is recorded that, in reply to the frequent ap-
                    peals to the gods, whom the consuls frequently invoked as witnesses to the
                    treaties, an expression of Annius was heard in contempt of the divinity of the
                    Roman Jupiter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Certainly, when aroused with
                    wrath he was proceeding with rapid steps from the porch of the temple, having
                    fallen down the stairs, his head being severely struck, he was dashed against a
                    stone at the bottom with such force, as to be deprived of sense. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> As all writers do not say that he was killed, I too
                    shall leave it in doubt; as also the circumstance, that a storm, with a dreadful
                    noise in the heavens, took place during the appeal made in reference to the
                    violated treaties; for they may both be true, and also invented aptly to express
                    in a striking manner the resentment of heaven. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Torquatus, being despatched by the senate to dismiss the ambassadors, on seeing
                    Annius lying prostrate, exclaimed, so as that his voice was heard both by the
                    people and the senate, <quote> It is well. The gods have excited a <pb n="510"
                            xml:id="p.510"/> just war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There is a
                        deity in heaven. Thou dost exist, great Jove; not without reason have we
                        consecrated thee the father of gods and men in this mansion. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Why do ye hesitate, Romans, and you, conscript
                        fathers, to take up arms under the direction of the gods? Thus will I lay
                        low the legions of the Latins, as you now see this man lying prostrate. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The words of the consul, received with the
                    approbation of the people, filled their breasts with such ardour, that the
                    ambassadors on their departure were protected from the anger and violence of the
                    people more by the care of the magistrates, who escorted them by order of the
                    consul, than by the law of nations. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The senate
                    also voted for the war; and the consuls, after raising two armies, marched into
                    the territories of the Marsians and Pelignians, the army of the Samnites having
                    joined them, and pitched their camp near Capua, where the Latins and their
                    allies had now assembled. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There it is said
                    there appeared to both the consuls, during sleep, the same form of a man larger
                    and more majestic than human, who said, <quote> Of the one side a general, of
                        the other an army was due to the dii Manes and to Mother Earth; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> from whichever army a general should devote the
                        legions of the enemy and himself, in addition, that the victory would belong
                        to that nation and that party. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When the consuls compared together these
                    visions of the night, it was resolved that victims should be slain for the
                    purpose of averting the anger of the gods; at the same time, that if the same
                    portents were exhibited in the entrails as those which had been seen during
                    sleep, either of the consuls should fulfil the fates. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> When the answers of the haruspices coincided with the
                    secret religious impression already implanted in their minds; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> then, having brought together the lieutenant-generals and
                    tribunes, and having openly expounded to them the commands of the gods, they
                    settle among themselves, lest the consul's voluntary death should intimidate the
                    army in the field, that on which side soever the Roman army should commence to
                    give way, the consul in that quarter should devote himself for the Roman people
                    and the Quirites. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> In this consultation it was
                    also suggested, that if ever on any occasion any war had been conducted with
                    strict discipline, then indeed military discipline should be reduced to the
                    ancient standard. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> What excited their
                    attention particularly was, that they had to contend against Latins, who
                    coincided with themselves in lan- <pb n="511" xml:id="p.511"/> guage, manners,
                    in the same kind of arms, and more especially in military institutions; soldiers
                    had been mixed with soldiers, centurions with centurions, tribunes with
                    tribunes, as com- rades and colleagues, in the same armies, and often in the
                    same companies. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Lest in consequence of this
                    the soldiers should be involved in any mistake, the consuls issue orders that no
                    one should fight against an enemy out of his post. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened that among the other prefects of
                    the troops, who had been sent out in all directions to reconnoitre, Titus
                    Manlius, the consul's son, came with his troop to the back of the enemy's camp,
                    so near that he was scarcely distant a dart's throw from the next post.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In that place were some Tusculan cavalry;
                    they were commanded by Geminus Metius, a man distinguished among his countrymen
                    both by birth and ex- ploits. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he
                    recognised the Roman cavalry, and con- spicuous among them the consul's son
                    marching at their head, (for they were all known <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> to each other, especially the men of note,) <quote> Romans,
                        are ye going to wage war with the Latins and allies with a single troop.
                        What in the interim will the con- suls, what will the two consular armies be
                        doing? </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>They will be here in good time,</quote> says Manlius, <quote> and with
                        them will be Jupiter himself, as a witness of the treaties violated by you,
                        who is stronger and more powerful. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If we
                        fought at the lake Regillus until you had quite enough, here also we shall
                        so act, that a line of battle and an encounter with us may afford you no
                        very great gratification. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In reply to this, Geminus, advancing some
                    distance from his own party, says, <quote> Do you choose then, until that day
                        arrives on which you are to put your armies in motion with such mighty
                        labour, to enter the lists with me, that from the result of a contest
                        between us both, it may be seen how much a Latin excels a Roman horseman? </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Either resentment, or shame at declining the
                    contest, or the invincible power of fate, arouses the determined spirit of the
                    youth. Forgetful therefore of his father's command, and the consul's edict, he
                    is driven headlong to that contest, in which it made not much difference whether
                    he conquered or was conquered. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The other
                    horsemen being removed to a distance as if to witness the sight, in the space of
                    clear ground which lay between them they spurred on their horses against each
                    other; and when they were together in fierce encounter, the spear of Manlius
                    passed over the helmet of his antagonist, that of Me- <pb n="512" xml:id="p.512"
                    /> Metius across the neck of the other's horse. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Then wheeling round their horses, when Manlius arose to repeat the blow, he
                    fixed his javelin between the ears of his opponent's horse. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> When, by the pain of this wound, the horse, having raised
                    his fore-feet on high, tossed his head with great violence, he shook off his
                    rider, whom, when he was raising himself from the severe fall, by leaning on his
                    spear and buckler, Manlius pierced through the throat, so that the steel passed
                    out through the ribs, and pinned him to the earth; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and having collected the spoils, he returned to his own
                    party, and with his troop, who were exulting with joy, he proceeds to <milestone
                        n="13??" unit="section"/> the camp, and thence to the general's tent to his
                    father, ignorant of what awaited him, whether praise or punishment had been
                    merited. <quote>Father,</quote> says he, <quote> that all may truly represent me
                        as sprung from your blood; when challenged, I slew my adversary, and have
                        taken from him these equestrian spoils. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When the consul heard this, immediately
                    turning away from his son, he ordered an assembly to be summoned by sound of
                    trumpet. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When these assembled in great
                    numbers, <quote>Since you, Titus Manlius,</quote> says he, "revering neither the
                    consular <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> power nor a father's majesty, have
                    fought against the enemy out of your post contrary to our orders, and, as far as
                    in you lay, have subverted military discipline, by which the Roman power has
                    stood to this day, and have brought me to this necessity, that I must either
                    forget the republic, or myself and mine; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> we
                    shall expiate our own transgressions rather than the republic should sustain so
                    serious a loss for our misdeeds. We shall be a melancholy example, but a
                    profitable one, to the youth of future ages. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    As for me, both the natural affection for my children, as well as that instance
                    of bravery which has led you astray by the false notion of honour, affects me
                    for you. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> But since either the authority of
                    consuls is to be established by your death, or by your forgiveness to be for
                    ever annulled; I do not think that even you, if you have any of our blood in
                    you, will refuse to restore, by your punishment, the military discipline which
                    has been subverted by your misconduct. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Go,
                    lictor, bind him to the stake. All became motionless, more through fear than
                    discipline, astounded by so cruel an order, each looking on the axe as if drawn
                    against himself. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Therefore when they stood in
                    profound silence, suddenly, when the blood spouted from his severed neck, their
                    minds recovering, as it <pb n="513" xml:id="p.513"/> were, from a state of
                    stupefaction, then their voices arose together in free expressions of complaint,
                    so that they spared neither lamentations nor execrations: <milestone n="22"
                        unit="section"/> and the body of the youth, being covered with the spoils,
                    was burned on a pile erected outside the rampart, with all the military zeal
                    with which any funeral could be celebrated: and Manlian orders w re considered
                    with horror, not only for the present, but of the most austere severity for
                    future times. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The severity of the punishment however
                    rendered the soldiers more obedient to the general; and besides that the guards
                    and watches and the regulation of the posts w re every where more strictly
                    attended to, such severity was also profitable in the final struggle when they
                    came into the field of battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But the battle
                    was very like to a civil war; so very similar was every thing among the Romans
                    and Latins, except with respect to courage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans formerly used targets; afterwards, when they began to receive pay,
                    they made shields instead of targets; and what before constituted phalanxes
                    similar to the Macedonian, afterwards became a line drawn up in distinct
                    companies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At length they were divided into
                    several centuries. A century contained sixty soldiers, two centurions, and one
                    standard-bearer. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The spearmen (hastati) formed
                    the first line in fifteen companies, with small intervals between them: a
                    company had twenty light-armed soldiers, the rest wearing shields; those were
                    called light who carried only a spear and short iron javelins. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> This, which constituted the van in the field of battle,
                    contained the youth in early bloom advancing towards the age of service. Next
                    followed men of more robust age, in the same number of companies, who were
                    called principes, all wearing shields, and distinguished by the completest
                    armour. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This band of thirty companies they
                    called antepilani, because there were fifteen others placed behind them with the
                    standards; of which each company consisted of three divisions, and the first
                    division of each they called a pilus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Each
                    company consisted of three ensigns, and contained one hundred and eighty-six
                    men. The first ensign was at the head of the Triarii, veteran soldiers of tried
                    bravery; the second, at the head of the Rorarii, men whose ability was less by
                    reason of their age and course of service; the third, at the head of the
                    Accensi, a body in whom very little confidence was reposed. For this reason also
                    they were thrown <pb n="514" xml:id="p.514"/> back to the rear. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When the army was marshalled according to this arrangement,
                    the spearmen first commenced the fight. If the spearmen were unable to repulse
                    the enemy, they retreated leisurely, and were received by the principes into the
                    intervals of the ranks. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The fight then
                    devolved on the principes; the spearmen followed. The Triarii continued kneeling
                    behind the ensigns, their left leg extended forward, holding their shields
                    resting on their shoulders, and their spears fixed in the ground, with the
                    points erect, so that their line bristled as if enclosed by a rampart.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If the principes also did not make
                    sufficient impression in the fight, they retreated slowly from the front to the
                    Triarii. Hence, when a difficulty is felt, <quote>Matters have come to the
                        Triarii,</quote> became a usual proverb. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The Triarii rising up, after receiving the principes and spearmen into the
                    intervals between their ranks, immediately closing their files, shut up as it
                    were the openings; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and in one compact body
                    fell upon the enemy, no other hope being now left: that was the most formidable
                    circumstance to the enemy, when having pursued them as vanquished, they beheld a
                    new line suddenly starting up, increased also in strength. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> In general about four legions were raised, each consisting
                    of five thousand infantry and three hundred horse. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> As many more were added from the Latin levy, who were at
                    that time enemies to the Romans, and drew up their line after the same manner;
                    and they knew that unless the ranks were disturbed they would have to engage not
                    only standard with standard, spearmen with spearmen, principles with principes,
                    but centurion also with centurion. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> There were
                    among the veterans two first centurions in either army, the Roman by no means
                    possessing bodily strength, but a brave man, and experienced in the service; the
                    Latin powerful in bodily strength, and a first-rate warrior; <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> they were very well known to each other, because they had
                    always held equal rank. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The Roman, somewhat
                    diffident of his strength, had at Rome obtained permission from the consuls, to
                    select any one whom he wished, his own subcenturion, to protect him from the one
                    destined to be his adversary; and this youth being opposed to him in the battle,
                    obtained the victory over the Latin centurion. <milestone n="19" unit="section"
                    /> They came to an engagement not far from the foot of Mount Vesuvius, where the
                    road led to the Veseris. <pb n="515" xml:id="p.515"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman consuls, before they marched out
                    their armies to the field, offered sacrifices. The aruspex is said to have shown
                    to Decius the head of the liver wounded on the side relating to himself, in
                    other respects the victim was ac- ceptable to the gods; whilst Manlius obtained
                    highly favour- able omens from his sacrifice. <quote>But all is well,</quote>
                    says Decius, if my colleague has offered an acceptable sacrifice." <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The ranks being drawn up in the order already
                    described, they marched forth to battle. Manlius commanded the right, Decius the
                    left wing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first the action was conducted
                    with equal strength on both sides, and with the same ardent courage. Afterwards
                    the Roman spearmen on the left wing, not sus- taining the violent assault of the
                    Latins, betook themselves to the principes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                    this state of trepidation the consul Decius cries out with a loud voice to
                    Marcus Valerius, <quote> Valerius, we have need of the aid of the gods. Come, as
                        public pontiff of the Roman people, dictate to me the words in which I may
                        devote myself for the legions. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The pontiff directed him to take the gown
                    called praetexta, and with his head covered and his hand thrust out under the
                    gown to the chin, standing upon a spear placed under his feet, to say these
                    words: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Janus, Jupiter, father Mars, Quirinus, Bellona, ye Lares, ye gods
                        Novensiles, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Novensiles were
                            nine deities brought to Rome by the Sabines: Lara, Vesta, Minerva,
                            Feronia, Concord, Faith, Fortune, Chance, Health. See Niebuhr III. n.
                            249. </note> ye gods Indigetes, ye divinities, under whose power we and
                        our enemies are, and ye dii Manes, <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I pray
                        you, I adore you, I ask your favour, that you would prosperously grant
                        strength and victory <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> to the Roman people,
                        the Quirites; and that ye may affect the enemies of the Roman people, the
                        Quirites, with terror, dismay, and death. In such manner as I have expressed
                        in words, so do I devote the legions and auxiliaries of the enemy, together
                        with myself, <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> to the dii Manes and to Earth
                        for the republic of the Quirites, for the army, legions, auxiliaries of the
                        Roman people, the Quirites. </quote> Having uttered this prayer, he orders
                    the lictors to go to Titus Manlius, and without delay to announce to his
                    colleague that he had devoted himself <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> for the
                    army. He, girding himself in a Gabine cincture, and fully armed, mounted his
                    horse, and rushed into the midst of the enemy. He was observed by both armies to
                    present a more majestic appearance than human, <pb n="516" xml:id="p.516"/> as
                    one sent from heaven as an expiation of all the wrath of the gods, to transfer
                    to the enemy destruction turned away from his own side: accordingly, <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> all the terror and panic being carried along with
                    him, at first disturbed the battalions of the Latins, then completely pervaded
                    their entire line. This <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> was most evident,
                    because, in whatever direction he was carried with his horse, there they became
                    panic-stricken, as if struck by some pestilential constellation; but when he
                    fell overwhelmed with darts, instantly the cohorts of the Latins, thrown into
                    manifest consternation, took to flight, leaving a void to a considerable extent.
                    At the same time also the Romans, their minds <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    being freed from religious dread, exerting themselves as if the signal was then
                    given for the first time, commenced to fight with renewed ardour. For the
                    Rorarii also pushed forward among the <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    antepilani, and added strength to the spearmen and principes, and the Triarii
                    resting on the right knee awaited the consul's nod to rise up. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Afterwards, as the contest proceeded, when the
                    superior numbers of the Latins had the advantage in some places, the consul,
                    Manlius, on hearing the circumstance of his colleague's death, after he had, as
                    was right and just, honoured his so glorious a death with tears, as well as with
                    praises so well merited, hesitated, for a little time, whether it was yet time
                    for the Triarii to rise; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> then judging it
                    better that they should be kept fresh for the decisive blow, he ordered the
                    Accensi to advance from the rear before the standards. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When they moved forward, the Latins immediately called up
                    their Triarii, as if their opponents had done the same thing: who, when they had
                    by desperate fighting for a considerable time both fatigued themselves, and had
                    either broken or blunted their spears, and were, however, beating back their
                    adversaries, thinking that the battle was now nearly decided, and that they had
                    come to the last line; then the consul. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> calls
                    to the Triarii, <quote> Arise now, fresh as ye are, against men now wearied,
                        mindful of your country and parents, your wives and children; mindful of
                        your consul who has submitted to death to insure your victory. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the Triarii arose, fresh as they were,
                    with their arms glittering, a new line which appeared unexpectedly, receiving
                    the antepilani into the intervals between the ranks, raised a shout, and broke
                    through the first line of the Latins; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and
                    goading their faces, after cutting down those <pb n="517" xml:id="p.517"/> who
                    constituted their principal strength, they passed almost intact through the
                    other companies, with such slaughter that they scarcely left one fourth of the
                    enemy. The Samnites also, drawn up at a distance at the foot of the mountain,
                    struck terror into the Latins. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But of all,
                    whether citizens or allies, the principal praise for that action was due to the
                    consuls; the one of whom turned on himself alone all the threats and dangers
                    (denounced) by the divinities of heaven and hell; the other evinced such valour
                    and such judgment in the battle, that it was universally agreed among both the
                    Romans and Latins who have transmitted to posterity an account of the battle,
                    that, on whichever side Titus Manlius held the command, the victory must belong
                    to that. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Latins in their flight betook
                    themselves to Minturnae. Immediately after the battle the camp was taken, and
                    great numbers still alive were surprised therein, chiefly Campanians. Night
                    surprised them in their search, and prevented the body of Decius from being
                    discovered on that day. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On the day after it
                    was found amid vast heaps of slaughtered enemies, pierced with a great number of
                    darts, and his funeral was solemnized under the direction of his colleague, in a
                    manner suited to his death. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It seems right to
                    add here, that it is lawful for a consul, a dictator, and a praetor, when he
                    devotes the legions of the enemy, to devote not himself particularly, but
                    whatever citizen he may choose out of a Roman legion regularly enrolled:
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> if the person who has been devoted die,
                    the matter is duly performed; if he do not perish, then an image, seven feet
                    high or more, must be buried in the ground, and a victim slain, as an expiation.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Where that image shall be buried, there
                    it is not lawful that a Roman magistrate should pass. But if he wish to devote
                    himself, as Decius did, unless he who has devoted himself die, he shall not with
                    propriety perform any act of religion regarding either himself or the public.
                    Should he wish to devote his arms to Vulcan or to any other god, he has a right,
                    whether he shall lease, by a victim, or in any other manner. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> It is not proper that the enemy should get possession of
                    the weapon, on which the consul, standing, pronounced the imprecation: if they
                    should get possession of it, then an expiation must be made to Mars by the
                    sacrifices called the Suove-taurilia. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Although the memory of every divine and human custom has been obliter- <pb
                        n="518" xml:id="p.518"/> ated, in consequence of preferring what is modern
                    and foreign to that which is ancient and belonging to our own country, I deemed
                    it not irrelevant to relate the particulars even in the very terms used, as they
                    have been handed down and expressed. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> I find it stated in some writers, that the
                    Samnites, having awaited the issue of the battle, came at length with support to
                    the Romans after the battle was over. Also aid from Lavinium, whilst they wasted
                    time in deliberating, was at length sent to the Latins after they had been
                    vanquished. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And when the first standards and
                    part of the army just issued from the gates, news being <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> brought of the defeat of the Latins, they faced about and
                    returned back to the city; on which occasion they say that their praetor,
                    Milionius, observed, that <quote>for so very short a journey a high price must
                        be paid to the Romans.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Such of the Latins as survived the battle,
                    after being scattered over many roads, collected themselves into a body, and
                    found refuge in the city of Vescia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There
                    their general, Numisius, insisted in their counsels, that "the truly common
                    fortune of war had prostrated both armies by equal losses, and that only the
                    name of victory rested with the Romans; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that
                    in other respects they too shared the lot of defeated persons; the two pavilions
                    of the consuls were polluted; one by the murder committed on a son, the other by
                    the blood of a devoted consul; that their army was cut down in every direction;
                    their spearmen and principes were cut down; great havoc was made before the
                    standards and behind them; the Triarii at length restored their cause.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though the forces of the Latins were cut
                    down in an equal proportion, yet for reinforcements, Latium or the Volscians
                    were nearer than Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Wherefore, if they
                    thought well of it, he would speedily call out the youth from the Latin and
                    Volscian states, and would return to Capua with a determined army, and by his
                    unexpected arrival strike dismay among the Romans, who were expecting nothing
                    less than battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Deceptive letters being sent
                    around Latium and the Volscian nation, a tumultuary army, hastily raised from
                    all quarters, was assembled, for as they had not been present at the battle,
                    they were more disposed to believe on slight grounds. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> This army the consul Torquatus met at Trisanum, a place
                    between Sinuessa and Minturnae. Before a place was selected for a <pb n="519"
                        xml:id="p.519"/> camp, the baggage on both sides being piled up in a heap,
                    they fought and terminated the war; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for so
                    impaired was their strength, that all the Latins surrendered themselves to the
                    consul, who was leading his victorious army to lay waste their lands, and the
                    Campanians followed the example of this surrender. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Latium and Capua were fined some land. The Latin with the
                    addition of the Privernian land; and the Falernian land, which had belonged to
                    the people of Campania, as far as the river Vulturnus, is all distributed to the
                    commons of Rome. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In the Latin land two acres
                    a man were assigned, so that they should receive an additional three-fourths of
                    an acre from the Privernian land; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> in the
                    Falernian land three acres were assigned, one fourth of an acre being further
                    added, in consideration of the distance. Of the Latins the Laurentians were
                    exempted from punishment, as also the horsemen of the Campanians, because they
                    had not revolted. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> An order was issued that
                    the treaty should be renewed with the Laurentians; and it is renewed every year
                    since, on the tenth day after the Latin festival. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> The rights of citizenship were granted to the Campanian
                    horsemen; and that it might serve as a memorial, they hung up a brazen tablet in
                    the temple of Castor at Rome. The Campanian state was also enjoined to pay them
                    a yearly stipend of four hundred and fifty denarii each; their number amounted
                    to one thousand six hundred. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The war being thus concluded, after rewards
                    and punishment were distributed according to the deserts of each, Titus Manlius
                    returned to Rome: on his approach it appears that the aged only went forth to
                    meet him; and that the young men, both then, and all his life after, detested
                    and cursed him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Antians made incursions on
                    the territories of Ostia, Ardea, and Solonia. The consul Manlius, because he was
                    unable by reason of his health to conduct that war, nominated as dictator Lucius
                    Papirius Crassus, who then happened to be praetor; by him Lucius Papirius Cursor
                    was appointed master of the horse. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nothing
                    worthy of mention was performed against the Antians by the dictator, although he
                    had kept a standing camp for several months in the Antian territory. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> To a year signalized by a victory over so many and
                    such powerful states, further by the illustrious death of one of the consuls, as
                    well as by the unrelenting, though memorable, severity of command in the other,
                    there succeeded as consuls Titus Aemi- <pb n="520" xml:id="p.520"/> lius
                    Mamercinus and Quintus Publilius Philo; neither to a similar opportunity of
                    exploits, and they themselves being mindful rather of their own interests as
                    well as of those of the parties in the state, than of the interests of their
                    country. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They routed on the plains of
                    Ferentinum, and stripped of their camp, the Latins, who, in resentment of the
                    land they had lost, took up arms again. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Publilius, under whose guidance and auspices the action had been fought,
                    receiving the submission of the Latin states, who had lost a great many of their
                    young men there, Aemilius marched the army to Pedum. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The people of Pedum were supported by the states of Tibur,
                    Praeneste, and Velitrae; auxiliaries had also come from Lanuvium and Antium.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Where, though the Romans had the advantage
                    in several engagements, still the entire labour remained at the city of Pedum
                    itself and at the camp of the allied states, which was adjoining the city:
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> suddenly leaving the war unfinished,
                    because he heard that a triumph was decreed to his colleague, he himself also
                    returned to Rome to demand a triumph before a victory had been obtained.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The senate displeased by this ambitious
                    conduct, and refusing a triumph unless Pedum was either taken or should
                    surrender, Aemilius, alienated from the senate in consequence of this act,
                    administered the remainder of the consulship like to a seditious tribuneship.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For, as long as he was consul, he neither
                    ceased to criminate the patricians to the people, his colleague by no means
                    interfering, because he himself also was a plebeian; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> (the scanty distribution of the land among the commons in
                    the Latin and Falernian territory afforded the groundwork of the criminations;)
                    and when the senate, wishing to put an end to the administration of the consuls,
                    ordered a dictator to be nominated against the Latins, who were again in arms,
                    Aemilius, <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> to whom the fasces then belonged,
                    nominated his colleague dictator; by him Junius Brutus was constituted master of
                    the horse. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The dictatorship was popular, both
                    in consequence of his discourses containing invectives against the patricians,
                    and because he passed three laws, most advantageous to the commons, and
                    injurious to the nobility; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> one, that the
                    orders of the commons should be binding on all the Romans; another, that the
                    patricians should, before the suffrages commenced, declare their approbation of
                    the laws which should be passed in the assemblies of the centuries; <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> the third, that one at least of the censors <pb
                        n="521" xml:id="p.521"/> should be elected from the commons, as they had
                    already gone so far as that it was lawful that both the consuls should be
                    plebeians. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The patricians considered that
                    more of detriment had been sustained on that year from the consuls and dictator
                    than was counterbalanced by their success and achievements abroad. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following year, Lucius Furius Camillus
                    and Caius Maenius were consuls, in order that the neglect of his duty by
                    Aemilius, the consul of the preceding year, might be rendered more markedly
                    reproachful, the senate loudly urge that Pedum should be assailed with arms,
                    men, and every kind of force, and be demolished; and the new consuls, being
                    forced to give that matter the precedence of all others, set out on that
                    expedition. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The state of affairs was now such
                    in Latium, that they could no longer submit to either war or peace. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> For war they were deficient in resources; they
                    spurned at peace through resentment for the loss of their land. It seemed
                    necessary therefore to steer a middle course, to keep within their towns, so
                    that the Romans by being provoked might have no pretext for hostilities;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and that if the siege of any town should
                    be announced to them, aid should be sent from every quarter from all the states.
                    And still the people of Pedum were aided by only a very few stated. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Tiburtians and Praenestines, whose territory lay
                    nearest, came to Pedum. Maenius suddenly making an attack, defeated the
                    Aricinians, and Lanuvians, and Veliternians, at the river Astura, the Volscians
                    of Antium forming a junction with them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    Tiburtian, far the strongest body, Camillus engages at Pedum, encountering much
                    greater difficulty, though with a result equally successful. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> A sudden sally of the townsmen during the battle chiefly
                    occasioned confusing: Camillus, turning on these with a part of his army, not
                    only drove them within their walls, but on the very same day, after he had
                    discomfited themselves and their auxiliaries, he took the town by scalade.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was then-resolved to lead round with
                    greater energy and spirit his victorious army from the storming of a single city
                    to the entire conquest of Latium. Nor did they stop until they reduced all
                    Latium, either by storming, or by becoming masters of the cities one after the
                    other by capitulation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then, disposing
                    garrisons in the towns which they had taken, they departed to Rome to a triumph
                        <pb n="522" xml:id="p.522"/> universally admitted to be due to them. To the
                    triumph was added the honour of having equestrian statues erected to them in the
                    forum, a compliment very unusual at that period. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Before they commenced holding the meeting for the election
                    of the consuls for the ensuing year, Camillus moved the senate concerning the
                    Latin states, and spoke thus: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Conscript fathers, that which was to be done by war and arms in Latium
                        has now been fully accomplished by the bounty of the gods and the valour of
                        the soldiers. The armies of the enemy have been cut down at Pedum and the
                        Astura. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> All the Latin towns, and Antium
                        belonging to the Volscians, either taken by storm, or received into
                        surrender, are occupied by your garrisons. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> It now remains to be considered, since they annoy us by their repeated
                        rebellions, how we may keep them in quiet submission and in the observance
                        of perpetual peace. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The immortal gods
                        have put the determination of this matter so completely in your power, that
                        they have placed it at your option whether Latium is to exist henceforward
                        or not. Ye can therefore insure to yourselves perpetual peace, as far as
                        regards the Latins, either by adopting severe or lenient measures. Do ye
                        choose to adopt cruel conduct towards people who have surrendered and have
                        been conquered? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Ye may destroy all
                        Latium, make a vast desert of a place whence, in many and serious wars, ye
                        have often made use of an excellent army of allies. Do you wish, according
                        to the example of your ancestors, to augment the Roman state by admitting
                        the vanquished among your citizens? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        Materials for extending your power by the highest glory are at hand. That
                        government is certainly by far the most secure, which the subjects feel a
                        pleasure in obeying. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But whatever
                        determination ye wish to come to, it is necessary that it be speedy. So many
                        states have ye in a state of suspense between hope and fear; and it is
                        necessary that you be discharged as soon as possible of your solicitude
                        about them, and that their minds, whilst they are still in a state of
                        insensibility from uncertainty, be at once impressed either by punishment or
                        clemency. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> It was our duty to bring
                        matters to such a pass that you may have full power to deliberate on every
                        matter; yours to decide what is most expedient to yourselves and the
                        commonwealth. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The principal members of the senate applauded
                    the <pb n="523" xml:id="p.523"/> consul's statement of the business on the
                    whole; but said that "as the states were differently circumstanced, that their
                    plan might be readily adjusted so that it might be determined according to the
                    desert of each, if they should put the question regarding each state
                    specifically. The question was therefore so put regarding each separately and a
                    decree past. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To the Lanuvians the right of
                    citizenship was granted, and the exercise of their religious rights was restored
                    to them with this provision, that the temple and grove of Juno Sospita should be
                    common between the Lanuvian burghers and the Roman people. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The Aricians, Nomentans, and Pedans were admitted into the
                    number of citizen on the same terms as the Lanuvians. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> To the Tusculans the rights of citizenship which they
                    already possessed were continued; and the crime of rebellion was turned from
                    disaffection on public grounds against a few instigators. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On the Veliternian, Roman citizens of long standing,
                    measures of great severity were inflicted because they had so often rebelled;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> their walls were razed, and their senate
                    removed from thence, and they were ordered to dwell on the other side of the
                    Tiber, so that the fine of any individual who should be caught on the hither
                    side of that river should amount to one thousand <hi rend="italics">asses;</hi>
                    and that the person who had apprehended him, should not discharge his prisoner
                    from confinement, until the money was paid down. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Into the land of the senators colonists were sent; from the additions of
                    which Velitrae recovered its appearance of former populousness. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A new colony was also sent to Antium, with this provision,
                    that if the Antians desired to be enrolled as colonists, permission to that
                    effect should be granted. Their ships of war were removed from thence, and the
                    people of Antium were interdicted the sea, and the rights of citizenship were
                    granted them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Tiburtians and Praenestines
                    were amerced in some land, not only on account of the recent guilt of the
                    rebellion, which was common to them with the other Latins; but also because,
                    from their dislike to the Roman government, they had formerly associated in arms
                    with the Gauls, a nation of savages. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> From the
                    other Latin states they took away the privileges of intermarriage commerce, and
                    of holding meetings. To the Campanians, in compliment to their horsemen, because
                    they had refused to join in rebellion with the Latins, and to the Fundans and
                    Formians, <pb n="524" xml:id="p.524"/> because the passage through their
                    territories had been always secure and peaceful, the freedom of the state was
                    granted with the right of suffrage. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was
                    determined that the people of Cumae and Suessula should have the same rights and
                    be on the same footing as Capua. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Of the ships
                    of the Antians some were drawn up to the docks at Rome, some were burned, and
                    with the prows of these a pulpit built in the forum was ordered to be decorated;
                    and that temple was called Rostra. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the consulship of Caius Sulpicius
                    Longus and Publius Aelius Paetus, when the Roman power not more than the kindly
                    feeling engendered by acts of kindness diffused the blessings of peace among all
                    parties, a war broke out between the Sidicinians and Auruncans. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Auruncans having been admitted into alliance on the
                    occasion of their surrendering, had since that period made no disturbance;
                    accordingly they had a juster pretext for seeking aid from the Romans.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But before the consuls led forth their
                    army from the city, (for the senate had ordered the Auruncans to be defended,)
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> intelligence is brought that the
                    Auruncans deserted their town through fear, and flying with their wives and
                    children, that they fortified Suessa, which is now called Aurunca; that their
                    ancient walls and city were demolished by the Sidicinians. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The senate being in consequence incensed against the
                    consuls, by whose delays the allies had been betrayed, ordered a dictator to be
                    created. Caius Claudius Regillensis was appointed, and he nominated Caius
                    Claudius Hortator as master of the horse. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A
                    scruple afterwards arose concerning the dictator; and when the augurs declared
                    that he seemed to have been created under an informality, the dictator and the
                    master of the horse laid down their office. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This year Minucia, a vestal, at first suspected on account of her dress being
                    more elegant than was becoming, afterwards being arraigned before the pontiffs
                    on the testimony of a slave, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> after she had
                    been ordered by their decree to abstain from meddling in sacred rites, and to
                    keep her slaves under her own power, when brought to trial, was buried alive at
                    the Colline gate, on the right of the causeway, in the field of wickedness. I
                    suppose that name was given to the place from her crime. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> On the same year Quintus Publilius Philo was the first of
                    the plebeians elected praetor, being opposed by Sulpicius the consul, who
                    refused to take any notice of him as a candidate; the senate, as they had not
                    suc- <pb n="525" xml:id="p.525"/> ceeded on that ground in the case of the
                    highest offices, being less earnest with respect to the praetorship. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following year, Lucius Papirius Crassus
                    and Kaeso Duilius being consuls, was distinguished by a war with the Ausonians,
                    as being new rather than important. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This
                    people inhabited the city Cales; they had united their arms with their
                    neighbours the Sidicinians; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and the army of
                    the two states being defeated in one battle scarcely worthy of record, was
                    induced to take to flight the earlier in consequence of the proximity of the
                    cities, and the more sheltered on their flight. Nor did the senate, however,
                    discontinue their attention to that war, because the Sidicinians had now so
                    often taken up arms either as principals, or had afforded aid to those who did
                    so, or had been the cause of hostilities. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly they exerted themselves with all their might, to raise to the
                    consulship for the fourth time, Marcus Valerius Corvus, the greatest general of
                    that day. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To Corvus was added Marcus Atilius
                    Regulus as colleague; and lest any disappointment might by any chance occur, a
                    request was made of the consuls, that, without drawing lots, that province might
                    be assigned to Corvus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Receiving the
                    victorious army from the former consuls, proceeding to Cales, whence the war had
                    originated, after he had, at the first shout and onset, routed the enemy, who
                    were disheartened by the recollection also of the former engagement, he set
                    about attacking the town itself. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And such was
                    the ardour of the soldiers, that they wished to advance immediately up to the
                    walls, and strenuously asserted that they would scale them. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Corvus, because that was a hazardous undertaking, wished to
                    accomplish his object rather by the labour than the risk of his men. Accordingly
                    he formed a rampart, prepared his vineae and advanced towers up to the walls;
                    but an opportunity which accidentally presented itself, prevented the occasion
                    for them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For Marcius Fabius, a Roman
                    prisoner, when, having broken his chains during the inattention of his guards on
                    a festival day, suspending himself by means of a rope which was fastened to a
                    battlement of the wall, he let himself down by the hands, persuaded the general
                    to make an assault on the enemy whilst stupified by wine and feasting; nor were
                    the Ausonians, together with their city, captured with greater difficulty than
                    they had been routed in the field. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A great
                    amount of booty was obtained; and a garrison being stationed at Cales, <pb
                        n="526" xml:id="p.526"/> the legions were marched back to Rome. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The consul triumphed in pursuance of a decree of the
                    senate; and that Atilius might not be without a share of glory, both the consuls
                    were ordered to lead the army against the Sidicinians. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> But first, in conformity with a decree of the senate, they
                    nominated as dictator for the purpose of holding the elections, Lucius Aemilius
                    Mamercinus; he named Quintus Publilius Philo his master of the horse. The
                    dictator presiding at the elections, Titus Veturius and Spurius Postumius were
                    elected consuls. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Though a part of the war
                    with the Sidicinians still remained; yet that they might anticipate, by an act
                    of kindness, the wishes of the commons, they proposed about sending a colony to
                    Cales; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and a decree of the senate being
                    passed that two thousand five hundred men should be enrolled for that purpose,
                    they appointed Kaeso Duilius, Titus Quinctius, and Marcus Fabius commissioners
                    for conducting the colony and distributing the land. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The new consuls then, recovering the army from
                    their predecessors, entered the enemy's territories and carried their
                    depredations up to the walls and the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    There because the Sidicinians, who had raised a numerous army, seemed determined
                    to fight vigorously for their last hope, and a report existed that Samnium also
                    was preparing for hostilities, Publius Cornelius Rufinus was created dictator by
                    the consuls in pursuance of a decree of the senate; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Marcus Antonius was nominated master of the horse.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A scruple afterwards arose that they were
                    elected under an informality: and they laid down their office; and because a
                    pestilence followed, recourse was had to an interregnum, as if all the auspices
                    had been infected by that irregularity. By Marcus Valerius Corvus, the fifth
                    interrex from the commencement of the interregnum, Aulus Cornelius a second
                    time, and Cneius Domitius were elected consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Things being now tranquil, the rumour of a Gallic war had the effect of a
                    real outbreak, so that they were determined that a dictator should be nominated.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Marcus Papirius Crassus was nominated, and
                    Publius Valerius Publicola master of the horse. And when the levy was conducted
                    by them with more activity than was deemed necessary in the case of neighbouring
                    wars, scouts were sent out and brought word, that there was perfect quiet with
                    the Gauls in every direction. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was suspected
                    that Samnium also was now for the second year <pb n="527" xml:id="p.527"/> in a
                    state of disturbance in consequence of their entertaining new designs:
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> hence the Roman troops were not wit drawn
                    from the Sidicinian territory. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But a hostile
                    attack made by Alexander of Epirus on the Lucanians drew away the attention of
                    the Samnites to another quarter; these two nations fought a pitched battle
                    against the king, as he was making a descent on the district adjoining Paestum.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Alexander, having come off victorious in
                    that contest, concluded a peace with the Romans; with what fidelity he would
                    have kept it, if his other projects had been equally successful, is uncertain.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The same year the census was performed,
                    and the new citizens were rated; on their account the Maecian and Scaptia tribes
                    were added: the censors who added them were Quintus Publilius Philo and Spurius
                    Postumius. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Acerrans were enrolled as
                    Romans, in conformity with a law introduce by the praetor, Lucius Papirius, by
                    which the right of citizenship with the privilege of suffrage was conferred.
                    These were the transactions at home and abroad during that year. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following year was disastrous, whether by
                    the in- temperature of the air, or by human guilt, Marcus Claudius Marcellus and
                    Caius Valerius being consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I find in the
                    annals Flaccus and Potitus variously given as the surname of the consul; but in
                    this it is of little consequence which is the true one. I would heartily wish
                    that this other account were a false one, (nor indeed do all writers mention
                    it,) viz. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that those persons, whose death
                    rendered the year signal for the pestilence, were carried off by poison. The
                    circumstance however must be stated as it is handed down to us, that I may not
                    detract from the credit of any writer. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When
                    the principal persons of the state were dying of similar diseases, and all
                    generally with the same result, a certain maid-servant undertook, before
                    Quintius Fabius Maximus, curule aedile, to discover the cause of the public
                    malady, provided the public faith would be given to her by him, that the
                    discovery should not be made detrimental to her. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Fabius immediately lays the matter before the consuls, and the consuls before
                    the senate, and with the concurrence of that order the public faith was pledged
                    to the informer. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was then disclosed that
                    the state was afflicted by the wickedness of certain women, and that certain
                    matrons were preparing those poisonous drugs; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    and if they wished to follow her forthwith, they mi ht be de- <pb n="528"
                        xml:id="p.528"/> tected in the very fact. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Having followed the informer, they found women preparing certain drugs, and
                    others of the same kind laid up. These being brought into the forum, and several
                    matrons, to the number of twenty, in whose possession they had been detected,
                    being summoned by the beadle, two of them, Cornelia and Sergia, both of
                    patrician rank, maintaining that these drugs were wholesome, were directed by
                    the informer who confronted them to drink some, that they might convict her of
                    having stated what was false; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> having taken
                    time to confer together, when, the crowd being removed, they referred the matter
                    to the other matrons in the open view of all; they also not refusing to drink,
                    they all drank off the preparation, and perished by their own wicked device.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Their attendants being instantly seized,
                    informed against a great number of matrons, of whom to the number of one hundred
                    and seventy were condemned. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Nor up to that
                    day was there ever an inquiry made at Rome concerning poisoning. The
                    circumstance was considered a prodigy; and seemed the act rather of insane
                    persons than of persons depraved by guilt. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore mention having been found in the annals, that formerly in the
                    secessions of the commons the nail had been driven by the dictator, and that the
                    minds of the people, distracted by discord, had been restored to a sane state,
                    it was determined that a dictator should be nominated for the purpose of driving
                    the nail. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Cneius Quinctilius being nominated,
                    appointed Lucius Valerius master of the horse, who, as soon as the nail was
                    driven, abdicated their offices. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Papirius Crassus a second time, and
                    Lucius Plautius Venno were elected consuls; at the commencement of which year
                    ambassadors came to Rome from the Fabraternians, a Volscian people, and from the
                    Lucanians, soliciting to be admitted into alliance: <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> [promising] that if they were defended from the arms of the
                    Samnites, they would continue in fidelity and obedience under the government of
                    the Roman people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Ambassadors were then sent
                    by the senate; and the Samnites were directed to withhold all violence from the
                    territories of those states; and this embassy proved effectual not so much
                    because the Samnites were desirous of peace, as because they were not prepared
                    for war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The same year a war broke out with
                    the people of Privernum; in which the people of Fundi were their supporters,
                    their leader also being <pb n="529" xml:id="p.529"/> a Fundanian, Vitruvius
                    Vaccus; a man of distinction not only at home, but in Rome also. He had a house
                    on the Palatine hill, which, after the building was razed and the ground thrown
                    open, was called the Vacciprata. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Lucius
                    Papirius having set out to oppose him whilst devastating extensively the
                    districts of Setia, Norba, and Cora, posted himself at no great distance from
                    his camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Vitruvius neither adopted the
                    prudent resolution to enclose himself with his trenches against an en my his
                    superior in strength, nor had he sufficient courage to engage at any great
                    distance from his camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When his army had
                    scarcely got out of the gate of the camp, and his soldiers were looking
                    backwards to flight rather than to battle or the enemy, he enters on an
                    engagement without judgment or boldness; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and
                    as he was conquered by a very slight effort and unequivocally, so did he by the
                    very shortness of the distance, and by the facility of his retreat into the camp
                    so near at hand, protect his soldiers without difficulty from much loss;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and scarcely were any slain in the
                    engagement itself, and but few in the confusion of the flight in the rear,
                    whilst they were making their way into the camp; and as soon as it was dark they
                    repaired to Privernum in trepidation, so that they might protect themselves
                    rather by walls than by a rampart. Plautius, the other consul, after laying
                    waste the lands in every direction and driving off the spoil, leads his army
                    into the Fundanian territory. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The senate of
                    the Fundanians met him as he was entering their borders; they declare that
                        <quote> they had not come to intercede in behalf of Vitruvius or those who
                        followed his faction, but in behalf of the people of Fundi, whose exemption
                        from any blame in the war had been proved by Vitruvius himself, when he made
                        Privernum his place of retreat, and not his native country, Fundi.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At Privernum, therefore, the enemies
                        of the Roman people were to be looked for, and punished, who revolted at the
                        same time from the Fundanians and the Romans, unmindful of both countries.
                        That the Fundanians were at peace, that they had Roman feelings and a
                        grateful recollection of the political rights received. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> They entreated the consul to withhold war from an
                        inoffensive people; their lands, city, heir own bodies and those of their
                        wives and children, were, and ever should be, at the disposal of the Roman
                        people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The consul, having commended the Fundanians,
                    and despatched letters to Rome that the Fundanians had preserved their
                    allegiance, <pb n="530" xml:id="p.530"/> turned his march to Privernum.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Claudius states, that the consul first
                    punished those who were at the head of the conspiracy; that three hundred and
                    fifty of the conspirators were sent in chains to Rome; and that such submission
                    was not received by the senate, because they considered that the people of Fundi
                    wished to come off with impunity by the punishment of needy and humble persons. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the siege of Privernum was being
                    conducted by the two consular armies, one of the consuls was recalled to Rome,
                    on account of the elections. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This year gaols
                    were first erected in the circus. While the attention of the public was still
                    occupied by the Privernian war, an alarming report of the Gauls being in arms, a
                    matter scarcely ever slighted by the senate, suddenly came on them. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The new consuls, therefore, Lucius Aemilius
                    Mamercinus and Caius Plautius, on the calends of July, the very day on which
                    they entered into office, received orders to settle the provinces immediately
                    between themselves; and Mamercinus, to whom the Gallic war fell, was directed to
                    levy troops, without admitting any plea of immunity: nay, it is said, that even
                    the rabble of handicrafts, and those of sedentary trades, of all the worst
                    qualified for military service, were called out; <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> and a vast army was collected at Veii, in readiness to meet the Gauls.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was thought proper not to proceed to a
                    greater distance, lest the enemy might by some other route arrive at the city
                    without being observed. In the course of a few days it being ascertained, on a
                    careful inquiry, that every thing on that side was quiet at the time; the whole
                    force, which was to have opposed the Gauls, was then turned against Priver- num.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Of the issue of the business, there are
                    two different accounts: some say, that the city was taken by storm; and that
                    Vitruvius fell alive into the hands [of the conquerors]: others maintain that
                    the townsmen, to avoid the extremities of a storm, presenting the rod of peace,
                    surrendered to the consul; and that Vitruvius was delivered up by his troops.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate, being consulted with respect
                    to Vitruvius and the Privernians, sent directions, that the consul Plautius
                    should demolish the walls of Privernum, and, leaving a strong garrison there,
                    come home to enjoy the honour of a triumph; at the same time ordering that
                    Vitruvius should be kept in prison, until the return of the consul, and that he
                    should then be beaten with rods, and put to death. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> His house, which stood <pb n="531" xml:id="p.531"/> on the
                    Palatine hill, they commanded to be razed to the ground, and his effects to be
                    devoted to Semo Sancus. With the money produced by the sale of them, brazen
                    globes were formed, and placed in the chapel of Sancus, opposite to the temple
                    of Quirinus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As to the senate of Privernum, it
                    was decreed, that every person who had continued to act as a senator of
                    Privernum, after the revolt from the Romans, should reside on the farther side
                    of the Tiber, under the same restrictions as those of Velitrae. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> After the passing of these decrees, there was no
                    further mention of the Privernians, un- til Plautius had triumphed. After the
                    triumph, Vitruvius, with his accomplices, having been put to death, the consul
                    thought that all being now fully gratified by the sufferings of the guilty,
                    allusion might be safely made to the business of the Privernians, he spoke in
                    the following manner: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Con- script fathers, since the authors of the revolt have received, both
                        from the immortal gods and from you, the punishment so well merited, what do
                        ye judge proper to be done with respect to the guiltless multitude?
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For my part, although my duty
                        consists rather in collecting the opinions of others than in offering my
                        own, yet, when I reflect that the Privernians are situated in the
                        neighbourhood of the Samnites, our peace with whom is exceedingly uncertain,
                        I should wish, that as little ground of animosity as possible may be left
                        between them and us. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The affair naturally admitted of a diversity
                    of opinions, each, agreeably to his particular temper, recommending either
                    severity or lenity; matters were still further perplexed by one of the
                    Privernian ambassadors, more mindful of the prospects to which he had been born,
                    than to the exigency of the present juncture: who being asked by one of the
                    advocates for severity, <quote>What punishment he thought the Privernians
                        deserved?</quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> answered, <quote>Such as those deserve who
                        deem themselves worthy of liberty.</quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul observing, that, by this stubborn
                    answer, those who were adverse to the cause of the Privernians were the more
                    exasperated against them, and wishing, by a question of favourable import, to
                    draw from him a more conciliating reply, said to him, <quote> What if <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> we re- mit the punishment, in what manner may
                        we expect that ye will observe the peace which shall be established between
                        us? </quote> He replied, <quote> If the peace which ye grant us be a good
                            <pb n="532" xml:id="p.532"/> one, both inviolable and eternal; if bad,
                        of no long continuance. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then indeed some exclaimed, that the
                    Privernian menaced them, and not in ambiguous terms; and that by such
                    expressions peaceable states were incited to rebellion. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But the more reasonable part of the senate interpreted his
                    answers more favourably, and said, that <quote> the words they had heard were
                        those of a man, and of a free-man. Could it be believed that any people, or
                        even any individual, would remain, longer than necessity constrained, in a
                        situation which he felt painful? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That
                        peace was faithfully observed, only when those at peace were voluntarily so;
                        but that fidelity was not to be expected where they wished to establish
                        slavery. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In this opinion they were led to concur,
                    principally, by the consul himself, who frequently observed to the consulars,
                    who had proposed the different resolutions, in such a manner as to be heard by
                    several, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> that <quote> surely those men only
                        who thought of nothing but liberty, were worthy of being made Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They consequently both carried their cause in
                    the senate; and, moreover, by direction of that body, a proposal was laid before
                    the people, that the freedom of the state should be granted to the Privernians.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The same year a colony of three hundred
                    was sent to Anxur, and received two acres of land each. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year following, in which the consuls were
                    Publius Plautius Proculus and Publius Cornelius Scapula, was re- markable for no
                    one transaction, civil or military, except the sending of a colony to Fregellae,
                    a district which had belonged to the Sidicinians, and afterwards to the
                    Volscians; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and a distribution of meat to the
                    people, made by Marcus Flavius, on occasion of the funeral of his mother.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There were many who represented, that,
                    under the appearance of doing honour to his parent, a deserved recompence was
                    made to the people, for having acquitted him, when prosecuted by the aediles on
                    a charge of having debauched a married woman. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This distribution of meat intended as a return for favours shown on the trial,
                    proved also the means of procuring him the honour of a public office; for, at
                    the next election, though absent, he was preferred before the candidates who
                    solicited in person the tribuneship of the commons. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The city of Palaepolis was situated at no great distance
                    from the spot where Neapolis now stands. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    two cities were inhabited by one people: these came from Cumae, and the Cumans
                    derive their origin <pb n="533" xml:id="p.533"/> from Chalcis in Euba. By means
                    of the fleet in which they had been conveyed hither, they possessed great power
                    on the coast of the sea, near which they dwelt. Having first landed on the
                    islands of Aenaria, and the Pithecusae, they afterwards ventured to transfer
                    their settlement to the continent. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This state,
                    relying both on their own strength, as well as on the treacherous nature of the
                    alliance of the Samnites with the Romans; or, encouraged by the report of a
                    pestilence having attacked the city of Rome, committed various acts of hostility
                    against the Romans settled in the Campanian and Falernian territories.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Wherefore, in the succeeding consulate of
                    Lucius Cornelius, and Quintus Publilius Philo a second time, heralds being sent
                    to Palaepolis to demand satisfaction, when a haughty answer was returned by
                    these Greeks, a race more mag- nanimous in words than in action, the people, in
                    pursuance of the direction of the senate, ordered war to be declared against the
                    Palaepolitans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On settling the provinces
                    between the consuls, the war against the Greeks fell to Publilius. Cor- nelius,
                    with another army, was appointed to watch the Sam- nites if they should attempt
                    any movement; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but a report pre- vailed that
                    they, anxiously expecting a revolt in Campania, intended to march their troops
                    thither; that was judged by Cornelius the properest station for him. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate received information, from both the
                    con- suls, that there was very little hope of peace with the Sam- nites.
                    Publilius informed them, that two thousand soldiers from Nolae, and four
                    thousand of the Samnites, had been received into Palaepolis, a measure rather
                    forced on the Greeks by the Nolans than agreeable to their inclination.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Cor- nelius wrote, that a levy of troops
                    had been ordered, that all Samnium was in motion, and that the neighbouring
                    states of Privernum, Fundi, and Formiae, were openly solicited to join them.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When in consequence it was thought proper,
                    that, before hostilities were commenced, ambassadors should be sent to the
                    Samnites, an insolent answer is returned by them; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> they even went so far as to accuse the Romans of behaving
                    injuriously towards them; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but, nevertheless,
                    they took pains to clear themselves of the charges made against them, assert-
                    ing, that <quote> the Greeks were not assisted with either counsel or aid by
                        their state, nor were the Fundanians or Formians tampered with by them; for,
                        if they were disposed to war, <pb n="534" xml:id="p.534"/> they had not the
                        least reason to be diffident of their own strength. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> However, they could not dissemble, that it gave great
                        offence to the state of the Samnites, that Fregellae, by them taken from the
                        Volscians and demolished, should have been rebuilt by the Romans; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> and that they should have established a colony
                        within the territory of the Samnites, to which their colonists gave the name
                        of Fregellae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This injury and affront, if
                        not done away by the authors, they were determined themselves to remove, by
                        every means in their power. </quote> When one of the Roman ambassadors
                    proposed to discuss the matter before their common allies and friends, their
                    magistrate said, <quote> Why do we disguise our sentiments? Romans, no
                        conferences of ambassadors, nor arbitration of any person whatever, can
                        terminate our differences; but the plains of Campania, in which we must
                        meet; our arms and the common fortune of war will settle the point.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Let our armies, therefore, meet
                        between Capua and Suessula; and there let us decide, whether the Samnite or
                        the Roman shall hold the sovereignty of Italy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To this the ambassadors of the Romans
                    replied, that they would go, not whither their enemy called, but whither their
                    commanders should lead." In the mean time, Publilius, by seizing an advantageous
                    post between Palaepolis and Neapolis, had cut off that interchange of mutual
                    aid, which they had hitherto afforded each other, according as either place was
                    hard pressed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly, when both the day
                    of the elections approached, and as it was highly inexpedient for the public
                    interest that Publilius should be called away when on the point of assailing the
                    enemy's walls, and in daily expectation of gaining possession of their city,
                    application was made to the tribunes, to <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                    recommend to the people the passing of an order, that Publilius Philo, when his
                    year of office should expire, might continue in command, as pro-consul, until
                    the war with the Greeks should be finished. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> A
                    letter was despatched to Lucius Cornelius, with orders to name a dictator; for
                    it was not thought proper that the consul should be recalled from the vigorous
                    prosecution of the war now that he had entered into Samnium. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> He nominated Marcus Claudius Marcellus, who appointed
                    Spurius Postumius master of the horse. The elections, however, were not held by
                    the dictator, because it became a question whether he had been appointed under
                    an irregularity; <pb n="535" xml:id="p.535"/> and the augurs being consulted,
                    pronounced that it appeared that the dictator's appointment was defective.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The tribunes inveighed against this
                    proceeding as dangerous and dishonourable; <quote>for it was not
                        probable,</quote> they said, <quote> that suc defect could have been
                        discovered, as the consul, rising in the night, had nominated the dictator
                        while every thing was still; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Any
                            noise happening during the taking of the auspices was reckoned
                            inauspicious; hence <hi rend="italics">silentium</hi> signified among
                            the augurs, every circum- stance being favourable. </note> nor had the
                        said consul in any of his letters, either public or private, made any
                        mention of such a thing to any <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> one; nor
                        did any person whatever come forward who said that he saw or heard any thing
                        which could vitiate the auspices. Neither could the augurs sitting at Rome
                        divine what inauspicious circumstance had occurred to the consul <milestone
                            n="17" unit="section"/> in the camp. Who did not plainly perceive, that
                        the dictator's being a plebeian, was the defect which the augurs had
                        discovered? </quote> These and other arguments were urged in vain by the
                    tribunes: the affair however ended in an interregnum. At last, after the
                    elections had been adjourned repeatedly on one pretext or another, the
                    fourteenth interrex, Lucius Aemilius, elected consuls Caius Paetelius, and
                    Lucius Papirius Mugillanius, or Cursor, as I find him named in some annals. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It has been recorded, that in this year
                    Alexandria in Egypt was founded; and that Alexander, king of Epirus, being slain
                    by a Lucanian exile, verified in the circumstances of his death the prediction
                    of Jupiter of Dodona. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the time when he was
                    invited into Italy by the Tarentines, a caution had been given him, <quote> to
                        beware of the Acherusian waters and the city Pandosia, for there were fixed
                        the limits of his destiny. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For that reason he made the greater haste to
                    pass over to Italy, in order to be at as great a distance as possible from the
                    city Pandosia in Epirus, and the river Acheron, which, after flowing through
                    Molossis, runs into the lakes called Infernal, and is received into the
                    Thesprotian gulf. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But, (as it frequently
                    happens, that men, by endeavouring to shun their fate, run directly upon it,)
                    after having often defeated the armies of Bruttium and Lucania, and taken
                    Heraclea, a colony of the Tarentines, Consentia and Metapontum from the
                    Lucanians, Terina from the Bruttians, and several other cities of the Messapians
                    and Lucanians; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and having sent <pb n="536"
                        xml:id="p.536"/> into Epirus three hundred illustrious families, whom he in-
                    tended to keep as hostages, he posted his troops on three hills, which stood at
                    a small distance from each other, not far from the city Pandosia, and close to
                    the frontiers of the Bruttians and Lucanians, in order that he might thence make
                    incursions into every part of the enemy's country. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At that time he kept about his person two hundred Lucanian
                    exiles, as faithful attendants, but whose fidelity, according to the general
                    disposition of people of that description, was ever ready to follow the changes
                    of fortune. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When continual rains spread such
                    an inundation over all the plains, as cut off from the three separate divisions
                    of the army all means of mutual aid, the two parties, in neither of which the
                    king was present, were suddenly attacked and overpowered by the enemy, who,
                    after putting them to the sword, employed their whole force in blockading the
                    king himself. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From this place the Lucanian
                    exiles sent emissaries to their countrymen, and stipulating a safe return for
                    themselves, promised to deliver the king, either alive or dead, into their
                    power. But he, bravely resolving to make an extraordinary effort, at the head of
                    a chosen band, broke through the midst of their forces; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> engaged singly, and slew the general of the Lucanians, and
                    collecting together his men, who had been scattered in the retreat, arrived at a
                    river which pointed out his road <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> by the
                    ruins of a bridge which had been recently broken by the violence of the flood.
                    Here, while the party was fording the river on a very uneven bottom, a soldier,
                    almost spent with fatigue and apprehension, cried out as a reflection on the
                    odious name of it,  <quote> You <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> are justly
                        named Acheros (dismal): </quote> which expression reaching the king's ears,
                    and instantly recalling to his mind the fate denounced on him, he halted,
                    hesitating whether he should cross over or not. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> Then Sotimus, one of the royal band of youths which attended him, asking why
                    he delayed in such a critical moment, showed him that the Lucanians were
                    watching an opportunity to perpetrate some act of treachery: whereupon the king,
                    looking back, and seeing them coming towards him in a body, drew his sword, and
                    pushed on his horse through the middle of the river. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> When he had now reached the shallow, a Lucanian exile from
                    a distance transfixed him with a javelin: after his fall, the current carried
                    down his lifeless body, with the weapon sticking in it, to the posts of the
                    enemy: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> there a <pb n="537" xml:id="p.537"/>
                    shocking mangling of it took place; for dividing it in the middle, they sent one
                    half to Consentia, and kept the other, as a subject of mockery, to themselves.
                    While they were throwing darts and stones at it, a woman mixing with the crowd,
                    who were enraged to a degree beyond the credible extent of human resentment,
                    prevailed on them to stop for a moment. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> She
                    then told them with tears in her eyes that she had a husband and children,
                    prisoners among the enemy; and that she hoped to be able with the king's body,
                    however disfigured, to ransom her friends: this put an end to their outrages.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The remnants of his limbs were buried at
                    Consentia, entirely through the care of the woman; and his bones were sent to
                    Metapontum to the enemy, from whence they were conveyed to Epirus to his wife
                    Cleopatra and his sister Olympias; the latter of whom was the mother, the former
                    the sister, of Alexander the Great. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Such was
                    the melancholy end of Alexander of Epirus; of which, although fortune did not
                    allow him to engage in hostilities with the Romans, yet, as he waged war in
                    Italy, I have thought it proper to give this brief account. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> This year, the fifth time since the building of the city,
                    the lectisternium was performed at Rome for procuring the favour of the same
                    deities to whom it was addressed before. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the new consuls had, by order of the
                    people, sent persons to declare war against the Samnites, and they themselves
                    were making all preparations with greater energy than against the Greeks, a new
                    accession of strength also came to them when expecting no such thing. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The Lucanians and Apulians, nations who, until that
                    time, had no kind of intercourse with the Roman people, proposed an alliance
                    with them, promising a supply of men and arms for the war: a treaty of
                    friendship was accordingly concluded. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the
                    same time, their affairs went on successfully in Samnium. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Three owns fell into their hands, Allifae, Callifae, and
                    Ruffrium; and the adjoining country to a great extent was, on the first arrival
                    of the consuls, laid entirely waste. Whilst the war on this side was commenced
                    with so much success, so the war in the other quarter where the Greeks were held
                    besieged, now drew towards a conclusion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For,
                    besides the communication between the two posts of the enemy being cut off, by
                    the besiegers having possession of part of the works through which it had been
                    carried on, they now suffered within the walls hardships far <pb n="538"
                        xml:id="p.538"/> more grievous than those with which the enemy threatened
                    them, and as if made prisoners by their own garrison, they were now subjected to
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the greatest indignities in the persons
                    of their wives and children, and to such extremities as are generally felt on
                    the sacking of cities. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When, therefore,
                    intelligence arrived that reinforcements were to come from Tarentum and from the
                    Samnites, all agreed that there were more of the latter already within the walls
                    than they wished; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but the young men of
                    Tarentum, who were Greeks as well as themselves, they earnestly longed for, as
                    they hoped to be enabled by their means to oppose the Samnites and Nolans, no
                    less than to resist their Roman enemies. At last a surrender to the Romans
                    appeared to be the lightest evil. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Charilaus
                    and Nymphius, the two principal men in the state, consulting together on the
                    subject, settled the part which each was to act; it was, that one should desert
                    to the Roman general, and the other stay behind to manage affairs in the city,
                    so as to facilitate the execution of their plan. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Charilaus was the person who came to Publilius Philo; he
                    told him that <quote> he had taken a resolution, which he hoped would prove
                        advantageous, fortunate, and happy to the Palaepolitans and to the Roman
                        people, of delivering the fortifications into his hands. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Whether he should appear by that deed to have betrayed
                        or preserved his country, depended on the honour of the Romans. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> That for himself in particular, he neither
                        stipulated nor requested any thing; but, in behalf of the state, he
                        requested rather than stipulated, that in case the design should succeed,
                        the Roman people would consider more especially the zeal and hazard with
                        which it sought a renewal of their friendship, than its folly and rashness
                        in deviating from its duty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He was commended by the general, and received
                    a body of three thousand soldiers, with which he was to seize on that part of
                    the city which was possessed by the Samnites; this detachment was commanded by
                    Lucius Quinctius, military tribune. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time also, Nymphius, on his part,
                    artfully addressing himself to the commander of the Samnites, prevailed upon
                    him, as all the troops of the Romans were employed either about Palaepolis or in
                    Samnium, to allow him to sail round with the fleet to the territory of Rome,
                    where he undertook to ravage, not only the sea-coast, but the country adjoining
                    the very city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But, in order to avoid
                    observation, it was necessary, <pb n="539" xml:id="p.539"/> he told him, to set
                    out by night, and to launch the ships imme- diately. That this might be effected
                    with the greater despatch, all the young Samnites, except the necessary guards
                    of the city, were sent to the shore. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While
                    Nymphius wasted the time there, giving contradictory orders, designedly, to
                    create confu- sion, which was increased by the darkness, and by the crowd, which
                    was so numerous as to obstruct each other's operations, Charilaus, according to
                    the plan concerted, was admitted by his associates into the city; and have
                    filled the higher parts of it with Roman soldiers, he ordered them to raise a
                    shout; on which the Greeks, who had received previous directions from their
                    leaders, kept themselves quiet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Nolans
                    fled through the opposite part of the town, by the road leading to Nola. The
                    flight of the Samnites, who were shut out from the city, was easier, but had a
                    more disgraceful appearance; for they re- turned to their homes without arms,
                    stripped, and destitute of every thing; all, in short, belonging to them being
                    left with their enemies; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> so that they were
                    objects of ridicule, not only to foreigners, but even to their own countrymen.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I know that there is another account of
                    this matter, according to which the town is represented to have been betrayed by
                    the Samnites; but I have this account on the authority most worthy of credit;
                    besides, the treaty of Neapolis, for to that place the seat of government of the
                    Greeks was then transferred, renders it more probable that the renewal of
                    friendship was voluntary on their side. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A
                    triumph was decreed to Publilius, because people were well convinced that the
                    enemy, reduced by the siege, had adopted terms of submission. These two
                    extraordi- nary incidents, which never before occurred in any case, befell this
                    man: a prolongation of command never before granted to any one; and a triumph
                    after the expiration of his office. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Another war soon after arose with the Greeks
                    of the other coast. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For the Tarentines having,
                    for a considerable time, buoyed up the state of Palaepolis with delusive hopes
                    of assistance, when they understood that the Romans had gotten possession of
                    that city, as if they were the persons who had suffered the disappointment, and
                    not the authors of it, they inveighed against the Palaepolitans, and became
                    furious in their anger and malice towards the Romans; on this account also,
                    because information was brought that the Lucanians and Apulians had submitted to
                    the Roman people; for a treaty of <pb n="540" xml:id="p.540"/> alliance had been
                    this year concluded with both these nations. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>The business,</quote> they observed, <quote> was now brought almost to
                        their doors; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and that the matter would
                        soon come to this, that the Romans must either be dealt with as enemies, or
                        received as masters: that, in fact, their interests were involved in the war
                        of the Samnites, and in its issue. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That
                        that was the only nation which continued to make opposition; and that with
                        power very inadequate, since the Lucanians left them: these however might
                        yet be brought back, and induced to renounce the Roman alliance, if proper
                        skill were used in sowing dissension between them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These reasonings being readily adopted, by
                    people who wished for a change, some young Lucanians of considerable note among
                    their countrymen, but devoid of honour, were procured for money; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> these having lacerated each other's persons with
                    stripes, after they had come naked into a public meeting of their countrymen,
                    exclaimed that, because they had ventured to go into the Roman camp, they had
                    been thus beaten with rods, by order of the consul, and had hardly escaped the
                    loss of their heads. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A circumstance, so
                    shocking in its nature, carrying strong proofs of the ill-treatment, none of
                    artifice, the people were so irritated, that, by their clamours, they compelled
                    the magistrates to call together the senate; and some standing round that
                    assembly, insisted on a declaration of war against the Romans, others ran
                    different ways to rouse to arms the multitude residing in the country.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus the tumult hurrying into imprudence
                    the minds even of rational men, a decree was passed, that the alliance with the
                    Samnites should be renewed, and ambassadors sent for that purpose. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Because this so sudden a proceeding was totally
                    devoid of any obvious cause for its adoption, and consequently was little relied
                    on for its sincerity; they were, however, obliged both to give hostages, and
                    also to receive garrisons into their fortified places; and they, blinded by
                    fraud and resentment, refused no terms. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In a
                    little time after, on the authors of the false charges removing to Tarentum, the
                    whole imposition came to light. But as they had given all power out of their own
                    hands, nothing was left them but unavailing repentance. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year there arose, as it were, a new era
                    of liberty to the Roman commons; in this that a stop was put to the practice of
                    confining debtors. This alteration of the law was effected in consequence of the
                    lust and signal cruelty of one usurer. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="541" xml:id="p.541"/> His name was Lucius Papirius. To him one Caius
                    Publilius having surrendered his person to be confined for a debt due by his
                    father, his youth and beauty, which ought to have excited commiseration,
                    operated on the other's mind as incentives to lust and insult. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He first attempted to seduce the young man by impure
                    discourses, considering the bloom of his youth his own adventitious gain; but
                    finding that his ears were shocked at their infamous tendency, he then
                    endeavoured to terrify him by threats, and reminded him frequently of his
                    situation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At last, convinced of his
                    resolution to act conformably to his honour- able birth, rather than to his
                    present condition, he ordered him to be stripped and scourged. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> When with the marks of the rods imprinted in his flesh the
                    youth rushed out into the public street, loudly complaining of the depravedness
                    and inhumanity of the usurer; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> a vast number of
                    people, moved by compassion for his early age, and indignation at his barbarous
                    treatment, reflecting at the same time on their own lot and that of their
                    children, flocked together into the forum, and from thence in a body to the
                    senate-house. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the consuls were obliged by
                    the sudden tumult to call a meeting of the senate, the people, falling at the
                    feet of each of the senators, as they were going into the senate-house,
                    presented to their view the lace- rated back of the youth. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> On that day, in consequence of the outrageous conduct of an
                    individual, the strongest bonds of credit were broken; and the consuls were
                    commanded to propose to the people, that no person should be held in fetters or
                    stocks, except convicted of a crime, and in order to punish- ment; but that, for
                    money due, the goods of the debtor, not his person, should be answerable.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus the confined debtors were released;
                    and provision made, for the time to come, that they should not be liable to
                    confinement. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the course of this year, while the war with
                    the Samnites was sufficient in itself to give full employment to the senate,
                    besides the sudden defection of the Lucanians, and the Tarentines, the promoters
                    of the defection, [another source of uneasiness] was added in a union formed by
                    the state of the Vestinians with the Samnites. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Which event, though it con- tinued, during the present year, to be the general
                    subject of con- versation, without coming under any public discussion, appeared
                    so important to the consuls of the year following, Lucius Fu- rius Camillus a
                    second time, and Junius Brutus Scaeva, that it <pb n="542" xml:id="p.542"/> was
                    the first business which they proposed to the consideration of the state.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And though the matter was still recent,
                    still great perplexity seized the senate, as they dreaded equally the
                    consequences, either of passing it over, or of taking it up; lest, on the one
                    hand, impunity might stir up the neighbouring states with wantonness and
                    arrogance; and, on the other, punishment inflicted on them by force of arms, and
                    dread of immediate danger, might produce the same effect by exciting resentment.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And the whole body, too, was in every way
                    equal in strength to the Samnites, being composed of the Marsians, the
                    Pelignians, and the Marrusinians; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> all of whom
                    would have to be encountered as enemies, if the Vestinians were to be interfered
                    with. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However, that side prevailed which
                    might, at the time, seem to have more spirit than prudence; but the event proved
                    that fortune assists the brave. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The people, in
                    pursuance of the direction of the senate, ordered war against the Vestinians;
                    that province fell by lot to Junius, Samnium to Camillus. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Armies were led to both places, and by carefully guarding
                    the frontiers, the enemy were prevented from joining their forces. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> But the other consul, Lucius Furius, on whom the
                    principal weight of the business rested, was withdrawn by chance from the war,
                    being seized with a severe sickness. Being therefore ordered to nominate a
                    dictator to conduct the business, he nominated Lucius Papirius Cursor, the most
                    celebrated general, by far, of any in that age, who appointed Quintus Fabius
                    Maximus Rullianus master of the horse: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> a pair
                    of commanders distinguished for their exploits in war; more so, however, for a
                    quarrel between themselves, and which proceeded almost to violence. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The other consul, in the territory of the
                    Vestinians, carried on operations of various kinds; and, in all, was uniformly
                    successful. For he both utterly laid waste their lands, and, by spoiling and
                    burning their houses and corn, compelled them to come to an engagement;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and, in one battle, he reduced the
                    strength of the Vestinians to such a degree, though not without loss on his own
                    side, that the enemy not only fled to their camp, but, fearing even to trust to
                    the rampart and trench, dispersed from thence into the several towns, in hopes
                    of finding security in the situation and fortifications of their cities.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At last, having undertaken to reduce
                    their towns by force, amid the great ardour of the soldiers, and their
                    resentment for the wounds which they <pb n="543" xml:id="p.543"/> had received,
                    (hardly one of them having come out of the battle unhurt,) he took Cutina by
                    scalade, and afterwards Cingilia. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The spoil
                    of both cities he gave to the soldiers, in consideration of their having bravely
                    surmounted the obstruction both of gates and walls. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commanders entered Samnium under uncertain
                    auspices; an informality which pointed, not at the event of war, for that was
                    prosperous, but at the furious passions and the quarrels which broke out between
                    the leaders. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For Papirius the dictator,
                    returning to Rome in order to take the auspices anew, in consequence of a
                    caution received from the aruspex, left strict orders with the master of the
                    horse to remain in his post, and not to engage in battle during his absence.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After the departure of the dictator,
                    Fabius having discovered by his scouts that the enemy were in as unguarded a
                    state as if there was not a single Roman in Samnium, the high-spirited youth,
                    (either conceiving <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> indignation at the sole
                    authority in every point appearing to be lodged in the hands of the dictator, or
                    induced by the opportunity of striking an important blow,) having made the
                    necessary preparations and dispositions, marched to a place called Imbrinium,
                    and there fought a battle with the Samnites. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    His success in the fight was such, that there was no one circumstance which
                    could have been improved to more advantage, if the dictator had been present.
                    The leader was not wanting to the soldiers, nor the soldier to their leader.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The cavalry too, (finding, after repeated
                    charges, that they could not break the ranks,) by the advice of Lucius Co-
                    minius, a military tribune, pulled off the bridles from their horses and spurred
                    them on so furiously, that no power could withstand them; forcing their way
                    through the thickest of the enemy, they bore down every thing before them; and
                    the in- fantry seconding the charge, the whole body was thrown into confusion.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Twenty thousand of the enemy are said to
                    have fallen on that day. I have authority for saying that there were two battles
                    fought during the dictator's absence, and two vic- tories obtained; but,
                    according to the most ancient writers, only this one is found, and in some
                    histories the whole trans- action is omitted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The master of the horse getting possession of abundance of spoils, in
                    consequence of the great numbers slain, collected the arms into a huge heap, and
                    burned them; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> either in pursuance of a vow to
                    some of the gods, or, if we <pb n="544" xml:id="p.544"/> choose to credit the
                    authority of Fabius, it was done on this account, that the dictator might not
                    reap the fruits of his glory, inscribe his name on them, or carry the spoils in
                    triumph. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> His letters also, containing an
                    account of the success, being sent to the senate, not to the dictator, showed
                    plainly that he wished not to impart to him any share of the honour; who
                    certainly viewed the proceeding in this light, for while others rejoiced at the
                    victory obtained, he showed only surliness and anger; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> insomuch that, immediately dismissing the senate, he
                    hastened out of the senate-house, and frequently repeated with warmth, that the
                    legions of the Samnites were not more effectually vanquished and overthrown by
                    the master of the horse, than were the dictatorial dignity and military
                    discipline, if such contempt of orders escaped with impunity. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Thus, breathing resentment and menaces, he set out for the
                    camp; but, though he travelled with all possible expedition, he was unable,
                    however, to outstrip the report of his coming. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> For messengers had started from the city before him, who brought intelligence
                    that the dictator was coming, eager for vengeance, and in almost every second
                    sentence applauding the conduct of Titus Manlius. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius instantly called an assembly, and
                    entreated the soldiers to <quote> show the same courage in protecting him, under
                        whose conduct and auspices they had conquered, from the outrageous cruelty
                        of the dictator, which they had so lately displayed in defending the
                        commonwealth from its most inveterate enemies. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He was now coming, </quote> he told them, <quote>
                        frantic with envy; enraged at another's bravery and success, he was mad,
                        because, in his absence, the business of the public had been executed with
                        remarkable success; and if he could change the fortune of the engagement,
                        would wish the Samnites in possession of victory rather than the Romans.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He talked much of contempt of orders;
                        as if his prohibition of fighting were not dictated by the same motive,
                        which caused his vexation at the fight having taken place. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He wished to shackle the valour of others through envy,
                        and meant to take away the soldiers' arms when they were most eager for
                        action, and that no use might be made of them in his absence: he was further
                        enraged too, because without Lucius Papirius the soldiers were not without
                        hands or arms, and because Quintus Fabius considered himself as master of
                        the horse, not <pb n="545" xml:id="p.545"/> as a beadle to the dictator.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> How would he have behaved, had the
                        issue of the fight been unfortunate; which, through the chances of war and
                        the uncertainty of military operations, might have been the case; since now,
                        when the enemy has been vanquished, (as completely, indeed, as if that
                        leader's own singular talents had been employed in the matter,) he yet
                        threatens the master of the horse with punishment? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Nor is he more incensed against the master of the
                        horse, than against the military tribunes, the centurions, and the soldiers.
                        On all, he would vent his rage if he could; and because that is not in his
                        power, he vents it on one. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Envy, like
                        flame, soars upwards; aims at the summit; that he makes his attack on the
                        head of the business, on the leader. If he could put him out of the way,
                        together with the glory of the service performed, he would then lord it,
                        like a conqueror over vanquished troops; and, without scruple, practise
                        against the soldiers what he had been allowed to act against their
                        commander. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That they should, therefore, in
                        his cause; support the general liberty of all. If the dictator perceived
                        among the troops the same unanimity in justifying their victory that they
                        had displayed in the battle, and that all interested themselves in the
                        safety of one, it would bend his temper to milder counsels. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> In fine, </quote> he told them, <quote>that he
                        committed his life, and all his interests, to their honour and to their cou
                        age.</quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> His speech was received with the loudest
                    acclamations from every part of the assembly, bidding him <quote> have courage;
                        for while the Roman legions were in being, no man should offer him violence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not long after, the dictator arrived, and
                    instantly summoned an assembly by sound of trumpet Then silence being made, a
                    crier cited Quintus Fabius, master of the horse, and as soon as, on the lower
                    ground, he had approached the tribunal, the dictator said, <quote> Quintus
                        Fabius, I demand of you, when the authority of dictator is acknowledged to
                        be supreme, and is submitted to by the consuls, officers endowed with regal
                        power; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and likewise by the praetors,
                        created under the same auspices with consuls; whether or no you think it
                        reasonable that it should not meet obedience from a master of the horse?
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I also ask you whether, when I knew
                        that I set out from home under uncertain auspices, the safety of the
                        commonwealth ought to have been endangered by me, whilst the omens were
                        confused, or whether the <pb n="546" xml:id="p.546"/> auspices ought to be
                        newly taken, so that nothing might be done while the will of the gods
                        remained doubtful? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And further, when a
                        religious scruple was of such a nature as to hinder the dictator from
                        acting, whether the master of the horse could be exempt from it and at
                        liberty? But why do I ask these questions, when, though I had gone without
                        leaving any orders, your own judgment ought to have been regulated according
                        to what you could discover of my intention? Why do you not answer?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Did I not forbid you to act, in any
                        respect, during my absence? Did I not forbid you to engage the enemy?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Yet, in contempt of these my orders,
                        while the auspices were uncertain, while the omens were confused, contrary
                        to the practice of war, contrary to the discipline of our ancestors, and
                        contrary to the authority of the gods, you dared to enter on the fight.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Answer to these questions proposed to
                        you. On any other matter utter not a word. Lictor, draw near him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To each of these particulars, Fabius, finding
                    it no easy matter to answer, at one time remonstrated against the same person
                    acting as accuser and judge, in a cause which affected his very existence; at
                    another, he asserted that his life should sooner be forced from him, than the
                    glory of his past services; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> clearing himself
                    and accusing the other by turns; so then Papirius' anger blazing out with fresh
                    fury, he ordered the master of the horse to be stripped, and the rods and axes
                    to be got ready. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Fabius, imploring the
                    protection of the soldiers, while the lictors were tearing his garments, betook
                    himself to the quarters of the veterans, who were already raising a commotion in
                    the assembly: from them the uproar spread through the whole body; in one place
                    the voice of supplication was heard; in another, menaces. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Those who happened to stand nearest to the tribunal,
                    because, being under the eyes of the general, they could easily be known,
                    entreated him to spare the master of the horse, and not in him to condemn the
                    whole army. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The remoter parts of the
                    assembly, and the crowd collected round Fabius, railed at the unrelenting spirit
                    of the dictator, and were not far from mutiny; nor was even the tribunal
                    perfectly quiet. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The lieutenants-general
                    standing round the general's seat besought him to adjourn the business to the
                    next day, and to allow time to his anger, and room for consideration;
                    representing that <quote> the indiscretion of Fabius had been sufficiently
                        rebuked; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        <pb n="547" xml:id="p.547"/> his victory sufficiently disgraced; and they
                        begged him not to proceed to the extreme of severity; not to brand with
                        ignominy a youth of extraordinary merit, or his father, a man of most
                        illustrious character, together with the whole family of the Fabii. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> When they made but little impression either
                    by their prayers or arguments, they desired him to observe the violent ferment
                    of the assembly, and told him that <quote> while the soldiers' tempers were
                        heated to such a degree, it became not either his age or his wisdom to
                        kindle them into a flame, and afford matter for a mutiny; <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> that no one would lay the blame of such an event on
                        Quintus Fabius, who only deprecated punishment; but on the dictator, if,
                        blinded by resent- ment, he should, by an ill-judged contest, draw on
                        himself the fury of the multitude: <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> and
                        lest he should think that they acted from motives of regard to Quintus
                        Fabius, they were ready to make oath that, in their judgment, it was not for
                        the interest of the commonwealth that Quintus Fabius should be punished at
                        that time. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When by these expostulations they rather
                    irritated the dictator against themselves, than appeased his anger against the
                    master of the horse, the lieutenants-general were ordered to go down from the
                    tribunal; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and after several vain attempts were
                    made to procure silence by means of a crier, the noise and tumult being so great
                    that neither the voice of the dictator himself, nor that of his apparitors,
                    could be heard; night, as in the case of a battle, put an end to the contest.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The master of the horse was ordered to
                    attend on the day following; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but when all
                    assured him that Papirius, being agitated and exasperated in the course of the
                    present contention, would proceed against him with greater violence, he fled
                    privately from the camp to Rome; where, by the advice of his father, Marcus
                    Fabius, who had been three times consul, and likewise dictator, he immediately
                    called a meeting of the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While he was
                    strenuously complaining before the fathers of the rage and injustice of the
                    dictator, on a sudden was heard the noise of lictors before the senate-house,
                    clearing the way, and Papirius himself arrived, full of resentment, having
                    followed, with a guard of light horse, as soon as he heard that the other had
                    quitted the camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The contention then began
                    anew, and the dictator ordered Fabius to be seized. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Where, when his unrelenting spirit persisted in its
                    purpose, notwith- <pb n="548" xml:id="p.548"/> standing the united intercessions
                    of the principal patricians, and of the whole senate, Fabius, the father, then
                    said, <quote> Since neither the authority of the senate has any weight with you;
                        nor my age, which you wish to render childless; nor the noble birth and
                        merit of a master of the horse, nominated by yourself; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> nor prayers which have often mitigated the rage of an
                        enemy, and which appease the wrath of the gods; I call upon the tribunes of
                        the commons for support, and appeal to the people; and since you decline the
                        judgment of your own army, as well as of the senate, I call you before a
                        judge who must certainly be allowed, though no other should, to possess more
                        power and authority than yourself, though dictator. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> I shall see whether you will submit to an appeal, to
                        which Tullus Hostilius, a Roman king, submitted. </quote> They proceeded
                    directly from the senate-house to the assembly; <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> where, being arrived, the dictator attended by few, the master of the horse
                    by all the people of the first rank in a body, Papirius commanded him to be
                    taken from the rostrum to the lower ground; his father, following him, said,
                        <quote> You do well in ordering us to be brought down to a place where even
                        as private persons we have liberty of speech. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At first, instead of regular speeches,
                    nothing but altercation was heard; at length, the indignation of old Fabius, and
                    the strength <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> of his voice, got the better
                    of noise, while he reproached Papirius with arrogance and cruelty. <quote>He
                        himself,</quote> he said, <quote> had been dictator at Rome; and no man, not
                        even the lowest plebeian, or centurion, or soldier, had been outraged by
                        him. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But Papirius sought for victory and
                        triumph over a Roman commander, as over the generals of the enemy. What an
                        immense difference between the moderation of the ancients, and modern
                        oppression and cruelty. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Quinctius
                        Cincinnatus when dictator exercised no further severity on Lucius Minucius
                        the consul, although rescued by him from a siege, than leaving him at the
                        head of the army, in the quality of lieutenant-general, instead of consul.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Marcus Furius Camillus, in the case
                        of Lucius Furius, who, in contempt of his great age and authority, had
                        fought a battle with a most disgraceful result, not only restrained his
                        anger at the time so as to write no unfavourable representation of his
                        conduct to the people or the senate; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> but
                        after returning home, when the patricians gave him a power of electing from
                        among his colleagues whoever he might approve as an associ- <pb n="549"
                            xml:id="p.549"/> ate with himself in the command, chose that very man in
                        pre- ference to all the other consular tribunes. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Nay, that not even the resentment of the people, with
                        whom lay the supreme power in all cases, was ever exercised with greater
                        severity towards those who, through rashness and ignorance, had occasioned
                        the loss of armies, than the fining them in a sum of money. <milestone
                            n="18" unit="section"/> Until that day, a capital prosecution for ill
                        conduct in war had never been instituted against any commander, but now
                        generals of the Roman people when victorious, and meriting the most
                        honourable triumphs, are threatened with rods and axes; a treatment which
                        would not have been deemed allow- able, even towards those who had been
                        defeated by an enemy. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> What would his son
                        have to suffer, if he had occasioned the loss of the army? if he had been
                        routed, put to flight, and driven out of his camp? To what greater length
                        could his re- sentment and violence be stretched, than to scourge him, and
                        put him to death? <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> How was it consistent
                        with reason, that through the means of Quintus Fabius, the state should be
                        filled with joy, exulting in victory, and occupied in thanks- givings and
                        congratulations; while at the same time, he who had given occasion to the
                        temples of the gods being thrown open, their altars yet smoking with
                        sacrifices, and <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/> loaded with honours and
                        offerings, should be stripped naked, and torn with stripes in the sight of
                        the Roman people; within view of the Capitol and citadel, and of those gods
                        not in vain invoked in two different battles? <milestone n="22"
                            unit="section"/> With what temper would the army which had conquered
                        under his conduct and auspices have borne it? What mourning would there be
                        in the Roman camp! what joy among their enemies! </quote>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> This speech he ac- companied with an abundant
                    flow of tears; uniting reproaches and complaints, imploring the aid both of gods
                    and men, and warmly embracing his son. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On his side stood the majesty of the senate,
                    the favour of the people, the support of the tribunes, and regard for the absent
                    army. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the other side were urged the
                    inviolable authority of the Roman government and military discipline; the edict
                    of the dictator, always observed as the mandate of a deity; the orders of
                    Manlius, and his postponing even parental affection to public utility.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>The same also,</quote> said the dictator, <quote> was the conduct of
                        Lucius Brutus, the founder of Roman liberty, in the case of his two sons.
                        That now fathers were <pb n="550" xml:id="p.550"/> become indulgent, and the
                        aged indifferent in the case of the authority of others being despised, and
                        indulge the young in the subversion of military order, as if it were a
                        matter of trifling consequence. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For his
                        part, however, he would persevere in his purpose, and would not remit the
                        smallest part of the punishment justly due to a person who fought contrary
                        to his orders, while the rites of religion were imperfectly ex- ecuted, and
                        the auspices uncertain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whether the
                        majesty of the supreme authority was to be perpetual or not, depended not on
                        him; but Lucius Papirius would not diminish aught of its rights. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> He wished that the tribunitian office, inviolate
                        itself, would not by its interposition violate the authority of the Roman
                        government; nor the Roman people, to their own detriment particularly,
                        annihilate the dictator and the rights of the dictatorship together.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But if this should be the case, not
                        Lucius Papirius but the tribunes and the people would be blamed by posterity
                        in vain; when military discipline being once dissolved, the soldier would no
                        longer obey the orders of the centurion, the centurion those of the tribune,
                        the tribune those of the lieutenant-general, the lieutenant-general those of
                        the consul, nor the master of the horse those of the dictator. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> No one would then pay any deference to men, no,
                        nor even to the gods. Neither edicts of generals nor auspices would be
                        observed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The soldiers, without leave of
                        absence, would straggle at random through the lands of friends and of foes;
                        and regardless of their oath would, influenced solely by a wanton humour,
                        quit the service whenever they might choose. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The standards would be unattended and forsaken: the men
                        would neither assemble in pursuance of orders, nor would any distinction be
                        made as to fighting by night or by day, on favourable or unfavourable
                        ground, by order or without the the orders of the general; nor would they
                        observe standards or ranks; the service, instead of being solemn and sacred,
                        would be confused and the result of mere chance, like that of freebooters.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Render yourselves then, tribunes of
                        the commons, accountable for all these evils to all future ages. Expose your
                        own persons to these heavy imputations in defence of the licentious conduct
                        of Quintus Fabius. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The tribunes now confounded, and more
                    anxiously concerned at their own situation than at his for whom their support
                    was sought, were freed from this embarrassment by the Roman <pb n="551"
                        xml:id="p.551"/> people unanimously having recourse to prayers and
                    entreaties, that the dictator would, for their sakes, remit the punishment of
                    the master of the horse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The tribunes
                    likewise, following the example set them of employing entreaties, earnestly
                    beseech the dictator to pardon human error, to consider the immaturity of the
                    offender's age; that he had suffered sufficiently; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and now the youth himself, now his father, Marcus Fabius,
                    disclaiming further contest, fell at the dictator's knees and deprecated his
                    wrath. Then the dictator, after causing silence, said, <quote> Romans, it is
                        well. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Military discipline has prevailed;
                        the majesty of government has prevailed; both which were in danger of
                        ceasing this day to exist. Quintus Fabius, who fought contrary to the order
                        of his commander, is not acquitted of guilt; <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> but after being condemned as guilty, is granted as a boon to the Roman
                        people; is granted to the college of tribunes, supporting him with their
                        prayers, not with the regular power of their office. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Live, Quintus Fabius, more happy in this united
                        sympathy of the state for your preservation, than in the victory in which
                        you lately exulted. Live, after having ventured on such an act, as your
                        father himself, had he been in the place of Lucius Papirius, would not have
                        pardoned. With me you shall be reconciled whenever you wish it. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> To the Roman people, to whom you owe your life,
                        you can perform no greater service than to let this day teach you a
                        sufficient lesson to enable you to submit to lawful commands, both in war
                        and peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then declared, that he no longer detained
                    the master of the horse, and as he retired from the rostrum, the senate being
                    greatly rejoiced, and the people still more so, gathered round him and escorted
                    him, on one hand commending the dictator, on the other congratulating the master
                    of the horse; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> while it was considered that the
                    authority of military command was confirmed no less effectually by the danger of
                    Quintus Fabius that the lamentable punishment of young Manlius. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> It so hap- pened, that, through the course of that
                    year, as often as the dictator left the army the Samnites were in motion: but
                    Mar- cus Valerius, the lieutenant-general who commanded in the camp, had Quintus
                    Fabius before his eyes for an example, not to fear any violence of the enemy, so
                    much as the unrelenting anger of the dictator. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> So that when a body of his foragers fell into an ambuscade and were cut to
                    pieces in disadvantageous ground, it was generally believed that the
                    lieutenant-general <pb n="552" xml:id="p.552"/> could have given them assistance
                    if he had not been held in dread by his rigorous orders. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The resentment for this also alienated the affections of
                    the soldiery from the dictator, already incensed against him because he had been
                    implacable towards Quintus Fabius, and because he had granted him pardon at the
                    intercession of the Roman people, a thing which he had refused to their
                    entreaties. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator, having appointed Lucius Papirius
                    Crassus, as master of the horse, to the command of the city, and prohibited
                    Quintus Fabius from acting in any case as magistrate, returned to the camp;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> where his arrival brought neither any
                    great joy to his countrymen, nor any degree of terror to the enemy: for on the
                    day following, either not knowing that the dictator had arrived, or little
                    regarding whether he were present or absent, they approached his camp in order
                    of battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of such importance, however, was
                    that single man, Lucius Papirius, that had the zeal of the soldiers seconded the
                    dispositions of the commander, no doubt was entertained that an end might have
                    been put that day to the war with the Samnites; <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> so judiciously did he draw up his army with respect to situation and
                    reserves, in such a manner did he strengthen them with every advantage of
                    military skill: but the soldiers exerted no vigour; and designedly kept from
                    conquering, in order to injure the reputation of their leader. Of the Sam-
                    nites, however, very many were slain; and great numbers of the Romans wounded.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The experienced commander quickly
                    perceived the circumstance which prevented his success, and that it would be
                    necessary to moderate his temper, and to mingle mildness with austerity.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly, attended by the
                    lieutenants-general, going round to the wounded soldiers, thrusting his head
                    into their tents, and asking them, one by one, how they were in health; then,
                    mentioning them by name, he gave them in charge to the officers, tribunes, and
                    praefects. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This behaviour, popular in itself,
                    he maintained with such dexterity, that by his attention to their recovery he
                    gradually gained their affection; nor did any thing so much contribute towards
                    their recovery as the circumstance of this attention being received with
                    gratitude. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The army being restored to health,
                    he came to an engagement with the enemy; and both himself and the troops, being
                    possessed with full confidence of success, he so entirely defeated and dispersed
                    the <pb n="553" xml:id="p.553"/> Samnites, that that was the last day they met
                    the dictator in the field. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The victorious
                    army, afterwards, directed its march wherever a prospect of booty invited, and
                    traversed the enemies' territories, encountering not a weapon, nor any
                    opposition, either openly or by stratagem. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It
                    added to their alacrity, that the dictator had, by proclamation, given the whole
                    spoil to the soldiers; so that they were animated not only by the public
                    quarrel, but by their private emolument. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Reduced by these losses, the Samnites sued to the dictator for peace, and, after
                    they had engaged to supply each of his soldiers with a suit of clothes
                        <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> and a year's pay, being ordered to
                    apply to the senate, they answered, that they would follow the dictator,
                    committing their cause wholly to his integrity and honour. On this the troops
                    were withdrawn out of Samnium. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator entered the city in triumph; and,
                    though desirous of resigning his office immediately, yet, by order of the
                    senate, he held it until the consuls were elected: these were Caius Sulpicius
                    Longus a second time, and Quintus Aemilius Cerretanus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Samnites, without finishing the treaty of peace, the
                    terms being still in negotiation brought home with them a truce for a year. Nor
                    was even that faithfully observed; so strongly was their inclination for war
                    excited, on hearing that Papirius was gone out of office. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In this consulate of Caius Sulpicius and Quintus Aemilius,
                    (some histories have Aulius,) to the revolt of the Samnites was added a new war
                    with the Apulians. Armies were sent against both. The Samnites fell by lot to
                    Sulpicius, the Apulians to Aemilius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some
                    writers say, that this war was not waged with the Apulians, but that the allied
                    states of that nation were defended against the violence and injustice of the
                    Samnites. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the circumstances of the
                    Samnites, who could with difficulty, at that period, support a war in which
                    themselves were engaged, render it more probable that they did not make war on
                    the Apulians, but that both nations were in arms against the Romans at the same
                    time. However, no memorable event occurred. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The lands of the Apulians and of Samnium were utterly laid waste; but in neither
                    quarter were the enemy to be found. At Rome, an alarm, which happened in the
                    night, suddenly roused the people from their sleep, in such a fright, that the
                    Capitol and citadel, the walls and gates, were all filled with men in arms.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But after they had called all to their <pb
                        n="554" xml:id="p.554"/> posts, and run together in bodies, in every
                    quarter, when day approached, neither the author nor cause of the alarm could be
                    discovered. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This year, in pursuance to the
                    advice of Flavius, the Tusculans were brought to a trial before the people.
                    Marcus Flavius, a tribune of the commons, proposed, that punishment should be
                    inflicted on those of the Tusculans, <quote> by whose advice and assistance the
                        Veliternians and Privernians had made war on the Roman people. </quote> The
                    Tusculans, with their wives and children, came to Rome. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The whole party in mourning habits, like persons under
                    accusation, went round the tribes, throwing themselves at the feet of the
                    citizens. The compassion thus excited operated more effectually towards
                    procuring them pardon, than all their arguments did towards clearing them of
                    guilt. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Every one of the tribes, except the
                    Pollian, negatived the proposition. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    sentence of the Pollian tribe was, that the grown-up males should be beaten and
                    put to death, and their wives and children sold by auction, according to the
                    rules of war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It appears that the resentment
                    which rose against the advisers of so rigorous a measure, was retained in memory
                    by the Tusculans down to the age of our fathers; and that hardly any candidate
                    of the Pollian tribe could, ever since, gain the votes of the Papirian. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following year, in the consulate of
                    Quintus Fabius and Lucius Fulvius, Aulus Cornelius Arvina being made dictator,
                    and Marcus Fabius Ambustus master of the horse, a levy being held with more than
                    usual rigour in consequence of their apprehension of a very serious war in
                    Samnium, (for it was reported that some young men had been hired from their
                    neighbours,) led forth a very strong army against the Samnites. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Although in a hostile country, their camp was pitched in as
                    careless a manner as if the foe were at a great distance; when, suddenly, the
                    legions of the Samnites approached with so much boldness as to advance their
                    rampart close to an out-post of the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Night was now coming on; that prevented their assaulting the works; but they did
                    not conceal their intention of doing so next day, as soon as the light should
                    appear. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The dictator found that there would be
                    a necessity for fighting sooner than he had expected, and lest the situation
                    should be an obstruction to the bravery of the troops, he led away the legions
                    in silence, leaving a great number of fires the better to deceive the enemy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On account of the proximity of the camps,
                        <pb n="555" xml:id="p.555"/> however, he could not escape their observation:
                    their cavalry instantly pursued, and pressed closely on his troops, in such a
                    way as to refrain from attacking them until the day appeared. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Their infantry did not even quit their camp before
                    daylight. As soon as it was dawn, the cavalry venturing to attack the enemy by
                    harassing the Roman rear, and pressing them in places of difficult passage,
                    considerably delayed their march. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Meanwhile
                    their infantry overtook the cavalry; and now the Samnites pursued close with
                    their entire force. The dictator then, finding that he could no longer go
                    forward without great inconvenience, ordered the spot where he stood to be
                    measured out for a camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But it was
                    impossible, while the enemy's horse were spread about on every side, that
                    palisades could be brought, and the work be begun: seeing it, therefore,
                    impracticable, either to march forward or to settle himself there, he drew up
                    his troops for battle, removing the baggage out of the line. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The enemy likewise formed their line opposite to his; fully
                    equal both in spirit and in strength. Their courage was chiefly improved from
                    not knowing that the motive of the Romans' retreat was the incommodiousness of
                    the ground, so that they imagined themselves objects of terror, and supposed
                    that they were pursuing men who fled through fear. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> This kept the balance of the fight equal for a considerable
                    time; though, of late, it had been unusual with the Samnites to stand even the
                    shout of a Roman army. Certain it is, that the contest, on this day, continued
                    so very doubtful from the third hour to the eighth, that neither was the shout
                    repeated, after being raised at the first onset, nor the standards moved either
                    forward or backward; nor any ground lost on either side. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They fought without taking breath or looking behind them,
                    every man in his post, and pushing against their opponents with their shields.
                    The noise continuing equal, and the terror of the fight the same, seemed to
                    denote, that the decision would be effected either by fatigue or by the night.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The men had now exhausted their strength,
                    the sword its power, and the leaders their skill; when, on a sudden, the Samnite
                    cavalry, having learned from a single troop which had advanced beyond the rest,
                    that the baggage of the Romans lay at a distance from their army, without any
                    guard or defence; through eagerness for booty, they attack it: of which the
                    dictator being informed by a hasty messenger, said, <quote> Let them only
                        encumber themselves with <pb n="556" xml:id="p.556"/> spoils. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Afterwards came several, one after another,
                    crying out, that they were plundering and carrying off all the effects of the
                    soldiers: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> he then called to him the master of
                    the horse, and said, <quote> Do you see, Marcus Fabius, that the fight has been
                        forsaken by the enemy's cavalry? They are entangled and encumbered with our
                        baggage. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Attack them whilst scattered
                        about, as is the case of every multitude employed in plundering; you will
                        find few mounted on horseback, few with swords in their hands; and, while
                        they are loading their horses with spoil, and unarmed, put them to the
                        sword, and make it bloody spoil for them. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        I will take care of the legions, and the fight of the infantry: yours be the
                        honour which the horse shall acquire. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The body of cavalry, in the most exact order
                    possible, charging the enemy, who were straggling and embarrassed, filled every
                    place with slaughter: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for amid the packages
                    which they hastily threw down, and which lay in the way of their feet, and of
                    the affrighted horses, as they endeavoured to escape, being now unable either to
                    fight or fly, they are slaughtered. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then
                    Fabius, after he had almost entirely cut off the enemy's horse, led round his
                    squadrons in a small circuit, and attacked the infantry in the rear. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The new shout, raised in that quarter, terrified the
                    Samnites on the one hand; and when, on the other, the dictator saw their troops
                    in the van looking behind them, their battalions in confusion, and their line
                    wavering, he earnestly exhorted and animated his men, calling on the tribunes
                    and chief centurions, by name, to join him in renewing the fight. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Raising the shout anew, they pressed forward, and as
                    they advanced, perceived the enemy more and more confused. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The cavalry now could be seen by those in front, and
                    Cornelius, turning about to the several companies, made them understand, by
                    raising his voice and hands, that he saw the standards and bucklers of his own
                    horsemen. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On hearing which, and at the same
                    time seeing them, they, at once, so far forgot the fatigue which they had
                    endured through almost the whole day, and even their wounds, that they rushed on
                    against the enemy with as much vigour and alacrity as if they were coming fresh
                    out of camp on receiving the signal for battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> The Samnites could no longer sustain the charge of horse and foot together;
                    part of them, enclosed on both sides, were cut off; the rest were scattered and
                    fled different ways. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The infantry slew those
                        <pb n="557" xml:id="p.557"/> who were surrounded and made resistance; and
                    the cavalry made great havoc of the fugitives, among whom fell their general.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This battle crushed, at length, the power
                    of the Samnites so effectually, that, in all their meetings, they said, <quote>
                        it was not at all to be wondered at, if in an impious war, commenced in
                        violation of a treaty, when the gods were, with justice, more incensed
                        against them than men, they succeeded in none of their undertakings.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That war must be expiated and atoned
                        for with a heavy penalty. The only alternative they had, was whether the
                        penalty should be the guilty blood of a few, or the innocent blood of all. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some now ventured to name the authors of the
                    war; one name in particular, by the united voices of all, was mentioned, that of
                    Brutulus Papius; he was a man of power and noble birth, and undoubtedly the
                    violator of the late truce. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The praetors
                    being compelled to take the opinion of the assembly concerning him, a decree was
                    made, <quote> that Brutulus Papius should be delivered into the hands of the
                        Romans; and that, together with him all the spoil taken from the Romans, and
                        the prisoners, should be sent to Rome, and that the restitution demanded by
                        the heralds, in conformity to treaty, should be made as was agreeable to
                        justice and equity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> In pursuance of this determination heralds
                    were sent to Rome, and also the dead body of Brutulus; for, by a voluntary
                    death, he avoided the punishment and ignominy intended for him. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> It was thought proper that his goods also should be
                    delivered up along with the body. But none of all those things were accepted,
                    except the prisoners, and such articles of the spoil as were recognised by the
                    owners. The dictator obtained a triumph by a decree of the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some writers affirm, that this war was
                    conducted by the consuls, and that they triumphed over the Samnites and also,
                    that Fabius advanced into Apulia, and carried off from thence abundance of
                    spoil. But that Aulus Cornelius was dictator that year is an undisputed fact.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Th question then is, whether he was
                    appointed for the purpose of conducting the war, or on occasion of the illness
                    of Lucius Plautius, the praetor; in order that there might be a magistrate to
                    give the signal for the starting of the chariots at the Roman games. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> This latter is asserted of him; and that after
                    performing the business, which in truth reflected no great lustre on his office,
                        <pb n="558" xml:id="p.558"/> he resigned the dictatorship. It is not easy to
                    determine between either the facts or the writers, which of them deserves the
                    preference: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I am inclined to think that
                    history has been much corrupted by means of funeral panegyrics and false
                    inscriptions on statues; each family striving by false representations to
                    appropriate to itself the fame of warlike exploits and public honours.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From this cause, certainly, both the
                    actions of individuals and the public records of events have been confused. Nor
                    is there extant any writer, contemporary with those events, on whose authority
                    we can with certainty rely. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
