<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Gothic War</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date>1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="https://archive.org/details/claudian02clau#page/124/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="poem"/>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa003.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.2.p.125" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="poem" n="praef" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PREFACE</head>
         <p>

After years of sloth my Muse, as if startled from
long slumber, rejoices to sing a Roman song to
Roman ears. Once more the same halls bring the
gathering I longed for, and Apollo's temple echoes
to the voice of a familiar bard. 'Twas here I sang
of the consular fasces and of the winning back of
Libya and here must I sing of the war that overthrew
the Getae.
         </p>
            <p>
But my former success won for me a brazen statue 1
and the Fathers set up my likeness in my honour ;
at the Senate's prayer the Emperor allowed the
claim — bethink thee. Muse, how strict a judgement
thou dost face ! Wit wins less favour when too
soon rewarded, and so great a gift refuses indulgence
for my song. Now that my name is read and my
features are known in the forum my Muse labours
for a sterner critic than before.
            </p>
            <p>
Yet my theme itself brings cheer and, as I begin
to speak, eagerly lightens much of my accustomed
fear. A gracious and more devoted hearing is
secured for me, be it by the war's deserving or be it
by Stilicho's love.
         </p>
            </div1>
<pb id="v.2.p.127"/>
         <div1 type="poem" id="poem.26" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N" n="1">
            <p>
When the intrepid Argo, passing between the
clashing rocks that guarded its entrance, burst
through the portals of the unfurrowed sea making
for Colchis where Aeëtes ruled, it is said that, when
all were panic-stricken by the nearing danger,
Tiphys alone — with heaven's help — kept safe the
almost uninjured bark. 'Twas thanks to him
that the Argo escaped the cliffs threatening ruin
and came out victorious into the open sea, cunningly
eluding the meeting shock of the floating rocks.
Amazed were the proud Symplegades thus subdued
by the hero's skill, and, submitting to the novel
laws of the fixed earth, offer unmoved an easy passage
to all ships since once they have learned defeat.
But if the merit of saving a single vessel from ruin
won, and rightly won, for Tiphys such meed of honour,
what praises shall suffice for thee, Stilicho, who hast
freed so great an empire from destruction ? Poets
may exaggerate the story ; they may boast that
Minerva toiled with her own hands to hew the Argo's
beams, and that she fitted together no senseless
timber from a dumb forest, but felled the augural
grove of Tomarian 1 Jove and with those prophetic
trees quickened its planks to speech. But though
they burden their recital with the story of countless
prodigies to captivate the mind of the unlettered

<pb id="v.2.p.129"/>
young, though they tell of fierce Harpies, of the
dragon whose unsleeping length lay curled in
protecting folds about the golden fleece, of yoked
bulls afire with flickering flames, of a springing
crop of helmets, a field from out whose furrows
grew a Martian race, of seeds of war whose increase
yielded a harvest, too, of war, yet do these fictions
fall short of the truth. Is it a nobler title to fame
to have driven off the greedy Harpies and banished
them from the table of a single man than to have
had the strength to beat back those countless Getic
maws that thirsted for the spoil of Latium ? Am
I to look with more admiration upon those earthborn
warriors struck down in the very furrows from
which they sprang, born and dying in a single day,
than upon the slaughtered ranks of Getae whom
the goddess of war reared on so many spoils and
whose martial life came to grey hairs, passed ever
beneath helmets ?</p>
            <p>
Thou and thou alone, Stilicho, hast dispersed the
darkness that enshrouded our empire and hast
restored its glory ; thanks to thee civilization, all
but vanished, has been freed from the gloomy
prison and can again advance. The old order of
justice now makes distinction between magistracies
which fear had made equal in a common gloom.
Thy right hand has snatched us from impending
death and restored to their homes and lands peoples
whom fate sentenced and thy valour saved. No
longer, herded together like sheep by a scare-crow,
do we watch from the ramparts our fields ablaze
with the enemy's fire, no longer measure the depth
of rivers which we feebly hope will retard our destruction
nor ask the streams and flying clouds to

<pb id="v.2.p.131"/>
keep the promise of their waters or complain that
the sunshine conspires against us with its splendour.</p>
            <p>
Thou, too, Rome, so long vexed with internal
discord, lift up thy hills at last more peacefully in
safety. Arise, honoured mother, be sure that God's
favour is with thee ; banish the lowly timorousness of
age. City that art coeval with the world, inexorable
Lachesis shall not exercise against thee her rights
of destruction until Nature has so changed the
immutable laws of the universe that Tanais turn
his course and water Egypt, Nile flow into Lake
Maeotis, Eurus blow from the west. Zephyr from
India, and the south wind rage in tempest o'er the
summit of Caucasus, while that of the north binds
the deserts of Africa with its frost.</p>
            <p>
Thus far came the fatal hordes ; now their
threats, whereof so many omens warned us, have
vanished away. Heaven's self was not always
at peace : they tell how even Jove trembled (if
one may dare to say so) when Typhoeus attacked
him, arming his hundred hands with a hundred
mountains and touching the astonished constellation
of the Bear with his towering snaky coils. What
wonder if trouble harasses mortal realms when
cruel Aloeus' two sons cast Mars in chains and
attempted to build that forbidden road to the stars
so that the universe almost ceased to move, what
time the three rocks 1 were uprooted in the war
of heaven ? But their blind fury was of no effect ;
wicked hopes never exult for long. Aloeus' children
never reached man's estate ; Otus, attempting
to uproot Pelion, was stricken down by Phoebus,
and Ephialtes as he died wearily let Ossa fall athwart
his side.</p>
<pb id="v.2.p.133"/>
            <p>
Lift up thy head, Rome, and behold thine enemy ;
see how, leading back in dishonour a shattered host,
he is cast forth from Italy. How different is he from
what he was when he sware that everything should
yield to his onset and took an oath by Danube whom
he and his fathers worshipped that he would never
unbuckle his breastplate until he had marched in
triumph through the Forum. How strange are the
changes Fate brings about ! He who destined the
women of Rome as victims of his lust has seen his
own wives and children led away captive ; he who in
imagination had drained the countless wealth of our
city became himself his victor's easy prey ; he who
once sought to corrupt the loyalty of our troops has
been deserted by his own people and has returned
to his country beggared of men and arms.
            </p>
            <p>
Then too if, laying hatred aside, thou shouldest
weigh the cause that won them pardon from their
doom, surely to spare a fallen foe is itself a triumph
and to see him on his knees punishment enough.
What vengeance so satisfying as when terror makes
pride stoop, and want bows down him who before
bore spoils ? But our clemency was in part due
to another cause, for we thought of thee, O Rome.
Concern for thee constrained us to offer a way
of escape to the beleaguered foe lest, with the
fear of death before their eyes, their rage should
glow the more terrible for being confined. An
enemy before thy very walls would have been too
heavy a price to pay for the destruction of the race
and name of the Getae. May Jove from on high
forbid that the barbarian should outrage even with
a glance Numa's shrine or Romulus' temple, or
discover aught of the secrets of our empire.
            </p>
<pb id="v.2.p.135"/>
            <p>
And yet — if duly I recall ancient conflicts — then
also when, fair liberty lending vigour, the senate
was everywhere successful with native troops, they
sought trophies from such wars as were waged far
away across the sea where our soldiers could exercise
their courage without danger to their homes ;
chariots and fettered kings were accounted but the
shows that overflowing fortune gave. But whenever
a dread storm burst upon Italy or hung threateningly
over her head their thought was not how
to give vent to profitless fury but how best at
such a crisis to secure the safety of the state. The
leader of their choice was not he who hazarded all
on one rash throw but one who gave careful thought
to each eventuality, were it fortunate or the reverse,
one who could bear adversity with fortitude and
success with moderation, and by slackening or
tightening the reins of government knew how to
make use of victory and to temporize after a setback.
The physician's skill deals more carefully with
grave diseases and ulcers that are near the heart :
here he is more sparing of the knife for fear lest
the blade, driven too deep, should slip and sever
beyond healing some vital organ.
            </p>
            <p>
Proud assuredly is the strain in which bards of
old sing of Curius who drove Pyrrhus, son of Aeacus,
from the shores of Italy ; 1 not more resplendent
were the triumphs of Paulus and of Marius who
dragged captive kings behind their white-horsed
chariots. The expulsion of Pyrrhus is more praised
than the capture of Jugurtha ; and although Curius
drove out a prince whose spirit had already been
broken by two reverses, at the hands of Decius and
of the blameless Fabricius whom neither bribes
<pb id="v.2.p.137"/>
nor arms could overcome, yet the whole glory of
that expulsion is given to him. But how much
greater the task we see fulfilled by Stilicho alone !
He has conquered not Chaones or Molossi, Epirot
tribes, nor yet the armies of Dodona that idly
boast their prophetic grove, but a mighty people
whose home lies in those snowy regions beneath the
icy constellation of the Bear.</p>
            <p>
Fabius was the first to stay by his slow struggles
Hannibal's lightning rush ; then Marcellus, meeting
him in the open field, taught him defeat, but it was
the valour of Scipio that drove him from the shores
of Italy. In the case of our latest foe Stilicho
succeeded in combining in himself the diverse skill
of all these three ; he broke their frenzy by delaying,
vanquished them in battle and drove the vanquished
host from Italy.</p>
            <p>
And all this in so short a time. Full five years did
Italy mourn beneath the scattered fires of Pyrrhus,
for well-nigh eighteen years did the African steeds
of the Carthaginians tread down and devastate our
harvests, and it was a second generation, born after
the outbreak of the war, that, exacting a tardy
vengeance for the first, with difficulty drove an aged
Hannibal back to his own country. Stilicho acted
more quickly : he saw to it that the winter of our
distress should last but one winter 1 but that spring
in its earliest months should bring back fair weather
alike to heaven and to fatherland.
            </p>
            <p>
Why should I make mention of the wars waged
all those weary years against Hannibal and Pyrrhus
when that vile gladiator Spartacus, ravaging all the
countryside with fire and sword, oft engaged the
consuls in open war and, driving out its feeble masters
<pb id="v.2.p.139"/>
from the Roman camp, put to rout the unwarlike
eagles defeated with shameful carnage by a band
of slaves ? We, unused to war's alarms, an age
enervated with luxury, grumble and give up in
despair if a ploughing ox is looted or our harvest
so much as touched. It was no slaves' prison that
loosed on us the Getic hordes ; these were not a crowd
of rebellious gladiators. Thrace, Haemus and Moesia
can tell you what manner of foe Stilicho expelled.</p>
            <p>
Thrice ten times has chill winter cast her snowy
mantle over leafless Haemus ; as oft has spring, when
those snows were melted, renewed the mountain's
verdant cloak since the Getic race, forgetful of its
native stars and once having crossed the Danube,
set destructive foot on Thracian soil. Whether fate
led them or the heavy anger of the gods planning
disaster upon disaster, from that day, whithersoever
the Furies have driven those errant bands, they
have poured pell-mell over remote lands, over every
obstacle, like a storm of hail or a pestilence. No
streams or rocks availed to defend their country.
Neither Rhodope nor huge Athos nor Hebrus could
save Thrace ; the Bessi cursed the Strymon crossed
with scornful ease and the Haliacmon that flowed
swiftly and to no purpose. The Macedonians in
amaze saw Olympus, too high even for clouds,
trodden by them as it had been a plain. Thessaly
bewails the uselessness of Tempe and conquered
Oeta's ridges made a mock. Sperchius and Enipeus,
loved of maidens, served to wash the barbarians'
hair. The barrier of Pindus could not save the
Dryopes nor cloud-capped Leucates the coasts of
Actium. Thermopylae itself that had once more
boldly withstood the Persians yielded a passage
<pb id="v.2.p.141"/>
at the first onset. Sciron's cliffs protected by the
waves, the wall that joins sea to sea across the
Isthmus of Corinth, the narrow pass of Lechaeum,
all lay open to their approach. Thou, Erymanthus,
couldst not protect the people of Arcadia with thy
leafy ridges and thou, Amyclae, didst tremble to see
the enemy's cavalry on the heights of Taygetus.</p>
            <p>
At last, however, the Alps avenged on the Getae
the disgrace of all mountains else and victorious
Eridanus that of all other rivers. The event has
proved that deep hidden are the ways of destiny.
Who would have believed that, once a passage had
been forced over the Alps, so much as the shadow
of Italy's name would survive ? Did not the awful
report of Rome's fall cross the sea and spread beyond
Gaul and over the Pyrenees ? Did not Rumour, her
sable wing sped on with panic, sweeping all before
lier in her flight, affright Ocean from Britain's coast to
Gades' city and far away from our world make distant
Thule tremble with the unaccustomed echoes of war ? </p>
            <p>
And shall we fling to the South-wind's blasts all
the terrors we endured, lest mid feasting sadness
trouble our ears ? Or rather does such memory
delight and does precursive pain ever changefully
heighten unexpected joy ? Even as to sailors
storm-tossed at the Pleiads' setting the rudeness
of the sea commends the harbour's calm, so to me
does Stilicho appear greater when I compare happiness
with hazard and all those troubles come again
before my mind.</p>
            <p>
Did not our steel-girt walls seem to fall at the
enemy's attack, feeble as the towers that crowned
them, and our doors of iron to open of their own
accord to give him entry ? It seemed as though
            
<pb id="v.2.p.143"/>
no rampart nor palisade were stout enough to
withstand his cavalry's wind-swift onset. Even now
they 1 make ready to go aboard their ships, to dwell
in Sardinia's creeks and Corsica's rocky, inhospitable
coast, and to guard their lives behind the foaming
main. Sicily herself, mistrusting the narrow strait,
would fain retreat, did but Nature permit, and
open a wider passage for the Ionian waves by
withdrawing Pelorus. The rich, setting no store
by their fretted golden ceilings, would rather have
lived in greater security in an Aeolian cave. Soon,
too, wealth was considered a burden, and greed of
gain was curbed at last by reason of anxieties more
overwhelming. Then — for that fear is by nature
a babbler and allows all sorts of tales to be invented
and believed — dreams, portents, and omens of ill
were discussed on all sides. What, men asked,
did that flight of birds portend, what message
would heaven fain deliver to mortals by the thunderbolt,
what did those prophetic books demand that
guard the destiny of Home ? Constant eclipses
of the moon alarmed us and night after night
throughout the cities of Italy sounded wailings
and the beating of brazen gongs to scare the shadow
from off her darkened face. Men would not believe
that the moon had been defrauded of her brother
the sun, forbidden to give light by the interposition
of the earth ; they thought that Thessalian witches,
accompanying the barbarian armies, were darkening
her rays with their country's magic spells. Then
with these new portents their troubled minds link
the signs of the past year and any omens that perchance
peaceful days had neglected— showers of
stones, bees swarming in strange places, furious
<pb id="v.2.p.145"/>
fires destroying houses from no known cause, a
comet — ne'er seen in heaven without disaster — which
first rose where Phoebus Ufts his rosy morning
beam and old Cepheus shines together with starry
Cassiopeia, his spouse ; then it withdrew little by
little to the constellation of Lycaon's daughter 1
and with its errant tail dimmed the stars of the
Getic Wain until at last its dying fires grew feeble
and vanished.</p>
            <p>
But what terrified men's minds still more was the
portent of the two slaughtered wolves. Ay, before
the Emperor's face as he practised his cavalry upon
the plain two wolves savagely attacked his escort.
Slain by darts they disclosed a horrid portent and
a wondrous sign of what was to be. In each
animal, on its being cut open, was found a human
hand, in the stomach of one a left hand, in that of
the other a right was discovered, both still twitching,
the fingers stretched out and suffused with living
blood. Wouldest thou search out the truth, the
beast as messenger of Mars foretold that the foe
would fall before the emperor's eyes. As the
hands were found to be living when the stomachs
were cut open, so, when the Alps had been broken
through, the might of Rome was to be discovered
unimpaired. But fear, ever a poor interpreter,
read disaster in the portent ; severed hands, 'twas
said, and nursing wolf threatened destruction
on Rome and her empire. Then they reckoned
up the years and, cutting off the flight of the
twelfth vulture, tried to shorten the centuries of
Rome's existence by hastening the end. 2</p>
            <p>
'Twas Stilicho alone who by his courage assured
despairing Rome the promise of a better fate ; at
<pb id="v.2.p.147"/>
this crisis he showed himself by his courage at once
general and seer. <q direct="unspecified"> A little patience,</q> said he ;
<q direct="unspecified">
away with womanly repinings : let us bear with
fortitude whatever fate lays upon us. What good
do the sailors' cries do to the storm-driven vessel ?
Neither waves nor winds will abate their fury for
coward tears or useless prayer. Now for the general
safety it befits us to use every effort, to struggle
with all our strength — to attend to the sails, work
the pumps, manage the various ropes, and obey
every order of the skilful captain. Because the
Getae have broken through, seizing by treachery
the hour for striking home, what time Raetia claimed
our attention and our regiments were busied with
another war — not for that is all hope lost. Marvel
indeed I might, if by some new guile, some discovered
 path, the barbarian ignorantly marched over
the unexplored Alps ; now, however, the successive
defeats of the two tyrants 1 have made the road
notorious, nor has the foeman missed the wellknown
track that was built for him by our civil strife.
They have come a well-known way and Roman
discord has opened the approach to barbaric war.</q></p>

<p><q direct="unspecified">Past generations have known a like fate. Full
often, we know, has Italy been attacked — but never
without the enemy's paying dear. With their own
blood did our country extinguish the fires lit by the
Senones and, once the victim of a German invasion,
she soon saw the squalid necks of Teutons and Cimbri
loaded with the chains of captivity. Of little value
is that glory whose worth has not been augmented
by previous hardship ; 'tis great dangers that beget
great triumphs.</q>
</p>
            <p><q direct="unspecified">Do you meditate shameful flight and fix your
<pb id="v.2.p.149"/>
eyes on Gaul ? Would you leave Latium and
establish on the banks of the Saône a camp of
refugees ? Is Rome to be ceded to Arctic tribes,
our empire to settle on the Rhone, and shall the trunk
survive the head ? If the thought of your children
has any weight with you, remember that I too
am not unaffected by similar feelings of nature ;
my heart is not so hard that I do not nor will not
recognize the sacred ties that bind son to father-
in-law, wife to husband and children to sire. But
never, forgetting honour, shall cowardly affection
seek refuge in ignominious flight. Nor do I give
you bold advice, more careful for myself alone ;
here is my family, my wife, a son-in-law whom I
love more than life itself ; not one of my relations
is beyond the reach of this tempest. O land of
Italy, know that my heart is set on bearing with
thee whatsoever ills thou art called on to bear.
Romans, hold your walls but for a short while till
I return, bringing back to the sound of trumpets
the flower of your host.</q></p>

         <p>
With these words he instilled courage into the
fearful hearts of the citizens and checked any
inclination towards flight in the Court. The dark
shadow fled and Italy dared raise her head once
more seeing her emperor ready to share her perils,
and stood her ground with such a hostage for
fortune. Where Larius clothes his banks with
shady olive-trees and with his fresh water imitates
the sea's salt waves, Stilicho crossed the lake
with all speed in a small boat. Next he ascended
those mountains, inaccessible in winter, with no
thought for the season or the weather. Even
so a lion, leaving his starving cubs within the
<pb id="v.2.p.151"/>
cave, issues forth hunger-maddened some winter
night and with silent tread goes out across the deep
snow with murder in his heart, his mane frozen
about his shoulders, and icicles clinging to his tawnycoat ;
nought recks he of death nor cares for snow nor
frost if only he can procure food for his little ones.</p>
            <p>
Near to the Hercynian forest the uplands of
Raetia stretch out towards the north, Raetia, proud
parent of Danube and Rhine, twain rivers that she
sets to guard the empire of Rome. Small are their
streams at first, but soon they grow in depth and
like kings compel the lesser waters to pass with
tributary wave beneath their name. The Cimbric
ocean receives Rhine's flood outpoured through his
two mouths ; the Thracian wave swallows that of
Ister flowing out through five channels. Both rivers
are navigable though both bear at times the marks of
chariot-wheels upon their frozen surface ; stout allies
both of the north wind and the god of war. But on
the side where Raetia marches with Italy precipitous
mountains touch the sky, scarce even in summer
offering an awful path. Many a man has there been
frozen to death as though he had looked on the
Gorgon's head ; many have been engulfed beneath
vast masses of snow, and often are carts and the
oxen that draw them plunged into the white depths
of the crevasse. Sometimes the mountain plunges
downwards in an avalanche of ice, loosening neath a
warmer sky foundations that trust vainly in the
precipitous slope.</p>
            <p>
Such was the country over which Stilicho passed
in mid winter. No wine was there ; Ceres' gifts
were sparing ; 'twas enough to snatch a hurried meal,
eaten sword in hand, while, burdened with rain-
<pb id="v.2.p.153"/>
drenched cloak, he urged on his half-frozen steed.
No soft bed received his weary limbs. If the darkness
forced him to halt in his advance he would either
enter some dreadful beast's den or sleep in some
shepherd's hut, his head pillowed upon his shield.
The shepherd stands pale at the sight of his stately
guest, and ignorant of his name the rustic mother
points out to her squalid infant the glory of his face.
It was those hard couches beneath the rough pines,
those nights amid the snow, all that care and anxious
toil, that won this peace for the world, this tranquillity
it had despaired of for the empire. From out those
Alpine huts, Rome, came thy salvation.</p>
            <p>
Now had the peoples broken their treaties and,
encouraged by the news of Latium's trouble, had
seized upon the glades of Vindelicia and the fields of
Noricum. Like slaves whom news of their master's
death lures into luxury with an idle tale, if mid the
debauch and while wild licence riots with wine and
dance some unexpected chance bring back their
lord, then they stand panic-stricken and, abhorring
liberty, servile terror shakes their guilty souls ; so all
the rebels were struck with terror at the sight of
the general and in one man the Emperor, Latium
and all Rome blazed before their eyes. Joy sat not
upon his countenance nor excess of gloom nor yet
dejection by reason of Rome's reverses but nobility
and indignation mixed, such as filled Hercules at
Eurystheus' inhuman orders, or such as dims the
face of heaven when at Jove's frown the troubled
sky is gathered into a murky cloud.
            </p>
            <p>
<q direct="unspecified"> Put ye such faith,</q> he cried, <q direct="unspecified"> in Getic arms ?
Is it they that swell your hearts with empty pride ?
Fate has not brought Rome's name so low that she
<pb id="v.2.p.155"/>
cannot punish your rebellion with but a handful of
her forces. Not to delay you with foreign tales,
hear this example from your deeds of old. When
warlike Hannibal was spreading destruction throughout
the cities of Italy, and Cannae had doubled
Trebia's cruel losses, a vain hope drove Philip of
Macedon to turn his feeble sword against a people
which, as he thought, was in difficulties. The
monstrous insult roused the Roman Fathers, although
more pressing dangers were crowding upon them,
and they took it ill that, while two great cities
were disputing the mastery of the world, a lesser
race should be insolent. They determine upon
instant vengeance and command Laevinus, even
while he conducts the war with Carthage, to do
battle also with the king of Macedonia. The consul
obeyed his orders, and Philip, intruding his feeble
arms between mighty nations, was routed by a
passing band and learned that it does not do to tempt
the anger of powerful peoples even when they are
in distress.</q></p>
            <p>
With this warning Stilicho alike checked the
threatened war and won new allies for war, enrolling
them at their entreaty and setting such number to
their forces as should best suit — neither a burden
to Italy nor a terror to its lord.
            </p>
            <p>
Then, indeed, at the news of his return, the legions,
such love they bore their general, hastened together
from every side, and at the sight of Stilicho their
courage revived and they broke out into sobbings
and tears of joy. So when a herd of cattle has been
scattered throughout some vast forest by the storm's
violence the beasts eagerly make for the sound
of the ox-herd's well-known song or whistle and
<pb id="v.2.p.157"/>
the pasture of their native vale, guiding their
steps in answer to his voice and glad faithfully to
reply with lowing, while, wherever his tones fall
upon their ear, horns show themselves here and
there through the dark foliage. First hasten up
the neighbouring troops, their loyalty attested by
their defence of Raetia and their mass of spoil
from Vindelicia ; next the legion that had been
left to guard Britain, 1 the legion that kept the
fierce Scots in check, whose men had scanned the
strange devices tattooed on the faces of the dying
Picts. Even the legions that faced the flaxenhaired
Sygambri, and those who held the Chatti
and wild Cherusci in subjection hither turned their
threatening arms, leaving the Rhine, whose garrison
they had formed, defended by but one thing — the
fear of Rome. Will any posterity credit the tale ?
Germany, once the home of peoples so proud and
fierce that former emperors could scarce keep them
in check with the whole weight of their armies,
now offers herself so willing a follower of Stilicho's
guiding hand that she neither attempts an invasion
of the territory exposed to her attack by the removal
of its frontier troops nor crosses the stream, too
timid to approach an undefended bank.</p>
            <p>
Greater art thou, Stilicho, than all ; thine only
rival is Camillus, whose arms broke the rash
power of Brennus as thine have broken that of
Alaric. At a time of dire peril ye both gave the
aid of gods ; but he too late avenged a captured
Rome, thou one still safe. What a reversal of
fortune did thy return bring about ! A new vigour
returned to every part of our empire alike, and the
glow of health came back to our suflfering cities. A
<pb id="v.2.p.159"/>
woman, so the story goes, who died to save the life
of a loved husband, was recalled to the upper world
by the might of Hercules. Diana with the help of
Circe's magic herbs restored to life Hippolytus whom
the scorned passion of a stepmother had caused to
be torn in pieces. Crete, if the fable be true, saw
Glaucus, son of Minos, issue living from the tomb ;
his body was discovered by the cries of birds to
Polyidus, the aged seer, who restored him to life
by means of simples ; strange indeed was the
ruling of fate which apportioned sweet honey as
the cause of his death and a hideous serpent as the
restorer of his life.1 But thy return, Stilicho, recalled
not one body from the shades but countless peoples
sunk in a common death, and snatched whole towns
from the jaws of Hell.</p>
            <p>
That very day Rome rang with the report (though
none ever knew its author) that the hero had arrived,
and the citizens, assured of Stilicho's protection,
applauded this augury of certain victory. Who
could tell of the Emperor's joy, who of the courtiers'
eager greetings ? From the lofty battlements we
sight a distant cloud of dust and know not whether its
obscurity conceals friend or foe. Suspense keeps us
all in silence. Then suddenly from that dusty cloud
emerged the helm of Stilicho, glittering like a star,
and we recognized his gleaming white hair. Up
rose the happy shout from the walls : <q direct="unspecified"> 'Tis he.</q>
Safe at last the crowd surges out through the gates
to meet and greet the army's return. Gone for
ever are our wretched impressed levies ; no longer
<pb id="v.2.p.161"/>
does the reaper, laying aside his sickle, try to
hurl the impotent javelin, nor Ceres lay aside her
harrow and, to the amusement of Bellona, essay
the buckler. Stilled are the noisy wrangles of untried
leaders ; here is Rome's true strength, her true
leader, Mars in human form.</p>
            <p>
The more happy hopes grew in our hearts the
more they deserted the Getae, who, touching the
stars with their heads, after crossing the Alps
accounted all their own and deemed nothing left
to do. But when they saw all our glorious youth,
all the quickly levied infantry, all the squadrons of
horse, a countryside protected by so many rivers
and fortresses, and themselves caught in a snare,
a trouble they dared not voice seized their hearts
and a regret that they had invaded Italy with too
forward eagerness ; and Rome they hoped within
their grasp seemed far away. Weariness of their
mighty undertaking steals over them. Yet Alaric's
face conceals his fear ; he bids to the council of war
those whose age or prowess had gained them the
dignity of leadership. There sat the senate of
long-haired, skin-clad Getic leaders. Many a scar
received in battle adorned their faces, spears guide
their tottering steps and, instead of a staff, old age,
refusing to disarm, supports itself on their tall shafts.
Then arose one older than the rest, trusted for his
counsel and advice, who, fixing his gaze upon the
ground, shaking his hoary locks and leaning on his
ivory hilt, thus spake ; <q direct="unspecified"> If I miscount not the
years this is well-nigh the thirtieth winter since we
swam across the swift Ister. All that time we have
escaped defeat at the hands of Rome. Yet never,
Alaric, has Mars brought your fortunes to such
<pb id="v.2.p.163"/>
straits. Take the advice of an old man who has been
through countless fights, one who like a father was
wont to give thee in thine earliest youth little quivers
to sling across thy back and to fit short bows to thy
young shoulders. Often did I urge in vain that
thou should'st observe the treaty and remain safe
at home in Emathia. But if the fire of hot youth
hurried thee into war, now at least, I beg thee,
make good thine escape from out this net if thou
hast any love left for thy people. The enemy's
forces are far away ; thou hast the chance ; flee
headlong from Italy's lands lest, in thy desire
for fresh spoils, thou lose even what thou hast got
and like a wolf pay the penalty of former depredations
to the shepherd by being killed within the
sheepfold. Why dost thou have ever on thy lips
the richness of Tuscan vineyards and some Rome
or other with its Tiber ? If our parents speak
sooth, never has any who has assailed that city in
mad war returned to boast that he has done her
violence. The gods desert not their own home ;
thunderbolts, they tell, are hurled from afar upon
her foes and unearthly fires flash before her walls,
whether 'tis heaven or Rome that thunders. If
thou fearest not the gods beware the might of
Stilicho ; fortune is ever on his side against assaulting
enemies. Thou thyself knowest how high with
bones he piled our funeral pyres in Arcadia, and
with what vast outpourings of our blood he made
the rivers of Greece run warm ; and thou hadst
been killed had not treason in the guise of law
and the goodwill of the Emperor of the East protected
thee.</q></p>
            <p>
While the elder spake thus Alaric, eyeing him
<pb id="v.2.p.165"/>
askance with fiery brow, brooked his words no
longer, but his enkindled pride broke forth in furious
speech : <q direct="unspecified"> Did not witless age that has deprived
thee of thy senses grant thee indulgence never,
on my life, should Danube listen unavenged to
such coward insults. Am I who have routed so
many emperors (Hebrus' river is my witness) to
endure flight at thine advice — I whom all nature
obeys ? Have I not seen the mountains levelled at
my feet, the rivers dried up ? Never may my
country's gods, the spirits of my forefathers, allow
that I retrace my footsteps on a backward path.
This land shall be mine whether I hold it in fee
as conqueror or in death as conquered. I have
overrun so many peoples and cities, I have burst
through the Alps and drunk of the waters of
Eridanus from out a victor's helmet. What is
left me but Rome ? My nation was strong even
when it had no allied arms to help it. But now
that I hold sway over Illyria, now that its people
has made me their leader, I have forced the
Thracians to forge me spears, swords, helmets with
the sweat of their brows, and Roman towns (whose
rightful overlord I now am) to contribute iron for
mine own uses. Thus is fate on my side. Rome,
whose territories I have laid waste year by year, has
become my slave. 'Tis she has supplied me with
arms ; her own metal has glowed in the furnace,
artfully molten and fashioned for her own undoing
by reluctant smiths. The gods, too, urge me on.
Not for me are dreams or birds but the clear cry
uttered openly from the sacred grove : ' Away with
delay, Alaric ; boldly cross the Italian Alps this
year and thou shalt reach the city.' Thus far the
<pb id="v.2.p.167"/>
path is mine. Who so cowardly as to dally after
this encouragement or to hesitate to obey the call
of Heaven?</q></p>
            <p>
So he spake and made ready his army to take the
road, exhorting them to combat. Prophecy serves
to augment his vain pride. Ah ! for the grudging
oracles ever dumb with mystic utterance ; 'tis the
event alone that (too late) discloses the true meaning
which the seers themselves could not read.
Alaric reached the farthest confines of Liguria
where flows a river with the strange name of the
City.^ There he suffered defeat and even then
scarcely realized (though that defeat made it clear)
that fate had tricked him with an ambiguous word.</p>
            <p>
Stilicho, too, fails not : at full speed he advanced
his army clamorous for battle and spurs their march
with these words : <q direct="unspecified"> Friends of Rome, the time
has now come for you to exact vengeance for outraged
Italy. Wipe out the disgrace which the
investment of your emperor by his foes has brought
upon you, and let your swords end the shame which
the defeat on the Timavus 2 and the enemy's passage
of the Alps has caused to Rome. This is the foe
whom ye so often put to flight on the plains of
Greece, whom not their own valour but a world
torn by civil strife has kept safe thus far, as they
treacherously mock at treaties and traffic in perjury
now with the West, now the East. Reflect that
all the fierce peoples of Britain and the tribes who
dwell on Danube's and Rhine's banks are watching
and stand ready. Win a victory now and so be
conquerors in many an unfought war. Restore
Rome to her former glory ; the frame of empire
is tottering ; let your shoulders support it. A
<pb id="v.2.p.169"/>
single battle and all will be well ; but one victory
and the world's peace will be assured. We fight
not on the slopes of Thracian Haemus nor await our
foe where Maenalus throws his shadow across the
banks of Alpheus. We defend not Tegea nor Argos.
No : as ye see, the scene of war is the very centre
and heart of Italy. Protect Father Tiber with your
shields.</q> Thus spake Stilicho to foot and horse.</p>
            <p>
Orders were at the same time sent to the auxiliary
troops. The Alans, now subject to Roman rule,
followed our trumpets' call, taught by their chief
to lay down their lives in the cause of Italy. Small
was his stature but great his soul and fierce anger
blazed from his eyes. Covered with wounds was he
and with a visage rendered the more glorious and
the more proud by reason of the scar some spearthrust
had left. At Stilicho's command he hastened
up with his cavalry, fated to bite the soil of Italy
in death. Happy warrior, worthy of the Elysian
fields and of my meed of song, who wast eager even
at the cost of life to cleanse thy loyalty from stain !
The sword that spilled thy generous blood, it was
thy judge, acquitting thee of that most unjust
charge of treachery. Thrown into confusion by
the hero's death his horsemen turned rein and, its
flank thus exposed, the whole host would have reeled
had not Stilicho quickly gathered a legion and
hastening to the spot rallied the cavalry to the fight
with infantry support.</p>
            <p>
What poet, were he inspired by the Muses or
even by Apollo himself, could relate the blessings
showered that day by Mars upon the city whose
founder he himself was ? Never was the sword of
Rome plunged so deep in the Scythians' throat ;
<pb id="v.2.p.171"/>
never was Tanais' pride abased by such a crushing
defeat nor the horns of Ister so broken. Thirsting
to drink the enemy's hateful blood our soldiers
passed by rich and varied raiment, carts laden
with gold, heaps of silver, and, eager for the foe's
destruction, spurned his wealth. They held blood
of more account than gold ; none of them would
stoop to pick up the fortune that lay at their feet
but drew their swords and sated their wild fury.
The crafty foe threw in the path of our advancing
troops the robes of scarlet dye, and other spoils
reft from Valens 1 who perished in the flames,
heavy mixing -bowls looted from unhappy Argos
and lifelike statues rescued from burning Corinth
— all in vain, for this ill-omened booty, so far from
delaying our men, reminded them of past reverses
and so the more inflamed their righteous indignation.</p>
            <p>
The crowd of prisoners is loosed from its fetters
and all the peoples of different tongue whom the
Getae had led away captive. Freed at last by the
slaughter of their captors they plant thankful
kisses on the bloody hands of their deliverers and
hasten back to their long-lost homes and their dear
children. At each his household looks in wonder
as they tell the story of their woes and then recount
the marvel of welcome victory.</p>
            <p>
What must then have been thy despair, Alaric,
when ruin overwhelmed thy wealth and all that
gear that years of robbing had won thee, when
there struck thine ear the cries of that wife of
thine who, too confident in her long unconquered
husband, demanded in her madness the jewelled
necklaces of Italian matrons for her proud neck
and Roman girls for her tire-women ! The fair girls
<pb id="v.2.p.173"/>
of Greece from Corinth and Sparta were, forsooth,
not good enough now for so great a lady. But
Nemesis, the goddess worshipped at Rhamnus, she
whose pleasure it is to check unbridled desire, was
wroth and turned her wheel ; harsh poverty overwhelms
the vanquished, and in one day Rome's
arm requites all that we have lost in thirty years.</p>
            <p>
Thy glory, Pollentia, shall live for ever ; worthy is
thy name to be celebrated by my song, a fit theme
for rejoicing and for triumph. Fate pre-ordained
thee to be the scene of our victory and the burialplace
of the barbarians. Full often have thy fields
and plains seen ample vengeance exacted for aggression
against the descendants of Romulus. 'Twas
there, in that same countryside, that the Cimbric
hordes, bearing down upon Rome from Ocean's
farthest shore and crossing the Alps by another
pass, suffered their final defeat. The coming
generation should mingle the bones of these two
races and engrave with this one inscription the
monument which records our double victory : <q direct="unspecified"> Here
beneath the soil of Italy lie the bodies of brave
Cimbri and Getae : their death they owed to our
famous generals Marius and Stilicho. Learn, presumptuous
peoples, not to despise Rome.</q></p>

            </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>