<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Panegyric on the Sixth Consulship of Honorius</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date>1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="https://archive.org/details/claudian02clau#page/70/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="poem"/>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa012.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.2.p.71" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 n="praef" type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PREFACE</head>
         <p>


All things that with waking sense desire ponders
kindly repose brings back to the slumbering mind.
The huntsman stretches his weary limbs upon the
couch, yet his mind ever returns to the woods where
his quarry lurks. The judge dreams of law-suits, the
charioteer of his chariot the nightly steeds of which
he guides past a shadowy turning-point. The lover
repeats love's mysteries, the merchant makes exchange
of goods, the miser still watchfully grasps
at elusive riches, and to thirsty sufferers all-pervading
sleep offers from a cooling spring idly alluring
draughts.
I am a lover of the Muses and in the silent night
I too am haunted by that my accustomed task.
For meseemed I stood upon the very summit of the
starry sky and laid my songs at Jove's feet, and,
in the flattery of sleep, the gods and all the sacred
band gathered about Jove's throne gave applause to
my words. I sang of Enceladus and conquered
Typhoeus, the first a prisoner beneath Inarime, the
second oppressed by the weight of Etna. How
<pb id="v.2.p.73"/>
joyous was that Jove whom, after the war with the
giants, heaven welcomed, enriched with the spoils
from Phlegra's field !
My dream has come true ; 'twas no vain imagining ;
nor did the false ivory gate ^ send forth an unaccomplished
dream. Behold our lord, behold earth
towering to heaven's height ! Here before me are
gods such as I then saw, gods worthy of all reverence.
Nought greater could dreams have fancied ; this
noble assembly offers the poet an audience like to
that of heaven.
<pb id="v.2.p.75"/>
         </p>
            </div1>
         <pb id="v.2.p.3" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="poem" n="1" id="poem.28" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>THE PANEGYRIC</head>
         <p>

If our ancestors vowed temples to <q direct="unspecified">Homebringing
Fortune</q> in honour of the return of their
generals, never would this goddess more worthily
claim for her services a noble temple than when their
proper majesty is restored alike to the consulship and
to Rome. The annual election in the Campus Martius
is not the accustomed farce, nor see we a consul of
other race than his electors nor a foreigner claiming
pretended rights. 1 The palace now our own wears a
native dress, and while Quirinus associates the people
with the armies of Italy, Mars gives back to his
own Field its imperial suffrage. What will the year
be like for mortals that is ushered in by omens on the
Palatine Hill so favourable to true sons of Rome and
inaugurated on the banks of the Tiber ? 'Tis true
that years marked by thy name have ever been rich
in omens of success and that victory has always
accompanied thy consulship, yet by its wondrous
dawn is this year set before all years, blessed by
the twofold deity of Rome and of her Emperor.
For as Babylonian lore gives assurance that propitious
stars do then promise the best fortune to
mortals when they hold the summit of the sky and
their course is at the zenith, not dimming their
<pb id="v.2.p.77"/>
light by a low position in the sky ; so the Standardbearer
of the Latin palace ^ at his zenith gives hope
of a brighter future for Italy in placing the star of
our empire in its true position. Omens that have
their origin in Rome's victorious soil are the more
sure of fulfilment.
When fair Apollo leaves Delphi's shrine and visits
the altars of the north, Castalia's waters differ in no
wise from those of any common stream, nor the
laurel from any common tree ; sad and silent is the
cave and the shrine without a worshipper. But if
Phoebus is there, Phoebus returned from Scythian
climes to his Delphic tripod, guiding thither his
yoked griffins, the woods, the caves regain their voice,
the streams their life ; the sacred ripple revisits the
face of the waters, a clearer echo resounds from the
shrine and the now inspired rocks tremble to the
voice of prophecy. Now the Palatine Mount is
exalted with honour and rejoices in the return of its
native deity ; far and wide among the suppliant
peoples it spreads oracles surer even than those of
Delphi and bids its laurels grow green again to
deck the standards of Rome.
Of a truth no other city could fitly be the home
of the world's rulers; on this hill is majesty most
herself, and knows the height of her supreme sway ;
the palace, raising its head above the forum that
lies at its feet, sees around it so many temples and
is surrounded by so many protecting deities. See
below the Thunderer's temple the Giants suspended
from the Tarpeian rock, behold the sculptured doors,
the cloud-capped statues, the sky-towering temples,
the brazen prows of many a vessel welded on to lofty
columns, the temples built on massy crags where the
<pb id="v.2.p.79"/>
hand of man has added to the work of nature, the
countless triumphal arches glittering with spoils.
The eyes are dazed by the blaze of metal and blink
outwearied by the surrounding gold.
Adored Prince, dost thou recognize thy house ? 'Tis
the same that thy loving sire showed to thy wondering
eyes while yet thou wert a boy of tender years.
Never in all his life did Theodosius, best of all the
gods, better deserve our love than when, triumphant
over all his foes, he came with thee to Rome to
sojourn within its walls, and there, following the
example of the noblest emperors, lived as a simple
citizen, not seeking to inspire terror by his name but
condescending to exchange banter and harmless
raillery with the people and as ready to lay aside his
rank and visit the homes of the poor as to enter the
palaces of the noble. *Tis thus the public love is
kindled when with just humanity modesty bids
royal state stoop to the people. And thee, while
still but a boy, though the crown had not yet
encircled thy head, thy father took to share his
honours, 1 cherishing thee in his royal bosom, giving
thy youth its first taste of triumphs and teaching it
the prelude of its mighty destiny. Peoples of every
tongue and Persian chiefs sent to solicit alliance in
Rome - once saw thee seated with thy father in
this very palace and bowing the knee laid their
crowns at thy feet. Thou wert at his side when he
summoned the tribes to receive a bounteous largess :
with thee he entered the hallowed portals of the
assembled senate clad in the consul's robe, right
glad to introduce his son to the good-will of the
Roman Fathers, that so his youthful heir might grow
familiar with empire.
<pb id="v.2.p.81"/>
Hence taking firmer root the love of Rome clung
to thee more closely and grew strong, deep-planted
in all thy heart. As thou grewest the affection which
thou hadst found in childhood for the city grew too ;
nor was Bosporus, whose cherished town was thy
nurse, able on thy return to seduce thee from that
love. Every time that thy sire in sport gave thee thy
choice of whatsoever cities thou didst prefer to govern
as thy share of empire, thou didst leave to thy brother
Arcadius the throne and riches of the East and the
lands which by inheritance should be his. <q direct="unspecified"> Let him
rule over the servile Assyrians,</q> thou saidst, <q direct="unspecified"> let
Nile, the river of Egypt, and the Tigris be his ; let me
have my beloved Rome.</q> Thy wishes have been fulfilled.
Fortune set up a new tyrant only to ensure
for thee the governance of Latium. So soon as ever
the war was brought to a successful conclusion thou
wert summoned from the court of Byzantium to
undertake the rule of Italy twice conquered by thy
father's arms. Serena herself left the East and
accompanied thee in thy journey across Illyria : fearless
in face of danger she bestowed a mother's care
on thee who wert to be lord of Latium and her
own son-in-law after Theodosius' translation to the
sky. She kept careful guard over the child entrusted
to her protection through the dangers of that critical
time and brought thee safe to her uncle's throne and
her husband's army. Stilicho and Serena vied in
love toward thee and what Serena's care had brought
safe home Stilicho 's affection welcomed there.
Happy father to enter heaven with no fears for the
future ; he knew that thou wert to succeed him
With what joy he looks down from above and sees his
glory enhanced by thine exploits ! Europe and
<pb id="v.2.p.83"/>
Africa were alike threatened by foes : from Mount
Atlas came fierce Gildo ; Alaric from Pence's savage
isle. Often had both with impious daring set at
nought the commands of thy sire. When he came
from the lands of Thrace Alaric closed against him
the waters of the Danube ; Gildo scorned his
command and, refusing assistance for a neighbouring
war, had seized on the fields of Libya he had long
forsworn. Theodosius recalls the anger he then
justly felt and rejoices to witness their discomfiture,
proud to have his son for his avenger. Orestes'
sword took vengeance on the son of Thyestes 1 ;
but guilt was blent with piety, and the sword-stroke
brings doubtful glory when honour is balanced by a
mother's murder ; Augustus sated the shade of
Caesar with his enemies' blood, but he made a false
advertisement of piety when, to the grief of his
fatherland, he offered the blood of citizens to his
father's ghost. But for thee thy sire's cause, linked
as it is with the general safety, doubles thy warlike
fame ; the same victory that has avenged thy sire
has restored peace to the world.
My lyre inspired by the Muses of Pieria has long
since sung of the defeat and capture of the Moor ;
but of late, too, in Stilicho's presence I have celebrated
in verse the wars against the Getae. To-day
I would fain sing the glories of thy home-coming
and, ceasing to tell of wars, would prelude a theme
of thankfulness.
Alaric, his hopes ruined by his bloody defeat at
Pollentia, though policy dictated that his life should
be spared, was nevertheless deserted by all his allies
and bereft of all his resources. He was forced to
leave Latium and to retrace his steps in ruin and
<pb id="v.2.p.85"/>
disgrace ; such was the complete reversal of his
fortune. 1 As when a pirate ship, the terror of every
sea, laden with the spoils of violence and the booty
taken from many a captured merchantman, falls in
with a great man-of-war and hopes to secure it for
its prey as vessels heretofore, then indeed crippled by
the slaughter of its oarsmen and the rending of its
sails, deprived of its rudder and all but destroyed by
the breaking of its yard-arms, it is driven this way and
that at the mercy of wind and wave and at last pays
the penalty for its piracy ; even so Alaric turned
backwards his vain threatenings, fleeing from Italy
that, once so easy for his advance, was now so difficult
for his retreat. His fear makes him believe every
road barred, and rivers, erstwhile left behind in
scorn, fill him with alarm on his return.
Meanwhile, as it fell out, father Eridanus in his
watery home beneath the crystal caverns, ignorant
as yet of what had happened, was pondering weighty
cares. What, he wondered, would be the outcome
of the war : would Jove approve empire and law
and Rome's days of peace, or would he, abhorring
order, condemn future ages to the primal ways of
brute beasts ? As he anxiously ponders such things
one of the Naiads with hair unbound came and
embraced her sire and said, <q direct="unspecified"> Alaric is other now
than once we saw him in his hour of triumph : thou
wilt wonder at the pallor of his countenance. Joy
it will be to reckon up his army and number the
remains of so great a host. Frown no more nor
complain ; let my sister nymphs once more enjoy
their dances.</q>
So spake she and he lifted his gracious head above
the gliding stream and on his dripping forehead
<pb id="v.2.p.87"/>
gleamed the golden horns that cast their brilliance
all along the banks. No common crown of reeds
adorned his oozy locks. The green branches of the
daughters of the sun ^ shadowed his head and amber
dripped from all his hair. A cloak was flung over
his broad shoulders, a cloak whose grey texture was
set aflame with an embroidery of Phaethon and his
father's chariot. Resting beneath his breast an urn
glorious with engraved stars makes clear its heavensent
beauty. For there Phoebus had set in the sky
all the sad stories of his woe : Cycnus changed
into a swan, Phaethon's sisters transformed into
trees, and the river that washed the wounds of
his dying son ; the charioteer is there in his icy
zone, the Hyades follow on their brother's traces,
while the Milky Way sprinkles the outstretched
wings of Cycnus who bears him company ; the
constellation of Eridanus 2 himself wets the clear
southern sky in its tortuous course and with starry
stream flows beneath Orion's dread sword.
Glorious in such guise the god looked forth and
saw the Getae advancing with bowed necks. Then
he spake : <q direct="unspecified"> What, Alaric, hast thou then changed
thy plans ? Why hastenest thou back ? Art wearied
so soon of the coasts of Italy ? Feedest thou not
thy horses on Tiber's grassy bank as thou thoughtest
to do ? Drivest not the plough on Etruria's hills ?
Fit object of all the punishments of Hell, thinkest
thou to attack the city of the gods with a Giant's
rage ? If none other, was not my Phaethon a
warning to thee, Phaëthon fall'n from heaven to
quench his flames in my waters, what time he
god, became a constellation — hence Eridanus is said to
<q direct="unspecified"> wet</q> the southern sky.
<pb id="v.2.p.89"/>
sought with mortal hand to hold the fiery reins of
the sky and hoped to spread day's brilliance from a
mortal countenance ? 'Tis the same mad crime, I
tell thee, whosoever aspires to spoil Rome or drive
the sun's chariot.</q>
So spake he, and rising yet farther out of the stream
he loudly summoned the rivers of Liguria and
Venetia. These raise their dripping heads from
among their leafy banks, fair Ticinus, blue Addua,
swift Athesis, slow Mincius, and Timavus with his
nine mouths. All mock at the fugitive and recall
the happy flocks to the now peaceful meadows ;
Lycaean Pan is bidden to return and the Dryads
and Fauns, gods of the countryside.
Thou too, Verona,^ didst add no small makeweight
to Rome's victory over the Getae ; not
even Pollentia nor the walls of avenging Hasta
did more for the salvation of Italy. Here, as once
again he breaks his bond, and driven by his losses
risks all in the attempt to change his present fortune,
Alaric learned that his mad treachery availed him
nothing and that change of place changes not
destiny. The vultures fed on the countless bodies
of his slaim and Athesis, carrying down the corpses
of Rome's enemies in its stream, turned the waters
of the Ionian sea into blood.
The treaty violated, Stilicho with all eagerness
grasped at the conflict proffered where Rome was
now far away from danger and Padus flowed between
witnessing the strife. He rejoices that now opportune
treachery has broken out in rebellious risings
and, setting an example of endurance, he shirks
neither fiery sun nor scorching dust. Himself he
is everywhere with dreadful arm ; he stations troops
<pb id="v.2.p.91"/>
at every point, even where the enemy little expected
them, and hastens in any and every direction to the
succour of him who needs it. If the soldiers flag
with wearied ranks he throws the auxiliaries into
the line heedless of their loss ; thus he cunningly
weakens the savage tribes of the Danube by opposing
one tribe to another and with twofold gain joins
battle that turns barbarians against themselves to
perish in either army for our sake. Thee too, Alaric,
he had captured and delivered over to death had not
the hasty zeal of the rash Alan chief upset his
carefully laid scheme. All but a prisoner thou
dost lash thy panting steed, nor do we regret
that escape. Rather get thee gone, thou last
remnant of thy race, sole survivor of so many
Danubian tribes ; get thee gone, the living witness
of Rome's triumph.
Yet was his 1 fierce spirit not cast down by these
great reverses ; he still attempted to discover an
unknown path across the mountains, hoping that
over their rocky summits he might fall suddenly on
the peoples of Raetia and Gaul. But Stilicho's
more soldierly vigilance put a stop to his projects.
Who indeed could hope to deceive that unsleeping
brain, those godlike eyes that watched o'er Italy ?
Never did an enemy succeed in discovering Stilicho's
plans or had power to conceal his own. Before
they knew them themselves the secrets of the
Getae were known to Stilicho, whose generalship
was quick to meet their every ruse.
Baulked in every attempt Alaric camped panicstricken
on a single hill. Though the horses, feeding
on bitter leaves, gnawed even the tree-bark, though
pestilence raged, brought on by foul food and
<pb id="v.2.p.93"/>
aggravated by the season's heat, though the soldiers
arrogantly heaped abuse on their beleaguered
leader and reminded him of their captured children ;
yet neither the ravages of disease nor famine that
teaches men to face all dangers, nor grief for spoils
lost, nor the voice of shame nor anger at bitter
gibes could tempt him to brave the perils of a
hand-to-hand fight, tried so often before and with
such ill success. What triumph more complete
than that of extorting from a conquered foe the
admission that he is conquered ? And now numbers
of deserters began to weaken his already reduced
strength and day by day his forces were diminished.
Surrender was not now the hidden work of a few
but meant the open defection of whole sections
and squadrons. Their general rides after them and
with angry curses and vain clamour seeks to hold
them back, waging war now on his own troops.
He weeps, calls the men by name, recalls them with
prayers and supplications ; he reminds them of past
campaigns and all to no purpose offers his throat
to their reluctant hands. His mind a prey to
melancholy he sees his forces desert him, his army
melt away, even as an old bee-master of Hybla, beating
Cybele's gong, tries, by means of that noise, to
recall his scattered bees who have wantonly left their
combs and fled the hive, till, himself wearied of the
useless sound, he weeps the loss of his store of honey
and cries out upon the faithless swarm that has forgotten
its accustomed home and left its cells empty.
And so when grief loosed the string of his tongue
that had long been mute he looked with tear-dimmed
eyes upon the well-known Alps and pondered upon
his present retreat, attended by a fate so different
<pb id="v.2.p.95"/>
from that which had prospered his advance. Then
with a single whisper he made war, with an outstretched
spear lightly overthrew walls, making a
mock of precipices ; now deserted and in despair
he offered a just spectacle to the mountains he
had so scornfully crossed. Then looking up at
the sky of Italy he said : <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Land of death for the
Getae, trod by me with such omens of disaster, let
thy wrath be now appeased by the sacrifice of so
many of the guilty ; let my sufferings at last excite
thy compassion. Behold me, once lord of the world,
the friend of fortune till I invaded thee ; now, like
an exile or an adjudged criminal, I feel upon my back
the nearer breath of my pursuers. Alas ! which of
my disasters shall I lament first, which last ? Not
thou, Pollentia, nor ye, my captured treasures,
have thus tortured me ; be that destiny's harsh lot
or the chance of war. I had not then lost all my
forces ; with troops still at my back, with my cavalry
intact, I retired with the remnant of my army to
the hills they call the Apennines. Its inhabitants
told me that this mountain stretched from the
confines of Liguria as far as the promontory of
Pelorus in Sicily and embraced all the peoples of
Italy, dividing with its unbroken chain the two
seas that wash their country's two coasts. If I had
pursued the plan that anger first dictated to me
and had in my desperation continued my march
along its crest, what lay beyond ? Giving everything 
to the flames I might have died with loftier
fame. Ay, and my dying eyes had beheld thee,
Rome, from not so far away, and my very death
would have cost the victor dear as he pursued me
over the well-tilled cornfields. But Rome held my
<pb id="v.2.p.97"/>
children captive, my wives, my wealth — yet, freed
from such hindrances, my advance had been the
more rapid.
</p>
               <p>With what cunning, with what skill, did Stilicho,
that ever fatal enemy, ensnare me ! His pretended
mercy did but blunt my warlike spirit, and availed
him to shift the war backwards across the Po. A
curse on that armistice, more damaging than the
yoke of slavery. 'Twas then the cause of the Getae
was undone, then that I signed my own deathwarrant.
More rudely than any weapon did mercy
destroy our people, beneath that semblance of peace
lay the deadliest form of war, and I myself fell
into the snare I had laid for others. I am weary of
it all ; where shall I find comfort or counsel ? I
fear my friends more than my foes.
</p>
               <p>Would God I had lost them all on that field. He
is ever mine that has fallen in hard conflict. Better
all had perished by the sword ; less bitter had been
my grief for losses inflicted by a victorious foe than
for those brought upon me by treachery. Is there
not left one faithful follower? My comrades have
turned against me, my friends hate me. My
life is a burden ; why prolong it ? Where hide
the remnants of my shipwrecked fortunes ? To
what land shall I flee where the names of Stihcho
and all too powerful Italy shall not sound for ever
in mine ears ? </p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>
So spake he, and with Stilicho pressing hard
upon him fled in terror before our eagles. With
him goes Pallor, black Hunger, Despair with bloodless,
wounded countenance and a hellish company
of shrieking Diseases. Then the learned priest whirls
around the sick body 1 the torch of purification
<pb id="v.2.p.99"/>
with its smoky, odorous flame of blue sulphur
and black bitumen ; he sprinkles the limbs with
holy water and with herbs that banish evil influences
and, praying to Jove the Purifier and to Diana,
with back-turned hands throws over his head towards
the South the torches which are to carry off with
them the spells cast over the sick.
Meanwhile the ardent desire of both senate and
people to behold their emperor demands his often
denied return. Not with such consent, our grandsires 
report, were public vows eagerly offered
throughout the city when warlike Trajan had
broken the power of Dacia and reduced the indignant 
north once more to subjection, what time
the Scythian river Hypanis beheld the Roman
axes and Lake Maeotis looked in amaze on a
Roman court administering Roman law. It was
a lesser enthusiasm which recalled the gentle
Marcus Aurelius to give thanks in Rome's temples
for Fortune's deliverance of Italy from a similar
pressure of surrounding nations. Then 'twas no
thanks to the generals ; for a fiery shower fell on the
enemy ; one man his scorched courser bore trembling
on its smoking back ; another sank down beneath his
fire-wasted helmet ; spears glowed molten by lightning
and swords vanished suddenly into smoke.
Heaven it was that fought that battle with no mortal
weapons, whether it was that Chaldean seers 1 had
by their magic spells won over the gods to our side
or, as I rather think, that Marcus' blameless life had
power to win the Thunderer's homage. To-day, also,
assuredly Heaven's favour would not be wanting to
Latium should our own hand fail, but a beneficent
<pb id="v.2.p.101"/>


providence has shown itself unwilling to rob human
endeavour of its honour or to let the lightning win
the well merited crown of laurel which the efforts of
thy father-in-law, Stilicho, have secured for thy brows.
Full often had the nobles, sent to urge thy return,
brought back the answer that as yet thou couldst
not come, until Rome herself, unable to bear any
longer the frustration of her citizens' common
prayer, came forth from the depths of her sanctuary
and, openly displaying her radiant face, urged the
hesitating emperor with complaints of her own.
</p>
         <p>
            <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Too long, my emperor, have I, thy mother, borne in
silence the hurt thy refusal to return hath done me.
How long shall favoured Liguria possess that for
which I desire ? How long shall the Rubicon,
separating me from the object of my prayers by so
narrow a space, torture the Tiber by the all-but-presence
of that divine being whose nearer sojourn
it is not allowed to enjoy ? Was it not enough to
have scorned me once when Africa, again at war,
mocked the city with hopes of its emperor's coming,
nor could we move thine obstinate ears with all our
prayers ? Yet did I harness for thee two steeds
whiter than snow to draw the chariot wherein thou
shouldst ride ; already had I builded in thy name
a triumphal arch through the which thou shouldst
pass clad in the garb of victory, and I was dedicating
it as a memorial of the war with an inscription to
be the undying witness of the salvation of Libya.
Even then were being prepared for Jove to see
from the Tarpeian rock models for the coming
triumph ; a fleet of ships was cast in metal, ships
whose oar-blades smote the golden sea ; the cities
of Africa were made to go before thy chariot and
<pb id="v.2.p.103"/>

Triton, with his conquered waters and his head 
crowned with Minerva's sacred reeds ; crowds of 
slaves with upgirt dresses bore a figure of trembling 
Atlas cast in bronze ; Gildo himself, destined to 
undergo in prison the punishment once meted out 
to Jugurtha, offered his stubborn neck to the yoke, 
Gildo fallen a captive to the arms of Rome, not to 
the treachery of a Bocchus and a Sulla. 1 

</p>
               <p>But I pass over what has been. Can the present 
triumph, too, of the Getic war escape me ? Does 
any spot give ampler room to so great renown ? The 
very blessings thou hast bestowed beg thee not to 
delay, and thy generosity, constrained by its own fair 
deeds, must needs love those whom it has saved. 
Now for a hundred summers the reaper's sickle has 
gathered the yellow harvest of Gargarus ; already 
the consul has introduced the games that occur but 
once in a century and upon which no man looks 
twice. During these years which number twice 
ten lustres, I have but thrice 2 seen an emperor enter 
my walls in triumph ; all at different times but for 
the same reason — civil war. Did they come in their 
pride that I should see their chariots stained with 
Italy's blood ? Can any think a mother finds joy 
in the tears of her offspring ? The tyrants were 
slain, but even they were my children. Caesar 
boasted him of his victories over the Gauls ; he said 
nought about Pharsalia. Where the two sides bear 
the same standards and are of one blood, as defeat is 
ever shameful so victory brings no honour. See thou 
to it that now a truer glory crown our arms ; give 
me back the joy, long a stranger to me, of honest 

other two may refer to Theodosius' victories over Eugenius 
and Maximus. 

<pb id="v.2.p.105"/>

fame won from the enemy, and make good guilty 
triumphs by the lawful spoils of foreign madness. 

</p>
               <p>How long shall our emperor's rule be a stranger to 
its true home and his governance stray from its 
rightful seat ? Why does my palace which has given 
its name to all palaces mourn in neglected decay ? 
Cannot the world be ruled therefrom ? Phoebus 
never deserts his centre path though his beams 
are shed upon all. Was the hand of those old 
emperors who made me their home any lighter 
laid upon the tribes of Danube and Rhine ? Was 
the awe felt by those of Tigris and Euphrates any 
less real when Mede and Indian came to this 
my capital of Rome to beg for alliance or sue for 
peace ? Here dwelt those emperors whom merit 
chose for merit, and so, adopting them as consuls 
for the Roman state, made judgement not blood 
continue a noble line. Here lived the Aelian family 
that traced its descent from Nerva, the peaceful 
Antonines, the warlike Severi. Thou art a citizen ; 
disdain not such a band ; give us back the counten- 
ance we beheld long since, that Father Tiber, 
remembering the glory that was, may with thy 
father-in-law welcome thee as a man whom as a 
boy he saw leave my city at his father's side.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>

While yet she entreated the emperor reassured 
her with these words : <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Never shalt thou complain 
that I have been deaf to thine entreaties ; I could 
not thwart thee, goddess, who art the mother of our 
laws. Bring no railing accusation against thy sons. 
Did I disregard my country's call after the African 
war ? Nay, I sent thee Stilicho to sit in the curule 
chair to take my place, a consul instead of an emperor, 
a father- instead of a son-in-law. In him thy 
<pb id="v.2.p.107"/>

citizens saw also myself ; so my love believes, for 
it has found that not blood alone but rather glorious 
deeds can show a parent. Had I a hundred tongues 
I could not touch on all the benefits he has bestowed 
upon me and upon the empire ; one deed alone 
of them all will I recount to thee, goddess, if so be 
it is as yet unknown to thee, a deed of which I was 
the spectator or the cause. 

</p>
               <p>Alaric had laid waste Greece and the coasts of 
Thrace and in the mad pride of his many victories 
and the arrogance inspired by his crossing of the 
Alps had laid siege to the trembling cities of Liguria 
with winter as his ally — a season that favours a race 
accustomed to inclement skies ; he then threatened 
to break down my defences and to lay strait siege to 
me also, bolstering up his hopes with the thought 
that, at the terror of his name and in fear of having 
none to aid me, I should come to terms with him on 
any conditions he chose. But I felt no fear, for I 
relied on the advance of Stilicho, and was mindful, 
O goddess, of those thy leaders who, even in face 
of death, never through base love of life made terms 
at the cost of honour. It was night ; where'er I 
looked I saw the watchfires of the enemy shining like 
stars. The bugle had already summoned the soldiers 
to the first watch when glorious Stilicho arrived from 
the frozen north. But the enemy held the road 
between my father-in-law and myself, and the bridge 
whose obstructing piers churn turbid Addua to yet 
fuller foam. What was Stilicho to do ? Halt ? My 
danger forbade the least delay. Break through the 
enemy's line ? His force was too small. In hasten- 
ing to my aid he had left behind him many auxiliaries 
and legionary troops. Placed in this dilemma he 
<pb id="v.2.p.109"/>

thought it long and tedious to wait for reinforcements 
and, putting aside his own peril, was eager only to 
deliver me from mine ; inspired by the courage that 
is born of love, heedless of his own danger, he broke 
through the enemy's midst and, sword in hand, 
cutting down all who sought to bar his passage, he 
passed like lightning through the barbarians' camp. 
</p>
               <p>Now let poets' songs praise me the son of Tydeus 
because, relying on Odysseus' help when the way 
was opened by Dolon's wiles and all was sunk in 
feasting and slumber, he broke into the Thracian 
camp of Rhesus and brought back to the Greek 
lines his captured steeds, which — if we may trust 
the too generous Muses — surpassed the winds in 
speed, the snows in whiteness. Here was a man 
who, with no treachery 'mid silent slumber, clave a 
path for himself with his sword in the open light of 
day and arrived within our lines covered with blood, 
thus surpassing the brave deeds of Diomede by as 
much as day surpasses night and open battle ambush. 
Alaric's position, moreover, on the river bank was a 
stronger one, and he himself a warrior with whom 
Rhesus, even when awake, could not be compared. 
Rhesus was king, Alaric the conqueror, of Thrace. 
Neither weapons nor the river's bar could stop 
Stilicho. So Horatius, standing on the falling bridge, 
drave back the threatening hosts of Etruria and then 
swam the Tiber, still carrying the shield wherewith to 
the amazement of Tarquin he had defended Rome, 
and from mid stream looked back with scornful 
gaze upon Porsenna. 'Twas the swift Addua my 
father breasted ; but, as he swam the flood, Horatius 
turned his back upon the Etruscans, Stilicho faced 
the barbarian foe. 
<pb id="v.2.p.111"/>
               </p>
               <p>Now, O Rome, lead forth the chorus that shall 
hymn a contest of such high renown and let thy best 
genius with all its eloquence voice the well-merited 
praises of my foster parent.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>

So spake he and, issuing from the walls of old 
Ravenna, advanced his standards. He crossed the 
mouths of the Po and left behind him that river 
harbour 1 where, in fixed succession, in flows the 
foaming main and bears up the vessels that ride 
there at anchor on forward and backward flowing 
stream, and again deserts the waveless shore, like 
moon-led tides upon the marge of Ocean. Next 
he comes to the old city of Fortune's Temple that 
bids him glad welcome and from its height looks 
down upon Metaurus threading its rocky valley 
where an arch, tunnelled through the living rock, 
affords a path through the mountain's very heart, 
rising above the temple of Jove and the dizzy altars 
set up by the shepherds of the Apennines. 'Twas 
thy good pleasure, too, to visit Clitumnus' wave, 2 
beloved of them that triumph, for thence do victors 
get them white-coated animals for sacrifice at Rome. 
Thou markest well also the stream's strange property, 
flowing gently on when one approaches with silent 
step, but swirling and eddying should one hasten 
with louder utterance ; and while it is the common 
nature of water to mirror the exact image of the 
body it alone boasts the strange power that it 
mimics not human form but human character. 
Next thy royal charger treads the streets of Narnia, 
looking out from its eminence upon the plain below : 
not far therefrom flows the strange-coloured stream 
which gives the town its name, its sulphurous waters 
<pb id="v.2.p.113"/>
flowing in tortuous course between opposed mountains
through dense forests of holm-oak. Then when
in greeting to Father Tiber thou hast poured a libation
of his waters thou art welcomed by Rome's arches
and all the magnificent buildings which line the
roads of that noble city's suburbs.
And as a careful mother at the approach of her
daughter's lover does all that trembling hand can
do to enhance the charms that are to win a husband,
oft readjusts dress and girdle, confines her breast
with bands of green jasper, gathers up her hair with
jewels, sets a necklace about her neck, and hangs
glistening pearls from her ears, so Rome, in order
to be pleasing in thy sight, offers herself to thy
admiring gaze more glorious and with hills made
higher and herself greater than thou hadst known her.
Still fairer than of old she seemed by reason of those
new walls that the rumour of the Getae's approach
had just caused to be built ; fear was the architect of
that beauteous work and, by a strange freak of
fortune, war put an end to the decay that peace
had brought. For fear it was that caused the
sudden upspringing of all those towers and renewed
the youth of Rome's seven hills by enclosing them
all within one long wall. Even the weather listened
favourably to our prayers and was finer than its
wont, although continuous rain had spoiled the
preceding night ; but the clouds melted away
before the glory of the sun and the emperor. All
the days before had the south wind troubled with
rain and dimmed the moon's young disc that heaven
might know it was for thee that the sunshine waited.
One huge crowd filled all the slope between the
Palatine hill and the Mulvian bridge and as far up
<pb id="v.2.p.115"/>
as it was possible to go on the house roofs ; the
ground seethed with men, the lofty buildings were
aglow with women. Those who are young rejoice
in an emperor of their own age, the old cease to
belaud the past and count their destiny happy that
they have lived to see such a day, blessing the kindly
times when a prince so easy of access, so singular
in courtesy, forbade the senators of Rome to march
before his chariot, even though Eucherius, in whose
veins ran regal blood on father's and on mother's
side, and his own sister did honour to his triumph
like simple soldiers. Such has been the teaching of
that stern but loving parent who showed no more
favour to his children than to himself, and refused
a son honours he granted to nobles. Bent age
and upstanding youth alike are loud in his praises
and, comparing the new with the ancient rule,
recognize in Honorius a true citizen, in his predecessors
tyrants.
The women of Rome never tire of gazing at those
blooming cheeks, those crowned locks, those limbs
clothed in the consul's jasper-studded robes, those
mighty shoulders, and that neck, beauteous as
Bacchus' own, with its necklace of Red Sea emeralds.
Many an innocent maid, while simple modesty
blushes in her cheek, would bend her gaze o'er all and
inquire of her aged nurse the meaning of the dragons
on the colours. <q direct="unspecified"> Do they,</q> she would ask, <q direct="unspecified">but
wave in the air or is theirs a veritable hiss, uttered as
they are about to seize an enemy in their jaws?</q>
When she sees the mail-clad knights and brazen-
armoured horses she would fain know whence that
iron race of men is sprung and what land it is gives
birth to steeds of bronze. <q direct="unspecified"> Has the god of Lemnos,</q>
            <pb id="v.2.p.117"/>
she would ask, <q direct="unspecified"> bestowed on metal the power to
neigh, and forged living statues for the fight?</q>
Joy and fear fill her mind ; she points with her finger
how Juno's bird decks the gay crests upon their
helmets, or how, beneath the golden armour on
their horses' backs, the red silk waves and ripples
over the strong shoulders.
Then it was, Stilicho, that Fortune repaid thee
for the labour of so many years when, mounted
in the same chariot, thou sawest thy son-in-law in
his prime pass in triumph through the streets of
Rome, and didst recall that day when in troubled
terror mid uncertain fortune the dying father
entrusted his son to thy care. Now thy many virtues
have found their meet reward : loyalty that has
kept safe that which was confided to it, singleness
of purpose that made a boy the master of the world,
affection that has bestowed such loving care on an
adopted son. This is the boy who to-day summons
Rome's citizens to ll^e place of meeting and from
his father's ivory throne tells to the fathers the
causes and the issues of his acts, and, following
ancient precedent, directs the deeds of empire at
the judgement-seat of the Senate. He piles up
no words, for confidence has nothing to conceal ;
his mind, conscious of true worth, refuses the aid of
artificial speech. The senators learn to know him ;
their chief wears the Gabine 1 garb, and thronged
with generals in the role of peace the Senate-house
prepares for service under the auspices of the warlike
court. Winged victory herself, Rome's faithful
guardian, was in her temple ; 2 her golden pinions
stretched in protection over the holy sanctuary where
the fathers meet together, and she herself, a tireless
<pb id="v.2.p.119"/>
attendant on thine armies, now at last has had her
wish granted and is able to promise that for all
time to come thou shalt be Rome's guardian and she
thine.
Hence the Sacred Way (now truly named) brings
thee back to thy home. Eagerly breaks out the
world's one - hearted welcome, that thou dost not
woo with lure of scattered gold ; nor for thee does
the treasury, seeking to corrupt good faith, court
venal applause ; to worth unpurchased love is offered
by a pure heart. For life that is dearer than any
gift makes all thy debtors. Away with wooing of
applause ! He can ask no payment who owes his life
to love.
Oh what mysterious power over the people does the
Empire's guardian-genius bring ! What majesty
bows to majesty as the prince, clad in imperial
scarlet, returns the salutations of the people that
crowd the tiers of the Circus ! The shouts of the
adoring populace rising from that immense circle
thunder to the sky, while the echoes of Rome's seven
hills repeat as with one voice the name of Honorius.
Nor does the Circus display only horse-races ; its
floor, whereon chariots were wont to drive, is surrounded
by a palisade, and in this new amphitheatre,
so far, so different, from their native valleys, Libyan
lions shed their blood. This is the scene, too, of a
military display ; here we often see armed bands
advancing and retiring in mazed movements that are
nevertheless executed according to a fixed plan ; we
watch them wheel in perfect order, extend with
disciplined precision, affording us the pleasing
spectacle of mimic warfare. The leader cracks
his whip and a thousand bodies execute in unison
<pb id="v.2.p.121"/>
their new movements ; now they clap their bucklers
to their sides, now they brandish them above
their heads ; deeply sound the clashing shields,
sharply ring the engaging swords, and, to the
rhythm of beaten targes, the echoing song of
steel is punctuated by the interclash of weapons.
Suddenly the whole phalanx falls on its knees
before thee and a thousand helmets bow down in
reverence. Then the companies separate, wheeling
and counter-wheeling with ordered skill, following
a course more tortuous than the corridors of the
Minotaur's Cretan palace or the reaches of Meander's
wandering stream. Then wheeling apart they form
with circular masses, and Janus, 1 emprisoning war
behind his ever unopening doors, after a happy
mimicry of battle bestows on peace the innocent
rewards of combat.
And now, his double head crowned with laurel,
Janus opens the new year with auspicious calendar ;
now Tiber sees united in Honorius Brutus' consular
robe and Romulus' kingly sceptre. The Palatine
hill rejoices after many generations again to look
upon a consul ; the rostra learn to know the curule
chair famed of old among our forefathers, and royal
lictors, a long unwonted sight, encircle with their
golden fasces the Forum of Trajan; while Honorius,
wreathing with Getic laurels the axes borne for the
sixth time before him, places a conqueror's foot upon
the neck of subdued Danube. Let this year springing
from its true source go forth among the nations more
glorious than any — a year the consul inaugurated,
not a stranger in a strange land, whose cradle the
Senate-house guarded, that Roman citizens first
beheld, that Victory, all wars o'ercome, auspiciously
<pb id="v.2.p.123"/>
brought to birth. Years in which mere commoners
held the consulship, and ye years when Theodosius
and his predecessors graced that office in Rome or
elsewhere, count your honours as nought and worship
this present year. Ay, you five previous consulships
of Honorius, even you that our emperor shall
hold in Rome in the days to come, give place to this
one. Wert thou, Honorius, to be consul every year,
yet is this thy sixth to be magnified above all thy
consulships, excelling all that are past and model of
all that are to come.
<pb id="v.2.p.125"/>
         </p>
            </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>