<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
                  <title>Against Rufinus</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian, with an English translation, in Two Volumes, Vol. I</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="editor">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date type="printing">1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="http://www.archive.org/stream/claudian01clau#page/24/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                              <state unit="book" delim="."/>                             
                              <state unit="poem"/>
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa009.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.25" TEIform="pb"/>
               <div1 type="book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                        <div2 type="poem" n="praef" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>
When Python had fallen, laid low by the arrow of
Phoebus, his dying limbs outspread o'er Cirrha's
heights — Python, whose coils covered whole mountains,
whose maw swallowed rivers and whose
bloody crest touched the stars — then Parnassus
was free and the woods, their serpent fetters shaken
off, began to grow tall with lofty trees. The mountain-ashes,
long shaken by the dragon's sinuous
coils, spread their leaves securely to the breeze, and
Cephisus, who had so often foamed with his poisonous
venom, now flowed a purer stream with limpid
wave. The whole country echoed with the cry,
<q direct="unspecified"> hail, Healer</q>: every land sang Phoebus' praise. A
fuller wind shakes the tripod, and the gods, hearing
the Muses' sweet song from afar off, gather in the
dread caverns of Themis.
</p>
         <p>A blessed band comes together to hear my song,
now that a second Python has been slain by the
weapons of that master of ours who made the rule
of the brother Emperors hold the world steady,
observing justice in peace and showing vigour
in war.
<pb id="v.1.p."/>
         </p>
                        
         <pb id="v.1.p.27" TEIform="pb"/>
         </div2>  
         <div2 type="poem" id="poem.3" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>

My mind has often wavered between two opinions:
have the gods a care for the world or is there no
ruler therein and do mortal things drift as dubious
chance dictates? For when I investigated the laws
and the ordinances of heaven and observed the sea's
appointed limits, the year's fixed cycle and the
alternation of light and darkness, then methought
everything was ordained according to the direction
of a God who had bidden the stars move by fixed
laws, plants grow at different seasons, the changing
moon fulfil her circle with borrowed light and the
sun shine by his own, who spread the shore before
the waves and balanced the world in the centre of
the firmament. But when I saw the impenetrable
mist which surrounds human affairs, the wicked
happy and long prosperous and the good discomforted,
then in turn my belief in God was weakened
and failed, and even against mine own will I embraced
the tenets of that other philosophy 1 which teaches
that atoms drift in purposeless motion and that new
forms throughout the vast void are shaped by chance
and not design — that philosophy which believes in
God in an ambiguous sense, or holds that there be
no gods, or that they are careless of our doings. At
<pb id="v.1.p.29"/>
last Rufinus' fate has dispelled this uncertainty and
freed the gods from this imputation. No longer
can I complain that the unrighteous man reaches
the highest pinnacle of success. He is raised aloft
that he may be hurled down in more headlong
ruin. Muses, unfold to your poet whence sprang
this grievous pest.
</p>
         <p>Dire Allecto once kindled with jealous wrath on
seeing widespread peace among the cities of men.
</p>
         <p>Straightway she summons the hideous council of
the nether-world sisters to her foul palace gates.
</p>
         <p>Hell's numberless monsters are gathered together,
Night's children of ill-omened birth . Discord, mother
of war, imperious Hunger, Age, near neighbour to
Death; Disease, whose life is a burden to himself;
Envy that brooks not another's prosperity, woeful
Sorrow with rent garments; Fear and foolhardy
Rashness with sightless eyes; Luxury, destroyer
of wealth, to whose side ever clings unhappy Want
with humble tread, and the long company of sleepless
Cares, hanging round the foul neck of their
mother Avarice. The iron seats are filled with
all this rout and the grim chamber is thronged with
the monstrous crowd. Allecto stood in their midst
and called for silence, thrusting behind her back
the snaky hair that swept her face and letting it
play over her shoulders. Then with mad utterance
she unlocked the anger deep hidden in her heart.
<q direct="unspecified"> Shall we allow the centuries to roll on in this
even tenour, and man to live thus blessed? What
novel kindliness has corrupted our characters?
Where is our inbred fury? Of what use the
lash with none to suffer beneath it? Why this
purposeless girdle of smoky torches? Sluggards, ye,
<pb id="v.1.p.31"/>
whom Jove has excluded from heaven, Theodosius
from earth. Lo! a golden age begins; lo! the
old breed of men returns. Peace and Godliness,
Love and Honour hold high their heads throughout
the world and sing a proud song of triumph over
our conquered folk. Justice herself (oh the pity of
it!), down -gliding through the limpid air, exults
over me and, now that crime has been cut down to
the roots, frees law from the dark prison wherein
she lay oppressed. Shall we, expelled from every
land, lie this long age in shameful torpor? Ere it
be too late recognize a Fury's duty: resume your
wonted strength and decree a crime worthy of this
august assembly. Fain would I shroud the stars in
Stygian darkness, smirch the light of day with our
breath, unbridle the ocean deeps, hurl rivers against
their shattered banks, and break the bonds of the
universe.</q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake she with cruel roar and uproused every
gaping serpent mouth as she shook her snaky locks
and scattered their baneful poison. Of two minds
was the band of her sisters. The greater number
was for declaring war upon heaven, yet some respected
still the ordinances of Dis and the uproar grew by
reason of their dissension, even as the sea's calm is
not at once restored, but the deep still thunders
when, for all the wind be dropped, the swelling tide
yet flows, and the last weary winds of the departing
storm play o'er the tossing waves.
</p>
         <p>Thereupon cruel Megaera rose from her funereal
seat, mistress she of madness' howlings and impious
ill and wrath bathed in fury's foam. No blood her
drink but that flowing from kindred slaughter and
forbidden crime, shed by a father's, by a brother's
<pb id="v.1.p.33"/>
sword. 'Twas she made e'en Hercules afraid and
brought shame upon that bow that had freed the
world of monsters; she aimed the arrow in Athamas' 1
hand: she took her pleasure in murder after murder,
a mad fury in Agamemnon's palace; beneath her
auspices wedlock mated Oedipus with his mother
and Thyestes with his daughter. Thus then she
speaks with dread-sounding words:
<q direct="unspecified"> To raise our standards against the gods, my
sisters, is neither right nor, methinks, possible;
but hurt the world we may, if such our wish, and
bring an universal destruction upon its inhabitants.
I have a monster more savage than the hydra brood,
swifter than the mother tigress, fiercer than the
south wind's blast, more treacherous than Euripus'
yellow flood — Rufinus. I was the first to gather
him, a new-born babe, to my bosom. Often did
the child nestle in mine embrace and seek my
breast, his arms thrown about my neck in a flood
of infant tears. My snakes shaped his soft limbs
licking them with their three-forked tongues. I
taught him guile whereby he learnt the arts of
injury and deceit, how to conceal the intended
menace and cover his treachery with a smile, fullfilled
with savagery and hot with lust of gain.
Him nor the sands of rich Tagus' flood by Tartessus'
town could satisfy nor the golden waters of ruddy
Pactolus; should he drink all Hermus' stream he
would parch with the greedier thirst. How skilled
to deceive and wreck friendships with hate! Had
that old generation of men produced such an one
as he, Theseus had fled Pirithous, Pylades deserted
Orestes in wrath, Pollux hated Castor. I confess
myself his inferior: his quick genius has outstripped
<pb id="v.1.p.35"/>
his preceptress: in a word (that I waste not your
time further) all the wickedness that is ours in
common is his alone. Him will I introduce, if the
plan commend itself to you, to the kingly palace of
the emperor of the world. Be he wiser than Numa,
be he Minos' self, needs must he yield and succumb
to the treachery of my foster child.</q>
         </p>
         <p>A shout followed her words: all stretched forth
their impious hands and applauded the awful plot.
</p>
         <p>When Megaera had gathered together her dress
with the black serpent that girdled her, and bound
her hair with combs of steel, she approached the
sounding stream of Phlegethon, and seizing a tall
pine-tree from the scorched summit of the flaming
bank kindled it in the pitchy flood, then plied her
swift wings o'er sluggish Tartarus.
</p>
         <p>There is a place where Gaul stretches her furthermost
shore spread out before the waves of Ocean:
'tis there that Ulysses is said to have called up the
silent ghosts with a libation of blood. There is
heard the mournful weeping of the spirits of the
dead as they flit by with faint sound of wings, and
the inhabitants see the pale ghosts pass and the
shades of the dead. 'Twas from here the goddess
leapt forth, dimmed the sun's fair beams and
clave the sky with horrid howlings. Britain felt
the deadly sound, the noise shook the country
of the Senones,1 Tethys stayed her tide, and Rhine
let fall his urn and shrank his stream. Thereupon,
in the guise of an old man, her serpent locks changed
at her desire to snowy hair, her dread cheeks furrowed
with many a wrinkle and feigning weariness
in her gait she enters the walls of Elusa,2 in search
of the house she had long known so well. Long
<pb id="v.1.p.37"/>
she stood and gazed with jealous eyes, marvelling
at a man worse than herself; then spake she thus:
<q direct="unspecified"> Does ease content thee, Rufinus? Wastest thou
in vain the flower of thy youth inglorious thus in
thy father's fields? Thou knowest not what fate
and the stars owe thee, what fortune makes ready.
So thou wilt obey me thou shalt be lord of the whole
world. Despise not an old man's feeble limbs: I
have the gift of magic and the fire of prophecy is
within me. I have learned the incantations wherewith
Thessalian witches pull down the bright moon,
I know the meaning of the wise Egyptians' runes,
the art whereby the Chaldeans impose their will
upon the subject gods, the various saps that flow
within trees and the power of deadly herbs; all
those that grow on Caucasus rich in poisonous plants,
or, to man's bane, clothe the crags of Scythia;
herbs such as cruel Medea gathered and curious
Circe. Often in nocturnal rites have I sought to
propitiate the dread ghosts and Hecate, and recalled
the shades of buried men to live again by my magic:
many, too, has my wizardry brought to destruction
though the Fates had yet somewhat of their life's
thread to spin. I have caused oaks to walk and
the thunderbolt to stay his course, aye, and made
rivers reverse their course and flow backwards to
their fount. Lest thou perchance think these be
but idle boasts behold the change of thine own
house.</q> At these words the white pillars, to his
amazement, began to turn into gold and the beams
of a sudden to shine with metal.
</p>
         <p>His senses are captured by the bait, and, thrilled
beyond measure, he feasts his greedy eyes on the
sight. So Midas, king of Lydia, swelled at first
<pb id="v.1.p.39"/>
with pride when he found he could transform everything
he touched to gold: but when he beheld his
food grow rigid and his drink harden into golden ice
then he understood that this gift was a bane and
in his loathing for the gold cursed his prayer. Thus
Rufinus, overcome, cried out; <q direct="unspecified"> Whithersoever thou
summonest me I follow, be thou man or god.</q> Then
at the Fury's bidding he left his fatherland and
approached the cities of the East, threading the once
floating Symplegades and the seas renowned for
the voyage of the Argo, ship of Thessaly, till he came
to where, beneath its high-walled town, the gleaming
Bosporus separates Asia from the Thracian coast.
</p>
         <p>When he had completed this long journey and,
led by the evil thread of the fates, had won his
way into the far-famed palace, then did ambition
straightway come to birth and right was no more.
</p>
         <p>Everything had its price. He betrayed secrets,
deceived dependents, and sold honours that had
been wheedled from the emperor. He followed up
one crime with another, heaping fuel on the inflamed
mind and probing and embittering the erstwhile
trivial wound. And yet, as Nereus knows no
addition from the infinitude of rivers that flow into
him and though here he drains Danube's wave and
there Nile's summer flood with its sevenfold mouth,
yet ever remains his same and constant self, so
Rufinus' thirst knew no abatement for all the
streams of gold that flowed in upon him. Had any
a necklace studded with jewels or a fertile demesne
he was sure prey for Rufinus: a rich property
assured the ruin of its own possessor: fertility was
the husbandman's bane. He drives them from their
homes, expels them from the lands their sires had
<pb id="v.1.p.41"/>
left them, either wresting them from the living
owners or fastening upon them as an inheritor.
</p>
         <p>Massed riches are piled up and a single house
receives the plunder of a world; whole peoples
are forced into slavery, and thronging cities bow
beneath the tyranny of a private man.
</p>
         <p>Madman, what shall be the end? Though thou
possess either Ocean, though Lydia pour forth for
thee her golden waters, though thou join Croesus'
throne to Cyrus' crown, yet shalt thou never be rich
nor ever contented with thy booty. The greedy
man is always poor. Fabricius, happy in his honourable
poverty, despised the gifts of monarchs; the
consul Serranus sweated at his heavy plough and a
small cottage gave shelter to the warlike Curii.
</p>
         <p>To my mind such poverty as this is richer than
thy wealth, such a home greater than thy palaces.
</p>
         <p>There pernicious luxury seeks for the food that
satisfieth not; here the earth provides a banquet
for which is nought to pay. With thee wool absorbs
the dyes of Tyre; thy patterned clothes are stained
with purple; here are bright flowers and the meadow's
breathing charm which owes its varied hues but to
itself. There are beds piled on glittering bedsteads;
here stretches the soft grass, that breaks not sleep
with anxious cares. There a crowd of clients dins
through the spacious hails, here is song of birds and
the murmur of the gliding stream. A frugal life is
best. Nature has given the opportunity of happiness
to all, knew they but how to use it. Had we
realized this we should now have been enjoying
a simple life, no trumpets would be sounding, no
whistling spear would speed, no ship be buffeted by
the wind, no siege-engine overthrow battlements.
<pb id="v.1.p.43"/>
Still grew Rufinus' wicked greed, and his impious
passion for new-won wealth blazed yet fiercer; no
feeling of shame kept him from demanding and
extorting money. He combines perjury with ceaseless
cajolery, ratifying with a hand-clasp the bond he
purposes to break. Should any dare to refuse his
demand for one thing out of so many, his fierce
heart would be stirred with swelling wrath. Was
ever lioness wounded with a Gaetuhan's spear, or
Hyrcan tiger pursuing the robber of her young, was
ever bruised serpent so fierce? He swears by the
majesty of the gods and tramples on his oath. He
reverences not the laws of hospitality. To kill a
wife and her husband with her and her children
sates not his anger; 'tis not enough to slaughter
relations and drive friends into exile; he strives to
destroy every citizen of Rome and to blot out the
very name of our race. Nor does he even slay
with a swift death; ere that he enjoys the infliction
of cruel torture; the rack, the chain, the lightless
cell, these he sets before the final blow. Why, this
remission is more savage, more madly cruel, than the
sword — this grant of life that agony may accompany
it! Is death not enough for him? With
treacherous charges he attacks; dazed wretches
find him at once accuser and judge. Slow to all else
he is swift to crime and tireless to visit the ends of
the earth in its pursuit. Neither the Dog-star's heat
nor the wintry blasts of the Thracian north wind
detain him. Feverish anxiety torments his cruel
heart lest any escape his sword, or an emperor's
pardon lose him an opportunity for injury. Neither
age nor youth can move his pity: before their
father's eyes his bloody axe severs boys' heads
<pb id="v.1.p.45"/>
from their bodies; an aged man, once a consul,
survived the murder of his son but to be driven
into exile. Who can bring himself to tell of so
many murders, who can adequately mourn such
impious slaughter? Do men tell that cruel Sinis
of Corinth e'er wrought such wickedness with his
pine-tree, or Sciron with his precipitous rock, or
Phalaris with his brazen bull, or Sulla with his prison?
</p>
         <p>O gentle horses of Diomede! O pitiful altars of
Busiris! Henceforth, compared with Rufinus thou,
Cinna, shalt ' be loving, and thou, Spartacus, a
sluggard.
</p>
         <p>All were a prey to terror, for men knew not where
next his hidden hatred would break forth, they
sob in silence for the tears they dare not shed and
fear to show their indignation. Yet is not the spirit
of great-hearted Stilicho broken by this same fear.
</p>
         <p>Alone amid the general calamity he took arms
against this monster of greed and his devouring
maw, though not borne on the swift course of any
wingèd steed nor aided by Pegasus' reins. In him
all found the quiet they longed for, he was their
one defence in danger, their shield out-held against
the fierce foe, the exile's sanctuary, standard confronting
the madness of Rufinus, fortress for the
protection of the good.
</p>
         <p>Thus far Rufinus advanced his threats and stayed;
then fell back in coward flight: even as a torrent
swollen with winter rains rolls down great stones
in its course, overwhelms woods, tears away bridges,
yet is broken by a jutting rock, and, seeking a
way through, foams and thunders about the cliff
with shattered waves.
</p>
         <p>How can I praise thee worthily, thou who sus-
<pb id="v.1.p.47"/>
tainedst with thy shoulders the tottering world in
its threatened fall? The gods gave thee to us
as they show a welcome star to frightened mariners
whose weary bark is buffeted with storms of wind
and wave and drifts with blind course now that
her steersman is beaten. Perseus, descendant of
Inachus, is said to have overcome Neptune's monsters
in the Red Sea, but he was helped by his wings;
no wing bore thee aloft: Perseus was armed with
the Gorgons' head that turneth all to stone; the
snaky locks of Medusa protected not thee. His
motive was but the love of a chained girl, thine the
salvation of Rome. The days of old are surpassed;
let them keep silence and cease to compare Hercules'
labours with thine. 'Twas but one wood that
sheltered the lion of Cleonae, the savage boar's
tusks laid waste a single Arcadian vale, and thou,
rebel Antaeus, holding thy mother earth in thine
embrace, didst no hurt beyond the borders of Africa.
</p>
         <p>Crete alone re-echoed to the bellowings of the fire-
breathing bull, and the green hydra beleaguered no
more than Lerna's lake. But this monster Rufinus
terrified not one lake nor one island: whatsoever
lives beneath the Roman rule, from distant Spain
to Ganges' stream, was in fear of him. Neither
triple Geryon nor Hell's fierce janitor can vie with
him nor could the conjoined terrors of powerful
Hydra, ravenous Scylla, and fiery Chimaera.
</p>
         <p>Long hung the contest in suspense, but the struggle
betwixt vice and virtue was ill-matched in character.
</p>
         <p>Rufinus threatens slaughter, thou stayest his hand;
he robs the rich, thou givest back to the poor; he
overthrows, thou restorest; he sets wars afoot, thou
winnest them. As a pestilence, growing from day
<pb id="v.1.p.49"/>
to day by reason of the infected air, fastens first
upon the bodies of animals but soon sweeps away
peoples and cities, and when the winds blow hot
spreads its hellish poison to the polluted streams,
so the ambitious rebel marks down no private prey,
but hurls his eager threats at kings, and seeks to
destroy Rome's army and overthrow her might.
</p>
         <p>Now he stirs up the Getae1 and the tribes on
Danube's banks, allies himself with Scythia and
exposes what few his cruelties have spared to the
sword of the enemy. There march against us a
mixed horde of Sarmatians and Dacians, the
Massagetes who cruelly wound their horses that
they may drink their blood, the Alans who break the
ice and drink the waters of Maeotis' lake, and the
Geloni who tattoo their limbs: these form Rufinus'
army. And he brooks not their defeat; he
frames delays and postpones the fitting season for
battle. For when thy right hand, Stilicho, had
scattered the Getic bands and avenged the death
of thy brother general, when one section of Rufmus'
army was thus weakened and made an easy prey,
then that foul traitor, that conspirator with the
Getae, tricked the emperor and put off the instant
day of battle, meaning to ally himself with the
Huns, who, as he knew, would fight and quickly join the enemies of Rome.2
These Huns are a tribe who live on the extreme
eastern borders of Scythia, beyond frozen Tanais;
most infamous of all the children of the north.
</p>
         <p>Hideous to look upon are their faces and loathsome
their bodies, but indefatigable is their spirit. The
chase supplies their food; bread they will not eat.
</p>
         <p>They love to slash their faces and hold it a
<pb id="v.1.p.51"/>
righteous act to swear by their murdered parents.
</p>
         <p>Their double nature fitted not better the twi-formed
Centaurs to the horses that were parts of them.
</p>
         <p>Disorderly, but of incredible swiftness, they often
return to the fight when little expected.
</p>
         <p>Fearless, however, against such forces, thou,
Stilicho, approachest the waters of foaming Hebrus
and thus prayest ere the trumpets sound and
the fight begins: <q direct="unspecified"> Mars, whether thou reclinest
on cloud-capped Haemus, or frost- white Rhodope
holdeth thee, or Athos, severed to give passage to
the Persian fleet, or Pangaeus, gloomy with dark
holm-oaks, gird thyself at my side and defend
thine own land of Thrace. If victory smile on us,
thy meed shall be an oak stump adorned with spoils.</q>
         </p>
         <p>The Father heard his prayer and rose from the
snowy peaks of Haemus shouting commands to his
speedy servants: <q direct="unspecified"> Bellona, bring my helmet; fasten
me. Panic, the wheels upon my chariot; harness
my swift horses, Fear. Hasten: speed on your
work. See, my Stilicho makes him ready for war;
Stilicho whose habit it is to load me with rich trophies
and hang upon the oak the plumed helmets of his
enemies. For us together the trumpets ever sound
the call to battle; yoking my chariot I follow wheresoever
he pitch his camp.</q> So spake he and leapt
upon the plain, and on this side Stilicho scattered the
enemy bands in broadcast flight and on that Mars;
alike the twain in accoutrement and stature. The
helmets of either tower with bristling crests, their
breastplates flash as they speed along and their
spears take their fill of widely dealt wounds.
</p>
         <p>Meanwhile Megaera, more eager now she has
got her way, and revelling in this widespread
<pb id="v.1.p.53"/>
calamity, comes upon Justice sad at heart in her
palace, and thus provokes her with horrid utterance:
<q direct="unspecified"> Is this that old reign of peace; this the return of
that golden age thou fondly hopedst had come to
pass? Is our power gone, and no place now left
for the Furies? Turn thine eyes this way. See
how many cities the barbarians' fires have laid low,
how vast a slaughter, how much blood Rufinus
hath procured for me, and on what widespread
death my serpents gorge themselves. Leave thou
the world of men; that lot is mine. Mount to the
stars, return to that well-known tract of Autumn
sky where the Standard-bearer dips towards the
south. The space next to the summer constellation
of the Lion, the neighbourhood of the winter
Balance has long been empty. And would I could
now follow thee through the dome of heaven.</q>
         </p>
         <p>The goddess made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Thou shalt rage no
further, mad that thou art. Now shall thy creature
receive his due, the destined avenger hangs over
him, and he who now wearies land and the very
sky shall die, though no handful of dust shall cover
his corpse. Soon shall come Honorius, promised of
old to this fortunate age, brave as his father Theodosius,
brilliant as his brother Arcadius; he shall
subdue the Medes and overthrow the Indians with
his spear. Kings shall pass under his yoke, frozen
Phasis shall bear his horses' hooves, and Araxes
submit perforce to be bridged by him. Then too
shalt thou be bound with heavy chains of iron and
cast out from the light of day and imprisoned in
the nethermost pit, thy snaky locks overcome and
shorn from thy head. Then the world shall be owned
by all in common, no field marked off from another
<pb id="v.1.p.55"/>
by any dividing boundary, no furrow cleft with
bended ploughshare; for the husbandman shall
rejoice in com that springs untended. Oak groves
shall drip with honey, streams of wine well up on
every side, lakes of oil abound. No price shall be
asked for fleeces dyed scarlet, but of themselves
shall the flocks grow red to the astonishment of the
shepherd, and in every sea the green seaweed will
laugh with flashing jewels.</q>
            <pb id="v.1.p.57"/>
         </p>
                  </div2>
               </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.3" TEIform="pb"/>
               <div1 type="book" n="2" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                        <div2 type="poem" n="praef" id="poem.4" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>

Return, ye Muses, and throw open rescued
Helicon; now again may your company gather
there. Nowhere now in Italy does the hostile trumpet
forbid song with its viler bray. Do thou too, Delian
Apollo, now that Delphi is safe and fear has been
dispelled, wreath thy avenger's head with flowers.
</p>
         <p>No savage foe sets profane lips to Castalia's spring
or those prophetic streams. Alpheus'1 flood ran
all his length red with slaughter and the waves
bore the bloody marks of war across the Sicilian
sea; whereby Arethusa, though herself not present,
recognized the triumphs freshly won and knew of
the slaughter of the Getae, to which that blood bore witness.
</p>
         <p>Let peace, Stilicho, succeed these age-long labours
and ease thine heart by graciously listening to my
song. Think it no shame to interrupt thy long toil
and to consecrate a few moments to the Muses. Even
unwearying Mars is said to have stretched his tired
limbs on the snowy Thracian plain when at last
the battle was ended, and, unmindful of his wonted
fierceness, to have laid aside his spear in gentler
mood, soothing his ear with the Muses' melody.
<pb id="v.1.p.."/>
         </p>
                        </div2>
                        <div2 type="poem" id="poem.5" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <pb id="v.1.p.59" TEIform="pb"/>
         <p>

After the subjugation of the Alpine tribes and
the salvation of the kingdoms of Italy the heavens
welcomed the Emperor Theodosius 1 to the place of
honour due to his worth, and so shone the brighter
by the addition of another star. Then was the power
of Rome entrusted to thy care, Stilicho; in thy hands
was placed the governance of the world. The
brothers' twin majesty and the armies of either
royal court were given into thy charge. But Rufinus
(for cruelty and crime brook not peace, and a tainted
mouth will not forgo its draughts of blood), Rufinus,
I say, began once more to inflame the world with
wicked wars and to disturb peace with accustomed
sedition. Thus to himself: <q direct="unspecified"> How shall I assure
my slender hopes of survival? By what means beat
back the rising storm? On all sides are hate and
the threat of arms. What am I to do? No help
can I find in soldier's weapon or emperor's favour.
Instant dangers ring me round and a gleaming sword
hangs above my head. What is left but to plunge
the world into fresh troubles and draw down innocent
peoples in my ruin? Gladly will I perish if the world
does too; general destruction shall console me for
<pb id="v.1.p.61"/>
mine own death, nor will I die (for I am no coward)
till I have accomplished this. I will not lay down
my power before my life.</q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake he, and as if Aeolus unchained the winds
so he, breaking their bonds, let loose the nations,
clearing the way for war; and, that no land should
be free therefrom, apportioned ruin throughout
the world, parcelling out destruction. Some pour
across the frozen surface of swift-flowing Danube
and break with the chariot wheel what erstwhile
knew but the oar; others invade the wealthy East,
led through the Caspian Gates and over the Armenian
snows by a newly-discovered pass. The fields of
Cappadocia reek with slaughter; Argaeus, father
of swift horses, is laid waste. Halys' deep waters
run red and the Cilician cannot defend himself
in his precipitous mountains. The pleasant plains of
Syria are devastated, and the enemy's cavalry
thunders along the banks of Orontes, home hitherto
of the dance and of a happy people's song. Hence
comes mourning to Asia, while Europe is left to be
the sport and prey of Getic hordes even to the borders
of fertile Dalmatia. All that tract of land lying
between the stormy Euxine and the Adriatic is laid
waste and plundered, no inhabitants dwell there;
'tis like torrid Africa whose sun-scorched plains never
grow kindlier through human tillage. Thessaly
is afire; Pelion silent, his shepherds put to flight;
flames bring destruction on Macedonia's crops.
</p>
         <p>For Pannonia's plain, the Thracians' helpless cities,
the fields of Mysia were ruined but now none wept;
year by year came the invader, unsheltered was the
countryside from havoc and custom had robbed
suffering of its sting. Alas, in how swift ruin perish
<pb id="v.1.p.63"/>
even the greatest things! An empire won and kept
at the expense of so much bloodshed, born from
the toils of countless leaders, knit together through
so many years by Roman hands, one coward traitor
overthrew in the twinkling of an eye.
</p>
         <p>That city,1 too, called of men the rival of great
Rome, that looks across to Chalcedon's strand, is
stricken now with terror at no neighbouring war;
nearer home it observes the flash of torches, the
trumpet's call, and its own roofs the target for an
enemy's artillery. Some guard the walls with
watchful outposts, others hasten to fortify the
harbour with a chain of ships. But fierce Rufinus
is full of joy in the leaguered city and exults in its
misfortunes, gazing at the awful spectacle of the
surrounding country from the summit of a lofty
tower. He watches the procession of women in
chains, sees one poor half-dead wretch drowned in
the water hard by, another, stricken as he fled,
sink down beneath the sudden wound, another
breathe out his life at the tower's very gates; he
rejoices that no respect is shown to grey hairs and that
mother's breasts are drenched with their children's
blood. Great is his pleasure thereat; from time to
time he laughs and knows but one regret — that
it is not his own hand that strikes. He sees the
whole countryside (except for his own lands) ablaze,
and has joy of his great wickedness, making no secret
of the fact that the city's foes are his friends. It is
his boast, moreover, that to him alone the enemy
camp opened its gates, and that there was allowed
right of parley between them. Whene'er he issued
forth to arrange some wondrous truce his companions
thronged him round and an armed band of depen-
<pb id="v.1.p.65"/>
dents danced attendance on a civilian's standards.
</p>
         <p>Rufinus himself in their midst drapes tawny skins of
beasts about his breast (thorough in his barbarity),
and uses harness and huge quivers and twanging bows
like those of the Getae — his dress openly showing the
temper of his mind. One who drives a consul's
chariot and enjoys a consul's powers has no shame to
adopt the manners and dress of barbarians; Roman
law, obliged to change her noble garment, mourns
her slavery to a skin-clad judge.
</p>
         <p>What looks then on men's faces! What furtive
murmurs! For, poor wretches, they could not even
weep nor, without risk, ease their grief in converse.
<q direct="unspecified"> How long shall we bear this deadly yoke? What
end shall there ever be to our hard lot? Who will free
us from this death-fraught anarchy, this day of tears?
On this side the barbarian hems us in, on that
Rufinus oppresses us; land and sea are alike denied
us. A pestilence stalks through the country: yes,
but a deadlier terror haunts our houses. Stilicho,
delay no more but succour thy dying land; of a
truth here are thy children, here thy home, here
were taken those first auspices for thy marriage,
so blessed with children, here the palace was illumined
with the torches of happy wedlock. Nay,
come even though alone, thou for whom we long;
wars will perish at thy sight and the ravening
monster's rage subside.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Such were the tempests that vexed the turbulent
East. But so soon as ever winter had given place
to the winds of spring and the hills began to lose
their covering of snow, Stilicho, leaving the fields of
Italy in peace and safety, set in motion his two armies
and hastened to the lands of the sunrise, combining
<pb id="v.1.p.67"/>
the so different squadrons of Gaul and of the East.
</p>
         <p>Never before did there meet together under one command
such numerous bands, never in one army such a
babel of tongues. Here were curly-haired Armenian
cavalry, their green cloaks fastened with a loose knot,
fierce Gauls with golden locks accompanied them,
some from the banks of the swift-flowing Rhone, or
the more sluggish Saône, some whose infant bodies
Rhine's flood had laved, or who had been washed by
the waves of the Garonne that flow more rapidly
towards, than from, their source, whenever they are
driven back by Ocean's full tide. One common
purpose inspires them all; grudges lately harboured
are laid aside; the vanquished feels no hate, the
victor shows no pride. And despite of present unrest,
of the trumpet's late challenge to civil strife, and of
warlike rage still aglow, yet were all at one in their
support of their great leader. So it is said that the
army that followed Xerxes, gathered into one from
all quarters of the world, drank up whole rivers in
their courses, obscured the sun with the rain of their
arrows, passed through mountains on board ship,
and walked the bridged sea with contemptuous foot.
</p>
         <p>Scarce had Stilicho crossed the Alps when the
barbarian hordes began to restrict their forays and
for fear of his approach gathered together in the
plain and enclosed their pasture lands within a
defensive ring. They then built an impregnable
fortification with a double moat, planted stakes two
deep at intervals along its summit and set wagons
rigged with ox-hide all round like a wall.
</p>
         <p>Panic fear seized upon Rufinus as he saw this from
afar, and his cheeks grew pale. He stood with ice-
cold face, not knowing whether to fly, to own himself
<pb id="v.1.p.69"/>
beaten and sue for mercy, or go over to an enemy
whose good faith his treachery had assured. Of
what use now were his riches, his vast stores of golden
ore, his halls upheld with red marble pillars, his sky-
towering palace? He hears of Stilicho's march and
counts the days, measuring his term of life according
to the distance of his enemy from him. He is
troubled with thoughts of coming peace and cannot
sleep, often starts up distraught from his bed and
suffers as punishment the fear of punishment. But
his fury repossesses him and, regaining his genius for
crime, he enters the sacred portal of the rich palace
and addresses Arcadius with prayers and threats:
<q direct="unspecified"> By thy brother's royal star, by the deeds of thy
divine sire and the flower of thine own age, I beg thee
deliver me from the edge of the sword; let me
escape the cruel threatenings of Stilicho. All Gaul
is sworn to my destruction. Tethys' extreme coasts,
the wandering tribes beyond the farthest Britons
are stirred up against me. Am I thought fit prey for
all those armies? Are so many standards advanced
against a solitary man? Whence comes this lust
for blood? Stilicho lays claim to either hemisphere
and will brook no equal. The world forsooth must
lie at his feet. Italy is his kingdom, Libya his
dominion, Spain and Gaul his empire. The sun's
path circumscribes him not, no nor the whole
universe. All the wealth collected here by Theodosius
or received by him after the war is Stilicho's
alone, and he has small mind to restore what he has
once acquired. Is he to enjoy his gains in peace and
quietness while 'tis mine to stand a siege? Why
should he encroach on thy share? Let him leave
Illyria, send back his Eastern troops, divide the
<pb id="v.1.p.71"/>
hosts fairly between the two brothers, and do thou
not be heir to the sceptre only but to thy forces. But
if thou neglect to come to mine aid and make not
ready to prevent my death, this head of mine shall
not fall alone — by the dead and the stars I swear it.
The blood of another shall be mingled with mine.
I will not go unaccompanied to the waters of Styx nor
shall the victor be free to exult in my death.</q>
         </p>
         <p>So saying he dictates a treasonable letter and
sends therewith an emissary to bear the message
extorted from the emperor's unwilling lips.
</p>
         <p>Meanwhile Stilicho, exulting in the thought of
advancing upon the foe and of the narrow stretch
of country that separated him from the fortifications,
inflames with his words the hearts of his troops
already thirsting for battle. On the left wing are
posted the Armenians, farther to the right the
Gauls. A beholder might have seen bits covered
with warm foam, clouds of dust uprising, and on all
sides waving banners bearing the device of a scarlet
dragon; the very air seemed to teem with these
fierce flying monsters. The glint of steel fills all
Thessaly and the cave of the wise Centaur; the
river whose banks supported Achilles' baby footsteps
and the forests of Oeta are agleam with arms, snowy
Ossa re-echoes to the sound and Olympus smitten
therewith sends it back twofold. Hearts beat high
with a courage that is lavish of life. Neither precipice
nor deep river could check their advance: their headlong
speed would have overthrown all barriers.
</p>
         <p>If the two armies had then joined battle in this
temper ruined Greece would not have witnessed such
disaster as she did, the cities of the Peloponnese would
still have been flourishing untouched by the hand
<pb id="v.1.p.73"/>
of war, Arcadia and Sparta's citadel would have
remained unravaged. Burning Corinth would not
have heated the waves of her two seas, nor would
cruel chains have led in captivity the matrons of
Athens. That day might have set an end to our
disasters and destroyed the seeds of future calamities.
</p>
         <p>For shame, envious Fortune, of what a triumph didst
thou rob us! The kingly mandate came to Stilicho
in arms amid the cavalry and the trumpets' din.
</p>
         <p>He stood amazed; anger and great grief o'erwhelm
the hero and he wonders that such power for ill is
allowed a coward. His wavering mind ponders the
uncertain issue: shall he continue his advance or fail
his brave beginnings? He longs to stem Illyria's
ruin but fears to disobey orders. Loyalty annuls the
prickings-on of valour. The public good urges him
one way, fear of the emperor's displeasure another.
</p>
         <p>At length in his distress he raises his hands to
heaven and speaks from deep within his heart: <q direct="unspecified"> Ye
gods not yet glutted with Rome's destruction, if
ye will that our empire be utterly uprooted, if ye
have resolved to blot out all the centuries with
one blow, if ye repent you of the race of man, then
let the sea's unrestrained fury burst forth upon the
land or let Phaethon, deviating from his ordained
course, drive his straying chariot at random. Shall
Rufinus be your tool? 'Twere shame that such an
one should be the author of the world's destruction.
O the grief of it! recalled in mid fight; forced to lay
down the swords we have drawn! Cities marked out
for the flames, walls doomed to destruction, I call
you to witness: see, I retire; I leave the unhappy
world to its fate. Turn your banners, captains; to
your homes, soldiers of the east. Needs must we obey.
<pb id="v.1.p.75"/>
Silence, ye clarions; men, forbear to shoot. The
foe is at hand, spare him; 'tis Rufinus' command.</q>
         </p>
         <p>At these words an unanimous roar went up from
all the companies. With less din are the cliffs of
Ceraunia buffeted by the Italian sea or the thunders
evoked from the western winds' wet storm-clouds.
</p>
         <p>They will not separate, and demand the battle of which
they have been defrauded. East and west claim the
leadership of that illustrious chief. It is a contest
of affection; insubordination that none can blame
threatens to sap the loyalty of both armies who thus
utter their common complaint: <q direct="unspecified">Who is it robs us
of our drawn swords? Who strikes the lance from our
hand and bids us unstring the bent bow? Who
dares dictate to an army under arms? Valour once
roused knows no abatement. Spears thirsting for
barbarian blood cast themselves from out our hands;
our headlong blades force our vengeful arms to follow
them; our very scabbards refuse to sheath an
unblooded sword. I will not bear it. Shall the Getae
ever profit by our dissension? Behold once more the
shadow of civil war. Why dost thou seek to separate
armies whose blood is one, standards of immemorial
alliance? We are a body one and indivisible. Thee
will we follow whithersoever thou goest; thee will
we accompany even as far as Thule lying icebound
beneath the pole-star, or to the burning sands of
Libya. Should thy path be by the waters of Ind,
or the bays of the Red Sea,1 I would go drink
Hydaspes' golden stream. Shouldst thou bid me
fare south and search out the hidden sources of the
stripling Nile, I would leave behind me the world
<pb id="v.1.p.77"/>
I know. Wheresoever Stilicho plants his tent there
is my fatherland.</q>
         </p>
         <p>But Stilicho said them nay: <q direct="unspecified">Cease, I beg you,</q>
he cried, <q direct="unspecified">stay your eager hands. Suffer to disperse
the mountain of hatred that towers over me. I hold
not victory so dear that I would fain seem to win it
for myself. Loyal gentlemen, so long my fellow-
soldiers, get you gone.</q> He said no more but turned
away, as a lion loath to retire makes off with empty
maw when the serried spears and the burning
branches in the hands of the shepherd band drive
him back and he droops his mane and closes his
downcast eyes and with a disappointed roar pushes
his way through the trembling forest.
</p>
         <p>When the armies saw that they had been parted
and left, they groaned deeply and bedewed their
helmets with a stream of tears. The sighs that
refused egress to their smothered words shook the
strong fastenings of their breastplates. <q direct="unspecified">We are
betrayed,</q> they cried, <q direct="unspecified">and forbidden to follow him
we love so well. Dost thou despise, matchless chief,
thine own right hands which have so often won thee
the victory? Are we thus vile? Is the Western sky
to be the happier which has won the right to enjoy
thy rule? What boots it to return to our country,
to see once more our children dear after so long an
absence, to live again in the home we love? Without
thee is no joy. Now must I face the tyrant's dread
wrath; mayhap e'en now he is making ready against
me some wicked snare and will make me a slave to
the foul Huns or restless Alans. Yet is not my
strength altogether perished nor so complete my
powerlessness to wield the sword. Rest thou beneath
the sun's westering course, Stilicho, thou art still
<pb id="v.1.p.79"/>
ever our general, and though we be not together
thou shalt still know our loyalty. Long has a victim
been owed thee; he shall be sacrificed and thou
placated by an immolation promised of old.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Sad at heart the army left Thessaly, reached the
borders of Macedon, and arrived before the walls
of Thessalonica. Indignation deep hid in their
hearts prepares the silent wrath of revenge. They
look for a place where they may wreak their
vengeance and a moment propitious for the blow,
and of all that vast army not one is found to divulge
with incautious speech his heart's intent. What
succeeding age and time but will marvel that a plot
so widespread could be kept hid, a deed of such
vast import concealed; that the ardour of their
minds was not rendered of no avail by the chance
word of a soldier on the march or a drunkard's
babbling? But discretion ruled all alike and the
people's secret was kept. The army crossed the
Hebrus, left Rhodope behind, and struck across the
uplands of Thrace until it came to the city called after Hercules.1
When Rufinus learned that Stilicho had retired
and that his troops were approaching he held his
head high in triumph, believing everything safe, and,
anxious to seize the power, inflamed his traitorous
minions with this speech: <q direct="unspecified">We have conquered;
have driven off our enemy; empire is within my
grasp, nor have we anything to fear from the foe.
Will one who dared not approach me when I stood
alone defeat me now that I am strengthened by
the addition of so great a force? Who could stand
against him armed whom unarmed he could not
conquer? Plot my destruction in exile, friend
<pb id="v.1.p.81"/>
Stilicho. What harm can that do so long as a
vast stretch of country divide us and Nereus' waves
thunder between? Thou shalt have no chance of
crossing the rocky Alps while I live. Transfix me
from thence with thine arrows, if thou canst. Seek
in thy fury a sword that from Italy shall reach my
city's walls. Does not the experience and the
example of those who have tried before deter thee?
Who that has dared approach can boast escape from
my hands? I have driven thee from the centre of
the civilized world and at the same time deprived
thee of thy great army. Now, my friends, is come
the time for feasting and making ready bountiful
gifts and bestowing gold upon these new legions.
To-morrow's light dawns prosperously for my purpose.
Needs must the emperor will what he would not
and bid a portion of his empire to be given to
me. Mine alone be the happy fortune to rise above
a private estate and yet escape the charge of
tyranny.</q>
         </p>
         <p>To such words they shout acclaim — that vile
band of traitors, waxed fat on plunder, whom one
principle makes fellows with Rufinus, the holding
nothing unlawful, and whose bond of friendship is
to guard guilt in silence. Straightway they joyfully
promise themselves foreign wives and all to no
purpose forecast the booty they will win and the
cities they will sack.
</p>
         <p>Night had begun to soothe human toils in her
deep bosom and sleep had spread his black wings
when Rufinus, whose mind had long been a prey to
anxiety, sank into a troubled slumber. Scarce had
quiet fastened on his heart when, lo, he sees flit
before his eyes the dread ghosts of those whom he
<pb id="v.1.p.83"/>
had killed. Of them one, more distinct than the rest,
seemed thus to address him: <q direct="unspecified">Up from thy couch!
why schemes thine anxious mind further? This
coming day shall bring thee rest and end thy toils.
High above the people shalt thou be raised, and happy
crowds shall carry thee in their arms.</q> Such was
the ambiguous prophecy of the ghost, but Rufinus
observed not the hidden omen and saw not it foretold
the elevation of his severed head upon a spear.
</p>
         <p>Now Lucifer touched the peak of Haemus with
his rays and Titan urged his hastening wheel quicker
than his wont, so soon to see at last the death of
Rufinus. Rufinus himself leapt from his bed and
bade make ready the capacious palace with regal
splendour in preparation for the feast; the gold to
be given in largesse he ordered to be stamped with
his own fateful image. Himself went to welcome the
troops returning from the battle in kingly pride and
arrogance above a prince's. Sure now of empire
he wore a woman's raiment about his neck; as
though the purple already clothed his limbs and the
jewelled crown blazed upon his brow.
</p>
         <p>Hard by a crowded quarter of the city of Constantinople,
towards the south, there lies a plain.
</p>
         <p>The rest is surrounded by the sea which here allows
itself to be parted by a narrow way. Here the
avenging army, bright with the panoply of the war
god, disposes its squadrons. On the left stands the
infantry. Over against them the cavalry seek to
restrain their eager steeds by holding tight the
reins. Here nod the savage waving plumes whose
wearers rejoice to shake the flashing colours of
their shoulder-armour; for steel clothes them
on and gives them their shape; the limbs within
<pb id="v.1.p.85"/>
give life to the armour's pliant scales so artfully
conjoined, and strike terror into the beholder. 'Tis
as though iron statues moved and men lived cast
from that same metal. The horses are armed in
the same way; their heads are encased in threatening
iron, their forequarters move beneath steel
plates protecting them from wounds; each stands
alone, a pleasure yet a dread to behold, beautiful,
yet terrible, and as the wind drops the particoloured dragons I sink with relaxing coils into repose.
</p>
         <p>The emperor first salutes the hallowed standards;
Rufinus follows him, speaking with that crafty voice
wherewith he deceived all, praising their devoted
arms and addressing each by name. He tells those
who have returned that their sons and fathers are
still alive. The soldiers, observing a feigned rivalry
in asking questions, begin to extend their long lines
behind his back and to join up the ends so as to
form a circle unnoticed by Rufinus. The space in
the centre grows smaller and the wings meeting with
serried shields gradually form into one lessening
circle. Even so the huntsman surrounds the grassy
glades with his widespread snares: so the spoiler
of the ocean drives to land the frightened fish,
narrowing the circuit of his nets and closing up all
possible ways of egress. All others they exclude.
</p>
         <p>In his eagerness he notes not yet that he is being
surrounded and, strongly seizing his robe, chides
the hesitating emperor: let him mount the lofty
platform and declare him sharer in his sceptre,
partaker in his dignities — when suddenly they
draw their swords and above the rest there rang
out a mighty voice: <q direct="unspecified"> Basest of the base, didst
<pb id="v.1.p.87"/>
thou hope to cast upon us the yoke of slavery?
Knewest thou not whence I return? Shall I allow
myself to be called another's servant, I who gave
laws to others and restored the reign of liberty?
Two civil wars have I quenched, twice forced the
barrier of the Alps. These many battles have taught
me to serve no tyrant.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Rufinus stood rooted to earth. There is no hope
of escape, for a forest of flashing spears hems
him in. Shut in on the right hand and on the left
he stood and gazed in wonder on the drawn blades
of the armed throng; as a beast who has lately left
his native hills, driven in exile from the wooded
mountains and condemned to the gladiatorial shows,
rushes into the arena while over against him
the gladiator, heartened by the crowd's applause
kneels and holds out his spear. The beast, alarmed
at the noise, gazes with head erect upon the rows
of seats in the amphitheatre and hears with amazement
the murmuring of the crowd.
</p>
         <p>Then one more daring than the rest drew his
sword and leapt forward from the crowd and with
fierce words and flashing eye rushed upon Rufinus
crying: <q direct="unspecified">It is the hand of Stilicho whom thou
vauntest that thou didst expel that smites thee;
his sword, which thou thoughtest far away, that
pierces thy heart.</q> So spake he and transfixed
Rufinus' side with a well-deserved thrust.
</p>
         <p>Happy the hand that first spilt such vile blood
and poured out vengeance for a world made weary.
</p>
         <p>Straightway all pierce him with their spears and
tear quivering limb from limb; one single body
warms all these weapons with its blood; shame
to him whose sword returns unstained therewith.
<pb id="v.1.p.89"/>
They stamp on that face of greed and while yet he
lives pluck out his eyes; others seize and carry off
his severed arms. One cuts off his foot, another
wrenches a shoulder from the torn sinews; one lays
bare the ribs of the cleft spine, another his liver, his
heart, his still panting lungs. There is not space
enough to satisfy their anger nor room to wreak their
hate. Scarce when his death had been accomplished
do they leave him; his body is hacked in pieces and
the fragments borne on the soldiers' spears. Thus
red with blood ran the Boeotian mountain when
the Maenads caused Pentheus' destruction or when
Latona's daughter seen by Actaeon betrayed the
huntsman, suddenly transformed into a stag, to
the fury of her Molossian hounds. Dost thou hope,
Fortune, thus to right thy wrongs? Seekest thou
to atone by this meting out of punishment for favour
ill bestowed? Dost thou with one death make
payment for ten thousand murders? Come, portion
out Rufinus' corpse among the lands he has
wronged. Give the Thracians his head; let Greece
have as her due his body. What shall be given
the rest? Give but a limb apiece, there are not
enough for the peoples he has ruined.
</p>
         <p>The citizens leave the town and hasten exulting
to the spot from every quarter, old men and girls
among them whom nor age nor sex could keep at
home. Widows whose husbands he had killed,
mothers whose children he had murdered hurry to
the joyful scene with eager steps. They are fain
to trample the torn limbs and stain their deep pressed
feet with the blood. So, too, they eagerly hurl a
shower of stones at the monstrous head, nodding
from the summit of the spear that transfixed it as it
<pb id="v.1.p.91"/>
was carried back in merited splendour to the city.
</p>
         <p>Nay his hand too, made over to their mockery, goes
a-begging for alms, and with its awful gains pays
the penalty for his greedy soul, while forced, in
mimicry of its living clutch, to draw up the fingers
by their sinews.
</p>
         <p>Put not now your trust in prosperity; learn that
the gods are inconstant and heaven untrustworthy.
</p>
         <p>That hand which sought to wield a sceptre, which a
humbled nobility stooped so often to kiss, now torn
from its wretched trunk and left long unburied
begs after death a baneful alms. Let him gaze
on this whoso carries his head high in pride of prosperity,
see trodden under foot at the cross-roads
him who built pyramids for himself and a tomb,
large as a temple, to the glory of his own ghost.
</p>
         <p>He who trusted to be clothed in Tyrian purple is
now a naked corpse and food for birds. See, he
who owns the world lies denied six foot of earth,
half covered with a sprinkling of dust, given no
grave yet given so many.
</p>
         <p>Heaven knew of his death and earth is freed of
her hated burden, now that the stars can breathe
again. His shade oppresses the rivers of Hell.
</p>
         <p>Old Aeacus shudders and Cerberus bays to stop,
in this case, the entry of a ghost. Then those shades
which he had sent to death beneath his cruel laws
flock round him and hale him away with horrid
shoutings to the tribunal of the gloomy judge: even
as bees whom a shepherd has disturbed swarm round
his head when he would rob them of their sweet
honey, and flutter their wings and put forth their
stings, making them ready for battle in the fastnesses
of their little rock, and seek to defend the
<pb id="v.1.p.93"/>
crevices of their home, their beloved pumice-stone
cave, swarming over the honeycombs therein.
</p>
         <p>There is a place where the unhallowed rivers of
Cocytus and Phlegethon mingle their dread streams
of tears and fire. Between the rivers yet nearer to
that of Phlegethon there juts a tower stiff with
solid adamant that bathes its left side in the flames;
its right hand wall extends into Cocytus' stream and
echoes the lamentation of the river of tears. Hither
come all the children of men whose life is ended;
here there abide no marks of earthly fortune;
no reverence is shown; the common beggar ousts
the king, now stripped of his empty title. Seen
afar on his lofty throne the judge Minos examines
the charges and separates the wicked from the
righteous. Those whom he sees unwilling to confess
their sins he remits to the lash of his stern brother;
for he, Rhadamanthus, is busy close at hand. When
he has closely examined the deeds of their earthly
life and all that they did therein, he suits the punishment
to their crimes and makes them undergo the
bonds of dumb animals. The spirits of the cruel
enter into bears, of the rapacious into wolves, of the
treacherous into foxes. Those, on the other hand,
who were ever sunk in sloth, sodden with wine,
given to venery, sluggish from excesses, he compelled
to enter the fat bodies of filthy swine. Was
any above measure talkative, a betrayer of secrets,
he was carried off, a fish, to live in the waters amid
his kind, that in eternal silence he might atone for
his garrulity. When for thrice a thousand years he
had forced these through countless diverse shapes,
he sends them back once more to the beginnings of
human form purged at last with Lethe's stream.
<pb id="v.1.p.95"/>
So then while he settles these suits, dread business
of that infernal court, while he examines in due order
the criminals of old, he marks afar Rufinus, scans
him with a stern scrutiny and speaks, shaking his
throne to its foundation. <q direct="unspecified"> Hither, Rufinus, scourge
of the world, bottomless sink of gold who wouldst
dare aught for money; hither conscienceless seller
of justice (that crime of crimes), faithless cause of
that northern war whose thousand slaughtered
victims now throng Hell's narrow entry and weigh
down Charon's crowded barque. Madman, why deny
what all know? The foul stains of wickedness are
branded upon thy heart, thy crimes have made
their impress on thy spirit and thy sins cannot be
hid. Right glad I am to sentence thee to every
kind of punishment. O'er thee shall hang the
threatening rock the moment of whose fall thou
knowest not. The circling wheel shall rack thee.
Thy lips the stream's waves shall flee, thirst shall
parch thee to whose chin its elusive waters mount.
The vulture shall leave his former prey and feast for
ever on thy heart. And yet all these, Rufinus,
whom the like punishments torment, how paltry
their wickedness compared with thine! Did bold
Salmoneus' thunderbolt or Tantalus' tongue ever
do like wrong or Tityos so offend with his mad
love? Join all their crimes together yet wilt thou
surpass them. What sufficient atonement can be
found for such wickedness? What to match thy
sum of crimes whose single misdeeds outmatch
all punishment? Shades, remove from this our
ghostly company that presence that disgraces it.
To have seen once is enough. Have mercy now
on our eyes, and cleanse the realm of Dis. Drive
<pb id="v.1.p.97"/>
him with whips beyond the Styx, beyond Erebus;
thrust him down into the empty pit beneath the
lightless prison of the Titans, below the depths of
Tartarus and Chaos' own realm, where He the
foundations of thickest midnight; deep hidden there
let him live while ever the vault of heaven carries
round the stars and the winds beat upon the land.</q>
            <pb id="v.1.p.99"/>
         </p>
                                 </div2>
                        </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>