<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 22</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="book">
                <head>The Disaster of Cannae</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Spring was now coming on; Hannibal
                        accordingly moved out of his winter quarters. His previous attempt to cross
                        the Apennines had been frustrated by the insupportable cold; to remain where
                        he was would have been to court danger. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The Gauls had rallied to him through the prospect of booty and spoil, but
                        when they found that instead of plundering other people's territory their
                        own had become the seat of war and had to bear the burden of furnishing
                        winter quarters for both sides, they diverted their hatred from the Romans
                        to Hannibal. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Plots against his life were
                        frequently hatched by their chiefs, and he owed his safety to their mutual
                        faithlessness, for they betrayed the plots to him in the same spirit of
                        fickleness in which they had formed them. He guarded himself from their
                        attempts by assuming different disguises, at one time wearing a different
                        dress, at another putting on false hair. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        But these constant alarms were an additional motive for his early departure
                        from his winter quarters. About the same time Cn. Servilius entered upon his
                        consulship at Rome, on the 15th of March. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        When he had laid before the senate the policy which he proposed to carry
                        out, the indignation against C. Flaminius broke out afresh. "Two consuls had
                        been elected, but as a matter of fact they only had one. What legitimate
                        authority did this man possess? What religious sanctions? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Magistrates only take these sanctions with them from
                        home, from the altars of the State, and from their private altars at home
                        after they have celebrated the Latin Festival, offered the sacrifice on the
                        Alban Mount, and duly recited the vows in the Capitol. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> These sanctions do not follow a private citizen, nor if
                        he has departed without them can he obtain them afresh in all their fulness
                        on a foreign soil." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To add to the general feeling of
                        apprehension, information was received of portents having occurred
                        simultaneously in several places. In Sicily several of the soldiers' darts
                        were covered with flames; in Sardinia the same thing happened to the staff
                        in the hand of an officer who was going his rounds to inspect the sentinels
                        on the wall; the shores had been lit up by numerous fires; <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> a couple of shields had sweated blood; some soldiers
                        had been struck by lightning; an eclipse of the sun had been observed; at
                        Praeneste there had been a shower of red-hot stones; at Arpi shields had
                        been seen in the sky and the sun had appeared to be fighting with the moon;
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> at Capena two moons were visible in
                        the daytime; at Caere the waters ran mingled with blood, and even the spring
                        of Hercules had bubbled up with drops of blood on the water; at Antium the
                        ears of corn which fell into the reapers' basket were blood-stained; at
                        Falerii the sky seemed to be cleft asunder as with an enormous rift and all
                        over the opening there was a blazing light; <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> the oracular tablets shrank and shrivelled without being touched and one
                            <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> had fallen out with this
                        inscription, "MARS IS SHAKING HIS SPEAR"; and at the same time the statue of
                        Mars on the Appian Way and the images of the Wolves sweated blood. Finally,
                        at Capua the sight was seen of the sky on fire and the moon falling in the
                        midst of a shower of rain. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then credence
                        was given to comparatively trifling portents, such as that certain people's
                        goats were suddenly clothed with wool, a hen turned into a cock, and a cock
                        into a hen. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> After giving the details
                        exactly as they were reported to him and bringing his informants before the
                        senate, the consul consulted the House as to what religious observances
                        ought to be proclaimed. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A decree was
                        passed that to avert the evils which these portents foreboded, sacrifices
                        should be offered, the victims to be both full-grown animals and sucklings,
                        and also that special intercessions should be made at all the shrines for
                        three days. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> What other ceremonial was
                        necessary was to be carried out in accordance with the instructions of the
                        decemvirs after they had inspected the Sacred Books and ascertained the will
                        of the gods. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> On their advice it was
                        decreed that the first votive offering should be made to Jupiter in the
                        shape of a golden thunderbolt weighing fifty pounds, gifts of silver to Juno
                        and Minerva, and <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> sacrifices of
                        full-grown victims to Queen Juno on the Aventine and Juno Sospita at
                        Lanuvium, whilst the matrons were to contribute according to their means and
                        bear their gift to Queen Juno on the Aventine. A lectisternium was to be
                        held, and even the freedwomen were to contribute what they could for a gift
                        to the temple of Feronia. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> When these
                        instructions had been carried out the decemvirs sacrificed full-grown
                        victims in the forum at Ardea, and finally in the middle of December there
                        was a sacrifice at the Temple of Saturn, a lectisternium was ordered (the
                        senators prepared the couch), and a public banquet. <milestone n="20"
                            unit="section"/> For a day and a night the cry of the Saturnalia
                        resounded through the City, and the people were ordered to make that day a
                        festival and observe it as such for ever. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the consul was occupied in these
                        propitiatory ceremonies and also in the enrolment of troops, information
                        reached Hannibal that Flaminius had arrived at Arretium, and he at once
                        broke up his winter quarters. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There were
                        two routes into Etruria, both of which were pointed out to Hannibal; one was
                        considerably longer than the other but a much better road, the shorter
                        route, which he decided to take, passed through the marshes of the Arno,
                        which was at the time in higher flood than usual. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He ordered the Spaniards and Africans, the main
                        strength of his veteran army, to lead, and they were to take their own
                        baggage with them, so that, in case of a halt, they might have the necessary
                        supplies; the Gauls were to follow so as to form the centre of the column;
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the cavalry were to march last, and
                        Mago and his Numidian light horse were to close up the column, mainly to
                        keep the Gauls up to the mark in case they fell out or came to a halt
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> through the fatigue and exertion of
                        so long a march, for as a nation they were unable to stand that kind of
                        thing. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Those in front followed wherever
                        the guides led the way, through the deep and almost bottomless pools of
                        water, and though almost sucked in by the mud through which they were
                        half-wading, half-swimming, still kept their ranks. The Gauls could neither
                        recover themselves when they slipped nor when once down had they the
                        strength to struggle out of the pools; depressed and hopeless they had no
                        spirits left to keep up their bodily powers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Some dragged their worn-out limbs painfully along, others gave up the
                        struggle and lay dying amongst the baggage animals which were lying about in
                        all directions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> What distressed them most
                        of all was want of sleep, from which they had been suffering for four days
                        and three nights. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As everything was
                        covered with water and they had not a dry spot on which to lay their wearied
                        bodies, they piled up the baggage in the water and lay on the top, whilst
                        some snatched a few minutes' needful rest by making couches of the heaps of
                        baggage animals which were everywhere standing out of the water. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal himself, whose eyes were affected by
                        the changeable and inclement spring weather, rode upon the only surviving
                        elephant so that he might be a little higher above the water. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Owing, however, to want of sleep and the night
                        mists and the malaria from the marshes, his head became affected, and as
                        neither place nor time admitted of any proper treatment, he completely lost
                        the sight of one eye. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After losing many men and beasts under
                        these frightful .circumstances, he at last got clear of the marshes, and as
                        soon as he could find some dry ground he pitched his camp. The scouting
                        parties he had sent out reported that the Roman army was lying in the
                        neighbourhood of Arretium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His next step
                        was to investigate as carefully as he possibly could all that it was
                        material for him to know-what mood the consul was in, what designs he was
                        forming, what the character of the country and the kind of roads it
                        possessed, and what resources it offered for the obtaining of supplies.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The district was amongst the most
                        fertile in Italy; the plains of Etruria, which extend from Faesulae to
                        Arretium, are rich in corn and live stock and every kind of produce.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul's overbearing temper, which
                        had grown steadily worse since his last consulship, made him lose all proper
                        respect and reverence even for the gods, to say nothing of the majesty of
                        the senate and the laws, and this self-willed and obstinate side of his
                        character had been aggravated by the successes he had achieved both at home
                        and in the field. It was perfectly obvious that he would not seek counsel
                        from either God or man, and whatever he did would be done in an impetuous
                        and headstrong manner. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By way of making
                        him show these faults of character still more flagrantly, the Carthaginian
                        prepared to irritate and annoy him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        left the Roman camp on his left, and marched in the direction of Faesulae to
                        plunder the central districts of Etruria. Within actual view of the consul
                        he created as widespread a devastation as he possibly could, and from the
                        Roman camp they saw in the distance an extensive scene of fire and
                        .massacre. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Flaminius had no intention of keeping
                        quiet even if the enemy had done so, but now that he saw the possessions of
                        the allies of Rome plundered and pillaged almost before his very eyes, he
                        felt it to be a personal disgrace that an enemy should be roaming at will
                        through Italy and advancing to attack Rome with none to hinder him.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All the other members of the council
                        of war were in favour of a policy of safety rather than of display; they
                        urged him to wait for his colleague, that they might unite their forces and
                        act with one mind on a <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> common plan, and
                        pending his arrival they should check the wild excesses of the plundering
                        enemy with cavalry and the light-armed auxiliaries. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Enraged at these suggestions he dashed out of the
                        council and ordered the trumpets to give the signal for march and battle;
                        exclaiming at the same time: "We are to sit, I suppose, before the walls of
                        Arretium, because our country and our household gods are here. Now that
                        Hannibal has slipped through our hands, he is to ravage Italy, destroy and
                        burn everything in his way till he reaches Rome, while we are not to stir
                        from here until the senate summons C. Flaminius from Arretium as they once
                        summoned Camillus from Veii." During this outburst, he ordered the standards
                        to be pulled up with all speed and at the same time mounted his horse.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No sooner had he done so than the
                        animal stumbled and fell and threw him over its head All those who were
                        standing round were appalled by what they took to be <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> an evil omen at the beginning of a campaign, and their
                        alarm was considerably increased by a message brought to the consul that the
                        standard could not be moved though the standard-bearer had exerted his
                        utmost strength. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He turned to the
                        messenger and asked him: "Are you bringing a despatch from the senate, also,
                        forbidding me to go on with the campaign? Go, let them dig out the standard
                        if their hands are too benumbed with fear for them to pull it up." Then the
                        column began its march. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The superior
                        officers, besides being absolutely opposed to his plans, were thoroughly
                        alarmed by the double portent, but the great body of the soldiers were
                        delighted at the spirit their general had shown; they shared his confidence
                        without knowing on what slender grounds it rested. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In order still further to exasperate his
                        enemy and make him eager to avenge the injuries inflicted on the allies of
                        Rome, Hannibal laid waste with all the horrors of war the land between
                        Cortona and Lake Trasumennus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had now
                        reached a position eminently adapted for surprise tactics, where the lake
                        comes up close under the hills of Cortona. There is only a very narrow road
                        here between the hills and the lake, as though a space had been purposely
                        left far it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Further on there is a small
                        expanse of level ground flanked by hills, and it was here that Hannibal
                        pitched camp, which was only occupied by his Africans and Spaniards, he
                        himself being in command. The Balearics and the rest of the light infantry
                        he sent behind the hills; the cavalry, conveniently screened by some low
                        hills, he stationed at the mouth of the defile, so that when the Romans had
                        entered it they would be completely shut in by the cavalry, the lake, and
                        the hills. Flaminius had reached the lake at sunset. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The next morning, in a still uncertain light, he passed
                        through the defile, without sending any scouts on to feel the way, and when
                        the column began to deploy in the wider extent of level ground the only
                        enemy they saw was the one in front, the rest were concealed in their rear
                        and above their heads. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the
                        Carthaginian saw his object achieved and had his enemy shut in between the
                        lake and the hills with his forces surrounding them, he gave the signal for
                        all to make a simultaneous attack, and they charged straight down upon the
                        point nearest to them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The affair was all
                        the more sudden and unexpected to the Romans because a fog which had risen
                        from the lake was denser on the plain than on the heights; the bodies of the
                        enemy on the various hills could see each other well enough, and it was all
                        the easier for them to charge all at the same time. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The shout of battle rose round the Romans before they
                        could see clearly from whence it came, or became aware that they were
                        surrounded. Fighting began in front and flank before they could form line or
                        get their weapons ready or draw their swords. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the universal panic, the consul
                        displayed all the coolness that could be expected under the circumstances.
                        The ranks were broken by each man turning towards the discordant shouts; he
                        re-formed them as well as time and place allowed, and wherever he could be
                        seen or heard, he encouraged his men and bade them stand and fight.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "It is not by prayers or entreaties to
                        the gods that you must make your way out," he said, "but by your strength
                        and your courage. It is the sword that cuts a path through the middle of the
                        enemy, and where there is less fear there is generally less danger."
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But such was the uproar and confusion
                        that neither counsel nor command could be heard, and so far was the soldier
                        from recognising his standard or his company or his place in the rank, that
                        he had hardly sufficient presence of mind to get hold of his weapons and
                        make them available for use, and some who found them a burden rather than a
                        protection were overtaken by the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                        such a thick fog ears were of more use than eyes; the men turned their gaze
                        in every direction as they heard the groans of the wounded and the blows on
                        shield or breastplate, and the mingled shouts of triumph and cries of panic.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some who tried to fly ran into a dense
                        body of combatants and could get no further; others who were returning to
                        the fray were swept away by a rush of fugitives. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> At last, when ineffective charges had been made in
                        every direction and they found themselves completely hemmed in, by the lake
                        and the hills on either side, and by the enemy in front and rear, it became
                        clear to every man that his only hope of safety lay in his own right hand
                        and his sword. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then each began to depend
                        upon himself for guidance and encouragement, and the fighting began afresh,
                        not the orderly battle with its three divisions of principes, hastati, and
                        triarii, where the fighting line is in front of the standards and the rest
                        of the army behind, and where each soldier is in his own legion and cohort
                        and maniple. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Chance massed them together,
                        each man took his place in front or rear as his courage prompted him, and
                        such was the ardour of the combatants, so intent were they on the battle,
                        that not a single man on the field was aware of the earthquake which
                        levelled large portions of many towns in Italy, altered the course of swift
                        streams, brought the sea up into the rivers, and occasioned enormous
                        landslips amongst the mountains. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For almost three hours the fighting went
                        on; everywhere a desperate struggle was kept up, but it raged with greater
                        fierceness round the consul. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He was
                        followed by the pick of his army, and wherever he saw his men hard pressed
                        and in difficulties he at once went to their help. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Distinguished by his armour he was the object of the
                        enemy's fiercest attacks, which his comrades did their utmost to repel,
                        until an Insubrian horseman who knew the consul by sight-his name was
                        Ducarius-cried out to his countrymen, "Here is the man who slew our legions
                        and laid waste our city and our lands! I will offer him in sacrifice to the
                        shades of my foully murdered countrymen." <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Digging spurs into his horse he charged into the dense masses of the enemy,
                        and slew an armour-bearer who threw himself in the way as he galloped up
                        lance in rest, and then plunged his lance into the consul; but the triarii
                        protected the body with their shields and prevented him from despoiling it.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then began a general flight, neither
                        lake nor mountain stopped the panic-stricken fugitives, they rushed like
                        blind men over cliff and defile, men and arms tumbled pell-mell on one
                        another. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A large number, finding no avenue
                        of escape, went into the water up to their shoulders; some in their wild
                        terror even attempted to escape by swimming, an endless and hopeless task in
                        that lake. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Either their spirits gave way
                        and they were drowned, or else finding their efforts fruitless, they
                        regained with great difficulty the shallow water at the edge of the lake and
                        were butchered in all directions by the enemy's cavalry who had ridden into
                        the water. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About 6000 men who had formed
                        the head of the line of march cut their way through the enemy and cleared
                        the defile, quite unconscious of all that had been going on behind them.
                        They halted on some rising ground, and listened to the shouting below and
                        the clash of arms, but were unable, owing to the fog, to see or find out
                        what the fortunes of the fight were. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At
                        last, when the battle was over and the sun's heat had dispelled the fog,
                        mountain and plain revealed in the clear light the disastrous overthrow of
                        the Roman army and showed only too plainly that all was lost. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Fearing lest they should be seen in the distance
                        and cavalry be sent against them, they hurriedly took up their standards and
                        disappeared with all possible speed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Maharbal pursued them through the night with the whole of his mounted force,
                        and on the morrow, as starvation, in addition to all their other miseries,
                        was threatening them, they surrendered to Maharbal, on condition of being
                        allowed to depart with one garment apiece. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> This promise was kept with Punic faith by Hannibal, and he threw them all
                        into chains. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was the famous battle at Trasumennus,
                        and a disaster for Rome memorable as few others have been. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Fifteen thousand Romans were killed in action; 1000
                        fugitives were scattered all over Etruria and reached the City by divers
                        routes; 2500 of the enemy perished on the field, many in both armies
                        afterwards of their wounds. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Other authors
                        give the loss on each side as many times greater, but I refuse to indulge in
                        the idle exaggerations to which writers are <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> far too much given, and what is more, I am supported by
                        the authority of Fabius, who was living during the war. Hannibal dismissed
                        without ransom those prisoners who belonged to the allies and threw the
                        Romans into chains. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then gave orders
                        for the bodies of his own men to be picked out from the heaps of slain and
                        buried; careful search was also made for the body of Flaminius that it might
                        receive honourable interment but it was not found. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as the news of this disaster reached Rome the
                        people flocked into the Forum in a great state of panic and confusion.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Matrons were wandering about the
                        streets and asking those they met what recent disaster had been reported or
                        what news was there of the army. The throng in the Forum, as numerous as a
                        crowded Assembly, flocked towards the Comitium and the Senate-house and
                        called for the magistrates. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At last,
                        shortly before sunset, M. Pomponius, the praetor, announced, "We have been
                        defeated in a great battle." Though nothing more definite was heard from
                        him, the people, full of the reports which they had heard from one another,
                        carried back to their homes the information that the consul had been killed
                        with the greater part of his army; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> only a
                        few survived, and these were either dispersed in flight throughout Etruria
                        or had been made prisoners by the enemy. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The misfortunes which had befallen the
                        defeated army were not more numerous than the anxieties of those whose
                        relatives had served under C. Flaminius, ignorant as they were of the fate
                        of each of their friends, and not in the least knowing what to hope for or
                        what to fear. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The next day and several
                        days afterwards, a large crowd, containing more women than men, stood at the
                        gates waiting for some one of their friends or for news about them, and they
                        crowded round those they met with eager and anxious inquiries, nor was it
                        possible to get them away, especially from those they knew, until they had
                        got all the details from first to last. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Then as they came away from their informants you might see the different
                        expressions on their faces, according as each had received good or bad news,
                        and friends congratulating or consoling them as they wended their way
                        homewards. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The women were especially
                        demonstrative in their joy and in their grief. They say that one who
                        suddenly met her son at the gate safe and sound expired in his arms, whilst
                        another who had received false tidings of her son's death and was sitting as
                        a sorrowful mourner in her house, no sooner saw him returning than she died
                        from too great happiness. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> For several
                        days the praetors kept the senate in session from sunrise to sunset,
                        deliberating under what general or with what forces they could offer
                        effectual resistance to the victorious Carthaginian. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before they had formed any definite plans,
                        a fresh disaster was announced; 4000 cavalry under the command of C.
                        Centenius, the propraetor, had been sent by the consul Servilius to the
                        assistance of his colleague. When they heard of the battle at Trasumennus
                        they marched into Umbria, and here they were surrounded and captured by
                        Hannibal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The news of this occurrence
                        affected men in very different ways. Some, whose thoughts were preoccupied
                        with more serious troubles, looked upon this loss of cavalry as a light
                        matter in comparison with the previous losses; others estimated the
                        importance of the incident not by the magnitude of the loss but by its moral
                        effect. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Just as where the constitution is
                        impaired, any malady however slight is felt more than it would be in a
                        strong robust person, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> so any misfortune
                        which befell the State in its present sick and disordered condition must be
                        measured not by its actual importance but by its effect on a State already
                        exhausted and unable to bear anything which would aggravate its condition.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly the citizens took refuge
                        in a remedy which for a long time had not been made use of or required,
                        namely the appointment of a Dictator. As the consul by whom alone one could
                        be nominated was absent, and it was not easy for a messenger or a despatch
                        to be sent through Italy, overrun as it was by the arms of Carthage, and as
                        it would have been contrary to <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> all
                        precedent for the people to appoint a Dictator, the Assembly invested Q.
                        Fabius Maximus with dictatorial powers and appointed M. Minucius Rufus to
                        act as his Master of the Horse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were
                        commissioned by the senate to strengthen the walls and towers of the City
                        and place garrisons in whatever positions they thought best, and cut down
                        the bridges over the various rivers, for now it was a fight for their City
                        and their homes, since they were no longer able to defend Italy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal marched in a straight course
                        through Umbria as far as Spoletum, and after laying the country round
                        utterly waste, he commenced an attack upon the city which was repulsed with
                        heavy loss. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As a single colony was strong
                        enough to defeat his unfortunate attempt he was able to form some conjecture
                        as to the difficulties attending the capture of Rome, and consequently
                        diverted his march into the territory <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> of
                        Picenum, a district which not only abounded in every kind of produce but was
                        richly stored with property which the greedy and needy soldiers seized and
                        plundered without restraint. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He remained
                        in camp there for several days during which his soldiers recruited their
                        strength after their winter campaigns and their journey across the marshes,
                        and a battle which though ultimately successful was neither without heavy
                        loss nor easily won. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When sufficient time
                        for rest had been allowed to men who delighted much more in plundering and
                        destroying than in ease and idleness, Hannibal resumed his march and
                        devastated the districts of Praetutia and Hadria, then he treated in the
                        same way the country of the Marsi, the Marrucini, and the Peligni and the
                        part of Apulia which was nearest to him, including the cities of Arpi and
                        Luceria. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Cn. Servilius had fought some
                        insignificant actions with the Gauls and taken one small town, but when he
                        heard of his colleague's death and the destruction of his army, he was
                        alarmed for the walls of his native City, and marched straight for Rome that
                        he might not be absent at this most critical juncture. </p>
                    <p> Q. Fabius Maximus was now Dictator for the second time. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> On the very day of his entrance upon office he summoned
                        a meeting of the senate, and commenced by discussing matters of religion. He
                        made it quite clear to the senators that C. Flaminius' fault lay much more
                        in his neglect of the auspices and of his religious duties than in bad
                        generalship and foolhardiness. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The gods
                        themselves, he maintained, must be consulted as to the necessary measures to
                        avert their displeasure, and he succeeded in getting a decree passed that
                        the decemvirs should be ordered to consult the Sibylline Books, a course
                        which is only adopted when the most alarming portents have been reported.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After inspecting the Books of Fate
                        they informed the senate that the vow which had been made to Mars in view of
                        that war had not been duly discharged, and that it must be discharged afresh
                        and on a much greater scale. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Great
                        Games must be vowed to Jupiter, a temple to Venus Erycina and one to Mens; a
                        lectisternium must be held and solemn intercessions made; a Sacred Spring
                        must also be vowed. All these things must be done if the war was to be a
                        successful one and the republic remain in the same position in which it was
                        at the beginning of the war. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As Fabius
                        would be wholly occupied with the necessary arrangements for the war, the
                        senate with the full approval of the pontifical college ordered the praetor,
                        M. Aemilius, to take care that all these orders were carried out in good
                        time. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After these resolutions had been passed in
                        the senate the praetor consulted the pontifical college as to the proper
                        means of giving effect to them, and L. Cornelius Lentulus, the Pontifex
                        Maximus, decided that the very first step to take was to refer to the people
                        the question of a "Sacred Spring," as this particular form of vow could not
                        be undertaken without the order of the people. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The form of procedure was as follows: "Is it," the
                        praetor asked the Assembly, "your will and pleasure that all be done and
                        performed in manner following? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That is to
                        say, if the commonwealth of the Romans and the Quirites be preserved, as I
                        pray it may be, safe and sound through these present wars-to wit, the war
                        between Rome and Carthage and the wars with the Gauls now dwelling on the
                        hither side of the Alps-then shall the Romans and Quirites present as an
                        offering whatever the spring shall produce from their flocks and herds,
                        whether it be from swine or sheep or goats or cattle, and all that is
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> not already devoted to any other
                        deity shall be consecrated to Jupiter from such time as the senate and
                        people shall order. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whosoever shall make
                        an offering let him do it at whatsoever time and in whatsoever manner he
                        will, and howsoever he offers it, it shall be accounted to be duly offered.
                        If the animal which should have been sacrificed die, it shall be as though
                        unconsecrated, there shall be no sin. If any man shall hurt or slay a
                        consecrated thing unwittingly he shall not be held guilty. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> If a man shall have stolen any such animal, the people
                        shall not bear the guilt, nor he from whom it was stolen. If a man offer his
                        sacrifice unwittingly on a forbidden day, it shall be accounted to be duly
                        offered. Whether he do so by night or day, whether he be slave or freeman,
                        it shall be accounted to be duly offered. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        If any sacrifice be offered before the senate and people have ordered that
                        it shall be done, the people shall be free and absolved from all guilt
                        therefrom." <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To the same end the Great
                        Games were vowed at a cost of 333,333 1/3 ases, and in addition 300 oxen to
                        Jupiter, and white oxen and the other customary victims to a number of
                        deities. When the vows had been duly pronounced a litany of intercession was
                        ordered, and not only the population of the City but the people from the
                        country districts, whose private interests were being affected by the public
                        distress, went in procession with their wives and children. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Then a lectisternium was held for three days under the
                        supervision of the ten keepers of the Sacred Books. Six couches were
                        publicly exhibited; one for Jupiter and Juno, another for Neptune and
                        Minerva, a third for Mars and Venus, a fourth for Apollo and Diana, a fifth
                        for Vulcan and Vesta, and the sixth for Mercury and Ceres. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> This was followed by the vowing of temples. Q. Fabius
                        Maximus, as Dictator, vowed the temple to Venus Erycina, because it was laid
                        down in the Books of Fate that this vow should be made by the man who
                        possessed the supreme authority in the State. T. Otacilius, the praetor,
                        vowed the temple to Mens. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the various obligations towards the
                        gods had thus been discharged, the Dictator referred to the senate the
                        question of the policy to be adopted with regard to the war, with what
                        legions and how many the senators thought he ought to meet their victorious
                        enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They decreed that he should take
                        over the army from Cneius Servilius, and further that he should enrol from
                        amongst the citizens and the allies as many cavalry and infantry as he
                        considered requisite; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> all else was left to
                        his discretion to take such steps as he thought desirable in the interests
                        of the republic. Fabius said that he would add two legions to the army which
                        Servilius commanded; these were raised by the Master of the Horse and he
                        fixed a day for their assembling at Tibur. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        A proclamation was also issued that those who were living in towns and
                        strongholds that were not sufficiently fortified should remove into places
                        of safety, and that all the population settled in the districts through
                        which Hannibal was likely to march should abandon their farms, after first
                        burning their houses and destroying their produce, so that he might not have
                        any supplies to fall back upon. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then
                        marched along the Flaminian road to meet the consul. As soon as he caught
                        sight of the army in the neighbourhood of Ocriculum near the Tiber, and the
                        consul riding forward with some cavalry to meet him, he sent an officer to
                        tell him that he was to come to the Dictator without his lictors. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> He did so, and the way they met produced a
                        profound sense of the majesty of the dictatorship amongst both citizens and
                        allies, who had almost by this time forgotten that greatest of all offices.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Shortly afterwards a despatch was
                        handed in from the City stating that some transports which were carrying
                        supplies for the army in Spain had been captured by the Carthaginian fleet
                        near the port of Cosa. The consul was thereupon ordered to man the ships
                        which were lying off Rome or at Ostia with full complements of seamen and
                        soldiers, and sail in pursuit of the hostile fleet and protect the coast of
                        Italy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A large force was raised in Rome,
                        even freedmen who had children and were of the military age had been sworn
                        in. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Out of these city troops, all under
                        thirty-five years of age were placed on board the ships, the rest were left
                        to garrison the City. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Dictator took over the consul's army
                        from Fulvius Flaccus, the second in command, and marched through Sabine
                        territory to Tibur, where he had ordered the newly raised force to assemble
                        by the appointed day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From there he
                        advanced to Praeneste, and taking a cross-country route, came out on the
                        Latin road. From this point he proceeded towards the enemy, showing the
                        utmost care in reconnoitring all the various routes, and determined not to
                        take any risks anywhere, except so far as necessity should compel him.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The first day he pitched his camp in
                        view of the enemy not far from Arpi; the Carthaginian lost no time in
                        marching out his men in battle order to give him the chance of fighting.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when he saw that the enemy kept
                        perfectly quiet and that there were no signs of excitement in their camp, he
                        tauntingly remarked that the spirits of the Romans, those sons of Mars, were
                        broken at last, the war was at an end, and they had openly foregone all
                        claim to valour and renown. He then returned into camp. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But he was really in a very anxious state of mind, for
                        he saw that he would have to do with a very different type of commander from
                        Flaminius or Sempronius; the Romans had been taught by their defeats and had
                        at last found a general who was a match for him. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was the wariness not the impetuosity of the Dictator
                        that was the immediate cause of his alarm; he had not yet tested his
                        inflexible resolution. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He began to harass
                        and provoke him by frequently shifting his camp and ravaging the fields of
                        the allies of Rome before his very eyes. Sometimes he would march rapidly
                        out of sight and then in some turn of the road take up a concealed position
                        in the hope of entrapping him, should he come down to level ground.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Fabius kept on high ground, at a
                        moderate distance from the enemy, so that he never lost sight of him and
                        never closed with him. Unless they were employed on necessary duty, the
                        soldiers were confined to camp. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they
                        went in quest of wood or forage they went in large bodies and only within
                        prescribed limits. A force of cavalry and light infantry told off in
                        readiness against sudden alarms, made everything safe for his own soldiers
                        and dangerous for the scattered foragers of the enemy. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He refused to stake everything on a general engagement,
                        whilst slight encounters, fought on safe ground with a retreat close at
                        hand, encouraged his men, who had been demoralised by their previous
                        defeats, and made them less dissatisfied with their own courage and
                        fortunes. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But his sound and common-sense
                        tactics were not more distasteful to Hannibal than they were to his own
                        Master of the Horse. Headstrong and impetuous in counsel and with an
                        ungovernable tongue, the only thing that prevented Minucius from making
                        shipwreck of the State was the fact that he was in a subordinate command.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At first to a few listeners,
                        afterwards openly amongst the rank and file, he abused Fabius, calling his
                        deliberation indolence and his caution cowardice, attributing to him faults
                        akin to his real virtues, and by disparaging his superior-a vile practice
                        which, through its often proving successful, is steadily on the increase-he
                        tried to exalt himself. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From the Hirpini Hannibal went across into
                        Samnium; he ravaged the territory of Beneventum and captured the city of
                        Telesia. He did his best to exasperate the Roman commander, hoping that he
                        would be so incensed by the insults and sufferings inflicted on his allies
                        that he would be able to draw him into an engagement on level ground.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Amongst the thousands of allies of
                        Italian nationality who had been taken prisoners by Hannibal at Trasumennus
                        and dismissed to their homes were three Campanian knights, who had been
                        allured by bribes and promises to win over the affections of their
                        countrymen. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They sent a message to
                        Hannibal to the effect that if he would bring his army up to Campania there
                        would be a good chance of his obtaining possession of Capua. Hannibal was
                        undecided whether to trust them or not, for the enterprise was greater than
                        the authority of those who advised it; however, they at last persuaded him
                        to leave Samnium for Campania. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He warned
                        them that they must make their repeated promises good by their acts, and
                        after bidding them return to him with more of their countrymen, including
                        some of their chief men, he dismissed them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Some who were familiar with the country told him that if he marched into
                        the neighbourhood of Casinum and occupied the pass, he would prevent the
                        Romans from rendering assistance to their allies. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He accordingly ordered a guide to conduct him there.
                        But the difficulty which the Carthaginians found in pronouncing Latin names
                        led to the guide understanding Casilinum instead of Casinum. Quitting his
                        intended route, he came down through the districts of Allifae, Callifae, and
                        Cales on to the plains of Stella. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When he
                        looked round and saw the country shut in by mountains and rivers he called
                        the guide and asked him where on earth he was. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> When he was told that he would that day have his
                        quarters at Casilinum, he saw the mistake and knew that Casinum was far away
                        in quite another country. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The guide was
                        scourged and crucified in order to strike terror into the others. After
                        entrenching his camp he sent Maharbal with his cavalry to harry the
                        Falernian land. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The work of destruction
                        extended to the Baths of Sinuessa; the Numidians inflicted enormous losses,
                        but the panic and terror which they created spread even further. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> And yet, though everything was wrapped in the
                        flames of war, the allies did not allow their terrors to warp them from
                        their loyalty, simply because they were under a just and equable rule, and
                        rendered a willing obedience to their superiors-the only true bond of
                        allegiance. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hannibal had encamped at the
                        Vulturnus and the loveliest part of Italy was being reduced to ashes and the
                        smoke was rising everywhere from the burning farms, Fabius continued his
                        march along the Massic range of hills. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For
                        a few days the mutinous discontent amongst the troops had subsided, because
                        they inferred from the unusually rapid marching that Fabius was hastening to
                        save Campania from being ravaged and plundered. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> But when they reached the western extremity of the
                        range and saw the enemy burning the farmsteads of the colonists of Sinuessa
                        and those in the Falernian district, while nothing was said about giving
                        battle, the feeling of exasperation was again roused, and studiously fanned
                        by Minucius. "Are we come here" he would ask, "to enjoy the sight of our
                        murdered allies and the smoking ruins of their homes? <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Surely, if nothing else appeals to us, ought we not to
                        feel ashamed of ourselves as we see the sufferings of those whom our fathers
                        sent as colonists to Sinuessa that this frontier might be protected from the
                        Samnite foe, whose homes are being <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> burnt
                        not by our neighbours the Samnites but by a Carthaginian stranger from the
                        ends of the earth who has been allowed to come thus far simply through our
                        dilatoriness and supineness? Have we, alas! <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> so far degenerated from our fathers that we calmly look on while the very
                        country, past which they considered it an affront for a Carthaginian fleet
                        to cruise, has now been filled with Numidian and Moorish invaders?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We who only the other day in our
                        indignation at the attack on Saguntum appealed not to men alone, but to
                        treaties and to gods, now quietly watch Hannibal scaling the walls of a
                        Roman colony! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The smoke from the burning
                        farms and fields is blown into our faces, our ears are assailed by the cries
                        of our despairing allies who appeal to us for help more than they do to the
                        gods, and here are we marching an army like a herd of cattle through summer
                        pastures and mountain paths hidden from view by woods and clouds! <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> If M. Furius Camillus had chosen this method of
                        wandering over mountain heights and passes to rescue the City from the Gauls
                        which has been adopted by this new Camillus, this peerless Dictator who has
                        been found for us in our troubles, to recover Italy from Hannibal, Rome
                        would still be in the hands of the Gauls, and I very much fear that if
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> we go on dawdling in this way the
                        City which our ancestors have so often saved will only have been saved for
                        Hannibal and the Carthaginians. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But on
                        the day that the message came to Veii that Camillus had been nominated
                        Dictator by senate and people, though the Janiculum was quite high enough
                        for him to sit there and watch the enemy, like the man and true Roman that
                        he was, he came down into the plain. and in the very heart of the City where
                        the Busta Gallica are now he cut to pieces the legions of the Gauls, and the
                        next day he did the same beyond Gabii. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Why, when years and years ago we were sent under the yoke by the Samnites at
                        the Caudine Forks, was it, pray, by exploring the heights of Samnium or by
                        assailing and besieging Luceria and challenging our victorious foe that L.
                        Papirius Cursor took the yoke off Roman necks and placed it on the haughty
                        Samnite? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> What else but rapidity of action
                        gave C. Lutatius the victory? The day after he first saw the enemy he
                        surprised their fleet laden with supplies and hampered by its cargo of
                        stores and equipment. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> It is mere folly to
                        fancy that the war can be brought to an end by sitting still or making vows
                        to heaven. Your duty is to take your arms and go down and meet the enemy man
                        to man. It is by doing and daring that Rome has increased her dominion not
                        by these counsels of sloth which cowards call caution." <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Minucius said all this before a host of Roman tribunes
                        and knights, as if he were addressing the Assembly, and his daring words
                        even reached the ears of the soldiery; if they could have voted on the
                        question, there is no doubt that they would have superseded Fabius for
                        Minucius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius kept an equally careful watch upon
                        both sides, upon his own men no less than upon the enemy, and he showed that
                        his resolution was quite unshaken. He was quite aware that his inactivity
                        was making him unpopular not only in his own camp, but even in Rome,
                        nevertheless his determination remained unchanged and he persisted in the
                        same tactics for the rest of the summer, and Hannibal abandoned all hopes of
                        the battle which he had so anxiously sought for. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> It became necessary for him to look round for a
                        suitable place to winter in, as the country in which he was, a land of
                        orchards and vineyards, was entirely planted with the luxuries rather than
                        the necessaries of life, and furnished supplies only for a few months not
                        for the whole year. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal's movements
                        were reported to Fabius by his scouts. As he felt quite certain that he
                        would return by the same pass through which he had entered the district of
                        Falernum, he posted a fairly strong detachment on Mount Callicula and
                        another to garrison Casilinum. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        Vulturnus runs through the middle of this town and forms the boundary
                        between the districts of Falernum and Campania. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He led his army back over the same heights, having
                        previously sent L. Hostilius Mancinus forward with 400 cavalry to
                        reconnoitre. This man was amongst the throng of young officers who had
                        frequently listened to the fierce harangues of the Master of the Horse. At
                        first he advanced cautiously, as a scouting party should do, to get a good
                        view of the enemy from a safe position. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        But when he saw the Numidians roaming in all directions through the
                        villages, and had even surprised and killed some of them, he thought of
                        nothing but fighting, and completely forgot the Dictator's <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> instructions, which were to go forward as far
                        as he could safely and to retire before the enemy observed him. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The Numidians, attacking and retreating in small
                        bodies, drew him gradually almost up to their camp, his men and horses by
                        this time thoroughly tired. Thereupon Carthalo, the general in command of
                        the cavalry, charged at full speed, and before they came within range of
                        their javelins put the enemy to flight and pursued them without slackening
                        rein for nearly five miles. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When Mancinus
                        saw that there was no chance of the enemy giving up the pursuit, or of his
                        escaping them, he rallied his men and faced the Numidians, though completely
                        outnumbered and outmatched. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He himself
                        with the best of his riders was cut off, the rest resumed their wild flight
                        and reached Cales and ultimately by different by-paths returned to the
                        Dictator. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It so happened that Minucius
                        had rejoined Fabius on this day. He had been sent to strengthen the force
                        holding the defile which contracts into a narrow pass just above Terracina
                        close to the sea. This was to prevent the Carthaginian from utilising the
                        Appian road for a descent upon the territory of Rome, when he left Sinuessa.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Dictator and the Master of the
                        Horse with their joint armies moved their camp on to the route which
                        Hannibal was expected to take. He was encamped two miles distant. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day the Carthaginian army began
                        its march and filled the whole of the road between the two camps. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans had taken up a position immediately
                        below their entrenchments, on unquestionably more advantageous ground, yet
                        the Carthaginian came up with his cavalry and light infantry to challenge
                        his enemy. They made repeated attacks and retirements, but the Roman line
                        kept its ground; the fighting was slack and more satisfactory to the
                        Dictator than to Hannibal; 200 Romans fell, and 800 of the enemy. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> It now seemed as if Hannibal must be hemmed in.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Capua and Samnium and all the rich
                        land of Latium behind them were furnishing the Romans with supplies, while
                        the Carthaginian would have to winter amongst the rocks of Formiae and the
                        sands and marshes of Liternum and in gloomy forests. Hannibal did not fail
                        to observe that his own tactics were being employed against him. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> As he could not get out through Casilinum, and
                        would have to make for the mountains and cross the ridge of Callicula, he
                        would be liable to be attacked by the Romans whilst he was shut up in the
                        valleys. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To guard against this he decided
                        upon a stratagem which, deceiving the eyes of the enemy by its alarming
                        appearance, would enable him to scale the mountains in a night march without
                        fear of interruption. The following was the ruse which he adopted.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Torch-wood gathered from all the
                        country round, and faggots of dry brushwood were tied on the horns of the
                        oxen which he was driving in vast numbers, both broken and unbroken to the
                        plough, amongst the rest of the plunder from the fields. About 2000 oxen
                        were collected for the purpose. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To
                        Hasdrubal was assigned the task of setting fire to the bundles on the horns
                        of this herd as soon as darkness set in, then driving them up the mountains
                        and if possible mostly above the passes which were guarded by the Romans.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as it was dark, the camp silently
                        broke up; the oxen were driven some distance in front of the column.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they had reached the foot of the
                        mountains where the roads began to narrow, the signal was given and the
                        herds with their flaming horns were driven up the mountain side. The
                        terrifying glare of the flames shooting from their heads and the heat which
                        penetrated to the root of their horns made the oxen rush about as though
                        they were mad. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At this sudden scampering
                        about, it seemed as though the woods and mountains were on fire, and all the
                        brushwood round became alight and the incessant but useless shaking of their
                        heads made the flames shoot out all the more, and gave the appearance of men
                        running about in all directions. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the
                        men who were guarding the pass saw fires moving above them high up on the
                        mountains, they thought that their position was turned, and they hastily
                        quitted it. Making their way up to the highest points, they took the
                        direction where there appeared to be the fewest flames, thinking this to be
                        the safest road. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even so, they came across
                        stray oxen separated from the herd, and at first sight they stood still in
                        astonishment at what seemed a preternatural sight of beings breathing fire.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When it turned out to be simply a
                        human device they were still more alarmed at what they suspected was an
                        ambuscade, and they took to flight. Now they fell in with some of Hannibal's
                        light infantry, but both sides shrank from a fight in the darkness and
                        remained inactive till daylight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the
                        meantime Hannibal had marched the whole of his army through the pass, and
                        after surprising and scattering some Roman troops in the pass itself, fixed
                        his camp in the district of Allifae. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius watched all this confusion and
                        excitement, but as he took it to be an ambuscade, and in any case shrank
                        from a battle in the night, he kept his men within their lines. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> As soon as it was light there was a battle just
                        under the ridge of the mountain where the Carthaginian light infantry were
                        cut off from their main body and would easily have been crushed by the
                        Romans, who had considerably the advantage in numbers, had not a cohort of
                        Spaniards come up, who had been sent back by Hannibal to their assistance.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These men were more accustomed to the
                        mountains and in better training for running amongst rocks and precipices,
                        and being both more lightly made and more lightly armed they could easily by
                        their method of fighting baffle an enemy drawn from the lowlands, heavily
                        armed and accustomed to stationary tactics. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> At last they drew off from a contest which was anything but an equal one.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Spaniards being almost untouched,
                        the Romans having sustained a heavy loss, each retired to their respective
                        camps. Fabius followed on Hannibal's track through the pass and encamped
                        above Allifae in an elevated position and one of great natural strength.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hannibal retraced his steps as far as
                        the Peligni, ravaging the country as he went, as though his intention was to
                        march through Samnium upon Rome. Fabius continued to move along the heights,
                        keeping between the enemy and the City, neither avoiding nor attacking him.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian left the Peligni, and
                        marching back into Apulia, reached Gereonium. This city had been abandoned
                        by its inhabitants because a portion of the walls had fallen into ruin.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Dictator formed an entrenched camp
                        near Larinum. From there he was recalled to Rome on business connected with
                        religion. Before his departure he impressed upon the Master of the Horse,
                        not only as commander-in-chief but as a friend giving good advice and even
                        using entreaties, the necessity of trusting more to prudence than to luck,
                        and following his own example rather than copying Sempronius and Flaminius.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was not to suppose that nothing had
                        been gained now that the summer had been spent in baffling the enemy, even
                        physicians often gained more by not disturbing their patients than by
                        subjecting them to movement and exercises; <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> it was no small advantage to have avoided defeat at the hands of a foe
                        who had been so often victorious and to have obtained a breathing space
                        after such a series of disasters. With these unheeded warnings to the Master
                        of the Horse he started for Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the commencement of this summer war
                        began in Spain both by land and sea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Hasdrubal added ten ships to those which he had received from his brother,
                        equipped and ready for action, and gave Himilco a fleet of forty vessels.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then sailed from New Carthage,
                        keeping near land, and with his army moving parallel along the coast, ready
                        to engage the enemy whether by sea or land. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> When Cn. Scipio learnt that his enemy had left his winter quarters he at
                        first adopted the same tactics, but on further consideration he would not
                        venture on a contest by land, owing to the immense reputation of the new
                        auxiliaries. After embarking the pick of his army he proceeded with a fleet
                        of thirty-five ships to meet the enemy. The day after leaving Tarraco he
                        came to anchor at a spot ten miles distant from the mouth of the Ebro.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Two despatch boats belonging to
                        Massilia had been sent to reconnoitre, and they brought back word that the
                        Carthaginian fleet was riding at anchor in the mouth of the river and their
                        camp was on the bank. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Scipio at once
                        weighed anchor and sailed towards the enemy, intending to strike a sudden
                        panic amongst them by surprising them whilst off their guard and
                        unsuspicious of danger. </p>
                    <p> There are in Spain many towers situated on high ground which are used both
                        as look-outs and places of defence against pirates. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> It was from there that the hostile ships were first
                        sighted, and the signal given to Hasdrubal; excitement and confusion
                        prevailed in the camp on shore before it reached the ships at sea, as the
                        splash of the oars and other sounds of advancing ships were not yet heard,
                        and the projecting headlands hid the Roman fleet from view. Suddenly one
                        mounted vidette after another from Hasdrubal galloped up with orders to
                        those who were strolling about on the shore or resting in their tents, and
                        expecting anything rather than the approach of an enemy or battle that day,
                        to embark with all speed and take their arms, for the Roman fleet was now
                        not far from the harbour. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This order the
                        mounted men were giving in all directions, and before long Hasdrubal himself
                        appeared with the whole of his army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Everywhere there was noise and confusion, the rowers and the soldiers
                        scrambled on board more like men flying from the shore than men going into
                        action. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hardly were all on board, when
                        some unfastened the mooring ropes and drifted towards their anchors, others
                        cut their cables; everything was done in too much haste and hurry, the work
                        of the seamen was hampered by the preparations which the soldiers were
                        making, and the soldiers were prevented from putting themselves in fighting
                        trim owing to the confusion and panic which prevailed amongst the seamen.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> By this time the Romans were not only
                        near at hand, they had actually lined up their ships for the attack. The
                        Carthaginians were paralysed quite as much by their own disorder as by the
                        approach of the enemy, and they brought their ships round for flight, after
                        abandoning a struggle which it would be more true to say was attempted
                        rather than begun. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But it was impossible
                        for their widely extended line to enter the mouth of the river all at once,
                        and the ships were run ashore in all directions. Some of those on board got
                        out through the shallow water, others jumped on to the beach, with arms or
                        without, and made good their escape to the army which was drawn up ready for
                        action along the shore. Two Carthaginian ships, however, were captured to
                        begin with and four sunk. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though the Romans saw that the enemy were
                        in force on land and that their army was extended along the shore, they
                        showed no hesitation in following up the enemy's panic-stricken fleet.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They secured all the ships which had
                        not staved their prows in on the beach, or grounded with their keels in the
                        mud by fastening hawsers to their sterns and dragging them into deep water.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Out of forty vessels twenty-five were
                        captured in this way. This was not, however, the best part of the victory.
                        Its main importance lay in the fact that this one insignificant encounter
                        gave the mastery of the whole of the adjacent sea. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The fleet accordingly sailed to Onusa, and there the
                        soldiers disembarked, captured and plundered the place and then marched
                        towards New Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They ravaged the
                        entire country round, and ended by setting fire to the houses which adjoined
                        the walls and gates. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Re-embarking laden
                        with plunder, they sailed to Longuntica, where they found a great quantity
                        of esparto grass which Hasdrubal had collected for the use of the navy, and
                        after taking what they could use they burnt the rest. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They did not confine themselves to cruising along the
                        coast, but crossed over to the island of Ebusus, where they made a
                        determined but unsuccessful attack upon the capital during the whole of two
                        days. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As they found that they were only
                        wasting time on a hopeless enterprise, they took to plundering the country,
                        and sacked and burnt several villages. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Here they secured more booty than on the mainland, and after placing it on
                        board, as they were on the point of sailing away, some envoys came to Scipio
                        from the Balearic isles to sue for peace. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        From this point the fleet sailed back to the eastern side of the province
                        where envoys were assembled from all the tribes in the district of the Ebro,
                        and many even from the remotest parts of Spain. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The tribes which actually acknowledged the supremacy of
                        Rome and gave hostages amounted to more than a hundred and twenty. The
                        Romans felt now as much confidence in their army as in their navy, and
                        marched as far as the pass of Castulo. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Hasdrubal retired to Lusitania where he was nearer to the Atlantic. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It now seemed as though the remainder of
                        the summer would be undisturbed, and it would have been so as far as the
                        Carthaginians were concerned. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But the
                        Spanish temperament is restless and fond of change, and after the Romans had
                        left the pass and retired to the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> coast,
                        Mandonius and Indibilis, who had previously been chief of the Ibergetes,
                        roused their fellow-tribesmen and proceeded to harry the lands of those who
                        were in peace and alliance with Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Scipio despatched a military tribune with some light-armed auxiliaries to
                        disperse them, and after a trifling engagement, for they were undisciplined
                        and without organisation, they were all put to rout, some being killed or
                        taken prisoners, and a large proportion deprived of their arms. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> This disturbance, however, brought Hasdrubal, who
                        was marching westwards, back to the defence of his allies on the south side
                        of the Ebro. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians were in
                        camp amongst the Ilergavonians; the Roman camp was at Nova, when unexpected
                        intelligence turned the tide of war in another direction. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The Celtiberi, who had sent their chief men as envoys
                        to Scipio and had given hostages, were induced by his representations to
                        take up arms and invade the province of New Carthage with a powerful army.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They took three fortified towns by
                        storm, and fought two most successful actions with Hasdrubal himself,
                        killing 15,000 of the enemy and taking 4000 prisoners with numerous
                        standards. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was the position of affairs when P.
                        Scipio, whose command had been extended after he ceased to be consul, came
                        to the province which had been assigned to him by the senate. He brought a
                        reinforcement of thirty ships of war and 8000 troops, also a large convoy of
                        supplies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This fleet, with its enormous
                        column of transports, excited the liveliest delight among the townsmen and
                        their allies when it was seen in the distance and finally reached the port
                        of Tarracona. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There the soldiers were
                        landed and Scipio marched up country to meet his brother; thenceforward they
                        carried on the campaign with their united forces and with one heart and
                        purpose. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As the Carthaginians were
                        preoccupied with the Celtiberian war, the Scipios had no hesitation in
                        crossing the Ebro and, as no enemy appeared, marching straight to Saguntum,
                        where they had been informed that the hostages who had been surrendered to
                        Hannibal from all parts of Spain were detained in the citadel under a
                        somewhat weak guard. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The fact that they
                        had given these pledges was the only thing that prevented all the tribes of
                        Spain from openly manifesting their leanings towards alliance with Rome;
                        they dreaded lest the price of their defection from Carthage should be the
                        blood of their own children. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From this
                        bond Spain was released by the clever but treacherous scheme of one
                        individual. </p>
                    <p> Abelux was a Spaniard of high birth living at Saguntum, who had at one time
                        been loyal to Carthage, but afterwards, with the usual fickleness of
                        barbarians, as the fortunes of Carthage changed so he changed his
                        allegiance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He considered that any one
                        going over to the enemy without having something valuable to betray was
                        simply a worthless and disreputable individual, and so he made it his one
                        aim to be of the greatest service he could to his new allies. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> After making a survey of everything which Fortune
                        could possibly put within his reach, he made up his mind to effect the
                        delivery of the hostages; that one thing he thought would do more than
                        anything else to win the friendship of the Spanish chieftains for the
                        Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was quite aware, however, that
                        the guardians of the hostages would take no step without the orders of
                        Bostar, their commanding officer, and so he employed his arts against Bostar
                        himself. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Bostar had fixed his camp
                        outside the city quite on the shore that he might bar the approach of the
                        Romans on that side. After obtaining a secret interview with him he warned
                        him, as though he were unaware of it, as to the actual state of affairs.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "Up to this time," he said, "fear
                        alone has kept the Spaniards loyal because the Romans were far away; now the
                        Roman camp is on our side the Ebro, a secure stronghold and refuge for all
                        who want to change their allegiance. Those, therefore, who are no longer
                        restrained by fear must be bound to us by kindness and feelings of
                        gratitude." <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Bostar was greatly surprised,
                        and asked him what boon could suddenly effect such great results. "Send the
                        hostages," was the reply, "back to their homes. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> That will evoke gratitude from their parents, who are
                        very influential people in their own country, and also from their
                        fellow-countrymen generally. Every one likes to feel that he is trusted; the
                        confidence you place in others generally strengthens their confidence in
                        you. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The service of restoring the
                        hostages to their respective homes I claim for myself, that I may contribute
                        to the success of my plan by my own personal efforts, and win for an act
                        gracious in itself still more gratitude." </p>
                    <p> He succeeded in persuading Bostar, whose intelligence was not on a par with
                        the acuteness which the other Carthaginians showed. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> After this interview he went secretly to the enemy's
                        outposts, and meeting with some Spanish auxiliaries he was conducted by them
                        into the presence of Scipio, to whom he explained what he proposed to do.
                        Pledges of good faith were mutually exchanged and the place and time for
                        handing over the hostages fixed, after which he returned to Saguntum.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The following day he spent in
                        receiving Bostar's instructions for the execution of the project. It was
                        agreed between them that he should go at night in order, as he pretended, to
                        escape the observation of the Roman outposts. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> He had already arranged with these as to the hour at
                        which he would come, and after awakening those who were in guard of the boys
                        he conducted the hostages, without appearing to be aware of the fact, into
                        the trap which he had himself prepared. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        The outposts conducted them into the Roman camp; all the remaining details
                        connected with their restoration to their homes were carried out as he had
                        arranged with Bostar, precisely as if the business were being transacted m
                        the name of Carthage. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Yet though the
                        service rendered was the same, the gratitude felt towards the Romans was
                        considerably greater than would have been earned by the Carthaginians, who
                        had shown themselves oppressive and tyrannical in the time of their
                        prosperity, and now that they experienced a change of fortune their act
                        might have appeared to be dictated by fear. <milestone n="20" unit="section"
                        /> The Romans, on the other hand, hitherto perfect strangers, had no sooner
                        come into the country than they began with an act of clemency and
                        generosity, and Abelux was considered to have shown his prudence in changing
                        his allies to such good purpose. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> All now
                        began with surprising unanimity to meditate revolt, and an armed movement
                        would have begun at once had not the winter set in, which compelled the
                        Romans as well as the Carthaginians to retire to their quarters. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These were the main incidents of the
                        campaign in Spain during the second summer of the Punic war. In Italy the
                        masterly inaction of Fabius had for a short time stemmed the tide of Roman
                        disasters. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was a cause of grave anxiety
                        to Hannibal, for he fully realised that the Romans had chosen for their
                        commander-in-chief a man who conducted war on rational principles and not by
                        trusting to chance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But amongst his own
                        people, soldiers and civilians alike, his tactics were viewed with contempt,
                        especially after a battle had been brought about owing to the rashness of
                        the Master of the Horse in the Dictator's absence which would be more
                        correctly described as fortunate rather than as successful. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Two incidents occurred which made the Dictator still
                        more unpopular. One was due to the crafty policy of Hannibal. Some deserters
                        had pointed out to him the Dictator's landed property, and after all the
                        surrounding buildings had been levelled to the ground he gave orders for
                        that property to be spared from fire and sword and all hostile treatment
                        whatever in order that it might be thought that there was some secret
                        bargain between them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The second cause of
                        the Dictator's growing unpopularity was something which he himself did, and
                        which at first bore an equivocal aspect because he had acted without the
                        authority of the senate, but ultimately it was universally recognised as
                        redounding very greatly to his credit. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In
                        carrying out the exchange of prisoners it had been agreed between the Roman
                        and the Carthaginian commanders, following the precedent of the first Punic
                        war, that whichever side received back more prisoners than they gave should
                        strike a balance by paying two and a half pounds of silver for each soldier
                        they received in excess of those they gave. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The Roman prisoners restored were two hundred and forty-seven more than
                        the Carthaginians. The question of this payment had been frequently
                        discussed in the senate, but as Fabius had not consulted that body before
                        making the agreement there was some delay in voting the money. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The matter was settled by Fabius sending his son
                        Quintus to Rome to sell the land which had been untouched by the enemy; he
                        thus discharged the obligation of the State at his own private expense.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When Hannibal burnt Gereonium after
                        its capture, he left a few houses standing to serve as granaries, and now he
                        was occupying a standing camp before its walls. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He was in the habit of sending out two divisions to
                        collect corn, he remained in camp with the third ready to move in any
                        direction where he saw that his foragers were being attacked. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman army was at the time in the
                        neighbourhood of Larinum, with Minucius in command, owing, as stated above,
                        to the Dictator having left for the City. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The camp had been situated in a lofty and secure position; it was now
                        transferred to the plain, and more energetic measures more in harmony with
                        the general's temperament were being discussed; suggestions were made for an
                        attack either on the dispersed parties of foragers or on the camp now that
                        it was left with a weak guard. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal
                        soon found out that the tactics of his enemies had changed with the change
                        of generals, and that they would act with more spirit than prudence, and
                        incredible as it may sound, though his <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                        enemy was in closer proximity to him, he sent out a whole division of his
                        army to collect corn, keeping the other two in camp. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The next thing he did was to move his camp still nearer
                        the enemy, about two miles from Gereonium on rising ground within view of
                        the Romans, so that they might know that he was determined to protect his
                        foragers in case of attack. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From this
                        position he was able to see another elevated position still closer to the
                        Roman camp, in fact looking down on it. There was no doubt that if he were
                        to attempt to seize it in broad daylight the enemy, having less distance to
                        go, would be there before him, so he sent a force of Numidians who occupied
                        it during the night. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The next day the
                        Romans, seeing how small a number were holding the position, made short work
                        of them and drove them off and then transferred their own camp there.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By this time there was but a very
                        small distance between rampart and rampart, and even that was almost
                        entirely filled with Roman troops, who were demonstrating in force to
                        conceal the movements of cavalry and light infantry who had been sent
                        through the camp gate farthest from the enemy to attack his foragers, upon
                        whom they inflicted severe losses. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Hannibal did not venture upon a regular battle because his camp was so
                        weakly guarded that it could not have repelled an assault. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Borrowing the tactics of Fabius he began to carry on
                        the campaign by remaining in almost complete inaction, and withdrew his camp
                        to its former position before the walls of Gereonium. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> According to some authors a pitched battle was fought
                        with both armies in regular formation; the Carthaginians were routed at the
                        first onset and driven to their camp; from there a sudden sortie was made
                        and it was the Romans' turn to flee, and the battle was once more restored
                        by the sudden appearance of Numerius Decimus, the Samnite general.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Decimus was, as far as wealth and
                        lineage go, the foremost man not only in Bovianum, his native place, but in
                        the whole of Samnium. In obedience to the Dictator's orders he was bringing
                        into camp a force of 8000 foot and 500 horse, and when he appeared in
                        Hannibal's rear both sides thought that it was a reinforcement coming from
                        Rome under Q. Fabius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Hannibal, it is
                        further stated, ordered his men to retire, the Romans followed them up, and
                        with the aid of the Samnites captured two of their fortified positions the
                        same day; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> 6000 of the enemy were killed
                        and about 5000 of the Romans, yet though the losses were so evenly balanced
                        an idle and foolish report of a splendid victory reached Rome together with
                        a despatch from the Master of the Horse which was still more foolish. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This state of affairs led to constant
                        discussions in the senate and the Assembly. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Amidst the universal rejoicing the Dictator stood alone; he declared that
                        he did not place the slightest credence in either the report or the
                        despatch, and even if everything was as it was represented, he dreaded
                        success more than failure. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On this M.
                        Metilius, tribune of the plebs, said it was really becoming intolerable that
                        the Dictator, not content with standing in the way of any success being
                        achieved when he was on the spot, should now be equally opposed to it after
                        it had been achieved in his absence. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "He
                        was deliberately wasting time in his conduct of the war in order to remain
                        longer in office as sole magistrate and retain his supreme command.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> One consul has fallen in battle, the
                        other has been banished far from Italy under pretext of chasing the
                        Carthaginian fleet; two praetors have their hands full with Sicily and
                        Sardinia, neither of which provinces needs a praetor at all at this time;
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> M. Minucius, Master of the Horse, has
                        been almost kept under guard to prevent him from seeing the enemy or doing
                        anything which savoured of war. And so, good heavens! <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> not only Samnium, where we retreated before the
                        Carthaginians as though it were some territory beyond the Ebro, but even the
                        country of Falernum, have been utterly laid waste, while the Dictator was
                        sitting idly at Casilinum, using the legions of Rome to protect his own
                        property. The Master of the Horse and the army, who were burning to fight,
                        were kept back and almost imprisoned within their lines; they were deprived
                        of their arms as though they were prisoners of war. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> At length, no sooner had the Dictator departed than,
                        like men delivered from a blockade, they left their entrenchments and routed
                        the enemy and put him to flight. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Under
                        these circumstances I was prepared, if the Roman plebs still possessed the
                        spirit they showed in old days, to take the bold step of bringing in a
                        measure to relieve Q. Fabius of his command; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> as it is I shall propose a resolution couched in very
                        moderate terms-'that the authority of the Master of the Horse be made equal
                        to that of the Dictator.' <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But even if
                        this resolution is carried Q. Fabius must not be allowed to rejoin the army
                        before he has appointed a consul in place of C. Flaminius." </p>
                    <p> As the line which the Dictator was taking was in the highest degree
                        unpopular, he kept away from the Assembly. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> Even in the senate he produced an unfavourable impression when he spoke
                        in laudatory terms of the enemy and put down the disasters of the past two
                        years to rashness and lack of generalship on the part of the commanders. The
                        Master of the Horse, he said, must be called to account for having fought
                        against his orders. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If, he went on to
                        say, the supreme command and direction of the war remained in <milestone
                            n="14??" unit="section"/> his hands, he would soon let men know that in
                        the case of a good general Fortune plays a small part, intelligence and
                        military skill are the main factors. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> To
                        have preserved the army in circumstances of extreme danger without any
                        humiliating defeat was in his opinion a more glorious thing than the
                        slaughter of many thousands of the enemy. But he failed to convince his
                        audience, and after appointing M. Atilius Regulus as consul, he set off by
                        night to rejoin his army. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He was anxious
                        to avoid a personal altercation on the question of his authority, and left
                        Rome the day before the proposal was voted upon. At daybreak a meeting of
                        the plebs was held to consider the proposal. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Though the general feeling was one of hostility to the
                        Dictator and goodwill towards the Master of the Horse, few were found bold
                        enough to give this feeling utterance and recommend a proposal which after
                        all was acceptable to the plebs as a body, and so, notwithstanding the fact
                        that the great majority were in favour of it, it lacked the support of men
                        of weight and influence. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> One man was
                        found who came forward to advocate the proposal, C. Terentius Varro, who had
                        been praetor the year before, a man of humble and even mean origin.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The tradition is that his father was
                        a butcher who hawked his meat about and employed his son in the menial
                        drudgery of his trade. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The money made in this business was left
                        to his son, who hoped that his fortune might help him to a more respectable
                        position in society. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He decided to become
                        an advocate, and his appearances in the Forum, where he defended men of the
                        lowest class by noisy and scurrilous attacks upon the property and character
                        of respectable citizens, brought him into notoriety and ultimately into
                        office. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After discharging the various
                        duties of the quaestorship, the two aedileships, plebeian and curule, and
                        lastly those of the praetor, he now aspired to the consulship. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> With this view he cleverly took advantage of the
                        feeling against the Dictator to court the gale of popular favour, and gained
                        for himself the whole credit of carrying the resolution. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Everybody, whether in Rome or in the army, whether
                        friend or foe, with the sole exception of the Dictator himself, looked upon
                        this proposal as intended to cast a slur on him. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> But he met the injustice done to him by the people,
                        embittered as they were against him, with the same dignified composure with
                        which he had previously treated the charges which his opponents had brought
                        against him before the populace. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While
                        still on his way he received a despatch containing the senatorial decree for
                        dividing his command, but as he knew perfectly well that an equal share of
                        military command by no means implied an equal share of military skill, he
                        returned to his army with a spirit undismayed by either his fellow-citizens
                        or the enemy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Owing to his success and popularity
                        Minucius had been almost unbearable before, but now that he had won as great
                        a victory over Fabius as over Hannibal, his boastful arrogance knew no
                        bounds. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "The man," he exclaimed, "who was
                        selected as the only general who would be a match for Hannibal has now, by
                        an order of the people, been put on a level with his second in command; the
                        Dictator has to share his powers with the Master of the Horse. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> There is no precedent for this in our annals, and
                        it has been done in that very State in which Masters of the Horse have been
                        wont to look with dread upon the rods and axes of Dictators. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> So brilliant have been my good fortune and my
                        merits. If the Dictator persists in that dilatoriness and inaction which
                        have been condemned by the judgment of gods and men, I shall follow my good
                        fortune wherever it may lead me." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Accordingly on his first meeting with Q. Fabius, he told him that the very
                        first thing that had to be settled was the method in which they should
                        exercise their divided authority. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The best
                        plan, he thought, would be for them each to take supreme command on
                        alternate days, or, if he preferred it, at longer intervals. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> This would enable whichever general was in
                        command to meet Hannibal with tactics and strength equal to his own should
                        an opportunity arise of striking a blow. Q. Fabius met this proposal with a
                        decided negative. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Everything, he argued,
                        which his colleague's rashness might prompt would be at the mercy of
                        Fortune; though his command was shared with another, he was not wholly
                        deprived of it; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> he would never therefore
                        voluntarily give up what power he still possessed of conducting operations
                        with common sense and prudence, and though he refused to agree to a division
                        of days or periods of command, he was prepared to divide the army with him
                        and use his best foresight and judgment to preserve what he could as he
                        could not save all. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So it was arranged
                        that they should adopt the plan of the consuls and share the legions between
                        them. The first and fourth went to Minucius, Fabius retained the second and
                        third. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The cavalry and the contingents
                        supplied by the Latins and the allies were also divided equally between
                        them. The Master of the Horse even insisted upon separate camps. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nothing that was going on amongst his
                        enemies escaped the observation of Hannibal, for ample information was
                        supplied to him by deserters as well as by his scouts. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He was doubly delighted, for he felt sure of entrapping
                        by his own peculiar methods the wild rashness of Minucius, and he saw that
                        Fabius' skilful tactics had lost half their strength. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Between Minucius' camp and Hannibal's there was some
                        rising ground, and whichever side seized it would undoubtedly be able to
                        render their adversaries' position less secure. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Hannibal determined to secure it, and though it would
                        have been worth while doing so without a fight, he preferred to bring on a
                        battle with Minucius, who, he felt quite sure, would hurry up to stop him.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The entire intervening country seemed,
                        at a first glance, totally unsuited for surprise tactics, for there were no
                        woods anywhere, no spots covered with brushwood and scrub, but in reality it
                        naturally lent itself to such a purpose, and all the more so because in so
                        bare a valley no stratagem of the kind could be suspected. In its windings
                        there were caverns, some so large as to be capable of concealing two hundred
                        men. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Each of these hiding-places was
                        filled with troops, and altogether 5000 horse and foot were placed in
                        concealment. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In case, however, the
                        stratagem might be detected by some soldier's thoughtless movements, or the
                        glint of arms in so open a valley, Hannibal sent a small detachment to seize
                        the rising ground already described in order to divert the attention of the
                        enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as they were sighted, their
                        small number excited ridicule, and every man begged that he might have the
                        task of dislodging them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Conspicuous
                        amongst his senseless and hot-headed soldiers the general sounded a general
                        call to arms, and poured idle abuse and threats on the enemy. He sent the
                        light infantry first in open skirmishing order, these were followed by the
                        cavalry in close formation, and at last, when he saw that reinforcements
                        were being brought up to the enemy, he advanced with the legions in line.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal on his side sent supports,
                        both horse and foot, to his men wherever they were hard <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> pressed, and the numbers engaged steadily grew until he
                        had formed his entire army into order of battle and both sides were in full
                        strength. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Roman light infantry moving
                        up the hill from lower ground were the first to be repulsed and forced back
                        to the cavalry who were coming up behind them. They sought refuge behind the
                        front ranks of the legions, who alone amidst the general panic preserved
                        their coolness and presence of mind. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Had
                        it been a straightforward fight, man to man, they would to all appearance
                        have been quite a match for their foes, so much had their success, a few
                        days previously, restored their courage. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        But the sudden appearance of the concealed troops and their combined attack
                        on both flanks and on the rear of the Roman legions created such confusion
                        and alarm that not a man had any spirit left to fight or any hope of
                        escaping by flight. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius' attention was first drawn to the
                        cries of alarm, then he observed in the distance the disordered and broken
                        ranks. "Just so," he exclaimed, "Fortune has overtaken his rashness, but not
                        more quickly than I feared. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fabius is his
                        equal in command, but he has found out that Hannibal is his superior both in
                        ability and in success. However, this is not the time for censure or rebuke,
                        advance into the field! Let us wrest victory from the foe, and a confession
                        of error from our fellow-citizens." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By
                        this time the rout had spread over a large part of the field, some were
                        killed, others looking round for the means of escape, when suddenly the army
                        of Fabius appeared as though sent down from heaven to their rescue.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before they came within range of their
                        missiles, before they could exchange blows, they checked their comrades in
                        their wild flight and the enemy in their fierce attack. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Those who had been scattered hither and thither after
                        their ranks were broken, closed in from all sides and reformed their line;
                        those who had kept together in their retreat wheeled round to face the
                        enemy, and, forming square, at one moment slowly retired, and at another
                        shoulder to shoulder stood their ground. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The defeated troops and those who were fresh on the field had now
                        practically become one line, and they were commencing an advance on the
                        enemy when the Carthaginian sounded the retreat, showing clearly that whilst
                        Minucius had been defeated by him he was himself vanquished by Fabius.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The greater part of the day had been
                        spent in these varying fortunes of the field. On their return to camp
                        Minucius called his men together and addressed them thus: "Soldiers, I have
                        often heard it said that the best man is he who himself advises what is the
                        right thing to do; next to him comes the man who follows good advice;
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but the man who neither himself knows
                        what counsel to give nor obeys the wise counsels of another is of the very
                        lowest order of intelligence. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Since the
                        first order of intelligence and capacity has been denied to us let us cling
                        to the second and intermediate one, and whilst we are learning to command,
                        let us make up our minds to obey him who is wise and far sighted. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Let us join camp with Fabius. When we have
                        carried the standards to his tent where I shall salute him as 'Father,' a
                        title which the service he has done us and the greatness of his office alike
                        deserve, you soldiers will salute as 'Patrons' those whose arms and right
                        hands protected you a little while ago. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        If this day has done nothing else for us, it has at all events conferred on
                        us the glory of having grateful hearts." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The signal was given and the word passed
                        to collect the baggage; they then proceeded in marching order to the
                        Dictator's camp much to his surprise and to the surprise of all who were
                        round him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the standards had been
                        stationed in front of his tribunal, the Master of the Horse stepped forward
                        and addressed him as "Father," and the whole of his troops saluted those who
                        were crowding round them as "Patrons." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                        then proceeded, "I have put you on a level, Dictator, with my parents as far
                        as I can do so in words, but to them I only owe my life, to you I owe my
                        preservation and the safety of all these men. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The decree of the plebs, which I feel to be onerous
                        rather than an honour, I am the first to repeal and annul, and with a prayer
                        that it may turn out well for you, for me, and for these armies of yours,
                        for preserved and preserver alike, I place myself again under your
                        auspicious authority and restore to you these legions with their standards.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I ask you, as an act of grace, to
                        order me to retain my office and these, each man of them, his place in the
                        ranks." <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then each man grasped his
                        neighbour's hand, and the soldiers were dismissed to quarters where they
                        were generously and hospitably entertained by acquaintances and strangers
                        alike, and the day which had a short time ago been dark and gloomy and
                        almost marked by disaster and ruin became a day of joy and gladness.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the report of this action reached
                        Rome and was confirmed by despatches from both commanders, and by letters
                        from the rank and file of both armies, every man did his best to extol
                        Maximus to the skies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His reputation was
                        quite as great with Hannibal and the Carthaginians; now at last they felt
                        that the were warring with Romans and on Italian soil. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> For the last two years they had felt such contempt for
                        Roman generals and Roman troops that they could hardly believe that they
                        were at war with that nation of whom they had heard such a terrible report
                        from their fathers. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal on his
                        return from the field is reported to have said, "The cloud which has so long
                        settled on the mountain heights has at last burst upon us in rain and
                        storm." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were occurring in
                        Italy, the consul., Cn. Servilius Geminus, with a fleet of 120 vessels,
                        visited Sardinia and Corsica and received hostages from both islands; from
                        there he sailed to Africa. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Before landing
                        on the mainland he laid waste the island of Menix and allowed the
                        inhabitants of Cercina to save their island from a similar visitation by
                        paying an indemnity of ten talents of silver. After this he disembarked his
                        forces on the African coast and sent them, both soldiers and seamen, to
                        ravage the country. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They dispersed far and
                        wide just as though they were plundering uninhabited islands, and
                        consequently their recklessness led them into an ambuscade. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Straggling in small parties, they were surrounded by
                        large numbers of the enemy who knew the country, whilst they were strangers
                        to it, with the result that they were driven in wild flight and with heavy
                        loss back to their ships. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After losing as
                        many as a thousand men-amongst them the quaestor Sempronius Blaesus-the
                        fleet hastily put to sea from shores lined with the enemy and held its
                        course to Sicily. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here it was handed over
                        to T. Otacilius, in order that his second in command, P. Sura, might take it
                        back to Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Servilius himself proceeded
                        overland through Sicily and crossed the Strait into Italy, in consequence of
                        a despatch from Q. Fabius recalling him and his colleague, M. Atilius, to
                        take over the armies, as his six months' tenure of office had almost
                        expired. All the annalists, with one or two exceptions, state that Fabius
                        acted against Hannibal as Dictator; Caelius adds that he was the first
                        Dictator who was appointed by the people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        But Caelius and the rest have forgotten that the <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> right of nominating a Dictator lay with the consul
                        alone, and Servilius, who was the only consul at the time, was in Gaul.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The citizens, appalled by three
                        successive defeats, could not endure the thought of delay, and recourse was
                        had to the appointment by the people of a man to act in place of a Dictator
                        ("pro dictatore"). His subsequent achievements, his brilliant reputation as
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> a commander, and the exaggerations
                        which his descendants introduced into the inscription on his bust easily
                        explain the belief which ultimately gained ground, that Fabius, who had only
                        been pro-dictator, was actually Dictator. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius army was transferred to Atilius,
                        Servilius Geminus took over the one which Minucius had commanded. They lost
                        no time in fortifying their winter quarters, and during the remainder of the
                        autumn conducted their joint operations in the most perfect harmony on the
                        line which Fabius had laid down. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When
                        Hannibal left his camp to collect supplies, they were conveniently posted at
                        different spots to harass his main body and cut off stragglers; but they
                        refused to risk a general engagement, though the enemy employed every
                        artifice to bring one on. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal was
                        reduced to such extremities that he would have marched back into Gaul had
                        not his departure looked like flight. No chance whatever would have been
                        left to him of feeding his army in that part of Italy if the succeeding
                        consuls had persevered in the same tactics. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> When the winter had brought the war to a standstill at Gereonium, envoys
                        from Neapolis arrived in Rome. They brought with them into the Senate-house
                        forty very heavy golden bowls, and addressed the assembled senators in the
                        following terms: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "We know that the Roman
                        treasury is being drained by the war, and since this war is being carried on
                        for the towns and fields of the allies quite as much as for the head and
                        stronghold of Italy, the City of Rome and its empire, we Neapolitans have
                        thought it but right to assist the Roman people with the <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> gold which has been left by our ancestors for the
                        enriching of our temples and for a reserve in time of need. If we thought
                        that our personal services would have been of any use we would just as
                        gladly have offered them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senators and
                        people of Rome will confer a great pleasure upon us if they look upon
                        everything that belongs to the Neapolitans as their own, and deign to accept
                        from us a gift, the value and importance <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        of which lie rather in the cordial goodwill of those who gladly give it than
                        in any intrinsic worth which it may itself possess." <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> A vote of thanks was passed to the envoys for their
                        munificence and their care for the interests of Rome, and one bowl, the
                        smallest, was accepted. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time a Carthaginian spy who
                        for two years had escaped detection was caught in Rome, and after both his
                        hands were cut off, he was sent away. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Twenty-five slaves who had formed a conspiracy in the Campus Martius were
                        crucified; the informer had his liberty given to him and 20,000 bronze ases.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Ambassadors were sent to Philip, King
                        of Macedon, to demand the surrender of Demetrius of Pharos, who had taken
                        refuge with him after his defeat, and another embassy was despatched to the
                        Ligurians to <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> make a formal complaint as
                        to the assistance they had given the Carthaginian in men and money, and at
                        the same time to get a nearer view of what was going on amongst the Boii and
                        the Insubres. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Officials were also sent to
                        Pineus, King of Illyria, to demand payment of the tribute which was now in
                        arrears, or, if he wished for an extension of time, to accept personal
                        securities for its payment. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So, though
                        they had an immense war on their shoulders, nothing escaped the attention of
                        the Romans in any part of the world, however distant. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> A religious difficulty arose about an unfulfilled vow.
                        On the occasion of the mutiny amongst the troops in Gaul two years before,
                        the praetor, L. Manlius, had vowed a temple to Concord, but up to that time
                        no contract had been made for its construction. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Two commissioners were appointed for the purpose by M.
                        Aemilius, the City praetor, namely, C. Pupius and Caeso Quinctius
                        Flamininus, and they entered into a contract for the building of the temple
                        within the precinct of the citadel. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        senate passed a resolution that Aemilius should also write to the consuls
                        asking one of them, if they approved, to come to Rome to hold the consular
                        elections, and he would give notice of the elections for whatever day they
                        fixed upon. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consuls replied that they
                        could not leave the army in the presence of the enemy without danger to the
                        republic, it would be therefore better for the elections to be held by an
                        interrex than that a consul should be recalled from the front. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The senate thought it better for a Dictator to
                        be nominated by the consul for the purpose of holding the elections. L.
                        Veturius Philo was nominated; he appointed Manlius Pomponius Matho his
                        Master of the Horse. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their election was
                        found to be invalid, and they were ordered to resign office after holding it
                        for four days; matters reverted to an interregnum. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> (216 B.C.)Servilius and Regulus had their
                        commands extended for another year. The interreges appointed by the senate
                        were C. Claudius Cento, son of Appius, and P. Cornelius Asina. The latter
                        conducted the elections amidst a bitter struggle between the patricians and
                        the plebs. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> C. Terentius Varro, a member of
                        their own order, had ingratiated himself with the plebs by his attacks upon
                        the leading men in the State and by all the tricks known to the demagogue.
                        His success in shaking the influence of Fabius and weakening the authority
                        of the Dictator had invested him with a certain glory in the eyes of the
                        mob, which was heightened by the other's unpopularity, and they did their
                        utmost to raise him to the consulship. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        patricians opposed him with their utmost strength, dreading lest it should
                        become a common practice for men to attack them as a means of rising to an
                        equality with them. Q. Baebius Herennius, a relation of Varro's, accused not
                        only the senate, but even the augurs, because they had prevented the
                        Dictator from carrying the elections through, and by thus embittering public
                        opinion against them, he strengthened the feeling in favour of his own
                        candidate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "It was by the nobility," he
                        declared, "who had for many years been trying to get up a war, that Hannibal
                        was brought into Italy, and when the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> war
                        might have been brought to a close, it was they who were unscrupulously
                        protracting it. The advantage which M. Minucius gained in the absence of
                        Fabius made it abundantly clear that <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        with four legions combined, a successful fight could be maintained, but
                        afterwards two legions had been exposed to slaughter at the hands of the
                        enemy, and then rescued at the very last moment in order that he might be
                        called 'Father' and 'Patron' because he would not allow the Romans to
                        conquer before they had been defeated. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Then as to the consuls; though they had it in their power to finish the war
                        they had adopted Fabius' policy and protracted it. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> This is the secret understanding that has been come to
                        by all the nobles, and we shall never see the end of the war till we have
                        elected as our consul a man who is really a plebeian, that is, one from the
                        ranks. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The plebeian nobility have all been
                        initiated into the same mysteries; when they are no longer looked down upon
                        by the patricians, they at once begin to look down upon the plebs.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Who does not see that their one aim
                        and object was to bring about an interregnum in order that the elections
                        might be controlled by the patricians? That was the object of the consuls in
                        both staying with the army; then, afterwards, because they had to nominate a
                        Dictator against their will to conduct the elections, they had carried their
                        point by force, and the Dictator's appointment was declared invalid by the
                        augurs. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Well, they have got their
                        interregnum; one consulship at all events belongs to the Roman plebs; the
                        people will freely dispose of it and give it to the man who prefers an early
                        victory to prolonged command." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Harangues like these kindled intense
                        excitement amongst the plebs. There were three patrician candidates in the
                        field, P. Cornelius Merenda, L. Manlius Vulso, and M. Aemilius Lepidus;
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> two plebeians who were now ennobled,
                        C. Atilius Serranus and Q. Aelius Paetus, one of whom was a pontiff, the
                        other an augur. But the only one elected was C. Terentius Varro, so that the
                        elections for appointing his colleague were in his hands. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The nobility saw that his rivals were not strong
                        enough, and they compelled L. Aemilius Paulus to come forward. He had come
                        off with a blasted reputation from the trial in which his colleague had been
                        found guilty, and he narrowly escaped, and for a long time stoutly resisted
                        the proposal to become a candidate owing to his intense dislike of the
                        plebs. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the next election day, after all
                        Varro's opponents had retired, he was given to him not so much to be his
                        colleague as to oppose him on equal terms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The elections of praetors followed; those elected were Manlius Pomponius
                        Matho and P. Furius Philus. To Philus was assigned the jurisdiction over
                        Roman citizens, to Pomponius the decision of suits between citizens and
                        foreigners. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two additional praetors were
                        appointed, M. Claudius Marcellus for Sicily, and L. Postumius Albinus to act
                        in Gaul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These were all elected in their
                        absence, and none of them, with the exception of Varro, were new to office.
                        Several strong and capable men were passed over, for at such a time it
                        seemed undesirable that a magistracy should be entrusted to new and untried
                        men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The armies were increased, but as to what
                        additions were made to the infantry and cavalry, the authorities vary so
                        much, both as to the numbers and nature of the forces, that I should hardly
                        venture to assert anything as positively certain. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Some say that 10,000 recruits were called out to make
                        up the losses; others, that four new legions were enrolled so that they
                        might carry on the war with eight legions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Some authorities record that both horse and foot in the legions were made
                        stronger by the addition of 1000 infantry and 100 cavalry to each, so that
                        they contained 5000 infantry and 300 cavalry, whilst the allies furnished
                        double the number of cavalry and an equal number of infantry. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Thus, according to these writers, there were
                        87,200 men in the Roman camp when the battle of Cannae was fought.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> One thing is quite certain; the
                        struggle was resumed with greater vigour and energy than in former years,
                        because the Dictator had given them reason to hope that the enemy might be
                        conquered. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But before the newly raised
                        legions left the City the decemvirs were ordered to consult the Sacred Books
                        owing to the general alarm which had been created by fresh portents.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was reported that showers of stones
                        had fallen simultaneously on the Aventine in Rome and at Aricia; that the
                        statues of the gods amongst the Sabines had sweated blood, and cold water
                        had flowed from the hot springs. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This
                        latter portent created more terror, because it had happened several times.
                        In the colonnade near the Campus several men had been killed by lightning.
                        The proper expiation of these portents was ascertained from the Sacred
                        Books. Some envoys from Paestum brought golden bowls to Rome. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Thanks were voted to them as in the case of the
                        Neapolitans, but the gold was not accepted. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time a fleet which had been
                        despatched by Hiero arrived at Ostia with a large quantity of supplies.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When his officers were introduced into
                        the senate they spoke in the following terms: "The news of the death of the
                        consul C. Flaminius and the destruction of his army caused so much distress
                        and grief to King Hiero <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> that he could
                        not have been more deeply moved by any disaster which could happen either to
                        himself personally or to his kingdom. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Although he well knows that the greatness of Rome is almost more to be
                        admired in adversity than in prosperity, still, notwithstanding that, he has
                        sent everything with which good and faithful allies can assist their friends
                        in time of war, and he earnestly intreats the senate not to reject his
                        offer. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To begin with, we are bringing, as
                        an omen of good fortune, a golden statue of Victory, weighing two hundred
                        and twenty pounds. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> We ask you to accept it
                        and keep it as your own for ever. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We have
                        also brought 300,000 pecks of wheat and 200,000 of barley that you may not
                        want provisions, and we are prepared to transport as much more as you
                        require to any place that you may decide upon. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The king is quite aware that Rome does not employ any
                        legionary soldiers or cavalry except Romans and those belonging to the Latin
                        nation, but he has seen foreigners serving as light infantry in the Roman
                        camp. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He has, accordingly, sent 1000
                        archers and slingers, capable of acting against the Balearics and Moors and
                        other tribes who fight with missile weapons." They supplemented these gifts
                        by suggesting that the praetor to whom Sicily had been assigned should take
                        the fleet over to Africa so that the country of the enemy, too, might be
                        visited by war, and less facilities afforded him for sending reinforcements
                        to Hannibal. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The senate requested the
                        officers to take back the following reply to the king: Hiero was a man of
                        honour and an exemplary ally; he had been consistently loyal all through,
                        and had on every occasion rendered most generous help to Rome, and for that
                        Rome was duly grateful. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The gold which
                        had been offered by one or two cities had not been accepted, though the
                        Roman people were very grateful for the offer. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> They would, however, accept the statue of Victory as an
                        omen for the future, and would give and consecrate a place for her in the
                        Capitol in the temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus. Enshrined in that
                        stronghold she will be gracious and propitious, constant and steadfast to
                        Rome. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The archers and slingers and the
                        corn were handed over to the consuls. The fleet which T. Otacilius had with
                        him in Sicily was strengthened by the addition of twenty-five quinqueremes,
                        and permission was given him to cross over to Africa if he thought it would
                        be in the interest of the republic. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After completing the enrolment the consuls
                        waited a few days for the contingents furnished by the Latins and the allies
                        to come in. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then a new departure was made;
                        the soldiers were sworn in by the military tribunes. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Up to that day there had only been the military oath
                        binding the men to assemble at the bidding of the consuls and not to disband
                        until they received orders to do so. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It
                        had also been the custom among the soldiers, when the infantry were formed
                        into companies of 100, and the cavalry into troops of 10, for all the men in
                        each company or troop to take a voluntary oath to each other that they would
                        not leave their comrades for fear or for flight, and that they would not
                        quit the ranks save to fetch or <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> pick up
                        a weapon, to strike an enemy, or to save a comrade. This voluntary covenant
                        was now changed into a formal oath taken before the tribunes. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Before they marched out of the City, Varro
                        delivered several violent harangues, in which he declared that the war had
                        been brought into Italy by the nobles, and would continue to feed on the
                        vitals of the republic if there were more generals like Fabius; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> he, Varro, would finish off the war the very day
                        he caught sight of the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His
                        colleague, Paulus, made only one speech, in which there was much more truth
                        than the people cared to hear. He passed no strictures on Varro, but he did
                        express surprise that any general, whilst still in the City before he had
                        taken up his command, or become acquainted with either his own army or that
                        of the enemy, or gained any information as to <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> the lie of the country and the nature of the ground,
                        should know in what way he <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> should
                        conduct the campaign and be able to foretell the day on which he would fight
                        a decisive battle with the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As for
                        himself, Paulus said that he would not anticipate events by disclosing his
                        measures, for, after all, circumstances determined measures for men much
                        more than men made circumstances subservient to measures. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> He hoped and prayed that such measures as were taken
                        with due caution and foresight might turn out successful; so far rashness,
                        besides being foolish, had proved disastrous. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> He made it quite clear that he would prefer safe to
                        hasty counsels, and in order to strengthen him in this resolve Fabius is
                        said to have addressed him on his departure in the following terms: </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> " L. Aemilius, if you were like your
                        colleague or, if you had a colleague like yourself-and I would that it were
                        so-my address would be simply a waste of words. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> For if you were both good consuls, you would, without
                        any suggestions from me, do everything that the interests of the State or
                        your own sense of honour demanded; if you were both alike bad, you would
                        neither listen to anything I had to say, nor take any advice which I might
                        offer. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As it is, when I look at your
                        colleague and consider what sort of a man you are, I shall address my
                        remarks to you. I can see that your merits as a man and a citizen will
                        effect nothing if one half of the commonwealth is crippled and evil counsels
                        possess the same force and authority as good ones. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> You are mistaken, L. Paulus, if you imagine that you
                        will have less difficulty with C. Terentius than with Hannibal; I rather
                        think the former will prove a more dangerous enemy than the latter.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With the one you will only have to
                        contend in the field, the opposition of the other you will have to meet
                        everywhere and always. Against Hannibal and his legions you will have your
                        cavalry and infantry, when Varro is in command he will use your own men
                        against you. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I do not want to bring ill
                        luck on you by mentioning the ill-starred Flaminius, but this I must say
                        that it was only after he was consul and had entered upon his province and
                        taken up his command that he began to play the madman, but this man was
                        insane before he stood for the consulship and afterwards while canvassing
                        for it, and now that he is consul, before he has seen the camp or the enemy
                        he is madder than ever. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If he raises such
                        storms amongst peaceful civilians as he did just now by bragging about
                        battles and battlefields, what will he do, think you, when he is talking to
                        armed men-and those young men-where words at once lead to action. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> And yet if he carries out his threat and brings
                        on an action at once, either I am utterly ignorant of military science, of
                        the nature of this war, of the enemy with whom we are dealing, or else some
                        place or other will be rendered more notorious by our defeat than even
                        Trasumennus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As we are alone, this is
                        hardly a time for boasting, and I would rather be thought to have gone too
                        far in despising glory than in seeking it, but as a matter of fact, the only
                        rational method of carrying on war against Hannibal is the one which I have
                        followed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This is not only taught us by
                        experience-experience the teacher of fools-but by reasoning which has been
                        and will continue to be unchanged as long as the conditions remain the same.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> We are carrying on war in Italy, in
                        our own country on our own soil, everywhere round us are citizens and
                        allies, they are helping us with men, horses, supplies, <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> and they will continue to do so, for they have proved
                        their loyalty thus far to us in our adversity; and time and circumstance are
                        making us more efficient, more circumspect, more self-reliant. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Hannibal, on the other hand, is in a foreign and
                        hostile land, far from his home and country, confronted everywhere by
                        opposition and danger; nowhere by land or sea can he find peace; no cities
                        admit him within their gates, no fortified towns; nowhere does he see
                        anything which he can call his own, he has to live on each day's pillage: he
                        has hardly a third of the army with which he crossed the Ebro; <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> he has lost more by famine than by the sword,
                        and even the few he has cannot get enough to support life. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Do you doubt then, that if we sit still we shall get
                        the better of a man who is growing weaker day by day, who has neither
                        supplies nor reinforcements nor money? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        How long has he been sitting before the walls of Gereonium, a poor fortress
                        in Apulia, as though they were the walls of Carthage? <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> But I will not sound my own praises even before you.
                        See how the late consuls, Cn. Servilius and Atilius, fooled him. This, L.
                        Paulus, is the only safe course to adopt, and it is one which your fellow
                        citizens will do more to make difficult and dangerous for you than the enemy
                        will. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> For your own soldiers will want the
                        same thing as the enemy; Varro though he is a Roman consul will desire just
                        what Hannibal the Carthaginian commander desires. You must hold your own
                        single-handed against both generals. And you will hold your own if you stand
                        your ground firmly against public gossip and private slander, if you remain
                        unmoved by false misrepresentations and your colleague's idle boasting. It
                        is said that truth is far too often eclipsed but never totally extinguished.
                        The man who scorns false glory will possess the true. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> Let them call you a coward because you are cautious, a
                        laggard because you are deliberate, unsoldierly because you are a skilful
                        general. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> I would rather have you give a
                        clever enemy cause for fear than earn the praise of foolish compatriots.
                        Hannibal will only feel contempt for a man who runs all risks, he will be
                        afraid of one who never takes a rash step. <milestone n="21" unit="section"
                        /> I do not advise you to do nothing, but I do advise you to be guided in
                        what you do by common sense and reason and not by chance. Never lose control
                        of your forces and yourself; be always prepared, always on the alert; never
                        fail to seize an opportunity favourable to yourself, and never give a
                        favourable opportunity to the enemy. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> The
                        man who is not in a hurry will always see his way clearly; haste blunders on
                        blindly." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul's reply was far from being a
                        cheerful one, for he admitted that the advice given was true, but not easy
                        to put into practice. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If a Dictator had
                        found his Master of the Horse unbearable, what power or authority would a
                        consul have against a violent and headstrong colleague? <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> "In my first consulship," he said, "I escaped, badly
                        singed, from the fire of popular fury. I hope and pray that all may end
                        successfully, but if any mischance befalls us I shall expose myself to the
                        weapons of the enemy sooner than to the verdict of the enraged citizens."
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With these words Paulus, it is said,
                        set forward, escorted by the foremost men amongst the patricians; the
                        plebeian consul was attended by his plebeian friends, more conspicuous for
                        their numbers than for the quality of the men who composed the crowd.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When they came into camp the recruits
                        and the old soldiers were formed into one army, and two separate camps were
                        formed, the new camp, which was the smaller one, being nearer to Hannibal,
                        while in the old camp the larger part of the army and the best troops were
                        stationed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> M. Atilius, one of the consuls
                        of the previous year, pleaded his age and was sent back to Rome; the other,
                        Geminus Servilius, was placed in command of the smaller camp with one Roman
                        legion and 2000 horse and foot of the allies. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Although Hannibal saw that the army opposed to him was
                        half as large again as it had been he was hugely delighted at the advent of
                        the consuls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For not only was there
                        nothing left out of his daily plunder, but there was nothing left anywhere
                        for him to seize, as all the corn, now that the country was unsafe, had been
                        everywhere stored in the cities. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Hardly
                        ten days' rations of corn remained, as was afterwards discovered, and the
                        Spaniards were prepared to desert, owing to the shortness of supplies, if
                        only the Romans had waited till the time was ripe. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An incident occurred which still further
                        encouraged Varro's impetuous and headstrong temperament. Parties were sent
                        to drive off the foragers; a confused fight ensued owing to the soldiers
                        rushing forward without any preconcerted plan or orders from their
                        commanders, and the contest went heavily against the Carthaginians.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As many as 1700 of them were killed,
                        the loss of the Romans and the allies did not amount to more than 100. The
                        consuls commanded on alternate days, and that day happened to be Paulus'
                        turn. He checked the victors who were pursuing the enemy in great disorder,
                        for he feared an ambuscade. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Varro was
                        furious, and loudly exclaimed that the enemy had been allowed to slip out of
                        their hands, and if the pursuit had not been stopped the war could have been
                        brought to a close. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal did not very
                        much regret his losses, on the contrary he believed that they would serve as
                        a bait to the impetuosity of the consul and his newly-raised troops, and
                        that he would be more headstrong than ever. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> What was going on in the enemy's camp was quite as well known to him as
                        what was going on in his own; he was fully aware that there were differences
                        and quarrels between the commanders, and that two-thirds of the army
                        consisted of recruits. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The following night
                        he selected what he considered a suitable position for an ambuscade, and
                        marched his men out of camp with nothing but their arms, leaving all the
                        property, both public and private, behind in the camp. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He then concealed the force behind the hills which
                        enclosed the valley, the infantry to the left and the cavalry to the right,
                        and took <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> the baggage train through the
                        middle of the valley, in the hope of surprising the Romans whilst plundering
                        the apparently deserted camp and hampered with their plunder. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Numerous fires were left burning in the camp in
                        order to create the impression that he wished to keep the consuls in their
                        respective positions until he had traversed a considerable distance in his
                        retreat. Fabius had been deceived by the same stratagem the previous year.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As it grew light the pickets were seen to
                        have been withdrawn, then on approaching nearer the unusual silence created
                        surprise. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When it was definitely learnt
                        that the camp was empty the men rushed in a body to the commanders' quarters
                        with the news that the enemy had fled in such haste that they left the tents
                        standing, and to secure greater secrecy for their flight had also left
                        numerous fires burning. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then a loud shout
                        arose demanding that the order should be given to advance, and that the men
                        should be led in pursuit, and that the camp should be plundered forthwith.
                        The one consul behaved as though he were one of the clamorous crowd; the
                        other, Paulus, repeatedly asserted the need of caution and circumspection.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At last, unable to deal with the
                        mutinous crowd and its leader in any other way, he sent Marius Statilius
                        with his troop of Lucanian horse to reconnoitre. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> When he had ridden up to the gates of the camp he
                        ordered his men to halt outside the lines, he himself with two of his
                        troopers entered the camp and after a careful and thorough examination he
                        brought back word that there was certainly a trick somewhere, the fires were
                        left <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> on the side of the camp which
                        fronted the Romans, the tents were standing open with all the valuables
                        exposed to view, in some parts he had seen silver lying about on the paths
                        as though it had been put there for plunder. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> So far from deterring the soldiers from satisfying their greed, as it was
                        intended to do, this report only inflamed it, and a shout arose that if the
                        signal was not given they would go on without their generals. There was no
                        lack of a general, however, for Varro instantly gave the signal to advance.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Paulus, who was hanging back, received
                        a report from the keeper of the sacred chickens that they had not given a
                        favourable omen, and he ordered the report to be at once carried to his
                        colleague as he was just marching out of the camp gates. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Varro was very much annoyed, but the recollection of
                        the disaster which overtook Flaminius and the naval defeat which the consul
                        Claudius sustained in the first Punic war made him afraid of acting in an
                        irreligious spirit. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It seemed as though
                        the gods themselves on that day delayed, if they did actually do away, the
                        fatal doom which was impending over the Romans. For it so happened that
                        whilst the soldiers were ignoring the consul's order for the standards to be
                        carried back into camp, two slaves, one belonging to a trooper from Formiae,
                        the other to one from Sidicinum, who had been captured with the foraging
                        parties when Servilius and Atilius were in command, had that day escaped to
                        their former masters. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They were taken
                        before the consul and told him that the whole of Hannibal's army was lying
                        behind the nearest hills. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The opportune
                        arrival of these men restored the authority of the consuls, though one of
                        them in his desire to be popular had weakened his authority by his
                        unscrupulous connivance at breaches of discipline. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hannibal saw that the ill-considered
                        movement which the Romans had commenced was not recklessly carried out to
                        its final stage, and that his ruse had been detected, he returned to camp.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Owing to the want of corn he was
                        unable to remain there many days, and fresh plans were continually cropping
                        up, not only amongst the soldiers, who were a medley of all nations, but
                        even in the mind of the general himself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Murmurs gradually swelled into loud and angry protests as the men demanded
                        their arrears of pay, and complained of the starvation which they were
                        enduring, and in addition, a rumour was started that the mercenaries,
                        chiefly those of Spanish nationality, had formed a plot to desert.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Even Hannibal himself, it is said,
                        sometimes thought of leaving his infantry behind and hurrying with his
                        cavalry into Gaul. With these plans being discussed and this temper
                        prevailing amongst the men, he decided to move into <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> the warmer parts of Apulia, where the harvest was
                        earlier and where, owing to the greater distance from the enemy, desertion
                        would be rendered more difficult for the fickle-minded part of his force. As
                        on the previous occasion, he ordered camp-fires to be lighted, and a few
                        tents left where they could be easily seen, in order that the Romans,
                        remembering a similar stratagem, might be afraid to move. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> However, Statilius was again sent to reconnoitre with
                        his Lucanians, and he made a thorough examination of the country beyond the
                        camp and over the mountains. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He reported
                        that he had caught a distant view of the enemy in line of march, and the
                        question of pursuit was discussed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As
                        usual, the views of the two consuls were opposed, but almost all present
                        supported Varro, not a single voice was given in favour of Paulus, except
                        that of Servilius, consul in the preceding year. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The opinion of the majority of the council prevailed,
                        and so, driven by destiny, they went forward to render Cannae famous in the
                        annals of Roman defeats. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was in the
                        neighbourhood of this village that Hannibal had fixed his camp with his back
                        to the Sirocco which blows from Mount Vultur and fills the arid plains with
                        clouds of dust. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This arrangement was a
                        very convenient one for his camp, and it proved to be extremely advantageous
                        afterwards, when he was forming his order of battle, for his own men, with
                        the wind behind them, blowing only on their backs, would fight with an enemy
                        who was blinded by volumes of dust. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls followed the Carthaginians,
                        carefully examining the roads as they marched, and when they reached Cannae
                        and had the enemy in view they formed two entrenched camps separated by the
                        same interval as at Gereonium, and with the same distribution of troops in
                        each camp. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The river Aufidus, flowing past
                        the two camps, furnished a supply of water which the soldiers got as they
                        best could, and they generally had to fight for it. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The men in the smaller camp, which was on the other
                        side of the river, had less difficulty in obtaining it, as that bank was not
                        held by the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal now saw his
                        hopes fulfilled, that the consuls would give him an opportunity of fighting
                        on ground naturally adapted for the movements of cavalry, the arm in which
                        he had so far been invincible, and accordingly he placed his army in order
                        of battle, and tried to provoke his foe to action by repeated charges of his
                        Numidians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman camp was again
                        disturbed by a mutinous soldiery and consuls at variance, Paulus bringing up
                        against Varro the fatal rashness of Sempronius and Flaminius, Varro
                        retorting by pointing to Fabius as the favourite model of cowardly and inert
                        commanders, and calling gods and men to witness that it was through no fault
                        of his that Hannibal had acquired, so to speak, a prescriptive right to
                        Italy; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> he had had his hands tied by his
                        colleague; his soldiers, furious and eager for fight, had had their swords
                        and arms taken away from them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Paulus, on
                        the other hand, declared that if anything happened to the legions flung
                        recklessly and betrayed into an ill-considered and imprudent action, he was
                        free from all responsibility for it, though he would have to share in all
                        the consequences. "See to it," he said to Varro, "that those who are so free
                        and ready with their tongues are equally so with their hands in the day of
                        battle." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst time was thus being wasted in
                        disputes instead of deliberation, Hannibal withdrew the bulk of his army,
                        who had been standing most of the day in order of battle, into camp.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He sent his Numidians, however, across
                        the river to attack the parties who were getting water for the smaller camp.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They had hardly gained the opposite
                        bank when with their shouting and uproar they sent the crowd flying in wild
                        disorder, and galloping on as far as the outpost in front of the rampart,
                        they nearly reached the gates of the camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        It was looked upon as such an insult for a Roman camp to be actually
                        terrorised by irregular auxiliaries that one thing, and one thing alone,
                        held back the Romans from instantly crossing the river and forming their
                        battle line-the supreme command that day rested with Paulus. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The following day Varro, whose turn it now was,
                        without any consultation with his colleague, exhibited the signal for battle
                        and led his forces drawn up for action across the river. Paulus followed,
                        for though he disapproved of the measure, he was bound to support it.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After crossing, they strengthened
                        their line with the force in the smaller camp and completed their formation.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the right, which was nearest to the
                        river, the Roman cavalry were posted, then came the infantry; on the extreme
                        left were the cavalry of the allies, their infantry were between them and
                        the Roman legions. The javelin men with the rest of the light-armed
                        auxiliaries formed the front line. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        consuls took their stations on the wings, Terentius Varro on the left,
                        Aemilius Paulus on the right. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as it grew light Hannibal sent
                        forward the Balearics and the other light infantry. He then crossed the
                        river in person and as each division was brought across he assigned it its
                        place in the line. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Gaulish and Spanish
                        horse he posted near the bank on the left wing in front of the Roman
                        cavalry; the right wing was assigned to the Numidian troopers. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The centre consisted of a strong force of
                        infantry, the Gauls and Spaniards in the middle, the Africans at either end
                        of them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> You might fancy that the Africans
                        were for the most part a body of Romans from the way they were armed, they
                        were so completely equipped with the arms, some of which they had taken at
                        the Trebia, but the most part at Trasumennus. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The Gauls and Spaniards had shields almost of the same
                        shape their swords were totally different, those of the Gauls being very
                        long and without a point, the Spaniard, accustomed to thrust more than to
                        cut, had a short handy sword, pointed like a dagger. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> These nations, more than any other, inspired terror by
                        the vastness of their stature and their frightful appearance: the Gauls were
                        naked above the waist, the Spaniards had taken up their position wearing
                        white tunics embroidered with purple, of dazzling brilliancy. The total
                        number of infantry in the field was 40,000, and there were 10,000 cavalry.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal was in command of the left
                        wing, Maharbal of the right; Hannibal himself with his brother Mago
                        commanded the centre. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was a great
                        convenience to both armies that the sun shone obliquely on them, whether it
                        was that they had purposely so placed themselves, or whether it happened by
                        accident, since the Romans faced the north, the Carthaginans the South.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The wind, called by the inhabitants
                        the Vulturnus, was against the Romans, and blew great clouds of dust into
                        their faces, making it impossible for them to see in front of them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the battle shout was raised the
                        auxiliaries ran forward, and the battle began with the light infantry. Then
                        the Gauls and Spaniards on the left engaged the Roman cavalry on the right;
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the battle was not at all like a
                        cavalry fight, for there was no room for maneuvering, the river on the one
                        side and the infantry on the other hemming them in, compelled them to fight
                        face to face. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Each side tried to force
                        their way straight forward, till at last the horses were standing in a
                        closely pressed mass, and the riders seized their opponents and tried to
                        drag them from their horses. It had become mainly a struggle of infantry,
                        fierce but short, and the Roman cavalry was repulsed and fled. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Just as this battle of the cavalry was finished,
                        the infantry became engaged, and as long as the Gauls and Spaniards kept
                        their ranks unbroken, both sides were equally matched in strength and
                        courage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At length after long and repeated
                        efforts the Romans closed up their ranks, echeloned their front, and by the
                        sheer weight of their deep column bore down the division of the enemy which
                        was stationed in front of Hannibal's line, and was too thin and weak to
                        resist the pressure. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Without a moment's
                        pause they followed up their broken and hastily retreating foe till they
                        took to headlong flight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cutting their way
                        through the mass of fugitives, who offered no resistance, they penetrated as
                        far as the Africans who were stationed on both wings, somewhat further back
                        than the Gauls and Spaniards who had formed the advanced centre. As the
                        latter fell back the whole front became level, and as they continued to give
                        ground it became concave and crescent-shaped, the Africans at either end
                        forming the horns. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As the Romans rushed on
                        incautiously between them, they were enfiladed by the two wings, which
                        extended and closed round them in the rear. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> On this, the Romans, who had fought one battle to no purpose, left the
                        Gauls and Spaniards, whose rear they had been slaughtering, and commenced a
                        fresh struggle with the Africans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        contest was a very one-sided one, for not only were they hemmed in on all
                        sides, but wearied with the previous fighting they were meeting fresh and
                        vigorous opponents. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time the Roman left wing, where
                        the allied cavalry were fronting the Numidians, had become engaged, but the
                        fighting was slack at first owing to a Carthaginian stratagem. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> About 500 Numidians, carrying, besides their
                        usual arms and missiles, swords concealed under their coats of mail, rode
                        out from their own line with their shields slung behind their backs as
                        though they were deserters, and suddenly leaped from their horses and flung
                        their shields and javelins at the feet of their enemy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They were received into their ranks, conducted to the
                        rear, and ordered to remain quiet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While
                        the battle was spreading to the various parts of the field they remained
                        quiet, but when the eyes and minds of all were wholly taken up with the
                        fighting they seized the large Roman shields which were lying everywhere
                        amongst the heaps of slain and commenced a furious attack upon the rear of
                        the Roman line. Slashing away at backs and hips, they made a great slaughter
                        and a still greater panic and confusion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Amidst the rout and panic in one part of the field and the obstinate but
                        hopeless struggle in the other, Hasdrubal, who was in command of that arm,
                        withdrew some Numidians from the centre of the right wing, where the
                        fighting was feebly kept up, and sent them m pursuit of the fugitives, and
                        at <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the same time sent the Spanish and
                        Gaulish horse to the aid of the Africans, who were by this time more wearied
                        by slaughter than by fighting. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Paulus was on the other side of the field.
                        In spite of his having been seriously wounded at the <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> commencement of the action by a bullet from a sling, he
                        frequently encountered Hannibal with a compact body of troops, and in
                        several places restored the battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        Roman cavalry formed a bodyguard round him, but at last, as he became too
                        weak to manage his horse, they all dismounted. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> It is stated that when some one reported to Hannibal
                        that the consul had ordered his men to fight on foot, he remarked, "I would
                        rather he handed them over to me bound hand and foot.'' Now that the victory
                        of the enemy was no longer doubtful this struggle of the dismounted cavalry
                        was such as might be <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> expected when men
                        preferred to die where they stood rather than flee, and the victors, furious
                        at them for delaying the victory, butchered without mercy those whom they
                        could not dislodge. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They did, however,
                        repulse a few survivors exhausted with their exertions and their wounds. All
                        were at last scattered, and those who could regained their horses for
                        flight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cn. Lentulus, a military tribune,
                        saw, as he rode by, the consul covered with blood sitting on a boulder.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "Lucius Aemilius," he said, "the one
                        man whom the gods must hold guiltless of this day's disaster, take this
                        horse while you have still some strength left, and I can lift you into the
                        saddle and keep by your side to protect you. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> Do not make this day of battle still more fatal by a consul's death,
                        there are enough tears and mourning without that." <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The consul replied: "Long may you live to do brave
                        deeds, Cornelius, but do not waste in useless pity the few moments left in
                        which to escape from the hands of the enemy. Go, announce publicly to the
                        senate that they must fortify Rome and make its defence strong before the
                        victorious enemy approaches, and tell Q. Fabius privately that I have ever
                        remembered his precepts in life and in death. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Suffer me to breathe my last among my slaughtered
                        soldiers, let me not have to defend myself again when I am <milestone
                            n="12??" unit="section"/> no longer consul, or appear as the accuser of
                        my colleague and protect my own innocence by throwing the guilt on another."
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> During this conversation a crowd of
                        fugitives came suddenly upon them, followed by the enemy, who, not knowing
                        who the consul was, overwhelmed him with a shower of missiles. Lentulus
                        escaped on horseback in the rush. Then there was flight in all directions;
                        7000 men escaped to the smaller camp, 10,000 to the larger, and about 2000
                        to the village of Cannae. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> These latter
                        were at once surrounded by Carthalo and his cavalry, as the village was
                        quite unfortified. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The other consul, who
                        either by accident or design had not joined any of these bodies of
                        fugitives, escaped with about fifty cavalry to Venusia; 45,500 infantry,
                        2700 cavalry-almost an equal proportion of Romans and allies-are said to
                        have been killed. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Amongst the number were
                        both the quaestors attached to the consuls, L. Atilius and L. Furius
                        Bibulcus, twenty-nine military tribunes, several ex-consuls, ex-praetors,
                        and ex-aediles (amongst them are included Cn. Servilius Geminus and M.
                        Minucius, who was Master of the Horse the previous year and, <milestone
                            n="17??" unit="section"/> some years before that, consul), and in
                        addition to these, eighty men who had either been senators or filled offices
                        qualifying them for election to the senate and who had volunteered for
                        service with the legions. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The prisoners
                        taken in the battle are stated to have amounted to 3000 infantry and 1500
                        cavalry. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the battle of Cannae, a battle as
                        famous as the disastrous one at the Allia; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        not so serious in its results, owing to the inaction of the enemy, but more
                        serious and more horrible in view of the slaughter of the army. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> For the flight at the Allia saved the army though
                        it lost the City, whereas at Cannae hardly fifty men shared the consul's
                        flight, nearly the whole army met their death in company with the other
                        consul. As those who had taken refuge in the two camps were only a
                        defenceless crowd without any leaders, the men in the larger camp sent a
                        message to the others asking them to cross over to them at night when the
                        enemy, tired after the battle and the feasting in honour of their <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> victory, would be buried in sleep. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Then they would go in one body to Canusium. Some
                        rejected the proposal with scorn. "Why," they asked, "cannot those who sent
                        the message come themselves, since they are quite as able to join us as we
                        to join them? Because, of course, all the country between us is scoured by
                        the enemy and they prefer to expose other people to that deadly peril rather
                        than themselves." Others did not disapprove of the proposal, but they lacked
                        courage to carry it out. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> P. Sempronius
                        Tuditanus protested against this cowardice. "Would you," he asked, "rather
                        be taken prisoners by a most avaricious and ruthless foe and a price put
                        upon your heads and your value assessed after you have been asked whether
                        you are a Roman citizen or a Latin ally, in order that another may win
                        honour from your misery and disgrace? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Certainly not, if you are really the fellow-countrymen of L. Aemilius, who
                        chose a noble death rather than a life of degradation, and of all the brave
                        men who are lying in heaps around him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        But, before daylight overtakes us and the enemy gathers in larger force to
                        bar our path, let us cut our way through the men who in disorder and
                        confusion are clamouring at our gates. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Good swords and brave hearts make a way through enemies, however densely
                        they are massed. If you march shoulder to shoulder you will scatter this
                        loose and disorganised force as easily as if nothing opposed you. Come then
                        with me, all you who want to preserve yourselves and the State." <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> With these words he drew his sword, and with his
                        men in close formation marched through the very midst of the enemy.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When the Numidians hurled their
                        javelins on the right, the unprotected side, they transferred their shields
                        to their right arms, and so got clear away to the larger camp As many as 600
                        escaped on this occasion, and after another large body had joined them they
                        at once left the camp and came through safely to Canusium. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> This action on the part of defeated men was due to the
                        impulse of natural courage or of accident rather than to any concerted plan
                        of their own or any one's generalship. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal's officers all surrounded him and
                        congratulated him on his victory, and urged that after such a magnificent
                        success he should allow himself and his exhausted men to rest for the
                        remainder of the day and the following night. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Maharbal, however, the commandant of the cavalry,
                        thought that they ought not to lose a moment. "That you may know," he said
                        to Hannibal, "what has been gained by this battle I prophesy that in five
                        days you will be feasting as victor in the Capitol. Follow me; I will go in
                        advance with the cavalry; they will know that you are come before they know
                        that you are coming." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To Hannibal the
                        victory seemed too great and too joyous for him to realise all at once. He
                        told Maharbal that he commended his zeal, but he needed time to think out
                        his plans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Maharbal replied: "The gods
                        have not given all their gifts to one man. You know how to win victory,
                        Hannibal, you do not how to use it." That day's delay is believed to have
                        saved the City and the empire. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next
                        day, as soon as it grew light, they set about gathering the spoils on the
                        field and viewing the carnage, which was a ghastly sight even for an enemy.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There all those thousands of Romans
                        were lying, infantry and cavalry indiscriminately as chance had brought them
                        together in the battle or the flight. Some covered with blood raised
                        themselves from amongst the dead around them, tortured by their wounds which
                        were nipped by the cold of the morning, and were promptly put an end to by
                        the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some they found lying with
                        their thighs and knees gashed but still alive; these bared their throats and
                        necks and bade them drain what blood they still had left. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Some were discovered with their heads buried in the
                        earth, they had evidently suffocated themselves by making holes in the
                        ground and heaping the soil over their faces. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> What attracted the attention of all was a Numidian who
                        was dragged alive from under a dead Roman lying across him; his ears and
                        nose were torn, for the Roman with hands too powerless to grasp his weapon
                        had, in his mad rage, torn his enemy with his teeth, and while doing so
                        expired. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="52" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After most of the day had been spent in
                        collecting the spoils, Hannibal led his men to the attack on the smaller
                        camp and commenced operations by throwing up a breastwork to cut off their
                        water supply from the river. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As, however,
                        all the defenders were exhausted by toil and want of sleep, as well as by
                        wounds, the surrender was effected sooner than he had anticipated. They
                        agreed to give up their arms and horses, and to pay for each Roman three
                        hundred "chariot pieces," for each ally two hundred, and for each officer's
                        servant one hundred, on condition that after the money was <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> paid they should be allowed to depart with one
                        garment apiece. Then they admitted the enemy into the camp and were all
                        placed under guard, the Romans and the allies separately. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst time was being spent there, all those in the
                        larger camp, who had sufficient strength and courage, to the number of 4000
                        infantry and 200 cavalry, made their escape to Canusium, some in a body,
                        others straggling through the fields, which was quite as safe a thing to do.
                        Those who were wounded and those who had been afraid to venture surrendered
                        the camp on the same terms as had been agreed upon in the other camp.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> An immense amount of booty was
                        secured, and the whole of it was made over to the troops with the exception
                        of the horses and prisoners and whatever silver there might be. Most of this
                        was on the trappings of the horses, for they used very little silver plate
                        at table, at all events when on a campaign. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> Hannibal then ordered the bodies of his own soldiers to be collected for
                        burial; it is said that there were as many as 8000 of his best troops.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some authors state that he also had a
                        search made for the body of the Roman consul, which he buried. Those who had
                        escaped to Canusium were simply allowed shelter within its walls and houses,
                        but a high-born and wealthy Apulian lady, named Busa, assisted them with
                        corn and clothes and even provisions for their journey. For this munificence
                        the senate, at the close of the war, voted her public honours </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="53" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although there were four military tribunes
                        on the spot-Fabius Maximus of the first legion, whose father had been lately
                        Dictator, L. Publicius Bibulus and Publius Cornelius Scipio of <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> the second legion, and Appius Claudius Pulcher
                        of the third legion, who had just been aedile-the supreme command was by
                        universal consent vested in P. Scipio, who was quite a youth, and Appius
                        Claudius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were holding a small
                        council to discuss the state of affairs when P. Furius Philus, the son of an
                        ex-consul, informed them that it was useless for them to cherish ruined
                        hopes; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the republic was despaired of and
                        given over for lost; some young nobles with L. Caecilius Metellus at their
                        head were turning their eyes seaward with the intention of abandoning Italy
                        to its fate and transferring their services to some king or other.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This evil news, terrible as it was and
                        coming fresh on the top of all their other disasters, paralysed those who
                        were present with wonder and amazement. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        They thought that a council ought to be summoned to deal with it, but young
                        Scipio, the general destined to end this war, said that it was no business
                        for a council. In such an emergency as that they must dare and act, not
                        deliberate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> "Let those," he cried, "who
                        want to save the republic take their arms at once and follow me. No camp is
                        more truly a hostile camp than one in which such treason is meditated."
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He started off with a few followers to
                        the house <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> where Metellus was lodging,
                        and finding the young men about whom the report had been made gathered there
                        in council, he held his naked sword over the heads of the conspirators and
                        uttered these words: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "I solemnly swear
                        that I will not abandon the Republic of Rome, nor will I suffer any other
                        Roman citizen to do so; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> if I knowingly
                        break my oath, then do thou, O Jupiter Optimus Maximus, visit me, my home,
                        my family, and my estate with utter destruction. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> I require you, L. Caecilius, and all who are here
                        present, to take this oath. Whoever will not swear let him know that this
                        sword is drawn against him." <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They were in
                        as great a state of fear as though they saw the victorious Hannibal amongst
                        them, and all took the oath and surrendered themselves into Scipio's
                        custody. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="54" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these things were happening at
                        Canusium, as many as 4500 infantry and cavalry, who had been dispersed in
                        flight over the country, succeeded in reaching the consul at Venusia.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The inhabitants received them with
                        every mark of kindness and distributed them all amongst their households to
                        be taken care of. They gave each of the troopers a toga and a tunic and
                        twenty-five "chariot pieces," and to each legionary ten pieces, and whatever
                        arms they required. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All hospitality was
                        shown them both by the government and by private citizens, for the people of
                        Venusia were determined not to be outdone in kindness by a lady of Canusium.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the large number of men, which now
                        amounted to something like 10,000, made the burden imposed upon Busa much
                        heavier. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For Appius and Scipio, on hearing
                        that the consul was safe, at once sent to him to inquire what amount of foot
                        and horse he had with him, and also whether he wanted the army to be taken
                        to Venusia or to remain at Canusium. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Varro
                        transferred his forces to Canusium, and now there was something like a
                        consular army; it seemed as though they would defend themselves successfully
                        behind their walls if not in the open field. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The reports which reached Rome left no room for hope that even these
                        remnants of citizens and allies were still surviving; it was asserted that
                        the army with its two consuls had been annihilated and the whole of the
                        forces wiped out. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Never before, while the
                        City itself was still safe, had there been such excitement and panic within
                        its walls. I shall not attempt to describe it, nor will I weaken the reality
                        by going into details. After the loss of the consul and the army at
                        Trasumennus the previous year, it was not wound upon wound but multiplied
                        disaster that was now announced. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For
                        according to the reports two consular armies and two consuls were lost;
                        there was no longer any Roman camp, any general, any single soldier in
                        existence; Apulia, Samnium, almost the whole of Italy lay at Hannibal's
                        feet. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Certainly there is no other nation
                        that would not have succumbed beneath such a weight of calamity. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> One might, of course, compare the naval defeat
                        of the Carthaginians at the Aegates, which broke their power to such an
                        extent that they gave up Sicily and Sardinia and submitted to the payment of
                        tribute and a war indemnity; or, again, the battle which they lost in
                        Africa, in which Hannibal himself was crushed. But there is no point of
                        comparison between these and Cannae, unless it be that they were borne with
                        less fortitude. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="55" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> P. Furius Philus and M. Pomponius, the
                        praetors, called a meeting of the senate to take measures for the defence of
                        the City, for no doubt was felt that after <milestone n="2??" unit="section"
                        /> wiping out the armies the enemy would set about his one remaining task
                        and advance to attack Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the
                        presence of evils the extent of which, great as they were, was still
                        unknown, they were unable even to form any definite plans, and the cries of
                        wailing women deafened their ears, for as the facts were not yet ascertained
                        the living and the dead were being indiscriminately bewailed in almost every
                        house. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Under these circumstances Q. Fabius
                        Maximus gave it as his opinion that swift horsemen should be sent along the
                        Appian and Latin roads to make inquiries of those they met, for there would
                        be sure to be fugitives scattered about the country, and bring back tidings
                        as to what had befallen the consuls and the armies, and if the gods out of
                        compassion for the empire had left any remnant of the Roman nation, to find
                        out where those forces were. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And also they
                        might ascertain whither Hannibal had repaired after the battle, what plans
                        he was forming, what he was doing or likely to do. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They must get some young and active men to find out
                        these things, and as there were hardly any magistrates in the City, the
                        senators must themselves take steps to calm the agitation and alarm which
                        prevailed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They must keep the matrons out
                        of the public streets and compel them to remain indoors; they must suppress
                        the loud laments for the dead and impose silence on the City; they must see
                        that all who brought tidings were taken to the praetors, and that the
                        citizens should, each in his own house, wait for any news which affected
                        them personally. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Moreover, they must
                        station guards at the gates to prevent any one from leaving the City, and
                        they must make it clear to every man that the only safety he can hope for
                        lies in the City and its walls. When the tumult has once been hushed, then
                        the senate must be again convened and measures discussed for the defence of
                        the City. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="56" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This proposal was unanimously carried
                        without any discussion. After the crowd was cleared out of the Forum by the
                        magistrates and the senators had gone in various directions to allay the
                        agitation, a despatch at last arrived from C. Terentius Varro. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> He wrote that L. Aemilius was killed and his army
                        cut to pieces; he himself was at Canusium collecting the wreckage that
                        remained from this awful disaster; there were as many as 10,000 soldiers,
                        irregular, unorganised; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the Carthaginian
                        was still at Cannae, bargaining about the prisoners' ransom and the rest of
                        the plunder in a spirit very unlike that of a great and victorious general.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The next thing was the publication of
                        the names of those killed, and the City was thrown into such universal
                        mourning that the annual celebration of the festival of Ceres was suspended,
                        because it is forbidden to those in mourning to take part in it, and there
                        was not a single matron who was not a mourner during those days. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> In order that the same cause might not prevent
                        other sacred observances from being duly honoured, the period of mourning
                        was limited by a senatorial decree to thirty days. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> When the agitation was quieted and the senate resumed
                        its session, a fresh despatch was received, this time from Sicily. T.
                        Otacilius, the propraetor, announced that Hiero's kingdom was being
                        devastated by a Carthaginian fleet, and when he was preparing to render
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> him the assistance he asked for, he
                        received news that another fully equipped fleet was riding at anchor off the
                        Aegates, and when they heard that he was occupied with the defence of the
                        Syracusan shore they would at once attack Lilybaeum and the rest of the
                        Roman province. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If, therefore, the senate
                        wished to retain the king as their ally and keep their hold on Sicily, they
                        must fit out a fleet. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="57" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the despatches from the consul and
                        the praetor had been read it was decided that M. Claudius, who was
                        commanding the fleet stationed at Ostia, should be sent to the army at
                        Canusium and instructions forwarded to the consul requesting him to hand
                        over his command to the praetor and come to Rome as soon as he possibly
                        could consistently with his duty to the republic. For, over and above these
                        serious disasters, considerable alarm was created by portents which
                        occurred. Two Vestal virgins, Opimia and Floronia, were found guilty of
                        unchastity. One was buried alive, as is the custom, at the Colline Gate, the
                        other committed suicide. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> L. Cantilius, one
                        of the pontifical secretaries, <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> now
                        called "minor pontiffs," who had been guilty with Floronia, was scourged in
                        the Comitium by the Pontifex Maximus so severely that he died under it.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This act of wickedness, coming as it
                        did amongst so many calamities, was, as often happens, regarded as a
                        portent, and the decemvirs were ordered to consult the Sacred Books.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Q. Fabius Pictor was sent to consult
                        the oracle of Delphi as to what forms of prayer and supplication they were
                        to use to propitiate the gods, and what was to be the end of all these
                        terrible disasters. Meanwhile, in obedience to the Books of Destiny, some
                        strange and unusual sacrifices were made, human sacrifices amongst them.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A Gaulish man and a Gaulish woman and
                        a Greek man and a Greek woman were buried alive under the Forum Boarium.
                        They were lowered into a stone vault, which had on a previous occasion also
                        been polluted by human victims, a practice most repulsive to Roman feelings. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the gods were believed to be duly
                        propitiated, M. Claudius Marcellus sent from Ostia 1500 men who had been
                        enrolled for service with the fleet to garrison Rome; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> the naval legion (the third) he sent on in advance with
                        the military tribunes to Teanum Sidicinum, and then, handing the fleet over
                        to his colleague, P. Furius Philus, hastened on by forced marches a few days
                        later to Canusium. On the authority of the senate M. Junius was nominated
                        Dictator and Ti. Sempronius Master of the Horse. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> A levy was ordered, and all from seventeen years
                        upwards were enrolled, some even younger; out of these recruits four legions
                        were formed and 1000 cavalry. They also sent to the Latin confederacy and
                        the other allied states to enlist soldiers according to the terms of their
                        treaties. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Armour, weapons, and other
                        things of the kind were ordered to be in readiness, and the ancient spoils
                        gathered from the enemy were taken down from the temples and colonnades.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The dearth of freemen necessitated a
                        new kind of enlistment; 8000 sturdy youths from amongst the slaves were
                        armed at the public cost, after they had each been asked whether they were
                        willing to serve or no. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These soldiers
                        were preferred, as there would be an opportunity of ransoming them when
                        taken prisoners at a lower price. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="58" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After his great success at Cannae,
                        Hannibal made his arrangements more as though his victory were a complete
                        and decisive one than as if the war were still going on. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The prisoners were brought before him and separated
                        into two groups; the allies were treated as they had been at the Trebia and
                        at Trasumennus, after some kind words they were dismissed without ransom;
                        the Romans, too, were treated as they had never been before, for when they
                        appeared before him he addressed them in quite a friendly way. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> He had no deadly feud, he told them, with Rome,
                        all he was fighting for was his country's honour as a sovereign power. His
                        fathers had yielded to Roman courage, his one object now was that the Romans
                        should yield to his good fortune and courage. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He now gave the prisoners permission to ransom
                        themselves; each horseman at 500 "chariot pieces" and each foot-soldier at
                        300, and the slaves at 100 per head. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This
                        was somewhat more than the cavalry had agreed to when they surrendered, but
                        they were only too glad to accept any terms. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> It was settled that they should elect ten of their number to go to the
                        senate at Rome, and the only guarantee required was that they should take an
                        oath to return. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were accompanied by
                        Carthalo, a Carthaginian noble, who was to sound the feelings of the
                        senators, and if they were inclined towards peace he was to propose terms.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the delegates had left the camp,
                        one of them, a man of an utterly un-Roman temper, returned to the camp, as
                        if he had forgotten something, and in this way hoped to free himself from
                        his oath. He rejoined his comrades before nightfall. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> When it was announced that the party were on their way
                        to Rome a lictor was despatched to meet Carthalo and order him in the name
                        of the Dictator to quit the territory of Rome before night. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="59" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Dictator admitted the prisoners'
                        delegates to an audience of the senate. Their leader, M. Junius, spoke as
                        follows: "Senators: we are every one of us aware that no State has held its
                        prisoners of war of less account than our own, but, unless <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> we think our case a better one than we have any
                        right to do, we would urge that none have ever fallen into the hands of the
                        enemy who were more deserving of consideration than we are. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> For we did not give up our arms during the battle from
                        sheer cowardice; standing on the heaps of the slain we kept up the struggle
                        till close on night, and only then did we retire into camp; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> for the remainder of the day and all through the night
                        we defended our entrenchments; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the
                        following day we were surrounded by the victorious army and cut off from the
                        water, and there was no hope whatever now of our forcing our way through the
                        dense masses of the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> We did not
                        think it a crime for some of Rome's soldiers to survive the battle of
                        Cannae, seeing that 50,000 men had been butchered there, and therefore in
                        the very last resort we consented to have a price fixed for our ransom and
                        surrendered to the enemy those arms which were no longer of the slightest
                        use to us. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Besides, we had heard that our
                        ancestors had ransomed themselves from the Gauls with gold, and that your
                        fathers, sternly as they set themselves against all conditions of peace, did
                        nevertheless send delegates to Tarentum to arrange the ransom of the
                        prisoners. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But neither the battle at the
                        Alia against the Gauls nor that at Heraclea against Pyrrhus was disgraced by
                        the actual losses sustained so much as by the panic and flight which marked
                        them. The plains of Cannae are covered by heaps of Roman dead, and we should
                        not be here now if the enemy had not lacked arms and strength to slay us.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There are some amongst us who were
                        never in the battle at all, but were left to guard the camp, and when it was
                        surrendered they fell into the hands of the enemy. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> I do not envy the fortune or the circumstances of any
                        man, whether he be a fellow-citizen or a fellow-soldier, nor would I wish it
                        to be said that I had glorified myself by depreciating others, but this I
                        will say, not even those who fled from the battle, mostly without arms, and
                        did not stay their flight till they had reached Venusia or Canusium, can
                        claim precedence over us or boast that they are more of a defence to the
                        State than we are. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But you will find both
                        in them and in us good and gallant soldiers, only we shall be still more
                        eager to serve our country because it will be through your kindness that we
                        shall have been ransomed and restored to our fatherland. You have enlisted
                        men of all ages and of every condition; I hear that eight thousand slaves
                        are armed. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Our number is no less, and it
                        will not cost more to ransom us than it did to purchase them, but if I were
                        to compare ourselves as soldiers with them, I should be offering an insult
                        to the name of Roman. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I should think,
                        senators, that in deciding upon a matter like this, you should also take
                        into consideration, if you are disposed to be too severe, to what sort of an
                        enemy you are going to abandon us. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Is it
                        to a Pyrrhus, who treated his prisoners as though they were his guests? Is
                        it not rather to a barbarian, and what is worse, a Carthaginian, of whom it
                        is difficult to judge whether he is more rapacious or more cruel? <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Could you see the chains, the squalor, the
                        disgusting appearance of your fellow-citizens, the sight would, I am sure,
                        move you no less than if, on the other hand, you beheld your legions lying
                        scattered over the plains of Cannae. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> You
                        can behold the anxiety and the tears of our kinsmen as they stand in the
                        vestibule of your House and await your reply. If they are in such anxiety
                        and suspense about us and about those who are not here, what, think you,
                        must be the feelings of the men themselves whose life and liberty are at
                        stake? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Why, good heavens! even if
                        Hannibal, contrary to his nature, chose to be kind to us, we should still
                        think life not worth living after you had decided that we did not deserve to
                        be ransomed. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Years ago the prisoners who
                        were released by Pyrrhus without ransom returned to Rome, but they returned
                        in company with the foremost men of the State who had been sent to effect
                        their ransom. Am I to return to my native country as a citizen not thought
                        worth three hundred coins? Each of us has his own feelings, senators.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> I know that my life and person are at
                        stake, but I dread more the peril to my good name, in case we depart
                        condemned and repulsed by you; for men will never believe that you grudged
                        the cost." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="60" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No sooner had he finished than a tearful
                        cry arose from the crowd in the comitium; they stretched their hands towards
                        the Senate-house and implored the senators to give them back their children,
                        their brothers, and their relations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fear
                        and affection had brought even women amongst the crowd of men who thronged
                        the Forum. After the strangers had withdrawn the debate commenced in the
                        senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was great difference of
                        opinion; some said that they ought to be ransomed at the expense of the
                        State, others were of opinion that no public expense ought to be incurred,
                        but they ought not to be prevented from defraying the cost from private
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> sources, and in cases where ready
                        money was not available it should be advanced from the treasury on personal
                        security and mortgages. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When it came to
                        the turn of T. Manlius Torquatus, a man of old-fashioned and, some thought,
                        excessive strictness, to give his opinion, he is said to have spoken in
                        these terms: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "If the delegates had
                        confined themselves to asking that those who are in the hands of the enemy
                        might be ransomed, I should have stated my opinion in few words without
                        casting reflections on any of them, for all that would have been necessary
                        would be to remind you that you should maintain the custom and usage handed
                        down from our forefathers by setting an example necessary for military
                        discipline. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But as it is, since they have
                        almost treated their surrender to the enemy as a thing to be proud of, and
                        think it right that they should receive more consideration than the
                        prisoners taken in the field or those who reached Venusia and Canusium, or
                        even the consul himself, I will not allow you to remain in ignorance of what
                        actually happened. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I only wish that the
                        facts which I am about to allege could be brought before the army at
                        Canusium, which is best able to testify to each man's courage or cowardice,
                        or at least that we had before us P. Sempronius Tuditanus, for if these men
                        had followed him they would at this moment be in the Roman camp, not
                        prisoners in the hands of the foe. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "The enemy had nearly all returned to
                        their camp, tired out with fighting, to make merry over their victory, and
                        these men had the night clear for a sortie. Seven thousand men could easily
                        have made a sortie, even through dense masses of the enemy, but they did not
                        make any attempt to do so on their own initiative, nor would they follow any
                        one else. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nearly the whole night through
                        P. Sempronius Tuditanus was continually warning them and urging them to
                        follow him, whilst only a few of the enemy were watching their camp, whilst
                        all was quiet and silent, whilst the night could still conceal their
                        movements; before it was light they could reach safety and be protected by
                        the cities of our allies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If he had
                        spoken as that military tribune P. Decius spoke in the days of our fathers,
                        or as Calpurnius Flamma, in the first Punic war, when we were young men,
                        spoke to his three hundred volunteers whom he was leading to the capture of
                        a height situated in the very centre of the enemy's position: 'Let us,' he
                        exclaimed, 'die, my men, and by our death rescue our blockaded legions from
                        their peril'-if, I say, P. Sempronius had spoken thus, I should not regard
                        you as men, much less as Romans, if none had come forward as the comrade of
                        so brave a man. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But the way he pointed
                        out to you led to safety quite as much as to glory, he would have brought
                        you back to your country, your parents, your wives, and your children.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> You have not courage enough to save
                        yourselves; what would you do if you had to die for your country? All round
                        you on that day were lying fifty thousand dead, Romans and allies. If so
                        many examples of courage did not inspire you, nothing ever will. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> If such an awful disaster did not make you hold
                        your lives cheap, none will ever do so. It is whilst you are free men, with
                        all your rights as citizens, that you must show your love for your country,
                        or rather, while it is your country and you are its citizens. Now you are
                        showing that love too late, your rights forfeited, your citizenship
                        renounced, you have become the slaves of the Carthaginians. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Is money going to restore you to the position
                        which you have lost through cowardice and crime? <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> You would not listen to your own countryman Sempronius
                        when he bade you seize your arms and follow him, you did listen shortly
                        afterwards to Hannibal when he bade you give up your arms and betray your
                        camp. But why do I only charge these men with cowardice when I can prove
                        them guilty of actual crime? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> For not only
                        did they refuse to follow him when he gave them good advice, but they tried
                        to stop him and keep him back, until a body of truly brave men drew their
                        swords and drove back the cowards. P. Sempronius had actually to force his
                        way through his own countrymen before he could do so through the enemy!
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Would our country care to have such
                        as these for her citizens when, had all those who fought at Cannae been like
                        them, she would not have had amongst them a single citizen worth the name!
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Out of seven thousand men in arms
                        there were six hundred who had the courage to force their way, and returned
                        to their country free men with arms in their hands. The enemy did not stop
                        these six hundred, how safe the way would have been, do you not think? for a
                        force of almost two legions. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> You would
                        have to-day, senators, at Canusium 20,000 brave loyal soldiers; but as for
                        these men, how can they possibly be good and loyal citizens? <milestone
                            n="21" unit="section"/> And as to their being 'brave,' they do not even
                        themselves assert that-unless, indeed, some one chooses to imagine that
                        whilst they were trying to stop the others from making the sortie, they were
                        really encouraging them, or that, fully aware that their own timidity and
                        cowardice was the cause of their becoming slaves, they feel no grudge
                        towards the others for having won both safety and glory through their
                        courage. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Though they might have got away
                        in the dead of the night, they preferred to skulk in their tents and wait
                        for the daylight and with it the enemy. But you will say, if they lacked
                        courage to leave the camp they had courage enough to defend it bravely;
                        blockaded for several days and nights, they protected the rampart with their
                        arms, and themselves with the rampart; <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> at
                        last, after going to the utmost lengths of endurance and daring, when every
                        support of life failed, and they were so weakened by starvation that they
                        had not strength to bear the weight of their arms, they were in the end
                        conquered by the necessities of nature more than by the force of arms.
                            <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> What are the facts? At daybreak the
                        enemy approached the rampart; within two hours, without trying their fortune
                        in any conflict, they gave up their arms and themselves. This, you see, was
                        their two days' soldiership. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> When duty
                        called them to keep their line and fight they fled to their camp, when they
                        ought to have fought at the rampart they surrendered their camp; they are
                        useless alike in the field and in the camp. Am I to ransom you? <milestone
                            n="26" unit="section"/> When you ought to have made your way out of the
                        camp you hesitated and remained there, when it was obligatory for you to
                        remain there and defend the camp with your arms you gave up camp, arms, and
                        yourselves to the enemy. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> No, senators, I
                        do not think that those men ought to be ransomed any more than I should
                        think it right to surrender to Hannibal the men who forced their way out of
                        the camp through the midst of the enemy and by that supreme act of courage
                        restored themselves to their fatherland." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="61" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although most of the senators had
                        relations among the prisoners, there were two considerations which weighed
                        with them at the close of Manlius' speech. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        One was the practice of the State which from early times had shown very
                        little indulgence to prisoners of war. The other was the amount of money
                        that would be required, for they were anxious that the treasury should not
                        be exhausted, a large sum having been already paid out in purchasing and
                        arming the slaves, and they did not wish to enrich Hannibal who, according
                        to rumour, was in particular need of money. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> When the melancholy reply was given that the prisoners were not ransomed,
                        the prevailing grief was intensified by the loss of so many citizens, and
                        the delegates were accompanied to the gates by a weeping and protesting
                        crowd. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> One of them went to his home
                        because he considered himself released from his vow by his pretended return
                        to the camp. When this became known it was reported to the senate, and they
                        unanimously decided that he should be arrested and conveyed to Hannibal
                        under a guard furnished by the State. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        There is another account extant as to the fate of the prisoners. According
                        to this tradition ten came at first, and there was a debate in the senate as
                        to whether they should be allowed within the City or not; they were admitted
                        on the understanding that the senate would not grant them an audience.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As they stayed longer than was
                        generally expected, three other delegates arrived-L. Scribonius, C.
                        Calpurnius, and L. Manlius-and a relative of Scribonius who was a tribune of
                        the plebs made a motion in the senate to ransom the prisoners. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The senate decided that they should not be
                        ransomed, and the three who came last returned to Hannibal, but the ten
                        remained in Rome. They alleged that they had absolved themselves from their
                        oath because after starting on their journey they had returned to Hannibal
                        under the pretext of reviewing the list of the prisoners' names. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The question of surrendering them was hotly
                        debated in the senate, and those in favour of this course were beaten by
                        only a few votes. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Under the next censors,
                        however, they were so crushed beneath every mark of disgrace and infamy that
                        some of them immediately committed suicide; the others not only avoided the
                        Forum for all their after life, but almost shunned the light of day and the
                        faces of men. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It is easier to feel
                        astonishment at such discrepancies amongst our authorities than to determine
                        what is the truth. </p>
                    <p> How far that disaster surpassed previous ones is shown by one simple fact.
                        Up to that day the loyalty of our allies had remained unshaken, now it began
                        to waver, for no other reason, we may be certain, than that they despaired
                        of the maintenance of our empire. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                        tribes who revolted to the Carthaginians were the Atellani, the Calatini,
                        the Hirpini, a section of the Apulians, all the Samnite cantons with the
                        exception of the Pentri, all the Bruttii and the Lucanians. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> In addition to these, the Uzentini and almost
                        the whole of the coast of Magna Graecia, the people of Tarentum Crotona and
                        Locri, as well as all Cisalpine Gaul. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Yet, in spite of all their disasters and the revolt of their allies, no one
                        anywhere in Rome mentioned the word "Peace," either before the consul's
                        return or after his arrival when all the memories of their losses were
                        renewed. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Such a lofty spirit did the
                        citizens exhibit in those days that though the consul was coming back from a
                        terrible defeat for which they knew he was mainly responsible, he was met by
                        a vast concourse drawn from every class of society, and thanks were formally
                        voted to him because he "had not despaired of the republic." <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Had he been commander-in-chief of the
                        Carthaginians there was no torture to which he would not have been
                        subjected. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
