<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six - 22</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp> literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by </resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>

                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1849</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="765" xml:id="p.765"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Hannibal, after an uninterrupted march of four days and three nights, ar-
                        rives in Etruria, through the marshes, in which he lost an eye. Caius
                        Flaminius, the consul, an inconsiderate man, having gone forth in opposi-
                        tion to the omens, dug up the standards which could not otherwise be raised,
                        and been thrown from his horse immediately after he had mounted, is insnared
                        by Hannibal, and cut off by his army near the Thrasimene lake. Three
                        thousand who had escaped are placed in chains by Hannibal, in violation of
                        pledges given. Distress occasioned in Rome by the intelligence. The
                        Sibylline books consulted, and a sacred spring decreed. Fabius Maximus sent
                        as dictator against Hannibal, whom he frustrates by caution and delay.
                        Marcus Minucius, the master of the horse, a rash and impetuous man, inveighs
                        against the caution of Fabius, and obtains an equality of command with him.
                        The army is divided be- tween them, and Minucius engaging Hannibal in an
                        unfavourable position, is reduced to the extremity of danger, and is rescued
                        by the dictator, and places himself under his authority. Hannibal, after
                        ravaging Campania, is shut up by Fabius in a valley near the town of
                        Casilinum, but escapes by night, putting to flight the Romans on guard by
                        oxen with lighted faggots attached to their horns. Hannibal attempts to
                        excite a suspicion of the fidelity of Fabius by sparing his farm while
                        ravaging with fire the whole country around it. Aemilius Paulus and
                        Terentius Varro are routed at Cannœ, and forty thousand men slain, among
                        whom were Paulus the consul, eighty senators, and thirty who had served the
                        office of consul, praetor, or aedile. A design projected by some noble
                        youths of quitting Italy in despair after this calamity, is intrepidly
                        quashed by Publius Cornelius Scipio, a military tribune, afterwards surnamed
                        Afri- canus. Successes in Spain, eight thousand slaves are enlisted by the
                        Ro- mans, they refuse to ransom the captives, they go out in a body to meet
                        Varro, and thank him for not having despaired of the commonwealth. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> SPRING was now at hand, when Hannibal quitted
                    his winter quarters, having both attempted in vain to cross the Apennines, from
                    the intolerable cold, and having remained with great danger and alarm.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Gauls, whom the hope of plunder and
                    spoil had collected, when, instead of being themselves engaged in carrying and
                    driving away booty from the fields of others, they saw their own lands made the
                    seat of war, and burdened by the wintering of the armies of both parties, turned
                    their hatred back again from the Romans upon Hannibal; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and though plots were frequently concerted <pb n="766"
                        xml:id="p.766"/> against him by their chieftains, he was preserved by the
                    treachery they manifested towards each other; disclosing their conspiracy with
                    the same inconstancy with which they had conspired; and by changing sometimes
                    his dress, at other times the fashion of his hair, he protected himself from
                    treachery by deception. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> However, this fear was
                    the cause of his more speedily quitting his winter quarters. Meanwhile Cneius
                    Servilius, the consul, entered upon his office at Rome, on the ides of March.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There, when he had consulted the senate on
                    the state of the republic in general, the indignation against Flaminius was
                    rekindled. They said <quote> that they had created indeed two consuls, that they
                        had but one; for what regular authority had the other, or what auspices?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That their magistrates took these with
                        them from home, from the tutelar deities of themselves and the state, after
                        the celebration of the Latin holidays; the sacrifice upon the mountain being
                        completed, and the vows duly offered up in the Capitol: <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> that neither could an unofficial individual take the
                        auspices, nor could one who had gone from home without them, take them new,
                        and for the first time, in a foreign soil. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Prodigies announced from many places at the
                    same time, augmented the terror: in Sicily, that several darts belonging to the
                    soldiers had taken fire; and in Sardinia, that the staff of a horseman, who was
                    going His rounds upon a wall, took fire as he held it in his hand; that the
                    shores had blazed with frequent fires; that two shields had sweated blood at
                    Praeneste; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that redhot stones had fallen from
                    the heavens at Arpi; that shields were seen in the heavens, and the sun fighting
                    with the moon, at Capena; that two moons rose in the daytime; that the waters of
                    Caere had flowed mixed with blood; and that even the fountain of Hercules had
                    flowed sprinkled with spots of blood. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the
                    territory of Antium, that bloody ears of corn had fallen into the basket as they
                    were reaping. At Falerii, that the heavens appeared cleft as if with a great
                    chasm; and, that where it had opened, a vast light had shone forth; that the
                    prophetic tablets had spontaneously become less; and that one had fallen out
                    thus inscribed, <quote>Mars shakes his spear.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> During the same time, that the statue of Mars
                    at Rome, on the Appian way, had sweated at the sight of images of wolves.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At Capua, that there had been the
                    appearance of the heavens being on fire, and of the moon as falling amidst rain.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After these, credit <pb n="767"
                        xml:id="p.767"/> was given to prodigies of less magnitude: that the goats of
                    certain persons had borne wool; that a hen had changed herself into a cock; and
                    a cock into a hen: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> these things having been
                    laid before the senate as reported, the authors being conducted into the
                    senate-house, the consul took the sense of the fathers on religious affairs.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> It was decreed that those prodigies
                    should be expiated, partly with full-grown, partly with sucking victims; and
                    that a supplication should be made at every shrine for the space of three days;
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> that the other things should be done
                    accordingly as the gods should declare in their oracles to be agreeable to their
                    will when the decemviri had examined the books. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                    /> By the advice of the decemviri it was decreed, first, that a golden
                    thunderbolt of fifty pounds' weight should be made as an offering to Jupiter;
                    that offerings of silver should be presented to Juno and Minerva; that
                    sacrifices of full-grown victims should be offered to Juno Regina on the
                    Aventine; and to Juno Sospita at Lanuvium; that the matrons, contributing as
                    much money as might be convenient to each, should carry it to the Aventine, as a
                    present to Juno Regina; and that a lectisternium should be celebrated.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Moreover, that the very freed-women
                    should, according to their means, contribute money from which a present might be
                    made to Feronia. When these things were done, the decemviri sacrificed with the
                    larger victims in the forum at Ardea. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Lastly,
                    it being now the month of December, a sacrifice was made at the temple of Saturn
                    at Rome, and a lectisternium ordered, in which senators prepared the couch and a
                    public banquet. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Proclamation was made through
                    the city, that the Saturnalia should be kept for a day and a night; and the
                    people were commanded to account that day as a holiday, and observe it for ever. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the consul employs himself at Rome in
                    appeasing the gods and holding the levy, Hannibal, setting out from his winter
                    quarters, because it was reported that the consul Flaminius had now arrived at
                    Arretium, although a <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> longer but more
                    commodious route was pointed out to him, takes the nearer road through a marsh
                    where the Arno had, more than usual, overflowed its banks. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He ordered the Spaniards and Africans (in these lay the
                    strength of his veteran army) to lead, their own baggage being intermixed with
                    them, lest, being compelled to halt any where, they should want what <pb n="768"
                        xml:id="p.768"/> might be necessary for their use: the Gauls he ordered to
                    go next, that they might form the middle of the marching body; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> the cavalry to march in the rear: next, Mago with the
                    light-armed Numidians to keep the army together, particularly coercing the
                    Gauls, if, fatigued with exertion and the length of the march, as that nation is
                    wanting in vigour for such exertions, they should fall away or halt. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The van still followed the standards wherever the
                    guides did but lead them, through the exceeding deep and almost fathomless
                    eddies of the river, nearly swallowed up in mud, and plunging themselves in.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Gauls could neither support themselves
                    when fallen, nor raise themselves from the eddies. Nor did they sustain their
                    bodies with spirit, nor their minds with hope; some scarce dragging on their
                    wearied limbs; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> others dying where they had
                    once fallen, their spirits being subdued with fatigue, among the beasts which
                    themselves also lay prostrate in every place. But chiefly watching wore them
                    out, endured now for four days and three nights. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> When, the water covering every place, not a dry spot could be found where
                    they might stretch their weary bodies, they laid themselves down upon their
                    baggage, thrown in heaps into the waters. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Piles of beasts, which lay every where through the whole route, afforded a
                    necessary bed for temporary repose to those seeking any place which was not
                    under water. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal himself, riding on the
                    only remaining elephant, to be the higher from the water, contracted a disorder
                    in his eyes, at first from the unwholesomeness of the vernal air, which is
                    attended with transitions from heat to cold; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    and at length from watching, nocturnal damps, the marshy atmosphere disordering
                    his head, and because he had neither opportunity nor leisure for remedies, loses
                    one of them. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Many men and cattle having been lost thus
                    wretchedly, when at length he had emerged from the marshes, he pitches his camp
                    as soon as he could on dry ground. And here he received information, through the
                    scouts sent in advance, that the Roman army was round the walls of Arretium.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Next the plans and temper of the consul,
                    the situation of the country, the roads, the sources from which provisions might
                    be obtained, and whatever else it was useful to know; all these things he
                    ascertained by the most diligent inquiry. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    country was among the most fertile of Italy, the plains <pb n="769"
                        xml:id="p.769"/> of Etruria, between Faesulae and Arretium, abundant in its
                    supply of corn, cattle, and every other requisite. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The consul was haughty from his former consulship, and felt
                    no proper degree of reverence not only for the laws and the majesty of the
                    fathers, but even for the gods. This temerity, inherent in his nature, fortune
                    had fostered by a career of prosperity and success in civil and military
                    affairs. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thus it was sufficiently evident
                    that, heedless of gods and men, he would act in all cases with presumption and
                    precipitation; and, that he might fall the more readily into the errors natural
                    to him, the Carthaginian begins to fret and irritate him; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and leaving the enemy on his left, he takes the road to
                    Faesulae, and marching through the centre of Etruria, with intent to plunder, he
                    exhibits to the consul, in the distance, the greatest devastation he could with
                    fires and slaughters. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Flaminius, who would not
                    have rested even if the enemy had remained quiet; then, indeed, when he saw the
                    property of the allies driven and carried away almost before his eyes,
                    considering that it reflected disgrace upon him that the Carthaginian now
                    roaming at large through the heart of Italy, and marching without resistance to
                    storm the very walls of Rome, though every other person in the council advised
                    safe rather than showy measures, urging that he should wait for his colleague,
                    in order <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> that, joining their armies, they
                    might carry on the war with united courage and counsels; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and that, meanwhile, the enemy should be prevented from his
                    unrestrained freedom in plundering by the cavalry and the light-armed
                    auxiliaries; in a fury hurried out of the council, and at once gave out the
                    signal for marching and for battle. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Nay, rather,</quote> says he, <quote> let us lie before the walls of
                        Arretium, for here is our country, here our household gods. Let Hannibal,
                        slipping through our fingers, waste Italy through and through; and, ravaging
                        and burning every thing, let him arrive at the walls of Rome; nor let us
                        move hence till the fathers shall have summoned Flaminius from Arretium, as
                        they did Camillus of old from Veii. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While reproaching them thus, and in the act
                    of ordering the standards to be speedily pulled up, when he had sprung upon his
                    horse, the animal fell suddenly, and threw the unseated consul over his head.
                    All the bystanders being alarmed at this as an unhappy <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> omen in the commencement of the affair, in addition word is
                    brought, that the standard could <pb n="770" xml:id="p.770"/> not be pulled up,
                    though the standard-bearer strove with all his force. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Flaminius, turning to the messenger, says, <quote> Do you
                        bring, too, letters from the senate, forbidding me to act. Go, tell them to
                        dig up the standard, if, through fear, their hands are so benumbed that they
                        cannot pluck it up. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then the army began to march; the chief
                    officers, besides that they dissented from the plan, being terrified by the
                    two-fold prodigy; while the soldiery in general were elated by the confidence of
                    their leader, since they regarded merely the hope he entertained, and not the
                    reasons of the hope. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal lays waste the country between the
                    city Cortona and the lake Trasimenus, with all the devastation of war, the more
                    to exasperate the enemy to revenge the injuries inflicted on his allies.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They had now reached a place formed by
                    nature for an ambuscade, where the Trasimenus comes nearest to the mountains of
                    Cortona. A very narrow passage only intervenes, as though room enough just for
                    that purpose had been left designedly; after that a somewhat wider plain opens
                    itself, and then some hills rise up. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On these
                    he pitches his camp, in full view, where he himself with his Spaniards and
                    Africans only might be posted. The Baliares and his other light troops he leads
                    round the mountains; his cavalry he posts at the very entrance of the defile,
                    some eminences conveniently concealing them; in order that when the Romans had
                    entered, the cavalry advancing, every place might be enclosed by the lake and
                    the mountains. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Flaminius, passing the defiles
                    before it was quite daylight, without reconnoitring, though he had arrived at
                    the lake the preceding day at sunset, when the troops began to be spread into
                    the wider plain, saw that part only of the enemy which was opposite to him; the
                    ambuscade in his rear and overhead escaped his notice. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> And when the Carthaginian had his enemy enclosed by the
                    lake and mountains, and surrounded by his troops, he gives the signal to all to
                    make a simultaneous charge; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and each running
                    down the nearest way, the suddenness and unexpectedness of the event was
                    increased to the Romans by a mist rising from the lake, which had settled
                    thicker on the plain than on the mountains; and thus the troops of the enemy ran
                    down from the various eminences, sufficiently well discerning each other, and
                    therefore with the greater regularity. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A shout
                    being raised on all sides, the Roman found himself <pb n="771" xml:id="p.771"/>
                    surrounded before he could well see the enemy; and the at- tack on the front and
                    flank had commenced ere his line could be well formed, his arms prepared for
                    action, or his swords unsheathed. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, while all were panic-struck,
                    himself sufficiently undaunted though in so perilous a case, marshals, as well
                    as the time and place permitted, the lines which were thrown into confusion by
                    each man's turning himself towards the various shouts; and wherever he could
                    approach or be heard, exhorts them, and bids them stand and fight: <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> for that they could not escape thence by vows and
                    prayers to the gods, but by exertion and valour; that a way was sometimes opened
                    by the sword through the midst of marshalled armies, and that generally the less
                    the fear the less the danger. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, from
                    the noise and tumult, neither his advice nor command could be caught; and so far
                    were the soldiers from knowing their own standards, and ranks, and position,
                    that they had scarce sufficient courage to take up arms and make them ready for
                    battle; and certain of them were surprised before they could prepare them, being
                    burdened rather than protected by them; while in so great darkness there was
                    more use of ears than of eyes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They turned
                    their faces and eyes in every direction towards the groans of the wounded, the
                    sounds of blows upon the body or arms, and the mingled clamours of the menacing
                    and the affrighted. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some, as they were making
                    their escape, were stopped, having encountered a body of men engaged in fight;
                    and bands of fugitives returning to the battle, diverted others. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> After charges had been attempted unsuccessfully in
                    every direction, and on their flanks the mountains and the lake, on the front
                    and rear the lines of the enemy enclosed them, when it was evident that there
                    was no hope of safety but in the right hand and the sword; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> then each man became to himself a leader, and encourager to
                    action; and an entirely new contest arose, not a regular line, with principes,
                    hastati, and triarii; nor of such a sort as that the vanguard should fight
                    before the standards, and the rest of the troops behind them; nor such that each
                    soldier should be in his own legion, cohort, or company: chance collects them
                    into bands; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and each man's own will assigned
                    to him his post, whether to fight in front or rear; and so great was the ardour
                    of the conflict, so intent <pb n="772" xml:id="p.772"/> were their minds upon
                    the battle, that not one of the combatants felt an earthquake which threw down
                    large portions of many of the cities of Italy, turned rivers from their rapid
                    courses, carried the sea up into rivers, and levelled mountains with a
                    tremendous crash. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle was continued near three hours, and
                    in every quarter with fierceness; around the consul, however, it was still
                    hotter and more determined. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Both the strongest
                    of the troops, and himself too, promptly brought assistance wherever he
                    perceived his men hard pressed and distressed. But, distinguished by his armour,
                    the enemy attacked him with the utmost vigour, while his countrymen defended
                    him; until an Insubrian horseman, named Ducarius, knowing him also by his face,
                    says to his countrymen, <quote> Lo, this is the consul who slew our legions and
                        laid waste our fields and city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Now will I
                        offer this victim to the shades of my countrymen, miserably slain; </quote>
                    and putting spurs to his horse, he rushes through a very dense body of the
                    enemy; and first slaying his armour-bearer, who had opposed himself to his
                    attack as he approached, ran the consul through with his lance; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> the triarii, opposing their shields, kept him off when
                    seeking to despoil him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then first the flight
                    of a great number began; and now neither the lake nor the mountains obstructed
                    their hurried retreat; they run through all places, confined and precipitous, as
                    though they were blind; and arms and men are tumbled one upon another.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A great many, when there remained no more
                    space to run, advancing into the water through the first shallows of the lake,
                    plunge in, as far as they could stand above it with their heads and shoulders.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some there were whom inconsiderate fear
                    induced to try to escape even by swimming; but as that attempt was inordinate
                    and hopeless, they were either overwhelmed in the deep water, their courage
                    failing, or, wearied to no purpose, made their way back, with extreme
                    difficulty, to the shallows; and there were cut up on all hands by the cavalry
                    of the enemy, which had entered the water. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Near upon six thousand of the foremost body having gallantly forced their way
                    through the opposing enemy, entirely unacquainted with what was occurring in
                    their rear, escaped from the defile; and having halted on a certain rising
                    ground, and hearing only the shouting and clashing of arms, they could not know
                    nor discern, by <pb n="773" xml:id="p.773"/> reason of the mist, what was the
                    fortune of the battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At length, the affair
                    being decided, when the mist, dispelled by the increasing heat of the sun, had
                    cleared the atmosphere, then, in the clear light, the mountains and plains
                    showed their ruin, and the Roman army miserably destroyed; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and thus, lest, being descried at a distance, the cavalry
                    should be sent against them, hastily snatching up their standards, they hurried
                    away with all possible expedition. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the
                    following day, when, in addition to their extreme sufferings in other respects,
                    famine also was at hand, Maharbal, who had followed them during the night with
                    the whole body of cavalry, pledging his honour that he would let them depart
                    with single garments, if they would deliver up their arms, they surrendered
                    themselves; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> which promise was kept by
                    Hannibal with Punic fidelity, and he threw them all into chains. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This is the celebrated battle at the
                    Trasimenus, and recorded among the few disasters of the Roman people. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Fifteen thousand Romans were slain in the battle. Ten
                    thousand, who had been scattered in the flight through all Etruria, returned to
                    the city by different roads. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> One thousand five
                    hundred of the enemy perished in the battle; many on both sides died afterwards
                    of their wounds. The carnage on both sides is related, by some authors, to have
                    been many times greater. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I, besides that I
                    would relate nothing drawn from a worthless source, to which the minds of
                    historians generally incline too much, have as my chief authority Fabius, who
                    was contemporary with the events of this war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Such of the captives as belonged to the Latin confederacy being dismissed
                    without ransom, and the Romans thrown into chains, Hannibal ordered the bodies
                    of his own men to be gathered from the heaps of the enemy, and buried: the body
                    of Flaminius too, which was searched for with great diligence for burial, he
                    could not find. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the first intelligence of
                    this defeat at Rome, a concourse of the people, dismayed and terrified, took
                    place in the forum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The matrons, wandering
                    through the streets, ask all they meet, what sudden disaster was reported? what
                    was the fate of the army? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And when the
                    multitude, like a full assembly, having directed their course to the comitium
                    and senate-house, were calling upon the magistrates, at length, a little before
                    sunset, Marcus Pomponius, the praetor, declares, <quote>We have been defeated in
                        a great battle;</quote> and <pb n="774" xml:id="p.774"/> though nothing more
                    definite was heard from him, yet, full of the rumours which they had caught one
                    from another, they carry back to their homes intelligence, that the consul, with
                    a great part of his troops, was slain; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that a
                    few only survived, and these either widely dispersed in flight through Etruria,
                    or else captured by the enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As many as had
                    been the calamities of the vanquished army, into so many anxieties were the
                    minds of those distracted whose relations had served under Flaminius, and who
                    were uninformed of what had been the fate of their friends, nor does any one
                    know certainly what he should either hope or fear. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> During the next and several successive days, a greater
                    number of women almost than men stood at the gates, waiting either for some one
                    of their friends, or for intelligence of them, surrounding and earnestly
                    interrogating those they met: nor could they be torn away from those they knew
                    especially, until they had regularly inquired into every thing. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Then as they retired from the informants, you might
                    discern their various expressions of countenance, according as intelligence,
                    pleasing or sad, was announced to each; and those who congratulated or condoled
                    on their return home. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The joy and grief of
                    the women were especially manifested. They report that one, suddenly meeting her
                    son, who had returned safe, expired at the very door before his face —that
                    another, who sat grieving at her house at the falsely reported death of her son,
                    became a corpse, from excessive joy, at the first sight of him on his return.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The praetors detained the senators in the
                    house for several days, from sunrise to sunset, deliberating under whose
                    conduct, and by what forces, the victorious Carthaginians could be opposed. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before their plans were sufficiently
                    determined another unexpected defeat is reported: four thousand horse, sent
                    under the conduct of C. Centenius, proprietor, by Servilius to his colleague,
                    were cut off by Hannibal in Umbria, to which place, on hearing of the battle at
                    Trasimenus, they had turned their course. The report of this event variously
                    affected the people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Some, having their minds
                    pre-occupied with heavier grief, considered the recent loss of cavalry trifling,
                    in comparison with their former losses; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> others
                    did not estimate what had occurred by itself, but considered that, as in a body
                    already labouring under disease, a slight cause <pb n="775" xml:id="p.775"/>
                    would be felt more violently than a more powerful one in a robust constitution;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> so whatever adverse event befell the state
                    in its then sickly and impaired condition, ought to be estimated, not by the
                    magnitude of the event itself, but with reference to its exhausted strength,
                    which could endure nothing that could oppress it. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The state therefore took refuge in a remedy for a long time
                    before neither wanted nor employed, the appointment of a dictator; and because
                    the consul was absent, by whom alone it appeared he could be nominated; and
                    because neither message nor letter could easily be sent to him through the
                    country occupied by Punic troops; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and because
                    the people could not appoint a dictator, which had never been done to that day,
                    the people created Quintus Fabius Maximus pro-dictator, and Marcus Minucius
                    Rufus master of the horse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To them the senate
                    assigned the task of strengthening the walls and towers of the city; of placing
                    guards in such quarters as seemed good, and breaking down the bridges of the
                    river, considering that they must now fight at home in defence of their city,
                    since they were unable to protect Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, marching directly through Umbria,
                    arrived at Spoletum; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> thence, having completely
                    devastated the adjoining country, and commenced an assault upon the city, having
                    been repulsed with great loss, and conjecturing from the strength of this one
                    colony, which had been not very successfully attacked, what was the size of the
                    city of Rome, turned aside into the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    territory of Picenum, which abounded not only with every species of grain, but
                    was stored with booty, which his rapacious and needy troops eagerly seized.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There he continued encamped for several
                    days, and his soldiers were refreshed, who had been enfeebled by winter marches
                    and marshy ground, and with a battle more successful in its result than light or
                    easy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When sufficient time for rest had been
                    granted for soldiers delighting more in plunder and devastation than ease and
                    repose; setting out, he lays waste the territories of Pretutia and Hadria, then
                    of the Marsi, the Marrucini, and the Peligni, and the contiguous region of'
                    Apulia around Arpi and Luceria. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Cneius
                    Servilius, the consul, having fought some slight battles with the Gauls, and
                    taken one inconsiderable town, when he heard of the defeat of his colleague and
                    the army, alarmed now for the walls of the capital, marched towards the city,
                    that he might not be absent <pb n="776" xml:id="p.776"/> at so extreme a crisis.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius Maximus, a second time
                    dictator, assembled the senate the very day he entered on his office; and
                    commencing with what related to the gods, after he had distinctly proved to the
                    fathers, that Caius Flaminius had erred more from neglect of the ceremonies and
                    auspices than from temerity and want of judgment, and that the gods themselves
                    should be consulted as to what were <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> the
                    expiations of their anger, he obtained a resolution that the decemviri should be
                    ordered to inspect the Sibylline books, which is rarely decreed, except when
                    some horrid prodigies were announced. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having
                    inspected the prophetic books, they reported, that the vow which was made to
                    Mars on account of this war, not having been regularly fulfilled, must be
                    performed afresh and more fully; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that the
                    great games must be vowed to Jupiter, temples to Venus Erycina and Mens; that a
                    supplication and lectisternium must be made, and a sacred spring vowed, if the
                    war should proceed favourably and the state continue the condition it was in
                    before the war. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Since the management of the
                    war would occupy Fabius, the senate orders Marcus Aemilius, the praetor, to see
                    that all these things are done in good time, according to the directions of the
                    college of pontiffs. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These decrees of the senate having been
                    passed, Lucius Cornelius Lentulus, pontifex maximus, the college of praetors
                    consulting with him, gives his opinion that, first of all, the people should be
                    consulted respecting a sacred spring: that it could not be without the order of
                    the people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The people having been asked
                    according to this form: Do ye will and order that this thing should be performed
                    in this manner? If the republic of the Roman people, the Quirites, shall be safe
                    and preserved, as I wish it may, from these wars for the next five years, (the
                    war which is between the Roman people and the Carthaginian, and the wars which
                    are <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> with the Cisalpine Gauls,) the Roman
                    people, the Quirites, shall present whatsoever the spring shall produce from
                    herds of swine, sheep, goats, oxen, and which shall not have been consecrated,
                    to be sacrificed to Jupiter, from the day which the senate and people shall
                    appoint. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Let him who shall make an offering do
                    it when he please, and in what manner he please; in whatsoever manner he does
                    it, let it be considered duly done. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If that
                    which ought to be sacrificed die, let it be unconsecrated, and let no <pb
                        n="777" xml:id="p.777"/> guilt attach; if any one unwittingly wound or kill
                    it, let it be no injury to him; if any one shall steal it, let no guilt attach
                    to the people or to him from whom it was stolen; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> if any one shall unwittingly offer it on a forbidden day, let it be esteemed
                    duly offered; also whether by night or day, whether slave or free-man perform
                    it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If the senate and people shall order it to
                    be offered sooner than any person shall offer it, let the people being acquitted
                    of it be free. On the same account great games were vowed, at an expense of
                    three hundred and thirty-three thousand three hundred and thirty-three <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi> and a third; moreover, it was decreed that
                    sacrifice should be done to Jupiter with three hundred oxen, to many other
                    deities with white oxen and the other victims. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The vows being duly made, a supplication was proclaimed; and not only the
                    inhabitants of the city went with their wives and children, but such of the
                    rustics also as, possessing any property themselves, were interested in the
                    welfare of the state. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then a lectisternium was
                    celebrated for three days, the decemviri for sacred things superintending. Six
                    couches were seen, for Jupiter and Juno one, for Neptune and Minerva another,
                    for Mars and Venus a third, for Apollo and Diana a fourth, for Vulcan and Vesta
                    a fifth, for Mercury and Ceres a sixth. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then
                    temples were vowed. To Venus Erycina, Quintus Fabius Maximus vowed a temple; for
                    so it was delivered from the prophetic books, that he should vow it who held the
                    highest authority in the state. Titus Otacilius, the praetor, vowed a temple to
                    Mens. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Divine things having been thus performed, the
                    dictator then put the question of the war and the state; with what, and how many
                    legions the fathers were of opinion that the victorious enemy should be opposed.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was decreed that he should receive the
                    army from Cneius Servilius, the consul: that he should levy, moreover, from the
                    citizens and allies as many horse and foot as seemed good; that he should
                    transact and perform every thing else as he considered for the good of the
                    state. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Fabius said he would add two legions to
                    the army of Servilius. These were levied by the master of the horse, and were
                    appointed by Fabius to meet him at Tibur on a certain day. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And then having issued proclamation that those whose towns
                    or castles were unfortified should quit them and assemble in places of security;
                    that all the inhabitants of that <pb n="778" xml:id="p.778"/> tract through
                    which Hannibal was about to march, should remove from the country, having first
                    burnt their buildings and spoiled their fruits, that there might not be a supply
                    of any thing; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> he himself set out on the
                    Flaminian road to meet the consul and his army; and when he saw in the distance
                    the marching body on the Tiber, near Ocriculum, and the consul with the cavalry
                    advancing to him, he sent a beadle to acquaint the consul that he must meet the
                    dictator without the lictors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When he had
                    obeyed his command, and their meeting had exhibited a striking display of the
                    majesty of the dictatorship before the citizens and allies, who, from its
                    antiquity, had now almost forgotten that authority; a letter arrived from the
                    city, stating that the ships of burden, conveying provisions from Ostia into
                    Spain to the army, had been captured by the Carthaginian fleet off the port of
                    Cossa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul, therefore, was immediately
                    ordered to proceed to Ostia, and, having manned the ships at Rome or Ostia with
                    soldiers and sailors, to pursue the enemy, and protect the coasts of Italy.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Great numbers of men were levied at Rome;
                    sons of freedmen even, who had children, and were of the military age, had taken
                    the oath. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Of these troops levied in the city,
                    such as were under thirty-five were put on board of ships, the rest were left to
                    protect the city. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator, having received the troops of
                    the consul from Fulvius Flaccus, his lieutenant-general, marching through the
                    Sabine territory, arrived at Tibur on the day which he had appointed the
                    new-raised troops to assemble. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thence he went
                    to Praeneste, and cutting across the country, came out in the Latin way, whence
                    he led his troops towards the enemy, reconnoitring the road with the utmost
                    diligence; not intending to expose himself to hazard any where, except so far as
                    necessity compelled him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The day he first
                    pitched his camp in sight of the enemy, not far from Arpi, the Carthaginian,
                    without delay, led out his troops, and forming his line gave an opportunity of
                    fighting: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but when he found all still with the
                    enemy, and his camp free from tumult and disorder, he returned to his camp,
                    saying indeed tauntingly, <quote> That even the spirit of the Romans, inherited
                        from Mars, was at length subdued; that they were warred down; and had
                        manifestly given up all claim to valour and renown: </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but burning inwardly with stifled vexation,
                    because <pb n="779" xml:id="p.779"/> he would have to encounter a general by no
                    means like Flaminius and Sempronius; and because the Romans, then at length
                    schooled by their misfortunes, had sought a general a match for Hannibal; and
                    that now he had no longer to fear the headlong violence, but the deliberate
                    prudence of the dictator. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having not yet
                    experienced his constancy, he began to provoke and try his temper, by frequently
                    shifting his camp and laying waste the territories of the allies before his
                    eyes: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and one while he withdrew out of sight
                    at quick march, another while he halted suddenly, and concealed himself in some
                    winding of the road, if possible to entrap him on his descending into the plain.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Fabius kept marching his troops along the
                    high grounds, at a moderate distance from the enemy, so as neither to let him go
                    altogether nor yet to encounter him. The troops were kept within the camp,
                    except so far as necessary wants compelled them to quit it; and fetched in food
                    and wood not by small nor rambling parties. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> An
                    outpost of cavalry and light-armed troops, prepared and equipped for acting in
                    cases of sudden alarm, rendered every thing safe to their own soldiers, and
                    dangerous to the scattered plunderers of the enemy. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was his whole cause committed to general hazard; while
                    slight contests, of small importance in themselves, commenced on safe ground,
                    with a retreat at hand, accustomed the soldiery, terrified by their former
                    disasters, now at length to think less meanly either of their prowess or good
                    fortune. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But he did not find Hannibal a
                    greater enemy to such sound measures than his master of the horse, who was only
                    prevented from plunging the state into ruin by his inferiority in command.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Presumptuous and precipitate in his
                    measures, and unbridled in his tongue, first among a few, then openly and
                    publicly, he taunted him with being sluggish instead of patient, spiritless
                    instead of cautious; falsely imputing to him those vices which bordered on his
                    virtues; and raised himself by means of depressing his superiors, which, though
                    a most iniquitous practice, has become more general from the too great successes
                    of many. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal crosses over from the Hirpini into
                    Samnium; lays waste the territory of Beneventum; takes the town of Telesia; and
                    purposely irritates the dictator, if perchance he could draw him down to a
                    battle on the plain, exasperated by so many indignities and disasters inflicted
                    on his allies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="780" xml:id="p.780"/> Among the multitude of allies of Italian
                    extraction, who had been captured by Hannibal at the Trasimenus, and dismissed,
                    were three Campanian horsemen, who had even at that time been bribed by many
                    presents and promises from Hannibal to win over the affections of their
                    countrymen to him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These, bringing him word
                    that he would have an opportunity of getting possession of Capua, if he brought
                    his army into the neighbourhood in Campania, induced Hannibal to quit Samnium
                    for Campania; though he hesitated, fluctuating between confidence and distrust,
                    as the affair was of more importance than the authorities. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He dismissed them, repeatedly charging them to confirm
                    their promises by acts, and ordering them to return with a greater number, and
                    some of their leading men. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal himself
                    orders his guide to conduct him into the territory of Casinum, being certified
                    by persons acquainted with the country, that if he seized that pass he would
                    deprive the Romans of a passage by which they might get out to the assistance of
                    their allies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But his Punic accent, ill
                    adapted to the pronunciation of Latin names, caused the guide to understand
                    Casilinum, instead of Casinum; and leaving his former course, he descends
                    through the territory of Allifae, Calatia, and Cales, into the plain of Stella,
                    where, seeing the country enclosed on all sides by mountains <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> and rivers, he calls the guide to him, and asks him where
                    in the world he was? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> when he replied, that on
                    that day he would lodge at Casilinum: then at length the error was discovered,
                    and that Casinum lay at a great distance in another direction. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Having scourged the guide with rods and crucified him, in
                    order to strike terror into all others, he fortified a camp, and sent Maharbal
                    with the cavalry into the Falernian territory to pillage. This depredation
                    reached as far as the waters of Sinuessa; the Numidians caused destruction to a
                    vast extent, but flight and consternation through a still wider space.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Yet not even the terror of these things,
                    when all around was consuming in the flames of war, could shake the fidelity of
                    the allies; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for this manifest reason, because
                    they lived under a temperate and mild government: nor were they unwilling to
                    submit to those who were superior to them, which is the only bond of fidelity. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But when the enemy's camp was pitched on the
                    Vulturnus, and the most delightful country in Italy was being <pb n="781"
                        xml:id="p.781"/> consumed by fire, and the farm-houses, on all hands, were
                    smoking from the flames, whilst Fabius led his troops along the heights of Mount
                    Massicus, then the strife had nearly been kindled anew, <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> for they had been quiet for a few days, because, as the
                    army had marched quicker than usual, they had supposed that the object of this
                    haste was to save Campania from devastation; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    but when they arrived at the extreme ridge of Mount Massicus, and the enemy
                    appeared under their eyes, burning the houses of the Falernian territory, and of
                    the settlers of Sinuessa, and no mention made of battle, Minucius exclaims,
                        <quote> Are we come here to see our allies butchered, and their property
                        burned, as a spectacle to be enjoyed? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and
                        if we are not moved with shame on account of any others, are we not on
                        account of these citizens, whom our fathers sent as settlers to Sinuessa,
                        that this frontier might be protected from the Samnite foe: <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> which now not the neighbouring Samnite wastes with
                        fire, but a Carthaginian foreigner, who has advanced even thus far from the
                        remotest limits of the world, through our dilatoriness and inactivity? What!
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> are we so degenerate from our
                        ancestors as tamely to see that coast filled with Numidian and Moorish foes,
                        along which our fathers considered it a disgrace to their government that
                        the Carthaginian fleets should cruise? We, who erewhile, indignant at the
                        storming of Saguntum, appealed not to men only, but to treaties and to gods,
                        behold Hannibal scaling the walls of a Roman colony unmoved. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The smoke from the flames of our farm-houses and
                        lands comes into our eyes and faces; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> our
                        ears ring with the cries of our weeping allies, imploring us to assist them
                        oftener than the gods, while we here are leading our troops, like a herd of
                        cattle, through shady forests and lonely paths, enveloped in clouds and
                        woods. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If Marcus Furius had resolved to
                        recover the city from the Gauls, by thus traversing the tops of mountains
                        and forests, in the same manner as this modern Camillus goes about to
                        recover Italy from Hannibal, who has been sought out for our dictator in our
                        distress, on account of his unparalleled talents, Rome would be the
                        possession of the Gauls; and I fear lest, if we are thus dilatory, our
                        ancestors will so often have preserved it only for the Carthaginians and
                        Hannibal; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> but that man and true Roman, on
                        the very day on which intelligence was <pb n="782" xml:id="p.782"/> brought
                        him to Veii, that he was appointed dictator, on the authority of the fathers
                        and the nomination of the people, came down into the plain, though the
                        Janiculum was high enough to admit of his sitting down there, and viewing
                        the enemy at a distance; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and on that very
                        day defeated the Gallic legions in the middle of the city, in the place
                        where the Gallic piles are now, and on the following day on the Roman side
                        of Gabii. What! <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> many years after this,
                        when we were sent under the yoke at the Caudine forks by the Samnite foe,
                        did Lucius Papirius Cursor take the yoke from the Roman neck and place it
                        upon the proud Samnites, by traversing the heights of Samnium? or was it by
                        pressing and besieging Luceria, and challenging the victorious enemy? A
                        short time ago, what was it that gave victory to Caius Lutatius but
                        expedition? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> for on the day after he
                        caught sight of the enemy, he surprised and overpowered the fleet, loaded
                        with provisions, and encumbered of itself by its own implements and
                        apparatus. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> It is folly to suppose that
                        the war can be brought to a conclusion by sitting still, or by prayers; the
                        troops must be armed and led down into the plain, that you may engage man to
                        man. The Roman power has grown to its present height by courage and
                        activity, and not by such dilatory measures as these, which the cowardly
                        only designate as cautious. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A crowd of Roman tribunes and knights poured
                    round Minucius, while thus, as it were, haranguing; his presumptuous expressions
                    reached the ears of the common soldiers; and had the question been submitted to
                    the votes of the soldiers, they showed evidently that they would have preferred
                    Minucius to Fabius for their general. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius, keeping his attention fixed no less
                    upon his own troops than on the enemy, first shows that his resolution was
                    unconquered by the former. Though he well knew that his procrastination was
                    disapproved, not only in his own camp, but by this time even at Rome; yet,
                    inflexibly adhering to the same line of policy, he delayed through the remainder
                    of the summer; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> in order that Hannibal, devoid
                    of all hope of a battle, which he so earnestly desired, might now look out for a
                    place for winter quarters; because that district was one of present, but not
                    constant, supply, consisting, as it did, of plantations and vineyards, and all
                    places planted with luxurious rather than useful produce. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This intelligence was <pb n="783" xml:id="p.783"/> brought
                    to Fabius by his scouts. When he felt convinced that he would return by the same
                    narrow pass through which he had entered the Falernian territory, he occupied
                    Mount Callicula and Casilinum with a pretty strong guard. Which city,
                    intersected by the river Vulturnus, divides the Falernian and Campanian
                    territories. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He himself leads back his troops
                    along the same heights, having sent Lucius Hostilius Mancinus with four hundred
                    of the allied cavalry to reconnoitre; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> who
                    being one of the crowd of youths who had often heard the master of the horse
                    fiercely haranguing, at first advanced after the manner of a scout, in order
                    that he might observe the enemy in security; and when he saw the Numidians
                    scattered widely throughout the villages, having gotten an opportunity, he also
                    slew a few of them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But from that moment his
                    mind was engrossed with the thoughts of a battle, and the injunctions of the
                    dictator were forgotten, who had charged him, when he had advanced as far as he
                    could with safety, to retreat before he came within the enemy's view. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The Numidians, party after party, skirmishing and
                    retreating, drew the general almost to their camp, to the fatigue of his men and
                    horses. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then Karthalo, who had the command of
                    the cavalry, charging at full speed, and having put them to flight before he
                    came within a dart's throw, pursued them for five miles almost in a continuous
                    course. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Mancinus, when he saw that the enemy
                    did not desist from the pursuit, and that there was no hope of escape, having
                    encouraged his troops, turned back to the battle, though inferior in every kind
                    of force. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly he himself, and the
                    choicest of his cavalry, being surrounded, are cut to pieces. The rest in
                    disorderly retreat fled first to Cales, and thence to the dictator, by ways
                    almost impassable. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It happened that on that
                    day Minucius had formed a junction with Fabius, having been sent to secure with
                    a guard the pass above Tarracina, which, contracted into a narrow gorge,
                    overhangs the sea, in order that Hannibal might not be able to get into the
                    Roman territory by the Appian way's being unguarded. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator and master of the horse, uniting their forces,
                    lead them down into the road through which Hannibal was about to march his
                    troops. The enemy was two miles from that place. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following day the Carthaginians filled the
                    whole <pb n="784" xml:id="p.784"/> road between the two camps with his troops in
                    marching order; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and though the Romans had
                    taken their stand immediately under their rampart, having a decidedly superior
                    position, yet the Carthaginian came up with his light horse, and, with a view to
                    provoke the enemy, carried on a kind of desultory attack, first charging and
                    then retreating. The Roman line remained in its position. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The battle was slow, and more conformable to the wish of
                    the dictator than of Hannibal. On the part of the Romans there fell two hundred,
                    on the part of the enemy eight hundred. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It now
                    began to appear that Hannibal was hemmed in, the road to Casilinum being
                    blockaded; and that while Capua, and Samnium, and so many wealthy allies in the
                    rear of the Romans might supply them with provisions, the Carthaginian, on the
                    other hand, must winter amid the rocks of Formiae and the sands and hideous
                    swamps of Liternum. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor did it escape Hannibal
                    that he was assailed by his own arts; wherefore, since he could not escape by
                    way of Casilinum, and since it was necessary to make for the mountains, and pass
                    the summit of Callicula, lest in any place the Romans should attack his troops
                    while enclosed in valleys; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> having hit upon a
                    stratagem calculated to deceive the sight, and excite terror from its
                    appearance, by means of which he might baffle the enemy, he resolved to come up
                    by stealth to the mountains at the commencement of night. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The preparation of his wily stratagem was of this
                    description. Torches, collected from every part of the country, and bundles of
                    rods and dry cuttings, are fastened before the horns of oxen, of which, wild and
                    tame, he had driven away a great number among other plunder of the country: the
                    number of oxen was made up to nearly two thousand. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> To Hasdrubal was assigned the task of driving to the
                    mountains that herd, after having set fire to their horns, as soon as ever it
                    was dark; particularly, if he could, over the passes beset by the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as it was dark the camp was moved in
                    silence; the oxen were driven a little in advance of the standards. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> When they arrived at the foot of the mountains and
                    the narrow passes, the signal is immediately given for setting fire to their
                    horns and driving them violently up the mountains before them. The mere terror
                    excited by the flame, which cast a glare from their heads, and the heat now
                    approaching <pb n="785" xml:id="p.785"/> the quick and the roots of their horns,
                    drove on the oxen as if goaded by madness. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By
                    which dispersion, on a sudden all the surrounding shrubs were in a blaze, as if
                    the mountains and woods had been on fire; and the unavailing tossing of their
                    heads quickening the flame, exhibited an appearance as of men running to and fro
                    on every side. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Those who had been placed to
                    guard the passage of the wood, when they saw fires on the tops of the mountains,
                    and some over their own heads, concluding that they were surrounded, abandoned
                    their post; making for the tops of the mountains in the direction in which the
                    fewest fires blazed, as being the safest course; however they fell in with some
                    oxen which had strayed from their herds. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At
                    first, when they beheld them at a distance, they stood fixed in amazement at the
                    miracle, as it appeared to them, of creatures breathing fire; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> afterwards, when it showed itself to be a human stratagem,
                    then, forsooth, concluding that there was an ambuscade, as they are hurrying
                    away in flight, with increased alarm, they fall in also with the light-armed
                    troops of the enemy. But the night, when the fear was equally shared, kept them
                    from commencing the battle till morning. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Meanwhile Hannibal, having marched his whole army through the pass, and having
                    cut off some of the enemy in the very defile, pitches his camp in the country of
                    Allifae. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius perceived this tumult, but concluding
                    that it was a snare, and being disinclined for a battle, particularly by night,
                    kept his troops within the works. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At break of
                    day a battle took place under the summit of the mountain, in which the Romans,
                    who were considerably superior in numbers, would have easily overpowered the
                    light-armed of the enemy, cut off as they were from their party, had not a
                    cohort of Spaniards, sent back by Hannibal for that very purpose, reached the
                    spot. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That body being more accustomed to
                    mountains, and being more adapted, both from the agility of their limbs and also
                    from the character of their arms, to skirmishing amid rocks and crags, easily
                    foiled, by their manner of fighting, an enemy loaded with arms, accustomed to
                    level ground and the steady kind of fighting. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Separating from a contest thus by no means equal, they proceeded to their camps;
                    the Spaniards almost all untouched; the Romans having lost a few. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Fabius also moved his camp, and passing the defile,
                    took up a position above Allifae, in a strong <pb n="786" xml:id="p.786"/> and
                    elevated place. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then Hannibal, pretending to
                    march to Rome through Samnium, came back as far as the Peligni, spreading
                    devastation. Fabius led his troops along the heights midway between the army of
                    the enemy and the city of Rome; neither avoiding him altogether, nor coming to
                    an engagement. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From the Peligni the
                    Carthaginian turned his course, and going back again to Apulia, reached
                    Geronium, a city deserted by its inhabitants from fear, as a part of its walls
                    had fallen down together in ruins. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    dictator formed a completely fortified camp in the territory of Larinum, and
                    being recalled thence to Rome on account of some sacred rites, he not only urged
                    the master of the horse, in virtue of his authority, but with advice and almost
                    with prayers, that he would trust rather to prudence than fortune; and imitate
                    him as a general rather than Sempronius and Flaminius; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> that he would not suppose that nothing had been achieved by
                    having worn out nearly the whole summer in baffling the enemy; that physicians
                    too sometimes gained more by rest than by motion and action. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> That it was no small thing to have ceased to be conquered
                    by an enemy so often victorious, and to have taken breath after successive
                    disasters. Having thus unavailingly admonished the master of the horse, he set
                    out for Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the summer in which these
                    events occurred, the war commenced by land and sea in Spain also. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> To the number of ships which he had received from his
                    brother, equipped and ready for action, Hasdrubal added ten. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The fleet of forty ships he delivered to Himilco: and thus
                    setting out from Carthage, kept his ships near the land, while he led his army
                    along the shore, ready to engage with whichever part of his forces the enemy
                    might fall in with. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Cneius Scipio, when he
                    heard that the enemy had quitted his winter quarters, at first formed the same
                    plan; but afterwards, not daring to engage him by land, from a great rumour of
                    fresh auxiliaries, he advances to meet him with a fleet of thirty-five ships,
                    having put some chosen soldiers on board. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Setting out from Tarraco, on the second day, he reached a convenient station,
                    ten miles from the mouth of the Iberus. Two ships of the Massilians, sent
                    forward from that place reconnoitring, brought word back that the Carthaginian
                    fleet was stationed in the mouth of the river, and that the camp was pitched
                    upon the bank. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In order, therefore, to
                    overpower them while off their guard and incautious, by a universal and
                    wide-spread <pb n="787" xml:id="p.787"/> terror, he weighed anchor and advanced.
                    In Spain there are several towers placed in high situations, which they employ
                    both as watch-towers and as places of defence against pirates. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> From them first, a view of the ships of the enemy having
                    been obtained, the signal was given to Hasdrubal; and a tumult arose in the
                    camp, and on land sooner than on the ships and at sea; the dashing of the oars
                    and other nautical noises not being yet distinctly heard, nor the promontories
                    disclosing the fleet. Upon this, suddenly one horseman after another, sent out
                    by Hasdrubal, orders those who were strolling upon the shore or resting quietly
                    in their tents, expecting any thing rather than the enemy and a battle on that
                    day, immediately to embark and take up arms: that the Roman fleet was now a
                    short distance from the harbour. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The horsemen,
                    despatched in every direction, delivered these orders; and presently Hasdrubal
                    himself comes up with the main army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> All
                    places resound with noises of various kinds; the soldiers and rowers hurrying
                    together to the ships, rather like men running away from the land than marching
                    to battle. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Scarcely had all embarked, when
                    some, unfastening the hawsers, are carried out against the anchors; others cut
                    their cables, that nothing might impede them; and by doing every thing with
                    hurry and precipitation, the duties of mariners were impeded by the preparations
                    of the soldiers, and the soldiers were prevented from taking and preparing for
                    action their arms, by the bustle of the mariners. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> And now the Roman was not only approaching, but had drawn
                    up his ships for the battle. The Carthaginians, therefore, thrown into disorder,
                    not more by the enemy and the battle than by their own tumult, having rather
                    made an attempt at fighting than commenced a battle, turned their fleet for
                    flight; and as the mouth of the river which was before them could not be entered
                    in so broad a line, and by so many pressing in at the same time, they ran their
                    ships on shore in every part. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And being
                    received, some in the shallows, and others on the dry shore, some armed and some
                    unarmed, they escaped to their friends, who were drawn up in battle-array over
                    the shore. Two Carthaginian ships were captured and four sunk on the first
                    encounter. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans, though the enemy was master of the
                    shore, and they saw armed troops lining the whole bank, promptly pursuing the
                    discomfited fleet of the enemy, towed out into the deep all the ships which had
                    not either shattered their prows <pb n="788" xml:id="p.788"/> by the violence
                    with which they struck the shore, or set their keels fast in the shallows.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They captured as many as twenty-five out
                    of forty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor was that the most splendid
                    result of their victory: but they became masters of the whole sea on that coast
                    by one slight battle; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> advancing, then, with
                    their fleet to Honosca, and making a descent from the ships upon the coast, when
                    they had taken the city by storm and pillaged it, they afterwards made for
                    Carthage: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> then devastating the whole
                    surrounding country, they, lastly, set fire also to the buildings contiguous to
                    the wall and gates. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thence the fleet, laden
                    with plunder, arrived at Longuntica, where a great quantity of oakum for naval
                    purposes had been collected by Hasdrubal: of this, taking away as much as was
                    sufficient for their necessities, they burnt all the rest. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Nor did they only sail by the prominent coasts of the
                    continent, but crossed over into the island Ebusus; where, having with the
                    utmost exertion, but in vain, carried on operations against the city, which is
                    the capital of the island, for two days, when they found that time <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> was wasted to no purpose upon a hopeless task, they
                    turned their efforts to the devastation of the country; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and having plundered and fired several villages, and
                    acquired a greater booty than they had obtained on the continent, they retired
                    to their ships, when ambassadors from the Baliares came to Scipio to sue for
                    peace. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> From this place the fleet sailed back,
                    and returned to the hither parts of the province, whither ambassadors of all the
                    people who dwell on the Iberus, and of many people in the most distant parts of
                    Spain, assembled. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But the number of states
                    who really became subject to the authority and dominion of the Romans, and gave
                    hostages, amounted to upwards of one hundred and twenty. The Roman therefore,
                    relying sufficiently on his land forces also, advanced as far as the pass of
                    Castulo. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal retired into Lusitania,
                    and nearer the ocean. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this, it seemed probable that the
                    remainder of the summer would be peaceful; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and
                    so it would have been with regard to the Punic enemy: but besides that the
                    tempers of the Spaniards themselves are naturally restless, and eager for
                    innovation, Mandonius, together with Indibilis, who had formerly <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> been petty prince of the Ilergetes, having stirred
                    up their countrymen, came to lay waste the peaceful country of the Roman allies,
                    after the Romans had retired from the pass to the sea-coast. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> A military tribune with some light-armed <pb n="789"
                        xml:id="p.789"/> auxiliaries being sent against these by Scipio, with a
                    small effort put them all to the rout, as being but a disorderly band: some
                    having been captured and slain, a great portion of them were deprived of their
                    arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This disturbance, however, brought back
                    Hasdrubal, who was retiring to the ocean, to protect his allies on this side the
                    Iberus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian camp was in the
                    territory of Ilercao, the Roman camp at the New Fleet, when unexpected
                    intelligence turned the war into another quarter. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The Celtiberians, who had sent the chief men of their
                    country as ambassadors to the Romans, and had given them hostages, aroused by a
                    message from Scipio, take up arms and invade the province of the Carthaginians
                    with a powerful army; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> take three towns by
                    storm; and after that, encountering Hasdrubal himself in two battles with
                    splendid success, slew fifteen thousand and captured four thousand, together
                    with many military standards. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This being the state of affairs in Spain,
                    Publius Scipio came into his province, having been sent thither by the senate,
                    his command being continued to him after his consulate, with thirty long ships,
                    eight thousand soldiers, and a large importation of provisions. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> That fleet, swelled to an enormous size by a multitude of
                    transports, being descried at a distance, entered safe the port of Tarraco, to
                    the great joy of the citizens and allies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Landing his troops there, Scipio set out and formed a junction with his brother,
                    and thenceforward they prosecuted the war with united courage and counsels.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While the Carthaginians, therefore, were
                    occupied with the Celtiberian war, they promptly crossed the Iberus, and not
                    seeing any enemy, pursue their course to Saguntum; for it was reported that the
                    hostages from every part of Spain, having been consigned to custody, were kept
                    in the citadel of that place under a small guard. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> That pledge alone checked the affections of all the people
                    of Spain, which were inclined towards an alliance with the Romans; lest the
                    guilt of their defection should be expiated with the blood of their children.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> One man, by a stratagem more subtle than
                    honourable, liberated the Spaniards from this restraint. There was at Saguntum a
                    noble Spaniard, named Abelux, hitherto faithful to the Carthaginians, but now
                    (such are for the most part the dispositions of barbarians) had changed his
                    attachment with fortune; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but considering that
                    a deserter going over to enemies without the betraying of something valuable,
                    would be <pb n="790" xml:id="p.790"/> looked upon only as a stigmatized and
                    worthless individual, was solicitous to render as great a service as possible to
                    his new confederates. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Having turned over in
                    his mind, then, the various means which, under the favour of fortune, he might
                    employ, in preference to every other, he applied himself to the delivering up of
                    the hostages; concluding that this one thing, above all others, would gain the
                    Romans the friendship of the Spanish chieftains. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> But since he knew that the guards of the hostages would do nothing without
                    the authority of Bostar, the governor, he addresses himself with craft to Bostar
                    himself. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Bostar had his camp without the
                    city, just upon the shore, in order to preclude the approach of the Romans from
                    that quarter. He informs him, taken aside to a secret place, and as if
                    uninformed, in what position affairs were: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That hitherto fear had withheld the minds of the Spaniards to them,
                        because the Romans were at a great distance: that now the Roman camp was on
                        this side the Iberus, a secure fortress and asylum for such as desired a
                        change, that therefore those whom fear could not bind should be attached by
                        kindness and favour. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When Bostar, in astonishment, earnestly asked
                    him, what sudden gift of so much importance that could be, he replied, <quote>
                        Send back the hostages to their states: <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        this will be an acceptable boon, privately to their parents, who possess the
                        greatest influence in their respective states, and publicly to the people.
                        Every man wishes to have confidence reposed in him; and confidence reposed
                        generally enforces the fidelity itself. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        The office of restoring the hostages to their homes, I request for myself;
                        that I may enhance my project by the trouble bestowed, and that I may add as
                        much value as I can to a service in its own intrinsic nature so acceptable. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When he had persuaded the man, who was not
                    cunning as compared with Carthaginian minds in general, having gone secretly and
                    by night to the outposts of the enemy, he met with some auxiliary Spaniards; and
                    having been brought by them into the presence of Scipio, he explains what
                    brought him. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Pledges of fidelity having been
                    given and received, and the time and place for delivering the hostages having
                    been appointed, he returns to Saguntum. The following day he spent with Bostar,
                    in taking his commands for effecting the business; <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> having so arranged it, that he should go by night, in order
                    that he might escape the observation of the enemy, he was dismissed; and
                    awakening the guards of the youths <pb n="791" xml:id="p.791"/> at the hour
                    agreed upon with them, set out and led them, as if unconsciously, into a snare
                    prepared by his own deceit. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> They were brought
                    to the Roman camp, and every thing else respecting the restoration of the
                    hostages was transacted as had been agreed upon with Bostar, and in the same
                    course as if the affair had been carried on in the name of the Carthaginians.
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> But the favour of the Romans was somewhat
                    greater than that of the Carthaginians would have been in a similar case; for
                    misfortune and fear might have seemed to have softened them, who had been found
                    oppressive and haughty in prosperity. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> The
                    Roman, on the contrary, on his first arrival, having been unknown to them
                    before, had begun with an act of clemency and liberality: and Abelux, a man of
                    prudence, did not seem likely to have changed his allies without good cause.
                        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Accordingly all began, with great
                    unanimity, to meditate a revolt; and hostilities would immediately have
                    commenced, had not the winter intervened, which compelled the Romans, and the
                    Carthaginians also, to retire to shelter. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the transactions in Spain also
                    during the second summer of the Punic war; while in Italy the prudent delay of
                    Fabius had procured the Romans some intermission from disasters; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> which conduct, as it kept Hannibal disturbed with no
                    ordinary degree of anxiety, for it proved to him that the Romans had at length
                    selected a general who would carry on the war with prudence, and not in
                    dependence on fortune; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> so was it treated with
                    contempt by his countrymen, both in the camp and in the city; particularly after
                    that a battle had been fought during his absence from the temerity of the master
                    of the horse, in its issue, as I may justly designate it, rather joyful than
                    successful. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Two causes were added to augment
                    the unpopularity of the dictator: one arising out of a stratagem and artful
                    procedure of Hannibal; for the farm of the dictator having been pointed out to
                    him by deserters, he ordered that the fire and sword and every outrage of
                    enemies should be restrained from it alone, while all around were levelled with
                    the ground; in order that it might appear to have been the term of some secret
                    compact: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the other from an act of his own, at
                    first perhaps suspicious, because in it he had not waited for the authority of
                    the senate, but in the result turning unequivocally to his highest credit, with
                    relation to the <pb n="792" xml:id="p.792"/> change of prisoners: <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> for, as was the case in the first Punic war, an
                    agreement had been made between the Roman and Carthaginian generals, that
                    whichever received more prisoners than he restored, should give two pounds and a
                    half of silver for every man. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And when the
                    Roman had received two hundred and forty-seven more than the Carthaginian, and
                    the silver which was due for them, after the matter had been frequently agitated
                    in the senate, was not promptly supplied, because he had not consulted the
                    fathers, he sent his son Quintus <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> to Rome and
                    sold his farm, uninjured by the enemy, and thus redeemed the public credit at
                    his own private expense. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Hannibal lay in a
                    fixed camp before the walls of Geronium, which city he had captured and burnt,
                    leaving only a few buildings for the purpose of granaries: thence he was in the
                    habit of sending out two-thirds of his forces to forage; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> with the third part kept in readiness, he himself remained
                    on guard, both as a protection to his camp, and for the purpose of looking out,
                    if from any quarter an attack should be made upon his foragers. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman army was at that time in the
                    territory of Larinum. Minucius, the master of the horse, had the command of it;
                    the dictator, as was before mentioned, having gone to the city. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But the camp, which had been pitched in an elevated and
                    secure situation, was now brought down into the plain; plans of a bolder
                    character, agreeably with the temper of the general, were in agitation; and
                    either an attack was to be made upon the scattered foragers, or upon the camp
                    now left with an inconsiderable guard. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor did
                    it escape the observation of Hannibal, that the plan of the war had been changed
                    with the general, and that the enemy would act with more boldness than counsel.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal himself too, which one would
                    scarcely credit, though the enemy was near, despatched a third part of his
                    troops to forage, retaining the remaining two-thirds in the camp. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> After that he advanced his camp itself nearer to the
                    enemy, to a hill within the enemy's view, nearly two miles from Geronium; that
                    they might be aware that he was on the alert to protect his foragers if any
                    attack should be made upon them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then he
                    discovered an eminence nearer to, and commanding the very camp of the Romans:
                    and because if he marched openly in the day-time to occupy it, the enemy would
                    doubtless anticipate him by a <pb n="793" xml:id="p.793"/> shorter way, the
                    Numidians having been sent privately in the night, took possession of it.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These, occupying this position, the
                    Romans, the next day, despising the smallness of their numbers, dislodge, and
                    transfer their camp thither themselves. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There
                    was now, therefore, but a very small space between rampart and rampart, and that
                    the Roman line had almost entirely filled; at the same time the cavalry, with
                    the light infantry sent out against the foragers through the opposite part of
                    the camp, effected a slaughter and flight of the scattered enemy far and wide.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor dared Hannibal hazard a regular
                    battle; because with so few troops, that he would scarcely be able to protect
                    his camp if attacked. And now he carried on the war (for part of his army was
                    away) according to the plans of Fabius, by sitting still and creating delays.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He had also withdrawn his troops to their
                    former camp, which was before the walls of Geronium. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Some authors affirm that they fought in regular line, and
                    with encountering standards; that in the first encounter the Carthaginian was
                    driven in disorder quite to his camp; but that, a sally thence having been
                    suddenly made all at once, the Romans in their turn became alarmed; that after
                    that the battle was restored by the arrival of Numerius Decimius the Samnite;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> that this man, the first in family and
                    fortune, not only in Bovianum, whence he came, but in all Samnium, when
                    conducting by command of the dictator to the camp eight thousand infantry and
                    five hundred horse, having shown himself on the rear of Hannibal, seemed to both
                    parties to be a fresh reinforcement coming with Quintus Fabius from Rome;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> that Hannibal, fearing also some
                    ambuscade, withdrew his troops; and that the Roman, aided by the Samnite,
                    pursuing him, took by storm two forts on that day; <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> that six thousand of the enemy were slain, and about five
                    thousand of the Romans; but that though the loss was so nearly equal,
                    intelligence was conveyed to Rome of a signal victory; and a letter from the
                    master of the horse still more presumptuous. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These things were very frequently discussed,
                    both in the senate and assemblies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the
                    dictator alone, while joy pervaded the city, attached no credit to the report or
                    letter; and granting that all were true, affirmed that he feared more from
                    success than failure; then Marcus Metilius, a plebeian tribune, declares that
                    such conduct surely could not <pb n="794" xml:id="p.794"/> be endured.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That the dictator, not only when present
                    was an obstacle to the right management of the affair, but also, being absent
                    from the camp, opposed it still when achieved; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    that he studiously dallied in his conduct of the war, that he might continue the
                    longer in office, and that he might have the sole command both at Rome and in
                    the army. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Since one of the consuls had fallen
                    in battle, and the other was removed to a distance from Italy, under pretext of
                    pursuing a Carthaginian fleet; and the two praetors were occupied in Sicily and
                    Sardinia, neither of which provinces required a praetor at this time. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> That Marcus Minucius, the master of the horse, was
                    almost put under a guard, lest he should see the enemy, and carry on any warlike
                    operation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That therefore, by Hercules, not
                    only Samnium, which had now been yielded to the Carthaginians, as if it had been
                    land beyond the Iberus, but the Campanian, Calenian, and Falernian territories
                    had been devastated, while the dictator was sitting down at Casilinum,
                    protecting his own farm with the legions of the Roman people: that the army,
                    eager for battle, as well as the master of the horse, were kept back almost
                    imprisoned within the rampart: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that their arms
                    were taken out of their hands, as from captured enemies: <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> at length, as soon as ever the dictator had gone away,
                    having marched out beyond their rampart, that they had routed the enemy and put
                    him to flight. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On account of which
                    circumstances, had the Roman commons retained their ancient spirit, that he
                    would have boldly proposed to them to annul the authority of Quintus Fabius; but
                    now he would bring forward a moderate proposition, to make the authority of the
                    master of the horse and the dictator equal; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    and that even then Quintus Fabius should not be sent to the army, till he had
                    substituted a consul in the room of Caius Flaminius. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator kept away from the popular assemblies, in
                    which he did not command a favourable hearing; and even in the senate he was not
                    heard with favourable ears, when his eloquence was employed in praising the
                    enemy, and attributing the disasters of the last two years to the temerity and
                    unskilfulness of the generals; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and when he
                    declared that the master of the horse ought to be called to account for having
                    fought contrary to his injunction. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> That
                        <quote> if the supreme command and administration of affairs were intrusted
                        to him, he would soon take care that men should know, that to a good <pb
                            n="795" xml:id="p.795"/> general fortune was not of great importance;
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> that prudence and conduct governed
                        every thing; that it was more glorious for him to have saved the army at a
                        crisis, and without disgrace, than to have slain many thousands of the
                        enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Speeches of this kind having been made
                    without effect, and Marcus Atilius Regulus created consul, that he might not be
                    present to dispute respecting the right of command, he withdrew to the army on
                    the night preceding the day on which the proposition was to be decided.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> When there was an assembly of the people
                    at break of day, a secret displeasure towards the dictator, and favour towards
                    the master of the horse, rather possessed their minds, than that men had not
                    sufficient resolution to advise a measure which was agreeable to the public; and
                    though favour carried it, influence was wanting to the bill. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> One man indeed was found who recommended the law, Caius
                    Terentius Varro, who had been praetor in the former year, sprung not only from
                    humble but mean parentage. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> They report that
                    his father was a butcher, the retailer of his own meat, and that he employed
                    this very son in the servile offices of that trade. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This young man, when a fortune left him by his
                    father, acquired in such a traffic, had inspired him with the hope of a higher
                    condition, and the gown and forum were <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the
                    objects of his choice, by declaiming vehemently in behalf of men and causes of
                    the lowest kind, in opposition to the interest and character of the good, first
                    came to the notice of the people, and then to offices of honour. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Having passed through the offices of quaestor,
                    plebeian, and curule aedile, and, lastly, that of praetor; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> when now he raised his mind to the hope of the consulship,
                    he courted the gale of popular favour by maligning the dictator, and received
                    alone the credit of the decree of the people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    All men, both at Rome and in the army, both friends and foes, except the
                    dictator himself, considered this measure to have been passed as an insult to
                    him; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but the dictator himself bore the wrong
                    which the infuriated people had put upon him, with the same gravity with which
                    he endured the charges against him which his enemies laid before the multitude;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and receiving the letter containing a
                    decree of the senate respecting the equalization of the command while on his
                    journey, satisfied that an equal share of military skill was not imparted
                    together with the equal share <pb n="796" xml:id="p.796"/> of command, he
                    returned to the army with a mind unsubdued alike by his fellow-citizens and by
                    the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But Minucius, who, in consequence of his
                    success and the favour of the populace, was scarcely endurable before, now
                    especially, unrestrained by shame or moderation, boasted not more in having
                    conquered Hannibal than Quintus Fabius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That he, who had been sought out in their distress as the only general,
                        and as a match for Hannibal; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that he, an
                        event which no record of history contains, was by the order of the people
                        placed upon an equal footing with himself, — a superior with an inferior
                        officer, a dictator with a master of the horse, —in that very city wherein
                        the masters of the horse are wont to crouch and tremble at the rods and axes
                        of the dictator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With such splendour had
                        his valour and success shone forth. That he therefore would follow up his
                        own good fortune, though the dictator persisted in his delay and sloth;
                        measures condemned alike by the sentence of gods and men. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly, on the first day on which he met
                    Quintus Fabius, he intimated <quote> that the first point to be settled was the
                        manner in which they should employ the command thus equalized. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> That he was of opinion that the best plan would
                        be for them to be invested with the supreme authority and command either on
                        alternate days, or, if longer intervals were more agreeable, for any
                        determinate periods; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> in order that the
                        person in command might be a match for the enemy, not only in judgment, but
                        in strength, if any opportunity for action should occur. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Fabius by no means approved of this
                    proposition: he said, <quote> that Fortune would have at her disposal all things
                        which the rashness of his colleague had; that his command had been shared
                        with him, and not taken away; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that he
                        would never, therefore, willingly withdraw from conducting the war, in
                        whatever post he could with prudence and discretion: nor would he divide the
                        command with him with respect to times or days, but that he would divide the
                        army, and that he would preserve, by his own measures, so much as he could,
                        since it was not allowed him to save the whole. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus he carried it, that, as was the custom
                    of consuls, they should divide the legions between them: the first and fourth
                    fell to the lot of Minucius, the second and third to Fabius. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They likewise divided equally between them the <pb n="797"
                        xml:id="p.797"/> cavalry, the auxiliaries of the allies and of the Latin
                    name. The master of the horse was desirous also that they should have separate
                    camps. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From this Hannibal derived a twofold joy; for
                    nothing which was going on among the enemy escaped him; the deserters revealing
                    many things, and he himself examining by his own scouts. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For he considered that he should be able to entrap the
                    unrestrained temerity of Minucius by his usual arts, and that half the force of
                    the sagacity of Fabius had vanished. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was
                    an eminence between the camps of Minucius and the Carthaginians; whoever
                    occupied it would evidently render the position of his enemy less advantageous.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal was not so desirous of gaining it
                    without a contest, though that were worth his while, as to bring on a quarrel
                    with Minucius, who, he well knew, would at all times throw himself in his way to
                    oppose him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> All the intervening ground was at
                    first sight unavailable to one who wished to plant an ambuscade, because it not
                    only had not any part that was woody, but none even covered with brambles, but
                    in reality formed by nature to cover an ambush; so much the more, because no
                    such deception could be apprehended in a naked valley: and there were in its
                    curvatures hollow rocks, such that some of them were capable of containing two
                    hundred armed men. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Within these recesses, five
                    thousand infantry and cavalry are secreted, as many as could conveniently occupy
                    each. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Lest, however, in any part, either the
                    motion of any one of them thoughtlessly coming out, or the glittering of
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> their arms, should discover the
                    stratagem in so open a valley, by sending out a few troops at break of day to
                    occupy the before-mentioned eminence, he diverts the attention of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Immediately, on the first view of them,
                    the smallness of their number was treated with contempt, and each man began to
                    request for himself the task of dislodging the enemy. The general himself, among
                    the most headstrong and absurd, calls to arms to go and seize the place, and
                    inveighs against the enemy with vain presumption and menaces First, he
                    despatches his light-armed; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> after that his
                    cavalry, in a close body; lastly, perceiving that succours were also being sent
                    to the enemy, he marches with his legions drawn up in order of battle.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hannibal also, sending band after band,
                    as the contest increased, as aids to his men when dis- <pb n="798"
                        xml:id="p.798"/> tressed, had now completed a regular army, and a battle was
                    fought with the entire strength of both sides. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> First, the light infantry of the Romans, approaching the eminence, which was
                    preoccupied, from the lower ground, being repulsed and pushed down, spread a
                    terror among the cavalry, which was marching up also and fled back to the
                    standards of the legions: the line of infantry alone stood fearless amidst the
                    panic-struck; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and it appeared that they would
                    by no means have been inferior to the enemy, had it been a regular and open
                    battle, so much confidence did the successful battle a few days before inspire.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> But the troops in ambush created such
                    confusion and alarm, by charging them on both flanks and on their rear, that no
                    one had spirit enough left to fight, or hope enough to try to escape. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then Fabius, first having heard the shout of
                    the terrified troops, and then having gotten a view of their disordered line,
                    exclaims, <quote> It is so; and no sooner than I feared, has adverse fortune
                        overtaken temerity. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Equalled to Fabius in
                        command, he sees that Hannibal is superior to him in courage and in fortune.
                        But another will be the time for reproaches and resentment. Now advance your
                        standards beyond the rampart: let us wrest the victory from the enemy, and a
                        confession of their error from our countrymen. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A great part of the troops having been now
                    slain, and the rest looking about for a way to escape; the army of Fabius showed
                    itself on a sudden for their help, as if sent down from heaven. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And thus, before he came within a dart's throw or joined
                    battle, he both stayed his friends from a precipitate flight and the enemy from
                    excessive fierceness of fighting. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those who
                    had been scattered up and down, their ranks being broken, fled for refuge from
                    every quarter to the fresh army; those who had fled together in parties, turning
                    upon the enemy, now forming a circle, retreat slowly, now concentrating
                    themselves, stand firm. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And now the vanquished
                    and the fresh army had nearly formed one line, and were bearing their standards
                    against the enemy, when the Carthaginians sounded a retreat; Hannibal openly
                    declaring that though he had conquered Minucius, he was himself conquered by
                    Fabius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The greater part of the day having
                    been thus consumed with varying success, Minucius calling together his soldiers,
                    when they had returned to the camp, thus addressed them; <quote> I have often
                        heard, soldiers, <pb n="799" xml:id="p.799"/> that he is the greatest man
                        who himself counsels what is expedient; and that he who listens to the man
                        who gives good advice is the second; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but
                        that he who neither himself is capable of counselling, and knows not how to
                        obey another, is of the lowest order of mind. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Since the first place of mind and talent has been
                        denied us, let us strive to obtain the second and intermediate kind; and
                        while we are learning to command, let us prevail upon ourselves to submit to
                        a man of prudence. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Let us join camps with
                        Fabius, and, carrying our standards to his pavilion, when I have saluted him
                        as my parent, which he deserves on account of the service he has rendered us
                        and of his dignity; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> you, my soldiers,
                        shall salute those men as patrons, whose arms and right-hands just now
                        protected you: and if this day has conferred nothing else upon us, it hath
                        at least conferred upon us the glory of possessing grateful hearts. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The signal being given, there was a general
                    call to collect the baggage: then setting out, and proceeding in order of march
                    to the dictator's camp, they excited at once the surprise of the dictator
                    himself and all around him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the standards
                    were planted before the tribunal, the master of the horse, advancing before the
                    rest, having saluted Fabius as father, and the whole body of his troops having,
                    with one voice, saluted the soldiers who surrounded him as patrons, said,
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> To my parents, dictator, to whom I have just now equalled you, only in
                        name, as far as I could express myself, I am indebted for my life only; to
                        you I owe both my own preservation and that of all these soldiers.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That order of the people, therefore,
                        with which I have been oppressed rather than honoured, I first cancel and
                        annul; and (may it be auspicious to me and you, and to these your armies, to
                        the preserved and the preserver,) I return to your authority and auspices,
                        and restore to you these standards and these legions; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> and I entreat you that, being reconciled, you would
                        order that I may retain the mastership of the horse, and that these soldiers
                        may each of them retain their ranks. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After that hands were joined, and when the
                    assembly was dismissed, the soldiers were kindly and hospitably invited by those
                    known to them and unknown: and that day, from having been a little while ago
                    gloomy in the extreme, and almost accursed, was turned into a day of joy.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At Rome, when the report of the action was
                    conveyed thither, and was <pb n="800" xml:id="p.800"/> afterwards confirmed, not
                    less by letters from the common soldiers of both armies, than from the generals
                    themselves, all men individually extolled Maximus to the skies. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> His renown was equal with Hannibal, and his enemies the
                    Carthaginians: and then at length they began to feel that they were engaged in
                    war with Romans, and in Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For the two
                    preceding years they entertained so utter a contempt for the Roman generals and
                    soldiers, that they could scarcely believe that they were waging war with the
                    same nation which their fathers had reported to them as being so formidable.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They relate also, that Hannibal said, as
                    he returned from the field, that at length that cloud, which was used to settle
                    on the tops of the mountains, had sent down a shower with a storm. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events occur in Italy, Cneius
                    Servilius Geminus, the consul, having sailed round the coast of Sardinia and
                    Corsica with a fleet of one hundred and twenty ships, and received hostages from
                    both places, crossed over into Africa; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and
                    before he made a descent upon the continent, having laid waste the island of
                    Meninx, and received from the inhabitants of Cercina ten talents of silver, in
                    order that their fields too might not be burnt and pillaged, he approached the
                    shores of Africa, and landed his troops. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Thence the soldiers were led out to plunder, and the crews scattered about just
                    as if they were plundering uninhabited islands; <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> and thus, carelessly falling upon an ambuscade, when they were surrounded
                    —the ignorant of the country by those acquainted with it, the straggling by
                    those in close array, they were driven back to their ships in ignominious
                    flight, and with great carnage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As many as one
                    thousand men, together with Sempronius Blaesus, the quaestor, having been lost,
                    the fleet hastily setting sail from the shore, which was crowded with the enemy,
                    proceeded direct for Italy, and was given up at Lilybaeum <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> to Titus Otacilius, the praetor, that it might be taken
                    back to Rome by his lieutenant, Publius Sura. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The consul himself, proceeding through Sicily on foot, crossed the strait into
                    Italy, summoned, as well as his colleague, Marcus Atilius, by a letter from
                    Quintus Fabius, to receive the armies from him, as the period of his command,
                    which was six months, had nearly expired. Almost all the annalists record that
                    Fabius conducted the war against Hannibal, as dictator. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Caelius also writes, that he was the first dictator created
                    by <pb n="801" xml:id="p.801"/> the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But it has escaped Caelius and all the others that Cneius Servilius, the consul,
                    who was then a long way from home in Gaul, which was his province, was the only
                    person who possessed the right of appointing a dictator; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and that as the state, terrified by the disasters which had
                    just befallen it, could not abide the delay, it had recourse to the
                    determination that the people should create a prodictator; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> that his subsequent achievements, his singular renown as a
                    general, and his descendants, who exaggerated the inscription of his statue,
                    easily brought it about that he should be called dictator, instead of
                    prodictator. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, Atilius and Geminus Servilius,
                    having received, the former the army of Fabius, the latter that of Minucius, and
                    fortified their winter quarters in good time, (it was the close of the autumn,)
                    carried on the war with the most perfect unanimity, according to the plans of
                    Fabius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In many places they fell upon the
                    troops of Hannibal when out on foraging excursions, availing themselves of the
                    opportunity, and both harassing their march and intercepting the stragglers.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They did not come to the chance of a
                    general battle, which the enemy tried by every artifice to bring about. And
                    Hannibal was so straitened by the want of provisions, that had he not feared in
                    retiring the appearance of flight, he would have returned to Gaul, no hope being
                    left of being able to subsist an army in those quarters, if the ensuing consuls
                    should carry on the war upon the same plan. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The war having been arrested in its progress at Geronium, the winter
                    interrupting it, ambassadors from Naples came to Rome. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> They carried into the senate-house forty golden goblets, of
                    great weight, and spoke to this effect: <quote> That they knew the treasury of
                        the Romans was exhausted by the war; and since the war was carried on alike
                        in defence of the cities and the lands of the allies, and of the empire and
                        city of Rome, the capital and citadel of Italy, that the Neapolitans thought
                        it but fair that <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> they should assist the
                        Roman people with whatever gold had been left them by their ancestors as
                        well for the decoration of their temples as for the relief of misfortune. If
                        they had thought that there was any resource in themselves, that they would
                        have offered it with the same zeal. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That
                        the Roman fathers and people would render an acceptable service to them, if
                        they would consider all the goods of the Neapolitans as their own;
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        <pb n="802" xml:id="p.802"/> and if they would think them deserving, that
                        they should accept a present at their hands, rendered valuable and of
                        consequence rather by the spirit and affection of those who gave it with
                        cheerfulness, than by its intrinsic worth. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thanks were given to the ambassadors for their
                    munificence and attention, and the goblet of least weight was accepted. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same days a Carthaginian spy, who
                    had escaped for two years, was apprehended at Rome, and his hands having been
                    cut off, was let go: and twenty-five slaves were crucified for forming a
                    conspiracy in the Campus Martius; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> his liberty
                    was given to the informer, and twenty thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> of
                    the heavy standard. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Ambassadors were also sent
                    to Philip, king of the Macedonians, to demand Demetrius of Pharia, who, having
                    been vanquished in war, had fled to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Others were sent to the Ligurians, to expostulate with them for having assisted
                    the Carthaginians with their substance and with auxiliaries; and, at the same
                    time, to take a near view of what was going on amongst the Boii and Insubrians.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Ambassadors were also sent to the
                    Illyrians to king Pineus, to demand the tribute, the day of payment of which had
                    passed; or if he wished to postpone the day, to receive hostages. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Thus, though an arduous war was on their shoulders,
                    no attention to any one concern in any part of the world, however remote,
                    escapes the Romans. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was made a matter of
                    superstitious fear also, that the temple of Concord, which Lucius Manlius, the
                    praetor, had vowed in Gaul two years ago, on occasion of a mutiny, had not been
                    contracted for to that day. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly,
                    Cneius Pupius and Caeso Quinctius Flaminius, created duumviri by Marcus
                    Aemilius, the city praetor, for that purpose, contract for the building a temple
                    in the citadel. By the same praetor a letter was sent to the consuls, agreeably
                    to a decree of the senate, to the effect that, if they thought proper, one of
                    them should come to Rome to elect consuls; and that he would proclaim the
                    election for whatever day they might name. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To
                    this it was replied by the consuls, that they could not leave the enemy without
                    detriment to the public; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that it would be
                    better, therefore, that the election should be held by an interrex, than that
                    one of the consuls should be called away from the war. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> It appeared more proper to the fathers, that a dictator
                    should be nominated by a consul, for the purpose of holding the election. <pb
                        n="803" xml:id="p.803"/> Lucius Veturius Philo was nominated, who chose
                    Manius Pomponius Matho master of the horse. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    These having been created with some defect, they were ordered to give up their
                    appointment on the fourteenth day; and the state came to an interregnum. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To the consuls the authority was continued for
                    a year longer. Caius Claudius Centho, son of Appius, and then Publius Cornelius
                    Asina, were appointed interreges by the fathers. During the interregnum of the
                    latter the election was held, with a violent contest between the patricians and
                    the people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Caius Terentius Varro, whom, as a
                    man of their own order, commended to their favour by inveighing against the
                    patricians and by other popular arts; who had acquired celebrity by maligning
                    others, by undermining the influence of Fabius, and bringing into contempt the
                    dictatorial authority, the commons strove to raise to the consulship. The
                    patricians opposed him with all their might, lest men, by inveighing against
                    them, should come to be placed on an equality with them. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Bœbius Herennius, a plebeian tribune, and kinsman
                    of Caius Terentius, by criminating not only the senate, but the augurs also, for
                    having prevented the dictator from completing the election, by the odium cast
                    upon them, conciliated favour to his own candidate. He asserted, <quote> that
                        Hannibal had been brought into Italy by the nobility, who had for many years
                        been desirous of a war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That by the
                        fraudulent machinations of the same persons the war had been protracted,
                        whereas it might have been brought to a conclusion. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> That it had appeared that the war could be maintained
                        with an army consisting of four legions in all, from Marcus Minucius's
                        having fought with success in the absence of Fabius. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That two legions had been exposed to be slain by the
                        enemy, and were afterwards rescued from absolute destruction, in order that
                        that man might be saluted as father and patron, who had deprived them of
                        victory before he delivered them from defeat. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> That subsequently the consuls, pursuing the plans of
                        Fabius, had protracted the war, whereas it was in their power to have put a
                        period to it. That this was an agreement made by the nobility in general;
                        nor would they ever have the war concluded till they had created a consul
                        really plebeian; that is, a new man: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> for
                        that plebeians who had attained nobility were now initiated into the
                        mysteries, <pb n="804" xml:id="p.804"/> and had begun to look down with
                        contempt upon plebeians, from the moment they ceased to be despised by the
                        patricians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Who was not fully aware that
                        their end and object was, that an interregnum should be formed, in order
                        that the elections might be under the influence of the patricians?
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That both the consuls had that in
                        view in tarrying with the army: and that afterwards a dictator having been
                        nominated to hold the election contrary to their wishes, they had carried
                        it, as it were, by storm, that the augurs should declare the dictator
                        informally elected. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That they therefore
                        had gotten an interregnum; but one consulate was surely in the hands of the
                        Roman people. Thus the people would have that at their own unbiassed
                        disposal, and that they would confer it on that man who would rather conquer
                        in reality than lengthen the term of his command. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the people had been inflamed by these
                    harangues, though there were three patrician candidates for the consulship,
                    Publius Cornelius Merenda, Lucius Manlius Vulso, and <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, two of plebeian families, who had
                    been ennobled, Caius Atilius Serranus and Quintus Aelius Paetus, one of whom was
                    pontiff, the other an augur, Terentius alone was created consul, that the
                    comitia for choosing his colleague might be in his own management. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Then the nobles, finding that the competitors whom
                    they had set up were not strong enough, though he strenuously refused for a long
                    time, prevail upon Aemilius Paulus, who was strongly opposed to the people, to
                    become a candidate. He had been consul before with Marcus Livius, and from the
                    condemnation of his colleague, and almost of himself, had come off scathed.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the next day of the election, all who
                    had opposed Varro withdrawing, he is given to the consul rather as a match to
                    oppose him than as a colleague. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Afterwards the
                    assembly for the election of praetors was held, and Manius Pomponius Matho and
                    Publius Furius Philus were chosen. The city lot for the administration of
                    justice at Rome fell to the lot of Pomponius; between Roman citizens and
                    foreigners, to Philus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two praetors were
                    added, Marcus Claudius Marcellus for Sicily, and Lucius Postumius for Gaul.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These were all appointed in their absence;
                    nor was an honour which he had not previously borne committed to any one of
                    them, except the consul Terentius, several brave and able men having been <pb
                        n="805" xml:id="p.805"/> passed over, because, at such a juncture, it did
                    not appear advisable that a new office should be committed to any one. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The forces also were augmented. But how great
                    was the augmentation of infantry and cavalry authors vary so much, that I
                    scarcely dare positively assert. Some state, that ten thousand soldiers were
                    levied as a reinforcement; others, four fresh legions, that there might be eight
                    legions in service. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It is said also, that the
                    complement of the legion was increased in respect both to foot and <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> horse, one thousand foot and one hundred horse
                    being added to each, so that each might contain five thousand foot and three
                    hundred horse; and that the allies furnished twice as many cavalry, and an equal
                    number of infantry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some authorities affirm
                    that there were eighty-seven thousand two hundred soldiers in the Roman camp
                    when the battle of Cannae was fought. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There is
                    no dispute, that the war was prosecuted with greater energy and spirit than
                    during former years, because the dictator had given them a hope that the enemy
                    might be subdued. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before, however, the
                    new-raised legions marched from the city, the decemviri were ordered to have
                    recourse to and inspect the sacred volumes, on account of persons having been
                    generally alarmed by extraordinary prodigies; for intelligence was brought, that
                    it had rained stones on the Aventine at Rome and at Aricia at the same time.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That among the Sabines, statues had
                    sweated blood copiously, and at Caere the waters had flowed warm from a
                    fountain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The latter prodigy excited a greater
                    degree of alarm, because it had frequently occurred. In a street called the
                    Arched Way, near the Campus Martius, several men were struck by lightning and
                    killed. These prodigies were expiated according to the books. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Ambassadors from Paestum brought some golden goblets to
                    Rome; they were thanked, as the Neapolitans were, but the gold was not accepted. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same time a fleet from Hiero
                    arrived at Ostia with a large cargo of supplies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The Syracusan ambassadors, on being introduced into the senate, delivered
                    this message: <quote> That king Hiero was so much affected at the slaughter
                        announced to him of Caius Flaminius the consul and his troops, that he could
                        not have been more distressed at any disasters which could have befallen
                        himself or his own kingdom; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and
                        accordingly, though he was well aware that <pb n="806" xml:id="p.806"/> the
                        greatness of the Roman people was almost more admirable in adversity than
                        prosperity, he had nevertheless sent every thing which good and faithful
                        allies are wont to contribute to assist the <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> operations of war, which he earnestly implored the
                        conscript fathers not to refuse to accept. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        First of all, for the sake of the omen, they had brought a golden statue of
                        Victory, of three hundred pounds' weight, which they begged them to accept,
                        keep by them, and hold as their own peculiar and lasting possession.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That they had also brought three
                        hundred thousand pecks of wheat, and two hundred thousand of barley, that
                        there might be no want of provisions; and that as much more as might be
                        necessary they would convey, as a supply, to whatever place they might
                        appoint. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He knew that the Roman people
                        employed no legionary troops or cavalry who were not Romans, or of the Latin
                        confederacy; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that he had seen foreign
                        auxiliary as well as native light-armed troops in the Roman camps;
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> he had, therefore, sent one thousand
                        archers and slingers, a suitable force against the Baliares and Moors, and
                        other nations which fought with missile weapons, </quote> To these presents
                    they added also advice: <quote> That the praetor to whose lot the province of
                        Sicily had fallen, should pass a fleet over to Africa, that the enemy also
                        might have a war in their own country, and that less liberty should be
                        afforded them of sending reinforcements to Hannibal. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The senate thus replied to the king: <quote>
                        That Hiero was a good man and an admirable ally; and that from the time he
                        first formed a friendship with the Roman people he had uniformly cultivated
                        a spirit of fidelity, and had munificently assisted the Roman cause at all
                        times and in every place. That this was, as it ought to be, a cause of
                        gratitude to the Roman people. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That the
                        Roman people had not accepted gold which had been brought them also from
                        certain states, though they felt gratitude for the act. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The Victory and the omen, </quote> they said, <quote>
                        they would accept, and would assign and dedicate to that goddess, as her
                        abode, the Capitol, the temple of Jupiter, the best and greatest of gods;
                        hoping that, consecrated in that fortress of the city of Rome, she would
                        continue there firm and immoveable, kind and propitious to the Roman people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The slingers, archers, and corn were handed
                    over to the consuls. To the fleet which Titus Otacilius the proprietor had in
                    Sicily, twenty-five quinqueremes were added, and permis- <pb n="807"
                        xml:id="p.807"/> sion was given him, if he thought it for the interest of
                    the state, to pass over into Africa. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The levy completed, the consuls waited a few
                    days, till the allies of the Latin confederacy arrived. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> At this time the soldiers were bound by an oath, which had
                    never before been the case, dictated by the military tribunes, that they would
                    assemble at the command of the consuls, and not depart without orders;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for up to that time the military oath only
                    had been employed; and further, when the soldiers met to divide into decuries or
                    centuries, the cavalry being formed into decuries and the infantry into
                    centuries, all swore together, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> amongst
                    themselves, of their own accord, that they would not depart or quit their ranks
                    for flight or fear, except for the purpose of taking up or fetching a weapon,
                    and either striking an enemy or saving a countryman. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This, from being a voluntary compact among the soldiers
                    themselves, was converted into the legal compulsion of an oath by the tribunes.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before the standards were moved from the
                    city, the harangues of Varro were frequent and furious, protesting that the war
                    had been invited into Italy by the nobles, and that it would continue fixed in
                    the bowels of the state if it employed any more such generals as Fabius;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that he would bring the war to conclusion
                    on the very day he got sight of the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His
                    colleague Paulus made but one speech, on the day before they set out from the
                    city, which was more true than gratifying to the people, in which nothing was
                    said severely against Varro, except this only. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That he wondered how any general, before he knew any thing of his own
                        army, or that of the enemy, the situation of the places, or the nature of
                        the country, even now while in the city, and with the gown on, could
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> tell what he must do when in arms,
                        and could even foretell the day on which he would fight standard to standard
                        with the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That, for his own part,
                        he would not, before the time arrived, prematurely anticipate those measures
                        which circumstances imposed on men, rather than men on circumstances. He
                        could only wish that those measures which were taken with due caution and
                        deliberation might turn out prosperously. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        That temerity, setting aside its folly, had hitherto been also unsuccessful. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This obviously appeared, that he would prefer
                    safe to precipitate counsels; but that he might persevere the more constantly
                        <pb n="808" xml:id="p.808"/> in this, Quintus Fabius Maximus is reported to
                    have thus addressed him on his departure. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> If you either had a colleague like yourself, Lucius Aemilius, which is
                        what I should prefer, or you were like your colleague, an address from me
                        would be superfluous. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For were you both
                        good consuls, you would do every thing for the good of the state from your
                        own sense of honour, even without my saying a word: and were you both bad
                        consuls, you would neither receive my words into your ears, nor my counsels
                        into your minds. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As the case now is,
                        looking at your colleague and yourself, a man of such character, my address
                        will be solely to you; who, I feel convinced, will prove yourself a good man
                        and a worthy citizen in vain, if the state on the other hand should halt.
                        Pernicious counsels will have the same authority and influence as those
                        which are sound. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For you are mistaken,
                        Lucius Paulus, if you imagine that you will have a less violent contest with
                        Caius Terentius than with Hannibal. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I know
                        not whether the former, your opponent, or the latter, your open enemy, be
                        the more hostile. With the latter you will have to contend in the field
                        only; with the former, at every place and time. Hannibal, moreover, you have
                        to oppose with your own horse and foot; while Varro will head your own
                        soldiers against you. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Let Caius Flaminius
                        be absent from your thoughts, even for the omen's sake. Yet he only began to
                        play the madman's consul, in his province, and at the head of the army. This
                        man is raving before he put up for the consulship, afterwards while
                        canvassing for it, and now having obtained it, before he has seen the camp
                        or the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And he who by talking
                        largely of battles and marshalled armies, even now excites such storms among
                        the citizens with their gowns on, what do you think he will effect among the
                        youth in arms, where words are followed forthwith by acts? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But be assured, if this man, as he protests he will,
                        shall immediately engage the enemy, either I am unacquainted with military
                        affairs, with this kind of war, and the character of the enemy, or another
                        place will become more celebrated than the Trasimenus by our disasters.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Neither is this the season for
                        boasting while I am addressing one man; and besides, I have exceeded the
                        bounds of moderation in despising rather than in courting fame. But the case
                        is really this. The only way of conducting the war <pb n="809"
                            xml:id="p.809"/> against. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal is
                        that which I adopted: nor does the event only, that instructor of fools,
                        demonstrate it, but that same reasoning which has continued hitherto, and
                        will continue unchangeable so long as circumstances shall remain the same.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> We are carrying on war in Italy, in
                        our own country, and our own soil. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> All
                        around us are countrymen and allies in abundance. With arms, men, horses,
                        and provisions, they do and will assist us. Such proofs of their fidelity
                        have they given in our adversity. Time, nay, every day makes us better,
                        wiser, and firmer. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Hannibal, on the
                        contrary, is in a foreign, a hostile land, amidst all hostile and
                        disadvantageous circumstances, far from his home, far from his country; he
                        has peace neither by land nor sea: no cities, no walls receive him: he sees
                        nothing any where which he can call his own: he daily lives by plunder. He
                        has now scarcely a third part of that army which he conveyed across the
                        Iberus. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Famine has destroyed more than
                        the sword; nor have the few remaining a sufficient supply of provisions.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Do you doubt, therefore, whether by
                        remaining quiet we shall not conquer him who is daily sinking into
                        decrepitude? who has neither provisions nor money? <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> How long before the walls of Geronium, a miserable
                        fortress of Apulia, as if before the walls of Carthage — —? But not even in
                        your presence will I boast. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> See how
                        Cneius Servilius and Atilius, the last consuls, fooled him. This is the only
                        path of safety, Lucius Paulus, which your countrymen will render more
                        difficult and dangerous to you than their enemies will. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> For your own soldiers will desire the same thing as
                        those of the enemy: Varro, a Roman consul, and Hannibal, a Carthaginian
                        general, will wish the same thing. You alone must resist two generals: and
                        you will resist them sufficiently if you stand firm against the report and
                        the rumours of men; if neither the empty glory of your colleague, and the
                        unfounded calumnies against yourself, shall move you. They say that truth
                        too often suffers, but is never destroyed. <milestone n="19" unit="section"
                        /> He who despises fame will have it genuine. Let them call you coward
                        instead of cautious, dilatory instead of considerate, unwarlike instead of
                        an expert general. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> I would rather that a
                        sagacious enemy should fear you, than that foolish countrymen should commend
                        you. A man who hazards all things Hannibal will despise, him who does
                        nothing rashly he will fear. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> And neither
                        do I advise that nothing should be done; but that in <pb n="810"
                            xml:id="p.810"/> what you do, reason should guide you, and not fortune.
                        All things will be within your own power, and your own. Be always ready
                        armed and on the watch, and neither be wanting when a favourable opportunity
                        presents itself, nor give any favourable opportunity to the enemy.
                            <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> All things are clear and sure to the
                        deliberate man. Precipitation is improvident and blind. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The address of the consul in reply was by no
                    means cheerful, admitting that what he said was true, rather than easy to put in
                    practice. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He said, <quote> That to him, as
                        dictator, his master of the horse was unbearable: what power or influence
                        could a consul have against a factious and intemperate colleague? <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> That he had in his former consulate escaped a
                        popular conflagration not without being singed: his prayer was, that every
                        thing might happen prosperously; but if, on the contrary, any misfortune
                        should occur, that he would rather expose his life to the weapons of the
                        enemy, than to the votes of his incensed countrymen. </quote> Directly after
                    this discourse, it is related that Paulus set out, escorted by the principal
                    senators. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The plebeian consul attended his own
                    plebeian party, more distinguished by their numbers than respectability.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When they had arrived at the camp, the old
                    and new troops being united, they formed two distinct camps, so that the new and
                    smaller one might be the nearer to Hannibal, and the old one might contain the
                    greater part, and all the choicest of the troops. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> They then sent to Rome Marcus Atilius, the consul of the
                    former year, who alleged his age in excuse. They appoint Geminus Servilius to
                    the command of a Roman legion, and two thousand of the allied infantry and
                    cavalry in the lesser camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hannibal, although
                    he perceived that the forces of the enemy were augmented by one-half, was yet
                    wonderfully rejoiced at the arrival of the consuls; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> for he had not only nothing remaining of the provisions
                    which he daily acquired by plunder, but there was not even any thing left which
                    he could seize, the corn in all the surrounding country having been collected
                    into fortified cities, when the country was too unsafe; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> so that, as was afterwards discovered, there scarcely
                    remained corn enough for ten days, and the Spaniards would have passed over to
                    the enemy, through want of food, if the completion of that time had been
                    awaited. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But fortune afforded materials also to the
                    headstrong and precipitate disposition of the consul, for in checking the <pb
                        n="811" xml:id="p.811"/> plundering parties a battle having taken place, of
                    a tumultuary kind, and occasioned rather by a disorderly advance of the
                    soldiers, than by a preconcerted plan, or by the command of the general, the
                    contest was by no means equal with the Carthaginians. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As many as one thousand seven hundred of them were slain,
                    but not more than one hundred of the Romans and allies. The consul Paulus,
                    however, who was in command on that day, (for they held the command on alternate
                    days,) apprehending an ambuscade, restrained the victorious troops in their
                    headstrong pursuit; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> while Varro indignantly
                    vociferated, that the enemy had been allowed to slip out of their hands, and
                    that the war might have been terminated had not the pursuit been stopped.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal was not much grieved at that
                    loss; nay, rather he felt convinced, that the temerity of the more presumptuous
                    consul, and of the soldiers, particularly the fresh ones, would be lured by the
                    bait; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and besides, all the circumstances of
                    the enemy were as well known to him as his own: that dissimilar and discordant
                    men were in command; that nearly two-thirds of the army consisted of raw
                    recruits. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly, concluding that he now
                    had both a time and place adapted for an ambuscade, on the following night he
                    led his troops away with nothing but their arms, leaving the camp filled with
                    all their effects, both public and private. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    His infantry drawn up he conceals on the left, on the opposite side of the
                    adjoining hills; his cavalry on the right; his baggage in an intermediate line
                    he leads over the mountains through a valley, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"
                    /> in order that he might surprise the enemy when busy in plundering the camp,
                    deserted, as they would imagine, by its owners, and when encumbered with booty.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Numerous fires were left in the camp, to
                    produce a belief that his intention was to keep the consuls in their places by
                    the appearance of a camp, until he could himself escape to a greater distance,
                    in the same manner as he had deceived Fabius the year before. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When it was day, the outpost withdrawn first
                    occasioned surprise, then, on a nearer approach, the unusual stillness.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At length, the desertion being manifest,
                    there is a general rush to the pavilions of the consuls, of those who announced
                    the flight of the enemy so precipitate, that they left their camp, with their
                    tents standing; and, that their flight might be the more secret, that numerous
                    fires were left. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then a clamour arose <pb
                        n="812" xml:id="p.812"/> that they should order the standards to be
                    advanced, and lead them in pursuit of the enemy, and to the immediate plunder of
                    the camp. The other consul too was as one of the common soldiers. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Paulus again and again urged, that they should see
                    their way before them, and use every precaution. Lastly, when he could no longer
                    withstand the sedition and the leader of the sedition, he sends Marius
                    Statilius, a prefect, with a Lucanian troop, to reconnoitre, who, when he
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> had ridden up to the gates, ordered the
                    rest to stay without the works, and entered the camp himself, attended by two
                    horsemen. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having carefully examined every
                    thing, he brings back word that it was manifestly a snare: that fires were left
                    in that part of the camp which faced the enemy: that the tents were open, and
                    that all their valuables were left exposed: that in some places he had seen
                    silver carelessly thrown about the passages, as if laid there for plunder.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This intelligence, which it was hoped
                    would deter their minds from greediness, inflamed them; and the soldiers
                    clamorously declaring, that unless the signal was given they would advance
                    without their leaders, they by no means wanted one, for Varro instantly gave the
                    signal for marching. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Paulus, whom, unwilling
                    from his own suggestions to move, the chickens had not encouraged by their
                    auspices, ordered the unlucky omen to be reported to his colleague, when he was
                    now leading the troops out of the gate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And
                    though Varro bore it impatiently, yet the recent fate of Flaminius, and the
                    recorded naval defeat of Claudius, the consul in the first Punic war, struck
                    religious scruples into his mind. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The gods
                    themselves (it might almost be said) rather postponed than averted the calamity
                    which hung over the Romans; for it fell out by mere accident, that when the
                    soldiers did not obey the consul who ordered them to return to the camp, two
                    slaves, one belonging to a horseman of Formiae, the other to one of Sidicinum,
                    who had been cut off by the Numidians among a party of foragers, when Servilius
                    and Atilius were consuls, had escaped on that day to their masters: <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> and being brought into the presence of the consuls,
                    inform them that the whole army of Hannibal was lying in ambush on the other
                    side of the adjoining mountains. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                    seasonable arrival of these men restored the consuls to their authority, when
                    the ambition of one of them had relaxed his influence with the soldiers, by an
                    undignified compliance. <pb n="813" xml:id="p.813"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, perceiving that the Romans had been
                    indiscreetly prompted rather than rashly carried to a conclusion, returned to
                    his camp without effecting any thing, as his stratagem was discovered.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He could not remain there many days, in
                    consequence of the scarcity of corn; and, moreover, not only among the soldiers,
                    who were mixed up of the off-scouring of various nations, but even with the
                    general himself, day by day new designs arose: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    for, first, when there had been murmuring of the soldiers, and then an open and
                    clamorous demand of their arrears of pay, and a complaint first of the scarcity
                    of provisions, and lastly of famine; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and there
                    being a report that the mercenaries, particularly the Spanish, had formed a plan
                    of passing over to the enemy, it is affirmed that Hannibal himself too sometimes
                    entertained thoughts of flying into Gaul, so that, having left all his infantry,
                    he might hurry away with his cavalry. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Such
                    being the plans in agitation, and such the state of feeling in the camp, he
                    resolved to depart thence into the regions of Apulia, which were warmer, and
                    therefore earlier in the harvest. Thinking also, that the farther he retired
                    from the enemy, the more difficult would desertion be to the wavering.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He set out by night, having, as before,
                    kindled fires, and leaving a few tents to produce an appearance; that a fear of
                    an ambuscade, similar to the former, might keep the Romans in their places.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But when intelligence was brought by the
                    same Lucanian Statilius, who had reconnoitred every place on the other side the
                    mountains, and beyond the camp, that the enemy was seen marching at a distance,
                    then plans began to be deliberated on about pursuing him. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls persisted in the same opinions they ever
                    entertained; but nearly all acquiesced with Varro, and none with Paulus except
                    Servilius, the consul of the former year. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In
                    compliance with the opinion of the majority, they set out, under the impulse of
                    destiny, to render Cannae celebrated by a Roman disaster. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal had pitched his camp near that village, with his
                    back to the wind Vulturnus, which, in those plains which are parched with
                    drought, carries with it clouds of dust. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This
                    circumstance was not only very advantageous to the camp, but would be a great
                    protection to them when they formed their line; as they, with the wind blowing
                    only on their <pb n="814" xml:id="p.814"/> backs, would combat with an enemy
                    blinded with the thickly blown dust. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consuls, employing sufficient
                    diligence in exploring the road in pursuit of the Carthaginian, had arrived at
                    Cannae, where they had the enemy in the sight of them, having divided their
                    forces, they fortify two camps with nearly the same interval as before, at
                    Geronium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The river Aufidus, which flowed by
                    both the camps, afforded approach to the watering parties of each, as
                    opportunity served, though not without contest. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> The Romans in the lesser camp, however, which was on the other side the
                    Aufidus, were more freely furnished with water, because the further bank had no
                    guard of the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal, entertaining a
                    hope that the consuls would not decline a battle in this tract, which was
                    naturally adapted to a cavalry engagement, in which portion of his forces he was
                    invincible, formed his line, and provoked the enemy by a skirmishing attack with
                    his Numidians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Upon this the Roman camp began
                    again to be embroiled by a mutiny among the soldiers, and the disagreement of
                    the consuls: since Paulus instanced to Varro the temerity of Sempronius and
                    Flaminius; while Varro pointed to Fabius, as a specious example to timid and
                    inactive generals. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The latter called both gods
                    and men to witness, <quote> that no part of the blame attached to him that
                        Hannibal had now made Italy his own, as it were, by right of possession;
                        that he was held bound by his colleague; that the swords and arms were taken
                        out of the hands of the indignant soldiers who were eager to fight. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The former declared, <quote> that if any
                        disaster should befall the legions thus exposed and betrayed into an ill-ad-
                        vised and imprudent battle, he should be exempt from any blame, though the
                        sharer of all the consequences. That he must take care that their hands were
                        equally energetic in the battle whose tongues were so forward and impetuous.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While time is thus consumed in altercation
                    rather than deliberating, Hannibal, who had kept his troops drawn up in order of
                    battle till late in the day, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> when he had led
                    the rest of them back into the camp, sends Numidians across the river to attack
                    a watering party of the Romans from the lesser camp. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Having routed this disorderly band by shouting and tumult,
                    before they had well reached the opposite bank, they advanced <pb n="815"
                        xml:id="p.815"/> even to an outpost which was before the rampart, and near
                    the very gates of the camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It seemed so great
                    an indignity, that now even the camp of the Romans should be terrified by a
                    tumultuary band of auxiliaries, that this cause alone kept back the Romans from
                    crossing the river forthwith, and forming their line, that the chief command was
                    on that day held by Paulus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly Varro,
                    on the following day, on which it was his turn to hold the command, without
                    consulting his colleague, displayed the signal for battle, and forming his
                    troops, led them across the river. Paulus followed, because he could better
                    disapprove of the proceeding, than withhold his assistance. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Having crossed the river, they add to their forces those
                    which they had in the lesser camp; and thus forming their line, place the Roman
                    cavalry in the right wing, which was next the river; and next them the infantry:
                    at the extremity of the left wing the allied cavalry; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> within them the allied infantry, extending to the centre,
                    and contiguous to the Roman legions. The darters, and the rest of the
                    light-armed auxiliaries, formed the van. The consuls commanded the wings;
                    Terentius the left, Aemilius the right. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To
                    Geminus Servilius was committed the charge of maintaining the battle in the
                    centre. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal, at break of day, having sent before
                    him the Baliares and other light-armed troops, crossed the river, and placed his
                    troops in line of battle, as he had conveyed them across the river. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The Gallic and Spanish cavalry he placed in the left
                    wing, opposite the Roman cavalry: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> the right
                    wing was assigned to the Numidian cavalry, the centre of the line being strongly
                    formed by the infantry, so that both extremities of it were composed of
                    Africans, between which Gauls and Spaniards were placed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> One would suppose the Africans were for the most part
                    Romans, they were so equipped with arms captured at the Trebia, and for the
                    greater part at the Trasimenus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The shields of
                    the Gauls and Spaniards were of the same shape; their swords unequal and
                    dissimilar. The Gauls had very long ones, without points. The Spaniards, who
                    were accustomed to stab more than to cut their enemy, had swords convenient from
                    their shortness, and with points. The aspect of these nations in other respects
                    was terrific, both as to the appearance they exhibited and the size of their
                    persons. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Gauls were naked above the navel:
                    the <pb n="816" xml:id="p.816"/> Spaniards stood arrayed in linen vests
                    resplendent with surprising whiteness, and bordered with purple. The whole
                    amount of infantry standing in battle-array was forty thousand, of cavalry ten.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The generals who commanded the wings were,
                    on the left Hasdrubal, on the right Maharbal: Hannibal himself, with his brother
                    Mago, commanded the centre. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The sun very
                    conveniently shone obliquely upon both parties; the Romans facing the south, and
                    the Carthaginians the north; either placed so designedly, or having stood thus
                    by chance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The wind, which the inhabitants of
                    the district call the Vulturnus, blowing violently in front of the Romans,
                    prevented their seeing far by rolling clouds of dust into their faces. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The shout being raised, the auxiliaries
                    charged, and the battle commenced in the first place with the light-armed
                    troops: then the left wing, consisting of the Gallic and Spanish cavalry,
                    engages with the Roman right wing, by no means in the manner of a cavalry
                    battle; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for they were obliged to engage front
                    to front; for as on one side the river, on the other the line of infantry hemmed
                    them in, there was no space left at their flanks for evolution, but both parties
                    were compelled to press directly forward. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At
                    length the horses standing still, and being crowded together, man grappling with
                    man, dragged him from his horse. The contest now came to be carried on
                    principally on foot. The battle, however, was more violent than lasting; and the
                    Roman cavalry being repulsed, turn their backs. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> About the conclusion of the contest between the cavalry, the battle between
                    the infantry commenced. At first the Gauls and Spaniards preserved their ranks
                    unbroken, not inferior in strength or courage: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    but at length the Romans, after long and repeated efforts, drove in with their
                    even front and closely compacted line, that part of the enemy's line in the form
                    of a wedge, which projected beyond the rest, which was too thin, and therefore
                    deficient in strength. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These men, thus driven
                    back and hastily retreating, they closely pursued; and as they urged their
                    course without interruption through this terrified band, as it fled with
                    precipitation, were borne first upon the centre line of the enemy; and lastly,
                    no one opposing them, they reached the African reserved troops. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> These were posted at the two extremities of the line, where
                    it was depressed; while the centre, where the Gauls and Spaniards were placed,
                    projected a little. When <pb n="817" xml:id="p.817"/> the wedge thus formed
                    being driven in, at first rendered the line level, but afterwards, by the
                    pressure, made a curvature in the centre, the Africans, who had now formed wings
                    on each side of them, surrounded the Romans <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    on both sides, who incautiously rushed into the intermediate space; and
                    presently extending their wings, enclosed the enemy on the rear also. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> After this the Romans, who had in vain finished one
                    battle, leaving the Gauls and Spaniards, whose rear they <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> had slaughtered, in addition commence a fresh encounter
                    with the Africans, not only disadvantageous, because being hemmed in they had to
                    fight against troops who surrounded them, but also because, fatigued, they
                    fought with those who were fresh and vigorous. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now also in the left wing of the Romans, in
                    which the allied cavalry were opposed to the Numidians, the battle was joined,
                    which was at first languid, commencing with a stratagem on the part of the
                    Carthaginians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> About five hundred Numidians,
                    who, besides their usual arms, had swords concealed beneath their coats of mail,
                    quitting their own party, and riding up to the enemy under the semblance of
                    deserters, with their bucklers behind them, suddenly leap down from their
                    horses; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and, throwing down their bucklers and
                    javelins at the feet of their enemies, are received into their centre, and being
                    conducted to the rear, ordered to remain there; and there they continued until
                    the battle became general. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But afterwards,
                    when the thoughts and attention of all were occupied with the contest, snatching
                    up the shields which lay scattered on all hands among the heaps of slain, they
                    fell upon the rear of the Roman line, and striking their backs and wounding
                    their hams, occasioned vast havoc, and still greater panic and confusion.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While in one part terror and flight
                    prevailed, in another the battle was obstinately persisted in, though with
                    little hope. Hasdrubal, who was then commanding in that quarter, withdrawing the
                    Numidians from the centre of the army, as the conflict with their opponents was
                    slight, <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> sends them in pursuit of the
                    scattered fugitives, and joining the Africans, now almost weary with slaying
                    rather than fighting the Spanish and Gallic infantry. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the other side of the field, Paulus, though
                    severely wounded from a sling in the very commencement of <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> the battle, with a compact body of troops, frequently
                    opposed <pb n="818" xml:id="p.818"/> himself to Hannibal, and in several
                    quarters restored the battle, the Roman cavalry protecting him; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> who, at length, when the consul had not strength enough
                    even to manage his horse, dismounted from their horses. And when some one
                    brought intelligence that the consul had ordered the cavalry to dismount, it is
                    said that Hannibal observed, <quote>How much rather would I that he delivered
                        them to me in chains.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The fight maintained by the dismounted cavalry
                    was such as might be expected, when the victory was undoubtedly on the side of
                    the enemy, the vanquished preferring death in their places to flight; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> and the conquerors, who were enraged at them for
                    delaying the victory, butchering those whom they could not put to flight. They
                    at length, however, drove the few who remained away, worn out with exertion and
                    wounds. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After that they were all dispersed,
                    and such as could, sought to regain their horses for flight. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Cneius Lentulus, a military tribune, seeing, as he rode by,
                    the consul sitting upon a stone and covered with blood, said to him: <quote>
                        Lucius Aemilius! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the only man whom the
                        gods ought to regard as being guiltless of this day's disaster, take this
                        horse, while you have any strength remaining, and I am with you to raise you
                        up and protect you. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Make not this battle
                        more calamitous by the death of a consul. There is sufficient matter for
                        tears and grief without this addition. </quote> In reply the consul said:
                        <quote> Do thou indeed go on and prosper, Cneius Servilius, in your career
                        of virtue! <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But beware lest you waste in
                        bootless commiseration the brief opportunity of escaping from the hands of
                        the enemy. Go and tell the fathers publicly, to fortify the city of Rome,
                        and garrison it strongly before the victorious enemy arrive: and tell
                        Quintus Fabius individually, that Lucius Aemilius lived, and now dies,
                        mindful of his injunctions. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Allow me to
                        expire amid these heaps of my slaughtered troops, that I may not a second
                        time be accused after my consulate, or <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                        stand forth as the accuser of my colleague, in order to defend my own
                        innocence by criminating another. </quote> While finishing these words,
                    first a crowd of their flying countrymen, after that the enemy, came upon them;
                    they overwhelm the consul with their weapons, not knowing who he was: in the
                    confusion his horse rescued Lentulus. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After
                    that they fly precipitately. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Seven thousand
                    escaped to the lesser camp, ten to the greater, about two thousand to the
                    village itself of <pb n="819" xml:id="p.819"/> Cannae, who were immediately
                    surrounded by Carthalo and the cavalry, no fortifications protecting the
                    village. The other consul, whether by design or by chance, made good his escape
                    to Venusia with about seventy horse, without mingling with any party of the
                    flying troops. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Forty thousand foot, two
                    thousand seven hundred horse, there being an equal number of citizens and
                    allies, are said to have been slain. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Among
                    these both the quaestors of the consuls, Lucius Atilius and Lucius Furius
                    Bibaculus; twenty-one military tribunes; several who had passed the offices of
                    consul, praetor, and aedile; among these they reckon Cneius Servilius Germinus,
                    and Marcus Minucius, who had been master of the horse on a former year, and
                    consul some years before: <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> moreover eighty,
                    either senators, or who had borne those offices by which they might be elected
                    into the senate, and who had voluntarily enrolled themselves in the legions.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Three thousand infantry and three hundred
                    cavalry are said to have been captured in that battle. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such is the battle of Cannae, equal in
                    celebrity to the defeat at the Allia: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> but as
                    it was less important in respect to those things which happened after it,
                    because the enemy did not follow up the blow, so was it more important and more
                    horrible with respect to the slaughter of the army; for with respect to the
                    flight at the Allia, as it betrayed the city, so it preserved the army.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Cannae, scarcely seventy accompanied
                    the flying consul: almost the whole army shared the fate of the other who died.
                    The troops collected in the two camps being a half-armed multitude without
                    leaders, those in the larger send a message to the others, that they should come
                    over to them at night, when the enemy was oppressed with sleep, and <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> wearied with the battle, and then, out of joy,
                    overpowered with feasting: that they would go in one body to Canusium.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some entirely disapproved of that advice.
                        <quote>For why,</quote> said they, <quote> did not those who sent for them
                        come themselves, since there would be equal facility of forming a junction?
                        Because, evidently, all the intermediate space was crowded with the enemy,
                        and they would rather expose the persons of others to so great a danger than
                        their own. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Others did not so much disapprove, as want
                    courage to fulfil the advice. Publius Sempronius Tuditanus, a military tribune,
                    exclaims, <quote> Would you rather, then, be captured by the most <pb n="820"
                            xml:id="p.820"/> rapacious and cruel enemy, and have a price set upon
                        your heads, and have your value ascertained by men who will ask whether you
                        are Roman citizens or Latin confederates, in order that from your miseries
                        and indignities honour may be sought for another? <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Not you, at least, if you are the fellow-citizens of
                        Lucius Aemilius, the consul who preferred an honourable death to a life of
                        infamy, and of so many brave men who lie heaped around him. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But, before the light overtakes us, and more numerous
                        bodies of the enemy beset the way, let us break through those disorderly and
                        irregular troops who are making a noise at our gates. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> By the sword and courage, a road may be made through
                        enemies, however dense. In a wedge we shall make our way through this loose
                        and disjointed band, as if nothing opposed us. Come along with me,
                        therefore, ye who wish the safety of yourselves and the state. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having thus said, he draws his sword, and
                    forming a wedge, goes through the midst of the enemy; and as the Numidians
                    discharged their javelins on their right side, which was exposed, they
                    transferred their shields to the right hand, and thus escaped, to the number of
                    six hundred, to the greater camp; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and setting
                    out thence forthwith, another large body having joined them, arrived safe at
                    Canusium. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These measures were taken by the
                    vanquished, according to the impulse of their tempers, which his own disposition
                    or which accident gave to each, rather than in consequence of any deliberate
                    plan of their own, or in obedience to the command of any one. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When all others, surrounding the victorious
                    Hannibal, congratulated him, and advised that, having completed so great a
                    battle, he should himself take the remainder of the day and the ensuing night
                    for rest, and grant it to his exhausted troops; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Maharbal, prefect of the cavalry, who was of opinion that no time should be
                    lost, said to him, <quote> Nay, rather, that you may know what has been achieved
                        by this battle, five days hence you shall feast in triumph in the Capitol.
                        Follow me: I will go first with the cavalry, that they may know that I am
                        arrived before they know of me as approaching. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To Hannibal this project appeared too full of
                    joy, and too great for his mind to embrace it and determine upon it at the
                    instant. Accordingly, he replied to Maharbal, that <quote>he applauded his zeal,
                        but that time was necessary to ponder the proposal.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Upon this Maharbal observed, <quote> Of a
                        truth the gods have not <pb n="821" xml:id="p.821"/> bestowed all things
                        upon the same person. You know how to conquer, Hannibal; but you do not know
                        how to make use of your victory. </quote> That day's delay is firmly
                    believed to have been the preservation of the city and the empire. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> On the following day, as soon as it dawned, they set
                    about gathering the spoils and viewing the carnage, which was shocking, even to
                    enemies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So many thousands of Romans were
                    lying, foot and horse promiscuously, according as accident had brought them
                    together, either in the battle or in the flight. Some, whom their wounds,
                    pinched by the morning cold, had roused, as they were rising up, covered with
                    blood, from the midst of the heaps of slain, were overpowered by the enemy.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some too they found lying alive with their
                    thighs and hams cut, who, laying bare their necks and throats, bid them drain
                    the blood that remained in them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Some were
                    found with their heads plunged into the earth, which they had excavated; having
                    thus, as it appeared, made pits for themselves, and having suffocated themselves
                    by overwhelming their faces with the earth which they threw over them.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A living Numidian, with lacerated nose and
                    ears, stretched beneath a lifeless Roman who lay upon him, principally attracted
                    the attention of all; for when his hands were powerless to grasp his weapon,
                    turning from rage to madness, he had died in the act of tearing his antagonist
                    with his teeth. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The spoils having been gathered for a great
                    part of the day, Hannibal leads his troops to storm the lesser camp, and, first
                    of all, interposing a trench, cuts it off from the river. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But as the men were fatigued with toil, watching, and
                    wounds, a surrender was made sooner than he expected. Having agreed to deliver
                    up their arms and horses, on condition that the ransom of every Roman should be
                    three hundred denarii, for an ally two hundred, for a slave one hundred, and
                    that on payment of that ransom they should be allowed to depart with <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> single garments, they received the enemy into the
                    camp, and were all delivered into custody, the citizens and allies being kept
                    separate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While the time is being spent there,
                    all who had strength or spirit enough, to the number of four thousand foot and
                    two hundred horse, quitted the greater camp and arrived at Canusium; some in a
                    body, others widely dispersed through the country, which was no less secure a
                    course: the camp itself was surrendered to the enemy <pb n="822" xml:id="p.822"
                    /> by the wounded and timid troops, on the same terms as the other was.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A very great booty was obtained; and with
                    the exception of the men and horses, and what silver there was, which was for
                    the most part on the trappings of the horses; for they had but very little in
                    use for eating from, particularly in campaign; all the rest of the booty was
                    given up to be plundered. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then he ordered the
                    bodies of his own troops to be collected for burial. They are said to have been
                    as many as eight thousand of his bravest men. Some authors relate, that the
                    Roman consul also was carefully searched for and buried. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Those who escaped to Canusium, being received by the people
                    of that place within their walls and houses only, were assisted with corn,
                    clothes, and provisions for their journey, by an Apulian lady, named Busa,
                    distinguished for her family and riches; in return for which munificence, the
                    senate afterwards, when the war was concluded, conferred honours upon her. </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But, though there were four military tribunes
                    there, Fabius Maximus of the first legion, whose father had been dictator the
                    former year; and of the second legion, Lucius Publicius Bibulus and Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and of the third legion,
                    Appius Claudius Pulcher, who had been aedile the last year; by the consent of
                    all, the supreme command was vested in Publius Scipio, then a very young man,
                    and Appius Claudius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To these, while
                    deliberating with a few others on the crisis of their affairs, Publius Furius
                    Philus, the son of a man of consular dignity, brings intelligence, <quote> That
                        it was in vain that they cherished hopes which could never be realized:
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that the state was despaired of, and
                        lamented as lost. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That certain noble
                        youths, the chief of whom was Lucius Caecilius Metellus, turned their
                        attention to the sea and ships, in order that, abandoning Italy, they might
                        escape to some king. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When this calamity, which was not only
                    dreadful in itself, but new, and in addition to the numerous disasters they had
                    sustained, had struck them motionless with astonishment and stupor; and while
                    those who were present gave it as their opinion that a council should be called
                    to deliberate upon it, young Scipio, the destined general of this war, asserts,
                        <quote> That it is not a proper subject for deliberation: that courage and
                        action, and not deliberation, were necessary in so great a calamity.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That those who wished the safety of
                        the state would attend him forthwith in arms; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> that in no place <pb n="823" xml:id="p.823"/> was the
                        camp of the enemy more truly, than where such designs were meditated. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He immediately proceeds, attended by a few, to
                    the lodging of Metellus; and finding there the council of youths of which he had
                    been apprized, he drew his sword over the heads of them, deliberating, and said,
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> With sincerity of soul I swear that neither will I myself desert the
                        cause of the Roman republic, nor will I suffer any other citizen of Rome to
                        desert it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If knowingly I violate my
                        oath, then, O Jupiter, supremely great and good, mayest thou visit my house,
                        my family, and my fortune with perdition the most horrible! <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> I require you, Lucius Caecilius, and the rest of
                        you who are present, to take this oath; and let the man who shall not take
                        it be assured, that this sword is drawn against him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Terrified, as though they were beholding the
                    victorious Hannibal, they all take the oath, and deliver themselves to Scipio to
                    be kept in custody. </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the time in which these things were
                    going on at Canusium, as many as four thousand foot and horse, who had been
                    dispersed through the country in the flight, came to Venusia, to the consul.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These the Venusini distributed throughout
                    their families, to be kindly entertained and taken care of; and also gave to
                    each horseman a gown, a tunic, and twenty-five denarii; and to each foot soldier
                    ten denarii, and such arms as they wanted; and every other kind of hospitality
                    showed them, both publicly and privately: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    emulously striving that the people of Venusia might not be surpassed by a woman
                    of Canusium in kind offices. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the great
                    number of her guests rendered the burden more oppressive to Busa, for they
                    amounted now to ten thousand men. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Appius and
                    Scipio, having heard that the other consul was safe, immediately send a
                    messenger to inquire how great a force of infantry and cavalry he had with him,
                    and at the same time to ask, whether it was his pleasure that the army should be
                    brought to Venusia, or remain at Canusium. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Varro himself led over his forces to Canusium. And now there was some appearance
                    of a consular army, and they seemed able to defend themselves from the enemy by
                    walls, if not by arms. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At Rome intelligence
                    had been received, that not even these relics of their citizens and allies had
                    survived, but that the two consuls, with their armies, were cut to pieces, and
                    all their forces annihilated. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Never when the
                    city was in safety <pb n="824" xml:id="p.824"/> was there so great a panic and
                    confusion within the walls of Rome. I shall therefore shrink from the task, and
                    not attempt to relate what in describing I must make less than the reality. The
                    consul and his army having been lost at the Trasimenus the year before, it was
                    not one wound upon another which was announced, but a multiplied disaster, the
                    loss of two consular armies, together with the two consuls: <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and that now there was neither any Roman camp, nor general,
                    nor soldiery: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that Apulia and Samnium, and
                    now almost the whole of Italy, were in the possession of Hannibal. No other
                    nation surely would not have been overwhelmed by such an accumulation of
                    misfortune. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Shall I compare with it the
                    disaster of the Carthaginians, sustained in a naval battle at the islands
                    Aegates, dispirited by which they gave up Sicily and Sardinia, and thenceforth
                    submitted to become tributary and stipendiary? Or shall I compare with it the
                    defeat in Africa, under which this same Hannibal afterwards sunk? In no respect
                    are they comparable, except that they were endured with less fortitude. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Publius Furius Philus and Manius Pomponius,
                    the praetors, assembled the senate in the curia hostilia, that they might
                    deliberate about the guarding of the city; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for
                    they doubted not but that the enemy, now their armies were annihilated, would
                    come to assault Rome, the only operation of the war which remained. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Unable to form any plan in misfortunes, not only very
                    great, but unknown and undefined, and while the loud lamentations of the women
                    were resounding, and nothing was as yet made known, the living and the dead
                    alike being lamented in almost every house; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    such being the state of things, Quintus Fabius gave it as his opinion, <quote>
                        That light horsemen should be sent out on the Latin and Appian ways, who,
                        questioning those they met, as some would certainly be dispersed in all
                        directions from the flight, might bring back word what was the fate of the
                        consuls and their armies; and if the gods, pitying the empire, had left any
                        remnant of the Roman name where these forces were; whither Hannibal had
                        repaired after the battle, what he was meditating; what he was doing, or
                        about to do. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That these points should be
                        searched out and ascertained by active youths. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That it should be the business of the fathers, since
                        there was a deficiency of magistrates, to do away with the tumult and <pb
                            n="825" xml:id="p.825"/> trepidation in the city; to keep the women from
                        coming into public, and compel each to abide within her own threshold; to
                        put a stop to the lamentations of families; <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> to obtain silence in the city; to take care that the bearers of every
                        kind of intelligence should be brought before the praetors; that each person
                        should await at home the bearer of tidings respecting his own fortune:
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> moreover, that they should post guards
                        at the gates, to prevent any person from quitting the city; and oblige men
                        to place their sole hopes of safety in the preservation of the walls and the
                        city. That when the tumult had subsided the fathers should be called again
                        to the senate-house, and deliberate on the defence of the city. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When all had signified their approbation of
                    this opinion, and after the crowd had been removed by the magistrates from the
                    forum, and the senators had proceeded in different directions to allay the
                    tumult; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> then at length a letter is brought
                    from the consul Terentius, stating, <quote> That Lucius Aemilius, the consul,
                        and his army were slain; that he himself was at Canusium, collecting, as it
                        were after a shipwreck, the remains of this great disaster; that he had
                        nearly ten thousand irregular and unorganized troops. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> That the Carthaginian was sitting still at Cannae,
                        bargaining about the price of the captives and the other booty, neither with
                        the spirit of a conqueror nor in the style of a great general. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then also the losses of private families were
                    made known throughout the several houses; and so completely was the whole city
                    filled with grief, that the anniversary sacred rite of Ceres was intermitted,
                    because it was neither allowable to perform it while in mourning, nor was there
                    at that juncture a single matron who was not in mourning. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, lest the same cause should occasion the
                    neglect of other public and private sacred rites, the mourning was limited to
                    thirty days, by a decree of the senate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now
                    when the tumult in the city was allayed, an additional letter was brought from
                    Sicily, from Titus Otacilius, the proprietor, stating, <quote> that the kingdom
                        of Hiero was being devastated by the Carthaginian fleet: <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> and that, being desirous of affording him the
                        assistance he implored, he received intelligence that another Carthaginian
                        fleet was stationed at the Aegates, equipped and prepared; in order that
                        when the Carthaginians had perceived that he was gone away to protect the
                        coast of Syracuse, they might im- <pb n="826" xml:id="p.826"/> mediately
                        attack Lilybaeum and other parts of the Roman province; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> that he therefore needed a fleet, if they wished him to
                        protect the king their ally, and Sicily. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The letters of the consul and the proprietor
                    having been read, they resolved that Marcus Claudius, who commanded the fleet
                    stationed at Ostia, should be sent to the army to Canusium; and a letter be
                    written to the consul, to the effect that, having delivered the army to the
                    praetor, he should return to Rome the first moment he could, consistently with
                    the interest of the republic. They were terrified also, in addition to these
                    disasters, both with other prodigies, and also because two vestal virgins,
                    Opimia and Floronia, were that year convicted of incontinence; one of whom was,
                    according to custom, buried alive at the Colline gate; the other destroyed
                    herself. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Lucius Cantilius, secretary of the
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> pontiff, whom they now call the lesser
                    pontiffs, who had debauched Floronia, was beaten by rods in the comitium, by
                    order of the chief pontiff, so that he expired under the stripes. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> This impiety being converted into a prodigy, as is
                    usually the case when happening in the midst of so many calamities, the
                    decemviri were desired to consult the sacred books. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius Pictor was also sent to Delphi, to inquire
                    of the oracle by what prayers and offerings they might appease the gods, and
                    what termination there would be to such great distresses. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Meanwhile certain extraordinary sacrifices were performed,
                    according to the directions of the books of the fates; among which a Gallic man
                    and woman, and a Greek man and woman, were let down alive in the cattle market,
                    into a place fenced round with stone, which had been already polluted with human
                    victims, a rite by no means Roman. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The gods
                    being, as they supposed, sufficiently appeased, Marcus Claudius Marcellus sends
                    from Ostia to Rome, as a garrison for the city, one thousand five hundred
                    soldiers, which he had with him, levied for the fleet. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He himself sending before him a marine legion, (it was the
                    third legion,) under the command of the military tribunes, to Teanum Sidicinum,
                    and delivering the fleet to Publius Furius Philus, his colleague, after a few
                    days, proceeded by long marches to Canusium. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Marcus Junius, created dictator on the authority of the senate, and Titus
                    Sempronius, master of the horse, proclaiming a levy, enrol the younger men from
                    the age of seventeen, and <pb n="827" xml:id="p.827"/> some who wore the toga
                    praetexta: of these, four legions and a thousand horse were formed. They send
                    also to the allies and the Latin confederacy, to receive the soldiers according
                    to the terms of the treaty. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They order that
                    arms, weapons, and other things should be prepared; and they take down from the
                    temples and porticoes the old spoils taken from the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They adopted also another and a new form of levy, from the
                    scarcity of free persons, and from necessity: they armed eight thousand stout
                    youths from the slaves, purchased at the public expense, first inquiring of each
                    whether he was willing to serve. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They
                    preferred this description of troops, though they had the power of redeeming the
                    captives at a less expense. </p>
                <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For Hannibal, after so great a victory at
                    Cannae, being occupied with the cares of a conqueror, rather than one who had a
                    war to prosecute, the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> captives having been
                    brought forward and separated, addressed the allies in terms of kindness, as he
                    had done before at the Trebia and the lake Trasimenus, and dismissed them
                    without a ransom; then he addressed the Romans too, who were called to him, in
                    very gentle terms: <quote> That he was not carrying on a war of extermination
                        with the Romans, but was contending for honour and empire. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> That his ancestors had yielded to the Roman valour; and
                        that he was endeavouring that others might be obliged to yield, in their
                        turn, to his good fortune and valour together. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Accordingly, he allowed the captives the liberty of
                        ransoming themselves, and that the price per head should be five hundred
                        denarii for a horseman, three hundred for a foot soldier, and one hundred
                        for a slave. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although some addition was made to that sum
                    for the cavalry, which they stipulated for themselves when they surrendered, yet
                    they joyfully accepted any terms of entering into the compact. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> They determined that ten persons should be selected, by
                    their own votes, who might go to Rome to the senate; nor was any other guarantee
                    of their fidelity taken than that they should swear that they would return.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With these was sent Carthalo, a noble
                    Carthaginian, who might propose terms, if perchance their minds were inclined
                    towards peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they had gone out of the
                    camp, one of their body, a man who had very little of the Roman character, under
                    pretence of having for- gotten something, returned to the camp, for the purpose
                    of <pb n="828" xml:id="p.828"/> freeing himself from the obligation of his oath,
                    and overtook his companions before night. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                    it was announced that they had arrived at Rome, a lictor was 'despatched to meet
                    Carthalo, to tell him, in the words of the dictator, to depart from the Roman
                    territories before night. </p>
                <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An audience of the senate was granted by the
                    dictator to the delegates of the prisoners. The chief of them, Marcus Junius,
                    thus spoke: <quote> There is not one of us, conscript fathers, who is not aware
                        that there never was a nation which held prisoners in greater contempt than
                        our own. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But unless our own cause is
                        dearer to us than it should be, never did men fall into the hands of the
                        enemy who less deserved to be disregarded than we do; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> for we did not surrender our arms in the battle through
                        fear; but having prolonged the battle almost till night-fall, while standing
                        upon heaps of our slaughtered countrymen, we betook ourselves to our camp.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For the remainder of the day and
                        during the following night, although exhausted with exertion and wounds, we
                        protected our rampart. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the following
                        day, when, beset by the enemy, we were deprived of water, and there was no
                        hope of breaking through the dense bands of the enemy; and, moreover, not
                        considering it an impiety that any Roman soldier should survive the battle
                        of Cannae, after fifty thousand of our army had been butchered; <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> then at length we agreed upon terms on which we
                        might be ransomed and let off; and our arms, in which there was no longer
                        any protection, we delivered to the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        We had been informed that our ancestors also had redeemed themselves from
                        the Gauls with gold, and that though so rigid as to the terms of peace, had
                        sent ambassadors to Tarentum for the purpose of ransoming the captives.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And yet both the fight at the Allia
                        with the Gauls, and at Heraclea with Pyrrhus, was disgraceful, not so much
                        on account of the loss as the panic and flight. Heaps of Roman carcasses
                        cover the plains of Cannae; nor would any of us have survived the battle,
                        had not the enemy wanted the strength and the sword to slay us. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> There are, too, some of us, who did not even
                        retreat in the field; but being left to guard the camp, came into the hands
                        of the enemy when it was surrendered. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For
                        my part, I envy not the good fortune or condition of any citizen or
                        fellow-soldier, nor would I endeavour to raise myself by depressing another:
                        but not even <pb n="829" xml:id="p.829"/> those men who, for the most part,
                        leaving their arms, fled from the field, and stopped not till they arrived
                        at Venusia or Canusium; not even those men, unless some reward is due to
                        them on account of their swiftness of foot and running, would justly set
                        themselves before us, or boast that there is more protection to the state in
                        them than in us. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But you will both find
                        them to be good and brave soldiers, and us still more zealous, because, by
                        your kindness, we have been ransomed and restored to our country. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> You are levying from every age and condition: I
                        hear that eight thousand slaves are being armed. We are no fewer in number;
                        nor will the expense of redeeming us be greater than that of purchasing
                        these. Should I compare ourselves with them, I should injure the name of
                        Roman. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I should think also, conscript
                        fathers, that in deliberating on such a measure, it ought also to be
                        considered, (if you are disposed to be over severe, which you cannot do from
                        any demerit of ours,) to what sort of enemy you would abandon us. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Is it to Pyrrhus, for instance, who treated us,
                        when his prisoners, like guests; or to a barbarian and Carthaginian, of whom
                        it is difficult to determine whether his rapacity or cruelty be the greater?
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> If you were to see the chains, the
                        squalid appearance, the loathsomeness of your countrymen, that spectacle
                        would not, I am confident, less affect you, than if, on the other hand, you
                        beheld your legions prostrate on the plains of Cannae. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> You may behold the solicitude and the tears of our
                        kinsmen, as they stand in the lobby of your senate-house, and await your
                        answer. When they are in so much suspense and anxiety in behalf of us, and
                        those who are absent, what think you must be our own feelings, whose lives
                        and liberty are at stake? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> By Hercules!
                        should Hannibal himself, contrary to his nature, be disposed to be lenient
                        towards us, yet we should not consider our lives worth possessing, since we
                        have seemed unworthy of being ransomed by you. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> Formerly, prisoners dismissed by Pyrrhus, without
                        ransom, returned to Rome; but they returned in company with ambassadors, the
                        chief men of the state, who were sent to ransom them. Would I return to my
                        country, a citizen, and not considered worth three hundred denarii? Every
                        man has his own way of thinking, conscript fathers. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> I know that my life and person are at stake. But the
                        danger which threatens my reputation affects me most, if we should <pb
                            n="830" xml:id="p.830"/> go away rejected and condemned by you; for men
                        will never suppose that you grudged the price of our redemption. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had finished his address, the crowd of
                    persons in the comitium immediately set up a loud lamentation, and stretched out
                    their hands to the senate, imploring them to restore to them their children,
                    their brothers, and their kinsmen. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Their fears
                    and affection for their kindred had brought the women also with the crowd of men
                    in the forum. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Witnesses being excluded, the
                    matter began to be discussed in the senate. There being a difference of opinion,
                    and some advising that they should be ransomed at the public charge, others,
                    that the state should be put to no expense, but that they should not be
                    prevented redeeming themselves at their own cost; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and that those who had not the money at present should
                    receive a loan from the public coffer, and security given to the people by their
                    sureties and properties; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Titus Manlius
                    Torquatus, a man of primitive, and, as some considered, over-rigorous severity,
                    being asked his opinion, is reported thus to have spoken: <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Had the deputies confined themselves to making a request, in behalf of
                        those who are in the hands of the enemy, that they might be ransomed, I
                        should have briefly given my opinion, without inveighing against any one.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For what else would have been
                        necessary but to admonish you, that you ought to adhere to the custom handed
                        down from your ancestors, a precedent indispensable to military discipline.
                        But now, since they have almost boasted of having surrendered themselves to
                        the enemy, and have claimed to be preferred, not only to those who were
                        captured by the enemy in the field, but to those also who came to Venusia
                        and Canusium, and even to the consul Terentius himself; I will not suffer
                        you to remain in ignorance of things which were done there. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> And I could wish that what I am about to bring before
                        you, were stated at Canusium, before the army itself, the best witness of
                        every man's cowardice or valour; or at least that one person, Publius
                        Sempronius, were here, whom had they followed as their leader, they would
                        this day have been soldiers in the Roman camp, and not prisoners in the
                        power of the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But though the enemy
                        was fatigued with fighting, and engaged in rejoicing for their victory, and
                        had, the greater part of them, retired into their camp, and they had the
                        night at their disposal for making a sally, and as they <pb n="831"
                            xml:id="p.831"/> were seven thousand armed troops, might have forced
                        their way through the troops of the enemy, however closely arrayed; yet they
                        neither of themselves attempted to do this, nor were willing to follow
                        another. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Throughout nearly the whole
                        night Sempronius ceased not to admonish and exhort them, while but few of
                        the enemy were about the camp, while there was stillness and quiet, while
                        the night would conceal their design, that they would follow him; that
                        before daybreak they might reach places of security, the cities of their
                        allies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If as Publius Decius, the
                        military tribune in Samnium, said, within the memory of our grandfathers; if
                        he had said, as Calpurnius Flamma, in the first Punic war, when we were
                        youths, said to the three hundred volunteers, when he was leading them to
                        seize upon an eminence situated in the midst of the enemy: <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> LET US DIE, SOLDIERS, AND BY OUR DEATHS RESCUE THE
                        SURROUNDED LEGIONS FROM AMBUSCADE; —if Publius Sempronius had said thus, he
                        would neither have considered you as Romans nor men, had no one stood
                        forward as his companion in so valorous an attempt. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> He points out to you the road that leads not to glory
                        more than to safety; he restores you to your country, your parents, your
                        wives and children. Do you want courage to effect your preservation?
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> What would you do if you had to die
                        for your country? Fifty thousand of your countrymen and allies on that very
                        day lay around you slain. If so many examples of courage did not move you,
                        nothing ever will. If so great a carnage did not make life less dear, none
                        ever will. While in freedom and safety, show your affection for your
                        country; nay, rather do so while it is your country, and you its citizens.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Too late you now endeavour to evince
                        your regard for her when degraded, disfranchised from the rights of
                        citizens, and become the slaves of the Carthaginians. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Shall you return by purchase to that degree which you
                        have forfeited by cowardice and neglect? You did not listen to Sempronius,
                        your countryman, when he bid you take arms and follow him; but a little
                        after you listened to Hannibal, when he ordered your arms to be surrendered,
                        and your camp betrayed. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> But why do I
                        charge those men with cowardice, when I might tax them with villany? They
                        not only refused to follow him who gave them good advice, but endeavoured to
                        oppose and hold him back, had not some men of the greatest bravery, drawing
                        their <pb n="832" xml:id="p.832"/> swords, removed the cowards. Publius
                        Sempronius, I say, was obliged to force his way through a band of his
                        countrymen, before he burst through the enemy's troops. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> Can our country regret such citizens as these, whom if
                        all the rest resembled, she would not have one citizen of all those who
                        fought at Cannae? <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Out of seven thousand
                        armed men, there were six hundred who had courage to force their way, who
                        returned to their country free, and in arms; nor did forty thousand of the
                        enemy successfully oppose them. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> How safe,
                        think you, would a passage have been for nearly two legions? Then you would
                        have had this day at Canusium, conscript fathers, twenty thousand bold and
                        faithful. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> But now how can these men be
                        called faithful and good citizens, (for they do not even call themselves
                        brave,) except any man suppose that they showed themselves such when they
                        opposed those who were desirous of forcing their way through the enemy? or,
                        unless any man can suppose, that they do not envy those men their safety and
                        glory acquired by valour, when they must know that their timidity and
                        cowardice were the cause of their ignominious servitude? <milestone n="22"
                            unit="section"/> Skulking in their tents, they preferred to wait for the
                        light and the enemy together, when they had an opportunity of sallying forth
                        during the silence of the night. But though they had not courage to sally
                        forth from the camp, had they courage to defend it strenuously? <milestone
                            n="23" unit="section"/> Having endured a siege for several days and
                        nights, did they protect their rampart by their arms, and themselves by
                        their rampart? At length, having dared and suffered every extremity, every
                        support of life being gone, their strength exhausted with famine, and unable
                        to hold their arms, were they subdued by the necessities of nature, rather
                        than by arms? <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> At sunrise, the enemy
                        approached the rampart: before the second hour, without hazarding any
                        contest, they delivered up their arms and themselves. Here is their military
                        service for you during two days. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> When
                        they ought to have stood firm in array and fight on, then they fled back
                        into their camp; when they ought to have fought before their rampart, they
                        delivered up their camp: good for nothing, either in the field or the camp.
                            <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> I redeem you? When you ought to sally
                        from the camp, you linger and hesitate; and when you ought to stay and
                        protect your camp in arms, you surrender the camp, your arms, and yourselves
                        to <pb n="833" xml:id="p.833"/> the enemy. <milestone n="27" unit="section"
                        /> I am of opinion, conscript fathers, that these men should no more be
                        ransomed, than that those should be surrendered to Hannibal, who sallied
                        from the camp through the midst of the enemy, and, with the most
                        distinguished courage, restored themselves to their country. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After Manlius had thus spoken, notwithstanding
                    the captives were related to many even of the senators, besides the practice of
                    the state, which had never shown favour to captives, even from the remotest
                    times, the sum of money also influenced them: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    for they were neither willing to drain the treasury, a large sum of money having
                    been already issued for buying and arming slaves to serve in the war, nor to
                    enrich Hannibal, who, according to report, was particularly in want of this very
                    thing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The sad reply, that the captives would
                    not be ransomed, being delivered, and fresh grief being added to the former on
                    account of the loss of so many citizens, the people accompanied the deputies to
                    the gate with copious tears and lamentations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    One of them went home, because he had evaded his oath by artfully returning to
                    the camp. But when this was known and laid before the senate, they all resolved
                    that he should be apprehended and conveyed to Hannibal by guards, furnished by
                    the state. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There is another account respecting
                    the prisoners, that ten came first, and that, the senate hesitating whether they
                    should be admitted into the city or not, they were admitted, on the
                    understanding that they should not have an audience of the senate. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> That when these staid longer than the expectation of
                    all, three more came, Scribonius, Calpurnius, and Manlius. That then at length a
                    tribune of the people, a relation of Scribonius, laid before the senate the
                    redemption of the captives, and that they resolved that they should not be
                    ransomed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the three last deputies
                    returned to Hannibal, and the ten former remained, because they had evaded their
                    oath, having returned to Hannibal after having set out, under pretence of
                    learning afresh the names of the captives. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    That a violent contest took place in the senate, on the question of surrendering
                    them, and that those who thought they ought <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    to be surrendered were beaten by a few votes, but that they were so branded by
                    every kind of stigma and ignominy by the ensuing censors, that some of them
                    immediately put themselves to death, and the rest, for all their life
                    afterwards, not only shunned the forum, <pb n="834" xml:id="p.834"/> but almost
                    the light and publicity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> You can more easily
                    wonder that authors differ so much than determine what is the truth. How much
                    greater this disaster was than any preceding, even this is a proof, that such of
                    the allies as had stood firm till that day then began to waver, for no other
                    cause certainly but that they despaired of the empire. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The people who revolted to the Carthaginians were these:
                    the Atellani, Calatini, the Hirpini, some of the Apulians, the Samnites, except
                    the Pentrians, all the Bruttians, and the Lucanians. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Besides these the Surrentinians, and almost the whole coast
                    possessed by the Greeks, the people of Tarentum, Metapontum, Croton, the
                    Locrians, and all Cisalpine Gaul. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Yet not
                    even these losses and defections of their allies so shook the firmness of the
                    Romans, that any mention of peace was made among them, either before the arrival
                    of the consul at Rome, or after he came thither, and renewed the memory of the
                    calamity they had suffered. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> At which very
                    juncture, such was the magnanimity of the state, that the consul, as he returned
                    after so severe a defeat, of which he himself was the principal cause, was met
                    in crowds of all ranks of citizens, and thanks bestowed because he had not
                    despaired of the republic, in whose case, had he been <milestone n="15??"
                        unit="section"/> a Carthaginian commander, no species of punishment would
                    have been spared. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
