<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="work">On Behalf Of Marcus Fonteius</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="M. Tullius Cicero">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!-- <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  -->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-04-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Minor edits and cleanup.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-10" who="Zach Himes">Converted section milestones to divs</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode </change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi007.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
   <head>THE FRAGMENTS WHICH REMAIN OF THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO ON BEHALF OF MARCUS
    FONTEIUS.</head>

   <div type="commentary" resp="editor">
    <head>The Argument.</head>
    <p>Fonteius had been praetor of <placeName key="tgn,7012209">Gallia Narbonensis</placeName> for
     three years, and was accused now by the people of the province, and by Induciomarus, one of
     their princes, of great oppression and exaction in his government, and especially of imposing
     an arbitrary tax upon their wines. There were two hearings of this cause, but we have only this
     one speech of Cicero's with reference to it remaining; and this is in a very mutilated
     state.</p>
   </div>
  
   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/><gap reason="lost"/> For I defend Marcus Fonteius, O judges, on this ground, and I assert that
    after the passing of the Valerian law, from the time that Marcus Fonteius was quaestor till the
    time when Titus Crispinus was quaestor, no one paid it otherwise. I say that he followed the
    example of all his predecessors, and that all those who came after him, followed his. What,
    then, do you accuse? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p> what do you find fault with? For because
    in these accounts, which he says were begun by Hirtuleius, he misses the assistance of
    Hirtuleius, I cannot think that he either does wrong himself, or wishes you to do wrong. For I
    ask you, O Marcus Plaetorius, whether you will consider our case established, if Marcus
    Fonteius, in the matter respecting which he is now accused by you, has the man whom you praise
    above all others, namely Hirtuleius, for his example; and if Fonteius is found to have done
    exactly the same as Hirtuleius in the matters in which you commend Hirtuleius? You find fault
    with the description of payment. The public registers prove that Hirtuleius paid in the same
    manner. You praise him for having established these peculiar accounts. Fonteius established the
    same, with reference to the same kind of money. For, that you may not ignorantly imagine that
    these accounts refer to some different description of debt, know that they were established for
    one and the same reason, and with reference to one and the same sort of money. For when<gap reason="lost"/>
    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/><gap reason="lost"/>No one—no one, I say, O judges—will be found, to say that he gave Marcus
    Fonteius one sesterce during his praetorship, or that he appropriated one out of that money
    which was paid to him on account of the treasury. In no account-books is there any hint of such
    a robbery among all the items contained in them there will not be found one trace of any loss or
    diminution of such monies. But all those men whom we ever see accused and found fault with by
    this sort of inquiry, are overwhelmed with witnesses; for it is difficult for him who has given
    money to a magistrate to avoid being either induced by dislike of him, or compelled by
    scrupulousness, to mention it; and in the next place, if the witnesses are deterred from
    appearing by any influence, at all events the account-books remain uncorrupted and honest.
    Suppose that every one was ever so friendly to Fonteius; that such a number of men to whom he
    was perfectly unknown, and with whom he was utterly unconnected, spared his life, and consulted
    his character; still, the facts of the case itself, the consideration of the documents, and the
    composition of the account-books, have this force, that from them, when they are once given in
    and received, everything that is forged, or stolen, or that has disappeared, is detected. All
    those men made entries of sums of money having been received for the use of the Roman people; if
    they immediately either paid or gave to others equally large sums, so that what was received for
    the Roman people was paid to some one or other, at all events nothing can have been embezzled.
    If any of them took any money home<gap reason="lost"/>
    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Oh, the good faith of gods and men! no witness is found in a case involving a sum of three
    million two hundred thousand sesterces! Among how many men? Among more than six hundred. In what
    countries did this transaction take place? In this place, in this very place which you see. Was
    the money given irregularly? No money at all was touched without many memoranda. What, then, is
    the meaning of this accusation, which finds it easier to ascend the <placeName key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName> than a few steps of the treasury; which defends the treasury of the Ruteni
    with more anxiety than that of the Roman people; which prefers using unknown witnesses to known
    ones, foreign witnesses to citizens; which thinks that it is establishing a charge more plainly
    by the capricious evidence of barbarians than by documents written by our fellow citizens?
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p> Of two magistracies, each of which is occupied in handling
    and dealing with large sums of money, the triumvirate <note anchored="true">There were several
     sorts of <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumviri</foreign> who were concerned in the pecuniary affairs
     of the state: the <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumviri mensarii</foreign>, who were a sort of
     bankers, but who seem to have been permanently employed by the state, in whose hands we read,
     that not only the <foreign xml:lang="lat">aerarium</foreign>, but also private individuals
     deposited sums of money which they had to dispose of. (<foreign xml:lang="lat">Vide</foreign>
     Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 613, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Mensarii</foreign>;) the <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumviri monetales</foreign>, who had the whole superintendence of the mint,
     and of the money that was coined in it; and the <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumviri
      capitales</foreign> who, among their other duties, enforced the payment of fines due to the
     state, and the <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumviri sacris conquirendis donisque
      persequendis</foreign>, who seem to have had to take care that all property given or
     consecrated to the gods was applied to that purpose, and who must therefore have been
     responsible for its application. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant p.
     1009, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Triumviri</foreign>.</note> and the quaestorship, such accurate
    accounts have been rendered, that in those things which were done in the sight of men, which
    affected many men's interests, and which were set forth both in public and private registers, no
    hint of robbery, no suspicion of any offence can possibly arise. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> The embassy to <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName> followed, in a most disturbed
    time of the republic; when, on the arrival of Lucius Sulla in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, great armies quarrelled about the tribunals and the laws; and in this
    desperate state of the republic<gap reason="lost"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>
    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p> If no money was paid, of what
    sum is that fiftieth a part? <gap reason="lost"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Since his cause is not the same as that of Verres<gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>a great quantity of corn from <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>; infantry, and a
    most numerous army from <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, a great number of cavalry
    from <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName><gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>That after this the Gauls would drink their wine more diluted, because they thought that there
    was poison in it<gap reason="lost"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p>
    <gap reason="lost"/>
    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>   
   <milestone unit="para"/><gap reason="lost"/>that in the time of this praetor <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>
    <note anchored="true">The passages preceding this figure do not occur in old editions; they were
     found in the <placeName key="tgn,7001168">Vatican</placeName> by Niebuhr, and published by him
     in <date when="1820">1820</date>. They are still in a very corrupt state. The Roman figures at
     the heads of the subsequent chapters are those which occur in all older editions, in which the
     oration began here.</note> was overwhelmed with debt. From whom do they say that loans of such
    sums were procured? From the Gauls? By no means. From whom then? From Roman citizens who are
    trading in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>. Why do we not hear what they have got
    to say? Why are no accounts of theirs produced? I myself pursue and press the prosecutor, O
    judges; I pursue him I say, and I demand witnesses. In this cause I am taking more pains and
    trouble to get them to produce their witnesses, than other advocates for the defence usually
    take to refute them. I say this boldly, O judges, but I do not assert it rashly. All <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> is filled with traders,—is full of Roman citizens. No
     <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> does any business without the aid of a Roman
    citizen; not a single sesterce in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> ever changes
    hands without being entered in the account-books of Roman citizens. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> See how I am descending, O judges, how far I seem to be departing from my
    ordinary habits, from my usual caution and diligence. Let one set of accounts be produced, in
    which there is any trace whatever which gives the least hint of money having been given to
    Fonteius; let them produce out of the whole body of traders, of colonists, of publicans, of
    agriculturists, of graziers, but one witness, and I will allow that this accusation is true. O
    ye immortal gods! what sort of a cause is this? what sort of a defence? Marcus Fonteius was
    governor of the province of <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, which consists of
    those tribes of men and of cities, some of whom (to say nothing of old times) have in the memory
    of the present generation carried on bitter and protracted wars with the Roman people; some have
    been lately subdued by our generals, lately conquered in war, lately made remarkable by the
    triumphs which we have celebrated over them, and the monuments which we have erected, and lately
    mulcted, by the senate, of their lands and cities: some, too, who have fought in battle against
    Marcus Fonteius himself, have by his toil and labour been reduced under the power and dominion
    of the Roman people. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> There is in the same province <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbo Martius</placeName>, <note anchored="true"><placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbo Martius</placeName> is the present town of <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbonne</placeName>.</note> a colony of our citizens, set up as a watch-tower of the Roman
    people, and opposed as a bulwark to the attacks of those very natives. There is also the city of
     <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Massilia</placeName>, which I have already mentioned, a city of
    most gallant and faithful allies, who have made amends to the Roman people for the dangers to
    which they have been exposed in the Gallic wars, by their service and assistance; there is,
    besides, a large number of Roman citizens, and most honourable men. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Of this province, consisting of this variety of people, Marcus Fonteius, as I have said, was
    governor. Those who were enemies, he subdued; those who had lately been so, he compelled to
    depart from the lands of which they had been deprived by the senate. From the rest, who had been
    often conquered in great wars, on purpose that they might be rendered obedient for ever to the
    Roman people, he exacted large troops of cavalry to serve in those wars which at that time were
    being carried on all over the world by the Roman people, and large sums of money for their pay,
    and a great quantity of corn to support our armies in the Spanish war. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> The man who has done all these things is now brought before a court of law.
    You who were not present at the transactions are, with the Roman people, taking cognisance of
    the cause; those men are our adversaries who were compelled to leave their lands by the command
    of Cnaeus Pompeius; those men are our adversaries who having escaped from the war, and the
    slaughter which was made of them, for the first time dare to stand against Marcus Fonteius, now
    that he is unarmed. What of the colonists of <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbo</placeName>?
    what do they wish? what do they think? They wish this man's safety to be ensured by you, they
    think that theirs has been ensured by him. What of the state of the Massilians? They
    distinguished him while he was among them by the greatest honours which they had to bestow; and
    now, though absent from this place, they pray and entreat you that their blameless character,
    their panegyric, and their authority may appear to have some weight with you in forming your
    opinions. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> What more shall I say? What is the inclination of
    the Roman citizens? There is no one of that immense body who does not consider this man to have
    deserved well of the province, of the empire, of our allies, and of the citizens. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Since, therefore, you now know who wish Marcus Fonteius to be attacked, and who wish him to be
    defended, decide now what your own regard for equity, and what the dignity of the Roman people
    requires; whether you prefer trusting your colonists, your traders, your most friendly and
    ancient allies, and consulting their interests, or the interests of those men, whom, on account
    of their passionate disposition, you ought not to trust; on account of their disloyalty you
    ought not to honour. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> What, if I produce also a still greater
    number of most honourable men to bear testimony to this man's virtue and innocence? Will the
    unanimity of the Gauls still be of more weight than that of men of such great authority? When
    Fonteius was governor of <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, you know, O judges, that
    there were very large armies of the Roman people in the two Spains, and very illustrious
    generals. How many Roman knights were there, how many military tribunes, how many ambassadors
    came to them! what eminent men they were, and how frequently did they come! Besides that, a very
    large and admirably appointed army of Cnaeus Pompeius wintered in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> while Marcus Fonteius was governor. Does not Fortune herself appear to have
    intended that they should be a sufficient number of sufficiently competent witnesses of those
    things which were done in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> while Marcus Fonteius
    was praetor? Out of all that number of men what witness can you produce in this cause? Who is
    there of all that body of men whose authority you are willing to cite? We will use that very man
    as our panegyrist and our witness. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p> Will you doubt any longer,
    O judges, that that which I stated to you at the beginning is most true, that there is another
    object in this prosecution, beyond causing others, after Marcus Fonteius has been overwhelmed by
    the testimonies of these men, from whom many contributions have been exacted, greatly against
    their will, for the sake of the republic, to be for the future more lax in governing, when they
    see these men attacked, who are such men that, if they are crushed, the empire of the Roman
    people cannot be maintained in safety <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>A charge has also been advanced that Marcus Fonteius has made a profit from the making of
    roads; taking money either for not compelling people to make roads, or for not disapproving of
    roads which had been made. If all the cities have been compelled to make roads, and if the works
    of many of them have not been passed, then certainly both charges are false,—the charge that
    money has been given for exemption, when no one was exempted; and for approval, when many were
    disapproved of. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> What if we can shift this charge on other
    most unimpeachable names? not so as to transfer any blame to others, but to show that these men
    were appointed to superintend that road-making, who are easily able to show that their duty was
    performed, and performed well. Will you still urge all these charges against Marcus Fonteius,
    relying on angry witnesses? When Marcus Fonteius was hindered by more important affairs of the
    republic, and when it concerned the republic that the Domitian road should be made, he entrusted
    the business to his lieutenants, men of the highest characters, Caius Annius, Bellienus, and
    Caius Fonteius. So they superintended it; they ordered what seemed necessary, as became their
    dignity, and they sanctioned what seemed well done. And you have at all events had opportunities
    of knowing these things, both from our documents, from documents which you yourselves have
    written, and from others which have been sent to you, and produced before you; and if you have
    not already read them, now hear us read what Fonteius wrote about those matters to his
    lieutenants, and what they wrote to him in answer. [The letters sent to Caius Annius the
    Lieutenant, and to Caius Fonteius the Lieutenant; also, the letters received from Caius Annius
    the Lieutenant, and from Caius Fonteius the Lieutenant, are read.] </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> I think it is plain enough, O judges, that this question about the road-making
    does not concern Marcus Fonteius, and that the business was managed by these men, with whom no
    one can find fault. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Listen now to the facts relating to the charge about wine, which they meant to be the most
    odious, and the most important charge. The charge, O judges, has been thus stated by Plaetorius:
    that it had not occurred to Fonteius for the first time when he was in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> to establish a transit duty on wine, but that he had thought
    of the plan in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, before he departed from
     <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. Accordingly, that Titurius had exacted at
     <placeName key="tgn,7008441">Tolosa</placeName> fourteen denarii for every amphora <note anchored="true">The amphora contained nearly six gallons, a denarius, as has been said before,
     was about eight pence-halfpenny; so that this duty was, as nearly as may be, one and eightpence
     a gallon. A <foreign xml:lang="lat">victoriatus</foreign> was half a <foreign xml:lang="lat">denarius</foreign>.</note> of wine, under the name of transit duty; that Portius and Numius
    at Crodunum had exacted three victoriati; that Serveus at Vulchalo had exacted two victoriati;
    and in those districts they believe that transit duty was exacted by these men at Vulchalo, in
    case of any one turning aside to Cobiamachus, which is a small town between <placeName key="tgn,7008441">Tolosa</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbo</placeName>, and
    not wishing to proceed so far as <placeName key="tgn,7008441">Tolosa</placeName>. Elesiodulus
    exacted only six denarii from those who were taking wine to the enemy. <note anchored="true">The
     whole of this passage is very corrupt; the last line or two so hopelessly so, and so
     unintelligible, that perhaps it would have been better to have marked them with asterisks
     instead of attempting to translate them.</note>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p> I see, O judges, that this is a charge, important both from
    the sort of crime imputed, (for a tax is said to have been imposed on our produce, and I confess
    that a very large sum of money might have been amassed by that means,) and from its unpopular
    nature; for our adversaries have endeavoured to make this charge as widely known as possible, by
    making it the subject of their conversation. But I think that the more serious a charge is,
    which is proved to be false, the greater is the wickedness of that man who invented it; for he
    wishes by the magnitude of the accusation to prejudice the minds of those who hear it, so that
    the truth may afterwards find a difficult entrance into them. <gap reason="lost"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>[Everything relating to the charge about the wine, to the war with the Vocontii, and the
    arrangement of winter quarters, is wanting.] <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/><gap reason="lost"/>But the Gauls deny this. But the circumstances of the case and the force of
    arguments prove it. Can then a judge refuse belief to witnesses? He not only can, but he ought,
    if they are covetous men, or angry men, or conspirators, or men utterly void of religion and
    conscience. In fact, if Marcus Fonteius is to be considered guilty just because the Gauls say
    so, what need have I of a wise judge? what need have I of an impartial judge? what need is there
    of an intelligent advocate? For the Gauls say so. We cannot deny it. If you think this is the
    duty of an able and experienced and impartial judge, that he must without the slightest
    hesitation believe a thing because the witnesses say it; then the Goddess of Safety herself
    cannot protect the innocence of brave men. But if, in coming to a decision on such matters, the
    wisdom of the judge has a wide field for its exercise in considering every circumstance, and in
    weighing each according to its importance, then in truth your part in considering the case is a
    more important and serious one than mine is in stating it. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
    For I have only to question the witness as to each circumstance once, and that, too, briefly,
    and often indeed I have not to question him at all; lest I should seem to be giving an angry man
    an opportunity of making a speech, or to be attributing an undue weight to a covetous man. You
    can revolve the same matter over and over again in your minds, you can give a long consideration
    to the evidence of one witness; and, if we have shown an unwillingness to examine any witness,
    you are bound to consider what has been our reason for keeping silence. Wherefore; if you think
    that to believe the witnesses implicitly is enjoined to a judge, either by the law or by his
    duty, there is no reason at all why one man should be thought a better or a wiser judge than
    another. For judgment formed by the mere ears is single and simple enough; it is a power given
    promiscuously to all in common, whether they are fools or wise men. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p> What, then, are the opportunities which wisdom has of distinguishing itself?
    When can a foolish and credulous auditor be distinguished from a scrupulous and discerning
    judge? When, forsooth, the statements which are made by the witnesses are committed to his
    conjectures, to his opinion, as to the authority, the impartiality of mind, the modesty; the
    good faith, the scrupulousness, the regard for a fair reputation, the care, and the fear with
    which they are made. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Or will you, in the case of the testimonies of barbarians, hesitate to do what very often
    within our recollection and that of our fathers, the wisest judges have not thought that they
    ought to hesitate to do with respect to the most illustrious men of our state? For they refused
    belief to the evidence of Cnaeus and Quintus Caepio, and to Lucius and Quintus Metellus, when
    they were witnesses against Quintus Pompeius, a new man; for virtuous, and noble, and valiant as
    they were, still the suspicion of some private object to be gamed, and some private grudge to be
    gratified, detracted from their credibility and authority as witnesses. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> Have we seen any man, can we with truth speak of any man, as having been equal
    in wisdom, in dignity, in consistency, in all other virtues, in all the distinguishing qualities
    of honour, and genius, and splendid achievements, to Marcus Aemilius Scaurus? And yet, though,
    when he was not on his oath, almost the whole world was governed by his nod, yet, when he was on
    his oath, his evidence was not believed against Caius Fimbria, nor against Caius Memmius. They,
    who were the judges, were unwilling that such a road should be opened to enmities, as for every
    man to be able to destroy by his evidence who ever he hated. Who is there who does not know how
    great was the modesty, how great the abilities, how great the influence of Lucius Crassus? And
    yet he, whose mere conversation had the authority of evidence, could not, by his actual
    evidence, establish the things which he had stated against Marcus Marcellus with hostile
    feelings. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> There was—there was in the judges of those times, O
    judges, a divinely-inspired and singular acuteness, as they thought that they were judges, not
    only of the defendant, but also of the accuser and of the witness, as to what was invented, what
    was brought into the case by chance or by the opportunity, what was imported into it through
    corruption, what was distorted by hope or by fear, what appeared to proceed from any private
    desire, or any private enmity. And if the judge does not embrace all these considerations in his
    deliberation, if he does not survey and comprehend them all in his mind,—if he thinks that
    whatever is said from that witness-box, proceeds from some oracle, then in truth it will be
    sufficient, as I have said before, for any judge to preside over this court, and to discharge
    this duty, who is not deaf. There will be no reason in the world for requiring any one, whoever
    he may be, to be either able or experienced, to qualify him for judging causes. <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Had then those Roman knights, whom we ourselves have seen who have lately flourished in the
    republic, and in the courts, so much courage and so much vigour as to refuse belief to Marcus
    Scaurus when a witness; and are you afraid to disbelieve the evidence of the Volcae and of the
    Allobroges? If it was not right to give credence to a hostile witness, was Crassus more hostile
    to Marcellus, or Scaurus to Fimbria, on account of any political differences, or any domestic
    quarrels, than the Gauls are to Fonteius? For of the Gauls, those even who stand on the best
    ground have been compelled once and again, and sorely against their will, to furnish cavalry,
    money, and corn; and of the rest, some have been deprived of their land in ancient wars, some
    have been overwhelmed and subdued in war by this very man. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p> If
    those men ought not to be believed who appear to say anything covetously with a view to some
    private gain, I think that the Caepios and Metelli proposed to themselves a greater gain from
    the condemnation of Quintus Pompeius, as by that they would have got rid of a formidable
    adversary to all their views, than all the Gauls hoped for from the disaster of Marcus Fonteius,
    in which that province believed that all its safety and liberty consisted. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>If it is proper to have a regard to the men themselves, (a thing which in truth in the case of
    witnesses ought to be of the greatest weight,) is any one, the most honourable man in all
     <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> to be compared, I will not say with the most
    honourable men of our city, but even with the meanest of Roman citizens? Does Induciomarus know
    what is the meaning of giving evidence? Is he affected with that awe which moves every
    individual among us when he is brought into that box? <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Recollect, O judges, with how much pains you are accustomed to labour, considering not only
    what you are going to state in your evidence, but even what words you shall use, lest any word
    should appear to be used too moderately, or lest on the other hand any expression should appear
    to have escaped you from any private motive. You take pains even so to mould your countenances,
    that no suspicion of any private motive may be excited; that when you come forward there may be
    a sort of silent opinion of your modesty and scrupulousness, and that, when you leave the box,
    that reputation may appear to have been carefully preserved and retained. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p> I suppose Induciomarus, when he gave his evidence, had all these fears and all
    these thoughts; he, who left out of his whole evidence that most considerate word, to which we
    are all habituated, “I think,” a word which we use even when we are relating on our oath what we
    know of our own knowledge, what we ourselves have seen; and said that he knew everything he was
    stating. He feared, forsooth, lest he should lose any of his reputation in your eyes and in
    those of the Roman people; lest any such report should get abroad that Induciomarus, a man of
    such rank, had spoken with such partiality, with such rashness. The truth was, he did not
    understand that in giving his evidence there was anything which he was bound to display either
    to his own countrymen or to our accusers, except his voice, his countenance, and his audacity.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p> Do you think that those nations are influenced in giving
    their evidence by the sanctity of an oath, and by the fear of the immortal gods, which are so
    widely different from other nations in their habits and natural disposition? For other nations
    undertake wars in defence of their religious feelings; they wage war against the religion of
    every people; other nations when waging war beg for sanction and pardon from the immortal gods;
    they have waged war with the immortal gods themselves. <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>These are the nations which formerly marched to such a distance from their settlements, as far
    as <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, to attack and pillage the Pythian Apollo,
    and the oracle of the whole world. By these same nations, so pious, so scrupulous in giving
    their evidence, was the Capitol besieged, and that
     <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, under the obligations of whose name our
    ancestors decided that the good faith of all witnesses should be pledged. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p> Lastly, can anything appear holy or solemn in the eyes of those men, who, if
    ever they are so much influenced by any fear as to think it necessary to propitiate the immortal
    gods, defile their altars and temples with human victims? So that they cannot pay proper honour
    to religion itself without first violating it with wickedness. For who is ignorant that, to this
    very day, they retain that savage and barbarous custom of sacrificing men? What, therefore, do
    you suppose is the good faith, what the piety of those men, who think that even the immortal
    gods can be most easily propitiated by the wickedness and murder of men? Will you connect your
    own religious ideas with these witnesses? Will you think that anything is said holily or
    moderately by these men? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p> Will your minds, pure and upright as
    they are, bring themselves into such a state that, when all our ambassadors who for the last
    three years have arrived in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, when all the Roman
    knights who have been in that province, when all the traders of that province, when, in short,
    all the allies and friends of the Roman people who are in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, wish Marcus Fonteius to be safe, and extol him on their oaths both in public
    and in private, you should still prefer to give your decision in unison with the Gauls?
    Appealing to comply with what? With the wishes of men? Is then the wish of our enemies to have
    more authority in your eyes than that of our countrymen? With the dignity of the witnesses? Can
    you then possibly prefer strangers to people whom you know, unjust men to just ones, foreigners
    to countrymen, covetous men to moderate ones, mercenary men to disinterested ones, impious men
    to conscientious ones, men who are the greatest enemies to our dominions and to our name, to
    good and loyal allies and citizens? <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Are you then hesitating, O judges, when all these nations have an innate hatred to and wage
    incessant war with the name of the Roman people? Do you think that, with their military cloaks
    and their breeches, they come to us in a lowly and submissive spirit, as these do, who having
    suffered injuries fly to us as suppliants and inferiors to beg the aid of the judges? Nothing is
    further from the truth. On the contrary, they are strolling in high spirits and with their heads
    up, all over the forum, uttering threatening expressions, and terrifying men with barbarous and
    ferocious language; which, in truth, I should not believe, O judges, if I had not repeatedly
    heard such things from the mouths of the accusers themselves in your presence,—when they warned
    you to take care, lest, by acquitting this man, you should excite some new Gallic war.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p> If, O judges, everything was wanting to Marcus Fonteius in
    this cause; if he appeared before the court, having passed a disgraceful youth and an infamous
    life, having been convicted by the evidence of virtuous men of having discharged his duties as a
    magistrate (in which his conduct has been under your own eye) and as a lieutenant, in a most
    scandalous manner, and being hated by all his acquaintances; if in his trial he were overwhelmed
    with the oral and documentary evidence of the Narbonnese colonists of the Roman people, of our
    most faithful allies the Massilians, and of all the citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; still it would be your duty to take the greatest care, lest you should
    appear to be afraid of those men, and to be influenced by their threats and menaced terrors, who
    were so prostrate and subdued in the times of your fathers and forefathers, as to be
    contemptible. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p> But now, when no good man says a word against
    him, but all your citizens and allies extol him; when those men attack him who have repeatedly
    attacked this city and this empire; and when the enemies of Marcus Fonteius threaten you and the
    Roman people; when his friends and relations come to you as suppliants, will you hesitate to
    show not only to your own citizens, who are mainly influenced by glory and praise; but also to
    foreign tribes and nations, that you, in giving your votes, prefer sparing a citizen to yielding
    to an enemy? <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Among other reasons, this, O judges, is a very great reason for his acquittal, to prevent any
    notable stain and disgrace from falling on our dominion, by news going to <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> that the senate and knights of the Roman people gave their
    decisions in a criminal trial just as the Gauls pleased; being influenced not by their evidence,
    but by their threats. But in that case, if they attempt to make war upon us, we must summon up
    Caius Marius from the shades below, in order that he may be equal in war to that great man, that
    threatening and arrogant Induciomarus. Cnaeus Domitius and Quintus Maximus must be raised from
    the dead, that they may again subdue and crush the nation of the Allobroges and the other tribes
    by their arms; or, since that indeed is impossible, we must beg my friend Marcus Plaetorius to
    deter his new clients from making war, and to oppose by his entreaties their angry feelings and
    formidable violence; or, if he be not able to do so, we will ask Marcus Fabius, his junior
    counsel, to pacify the Allobroges, since among their tribe the name of Fabius is held in the
    highest honour, and induce them either to be willing to remain quiet, as defeated and conquered
    nations usually are, or else to make them understand that they are holding out to the Roman
    people not a terror of war, but a hope of triumph. 
   <milestone unit="para"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p> And if, even in the case of an ignoble defendant, it would
    not be endurable that those men should think they had effected anything by their threats, what
    do you think you ought to do in the case of Marcus Fonteius? concerning whom, O judges, (for I
    think that I am entitled to say this now, when I have almost come to the termination of two
    trials,) concerning whom, I say, you have not only not heard any disgraceful charge invented by
    his enemies, but you have not even heard any really serious reproach. Was ever any defendant,
    especially when he had moved in such a sphere as this man, as a candidate for honours, as an
    officer in command, and as a governor, accused in such a way, that no disgraceful act, no deed
    of violence, no baseness originating either in lust or insolence or audacity, was attributed to
    him, if not with truth, at least with some suspicious circumstances giving a reasonable
    colouring to the invention? <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>We know that Marcus Aemilius Scaurus, the most eminent man of our city, was accused by Marcus
    Brutus. The orations are extant by which it can be seen that many things are alleged against
    Scaurus himself, no doubt falsely; but still they were alleged against him and urged against him
    by an enemy. How many things were said against Manius Aquilius on his trial? How many against
    Lucius Cotta? and, lastly, against Publius Rutilius? who, although he was condemned, still
    appears to me to deserve to be reckoned among the most virtuous and innocent men. Yet that most
    upright and temperate man had many things attributed to him on his trial, which involved
    suspicion of adultery, and great licentiousness. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p> There is an
    oration extant of a man, by far (in my opinion, that is,) the ablest and most eloquent of all
    our countrymen, Caius Gracchus; in which oration Lucius Piso is accused of many base and wicked
    actions. What a man to be so accused! A man who was of such virtue and integrity, that even in
    those most admirable: times, when it was not possible to find a thoroughly worthless man, still
    he alone was called Thrifty. And when Gracchus was ordering him to be summoned before the
    assembly, and his lictor asked him which Piso, because there were many of the name, “You are
    compelling me,” says he, “to call my enemy, Thrifty.” That very man then, whom even his enemy
    could not point out with sufficient clearness without first praising him; whose one surname
    pointed not only who he was, but what sort of man he was; that very man was, nevertheless,
    exposed to a false and unjust accusation of disgraceful conduct. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus"><p> Marcus Fonteius has been accused in two trials, in such a way, that nothing
    has been alleged against him from which the slightest taint of lust, or caprice, or cruelty, or
    audacity can be inferred. They not only have not mentioned any atrocious deed of his, but they
    have not even found fault with any expression used by him. <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But if they had either had as much courage to tell a lie, or as much ingenuity to invent one,
    as they feel eagerness to oppress Fonteius, or as they have displayed licence in abusing him;
    then he would have had no better fortune, as far as relates to not having disgraceful acts
    alleged against him, than those men whom I have just mentioned. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>You see then another Thrifty,—a thrifty man, I say, O judges, and a man moderate and temperate
    in every particular of his life; a man full of modesty, full of a sense of duty, full of
    religion, depending on your good faith and power, and placed in your power in such a way as to
    be committed wholly to the protection of your good faith. 
   <milestone unit="para"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p> Consider, therefore, whether it is more just that a most
    honourable and brave man, that a most virtuous citizen, should be given up to the most hostile
    and ferocious nations, or restored to his freedom, especially when there are so many
    circumstances which cooperate in entreating your favourable disposition in aid of this man's
    safety. First of all, there is the antiquity of his family, which we are aware proceeds from
     <placeName key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName>, a most illustrious municipality, and
    whose fame is engraved and handed down on monuments of the exploits of its members; secondly,
    there have been continual praetorships in that family, which have been distinguished by every
    sort of honour, and especially by the credit of unimpeachable innocence; besides that, there is
    the recent memory of his father, by whose blood, not only the troop of <placeName key="perseus,Asculum">Asculum</placeName>, by whom he was slain, but the whole of that social
    war has been stained with the deep dye of wickedness; lastly, there is the man himself,
    honourable and upright in every particular of his life, and in military affairs not only endued
    with the greatest wisdom, and the most brilliant courage, but also skillful through personal
    experience in carrying on war, beyond almost any man of the present age. <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, if you do require to be reminded at all by me, O judges, (which, in truth, you do
    not,) it seems to me I may, without presuming too much on my authority, give you this gentle
    hint,—that you ought to consider that those men are carefully to be preserved by you, whose
    valour, and energy, and good fortune in military affairs have been tried and ascertained. There
    has been a greater abundance of such men in the republic than there is now; and when there was,
    people consulted not only their safety, but their honour also. What, then, ought you to do now,
    when military studies have become obsolete among our youth, and when our best men and our
    greatest generals have been taken from us, partly by age, and partly by the dissensions of the
    state and the ill fortune of the republic? When so many wars are necessarily undertaken by us,
    when so many arise suddenly and unexpectedly, do you not think that you ought to preserve this
    man for the critical occasions of the republic, and to excite others by his example to the
    pursuit of honour and virtue? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p> Recollect what lieutenants
    Lucius Julius, and Publius Rutilius, and Lucius Cato, and Cnaeus Pompeius have lately had in
    war. You will see that at that time there existed also Marcus Cornutus, Lucius Cinna, and Lucius
    Sulla, men of praetorian rank, and of the greatest skill in war; and, besides them, Caius
    Marius, Publius Didius, Quintus Catulus, and Publius Crassus, men not learned in the science of
    war through books, but accomplished and renowned by their achievements and their victories. Come
    now, cast your eyes over the senate house, look thoroughly into every part of the republic; do
    you see no possible event in which you may require men like those? or, if any such event should
    arise, do you think that the Roman people is at this moment rich in such men? And if you
    carefully consider all these circumstances, you will rather, O judges, retain at home, for
    yourselves and for your children, a man energetic in undertaking the toils of war, gallant in
    encountering its dangers, skillful in its practice and its discipline, prudent in his designs,
    fortunate and successful in their accomplishment, than deliver him over to nations most hostile
    to the Roman people, and most cruel, by condemning him. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But the Gauls are attacking Fonteius with hostile standards as it were; they pursue him, and
    press upon him with the most extreme eagerness, with the most extreme audacity. I see it. But
    we, O judges, you being our helpers, with many and strong defences, will resist that savage and
    intolerable band of barbarians. Our first bulwark against their attacks is <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, a province loyal and well affected to the Roman
    people, which says, that itself and its cities were preserved, not only by the wisdom, but even
    by the hand of Fonteius, and which now repels the attacks and dangers of the Gauls from his
    head, as it was defended itself from the invasion and desolation of the Thracians. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p> On the opposite side stands the further <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, which is able in this case not only to withstand the eagerness of the
    accusers by its own honest disposition, but which can even refute the perjuries of wicked men by
    its testimonies and by its panegyrics. And even from <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> itself most faithful and most important assistance is derived. As an
    assistance to this unhappy and innocent man, the city of the Massilians has come forward, which
    is labouring now, not only in order to appear to requite with proper gratitude the exertions of
    the man by whom it has been preserved, but which also believes that it has been placed in those
    districts for that very object, and with that express destiny, to prevent those nations from
    being able to injure our countrymen. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus"><p> The colony of <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbonne</placeName> fights equally on behalf of the safety of Marcus
    Fonteius, which, having been lately delivered from the blockade of the enemy by this man, is now
    moved at his misery and danger. Lastly, as is right in a Gallic war—as the principles and
    customs of our ancestors enjoin—there is not one Roman citizen who thinks he requires any excuse
    for being eager in this man's behalf. All the publicans of that province, all the farmers, all
    the graziers, all the traders, with one heart and one voice, defended Marcus Fonteius.
     <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But if Induciomarus himself, the leader of the Allobroges, and of all the rest of the Gauls,
    despise such powerful aid as this which we have, shall he still tear and drag away this man from
    the embrace of his mother, a most admirable and most miserable woman, and that, too, while you
    are looking on? especially when a vestal virgin on the other side is folding her own brother in
    her embraces, and imploring, O judges, your good faith, and that of the Roman people; she who
    has been, on behalf of you and of your children, occupied for so many years in propitiating the
    immortal gods, in order now to be able to propitiate you when supplicating for her own safety
    and that of her brother. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p> What protection, what comfort, will
    that unhappy maiden have left, if she loses this her brother? For other women can bring forth
    protectors for themselves—can have in their homes a companion and a partner in all their
    fortunes; but to this maiden, what is there that can be agreeable or dear, except her brother?
    Do not, O judges, allow the altars of the immortal gods, and of our mother Vesta, to be reminded
    of your tribunal by the daily lamentations of a holy virgin. Beware lest that eternal flame,
    which is now preserved by the nightly toils and vigils of Fonteia, should be said to have been
    extinguished by the tears of your priestess. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p> A vestal virgin
    is stretching out towards you her suppliant hands, those same hands which she is accustomed to
    stretch out, on your behalf, to the immortal gods. Consider how dangerous, how arrogant a deed
    it would be for you to reject her entreaties, when, if the immortal gods were to despise her
    prayers, all these things which we see around us could not be preserved. Do not you see, O
    judges, that all of a sudden, Marcus Fonteius himself, brave as he is, is moved to shed tears at
    the mention of his parent and his sister?—he who never has known fear in battle, he who in arms
    has often thrown himself on the ranks and numbers of the enemy, thinking, while he was facing
    such dangers, that he left behind him the same consolation to his relatives that his own father
    had left to him; yet now, for all that, is agitated and alarmed, lest he should not only cease
    to be an ornament and an assistant to his family, but lest he should even leave them eternal
    disgrace and ignominy, together with the bitterest grief. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p> Oh
    how unequal is thy fortune, O Marcus Fonteius! If you could have chosen, how much would you have
    preferred perishing by the weapons of the Gauls rather than by their perjuries! For then virtue
    would have been the companion of your life, glory your comrade in death; but now, what agony is
    it for you to endure the sufferings caused by their power and victory over you, at their
    pleasure, who have before now been either conquered by your arms, or forced to submit against
    their will to your authority. From this danger, O judges, defend a brave and innocent citizen:
    take care to be seen to place more confidence in our own witnesses than in foreigners; to have
    more regard for the: safety of our citizens than for the pleasure of our enemies; to think the
    entreaties of her who presides over your sacrifices of more importance than the audacity of
    those men who have waged war against the sacrifices and temples of all nations. Lastly, take
    care, O judges, (the dignity of the Roman people is especially concerned in this,) to show that
    the prayers of a vestal virgin have more influence over you than the threats of <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>.
    </p>
    </div>
   </div>
 </body>
 </text>

</TEI>
