<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
             <title>The War Against Gildo</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date>1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="http://www.archive.org/stream/claudian01clau#page/98/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
            <p>Keyboarding</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">            
                              <state unit="book"/>            
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa002.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.99" TEIform="pb"/>
               <div1 type="book" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <p>

The kingdom of the south is restored to our empire,
the sky of that other hemisphere is once more
brought into subjection. East and West live in
amity and concord beneath the sway of one ruler.
</p>
         <p>We have joined Europe again to Africa, and unswerving
singleness of purpose unites the brother
emperors. The would-be third participant of empire
has fallen before the prowess of Honorius the son
— that one victory that failed to grace the arms of
Theodosius, the father. Still is my mind troubled
and admits not the universal joy for very amazement,
nor can believe the fulfilment of its heartfelt prayers.
</p>
         <p>Not yet had the army landed upon Africa's2 coasts
when Gildo yielded to defeat. No difficulties
delayed our victorious arms, neither length of march
nor intervening ocean. One and the same word
brings news of the conflict, the flight, the capture of
Gildo. The news of victory outstripped the news of
the war that occasioned it. What god wrought this
for us? Could madness so strong, so deep-seated
be overcome so soon? The enemy whom early
winter brought upon us, spring destroyed.
<pb id="v.1.p.101"/>
Rome, the goddess, fearing for her city's destruction
and weak with corn withheld, hastened to the thresh-
old of revolving Olympus with looks unlike her own;
no with such countenance does she assign laws
to the Britons, or subject the frightened Indians to
her rule. Feeble her voice, slow her step, her eyes
deep buried. Her cheeks were sunken and hunger
had wasted her limbs . Scarce can her weak shoulders
support her unpolished shield. Her ill-fitting helmet
shows her grey hairs and the spear she carries is
a mass of rust. At last she reaches heaven and
falls at the Thunderer's feet and utters this mournful
complaint: <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>If prophecy rightly foretold the
permanence of the rising walls of Rome; if the
Sibyl's verse is unalterable; if thou art not yet
wearied of our city and the Capitol, I come to thee
as a suppliant. My prayer is not that a consul
may march in triumph along Araxes' banks, nor that
Rome's power may crush the archer Persians and
Susa their capital, nor yet that we may plant our
standards on the Red Sea's strand. All this thou
grantedst us of old. 'Tis but food I, Rome, ask for
now; father, take pity on thy chosen race and ease
us of this hunger unto death. Whatever thy displeasure,
we have surely sated it. The very Getae
and Suebi would pity our sufferings; Parthia's self
would shudder at my disasters. What need have I
to mention the pestilence, the heaps of corpses, the
numberless deaths wherewith the very air is corrupted?
Why tell of Tiber's flooded stream, sweeping
betwixt roofs and threatening the very hills? My
submerged city has borne mighty ships, echoed the
sound of oars, and experienced Pyrrha's flood.</p>
               <p>
Woe is me, whither are fled the power of Latium
<pb id="v.1.p.103"/>
and the might of Rome? To what a shadow of our
former glory are we by gradual decline arrived!
</p>
               <p>Time was when my men bore arms and my grey-
beards met in council; mistress of the world was I
and lawgiver to mankind. From rising to setting
sun I sped in triumph. When proud Caesar had
transferred my people's power to himself, when
manners became corrupt and forgetful of war's old
discipline I declined into the servile lap of peace, the
emperors rewarded me with Africa and Egypt
that they might nourish the sovereign people and
the Senate, arbiter of peace and war, by means of
summer-sped fleets, and that the winds, blowing
alternately from either shore, should fill our granaries
with corn. Our provisioning was secure. Should
Memphis perchance have denied us food, I would
make up for the failure of Egypt's harvest by the
African supply. I saw competition between grain-
bearing vessels, and where'er I looked I beheld the
fleet of Carthage strive in rivalry with that of the
Nile. When a second Rome arose and the Eastern
Empire assumed the toga of the West, Egypt fell
beneath that new sway. Africa remained our only
hope and scarcely did she suffice to feed us, whose
corn-ships none but the south wind wafted across.
</p>
               <p>Her promise for the future was insecure, as, ever
helpless, she demanded the loyalty of the wind
and of the season.1 This province, too, Gildo
seized towards the close of autumn. Anxiously and
prayerfully we scan the blue sea to glance a coming
sail in the fond hope that perchance a sense of
shame has extorted somewhat from the powerful
tyrant, or the conqueror left some corner unconquered.
</p>
               <p>We are fed at the pleasure of the Moor,
<pb id="v.1.p.105"/>
who boasts that he does not repay a debt but that
he gives us of his own, and rejoices to apportion out
my daily food to me, as though I were his slave;
with a barbarian's pride he weighs me life or death
by hunger, triumphs in a people's tears, and holds
above our heads an universal destruction. He
sells Rome's crops and possesses land won by my
wounds. Was it for this that I waged lamentable
war with proud Carthage for so many years? For
this that Regulus reckoned his life as naught and
would fain return to his captors? Is this my reward,
father, for my losses on Cannae's field? Have the
Spanish and Sicilian seas resounded so often to our
navies' clarion for naught? For naught my lands
been laid waste, so many of my generals slain, the
Carthaginian invader broken his way through the
Alps, Hannibal approached my affrighted capital?
Have I kept the foe at bay with my walls and spent
nights of slaughter before the Colline gate to enable
a barbarian to reap the fruits of conquered Africa?
Has thrice-conquered Carthage fallen for Gildo's
benefit? Was this the object of mourning Italy's
thousand disasters, of centuries spent in war, of
Fabius' and Marcellus' deeds of daring — that Gildo
should heap him up riches? We forced cruel
Syphax to drink poison, drove fierce Iugurtha,
whose power Metellus had broken, beneath Marius'
yoke — and shall Africa be Gildo's? Alas for our
toil and those many deaths: the two Scipios have
laboured, it seems, to further Bocchus'1 native rule;
Roman blood has given victory to the Moors. That
long warlike race, lord of the world, that appointed
consuls and kings, whom foreign nations found ever
formidable in war, though gentle once they had
<pb id="v.1.p.107"/>
been subdued, dishonoured now and poverty-stricken,
bends beneath the cruel lash of peace, and though
not openly beleaguered by any foe yet has all the
hazard of a siege. Destruction threatens me
hourly; a few days will set a limit to my uncertain
food-supply. Out upon thee, prosperity! Why
hast thou given me seven hills and such a population
as a small supply cannot nourish? Happier I, had
my power been less. Better to have put up with
the Sabines and Veii; in narrower bonds I passed
securer days. My very magnitude undoes me;
would that I could return to my former boundaries
and the walls of poor Ancus. Enough for me then
would be the ploughlands of Etruria and Campania,
the farms of Cincinnatus and Curius, and at his
country's prayer the rustic dictator 1 would bring
his home-grown wheat.
What am I to do now? Gildo holds Libya,
another2  Egypt; while I, who subdued land and sea
with my strong arm, am left to perish. Veteran of so
many wars, can I claim no reward in mine old age?
Ye gods in whose despite, it seems, I increased, now
aid me at the last; pray Jove for me. And thou,
Cybele, if ever of thine own free will thou wert
carried over the sea and in exchange for Mount Ida
tookest the hills of Rome and didst bathe thy Phrygian
lions in Almo's more favoured stream, move now thy
son3 with a mother's entreaties. But if the fates forbid
and our first founder was misled by augury untrue,
o'erwhelm me at least in some different ruin, and
change the nature of my punishment. Let Porsenna
bring back the Tarquins; let Allia renew her bloody
battle. Let me fall rather into the hands of cruel
<pb id="v.1.p.109"/>
Pyrrhus; abandon me to the fury of the Senones
or the flames of Brennus. Welcome all this rather
than to starve!</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake she, and upwelling tears choked her voice.
</p>
         <p>Venus, mother of Aeneas, wept, and Mars, father of
Romulus and Minerva, mindful of Vesta's sacred
charge.! Nor Cybele nor Juno stood with dry eyes.
</p>
         <p>The heroes mourn and all the gods whose worship
Rome received from without or herself inaugurated.
</p>
         <p>And now began the heart of Jove to soften. With
hand outstretched he was checking the murmurings of
the gods when, shaking heaven with distraught cries,
Africa, her cheeks torn, appeared in the distance
advancing amid the stars. Torn was her raiment,
scattered her crown of corn. Her head was wounded
and the ivory comb that secured her hair hung
loose and broken. She rushed into Heaven's
halls shouting thus: <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Great Jove, why delayest
thou to loose the bonds of sea, to break its
decree and hurl thy brother 2 in wrath against
the land? May I be the first to be overwhelmed.
Welcome the broken waters from Pachynus' cape;
sink my cities in the freed Syrtes. If so be fate
cannot rid me of Gildo, rid Gildo of me. Happier
that region of Libya that defends itself by means
of its own excessive heat and thus knows not the
irksome rule of so savage a tyrant. Let the torrid
zone spread. Let the midmost path of the scorching
sky bum me also. Better I lay a desert nor ever
suffered the plough. Let the dust-snake lord it in
a cornless land and the thirsty earth give birth to
nought but vipers. What avails me a healthy
climate, a milder air? My fruitfulness is but for
<pb id="v.1.p.111"/>
Gildo. Twelve courses has the sun's chariot run
since first I wore this sorry yoke. He has now grown
old amid our miseries and these many years have
set their seal upon his rule. Rule — would it were
rule: a private owner possesses me, as it had been
some pelting farm. From Nile to Atlas' mount,
from scorched Barce to western Gades, from Tingi 1
to Egypt's coast Gildo has appropriated the land
as his own. A third of the world belongs to one
robber-chief.
</p>
               <p>He is a prey to the most diverse vices: whatsoe'er
his bottomless greed has stolen, a yet more insatiable
profligacy squanders. He is the terror of the living,
the heir of the dead, the violator of the unwed, and
the foul corrupter of the marriage-bed. He is never
quiet; when greed is sated lust is rampant; day
is a misery to the rich, night to the married. Is
any wealthy or known to possess a beautiful wife,
he is overwhelmed by some trumped - up charge.
</p>
               <p>If no charge be brought against him, he is asked
to a banquet and there murdered. No form of
death but is known to this artist in crime. He
investigates the properties of different poisons and
serpents' livid venom and knows of deadly herbs unknown
even to stepmothers. If any condemns what
he sees by a look or sighs with too much freedom,
at the very festal board out darts some henchman
with drawn sword at a nod from his master.
</p>
               <p>Each glued to his seat tastes in silent fear of the
deadly banquet; drains, pale of face, the treacherous
cup, and looks around at the weapons that threaten
his life. The deadly board is decked in infernal
splendour, wet with slaughter, dreadful with fear
of sword and suspected poison. When wine has
<pb id="v.1.p.113"/>
inflamed the passions, his lust rages more savagely;
'midst the mingled smell of scents and flowers,
'midst curled minions and youthful choirs he bids
go sport the widowed wives whose husbands he
but a moment ago has murdered. Better Phalaris
and the torments of his furnace, better to listen to
the bellowings of the Sicilian bull than to such
songs as these. Nor is the base sacrifice of their
good name enough. When tired of each noblest
matron Gildo hands her over to the Moors. Married
in Carthage city these Sidonian mothers needs must
mate with barbarians. He thrusts upon me an
Ethiopian as a son-in-law, a Berber as a husband.
The hideous half-breed child affrights its cradle.
Thanks to those base allies his state is more regal
than that of the emperor himself. Before him goes
a body of foot-soldiers, squadrons of cavalry surround
him and client kings whom he enriches with our
spoils. He drives one and all from their ancestral
houses and expels husbandmen from farms so long
theirs. My people are scattered in exile. Are my
citizens never to return from their wanderings
to their native soil?</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>She would have spoken further in her grief had
not Jove begun from his lofty throne — Atropos
wrote down his words in adamant and Lachesis spun
them in with her thread — <q direct="unspecified">Neither thou, Rome,
nor yet thou, Africa, will we suffer to go long unavenged.
Honorius shall disperse your common foe.
Go in peace. No violence shall part your companionship;
Africa shall serve Rome, and Rome alone.</q>
         </p>
         <p>He spake and breathed into Rome a youth renewed.
</p>
         <p>Straightway her former strength returned, and her
hair put off its grey of eld; her helmet grew solid,
<pb id="v.1.p.115"/>
upright stood the plumes, the round shield shone
once more, and gone was every trace of rust from
her wingèd, gleaming spear.
</p>
         <p>Sleep was now driving the dew-drenched steeds
of night, guiding them with the reins of Lethe and
carrying round the stars in her silent course, when
the elder and the younger Theodosius,1 chief among
the heroes divine, came to bring peace to men.
</p>
         <p>They bore Jove's secret message and mandate to
the two brothers and ratified the treaty between
the two empires. So when at dead of night the
driving tempest has brought the helmsman's skill
to nought and the sinking ship groans and shudders
at the waves' ceaseless shock, Leda's Spartan-born
sons sustain the foundering bark in answer to the
sailors' prayers. At the rise of the full moon the
twain parted. The elder directed his steps towards
the coasts of Italy, the younger visited the couch
of Arcadius, gliding down to that Eastern city where
Bosporus narrows the entrance to the Euxine. As
soon as the son saw his father (for the moon was
shining brightly), he wept, yet trembled for joy, and
embracing that form he had little hoped ever to
embrace again, said: <q direct="unspecified">O thou restored now to me
for the first time since thy triumphs in the Alps,
whence comest thou to thy loving son? Let me
touch that hand that has conquered so many barbarian
races! Who hath robbed the world of
such a defender? How long a while has mankind
prayed thine aid, and missed thy goodness and thy
might!</q>
         </p>
         <p>Sighing, the father made answer: <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Was it for
this? Is a Moor become a cause of discord between
two brothers? Does the empire and court of the
<pb id="v.1.p.117"/>
East quarrel with those of the West? Can Gildo's
salvation be fit guerdon for this mad rivalry? Great
no doubt are his virtues, great should be the price
paid to preserve them and such his merits as to
banish affection in a brother. Look you, though I,
thy sire, willed it not, civil war raged; the fortunes of
Rome stood on a razor's edge. Was there a distant
king of Armenia, an unknown monarch by Maeotis'
shore but sent aid to mine enterprises? The Getae
gave me succour, the Geloni came to my assistance.
</p>
               <p>Gildo alone sent not a man, not a ship, but waited
the issue in wavering loyalty. Had he sought the
confronting host as an open foe my wrath had been
less bitter. He stood apart on Fortune's watchtower
and, withdrawn from the throng, weighed this
side against that, meaning to let the event decide him,
dependent upon the turn things might take and ready
to embrace the side of the victor. His fortune hung in
the balance as well as his intention. Had I not been
hurried to heaven by the impatient stars I would have
followed the example of Tullus Hostilius and dragged
the impious wretch limb from limb fastened to
chariots driven different ways through thorn bushes.1
Up to this time he has owed obedience to thy brother,
now behold he spurns his commands. After thy
father's and thy brother's fate art thou ready to
trust thyself to such a villain? Is thine answer that
he maketh great return and hath brought over many
cities to thine allegiance? Shall honour, then, give
place to utility? Can gain render treachery welcome?
</p>
               <p>I make no mention of his cruel betrayal of thy brother;
of his fickle nature; were a traitor to bring safety
even when at peril's height death threatened, never
shall he win gratitude. When our life is saved
<pb id="v.1.p.119"/>
we condemn the treachery nor brook to entrust
ourselves to such protection. 'Tis this sort that
offers for purchase cities and their inhabitants,
that sells its fatherland. Most make use of such for
the moment but soon learn to hate them. 'Twas
thus that Philip held the cities of Greece; liberty
fell before the attack of Macedonian gold. Rome
has ever despised the ministers of guilt. Fabricius,
discovering the plot, sent back to King Pyrrhus the
slave who had promised to mingle deadly poison for
his lord; fierce war raged between them, but
Fabricius refused to end it by means of the
treachery of a slave. Camillus, too, gave back to
the beleaguered city the boys brought to his camp
from out the walls.
</p>
               <p>These were consigned to punishment for seeking
to put an end to wars. Is Gildo to live that he
may kindle them? Takest thou such measures
against thy brother as another would disdain to
take against an enemy? O shame for unending
ages! Gildo entrusts the governance of the south
to whom he will; the great province of Africa
obeys a tyrant's whim. To whichever side his
fickle mind inclines, he carries Libya over with him
and malignantly subjects it to a rule shifting as
the tide. Africa was the gift of the Moor. Away
with the trickery of the Massyli, their treacherous
wiles and their words that breathe forth the poison
of their land. Let not brother wage war on brother,
I pray. That were worthy of cruel Thebes and
Mycenae; let that accusation be levelled against
the Moors.
</p>
               <p>What wrong is Stilicho devising? when did he
fail in his obedience? than him what more loyal
<pb id="v.1.p.121"/>
supporter have we? I will not mention the various
brave deeds he did while yet with me; of those
only I will tell which I saw after my death. When
I was raised to heaven disorder — I admit it — and
tumult did I leave behind me. The army was still
drawing the forbidden sword in that Alpine war,
and conquerors and conquered gave alternate cause
for dissension. Scarce could this madness have been
calmed by my vigilance, much less by a boy's rule.
Ah, how I feared for you what the uncontrolled
might of such vast armies might dare, when, your
sire removed, there came the fevered delight in
change! Dangerous was discord, more dangerous
still unanimity. 'Twas then that Stilicho took
my place in paternal love for thee, tended thine
immature youth, and brought thee to the years
and estate of an emperor. 'Twas he drove back
Rufinus whom thou didst confess thou fearedst.
Gratitude and loyalty I find in him alone. Did
I want or seem to want aught, while yet I
lived he accomplished it. Now I am dead he
worships me as worthy of veneration and an ever
present helper. If the thought of his goodness
move thee not, at least show respect to thy brother's
father-in-law: bethink thee of Honorius' marriage,
the royal espousal of my niece Serena. Thou
oughtest to face thy brother's foes, he thine. Could
any nation, could the combined forces of Rhine and
Danube have stood against you twain allied?
Enough! bring about but the defeat of Gildo: I ask
nought else. Though he entrench himself behind the
protecting Syrtes and rely for safety on the intervening
ocean; though he think to be defended by
reason of his serpent-infested country and the fierce
<pb id="v.1.p.123"/>
sun's mid-day heat, yet well I know Stilicho's ingenuity
—that mind of his equal to any emergency.
He will force his way through the desert, his own
greatness will lead him.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>Thus spake the dead emperor, whereon thus
the son answered: <q direct="unspecified">Right willingly, father, will I
fulfil thy commands: ever ready am I to welcome
thy behests. None is dearer to me than my kinsman
Stilicho. Let the impious Gildo atone for his wrongs,
and Africa be restored to my brother still safer
than before.</q>
         </p>
         <p>While father and son thus debated in long converse,
Theodosius the grandfather made his way to Italy
and entered the chaste bedchamber where on his
couch of Tyrian purple Honorius lay in sweet sleep
by the side of his wife Maria. At his head he stood
and thus spake to him in a dream. <q direct="unspecified"> What rash
confidence is this, dear grandson, that fills the
conquered Moors? Does the mad race descended
from Juba, the people whom I subdued, once more
conspire to oppose Rome's power and recommence
the war with its conqueror's grandson? Have they
forgotten the defeat of Firmus 1? Do they think to
repossess Libya won back by the sweat of battle?
Dares Gildo strive with Rome? Does he not fear
his brother's fate. Fain would I go myself, old
though I be, and show him the face he knows but
too well. Will not the Moor flee my very shade,
should he behold it? Why delayest thou? Up from
thy bed; attack the rebel; give me back my
prisoner; waste no more time. 'Tis Fate's gift to
thy family. While yet the race of Theodosius treads
the earth the palace of Bocchus shall go in fear. Let
the spoils of Gildo be added to those of Firmus;
<pb id="v.1.p.125"/>
let the bays of Mauretania deck chariots twain and
one house triumph thus many times over one race.
Thanks be to the gods who have interposed so many
years between the sacrifice of Firmus to my arms
and that of Firmus' brother to those of my grandson.</q>
         </p>
         <p>He spake, then fled, as he felt the breath of
the approaching dawn.
</p>
         <p>Then emulous courage roused the emperor with
insistent goad. He burns to set sail, to cleave the
main, to assail with the spear the distant Moors. So
he summons his father-in-law 1 and clasping his hand
asks what course of action he advises. <q direct="unspecified">Full often,
reverend sire, is the future revealed to me in dreams;
many a night brings prophecy. Methought I
surrounded in hunting the distant glades of Africa
and scoured the Gaetulian mountains with my
hounds. The district was distressed by reason of
the incursions of a ravening Hon. On all sides were
slaughtered beasts and mangled heifers, and still
their homesteads ran red with blood, and corpses of
many a shepherd lay weltering in the bloody fields.
I approached the beast's cave and saw a sight
wonderful to relate. Gone was that noble form,
drooping on the neck the threatening mane; there
he crouched, defeated, humbled, with slavish moans;
fetters were upon his paws and a chain clanked
of a sudden on his neck. Now, too, my grandsire
eagerly urges me to rival his triumphs with
my own. Why, he asked, did I delay and hesitate so
long? Already my ships should have been manned
and the sea's threatened opposition overcome. I
myself am ready to cross in the first vessel. Let
every foreign nation that is bound beneath my rule
come to our aid. Let all Germany be transported and
<pb id="v.1.p.127"/>
the Sygambri come with allied fleet. Let trembling
Africa now have experience of the dwellers on Rhine's
banks. Or shall I sit here and submit to such
disgrace? Shall I relinquish, now that I am a man,
what I ruled and governed as a boy? Twice my
father hurried to the Alps to defend another's
realm. Am I to be an easy prey, an object of scorn?</q>
         </p>
         <p>He ended and Stilicho thus made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Wilt
thou, an emperor, deign to challenge a Moor to
fight? Is that coward to have the consolation of
death in battle at thy hand? Shall Honorius fight
on our side and Gildo on the other? Ere that, chaos
shall plunge the stars into Hell. 'Tis enough to
command his punishment. Thy name shall strike
greater terror into him than thy sword. Presence
will minish awe; he who stands in the lists admits
equality, and struggling hosts regard not majesty.
Listen and I will tell thee something at once more
profitable for thyself and of more effect against the
enemy. Gildo has a brother of like descent but unlike
in character, Mascezel, who, avoiding the evil courses
of his brother, has entrusted his hopes and his life to
thy keeping. When Gildo, after many vain attempts,
found no means to kill Mascezel, he turned his
anger from the father to the children and slew those
whom himself had nursed as infants in his arms;
then cast aside their unburied bodies and refused
sepulchre to the shades of those that had been his
kin. The bloody tyrant stifled all natural feelings,
forgot he was a brother, forgot he was a man, and
begrudged the slain a handful of dust. 'Twas a like
deed brought its ill repute upon Mycenae, that put
the sun to rout and turned back the day. But while
Atreus paid back crime for crime and had excuse
<pb id="v.1.p.129"/>
for the bloody banquet in the unfaithfulness of his
wife, Gildo's motive was hatred, not vengeance.
Violated rights, the sorrowing father, the unburied
dead, the unnatural crime all call upon thee as
avenger. If thou, Athens, didst dedicate an altar
to the sorrowing and ordain to those that mourn a
special deity, if the women of Argos won to their
aid the Athenian phalanx by their tears and bought
burial for their slain lords at the price of war; 1 if
Adherbal, driven from his throne, roused the Senate
against the Numidians by the sad appeal of unkempt
locks and by his tears, then let Gildo be sorry that
now this man also whom he has crushed by so many
murders is come into the field against him, and let
him learn that he must bow before thy suppliants.
Let Gildo flee headlong before him whom he put to
flight and fear him whom he o'erwhelmed with the
murder of his children. As he is being dragged off to
the slaughter let him recognize his brother's hand.</q>
         </p>
         <p>When this advice had been accepted by his son-
in-law, Stilicho made ready for war the most famous
regiments in the army, selecting therefrom special
companies of picked men; he further prepared the
fleet in the harbours of Etruria. Alcides himself
commands the Herculean cohort; the king of the
gods leads the Jovian. No standard-bearer feels the
weight of his eagle, so readily do the very standards
press forward. The Nervian cohort follows and the
Felix, well deserving its name, the legion, too,
named after Augustus, that well called The Unconquered,
and the brave regiment of the Lion 2
to whose name their shields bear witness.
</p>
         <p>But before they start the emperor, standing upon
a platform of earth, heartens them with his words:
<pb id="v.1.p.131"/>
leaning upon their spears the soldiers throng around
him and attune their ready ears to his inspiring
voice. <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>My men, so soon to bring defeat upon
Gildo, now is the time to fulfil your promises and
make good your threats. If you felt indignation
on my behalf, now take up arms and prove it.
Wash out the stain of civil war by means of a great
and deserved triumph. Let the empire of the East
know, let it be plain to all the world, that Gaul can
only owe defeat to the badness of a cause, not to
her enemies' strength.1 Let not Gildo affright you
though he have all barbary at his back. Shall Moors
stand up against the shock of your clashing shields
and the near threat of your swords? You shall not
oppose men armed with shields or shining blades.
These savages put their trust in javelins hurled from
afar. Once he has discharged his missile the enemy
will be disarmed. With his right hand he hurls
his spear, with his left he holds his cloak before him;
no other armour has the horseman. His steed
knows not the rein; a whip controls it. Obedience
and discipline are unknown in their ranks. Their
arms are a burden to them, their salvation lies in
flight. Though each has many wives, ties of family
bind them not, nor have they any love for their
children whose very number causes affection to fail.
Such are the troops. The chief will come to battle
crowned with roses, drenched with scents, his last
feast still undigested; drunken with wine, foredone
with eld, enervated with disease and venery. Let
the war trumpet rouse him from a bed of incest, let
him beg aid of lutes and choirs, for he likes not the
clarion's note, and let him learn (all unwilling) to
spend in war nights that he now dedicates to love.
<pb id="v.1.p.133"/>
               </p>
               <p>Is not death preferable to a life disgraced? If,
in addition to the loss of Illyria, Africa is to be
surrendered to Moorish kings, what lands still remain
to us? The empire of Italy, once bounded by the
Nile and the Red Sea, is limited to-day by the sea
of Tuscany; shall Sicily now be the most distant
province of Roman rule, to which in days of old
neither Egypt nor India set an end? Go: win back
that southern realm a rebel has reft from me. It
depends on your arms whether Rome, the unconquerable
mistress of the world, stands or falls. You
owe me so many peoples, countries, cities lost.
Fight but one battle in defence of Libya. Let
empire restored attend on your oars and sails. Give
back to Africa the laws of Rome she now disregards.
Let history repeat itself, and the sword smite from
its trunk the head of this third tyrant 1 and so end
at last the series of bloody usurpers.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>An omen confirms his word and before the eyes
of all, the tawny bird, armour-bearer of Jove, swoops
down from the open sky and seizes a snake in his
curved talons; and while the eagle tears his struggling
prey with his hooked beak, his claws are embedded
in its head. The severed body falls to earth. Straight-
way the soldiers come hurrying up, crossing rocks
and streams in their eagerness at the call of this
portent. Neither mountains nor woods delay them.
</p>
         <p>Even as the cranes leave their summer home of
Thrace clamorously to join issue in doubtful war
with the Pygmies, when they desert the Strymon
for warm-watered Nile, the letter 2 traced by the
speeding line stands out against the clouds and the
heaven is stamped with the figure of their flight.
</p>
         <p>When they reached the coast still fiercer blazed
<pb id="v.1.p.135"/>
their enthusiasm. They seize upon the ships and
themselves make ready the hawsers; furl the sails
and fix the yards to the masts. Etruria's shore
is shaken with their uproar and Arcadian-founded
Pisa cannot contain so great a number of ships.
</p>
         <p>So Aulis rang with countless voices what time
avenging Greece loosed the cables of Agamemnon's
fleet. No storm-blast deterred them nor threat of
coming tempest nor the presence of the treacherous
south wind. <q direct="unspecified">Seize the rope, fellow-soldiers,</q> they
cry, <q direct="unspecified">seize the rope: let us sail against Gildo though
the very seas be against us. Let the storm drive
us to battle by how crooked so ever a course. Fain
would I seize upon that shore though my ships' beaks
be shattered. Cowards ye, who cautiously observe
whether or no the sea-gulls fly back or the crow
pace the beach. What if clouds fleck the face of the
setting sun or a stormy moon wear the halo that
betokens hurricane? What if comets wave their
spreading tails, or the constellation of the Kids
threatens rain, or the cloudy Hyades lead forth the
Bull and all Orion sink 'neath the waves? Put your
trust in the sky, but put more in Honorius.
Beneath his auspices I, his soldier, range the boundless
seas nor look to the Plough or the Bear to guide
me. Make no account of Boötes, sailor; launch your
bark in mid tempest. If winds and storms deny me
Libya, my emperor's fortune will grant it.</q>
         </p>
         <p>The fleet is launched. They pass Liguria on their
right hand, Etruria on their left, avoiding the sunken
reefs of Corsica. There lies an island formed like
a human foot (Sardinia its former inhabitants called
it), an island rich in the produce of its fields, and
conveniently situated for them who sail either to
<pb id="v.1.p.137"/>
Africa or Italy. The part that faces Africa is flat
and affords good anchorage for ships; the northern
shore is inhospitable, rock-bound, stormy, and loud
with sudden gales. The sailor curses these wild
cliffs. Here the pestilence falls on men and beasts,
so plague-ridden and deadly is the air, so omnipotent
the South wind and the North winds banished.
</p>
         <p>When their much buffeted vessels had given a
wide berth to these dangers, they came to land at
different places on the broken coast-line. Some
are beached at Sulci, a city founded by Carthage
of old. The sea-wall of Olbia shelters others. The
city of Caralis over against the coast of Libya, a
colony of great Phoenician Carthage, juts out into
the sea and extends into the waves, a little promontory
that breaks the force of the opposing
winds. Thus in the midst a harbour is found and
in a huge bay the quiet waters lie safe from every
wind. For this harbour they make with every effort,
and reversing their vessels they await the favouring
breezes of the west wind with fleet at anchor.1
<pb id="v.1.p.139"/>
         </p>
               </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>