<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the Subject of the Consular Provinces </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <head> THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO ON THE SUBJECT OF THE CONSULAR PROVINCES.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>This speech was delivered about the middle of the year of the consulship of
                    Cnaeus Cornelius Lentulus Marcellinus and Lucius Marcius Philippus, A. U. C.
                    698. Before the new consuls were elected, the senate assembled to deliberate on
                    what province should be allotted to them on the expiration of their year of
                    office. The provinces about which the question really was were the two Gauls
                    which Caesar had, and <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> and
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> which had been given to
                    Lucius Calpurnius Piso Caesonius, and to Aulus Gabinius, the consuls of the year
                    696. Several senators had spoken when Cicero rose, and had all, except
                    Servilius, advocated the taking one or both of the Gauls from Caesar, which was
                    in fact what the senate was desirous to do, but Cicero, who had himself been
                    treated with the greatest indignity by Piso and Gabinius, was anxious instead to
                    get them recalled with some marks of disgrace, and to have their provinces
                    assigned to the consuls, and he urged also that Caesar's command should be
                    continued to him till he had finished the war which he was carrying on with such
                    success and till he had settled the conquered countries. This was much against
                    the wishes of the senate and even of the existing consuls, who were principally
                    concerned in the matter so that Philippus reproached Cicero, and reminded him
                    that he had received worse treatment from Caesar than he had even from Gabinius
                    since Caesar had been the real author of the calamities which had befallen him.
                    But Cicero replied that his object was not the satisfying of his own private
                    resentment, but the promotion of the real interests of the republic; that Caesar
                    was deserving well of his country, that if he remained in his province, he would
                    soon reduce all <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> to subjection, but
                    that Piso and Gabinius were only tyrannizing over and draining their provinces
                    while they were objects of contempt to all foreign enemies. The result was that
                    he brought the senate entirely over to this opinion, and they continued Caesar's
                    command in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> and recalled <placeName
                        key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName> and Gabinius from their provinces which
                    were given to the new consuls.<note anchored="true">See the oration against
                            <placeName key="tgn,2040810">Piso</placeName>.</note>
                </p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>If any one of you, O conscript fathers, is waiting to see what provinces I shall
                propose to decree to the consuls, let him consider in his own mind what men I must
                think it most desirable to recall from the provinces; and then he will not <pb
                    n="286"/> have any doubt what ought to be my sentiments, when he has once
                seriously thought what it is absolutely inevitable that they should be. And if I
                were the first to deliver the opinion which I am about to state, you would in truth
                praise it; if I were to stand alone in it, at all events you would pardon me. Even
                if my opinion were to appear to you on the whole somewhat ineligible, still you
                would make some allowance for my just indignation. But, as the case stands at
                present, O conscript fathers, I feel no ordinary delight because it is so entirely
                for the advantage of the republic that <placeName key="tgn,1000140"
                    >Syria</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> should
                be the provinces decreed to the consuls, that my own private feelings are in no
                respect at variance with the general good; and because also I can cite the authority
                of Publius Servilius, who has delivered his opinion before me, a most illustrious
                man, and of singular good faith and attachment both to the republic in general, and
                to my safety in particular. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And if he, both just
                now, and whenever he has had any opportunity or possibility of speaking on the
                subject, has thought it his duty to brand not only with his adverse opinion but with
                the greatest severity of language, Gabinius and Piso, as the two monsters who have
                been almost the destruction of the republic, both on other accounts, and also most
                especially because of their extraordinary wickedness and unseemly inhumanity towards
                me, with what feelings ought I myself to be actuated towards those men,—I whose
                safety they devoted and ruined for the gratification of their own evil passions? </p>
            <p>But in declaring my sentiments at this time, I will not be guided by my indignation,
                nor will I make my speech subservient to my enmity. The same feelings which every
                individual among you ought to entertain towards those men, shall influence me also.
                My own predominant and peculiar feeling of private indignation, which, however, you
                have always considered as belonging to yourselves in common with me, I will put
                aside while delivering my opinion, and reserve for a more fitting opportunity of
                revenge. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>There are four provinces, O conscript fathers, concerning which I understand that
                opinions have as yet been delivered: the two Gauls, which at present we see united
                under one command; and <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>; and
                    <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>; which, against your will,
                and when you were suffering under oppression <pb n="287"/> and constraint, those
                pernicious consuls seized on as their reward for having overturned the republic.
                According to the provisions of the Sempronian law, we have now to decree two to the
                consuls. How is it possible for us to doubt about <placeName key="tgn,1000140"
                    >Syria</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> being
                these two? I say nothing of the fact that those men are holding them at present who
                procured them in such a way that they did not get them till they condemned this
                order of ours till they had destroyed your authority and put an end to it in the
                state till they had destroyed all public credit and good faith endangered the
                lasting safety of the Roman people, and harassed me and my friends and relations in
                the most shameful and barbarous manner. </p>
            <p><milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All these private matters, all these transactions
                which took place in the city, I say nothing about; though they are of such a nature
                that Hannibal himself never wished so much evil to this city, as those men have
                done. I come to the case of the provinces themselves, of which <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, which was formerly fortified not by the
                towers built, but by the trophies erected by numbers of our generals, which had long
                ago been reduced to a state of tranquillity by many victories and triumphs, is now
                so harassed by the barbarians who are not allowed to rest in peace in consequence of
                the avarice of the late consul, that the people of <placeName key="tgn,7011182"
                    >Thessalonica</placeName>, placed in the lap as it were of our empire are
                compelled to abandon their town and to fortify their citadel, that that military
                road of ours which reaches all through <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                    >Macedonia</placeName> as far as the <placeName key="tgn,7002638"
                    >Hellespont</placeName> is not only infested by the incursions of the barbarians
                but is even studded with and divided among Thracian encampments. And so those
                nations which had given large sums of money to our illustrious commanders to
                purchase the blessings of peace, in order to be able to replenish their houses which
                had been thus drained, instead of the peace which they had purchased, have waged
                against us what is little short of a regular war. And now that very army of ours,
                collected by a most splendid enlistment, and by a very rigid levy, has almost
                entirely perished. I say this with the most real grief. <milestone n="3"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="5" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>The soldiers of the Roman people have been taken prisoners, put to death, abandoned,
                and dispersed in a most miserable manner. They have been wasted away by neglect, <pb
                    n="288"/> by famine, by disease, by every sort of disaster; so that (and it is a
                most scandalous thing) the wickedness of the general appears <gap reason="* * *"/>to
                have been chastised by the punishment of the fatherland and the army. And this
                    <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, as all the neighbouring
                nations had been subdued, and all the barbarians checked, we used to be able to
                preserve by its own resources, in a peaceable state, and in perfect tranquillity,
                with a very slight garrison, and a small army, even without a commander-in-chief, by
                means of lieutenants, and by the bare name of the Roman people. And yet now, when
                there is a man there with consular command and a consular army, it is so harassed
                that it is scarcely able to recruit its strength by a peace of any duration. And in
                the meantime who is there of you who has not heard and who does not know that the
                Achaeans are every year paying a vast sum to Lucius Piso? that all the revenues and
                harbour duties of the Dyrrachians have been converted to a source of profit for this
                one man? that the city of the Byzantines, a city most loyal to you and to this
                empire, is harassed as if it belonged to an enemy? to which city he, after he could
                no longer squeeze anything out of them, because of the poverty to which he had
                reduced them, and could not by any acts of violence extort anything more from them,
                miserable as they were, sent his cohorts into winter quarters, and gave them
                commanders whom he thought likely to be his most complying and diligent agents in
                wickedness, and ministers to his desires. </p>
            <p><milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I say nothing of the way in which he exercised his
                jurisdiction in a free city contrary to the laws and to the resolutions of the
                senate. I pass over his murders, I omit all mention of his acts of lust; of which
                there is a most bitter token, for the lasting recollection of his infamy, and almost
                bringing even our sovereignty into just odium, in the fact that it is notorious that
                some virgins of the noblest birth threw themselves into wells, and by a voluntary
                death escaped from otherwise inevitable disgrace. Nor do I omit them now because
                they are not most enormous atrocities, but because I am speaking without the support
                of any witnesses. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But who is there who is ignorant that the city of the Byzantines was entirely filled
                and superbly decorated with statues? which the citizens, even when exhausted by the
                great <pb n="289"/> expenses of important wars, while sustaining the attacks of
                Mithridates, and the whole force of <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>,
                boiling over and pouring itself over all <placeName key="tgn,1000004"
                    >Asia</placeName> which they repulsed with difficulty at their own great
                risk,—even then, I say, and afterwards, the Byzantines preserved those statues and
                all the other ornaments of their city and guarded them most religiously. <milestone
                    n="7" unit="section"/> But when you, O most unhappy and most infamous of men,
                became the commander there, O Caesoninus Calventius then a free city, and one which
                had been made so by the senate and people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName>, on account of its recent services, was so plundered and
                stripped of everything, that, if Caius Virgilius the lieutenant, a very brave and
                incorruptible man, had not interfered, the Byzantines would not have retained one
                single statue out of all their great number. </p>
            <p>What temple in all <placeName key="tgn,7002733">Achaia</placeName>? what spot or what
                grove in the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, was there of
                such sanctity that a single statue or a single ornament has been left in it? You
                purchased from a most infamous tribune of the people, at the time of that general
                shipwreck of the city, which you, the very man who were bound to govern it rightly,
                had been the main agent in overturning; you purchased, I say, at that time, for an
                immense sum of money, the power of pronouncing judgment on the people of the free
                cities, with respect to the moneys which had been advanced, contrary to the
                resolutions of the senate, and the law of your own son-in-law. What you had bought,
                you sold in such a manner that you either never gave any decision at all, or else
                you deprived Roman citizens of their property. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                I am not bringing forward these facts at this moment, O conscript fathers, as
                charges against this man, I am merely arguing with respect to the province.
                Therefore I pass over all those things which you have often heard of and which you
                are well aware of, even when you do not hear of them. I say nothing of his audacious
                conduct in the city, which he has fixed deep in the recollection of your eyes and
                minds; I say nothing of his arrogance, of his insolence, of his cruelty. Let those
                dark acts of lust of his lie hid, acts which he tried to conceal by his stern
                countenance and supercilious look, not by modesty and temperance. I am arguing about
                the province, the welfare of which is at stake in this matter. Will you not send a
                successor to such a man as this? Will you allow him to remain any longer? a man
                whose fortune, from the very moment <pb n="290"/> that he first reached the
                province, has so vied with his wickedness, that no one could decide whether he was
                more undeserving or more unfortunate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But as for <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, is that Semiramis any
                longer to be retained there? a man whose march into the province bore the appearance
                of king Ariobarzanes having hired your consul to come and commit murder, as if he
                were some Thracian. His very first arrival in <placeName key="tgn,1000140"
                    >Syria</placeName> was signalized by the destruction of the cavalry; after that,
                all his best cohorts were cut to pieces. Therefore, in <placeName key="tgn,1000140"
                    >Syria</placeName>, since he has been the commander-in-chief, nothing has been
                done beyond making money-bargains with tyrants, and selling decisions, and
                committing robbery and piracy and massacre; while the general of the Roman people,
                with his army in battle array, stretching forth his right hand, did not exhort his
                soldiers to the pursuit of glory, but only kept crying out that everything had been
                bought by him and was to be bought still. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="10" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And as for the miserable farmers of the revenue, (miserable man that I also am, when
                I see the miseries and sufferings of those men who have deserved so well at my
                hands,) he handed them over as slaves to the Jews and Syrian nations, themselves
                born for slavery. He laid down as a rule from the very beginning, and he persevered
                in it, never to decide an action in favour of a farmer of the revenue; he rescinded
                covenants that had been made without any injustice, he took away all the garrisons
                established for their protection; he released many people who were subject to pay
                tributes and taxes from such payments; whatever town he was living in or whatever
                town he arrived at, there he forbade any farmer of the revenue or any servant of
                such farmer to remain. Why need I enlarge on this? He would be considered a cruel
                man if he had shown such a disposition towards our enemies, as he did show towards
                Roman citizens, especially towards those of that order which has hitherto always
                been maintained by its own dignity and by the goodwill of the magistrates.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, O conscript fathers, you see that the farmers of the revenue were ground
                down and nearly ruined, not by any rashness with which they had entered into their
                contracts, nor by any ignorance of the proper methods of transacting business, but
                by the avarice, the pride, and the cruelty of Gabinius. And to their assistance
                indeed, in the present difficulties of the treasury, <pb n="291"/> it is actually
                indispensable that you should come. Although there are many of them whom you cannot
                now relieve, men who by the means of that enemy of the senate of that most bitter
                foe of the equestrian order and of all virtuous men, wretched that they are, have
                lost not only their property but their honourable position; men whom neither
                parsimony nor temperance nor virtue nor labour nor respectability of character, have
                been able to protect against the audacity of that glutton and robber. <milestone
                    n="12" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>What are we to do? shall we suffer those men to perish who are even now supporting
                themselves on the resources of their patrimony or on the liberality of their
                friends? Or, suppose any man has been prevented by the enemies means from enjoying
                his public rights is that man protected by the law of the censors? but in the case
                of a man who is prevented by one who is an enemy, though he may not be actually
                called one, is that a man whom we ought not to assist? Retain then in the province a
                little longer that man who makes covenants with the enemy respecting the allies and
                with the allies respecting the citizens,—who thinks himself a more important man
                than his colleague on this account that he has deceived you by his morose appearance
                and by his countenance, while he himself has never once pretended to be less
                worthless than he really is. But Piso boasts in another sort of fashion that he in a
                very short time has brought it to pass that Gabinius is not thought the most
                infamous of all men. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="13"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Do not you think that you ought to recall these men from their provinces even if you
                had no one to send thither in their places? Would you, could you retain there these
                two pests of the allies, these men who are the destruction of the soldiers, the ruin
                of the farmers of the revenue, the desolators of the provinces, the disgracers of
                the empire? But you, yourselves, in the preceding year did recall these very men
                when they had only just arrived in the provinces. And if at that time your judgment
                had been unfettered and if the matter had not been so frequently adjourned and at
                the last taken wholly out of your hands you would have restored your authority, as
                you were most anxious to do recalling those men by whom it had been lost and
                compelling them to render up the rewards which they had received and whom had been
                conferred on them in return for their wickedness and for the <pb n="292"/> overthrow
                of their country. And if they at that time escaped from that punishment, through no
                merit of their own, but through the influence of others, greatly against your
                consent, still they have undergone a much greater and severer punishment. <milestone
                    n="14" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>For what severer punishment could befall any one, in whom there exists, if not any
                respect for his reputation, at all events some fear of punishment, than to have
                those letters of theirs utterly disbelieved which announced that the republic had
                been very successful in war? The senate decided this, when in a very full house it
                refused Gabinius a supplication; they decided, in the first place, that no belief at
                all could be given to a man polluted with every sort of guilt and wickedness; and,
                secondly, that the affairs of the republic could not possibly be managed
                successfully by a traitor, especially by that man who was known to be at the time an
                enemy of the republic; and, lastly, that even the immortal gods themselves did not
                choose their temples to be thrown open, and supplications to be addressed to them in
                the name of a most profligate and wicked man. </p>
            <p>Therefore, that other man is either himself a learned man, and one well instructed by
                his Greek slaves, with whom he now sups behind the scenes, as he used to do before
                the curtain, or else he has wiser friends than Gabinius, from whom no letters are
                produced. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="15" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Shall we then have these men for our generals? the one of whom does not venture to
                inform us whether <gap reason="* * * *"/>he is styled <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >Imperator</foreign>; and the other must in a few days repent of having ventured
                to mention such a thing to us, if his clerks do not tire of writing. And if that man
                has any friends, or indeed, if it be possible that any one should be a friend to so
                savage and foul a brute, they comfort themselves with this consolation, that this
                senatorial order once refused an application to Titus Albucius. But first of all,
                the cases are very unlike. The proprietor had had a battle with one auxiliary cohort
                against a lot of banditti clad in sheepskins in <placeName key="tgn,7003121"
                    >Sardinia</placeName>. And a war against the mightiest nations and tyrants of
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> was brought to a termination by
                means of a consular army, and a magistrate invested with the supreme military
                command. In the next place, Albucius had had already decreed to himself in
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> the same thing which he was
                soliciting <pb n="293"/> from the senate. For it was notorious that he like a Greek,
                and like a light-headed inconsiderate man as he was had celebrated something like a
                triumph in the province itself. And therefore the senate marked their displeasure at
                this precipitate conduct of his by the refusing of a supplication. <milestone n="16"
                    unit="section"/> But let him in truth enjoy this as some comfort, and let him
                think this very eminent mark of disgrace all the less considerable because it has
                been inflicted on himself alone, provided only that he is content to expect the same
                end as that man by whose precedent he consoles himself. Especially as Albucius was
                not liable to the reproach of either Piso's lust or Gabinius's audacity and yet fell
                by this one blow, the infamy with which he was branded by the senate. <milestone
                    n="17" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But the man who proposes to decree the two Gauls to the two consuls would return both
                these men in their provinces. But he who proposes to decree them one of the Gauls
                and either <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> or <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> still would retain one of these men; and
                while they are both equal in wickedness, he proposes to make their future condition
                unequal. No, I will make them, says he, praetorian provinces in order that Piso and
                Gabinius may have successors appointed immediately. Yes; if you are allowed to do
                so. For then the tribune will be able to intercede with his veto; but at present he
                cannot do so. Therefore I myself who now propose to decree to the consuls who are to
                be elected <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> and <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, am prepared also to make them
                praetorian provinces, in order that the praetors may have their provinces for a
                year, and that we may see those men among us as soon as possible whom we cannot see
                at all with any equanimity. <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But believe me, those men will never have successors appointed to them, except when a
                motion shall be made in accordance with the provisions of that law by which it is
                unlawful for any one to interpose his veto while the debate is pending about the
                provinces; therefore, as this opportunity is lost, you must now wait an entire year;
                during which interval the calamities of the citizens, the miseries of the allies,
                and the impunity of the most wicked men may be extended. <milestone n="18"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But even if they were the most excellent of men, still, in my opinion, it could never
                be advisable to appoint a successor to Caius Caesar. Now, concerning this matter, O
                conscript <pb n="294"/> fathers. I shall declare my real sentiments, and I shall not
                be disconcerted by that interruption of my most intimate friend, who did a little
                while ago interrupt my speech, as you heard. That excellent man says that I ought
                not to be more hostile to Gabinius than to Caesar; for that all that storm, to which
                I yielded, was raised by the instigation and assistance of Caesar. And if I were in
                the first instance to reply that I was having regard to the common advantage, and
                not to my own private sufferings, could I not establish that, when I say that I am
                doing what I well may do according to the example of other most valiant and most
                illustrious citizens? Did Tiberius Gracchus (I am speaking of the father, and would
                that his son had never degenerated from that father's virtue!) gain such great glory
                because he, while tribune of the people, was the only one of the whole college who
                was any assistance to Lucius Scipio, though he was the bitterest possible enemy,
                both to him and to his brother Africanus; and did he not swear in the public
                assembly that he had by no means become reconciled to him, but that it seemed to him
                quite inconsistent with the dignity of the empire that, after the generals of the
                enemy had been led to prison while Scipio was celebrating his triumph, the very man
                also who had triumphed should be led to the same place? <milestone n="19"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Who had a greater number of enemies than Caius Marius? There were Lucius Crassus,
                Marcus Scaurus, (were there no more?) and all the Metelli. But those men not only
                forbore to recall that enemy of theirs from <placeName key="tgn,1000070"
                    >Gaul</placeName> by their votes, but also, out of consideration for the Gallic
                war, they even voted him the province out of the regular order. A most important war
                has been waged in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>; very mighty nations
                have been subdued by Caesar; but they are not yet established with laws, or with any
                fixed system of rights, or by a peace which can be very thoroughly depended on. We
                see that the war has been carried on, and, to say the truth, nearly brought to a
                conclusion; but we shall only see it all actually terminated in a successful manner,
                if the man who commenced it remains to follow it up to the last. If a successor is
                appointed to him, there is great danger that we may hear that the embers of this
                momentous war are again fanned into a flame and rekindled. Therefore I, a senator,
                an enemy, if you please, of the man himself, feel it my duty to be, as I always have
                been, <pb n="295"/> a friend to the republic.<milestone n="20" unit="section"/> What
                if I lay aside my enmity itself for the sake of the republic, who, I should like to
                know, would have a right to blame me? especially as I have at all times thought that
                I ought to seek for the models for all my intentions and for all my actions in the
                conduct of the most illustrious men. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Was not, I should like to know, was not that great man Marcus Lepidus, who was twice
                consul, and also <foreign xml:lang="la">Pontifex Maximus</foreign>, praised not only
                by the evidence of men's recollection, but also in the records of our annals, and by
                the voice of an immortal poet, because on the day that he was made censor, he
                immediately in the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName>
                reconciled himself to Marcus Fulvius his colleague a man who was his bitterest enemy
                in order that they might perform their common duty devolving on them in the
                censorship with one common feeling and union of good will? <milestone n="21"
                    unit="section"/> And to pass over ancient instances, of which there is no end,
                did not your own father, O Philippus, did not he become reconciled at one and the
                same time with all his greatest enemies? to all of whom the same attachment to the
                republic now reconciled him which had previously separated him from them. <milestone
                    n="22" unit="section"/> I pass over many instances because I see before me these
                lights and ornaments of the republic Publius Servilius and Marcus Lucullus; would
                that that great man, Lucius Lucullus, were still alive! What enmities were ever more
                bitter in this city that those which subsisted between the Luculli and the Servilii?
                But in those most gallant men the welfare of the republic, and their own dignity,
                not only put an end to that ill-feeling, but even changed it into friendship and
                intimacy. What? did not Quintus Metellus Nepos while consul in the temple of the all
                good and all powerful <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, influenced by
                your authority and also by the incredible dignity of eloquence of that same Publius
                Servilius, become reconciled to me though I was far away, and do me the greatest
                possible service? Is it possible for me to be an enemy to this man, by whose
                letters, by whose glory, and by whose messengers my ears are every day saluted with
                previously unknown names of tribes, and nations, and places? <milestone n="23"
                    unit="section"/> I burn, believe me, O conscript fathers, (as indeed you do
                believe of me, and as you feel yourselves,) with an incredible love for my country;
                which love compelled me formerly to encounter most terrible <pb n="296"/> dangers
                which were hanging over it, at the risk of my own life; and again, when I saw every
                sort of weapon aimed from all quarters against my country, drove me to put myself in
                their way, and to expose myself singly to their blows on behalf of the whole body of
                citizens. And this, my ancient and perpetual disposition towards the republic, now
                reunites and reconciles me to and unites me in friendship with Caius Caesar. In
                short, let men think what they please; it is impossible for me to be other than a
                friend to one who deserves; well of his country. <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="24" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>In truth, if I have not only taken on myself the enmity of, but have declared and
                waged open war against those men who wished to destroy all these things with fire
                and sword; though some of them were my own personal acquaintances, and some had been
                saved on capital trials through my defence of them; why should not the same republic
                which was able to make me hostile to my friends, be able also to reconcile me to my
                enemies? What reason had I for hating Publius Clodius, except that I thought him
                likely to prove a mischievous citizen to my country, inasmuch as, inflamed by the
                most infamous lust, he trampled under foot by one crime two most holy
                considerations, religion and chastity? Is it, therefore, doubtful from these
                actions, which he has done and which he is doing every day, that I in opposing him
                was consulting the interests of the republic more than my own tranquillity; but that
                some others, who defended him, thought more of their own ease than they did of the
                peace of the community? </p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> I admit that I was of a different opinion to
                Caesar with respect to the affairs of the republic, and that I agreed with all of
                you: but now I am agreeing also with you with whom I felt in common before. For
                you,—to whom Lucius Piso does not venture to send letters respecting his
                exploits,—you who have condemned the letters of Gabinius with a most remarkable
                stigma, and an unprecedented mark of disgrace have decreed supplications to Caius
                Caesar in such number, as were never decreed before to any one in one war, and with
                such attending circumstances of honour as were never voted to any one at all. Why,
                then, need I wait for any man to act as a mediator between us, in order to reconcile
                me to him? This most honourable order has mediated between us; that <pb n="297"/>
                order which is the instigator and the leader both of the public counsels and of all
                my own designs. I am following you, O conscript fathers, I am obeying you, I am
                adopting your opinions;—yours, I say, who, as long as you had no very favourable
                opinion of the designs of Caius Caesar with respect to the republic saw that I too
                was very little connected with him; since you changed your opinions and inclinations
                on account of his great achievements you have seen me also not only the sharer of
                your sentiments but also the panegyrist and advocate of them. <milestone n="11"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="26" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But what is the reason why in this cause men so exceedingly marvel at and find fault
                with my opinions when I also before now proposed and voted for many things which
                concerned that man's dignity more than they did the safety of the republic? I
                proposed and carried a supplication of fifteen days in Caesar's honour the bill
                being passed in the terms which I drew up. It would have been sufficient for the
                good of the republic to have had it last only the same number of days as the
                supplication in honour of Caius Marius. That could not have been accounted by the
                immortal gods a scanty thanksgiving which was as great as had heretofore been
                offered in the most important wars. Therefore that increased number of days was
                given to the dignity of the men. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> And in respect
                of that, I, who as consul brought forward the motion, first, for decreeing a
                supplication of ten days to Cnaeus Pompeius after Mithridates had been slain and the
                Mithridatic war been terminated,—I, in compliance with whose opinion it was that the
                ordinary number of days that a supplication in honour of a consul lasted was doubled
                (for you all agreed with me when, having had the letters of that same Pompeius read,
                and knowing that all wars both by sea and land were happily terminated, you decided
                a supplication of twelve days)—I, I say, admired the virtue and greatness of mind of
                Pompeius in that, when he himself had hitherto been preferred to all other men in
                every sort of honour, he now was giving a more ample honour to another than he
                himself had received. Therefore, in that supplication which I proposed, the honour
                was paid to the immortal gods, and to the established usages of our ancestors, and
                to the welfare of the republic. But the dignity of the language in which the decree
                was couched, and the honour and the novelty of the attendant circumstances, <pb
                    n="298"/> and the number of the days,<note anchored="true">
                    <p>A <foreign xml:lang="la">supplicatio</foreign> was a solemn thanksgiving or
                        supplication to the gods, decreed by the senate, when all the temples were
                        opened, and the statues of the gods were frequently placed in public upon
                        couches. (<foreign xml:lang="la">pulvinaria</foreign>,) to which the people
                        offered up their thanksgivings and prayers. (See <bibl n="Cic. Catil. 3.10"
                            >Cic. <title>in Cat.</title> 3.10</bibl>.) </p>
                    <p>It was decreed after great victories, and also in times of public danger and
                        distress, and on account of prodigies, to avert the anger of the gods. </p>
                    <p>When decreed for a victory, the number of days during which it was to last
                        was proportioned to the importance of the victory. Sometimes it was decreed
                        for only one day, but more commonly for three or five days. After the
                        supplication mentioned here of fifteen days, one of twenty days was decreed
                        to Caesar in honour of his victory over Vercingetorix; and from this time
                        forward the senate appears to have increased the number of days out of
                        compliment to the general, so that we find mention of supplications for
                        forty and fifty days, (see <bibl n="Cic. Phil. 14.14">Cic.
                                <title>Phil.</title> 14.14</bibl>,) and even sixty days. It was
                        generally regarded as a prelude to a triumph, but was not always followed by
                        one; as in the case of Cicero himself, to whom a supplication was decreed
                        for his suppression of Catiline's conspiracy, which was no subject for a
                        triumph, being a civil transaction. <foreign xml:lang="la">Vide</foreign>
                        Smith, Dict. Ant. v. <foreign xml:lang="la">Supplicatio</foreign>.</p>
                </note> was meant as a compliment to the renown and glory of Caesar himself.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>A motion was lately brought forward before our body concerning the pay of the army. I
                not only voted for it myself, but I laboured earnestly to induce you to vote for it;
                I replied to many of the arguments of those who objected to it; I supported it also
                by writing. In that case also, I was rather considering the dignity of the man who
                commanded the army, than any particular necessity that existed for the measure. For
                I thought that he, even without this additional supply of money, was able to
                maintain his army with the booty that he had already acquired, and to terminate the
                war. But I thought it would be unbecoming to diminish the glory and splendour of
                that triumph of his by any parsimony on our part. </p>
            <p>A discussion took place also about the ten lieutenants whom he wished to have
                appointed; and some voted altogether against giving them, others asked for
                precedents, others wished to adjourn the consideration of the question, and others
                declared their opinion in favour of it without any complimentary expressions to
                Caesar himself. But on that occasion, I spoke in such a manner as to let all men see
                that, though I thought the measure advantageous to the republic, I was promoting it
                    <pb n="299"/> more cordially out of a desire to pay due honour to the dignity of
                Caesar. <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="29" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And I who have been received in all those discussions with silent attention now that
                the question is about the provinces which are to be decreed to the consuls am
                interrupted; though in all the former transactions it was only a compliment to an
                individual that I urged, while now I have no motive but the consideration of the war
                and the general welfare of the republic. For, as for Caesar himself, what reason can
                there be why he should wish any longer to remain in the province, except for the
                purpose of not giving over to the republic the measures which have been undertaken
                by him before they are completely consummated? It is the delightful nature of the
                country, I suppose, and the splendour of the cities, and the civilized state and
                accomplished habits of those nations and natives,—it is a desire for victory, it is
                a wish to extend the boundaries of our empire, that detains him there! What is there
                anywhere more severe than those countries? what more uncivilized than their towns?
                what more barbarous than their citizens? Moreover what can be imagined more
                desirable than the victories which he has already gained or what can be discovered
                beyond the ocean? Is his return to his country likely to be disagreeable to any one?
                Can it be so either to the people by whom he was sent on his command, or to the
                senate from whom he has received so many distinctions? Does time foster his wish to
                see his country again, or does it rather increase his forgetfulness of it? And do
                those laurels of his which he has gained amid such dangers, lose their greenness by
                the time that elapses after their acquisition? If, then, there be any one who is not
                attached to that man, still such an one has no reason for recalling him from his
                province. It is only recalling him to glory to triumph, to receive congratulations,
                to receive the highest honours which the senate can bestow, to receive the thanks of
                the equestrian order, and to become the object of the devoted affection of the
                people. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But if he, out of his regard for the interests of the republic, does not hasten to
                the enjoyment of that extraordinary good fortune which is in store for him,
                preferring to remain and finish everything; what ought I to do as a senator,—I, who
                ought to think only of the advantage of the republic, even if <pb n="300"/> his
                wishes were opposed to it? For I feel, O conscript fathers, that we at this time,
                while engaged in decreeing provinces to the consuls, ought to have a regard to the
                preservation of perpetual peace. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/> For who is there
                who is not aware that all our other possessions are safe from all danger, and even
                from all suspicion of wars? We have for some time seen that immense sea,—by the
                disturbed condition of which not only our voyages by sea were impeded, but even our
                cities and our military marches and roads were exposed to annoyance,—now, in
                consequence of the valour of Cnaeus Pompeius, possessed from the ocean to the very
                extremity of <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>, like one vast harbor
                in a safe and defensible state; and as for those nations, which by their mere
                numbers and the immensity of their population, were sufficient to overthrow our
                provinces, we have seen some of them so thinned in numbers, and others so severely
                checked by that same man, that <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, which
                was formerly the limit of our empire, is now itself bounded on the further side by
                three of our provinces. I might go on speaking of every region and of every race of
                men. There is no nation which is not either so far destroyed as scarcely to have any
                existence at all, or so utterly subdued as to be quite tranquil; or else so entirely
                at peace with us, as to share our exultation at our victories and at the extension
                of our empire. <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="32" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>The war with <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, O conscript fathers, has
                been carried on actively since Caius Caesar has been our commander-in-chief;
                previously, we were content to act on the defensive, and to repel attacks. For our
                generals at all times thought it better to limit themselves to repulsing those
                nations, than to provoke their hostility by any attack of our own. Even that great
                man, Caius Marius, whose godlike and amazing valour came to the assistance of the
                Roman people in many of its distresses and disasters, was content to check the
                enormous multitudes of Gauls who were forcing their way into <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, without endeavouring to penetrate himself
                into their cities and dwelling-places. And lately, that partner of my labours, and
                dangers, and counsels, Caius Pomptinus, that most gallant man, crushed in battle a
                war of the Allobroges which rose up suddenly against us, and which was excited by
                that impious conspiracy, and defeated those tribes who had provoked us, and then he
                remained quiet, contented <pb n="301"/> with the victory by which be had delivered
                the republic from alarm. </p>
            <p>But I see that the counsels of Caius Caesar are widely different. For he thought it
                his duty, not only to war against those men whom he saw already in arms against the
                Roman people, but to reduce the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000070"
                    >Gaul</placeName> under our dominion. <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                Therefore, he fought with the greatest success against those most valiant and
                powerful nations the Germans and Helvetians; and the other nations he alarmed and
                drove back and defeated, and accustomed to yield to the supremacy of the Roman
                people, so that those districts and those nations which were previously known to us
                neither by any one's letters, nor by the personal account of any one, nor even by
                vague report, have now been overrun and thoroughly examined by our own general, by
                our own army, and by the arms of the Roman people. </p>
            <p>Hitherto, O conscript fathers, we have only known the road into <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>. All other parts of it were possessed by
                nations which were either hostile to this empire, or treacherous, or unknown to us,
                or, at all events, savage, barbarian, and warlike;—nations which no one ever existed
                who did not wish to break their power and subdue: nor has any one, from the very
                first rise of this empire, ever carefully deliberated about our republic, who has
                not thought <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> the chief object of
                apprehension to this empire. But still, on account of the power and vast population
                of those nations, we never before have had a war with all of them; we have always
                been content to resist them when attacked. Now, at last, it has been brought about
                that there should be one and the same boundary to our empire and to those nations.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="34" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Nature had previously protected <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> by the
                    <placeName key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName>, not without some especial
                kindness of the gods in providing us with such a bulwark. For if that road had been
                open to the savage disposition and vast numbers of the Gauls, this city would never
                have been the home and chosen seat of the empire of the world. Now, indeed, they are
                at liberty to sink down if they please; for there is nothing beyond those lofty
                heights as far as the ocean itself, which can be any object of fear to <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. But still it will be the work of one or two
                summers finally to bind the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>
                in everlasting chains either by fear, or hope, or punishment or reward, or <pb
                    n="302"/> arms, or laws. And if our affairs there are left in an unfinished
                state, and while there is still some bitterness of feeling remaining, although the
                enemy may be pruned back severely for the present, still they will raise their heads
                again some time or other, and come forth with recruited strength to renew the war.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/> Let, then, <placeName key="tgn,1000070"
                    >Gaul</placeName> be left in the guardianship of that man to whose valour, and
                good faith, and good fortune it has already been entrusted. If, in truth, he, having
                been distinguished by such marked kindness of Fortune, were unwilling to risk the
                favour of that fickle goddess too often; if he were anxious himself to return to his
                country, to his household gods, to that dignity which he sees in store for him in
                this city, to his most charming children, and to his most illustrious
                    son-in-law;<note anchored="true">Pompeius</note> if he were impatient to be
                borne in triumph as a conqueror to the Capitol, crowned with the illustrious laurel
                of victory; if, in short, he were apprehensive of some disaster, as no event can now
                add so much glory to him as a mishap might deprive him of—still it would be your
                duty to insist on all those affairs being brought to a termination by the same man
                who has begun them so successfully. But when he has not yet satisfied his own desire
                for glory and for the safety of the republic, and as he prefers coming at a later
                period to reap the rewards of his toils rather than not discharging to the full the
                duty which the republic has committed to him; then certainly, we, for our part,
                ought not to recall a general who is so eager to conduct the affairs of the republic
                gloriously, nor to throw into confusion and to hinder his plans for the whole Gallic
                war, which are now almost matured and accomplished. <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="36" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For I cannot at all approve of those opinions which have been expressed by some most
                illustrious men, one of whom proposes to give the consuls the further <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1000140"
                    >Syria</placeName>, and the other inclines to the nearer <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>. He who proposes the further <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, throws all those matters into confusion
                about which I have just been speaking, and shows at the same time that he is
                advocating a law which he affirms to be no law at all; and that he is taking away
                that part of the province to which no interruption can be given, but is not touching
                that part which has a defender. The effect of his conduct also is not to meddle with
                that which has been conferred <pb n="303"/> by the people while at the same time he
                a senator is anxious to take away what has been given by the senate. </p>
            <p>The other disregards all consideration of the Gallic war; he discharges the duty of a
                virtuous senator: though he thinks the law invalid, still he observes it; for he
                fixes beforehand a day for his successor to enter on his office. <gap
                    reason="* *  *"/> But it seems to me that nothing is more inconsistent with the
                dignity and principles of our ancestors than for the consul, who on the first of
                January is to have a province, to have it promised to him in this way, and not
                regularly decreed to him. Suppose he were during the whole of his consulship without
                a province, though even before he was elected a province was decreed to him, is he
                to cast lots for a province, or not? <milestone n="37" unit="section"/> For it is
                absurd not to draw lots for one,—absurd also not to get that which one has drawn by
                lot. Is he to march out in the robe of a commander in chief? Whither is he to march?
                Why, to a place where he may not arrive before a certain fixed day. All January and
                February he is not to have a province. At last on the first of March up will spring
                a province for him all on a sudden. <milestone n="38" unit="section"/> Nevertheless
                if these sentiments prevail, Piso will remain in his province. </p>
            <p>And though these are weighty considerations, still none of them are more serious than
                this—that it is an insulting thing for a commander in chief to be mulcted as it were
                by a diminution of his provinces, and we ought to take great care that such a thing
                should not be allowed to happen, not only not in the case of a most illustrious man,
                but not even in that of a man of moderate reputation. <milestone n="16"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I am well aware, O conscript fathers, that you have decreed many extraordinary
                honours to Caius Caesar; honours which are almost unprecedented. In that he has
                amply merited them, you have been grateful; if I add, too, that he is a man most
                thoroughly attached to this order of the senate, you have been wise and provident.
                For this order has never heaped its distinctions and kindness on any one who has
                subsequently thought any dignity preferable to that which he had obtained by your
                favour. For it is not possible for any one to be the leading man in this body who
                has preferred courting the favour of the people. But all men who have done this,
                have either distrusted themselves on account of their consciousness of their want of
                worth, or else they have <pb n="304"/> been driven away from a union with this order
                on account of the disparagement of their merits by the rest, and so they have been
                almost constrained to throw themselves out of this harbour on those stormy billows.
                And if, after they have been tossed about on those surges, and have become wearied
                of their voyage amid the whims of the people, having been successful in the conduct
                of the affairs of the republic, they show their faces again in the senate-house, and
                wish to gain the favours of this most honourable order, I say that they are not only
                not to be repelled, but are to be received with open arms, and courted. <milestone
                    n="39" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>We are warned by the bravest man and most admirable consul who has ever existed in
                the memory of man, to take care that the nearer <placeName key="tgn,1000070"
                    >Gaul</placeName> be not decreed against our will to any one after the election
                of those consuls who are now about to be elected, and that it be not for the future
                occupied forever by these men who are the constant attackers of this order, by some
                turbulent system of currying favour with the mob. And although I am not indifferent
                to the evil consequences of such a measure, O conscript fathers, especially when
                warned of them by a consul of the greatest wisdom, and one who is an especial
                guardian of peace and tranquillity, still I think that there is an evil to be
                regarded with even more apprehension than that,—the evil, I mean, of diminishing the
                honours of most illustrious and powerful citizens, and rejecting their zeal for the
                maintenance of this order. </p>
            <p>For even supposing that Caius Julius, having been distinguished by all sorts of
                extraordinary and unprecedented honours by the senate, were compelled to deliver up
                this province to one whom you would be very unwilling to see there, still I cannot
                possibly be induced to suspect that be would deprive that body of liberty by which
                he himself had the greatest glory conferred on him. Lastly, what disposition every
                one will have I know not; I am aware only of what my own hopes are. I, as a senator,
                am bound to take care, as far as I can, that no illustrious or powerful man shall
                appear to have any right to feel offended with this body. <milestone n="40"
                    unit="section"/> These sentiments I should express out of regard to the
                republic, even were I ever so great an enemy to Caius Caesar. <milestone n="17"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But I do not think it foreign to the present discussion, with the object of being for
                the future less frequently <pb n="305"/> interrupted by certain persons, or less
                reproved in the opinion of some who forbear to interrupt me, to explain briefly what
                is the nature of my relations with Caesar. And in the first place, I pass over that
                period of familiarity and intimacy which existed between him and me, and my brother
                and Caius Varro, our cousin, from the time that we were all young men. After that I
                became deeply engaged in public affairs, my sentiments on matters of state were no
                different from his, that we were of entirely opposite public parties though without
                any interruption of our private friendship. <milestone n="41" unit="section"/> He,
                as consul, adopted measures in which he wished to have me for a partner; and if I
                was opposed to the measures themselves, still I could not avoid being pleased at the
                opinion of me which he displayed by that wish. He entreated me also to accept the
                office of quinquevir.<note anchored="true">Some read here <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >vigentiviratum</foreign> referring it to the commission of twenty citizens
                    for the division of the lands in <placeName key="tgn,7003005"
                        >Campania</placeName>, a place in which was offered to Cicero and refused by
                    him. And Orellius thinks that reading not to be disregarded but retains the one
                    translated in the text (<foreign xml:lang="la">quinqueviratum</foreign>),
                    because (<bibl n="Cic. Att. 2.7"><title>Epist ad Att.</title> ii. 7</bibl>,) he
                    also speaks of a <foreign xml:lang="la">quinqueviratus</foreign>, which
                    therefore Orellius thinks may refer to some project which was never brought to
                    bear.</note> He wished me to be one of three men of consular rank<note
                    anchored="true">Cicero speaks also in his Letters to Atticus (<bibl
                        n="Cic. Att. 2.3">ii.3</bibl>) of Caesar's overtures to him to join him and
                    Pompeius and Crassus in their partition of all power between them and of
                    Caesar's sending him word by Balbus that he would be governed in all his
                    proceedings by him and Pompeius and Crassus; but Cicero refused entering into
                    any engagements with the three whose union he thought dangerous to the state,
                    and at that time too he certainly had great suspicions of Caesar.</note> most
                closely connected with himself; and he offered me any lieutenancy or embassy I
                pleased, with as much honour and distinction as was agreeable to me. All which
                offers I rejected with great firmness in my own sentiments, but not without feeling
                obliged to him for them. How wisely I acted is not now the question; for many will
                not approve of my conduct. At all events I acted with consistency and firmness,
                inasmuch as though by accepting them I might have fortified myself by the most
                irresistible assistance against all the wickedness of my enemies and should have
                been able to repel the attacks of popularity hunters by the protection of popular
                men, I preferred to meet any fortune to encounter any violence and any in jury,
                rather than differ from the wise and righteous sentiments <pb n="306"/> of the
                senate, or deviate from the line of conduct which I had marked out for myself. </p>
            <p>But a man is bound to be grateful, not only if he has received a kindness, but if he
                has had an opportunity of receiving one. I did not think that all those compliments
                and distinctions with which he was loading me became me, or were suited to the
                exploits which I had performed. But I saw that he regarded me with the same friendly
                disposition with which he looked on that chief of the citizens, his own son-in-law.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/> He afterwards assisted my great enemy in
                passing over to the ranks of the plebeians, either because he was angry with me when
                he saw that I could not be allured, not even by all his kindness, to unite with him,
                or because he was unable to withstand the entreaties of Clodius. And even that was
                no injury to me in his opinion; for he afterwards not only advised but actually
                entreated me to act as his lieutenant. Even that I would not accept; not because I
                thought it inconsistent with my dignity, but because I had no suspicion that such
                wicked designs against the republic were entertained by the succeeding consuls as
                afterwards proved to be. <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Therefore I have much more reason to fear that I may be blamed for arrogance of
                conduct with respect to his liberality towards me, than that I should be reproached
                with the injuries which he has done me in spite of our friendship. <milestone n="43"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Turn your eyes to that tempest—to that season of darkness to all good men,—to that
                sudden and unforeseen danger which overwhelmed all things,—to that cloud which came
                over the republic—to the ruin and conflagration of the city—to the alarm given to
                Caesar with respect to all the acts of his consulship,—to the fear of massacre with
                which all good men were struck,—to the wickedness, and covetousness, and indigence,
                and audacity of the consuls! If I was not aided by him then, he was under no
                obligation to aid me; if I was deserted by him, perhaps he was providing for his own
                safety; if I was even attacked by him, as some men think, or at all events wish me
                to think, then our friendship was violated, I received an injury, and he has
                deserved that I should be his enemy. I do not deny it; but still, if he was anxious
                for my safety when you were all regretting me like the dearest of your sons, and if
                you all at the same time thought it of great <pb n="307"/> importance to my cause
                that the inclinations of Caius Caesar should not be averse to my safety; and if I
                have his son in law as a witness of his good will towards me at that time, who
                himself stirred up all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> in the
                municipal towns and the Roman people in the assembly, and you too who were always
                most devoted to me, in the Capitol, to take measures for my safety; if in short
                Cnaeus Pompeius is at the same time a witness to me of the good will which Caesar
                entertains for me, and a surety to him of my attachment to him; does it not appear
                to you that I ought rather to recollect the times that are long past and also to
                remember this time which is nearest to us now, and by means of these memories to
                eradicate that middle time so full of infamy and misery, if not from the history of
                events, (which indeed may be impossible,) at all events from my own mind? <milestone
                    n="44" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But I, if I may not (as some people think I ought not) boast that I have sacrificed
                my own private feelings of indignation and enmity to the republic, which it appears
                to me to be the duty of a great and wise man to do, will at all events avail myself
                of this plea,—which is of force not so much to gain praise as to avoid
                reproach,—namely, that I am a grateful person, and that I am inclined to be moved,
                not only by such exceeding services as his, but even by a moderate display of
                good-will towards me. <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I entreat of some most gallant men, who have done me great service, that, if I have
                been unwilling that they should be partakers of my labours and distresses, they will
                also spare me from being the partaker of their enmities; especially as they have
                granted to me that I have a right to defend those acts of Caesar's which I neither
                attacked nor defended before. <milestone n="45" unit="section"/> For the most
                eminent men of the state, by whose counsels I acted when I preserved the republic,
                and in deference to whose authority I avoided that union with Caesar to which he
                invited me, deny that the Julian laws, and the others which were passed during his
                consulship, were legally passed at all. And at the same time they say that the bill
                for my proscription was passed in a manner contrary to the safety of the republic,
                but still without any illegal disregard of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >auspices</foreign>. Therefore a man of the highest authority, and of the
                greatest eloquence, said with great positiveness that that disaster of mine was a
                funeral of the republic, but <pb n="308"/> a funeral performed with all regular
                solemnity. To me myself it is altogether excessively complimentary, that my
                departure should be called the funeral of the republic. His other expressions I do
                not find any fault with, but I will assume them as a foundation for the sentiments
                which I feel. For if men have ventured to say that that proposition was carried in a
                regular manner, for which there was no precedent nor any law authorizing such a bill
                to be carried, merely because no one had been observing the heavens at the time, had
                they forgotten that, at the time that the man who carried this bill was made a
                plebeian by a <foreign xml:lang="la">lex curiata</foreign>, it was announced that a
                magistrate was observing the heavens? And if it was absolutely irregular for him to
                be made a plebeian, how could he be made a tribune of the people? And if his
                tribuneship be declared valid, there is then no one of Caesar's acts which can
                possibly be invalid; and so, will not, not merely his tribuneship, but also other
                matters the most mischievous imaginable, appear to have been passed with proper
                regularity, if it be decided that the religious respect due to the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign> was preserved? <milestone n="46" unit="section"
                />
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore you must decide either that the Aelian law still exists, that the Fufian
                law has not been abrogated, and that it is not lawful for a law to be passed on
                every one of the <foreign xml:lang="la">dies fasti</foreign>; that, when a law is
                being passed, there is no objection to observations of the heavens being taken, or
                to such an announcement being made by the magistrates, or to any one interposing his
                veto; that the decisions and animadversions of the censors, and that most strict
                inspection of morals, has not been abolished in the city by nefarious laws; that if
                a patrician has been tribune of the people, he has been so in violation of the most
                sacred laws,—if a plebeian, in disregard of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >auspices</foreign>: or else men must grant to me that it is not necessary for
                me in the case of good measures to be bound by those rules which they themselves do
                not adhere to in shameful ones; especially as it has been a proposal made by them to
                Caius Caesar several times, that he should carry the same measures in some other
                manner, (in some manner, that is, which the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >auspices</foreign> required and which the law sanctioned;) and when, in the
                case of Clodius, the history of the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign> is
                just the same, and all the laws of the state have been overturned and destroyed. <pb
                    n="309"/>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>This is the last thing which I have to say. If I
                had any enmity against Caius Caesar, still at this time I ought to consult the
                interests of the republic, and to reserve my hostility for another time. I might
                even, following the precedent of most eminent men, lay aside my enmity altogether
                for the sake of the republic; but as I have never entertained any enmity to him, and
                as the idea of having been injured by him has been extinguished by services which he
                has done me, I, by my opinion, O conscript fathers, if the dignity of Caius Caesar
                is at stake, shall vote for the man;—if any honour to be paid to him is under
                discussion, I shall consult the unanimous feeling of the senate if the authority of
                your decrees is the main point to be regarded, I shall uphold the consistency of our
                order by voting distinctions to this same commander-in-chief;—if the everlasting
                consideration of the Gallic war is to be taken into the account, I shall consult the
                interests of the republic if I may have respect to my own private duty I shall show
                that I am not ungrateful. </p>
            <p>And I wish, O conscript fathers, to induce you all to approve of my sentiments; but I
                shall not be greatly concerned if I fail to induce those men to approve of them who
                shielded my enemy in spite of your authority; or those who found fault with my
                reconciliation with their enemy, while they themselves do not hesitate to be
                reconciled both to my enemy and to their own.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
